<!--

File produced by pipelineRunner package (for JATS 2 SCJATS with pipeline SCJATS)
At: 2025-05-22T15:36:11.338Z

Version        : 1.16.1
Last update    : 2024-08-27
Modified by    : dunnm

-->
<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Soc Cogn Affect Neurosci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Soc Cogn Affect Neurosci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">scan</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Social Cognitive and Affective Neuroscience</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1749-5016</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1749-5024</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>UK</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39891393</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11799862</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/scan/nsaf014</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">nsaf014</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research &#x02013; Neuroscience</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection"><subject>AcademicSubjects/SCI01880</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Premovement activity in the corticospinal tract is amplified by the placebo effect: an active inference account</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8238-9969</contrib-id><name><surname>Emadi Andani</surname><given-names>Mehran</given-names></name><!--mehran.emadiandani@univr.it--><aff>
<institution content-type="department">Department of Neurosciences, Biomedicine and Movement Sciences, University of Verona</institution>, Verona 37131, <country country="IT">Italy</country></aff><xref rid="COR0001" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8306-3503</contrib-id><name><surname>Braga</surname><given-names>Miriam</given-names></name><aff>
<institution content-type="department">Department of Neurosciences, Biomedicine and Movement Sciences, University of Verona</institution>, Verona 37131, <country country="IT">Italy</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Da Dalt</surname><given-names>Francesco</given-names></name><aff>
<institution content-type="department">Department of Neurosciences, Biomedicine and Movement Sciences, University of Verona</institution>, Verona 37131, <country country="IT">Italy</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5705-2173</contrib-id><name><surname>Piedimonte</surname><given-names>Alessandro</given-names></name><aff>
<institution content-type="department">Department of Neuroscience, University of Turin</institution>, Turin 10125, <country country="IT">Italy</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8472-656X</contrib-id><name><surname>Carlino</surname><given-names>Elisa</given-names></name><aff>
<institution content-type="department">Department of Neuroscience, University of Turin</institution>, Turin 10125, <country country="IT">Italy</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6356-0211</contrib-id><name><surname>Fiorio</surname><given-names>Mirta</given-names></name><!--mirta.fiorio@univr.it--><aff>
<institution content-type="department">Department of Neurosciences, Biomedicine and Movement Sciences, University of Verona</institution>, Verona 37131, <country country="IT">Italy</country></aff><xref rid="COR0001" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="COR0001">*Corresponding author. Department of Neurosciences, Biomedicine and Movement Sciences, University of Verona, Via Casorati-43, 37131 Verona, Italy. E-mails: <email xlink:href="mirta.fiorio@univr.it">mirta.fiorio@univr.it</email>; Mehran Emadi Andani: <email xlink:href="mehran.emadiandani@univr.it">mehran.emadiandani@univr.it</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2025-02-01"><day>01</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>01</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>20</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>nsaf014</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>6</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>03</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>31</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="editorial-decision"><day>20</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="corrected-typeset"><day>05</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2025. Published by Oxford University Press.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="nsaf014.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><p>The aim of this study is to investigate whether expectancy, induced through a placebo procedure, favors the activation of the corticospinal tract before movement initiation. By adopting the premovement facilitation paradigm, we applied transcranial magnetic stimulation over the left or right primary motor cortex at rest and 100&#x02009;ms or 50&#x02009;ms before movement onset while healthy volunteers performed a reaction time (RT) motor task consisting of abductions of the right or left thumb after a go signal. Participants in the placebo group received an inert electrical device applied on the right forearm along with information on its speed-enhancing properties. A control group received the same device with overt information about its inert nature, while another control group underwent no intervention. Along with RT, we measured the amplitude of the motor evoked potential (MEP) before and after the procedure. Compared to the control groups, the placebo group had faster RT and greater MEP amplitude before movement initiation. This study demonstrates that the placebo effect can boost the activity of the corticospinal tract before movement onset, and this modulation positively impacts motor performance. These results give experimental support to the active inference account.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>premovement facilitation</kwd><kwd>transcranial magnetic stimulation</kwd><kwd>expectancy</kwd><kwd>placebo effect</kwd><kwd>active inference model</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>PRIN</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source><award-id>2022AL38E4</award-id></award-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>National Recovery and Resilience Plan (NRRP)</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>MNESYS</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source><award-id>PE0000006</award-id></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>PRIN</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source><award-id>2022AL38E4</award-id></award-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>National Recovery and Resilience Plan (NRRP)</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>MNESYS</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source><award-id>PE0000006</award-id></award-group></funding-group><counts><page-count count="11"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Mounting evidence indicates that expectancy <italic toggle="yes">per se</italic> influences motor performance (<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">Hurst and Beedie 2023</xref>). In fact, individuals who expect to perform well following an intervention or a treatment show objective improvement in a variety of motor functions, including force exertion, speed, balance control, and resistance to fatigue, even if the treatment itself is actually inert (<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">Beedie and Foad 2009</xref>, <xref rid="R61" ref-type="bibr">Villa&#x02010;S&#x000e1;nchez et&#x000a0;al. 2019</xref>, <xref rid="R59" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>, <xref rid="R62" ref-type="bibr">2023</xref>, <xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">Fiorio et&#x000a0;al. 2022</xref>). This psychobiological phenomenon, known as the &#x0201c;placebo effect,&#x0201d; is tangible proof of the power of the mind over the body.</p><p>Predictive coding theories, and in particular the active inference account, provide a good theoretical framework for explaining the placebo effect and, therefore, the influence of expectancy on motor performance (<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">B&#x000fc;chel et&#x000a0;al. 2014</xref>, <xref rid="R43" ref-type="bibr">Ongaro and Kaptchuk 2019</xref>). According to this framework, the brain uses priors, which can be defined as beliefs about future outcomes, to predict the consequence of an action, combining expectations with sensory input (<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">Friston et&#x000a0;al. 2010</xref>, <xref rid="R53" ref-type="bibr">Smith et&#x000a0;al. 2022</xref>). The model assumes that priors and actions interact with each other so that, on the one hand, top-down processes provide predictions to lower-level layers, preparing perceptual and motor processes in advance, and, on the other hand, lower-level layers provide details of the movement to be performed, allowing predictions to be updated during the execution of a motor act (<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">Adams et&#x000a0;al. 2013</xref>). Thus, according to the model, action preparation and execution continuously interact to create a reliable prediction of future outcomes, as the brain attempts to minimize prediction error, i.e. the discrepancy between priors and sensory information (<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">Adams et&#x000a0;al. 2013</xref>).</p><p>This framework not only explains well the impact of expectancy on motor performance but also lends support to the use of placebo procedures as appropriate strategies to experimentally manipulate the induction of priors in a controlled manner (<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">B&#x000fc;chel et&#x000a0;al. 2014</xref>, <xref rid="R43" ref-type="bibr">Ongaro and Kaptchuk 2019</xref>). Interestingly, previous neurophysiological evidence in the motor domain showed that the induction of expectancy through a placebo procedure changes the activity of motor-related brain regions (<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">Fiorio 2018</xref>). Specifically, by applying transcranial magnetic stimulation (TMS) over the primary motor cortex (M1), it was demonstrated that healthy individuals who were induced to believe in the force-enhancing properties of a placebo device showed an increase in force production associated with increased excitability of the corticospinal tract from M1 (<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">Fiorio et&#x000a0;al. 2014</xref>). In the current study, we aim at investigating whether expectancy favors the activation of the corticospinal tract even before movement initiation.</p><p>We exploited the premovement facilitation paradigm as a suitable way to study the neurophysiological correlates of expectancy. Premovement facilitation is represented by an increase in excitability of the corticospinal tract from M1 that typically begins 80&#x02013;100&#x02009;ms before movement onset (<xref rid="R51" ref-type="bibr">Rossini et&#x000a0;al. 1988</xref>, <xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">Hiraoka et&#x000a0;al. 2010</xref>, <xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">Cirillo et&#x000a0;al. 2021</xref>). It can be evoked by asking individuals to perform rapid movements after a go signal and by delivering a TMS pulse to the contralateral M1 in a time window between the go and the movement onset. As such, premovement facilitation can give information on the preparatory mechanisms that combine higher-level layers, like M1, and lower-level layers, like the spinal cord. To induce positive expectations, we adopted an ergogenic placebo procedure in which a group of participants received the application of an electrical stimulation device on the right forearm passed off as having speed-enhancing properties. A control group underwent the application of the same electrical device as the placebo group but with explicit verbal information on its inert nature, while another control group received neither the device nor any information about it. According to the active inference account, priors should activate motor and premotor cortices in the preparatory phase of a movement (<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">Bestmann et&#x000a0;al. 2008</xref>, <xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">Brown et&#x000a0;al. 2011</xref>, <xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr">Pezzulo and Ognibene 2012</xref>), and therefore we hypothesized that the induction of expectancy in the placebo group should result in faster movements and in higher MEP amplitude before movement onset compared to the control groups. Furthermore, since the model assumes that attention is involved in processing relevant information to prepare and execute an action (<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">Fagioli et&#x000a0;al. 2007</xref>, <xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">Brown et&#x000a0;al. 2011</xref>), we tested the behavioral and neurophysiological effects of our procedure both on the body side on which the placebo device was applied (i.e. the right forearm) and on the contralateral side, with the hypothesis that a greater modulation of performance and brain activation should be present in the treated side as a result of the interplay between expectancy and attention.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="s2-s1"><title>Participants</title><p>Sample size computation was performed with G-Power 3.1 (<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">Faul et&#x000a0;al. 2007</xref>), considering F tests for a within-between interaction with three groups and two sessions. Assuming an anticipated effect size <italic toggle="yes">f</italic> of 0.25 (considered medium by <xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">Cohen 1988</xref>), &#x003b1; error probability of 0.05, power (1 &#x02212; &#x003b2; error probability) of 0.80, correlation among repeated measures of 0.5 and nonsphericity correction &#x003b5; of 1, the resulting sample size is 42. To prevent a reduction of power due to potential dropouts, we recruited a total of 48 healthy subjects. Participants were recruited from the student population of the University of Verona (Italy) and randomly assigned to 3 groups of 16 subjects each: placebo group (mean age: 21.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.2; 7 women; 14 right-handed), control transcutaneous electrical nerve stimulation (TENS) group (mean age: 21.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.4; 7 women; 13 right-handed), control NoTENS group (mean age: 22.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.0; 6 women; 15 right-handed).</p><p>Prior to the experiment, participants were screened for any contraindications to TMS and for neurological or psychiatric disorders (<xref rid="R50" ref-type="bibr">Rossi et&#x000a0;al. 2009</xref>). Participants were not taking any medications at the time of the experiment and had normal or corrected to normal vision. Written informed consent was obtained from all participants prior to study participation. The study was approved by the Human Research Approval Committee (CARP 17.R1/2022) of the University of Verona and conducted in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki.</p></sec><sec id="s2-s2"><title>Simple reaction time motor task</title><p>Participants sat on a comfortable chair in front of a PC monitor (ASUS Full HD; screen size: 29&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;38.6&#x02009;cm; screen resolution: 1280&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;1024 pixels) with the forearms relaxed on a table. They were asked to perform a simple reaction time (RT) motor task by abducting the thumb as quickly as possible after the appearance of a visual cue (i.e. a black circle, 2.5&#x02009;cm diameter) presented in the center of the PC monitor on a gray background (<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">Chen et&#x000a0;al. 1998</xref>, <xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr">Morgante et&#x000a0;al. 2011</xref>, <xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">Cirillo et&#x000a0;al. 2021</xref>). RT was defined as the latency between the presentation of the visual cue and the electromyographic (EMG) onset of movement recorded with surface electrodes from the abductor pollicis brevis (APB), the muscle directly involved in the task. The EMG onset was defined as the time point at which the EMG signal amplitude exceeded a predetermined threshold, indicating the beginning of muscle activation. In our study, the threshold was set at 2 SD above the baseline EMG amplitude, defined as the EMG recorded during the 50&#x02009;ms preceding the onset of the visual cue.</p><p>At the beginning of each experimental phase, participants were asked to perform 10 trials of the motor task (i.e. 10 thumb abduction movements). An interval of 8&#x02009;s (&#x000b1; 1) was inserted between two consecutive trials (<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">Cirillo et&#x000a0;al. 2021</xref>). We called this condition &#x0201c;Task-only.&#x0201d; By averaging the RT of the 10 trials, we obtained the mean RT for each participant which was used not only to have a measure of performance but also to calculate the time window in which to apply the TMS pulse necessary to evaluate the premovement facilitation (details are reported in the procedure) (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;1a</xref>). The motor task was performed separately with the right and the left hands in a counterbalanced order across participants.</p><fig position="float" id="F1" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Schematic representation of the motor task and the procedure. (a) The simple RT motor task consisted of 10 rapid thumb abduction movements after the presentation of a visual go signal (a white dot appearing on the screen). In the Task-only condition, participants performed the motor task alone with the right or left hand with a blocked design and a counterbalanced order across participants. In the TMS<sub>Rest</sub> condition, the TMS pulse was applied over the left or right M1 (depending on the hand performing the task) while the subjects were at rest. In the TMS<sub>Task</sub> condition, the TMS pulse was delivered over the left or right M1 (depending on the hand performing the task) while the subjects performed the motor task. In this condition, the TMS pulse could be randomly delivered at 100&#x02009;ms or 50&#x02009;ms before the onset of the EMG. MEPs were recorded from the APB and ADM muscles of the right or the left hand. The APB was the muscle of interest, being involved in the task, while the ADM was a control muscle. (b) The three conditions (Task-only, TMS<sub>Rest</sub>, TMS<sub>Task</sub>) were performed before (Baseline) and after (Test) the placebo manipulation or the control procedures.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nsaf014f1" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2-s3"><title>Transcranial magnetic stimulation</title><p>Single-pulse TMS was applied over the M1 contralateral to the hand performing the task (either the right or the left) with a blocked design and with a counterbalanced order across participants. The TMS pulses were delivered through a standard figure-of-eight coil with mean loop diameter of 90&#x02009;mm, connected to a STM 9000 stimulator (EB Neuro). The coil was positioned tangentially to the skull at an angle of 45&#x000b0; to the sagittal plane.</p><p>Surface EMG was recorded from the APB and the abductor digiti minimi (ADM) muscles by means of unipolar self-adhesive Ag/AgCl electrodes (1.5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;2.5&#x02009;cm) in a belly-tendon montage. The APB was considered the muscle of interest, being directly involved in the task, while the ADM served as the control muscle (<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">Duqu&#x000e9; et&#x000a0;al. 2010</xref>, <xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">Cirillo et&#x000a0;al. 2021</xref>). The ground electrode was placed on the palm. EMG signals were amplified (&#x000d7;1000), filtered by bandpass from 10 to 500&#x02009;Hz plus a notch filter set at 50&#x02009;Hz (LabChart 8 pro, ADInstruments Co.), sampled at the frequency of 2&#x02009;kHz, and digitized by PowerLab 16/35 (ADInstruments Co.). EMG signals were analyzed in real-time and offline with MATLAB 2014a (MathWorks Inc.).</p><p>The APB optimal scalp position was identified by moving the coil in small steps around the vertex and by delivering TMS pulses at 50% of the maximum stimulator power until stable and maximal MEP could be evoked in the APB muscle. The resting motor threshold (RMT) was defined for each subject and each hemisphere as the lowest stimulus intensity able to evoke an MEP with an amplitude of at least 50&#x02009;&#x003bc;V in 5 out of 10 trials in the contralateral APB muscle (<xref rid="R54" ref-type="bibr">Temesi et&#x000a0;al. 2014</xref>).</p><p>During the experiment, single-pulse TMS was delivered at 120% of the RMT in two conditions: at rest (TMS<sub>Rest</sub>) and during the motor task (TMS<sub>Task</sub>). In the TMS<sub>Rest</sub> condition, 10 TMS pulses were applied over the right and left M1 while participants were at rest. This allowed us to measure the baseline corticospinal excitability of each participant. In the TMS<sub>Task</sub> condition, TMS pulses were delivered during the motor task. This condition consisted of a total of 20 randomly presented trials: in 10 trials the TMS pulse was delivered 100&#x02009;ms before the movement onset (TMS<sub>Task100</sub>) and in 10 trials the TMS pulse was delivered 50&#x02009;ms before the movement onset (TMS<sub>Task50</sub>) (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;1a</xref>). Since our protocol comprised several conditions (i.e. rest and active, right and left hand, baseline and test sessions), 10 TMS pulses per condition appear to provide an optimal balance between feasibility and reliable measurements (<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">Cavaleri et&#x000a0;al. 2017</xref>, <xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">Biabani et&#x000a0;al. 2018</xref>, <xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">Cirillo et&#x000a0;al. 2021</xref>).</p><p>TMS pulses were automatically triggered with MATLAB through a USB-6009 (National Instruments Corporation). As anticipated above, the time to apply the TMS pulse was derived from the mean RT obtained from the 10 trials of the simple RT motor task (Task-only) for each participant at the beginning of each session. Like in the Task-only condition, we considered an interval of 8&#x02009;s (&#x000b1; 1) between two consecutive trials (<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">Cirillo et&#x000a0;al. 2021</xref>).</p><p>The neurophysiological parameter considered in this study was the peak-to-peak MEP amplitude (mV) recorded from the APB and ADM muscles. To rule out any effect of prestimulus EMG activity on MEP amplitude, prestimulation EMG activity was calculated on both muscles as the root mean square of the EMG over 50&#x02009;ms prior to the TMS pulse.</p></sec><sec id="s2-s4"><title>Procedure</title><p>After a short familiarization with the motor task (three trials), participants underwent the three conditions described above, presented always with the same blocked order: Task-only, TMS<sub>Rest</sub>, and TMS<sub>Task</sub> (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;1b</xref>). The blocked order was chosen based on previous studies on premovement facilitation (<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">Chen et&#x000a0;al. 1998</xref>, <xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr">Morgante et&#x000a0;al. 2011</xref>, <xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">Cirillo et&#x000a0;al. 2021</xref>), in which the &#x0201c;Task-only&#x0201d; condition must inevitably always be performed at the beginning of the procedure to determine the individual&#x02019;s mean RT used to apply the subsequent TMS pulse (at 100&#x02009;ms or 50&#x02009;ms before movement onset). For the two TMS conditions (i.e. TMS<sub>Rest</sub> and TMS<sub>Task</sub>), we again used a blocked design because the TMS<sub>Rest</sub> condition was conceived of as a &#x0201c;baseline&#x0201d; assessment of corticospinal excitability and counterbalancing the order of the TMS conditions would have carried out the potential risk of having varying levels of &#x0201c;baseline&#x0201d; corticospinal excitability across participants, as demonstrated by previous evidence where the application of consecutive TMS pulses over M1 induced cumulative changes in neural activity, resulting in increased corticospinal excitability (<xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr">Pellicciari et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>).</p><p>The conditions were separated by a time window of about 2&#x02009;min and were performed in two sessions: baseline and test (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;1b</xref>). The baseline session served to evaluate performance and premovement facilitation before any manipulation. Between the baseline and test session, the placebo group underwent a placebo manipulation, consisting of the application of 10&#x02009;Hz transcutaneous electrical nerve stimulation (TENS) with two surface electrodes (1.5&#x02009;cm diameter) over the volar surface of the right forearm. This stimulation <italic toggle="yes">per se</italic> does not produce any enhancing effects on motor performance (<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">Fiorio et&#x000a0;al. 2014</xref>). Nonetheless, the placebo group received positive verbal information about the effect of TENS on speeding-up thumb movements at the motor task. TENS intensity was adjusted so that participants felt a slight tingling sensation on the skin, though without any muscle contraction. The slight sensation served to convince participants that the device was active, thus boosting their expectation of TENS effectiveness. After 4&#x02009;min, participants performed the test session. This time window appears to be adequate to let participants believe in the effectiveness of the device in the experimental condition (<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">Fiorio et&#x000a0;al. 2022</xref>, <xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">Emadi Andani et&#x000a0;al. 2024</xref>). For consistency, the same time between sessions was maintained also in the control groups. During the test session, the TENS electrodes were still attached to the forearm, but with the stimulation intensity at zero level. This procedure served to maintain subjects&#x02019; belief about TENS effectiveness throughout the test session, without any confounding factor linked to skin sensation.</p><p>Two control groups (control TENS and control NoTENS), not exposed to any placebo manipulation, differed in terms of verbal information and procedures received. The control TENS group received TENS over the right forearm in the same (inert) modality of stimulation as the placebo group, though without any positive suggestion that TENS would enhance performance. In particular, participants of this group were told that they belonged to a control group, and therefore, the device was set at frequencies that have no effect on performance. This group served to control for potential effects due to the mere sight of TENS electrodes on task performance. Participants of the control NoTENS group received neither TENS nor any information about it and served to control for the natural course of performance throughout the procedure. Participants of this group had a rest of 4&#x02009;min between the baseline and test sessions.</p><p>By applying TENS on the right forearm and asking participants to perform the task with the right and left hand, we had the secondary aim of investigating whether the placebo effect was specific for the treated side (i.e. right hand, left M1) or could generalize to the contralateral side.</p></sec><sec id="s2-s5"><title>Subjective ratings</title><p>As a manipulation check for our placebo procedure, before the test session subjects were asked to judge how they expected their performance to change compared to baseline, by using a numerical rating scale (NRS), ranging from &#x02212;3 (&#x0201c;much slower than before&#x0201d;) to +3 (&#x0201c;much faster than before&#x0201d;), with 0 denoting &#x0201c;like before.&#x0201d; Moreover, at the end of the experiment subjects were asked to rate the perceived effectiveness of TENS, on a 10&#x02009;cm visual analog scale (VAS) ranging from 0 (&#x0201c;not effective at all&#x0201d;) to 10 (&#x0201c;very much effective&#x0201d;). Finally, after the motor task subjects were asked to evaluate their own performance on a VAS ranging from 0 (&#x0201c;very slow&#x0201d;) to 10 (&#x0201c;very fast&#x0201d;).</p><p>Importantly, the experimenter (M.B.), who was in direct contact with the participants, was responsible for giving them the information sheet, collecting signed informed consent, instructing participants on the RT task and collecting subjective scores. This experimenter was completely unaware of the group assignment, which was instead performed by a third researcher (M.E.A), who was never present in the laboratory, thus ensuring for the double-blind nature of our design. The experimenter who applied the TMS pulse (F.D.D.) was not blind, since he also applied the placebo or control intervention. For these reasons, we can exclude any experimenter bias on variables sensitive to it, such as RTs and subjective scores.</p></sec><sec id="s2-s6"><title>Data handling</title><p>Trials of the TMS<sub>Task</sub> conditions were inspected for muscle contraction preceding the TMS pulse, defined as EMG activity greater than 2 SD of the mean value recorded in the rest condition. Prestimulation EMG activity was below this threshold in all TMS<sub>Task</sub> trials. Afterwards, MEP amplitude was inspected to exclude outliers (i.e. values 2.5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;SD above or below the mean value for each subject in each session and condition). Following this procedure, for the right hand we removed 0.52% of trials in the placebo group, 0.73% in the control TENS group, and 0.63% in the control NoTENS group; for the left hand we removed 0.63% of trials in the placebo group, 0.94% in the control TENS group, and 0.31% in the control NoTENS group.</p></sec><sec id="s2-s7"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>The three groups were compared for gender distribution and hand-dominance by means of chi-squared test and for age and RMT with one-way analysis of variance. Behavioral and neurophysiological data were normally distributed (Shapiro&#x02013;Wilk test, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;.061), with equal variances between groups (Levene&#x02019;s test, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;.085). RTs obtained in the Task-only condition were analyzed by means of repeated measures analysis of variance (rmANOVA) with Phase (baseline and test) as within-subjects factor and Group (placebo, control TENS, and control NoTENS) as between-subjects factor. This analysis allowed to determine whether the placebo procedure was effective in modifying participants&#x02019; performance without any interference induced by the TMS pulse.</p><p>MEP amplitude and prestimulation EMG activity were analyzed, separately for the APB and ADM muscles, by means of rmANOVAs, with Phase (baseline and test) and Time (TMS<sub>Rest</sub>, TMS<sub>Task100</sub>, TMS<sub>Task50</sub>) as within-subjects factors and group as between-subjects factor.</p><p>Subjective variables were analyzed with nonparametric tests due to the ordinal nature of the data. In particular, the Wilcoxon signed rank test was used to compare the sessions within each group separately, and the Kruskal&#x02013;Wallis test to compare the groups within each session separately.</p><p>All analyses were conducted for the right and left hand, separately. Post-hoc comparisons were performed with paired- and independent-samples <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-tests for parametric analyses and Mann&#x02013;Whitney test for nonparametric analyses. The effect size of all significant results was reported with partial eta-square (&#x003b7;<sub>p</sub><sup>2</sup>) and Cohen&#x02019;s d for rmANOVA and parametric post-hoc tests, respectively (<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">Fritz et&#x000a0;al. 2012</xref>) and with Kendall&#x02019;s W, and r for Kruskal&#x02013;Wallis, and nonparametric post-hoc tests, respectively (<xref rid="R57" ref-type="bibr">Tomczak and Tomczak 2014</xref>).</p><p>Bayes factors quantifying the evidence in favor of the alternative hypothesis (BF<sub>10</sub>) were computed (<xref rid="R58" ref-type="bibr">van Doorn et&#x000a0;al. 2020</xref>). A Bayes factor BF<sub>10</sub>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;3 was interpreted as substantial, and a BF<sub>10</sub>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;10 as strong evidence against the null hypothesis.</p><p>Spearman&#x02019;s coefficient of correlation was used to correlate the subjective data with the change (&#x00394;) in neurophysiological and behavioral data from the baseline to the test sessions computed for each participant as follows:</p><disp-formula id="UM0001">
<tex-math notation="LaTeX" id="UM0001-Latex">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
$${\Delta {\rm {RT = R}}}{{\mathrm{T}}_{{\mathrm{Baseline}}}}{\mathrm{- R}}{{\mathrm{T}}_{{\mathrm{Test}}}}$$\end{document}</tex-math>
</disp-formula><disp-formula id="UM0002">
<tex-math notation="LaTeX" id="UM0002-Latex">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
$${\Delta {\rm {MEP = ME}}}{{\mathrm{P}}_{{\mathrm{Baseline}}}}{\mathrm{- ME}}{{\mathrm{P}}_{{\mathrm{Test}}}}$$\end{document}</tex-math>
</disp-formula><p>
where &#x00394;RT or &#x00394;MEP is the difference between the baseline and test phase in RTs (obtained in the Task-only condition) or MEPs (measured at 100&#x02009;ms and 50&#x02009;ms before EMG onset). The delta is informative of the amount of change in performance and corticospinal excitability before and after the procedure and can be considered as a proxy of the placebo effect. Additionally, we plotted &#x00394;RT and &#x00394;MEP together and analyzed their relationship with a quadrant analysis described in the <xref rid="s5" ref-type="sec">Supplementary material</xref>. The &#x00394;MEP was also submitted to a further analysis by including Muscle and Hand as factors (see <xref rid="s5" ref-type="sec">Supplementary material</xref> for details and results).</p><p>Bonferroni correction for multiple comparisons was applied where necessary and the significance level was set at <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;.050.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Results</title><p>The three groups did not statistically differ for gender, hand-dominance (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;.669, for both), age, and RMT (right hemisphere, placebo: 55.37&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;7.89, control TENS: 61.09&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;10.54, control NoTENS: 59.74&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.32; left hemisphere, placebo: 56.98&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;9.32, control TENS: 58.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;8.62, control NoTENS: 58.33&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;10.75; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;.163, for both hemispheres).</p><sec id="s3-s1"><title>Reaction times</title><p>On the right hand, the significant interaction Phase&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;Group (F<sub>(2,45)</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;13.935, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;.001, &#x003b7;<sub>P</sub><sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.382) revealed that RTs were shorter in the placebo group compared to the two control groups, specifically in the test session (t<sub>(30)</sub>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;2.56, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;.029, Cohen&#x02019;s d&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.45, BF<sub>10</sub>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;3.40). Furthermore, in the placebo group RTs were shorter at test than at baseline (t<sub>(15)</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3.31, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;.001, d&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.59, BF<sub>10</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;9.52), while in the two control groups RTs were longer at test compared to baseline (t<sub>(15)</sub>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;2.86, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;.036, d&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.51, BF<sub>10</sub>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;4.31) (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;2a</xref>). These findings suggest that the procedure was effective in speeding up RTs in the placebo group. The effect of Phase or Group was not statistically significant (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;.279). No statistically significant result was found on the left hand (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;.925, BF<sub>10</sub>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.26), indicating that the improvement of RTs in the placebo group was specifically localized on the hand on which the placebo device was applied (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;2b</xref>). Additional analyses are reported in the <xref rid="s5" ref-type="sec">Supplementary material</xref> and <xref rid="s5" ref-type="sec">Supplementary</xref> &#x000a0;<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>.</p><fig position="float" id="F2" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Mean RTs in the Task-only condition for the right and left hand. (a) RTs on the right hand were shorter in the test compared to the baseline session in the placebo group (red bar), while they were longer in the test compared to the baseline in the control TENS (light blue bar) and control NoTENS groups (dark blue bar). In the test session, the RTs of the placebo group were shorter compared to the two control groups (black lines). (b) RTs on the left hand were stable across sessions and groups. Asterisks represent <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;.05. Error bars represent the standard error of the mean.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nsaf014f2" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3-s2"><title>Neurophysiological data</title><p>On the right hand, APB MEP amplitude was greater in the TMS<sub>Task100</sub> than in the TMS<sub>Rest</sub> condition, and it was also greater in the TMS<sub>Task50</sub> compared to the other two conditions (main effect of Time: F<sub>(2,90)</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;67.481, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;.001, &#x003b7;<sub>P</sub><sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.600; post-hoc comparisons: for all, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;.001). This finding certifies the presence of premovement facilitation at 100&#x02009;ms and 50&#x02009;ms before EMG onset and is in line with previous studies (<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">Cirillo et&#x000a0;al. 2021</xref>). More interestingly, the interactions Phase&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;Group (F<sub>(2,45)</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;11.936, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;.001, &#x003b7;<sub>P</sub><sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.347) and Phase&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;Time&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;group were significant (F<sub>(4,90)</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2.668, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;.037, &#x003b7;<sub>P</sub><sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.106). Since the latter interaction encompassed the former, it was further analyzed. Consistent with our hypotheses, post-hoc comparisons revealed that APB MEP amplitude was greater in the placebo group compared to both control groups in the test session of the TMS<sub>Task50</sub> condition (t<sub>(30)</sub>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;2.70, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;.033, d&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.95, BF<sub>10</sub>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;4.46). Furthermore, in the placebo group a greater APB MEP amplitude was found at test compared to baseline at TMS<sub>Task50</sub> and TMS<sub>Task100</sub> (t<sub>(15)</sub>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;3.13, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;.021, d&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.11, BF<sub>10</sub>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;6.90) (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3a</xref>). On the left hand, MEP amplitude increased across times (main effect of Time: F<sub>(2,90)</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;74.25, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;.001, &#x003b7;<sub>P</sub><sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.623), certifying the presence of the premovement facilitation (<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">Cirillo et&#x000a0;al. 2021</xref>), but no significant effect was found for Phase, Group, or their interactions (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;.062, BF<sub>10</sub>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.84), indicating that the placebo effect did not affect the left hand (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;3b</xref>). No significant effect was found on the ADM (for all factors, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;.298, BF<sub>10</sub>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.43) (<xref rid="F3 F3" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;3c and d</xref>). Representative MEPs from the APB are shown in <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;4</xref>.</p><fig position="float" id="F3" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Mean amplitude of the MEP across sessions and conditions. (a) The amplitude of the MEPs recorded from the right APB was greater in the test session compared to the baseline in the placebo group (solid red lines) both at 100&#x02009;ms and 50&#x02009;ms before EMG onset. In the test session, the MEP amplitude of the placebo group was higher than that of both control groups at 50&#x02009;ms before EMG onset (vertical black line). (b) Left APB MEP amplitude did not change across sessions, groups, and conditions. (c) Right ADM MEP amplitude was stable across sessions, groups, and conditions. (d) Left ADM MEP amplitude did not change across sessions, groups, and conditions. Asterisks represent <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;.05. Error bars represent the standard error of the mean.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nsaf014f3" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F4" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Representative traces of the motor evoked potentials. (a) Neurophysiological traces recorded in the baseline session from the APB muscle of the right hand in one subject of the placebo group (red traces), one subject of the control TENS group (turquoise traces), and one subject of the control NoTENS group (blue traces). (b) Neurophysiological traces recorded in the test session. Vertical lines indicate TMS pulse delivery. Black lines represent MEPs at rest, colored dashed lines represent MEPs for TMS pulse delivered 100&#x02009;ms before EMG onset and colored continuous lines the MEPs for TMS pulse delivered 50&#x02009;ms before EMG onset. MEP amplitude is reported in mV and trace duration is shown in ms. As illustrated in the figure, MEP amplitude was higher 50&#x02009;ms and 100&#x02009;ms before EMG onset, indicative of premovement facilitation. In the test session, the subject of the placebo group presents an amplification of the premovement facilitation before EMG onset.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nsaf014f4" position="float"/></fig><p>Analysis of the prestimulation EMG activity disclosed no significant effect (for all factors, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;.282), indicating that MEP amplitude was not influenced by differences in preceding EMG activity.</p></sec><sec id="s3-s3"><title>Subjective data and correlation</title><p>On the right hand, the placebo group reported higher expectation ratings compared to the control TENS group (Z&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02212;2.26, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;.029, r&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.40, BF<sub>10</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;6.67), while no difference was found on the left hand (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;.616, BF<sub>10</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.32) (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;5a and b</xref>). Similarly, on the right hand, the placebo group reported higher ratings of TENS effectiveness compared to the control TENS group (Z&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02212;2.43, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;.015, r&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.43, BF<sub>10</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3.29), with no difference on the left hand (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;.341, BF<sub>10</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.36) (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;5c and d</xref>). These findings indicate that the placebo procedure was effective in inducing positive expectations and belief in TENS effectiveness in the placebo group.</p><fig position="float" id="F5" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Mean values of the subjective variables. (a) Expectation scores on the right hand were higher in the placebo group (red bar) compared to the control TENS group (light blue bar). (b) No difference was found between groups on the left hand. (c) Perception of TENS effectiveness on the right hand was higher in the placebo group compared to the control TENS group (black line). (d) No difference was found between groups on the left hand. Asterisks represent <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;.05. Error bars represent the standard error of the mean.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nsaf014f5" position="float"/></fig><p>Participants of the placebo group reported higher performance scores in the test than in the baseline session, only on the left hand (Z&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02212;2.84, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;.004, r&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.50, BF<sub>10</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;27.78).</p><p>A positive correlation was found in the placebo group between expectation scores and &#x00394;RT on the right hand (rho&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.542, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;.030, <xref rid="s5" ref-type="sec">Supplementary Fig. S2</xref>). This correlation indicates that the higher the expectation of improvement, the greater the improvement at the motor task. Further analyses on the relation between &#x00394;RT and &#x00394;MEP are reported in the <xref rid="s5" ref-type="sec">Supplementary materials</xref> and in <xref rid="s5" ref-type="sec">Supplementary Figs. S3</xref> and <xref rid="s5" ref-type="sec">S4</xref>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>Taking advantage of the premovement facilitation paradigm, we demonstrate for the first time that the placebo effect can boost the excitability of the corticospinal tract before movement onset. Our results help refine the knowledge of the neurophysiological basis of the placebo effect in the motor domain and can be interpreted in the light of the active inference account.</p><sec id="s4-s1"><title>Premovement facilitation reveals a highly specific placebo effect before movement initiation</title><p>First of all, our results provide evidence that the paradigm was suitable for obtaining a reliable and clear premovement facilitation in all groups, as revealed by the increase in MEP amplitude in the muscle directly involved in the task (i.e. right and left APB) before movement initiation (i.e. 100&#x02009;ms and 50&#x02009;ms before EMG onset). The novel finding of the present study is that premovement facilitation turned out to be amplified in a very specific way after the placebo manipulation, thus suggesting a role of the placebo effect on the activation of the corticospinal tract from M1 prior to movement onset.</p><p>Previous studies using central (TMS and electroencephalography) or peripheral (EMG) techniques converged to indicate the existence of a top-down mechanism through which positive expectancy induced by placebo procedures could enhance the activity of the corticospinal system (<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">Fiorio et&#x000a0;al. 2014</xref>, <xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">Emadi Andani et&#x000a0;al. 2015</xref>, <xref rid="R48" ref-type="bibr">Piedimonte et&#x000a0;al. 2015</xref>, <xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">Fiorio 2018</xref>, <xref rid="R49" ref-type="bibr">Rossettini et&#x000a0;al. 2018</xref>, <xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">Corsi et&#x000a0;al. 2019</xref>). Taking advantage of the good spatial and temporal resolution of TMS (<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">Garcia-Sanz et&#x000a0;al. 2022</xref>), we were able to demonstrate that the placebo effect induced a precise amplification of premovement facilitation that was specific to the muscle involved in the task (i.e. APB) and localized on the treated side of the body (i.e. on the right). Indeed, the homologous muscle on the untreated side of the body (i.e. left APB) or adjacent muscles not involved in the task (i.e. right and left ADM) did not show any change in MEP amplitude.</p><p>This neurophysiological finding is consistent with the behavioral data, as the performance improvement was found specifically on the side of the body on which the placebo treatment was applied. The subjective data confirmed that our manipulation was effective in inducing positive expectations and beliefs about the effectiveness of TENS, particularly on the right hand, giving further support to the specificity of the placebo effect on the treated body part. The spatial localization of the placebo effect has also been observed in other domains, such as pain. For instance, a placebo analgesic effect was observed only on the participant&#x02019;s arm treated with a placebo cream when expectancy was directed toward the same body part (<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">Benedetti et&#x000a0;al. 1999</xref>). Similarly, <xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">Colloca et&#x000a0;al. (2008)</xref> confirmed a placebo analgesic effect localized to the treated hand that was associated with a specific neurophysiological reduction of the N2-P2 component, a brain wave evoked by laser stimulation and representing the emotional component of pain (<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">Colloca et&#x000a0;al. 2008</xref>). Altogether, this evidence suggests that when the placebo intervention is spatially localized, the resulting sensory, motor, or neurophysiological effects are specific to the body part or muscle treated.</p><p>It should be noted that in our study the placebo treatment had some characteristics that could have favored a &#x0201c;spatially localized effect.&#x0201d; First, the placebo consisted of a tangible device (i.e. TENS) that was clearly applied over a specific body part (i.e. the forearm). Second, the placebo device was expected to affect a task involving a restricted body district (i.e. the right thumb). Consequently, given these characteristics, it was reasonable to expect that the placebo effect could be explicitly localized to the right hand. Although predictable, this result represents the first experimental behavioral and neurophysiological evidence for a spatial localization effect of a placebo device in the motor domain. Therefore, our study could provide a benchmark for comparing the effects of less tangible types of placebos (e.g. oral pills, oxygen inhalation, etc.) on movements performed with one or multiple body districts. To date, only one study on pain (<xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">Kong et&#x000a0;al. 2013</xref>) has tried to compare different types of placebos, demonstrating that verbally suggested placebo pills or sham needles can induce different responses and supporting the idea that the type of intervention could likely play a role in shaping the placebo effect.</p></sec><sec id="s4-s2"><title>A dissociation between behavioral and subjective variables</title><p>While the placebo group showed a shortening of RTs on the right hand, the two control groups showed an increase in RTs from the baseline to the test session. A possible explanation for this result could be related to the mindset instilled in all participants from the beginning of the procedure. In fact, before signing the consent form, all participants read an information sheet in which the general objective of the project was passed off as research on a new TENS intervention to improve motor performance. This could have fueled certain expectations about the nature of the study. Therefore, while participants assigned to the placebo group found these expectations met, those assigned to the control groups may have had the feeling that the intervention had been denied (either because it had been applied at inert frequencies, as the control TENS group was told, or because they had not received TENS at all, as was the case with the control NoTENS group). We could reason that a sort of &#x0201c;negative mindset&#x0201d; was induced in the control groups, thus consequently worsening motor performance on the right hand in test session. This hypothesis should be tested in future studies in which a nocebo group will be included (i.e. a group that receives the same TENS device with negative verbal information). The lack of modulation on the left hand could be interpreted in the light of previous evidence showing that motor performance of the nondominant hand is typically slower than the dominant hand (<xref rid="R55" ref-type="bibr">Todor and Kyprie 1980</xref>, <xref rid="R56" ref-type="bibr">Todor et&#x000a0;al. 1982</xref>, <xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">Heuer 2007</xref>). Since our participants were mostly right-handed (87.5% in the placebo group, 81.3% in the control TENS group, and 93.8% in the control NoTENS group), we can speculate that the left hand performance was overall slow, and this might have limited further worsening of RTs in the test phase, as a sort of &#x0201c;floor&#x0201d; effect. Future research with longer task durations may allow us to investigate whether performance impairment would occur in the control groups on the left hand.</p><p>Although they were objectively faster with their right hand, participants of the placebo group perceived themselves as faster with their left hand after the placebo procedure, hinting at a dissociation between the behavioral and subjective levels. Again, given that most participants were right-handed, we could hypothesize that they may have been imprecise in judging the performance of the left, nondominant hand, thus subjectively reporting an improvement that, however, was not objectively detected. A similar dissociation was described in a previous study in which participants reported perceiving the positive effects of a placebo treatment on performance despite the lack of effect detected by the objective measure of actual performance (<xref rid="R52" ref-type="bibr">Schwarz et&#x000a0;al. 2015</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-s3"><title>The placebo effect through the lens of active inference</title><p>Our findings can be interpreted according to the active inference account (<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">Adams et&#x000a0;al. 2013</xref>). If we consider verbal suggestion as a contextual psychosocial factor that can shape internal predictions (<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">Kaptchuk et&#x000a0;al. 2020</xref>, <xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr">Pagnini et&#x000a0;al. 2023</xref>), we can hypothesize that the information provided to participants assigned to the placebo group could have acted as a reliable contextual cue regarding the achievable speed, thus modeling precise internal predictions about the consequence of the motor act (i.e. faster performance at the thumb abduction task). Therefore, individuals in the placebo group likely updated their internal predictions on the upcoming action based on the verbal suggestion received. In other words, the expectancy of being faster at the motor task could have induced a peculiar mindset characterized by positive and precise internal predictions about motor performance. The subjective data support this hypothesis, as the placebo group had a strong expectancy about the effects of TENS in speeding up RTs and a strong belief that TENS was an effective intervention.</p><p>This mindset could have impacted both the behavioral level, with faster movements in the placebo group, and the neurophysiological, with an amplified premovement facilitation. The latter could be interpreted as a sign of precise internal predictions about the upcoming movement outcome (i.e. faster RTs). In keeping with this interpretation, a previous TMS study showed that the presence of reliable prior information about an upcoming motor response (like, for instance, a visual cue indicative of the effector to be moved) induced an increase in MEP amplitude, specific for the muscle involved in the task (<xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">Mars et&#x000a0;al. 2007</xref>). Consistently, another TMS study showed that MEP amplitude increased in the preparatory phase in trials characterized by valid cues compared to trials characterized by invalid cues (<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">Bestmann et&#x000a0;al. 2008</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-s4"><title>Limitations and concluding remarks</title><p>It should be acknowledged that our study presents some limitations. First, our sample was predominantly represented by right-handers and therefore we cannot clarify whether the side of the body on which the placebo device was applied interacted with handedness in determining the placebo effects observed here.</p><p>Second, we did not directly measure fatigue and fatigability in our study and therefore we cannot completely exclude the presence of fatigue in our participants, especially in the two control groups (<xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">Langner et&#x000a0;al. 2010</xref>, <xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">Jaydari Fard et&#x000a0;al. 2019</xref>). Nonetheless, we consider a potential effect of fatigue on our data very unlikely, because (i) the conditions in which participants were required to perform the RT task (i.e. the Task-only and the TMS<sub>Task</sub>) were interleaved by a rest period (i.e. TMS<sub>Rest</sub> condition); (ii) the baseline and test sessions were interleaved by 4&#x02009;min rest, thus further allowing for recovery; (iii) the abduction movements of the RT task were very brief and separated by an intertrial interval of about 8&#x02009;s; (iv) the task did not require exerting maximum voluntary muscle contraction or certain levels of force, as typically required in fatigue inducing tasks (<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">Enoka and Duchateau 2007</xref>). Considering all these aspects, we would exclude the effect of fatigue on our results.</p><p>Third, we focused on the corticospinal tract, leaving open the question on the role of other brain regions in modulating these effects. Namely, a reasonable hypothesis is that the neural bases of our findings may be related to a complex brain network involved in motor control. As anticipated above, motor-related brain areas have been already shown to play a role in the placebo effect (<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">Fiorio 2018</xref>). In this regard, we hypothesize that the dorsolateral prefrontal cortex (DLPFC) may play a fundamental role, being a brain region involved in processing expectation and often being active in neuroimaging studies on the placebo effect (<xref rid="R63" ref-type="bibr">Wager et&#x000a0;al. 2004</xref>, <xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">Kong et&#x000a0;al. 2006</xref>, <xref rid="R64" ref-type="bibr">Watson et&#x000a0;al. 2009</xref>, <xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">Krummenacher et&#x000a0;al. 2010</xref>, <xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>, <xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">Lui et&#x000a0;al. 2010</xref>, <xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">Geuter et&#x000a0;al. 2013</xref>, <xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">Jubb and Bensing 2013</xref>, <xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr">Peci&#x000f1;a et&#x000a0;al. 2013</xref>, <xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">Egorova et&#x000a0;al. 2015</xref>, <xref rid="R60" ref-type="bibr">Villa&#x02010;S&#x000e1;nchez et&#x000a0;al. 2018</xref>). Interestingly, the DLPFC has functional connections with M1 and is involved, together with other frontal regions, in the cognitive control of motor behavior (<xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">Miller and Cohen 2001</xref>, <xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">Hasan et&#x000a0;al. 2013</xref>). Therefore, our hypothesis is that the positive expectations induced by the placebo procedure might recruit the DLPFC and strengthen its projections to M1, thus enhancing corticospinal excitability before movement onset and consequently speeding up movement execution.</p><p>These limitations notwithstanding, our study represents the first demonstration that the corticospinal tract from M1 can be boosted by the placebo effect before movement onset, thus, in turn, facilitating movement preparation and execution. This study contributes to broadening our understanding of how expectancy influences motor behavior and the complex neural circuits underlying motor control and provides experimental support for the active inference account. Albeit cautiously, this investigation encourages future advances in the clinical field, where tailored placebo procedures could be used to address individuals&#x02019; spared motor resources, potentially supporting motor recovery.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="sup1" position="float" content-type="local-data"><label>nsaf014_Supp</label><media xlink:href="nsaf014_supp.zip"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><sec id="s5"><title>Supplementary data</title><p>
<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary data</xref> is available at <italic toggle="yes">SCAN</italic> online.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s6"><title>Conflict of interest:</title><p>All authors declare that they have no conflicts of interest.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Funding</title><p>M.F. was supported by #NEXTGENERATIONEU (NGEU) and funded by the Ministry of University and Research (MUR) under the National Recovery and Resilience Plan (NRRP), project MNESYS (PE0000006) &#x0201c;A Multiscale Integrated Approach to the Study of the Nervous System in Health and Disease&#x0201d; (DN. 1553 11.10.2022). M.F. and E.C. were funded by the PRIN 2022 for the project 2022AL38E4 &#x02013; &#x0201c;Ergogenic Words, which characterizes the cognitive and neural mechanisms of the placebo effect in the motor domain.&#x0201d;</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s8"><title>Data availability</title><p>The data underlying this article will be shared upon reasonable request to the corresponding author.</p></sec><ref-list id="ref1"><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Adams</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shipp</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Friston</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>KJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Predictions not commands: active inference in the motor system</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brain Struct Funct</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2013</year>;<volume>218</volume>:<fpage>611</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>43</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00429-012-0475-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23129312</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Beedie</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Foad</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The placebo effect in sports performance</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sports Med</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2009</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>313</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>29</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2165/00007256-200939040-00004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19317519</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Benedetti</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Arduino</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Amanzio</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Somatotopic activation of opioid systems by target-directed expectations of analgesia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Neurosci</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>1999</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>3639</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>48</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/jneurosci.19-09-03639.1999</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10212322</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Bestmann</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harrison</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Blankenburg</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>F</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al</etal>. <article-title>Influence of uncertainty and surprise on human corticospinal excitability during preparation for action</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Biol</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2008</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>775</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>80</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2008.04.051</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18485711</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Biabani</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Farrell</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zoghi</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al</etal>. <article-title>The minimal number of TMS trials required for the reliable assessment of corticospinal excitability, short interval intracortical inhibition, and intracortical facilitation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurosci Lett</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2018</year>;<volume>674</volume>:<fpage>94</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>100</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neulet.2018.03.026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29551425</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Brown</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Friston</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bestmann</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Active inference, attention, and motor preparation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Psychol</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2011</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<page-range>218</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2011.00218</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>B&#x000fc;chel</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Geuter</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sprenger</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>C</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al</etal>. <article-title>Placebo analgesia: a predictive coding perspective</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuron</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2014</year>;<volume>81</volume>:<fpage>1223</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>39</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2014.02.042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24656247</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Cavaleri</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schabrun</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chipchase</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>LS</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The number of stimuli required to reliably assess corticomotor excitability and primary motor cortical representations using transcranial magnetic stimulation (TMS): a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Syst Rev</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2017</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<page-range>48</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13643-017-0440-8</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Chen</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yaseen</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cohen</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>LG</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al</etal>. <article-title>Time course of corticospinal excitability in reaction time and self&#x02010;paced movements</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Neurol</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>1998</year>;<volume>44</volume>:<fpage>317</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>25</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ana.410440306</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9749597</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Cirillo</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Di Vico</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>IA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Andani</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al</etal>. <article-title>Changes in corticospinal circuits during premovement facilitation in physiological conditions</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Human Neurosci</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2021</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<page-range>684013</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnhum.2021.684013</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Cohen</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>
</person-group>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Statistical Power Analysis for the Behavioral Sciences</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge eBooks</publisher-name>, <year>1988</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Colloca</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tinazzi</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Recchia</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al</etal>. <article-title>Learning potentiates neurophysiological and behavioral placebo analgesic responses</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PAIN</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2008</year>;<volume>139</volume>:<fpage>306</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pain.2008.04.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18538928</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Corsi</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Emadi Andani</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sometti</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>D</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al</etal>. <article-title>When words hurt: verbal suggestion prevails over conditioning in inducing the motor nocebo effect</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Neurosci</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2019</year>;<volume>50</volume>:<fpage>3311</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>26</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ejn.14489</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31209960</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Duqu&#x000e9;</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lew</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mazzocchio</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al</etal>. <article-title>Evidence for two concurrent inhibitory mechanisms during response preparation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Neurosci</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2010</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>3793</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>802</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/jneurosci.5722-09.2010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20220014</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Egorova</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yu</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kaur</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>N</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al</etal>. <article-title>Neuromodulation of conditioned placebo/nocebo in heat pain: anodal vs cathodal transcranial direct current stimulation to the right dorsolateral prefrontal cortex</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PAIN</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2015</year>;<volume>156</volume>:<fpage>1342</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>47</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/j.pain.0000000000000163</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25806605</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Emadi Andani</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barbiani</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bonetto</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al</etal>. <article-title>Preserving the placebo effect after disclosure: a new perspective on non&#x02010;deceptive placebos</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Br J Psychol</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2024</year>;<volume>115</volume>:<fpage>437</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>53</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/bjop.12696</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38226695</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Emadi Andani</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tinazzi</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Corsi</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>N</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al</etal>. <article-title>Modulation of inhibitory corticospinal circuits induced by a nocebo procedure in motor performance</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLOS ONE</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2015</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<page-range>e0125223</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0125223</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Enoka</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>RM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duchateau</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Muscle fatigue: what, why and how it influences muscle function</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Physiol</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2007</year>;<volume>586</volume>:<fpage>11</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>23</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/jphysiol.2007.139477</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17702815</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Fagioli</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hommel</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schubotz</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>RI</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Intentional control of attention: action planning primes action-related stimulus dimensions</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychol Res</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2007</year>;<volume>71</volume>:<fpage>22</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>29</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00426-005-0033-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16317565</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Faul</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Erdfelder</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lang</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>AG</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al</etal>. <article-title>G*Power 3: a flexible statistical power analysis program for the social, behavioral, and biomedical sciences</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Behav Res Methods</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2007</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>175</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>91</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3758/bf03193146</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17695343</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Fiorio</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Modulation of the motor system by placebo and nocebo effects</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int Rev Neurobiol</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2018</year>;<volume>139</volume>:<fpage>297</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>319</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/bs.irn.2018.07.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30146052</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Fiorio</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Emadi Andani</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marotta</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al</etal>. <article-title>Placebo-induced changes in excitatory and inhibitory corticospinal circuits during motor performance</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Neurosci</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2014</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>3993</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4005</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/jneurosci.3931-13.2014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24623777</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Fiorio</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Villa&#x02010;S&#x000e1;nchez</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rossignati</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>F</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al</etal>. <article-title>The placebo effect shortens movement time in goal-directed movements</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Rep</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2022</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<page-range>19567</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-022-23489-y</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Friston</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>KJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Daunizeau</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kilner</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al</etal>. <article-title>Action and behavior: a free-energy formulation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biol Cybern</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2010</year>;<volume>102</volume>:<fpage>227</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>60</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00422-010-0364-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20148260</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Fritz</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>CO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morris</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>PE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Richler</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect size estimates: current use, calculations, and interpretation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Exp Psychol Gen</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2012</year>;<volume>141</volume>:<fpage>2</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>18</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/a0024338</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21823805</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Garcia-Sanz</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ghotme</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hedmont</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>D</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al</etal>. <article-title>Use of transcranial magnetic stimulation for studying the neural basis of numerical cognition: a systematic review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Neurosci Methods</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2022</year>;<volume>369</volume>:<page-range>109485</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jneumeth.2022.109485</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Geuter</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eippert</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Attar</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>CH</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al</etal>. <article-title>Cortical and subcortical responses to high and low effective placebo treatments</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">NeuroImage</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2013</year>;<volume>67</volume>:<fpage>227</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>36</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2012.11.029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23201367</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Hasan</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Galea</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Casula</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>EP</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al</etal>. <article-title>Muscle and timing-specific functional connectivity between the dorsolateral prefrontal cortex and the primary motor cortex</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Cognitive Neurosci</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2013</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>558</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>70</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1162/jocn_a_00338</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Heuer</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Control of the dominant and nondominant hand: exploitation and taming of nonmuscular forces</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Exp Brain Res</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2007</year>;<volume>178</volume>:<fpage>363</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>73</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00221-006-0747-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17103210</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Hiraoka</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kamata</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Matsugi</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al</etal>. <article-title>Premovement facilitation of corticospinal excitability before simple and sequential movement</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Perceptual Motor Skills</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2010</year>;<volume>111</volume>:<fpage>129</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>40</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2466/15.25.27.pms.111.4.129-140</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21058594</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Hurst</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Beedie</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>C</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Placebo Effects in Sport and Exercise</italic></source>. <edition>1st</edition> edn. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>, <year>2023</year>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4324/9781003229001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Jaydari Fard</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tahmasebi Boroujeni</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lavender</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>AP</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Mental fatigue impairs simple reaction time in non-athletes more than athletes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Fatigue</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2019</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>117</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>26</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/21641846.2019.1632614</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Jubb</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bensing</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The sweetest pill to swallow: how patient neurobiology can be harnessed to maximise placebo effects</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurosci Biobehav Rev</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2013</year>;<volume>37</volume>:<fpage>2709</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neubiorev.2013.09.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24055773</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Kaptchuk</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>TJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hemond</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>CC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Miller</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>FG</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Placebos in chronic pain: evidence, theory, ethics, and use in clinical practice</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Br Med J</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2020</year>;<volume>370</volume>:<page-range>m1668</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.m1668</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Kong</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gollub</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rosman</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>IS</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al</etal>. <article-title>Brain activity associated with expectancy-enhanced placebo analgesia as measured by functional magnetic resonance imaging</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Neurosci</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2006</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>381</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>88</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/jneurosci.3556-05.2006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16407533</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Kong</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Spaeth</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cook</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al</etal>. <article-title>Are all placebo effects equal? Placebo pills, sham acupuncture, cue conditioning and their association</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLOS ONE</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2013</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<page-range>e67485</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0067485</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Krummenacher</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Candia</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Folkers</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>G</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al</etal>. <article-title>Prefrontal cortex modulates placebo analgesia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PAIN</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2010</year>;<volume>148</volume>:<fpage>368</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>74</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pain.2009.09.033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19875233</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Langner</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Steinborn</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>MB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chatterjee</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al</etal>. <article-title>Mental fatigue and temporal preparation in simple reaction-time performance</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Acta Psychologica</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2010</year>;<volume>133</volume>:<fpage>64</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>72</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.actpsy.2009.10.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19878913</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Lui</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Colloca</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duzzi</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>D</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al</etal>. <article-title>Neural bases of conditioned placebo analgesia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pain</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2010</year>;<volume>151</volume>:<fpage>816</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>24</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pain.2010.09.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20943318</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Mars</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>RB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bestmann</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rothwell</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al</etal>. <article-title>Effects of motor preparation and spatial attention on corticospinal excitability in a delayed-response paradigm</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Exp Brain Res</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2007</year>;<volume>182</volume>:<fpage>125</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>29</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00221-007-1055-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17634929</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Miller</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>EK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cohen</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>An integrative theory of prefrontal cortex function</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Annu Rev Neurosci</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2001</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>167</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>202</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.neuro.24.1.167</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11283309</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Morgante</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dattola</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Crupi</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>D</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al</etal>. <article-title>Is central fatigue in multiple sclerosis a disorder of movement preparation?</article-title> &#x000a0;<source><italic toggle="yes">J Neurol</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2011</year>;<volume>258</volume>:<fpage>263</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>72</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00415-010-5742-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20859746</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Ongaro</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kaptchuk</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>TJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Symptom perception, placebo effects, and the Bayesian brain</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pain</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2019</year>;<volume>160</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/j.pain.0000000000001367</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30086114</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Pagnini</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barbiani</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cavalera</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>C</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al</etal>. <article-title>Placebo and nocebo effects as Bayesian-brain phenomena: the overlooked role of likelihood and attention</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Perspectives Psychol Sci</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2023</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>1217</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>29</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/17456916221141383</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Peci&#x000f1;a</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stohler</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>CS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zubieta</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Neurobiology of placebo effects: expectations or learning?</article-title> &#x000a0;<source><italic toggle="yes">Soc Cognit Affective Neurosci</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2013</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>1013</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>21</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/scan/nst079</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Pellicciari</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Miniussi</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ferrari</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>C</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al</etal>. <article-title>Ongoing cumulative effects of single TMS pulses on corticospinal excitability: an intra- and inter-block investigation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Neurophysiol</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2016</year>;<volume>127</volume>:<fpage>621</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>28</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clinph.2015.03.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25823698</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Pezzulo</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ognibene</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>D</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Proactive action preparation: seeing action preparation as a continuous and proactive process</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Motor Control</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2012</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>386</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>424</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1123/mcj.16.3.386</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22643383</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Piedimonte</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Benedetti</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carlino</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>E</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Placebo-induced decrease in fatigue: evidence for a central action on the preparatory phase of movement</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Neurosci</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2015</year>;<volume>41</volume>:<fpage>492</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>97</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ejn.12806</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25522899</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Rossettini</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Andani</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Negra</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>FD</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al</etal>. <article-title>The placebo effect in the motor domain is differently modulated by the external and internal focus of attention</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Rep</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2018</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<page-range>12296</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-30228-9</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Rossi</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hallett</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rossini</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>PM</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al</etal>. <article-title>Safety, ethical considerations, and application guidelines for the use of transcranial magnetic stimulation in clinical practice and research</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Neurophysiol</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2009</year>;<volume>120</volume>:<fpage>2008</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>39</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clinph.2009.08.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19833552</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Rossini</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zarola</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>St&#x000e5;lberg</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>E</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al</etal>. <article-title>Pre-movement facilitation of motor-evoked potentials in man during transcranial stimulation of the central motor pathways</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brain Res</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>1988</year>;<volume>458</volume>:<fpage>20</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>30</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0006-8993(88)90491-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3208099</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Schwarz</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>B&#x000fc;chel</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Costantini</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Cognition and the placebo effect &#x02013; dissociating subjective perception and actual performance</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLOS One</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2015</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<page-range>e0130492</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0130492</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Smith</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Friston</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>KJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Whyte</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>A step-by-step tutorial on active inference and its application to empirical data</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Math Psychol</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2022</year>;<volume>107</volume>:<page-range>102632</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jmp.2021.102632</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Temesi</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gruet</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rupp</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>T</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al</etal>. <article-title>Resting and active motor thresholds versus stimulus&#x02013;response curves to determine transcranial magnetic stimulation intensity in quadriceps femoris</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Neuroeng Rehabil</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2014</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<page-range>40</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1743-0003-11-40</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Todor</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kyprie</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>PM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Hand differences in the rate and variability of rapid tapping</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Motor Behav</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>1980</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>57</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>62</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00222895.1980.10735205</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Todor</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kyprie</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Price</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>HL</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Lateral asymmetries in arm, wrist and finger movements</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cortex</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>1982</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>515</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>23</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0010-9452(82)80050-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7166039</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Tomczak</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tomczak</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>E</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The need to report effect size estimates revisited. an overview of some recommended measures of effect size</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Trends Sport Sci</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2014</year>;<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>19</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>25</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>van Doorn</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ly</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marsman</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al</etal>. <article-title>Bayesian rank-based hypothesis testing for the rank sum test, the signed rank test, and Spearman&#x02019;s &#x003c1;</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Appl Stat</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2020</year>;<volume>47</volume>:<fpage>2984</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3006</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/02664763.2019.1709053</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35707708</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Villa&#x02010;S&#x000e1;nchez</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Emadi Andani</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cesari</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>P</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al</etal>. <article-title>The effect of motor and cognitive placebos on the serial reaction time task</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Neurosci</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2021</year>;<volume>53</volume>:<fpage>2655</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>68</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ejn.15148</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33587782</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Villa&#x02010;S&#x000e1;nchez</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Emadi Andani</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fiorio</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The role of the dorsolateral prefrontal cortex in the motor placebo effect</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Neurosci</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2018</year>;<volume>48</volume>:<fpage>3410</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>25</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ejn.14217</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30362195</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Villa&#x02010;S&#x000e1;nchez</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Emadi Andani</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Menegaldo</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>G</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al</etal>. <article-title>Positive verbal suggestion optimizes postural control</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Rep</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2019</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<page-range>6408</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-42888-2</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Villa&#x02010;S&#x000e1;nchez</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gandolfi</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Emadi Andani</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al</etal>. <article-title>Placebo effect on gait: a way to reduce the dual-task cost in older adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Exp Brain Res</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2023</year>;<volume>241</volume>:<fpage>1501</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00221-023-06620-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37085646</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Wager</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>TD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rilling</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smith</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>EE</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al</etal>. <article-title>Placebo-Induced changes in FMRI in the anticipation and experience of pain</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Science</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2004</year>;<volume>303</volume>:<fpage>1162</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>67</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1093065</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14976306</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R64"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Watson</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>El&#x02010;Deredy</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Iannetti</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>GD</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al</etal>. <article-title>Placebo conditioning and placebo analgesia modulate a common brain network during pain anticipation and perception</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pain</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2009</year>;<volume>145</volume>:<fpage>24</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>30</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pain.2009.04.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19523766</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>