<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="issn">2168-8184</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cureus</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2168-8184</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cureus</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Palo Alto (CA)</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12102635</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7759/cureus.82865</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Neurology</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Urology</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Physical Medicine &#x00026; Rehabilitation</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Effect of Oxybutynin on Detrusor Leak Point Pressure in Spinal Cord Injury Patients With Neurogenic Detrusor Overactivity: A Subgroup Analysis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Muacevic</surname><given-names>Alexander</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>John R</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bharti</surname><given-names>Vineet</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>Mrinal</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Saini</surname><given-names>Neha</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff-1">
<label>1</label>
Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation, Employees State Insurance Corporation (ESIC) Medical College and Hospital, Faridabad, IND </aff><aff id="aff-2">
<label>2</label>
Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation, Sawai Man Singh (SMS) Medical College, Jaipur, IND </aff><aff id="aff-3">
<label>3</label>
Microbiology, Vardhman Mahavir Medical College and Safdarjung Hospital, Faridabad, IND </aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">
Neha Saini <email>coolneha67@gmail.com</email>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>23</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic"><month>4</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>17</volume><issue>4</issue><elocation-id>e82865</elocation-id><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2025, Bharti et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Bharti et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License CC-BY 4.0., which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="https://www.cureus.com/articles/360680-effect-of-oxybutynin-on-detrusor-leak-point-pressure-in-spinal-cord-injury-patients-with-neurogenic-detrusor-overactivity-a-subgroup-analysis">This article is available from https://www.cureus.com/articles/360680-effect-of-oxybutynin-on-detrusor-leak-point-pressure-in-spinal-cord-injury-patients-with-neurogenic-detrusor-overactivity-a-subgroup-analysis</self-uri><abstract><p>Following spinal cord injury, neurogenic detrusor overactivity elevates detrusor leak point pressure, endangering renal function. This research examined oxybutynin's effects on detrusor leak point pressure and urodynamic parameters in 30 individuals with spinal cord injury and neurogenic detrusor overactivity, emphasizing variations across subgroups. Patients were given 5 mg of oxybutynin each day for a week, with urodynamic assessments conducted pre- and post-treatment. Decreases in detrusor leak point pressure were noted, especially among those with detrusor hyperreflexia combined with detrusor sphincter dyssynergia, cervical-level injuries, and injuries exceeding six months. Improvements in bladder compliance and capacity occurred universally, yet detrusor leak point pressure reductions differed by subgroup. Oxybutynin proves useful in reducing detrusor leak point pressure in vulnerable spinal cord injury patients, promoting its application in customized neurogenic detrusor overactivity care.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>bladder compliance</kwd><kwd>cervical injury</kwd><kwd>chronic injury</kwd><kwd>detrusor hyperreflexia</kwd><kwd>detrusor leak point pressure</kwd><kwd>neurogenic detrusor overactivity</kwd><kwd>oxybutynin</kwd><kwd>spinal cord injury</kwd><kwd>subgroup analysis</kwd><kwd>urodynamics</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Spinal cord injury (SCI) is a profound condition often caused by traumatic incidents, such as motor vehicle crashes or falls, or non-traumatic factors such as vascular disorders or infections [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Globally, traumatic SCI incidence spans 3.6 to 195.4 cases per million people annually, with developing countries averaging 25.5 cases per million [<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Over the past seven decades, enhanced medical interventions, particularly in urinary tract care, have significantly extended survival, reducing mortality from urological issues [<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Neurogenic bladder dysfunction affects over 90% of SCI patients, heightening risks of urinary tract infections (UTIs), kidney damage, and bladder stones [<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>].</p><p>Urodynamic assessments have revolutionized the management of bladder dysfunction post-SCI, revealing how neurogenic detrusor overactivity (NDO), characterized by involuntary detrusor contractions during filling, increases detrusor leak point pressure (DLPP) [<xref rid="REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. A DLPP exceeding 40 cm H&#x02082;O threatens upper urinary tract health, potentially causing vesico-ureteric reflux (VUR) and renal impairment [<xref rid="REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Effective treatment focuses on preserving kidney function and enhancing the quality of life by maintaining low bladder storage pressures and improving compliance [<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].</p><p>Oxybutynin, an antimuscarinic medication with muscle-relaxant properties, is a primary therapy for NDO [<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Its metabolite, N-desethyl oxybutynin, suppresses unintended bladder contractions by inhibiting muscarinic receptors [<xref rid="REF11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Combined with clean intermittent catheterization (CIC), it achieves renal protection and continence in over 90% of patients [<xref rid="REF12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Despite its global use, evidence about its effectiveness in specific contexts, such as India, is limited. This study evaluates oxybutynin's impact on DLPP, bladder compliance, and capacity in SCI patients with NDO, analyzing variations across injury and clinical subgroups.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><p>Study design and setting</p><p>This prospective, non-randomized interventional study was conducted at the Department of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation, Sawai Man Singh (SMS) Medical College and Hospitals, Jaipur, India, from July 2015 to September 2016.</p><p>Participants</p><p>Thirty SCI patients with urodynamically confirmed NDO were enrolled via consecutive sampling. Inclusion criteria included age over 18 years, SCI duration exceeding three months (post-spinal shock), American Spinal Injury Association (ASIA) classification A-D, DLPP above 40 cm H&#x02082;O, and informed consent. Exclusion criteria encompassed medications altering bladder function, conditions complicating urodynamic tests, detrusor areflexia, active UTIs, or oxybutynin contraindications (e.g., glaucoma). The sample size was calculated as 26, based on a 96.3 mL mean difference in cystometric capacity (SD 167.71), with an alpha of 0.05 and 80% power, increased to 30 to account for 10% attrition.</p><p>Intervention</p><p>Participants were given 5 mg of oral oxybutynin daily for seven days. Those with UTIs (symptomatic or asymptomatic) received seven days of antibiotics, guided by urine culture sensitivity, before urodynamic assessments.</p><p>Urodynamic evaluation</p><p>Pre- and post-treatment urodynamic tests were performed using a Laborie urodynamic system (Laborie Medical Technologies, Portsmouth, New Hampshire, USA). The protocol involved cystometry (filling and voiding phases) and perineal electromyography (EMG) in a supine right oblique position. Intravesical pressure was measured via a 7F double-lumen catheter, and abdominal pressure via a 10F rectal catheter. Bladder filling occurred at 10 mL/minute with 2% xylocaine jelly lubrication. Measured parameters included DLPP, bladder compliance (mL/cm H&#x02082;O), and capacity (mL).</p><p>Statistical analysis</p><p>Paired t-tests evaluated changes in urodynamic outcomes, with subgroup analyses based on detrusor hyperreflexia (DH) with/without detrusor sphincter dyssynergia (DSD), injury level (cervical vs. dorsal/lumbar), and injury duration (&#x0003e;6 months vs. &#x02264;6 months). Chi-square tests assessed associations between neurological level/ASIA grade and bladder patterns. Significance was defined as P &#x0003c; 0.05.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p>Participant characteristics</p><p>Of the 30 participants, 93.3% were male, 53.3% were 30 years or younger, and 63.3% had formal education. Most injuries (56.7%) were less than six months old, primarily caused by falls (46.7%) or road traffic accidents (43.3%). Cervical and lower dorsal injuries comprised 80% of cases, with 86.7% classified as ASIA A. Bladder patterns included 73.3% with DH and DSD, 23.3% with DH alone, and 86.7% lacked a bulbocavernosus reflex.</p><p>Urodynamic outcomes</p><p>Overall, DLPP decreased from 56.19 &#x000b1; 35.36 to 42.39 &#x000b1; 46.11 cm H&#x02082;O (P=0.036, t=1.988), compliance improved from 6.11 &#x000b1; 10.59 to 17.95 &#x000b1; 33.16 mL/cm H&#x02082;O (P=0.023, t=-2.393), and capacity rose from 165.3 &#x000b1; 163.8 to 229.7 &#x000b1; 184.5 mL (P&#x0003c;0.001, t=-3.872).</p><p>Subgroup analysis</p><p>Subgroup analysis revealed varied responses to oxybutynin treatment across different patient characteristics, as detailed in Tables <xref rid="TAB1" ref-type="table">1</xref>,&#x000a0;<xref rid="TAB2" ref-type="table">2</xref>. Significant reductions in DLPP&#x000a0;were observed in patients with DH&#x000a0;combined with DSD, those with cervical injuries, and individuals with chronic injuries exceeding six months. In contrast, patients with DH alone or dorsal/lumbar injuries showed less pronounced changes in DLPP. Bladder capacity increased significantly across most subgroups, particularly in those with DH and DSD, cervical injuries, and chronic injuries, with notable improvements in compliance for the DH with DSD and cervical injury subgroups.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Changes in Detrusor Leak Point Pressure (DLPP) Across Subgroups</title><p>DH: Detrusor Hyperreflexia; DSD: Detrusor Sphincter Dyssynergia; DLPP: Detrusor Leak Point Pressure</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Subgroup
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
N
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Pre-DLPP (cm H&#x02082;O)
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Post-DLPP (cm H&#x02082;O)
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
P-value
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
t-value
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
DH with DSD
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
22
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
55.3 &#x000b1; 37.17
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
38.96 &#x000b1; 28.02
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
0.017
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
2.62
</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
DH Alone
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
8
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
58.64 &#x000b1; 32.01
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
51.8 &#x000b1; 79.46
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
0.745
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
0.33
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Cervical
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
12
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
47.77 &#x000b1; 25.87
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
33.18 &#x000b1; 27.55
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
0.005
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
3.52
</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Dorsal/Lumbar
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
18
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
61.81 &#x000b1; 40.2
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
48.52 &#x000b1; 55.1
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
0.259
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
1.17
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
&#x0003e;6 Months
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
13
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
53.43 &#x000b1; 42.58
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
33.06 &#x000b1; 27.99
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
0.008
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
3.00
</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
&#x02264;6 Months
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
17
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
58.51 &#x000b1; 29.92
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
49.52 &#x000b1; 57.16
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
0.446
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
0.78
</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Changes in Bladder Capacity Across Subgroups</title><p>DH: Detrusor Hyperreflexia; DSD: Detrusor Sphincter Dyssynergia</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subgroup</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre-Capacity (mL)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post-Capacity (mL)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-value</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">t-value</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DH with DSD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">152.3 &#x000b1; 170.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">240.8 &#x000b1; 195.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.89</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DH Alone</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">198.7 &#x000b1; 160.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">203.5 &#x000b1; 175.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.842</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cervical</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">175.9 &#x000b1; 180.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">235.4 &#x000b1; 205.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.85</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dorsal/Lumbar</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">158.6 &#x000b1; 160.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">225.8 &#x000b1; 183.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.22</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;6 Months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">170.2 &#x000b1; 175.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">245.6 &#x000b1; 200.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.33</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;6 Months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">162.1 &#x000b1; 163.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">216.9 &#x000b1; 184.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.91</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Oxybutynin at 5 mg daily for one week reduced DLPP in SCI patients with NDO, with significant effects in those with DH and DSD (P = 0.017), cervical injuries (P = 0.005), and chronic injuries over six months (P = 0.008). This aligns with its mechanism, antagonizing muscarinic receptors and relaxing the detrusor muscle, effectively curbing overactivity [<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="REF13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. The notable DLPP reduction in the DH with DSD subgroup underscores its efficacy in managing combined detrusor sphincter dysfunction, consistent with prior findings [<xref rid="REF14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Cervical injury patients showed a strong response, likely due to higher baseline pressures from upper spinal lesions, as noted in studies linking injury level to bladder dynamics [<xref rid="REF15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].</p><p>Chronic injuries (&#x0003e;6 months) exhibited robust improvements, possibly reflecting stabilized neural changes that enhance treatment response [<xref rid="REF16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Bladder compliance improved significantly in the DH with DSD and cervical subgroups (P &#x0003c; 0.001 and P = 0.019, respectively), while capacity increased universally, with the greatest gains in DH with DSD and chronic cases (P &#x0003c; 0.001) [<xref rid="REF17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. These results echo findings from Kim et al. (1997), who reported better compliance and lower DLPP with reduced hydronephrosis in SCI patients on oxybutynin [<xref rid="REF12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Similarly, Di Stasi et al. (2001) observed significant urodynamic improvements with oxybutynin in neurogenic bladder patients, reinforcing its therapeutic role [<xref rid="REF18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].</p><p>The lack of significant DLPP changes in DH alone, dorsal/lumbar injuries, and acute cases may stem from smaller subgroup sizes or variable baseline pressures, a pattern seen in Madhuvrata et al.'s (2012) review of anticholinergics for NDO [<xref rid="REF15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. This study's emphasis on urodynamic-guided therapy aligns with Linsenmeyer et al. (2013), who advocate regular urodynamic monitoring to optimize bladder management and prevent renal damage [<xref rid="REF16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Panicker et al. (2015) further support integrating clinical and urodynamic data for tailored NDO treatment [<xref rid="REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. The absence of correlation between neurological level or ASIA grade and bladder pattern (P = 0.800 and P = 0.599) supports Aggarwal and Joshi (2015), who noted discrepancies between somatic findings and urodynamic outcomes, advocating routine urodynamic evaluations [<xref rid="REF13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].</p><p>The limitations of this study include a modest sample size (n = 30), short treatment duration (one week), and a non-randomized design, which may introduce bias. The effectiveness of bladder emptying methods (e.g., CIC) could not be fully assessed due to limited subgroup numbers, though prior studies confirm CIC's safety in SCI management [<xref rid="REF19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Future research should involve larger, randomized trials comparing oxybutynin with newer agents like tolterodine or solifenacin, especially in resource-constrained settings where its low cost is advantageous [<xref rid="REF20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>].</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Oxybutynin at 5 mg daily effectively lowers DLPP and enhances bladder compliance and capacity in SCI patients with NDO, with superior outcomes in DH with DSD, cervical injuries, and chronic cases (&#x0003e;6 months). These results support its use for personalized bladder management, particularly in high-risk patients, and highlight its value due to broad efficacy and affordability. Larger studies comparing it to modern alternatives could refine its application, but its cost-effectiveness makes it a practical choice for NDO treatment in regions like India.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group content-type="conflict"><title>Disclosures</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Human subjects:</bold> Consent for treatment and open access publication was obtained or waived by all participants in this study. Office of the Ethics Committee, SMS Medical College &#x00026; Attached Hospital, Jaipur, issued approval 2747/MC/EC/2016.</p><p><bold>Animal subjects:</bold> All authors have confirmed that this study did not involve animal subjects or tissue.</p><p><bold>Conflicts of interest:</bold> In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following:</p><p><bold>Payment/services info:</bold> All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work.</p><p><bold>Financial relationships:</bold> All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work.</p><p><bold>Other relationships:</bold> All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="other"><title>Author Contributions</title><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Concept and design:</bold>&#x000a0; Vineet Bharti, Mrinal Joshi, Neha Saini</p><p><bold>Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data:</bold>&#x000a0; Vineet Bharti, Mrinal Joshi, Neha Saini</p><p><bold>Drafting of the manuscript:</bold>&#x000a0; Vineet Bharti, Mrinal Joshi, Neha Saini</p><p><bold>Critical review of the manuscript for important intellectual content:</bold>&#x000a0; Vineet Bharti, Mrinal Joshi, Neha Saini</p><p><bold>Supervision:</bold>&#x000a0; Mrinal Joshi</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="REF1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Is 40 cm H2O detrusor leak point pressure cut-off reliable for upper urinary tract protection in children with myelodysplasia?</article-title><source>Neurourol Urodyn</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Tarcan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sekerci</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>759</fpage><lpage>763</lpage><volume>36</volume><year>2017</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27080436</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Global prevalence and incidence of traumatic spinal cord injury</article-title><source>Clin Epidemiol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tetreault</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kalsi-Ryan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nouri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fehlings</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>309</fpage><lpage>331</lpage><volume>6</volume><year>2014</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25278785</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Survival from spinal cord injury</article-title><source>J Chronic Dis</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Le</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>487</fpage><lpage>492</lpage><volume>35</volume><year>1982</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7076789</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>A prospective study of health and risk of mortality after spinal cord injury</article-title><source>Arch Phys Med Rehabil</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Krause</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pickelsimer</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>1482</fpage><lpage>1491</lpage><volume>89</volume><year>2008</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18674984</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Bladder management after spinal cord injury in the United States 1972 to 2005</article-title><source>J Urol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wallner</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tate</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sarma</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Clemens</surname><given-names>JQ</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>213</fpage><lpage>217</lpage><volume>184</volume><year>2010</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20478597</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>The development of urologic complications in relationship to bladder pressure in spinal cord injured patients</article-title><source>J Am Paraplegia Soc</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Shingleton</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bodner</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>14</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><volume>16</volume><year>1993</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8426179</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Lower urinary tract dysfunction in the neurological patient: clinical assessment and management</article-title><source>Lancet Neurol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Panicker</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fowler</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kessler</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>720</fpage><lpage>732</lpage><volume>14</volume><year>2015</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26067125</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Predicting renal calculus occurrence in spinal cord injury patients</article-title><source>Arch Phys Med Rehabil</source><person-group>
<name><surname>De Vivo</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fine</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>722</fpage><lpage>725</lpage><volume>67</volume><year>1986</year><uri xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/3767488/">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/3767488/</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3767621</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>The management of neurogenic bladder and sexual dysfunction after spinal cord injury</article-title><source>Spine (Phila Pa 1976)</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Burns</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rivas</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ditunno</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>0</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><volume>26</volume><year>2001</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Oxybutynin and the overactive bladder</article-title><source>World J Urol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chapple</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>319</fpage><lpage>323</lpage><volume>19</volume><year>2001</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11760780</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Medical management of neurogenic bladder with oral therapy</article-title><source>Transl Androl Urol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>51</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><volume>5</volume><year>2016</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26904412</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>The role of oxybutynin in spinal cord injured patients with indwelling catheters</article-title><source>J Urol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bird</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Priebe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>2083</fpage><lpage>2086</lpage><volume>158</volume><year>1997</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9366317</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Urodynamic patterns after traumatic spinal cord injury</article-title><source>J Spinal Cord Med</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Aggarwal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>128</fpage><lpage>133</lpage><volume>38</volume><year>2015</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24090106</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Association of level of injury and bladder behavior in patients with post-traumatic spinal cord injury</article-title><source>Urology</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Weld</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dmochowski</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>490</fpage><lpage>494</lpage><volume>55</volume><year>2000</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10736489</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Anticholinergic drugs for adult neurogenic detrusor overactivity: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Eur Urol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Madhuvrata</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hasafa</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Abdel-Fattah</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>816</fpage><lpage>850</lpage><volume>62</volume><year>2012</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22397851</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Impact of annual urodynamic evaluations on guiding bladder management in individuals with spinal cord injuries</article-title><source>J Spinal Cord Med</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Linsenmeyer</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Linsenmeyer</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>420</fpage><lpage>426</lpage><volume>36</volume><year>2013</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23941789</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Acute spinal cord injury&#x02014;do ambulatory patients need urodynamic investigations?</article-title><source>J Urol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Bellucci</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wollner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gregorini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>1369</fpage><lpage>1373</lpage><volume>189</volume><year>2013</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23069382</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Intravesical electromotive administration of oxybutynin in patients with detrusor hyperreflexia unresponsive to standard anticholinergic regimens</article-title><source>J Urol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Di Stasi</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Giannantoni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vespasiani</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Navarra</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Capelli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Massoud</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stephen</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>491</fpage><lpage>498</lpage><volume>165</volume><year>2001</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11176403</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>The neurogenic bladder in spinal cord injury--pattern and management</article-title><source>Ann Acad Med Singapore</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Chua</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tow</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>553</fpage><lpage>557</lpage><volume>25</volume><year>1996</year><uri xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/8893929/">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/8893929/</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8893929</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Detrusor function in suprasacral spinal cord injuries</article-title><source>J Urol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Light</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Beric</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>355</fpage><lpage>358</lpage><volume>148</volume><year>1992</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1635134</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>