<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" id="cre270080" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Clin Exp Dent Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Clin Exp Dent Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.1002/(ISSN)2057-4347</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CRE2</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Clinical and Experimental Dental Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2057-4347</issn><publisher><publisher-name>John Wiley and Sons Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Hoboken</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39888250</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11780601</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cre2.70080</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">CRE270080</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Assessing the Correlation Between Langerhans Cells Population and Prognosis of Tongue Squamous Cell Carcinoma</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="cre270080-cr-0001" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Ghazi</surname><given-names>Narges</given-names></name><xref rid="cre270080-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><address><email>nargesghazi10@gmail.com</email></address></contrib><contrib id="cre270080-cr-0002" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Saghravanian</surname><given-names>Nasrollah</given-names></name><xref rid="cre270080-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="cre270080-cr-0003" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Saeedi</surname><given-names>Pooya</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0009-0002-3213-4110</contrib-id><xref rid="cre270080-aff-0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="cre270080-cr-0004" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Maboudinezhad</surname><given-names>Mohammad Mahdi</given-names></name><xref rid="cre270080-aff-0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="cre270080-aff-0001">
<label>
<sup>1</sup>
</label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Department of Oral and Maxillofacial Pathology, School of Dentistry</named-content>
<institution>Mashhad University of Medical Sciences</institution>
<city>Mashhad</city>
<country country="IR">Iran</country>
</aff><aff id="cre270080-aff-0002">
<label>
<sup>2</sup>
</label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">School of Dentistry</named-content>
<institution>Mashhad University of Medical Sciences</institution>
<city>Mashhad</city>
<country country="IR">Iran</country>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="correspondenceTo">
<label>*</label>
<bold>Correspondence:</bold> Narges Ghazi (<email>nargesghazi10@gmail.com</email>)<break/>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>2</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue seq="59">1</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cre2.v11.1</issue-id><elocation-id>e70080</elocation-id><history>
<date date-type="rev-recd"><day>17</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></date>
<date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>2</month><year>2024</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></date>
</history><permissions><!--&#x000a9; 2025 The Author(s). Clinical and Experimental Dental Research published by John Wiley & Sons Ltd.--><copyright-statement content-type="article-copyright">&#x000a9; 2025 The Author(s). <italic toggle="yes">Clinical and Experimental Dental Research</italic> published by John Wiley &#x00026; Sons Ltd.</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link> License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="file:CRE2-11-e70080.pdf"/><abstract><title>ABSTRACT</title><sec id="cre270080-sec-0010"><title>Background and Objective</title><p>Tongue squamous cell carcinoma (TSCC) is the most prevalent oral cancer. Despite considerable advancements in treatment, the 5&#x02010;year survival rate remains relatively unchanged. Langerhans cells (LCs) play an important role in antitumor immunity. Therefore, we attempt to evaluate the correlation between the LC count and disease prognosis.</p></sec><sec id="cre270080-sec-0020"><title>Materials and Methods</title><p>Histopathologic slides from 24 cases, with at least 2 years of follow&#x02010;up, were selected and categorized into early&#x02010;stage (12 cases) and advanced&#x02010;stage (12 cases) groups. An additional 12 slides of normal tissue comprised the control group. Immunohistochemical staining with the CD1a marker was performed to analyze the density of LCs. Statistical analysis assessed the impact of CD1a immune expression on patient survival and other variables such as age, gender, stage, and histopathological grade.</p></sec><sec id="cre270080-sec-0030"><title>Results</title><p>Comparison of CD1a+ cell counts across the three groups revealed a significant decrease in the advanced group. Furthermore, a lower count of CD1a+ cells correlated with poorer disease&#x02010;free survival (DFS) (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001) and overall survival (OS) (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.049). Although the CD1a+ cell count did not independently affect OS significantly (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.210), it did show a significant impact on DFS as an independent variable (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.002).</p></sec><sec id="cre270080-sec-0040"><title>Conclusion</title><p>The significant correlation between CD1a expression and patients' prognosis and survival rates suggests that CD1a+ cells could serve as a crucial prognostic factor in the management and treatment of TSCC.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd id="cre270080-kwd-0001">CD1a</kwd><kwd id="cre270080-kwd-0002">Langerhans cell</kwd><kwd id="cre270080-kwd-0003">prognosis</kwd><kwd id="cre270080-kwd-0004">tongue squamous cell carcinoma</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="funding-0001"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>The study was supported by the Mashhad University of Medical Sciences.
</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100004748</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="3"/><table-count count="4"/><page-count count="8"/><word-count count="3897"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>source-schema-version-number</meta-name><meta-value>2.0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>February 2025</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>details-of-publishers-convertor</meta-name><meta-value>Converter:WILEY_ML3GV2_TO_JATSPMC version:6.5.4 mode:remove_FC converted:07.04.2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="cre270080-sec-0050"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p>Oral cavity cancer ranked as the 18th most prevalent malignancy globally in 2020, posing a substantial health challenge (Sung et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270080-bib-0022" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>). Squamous cell carcinomas of the oral cavity (OSCC), which constitute over 90% of oral cavity cancers, originate from the squamous epithelium. These cancers show a 2.2 male&#x02010;to&#x02010;female ratio, with the majority of cases occurring in individuals aged 50&#x02013;70 years (Vered et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270080-bib-0025" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>; Mirhashemi et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270080-bib-0015" ref-type="bibr">2023</xref>). Annually, more than 400,000 cases of oral cancer are diagnosed, with over half attributed to the tongue (Ganly, Patel, and Shah&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270080-bib-0005" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Warnakulasuriya&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270080-bib-0027" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>).</p><p>In contrast to other malignancies, tongue squamous cell carcinoma (TSCC) is on the rise, particularly among individuals aged 20&#x02013;44 years (Rethman et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270080-bib-0017" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Vered, Dayan, and Salo&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270080-bib-0024" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). In many countries, tongue cancer is recognized as a significant public health concern due to its elevated morbidity and mortality rates (Annertz et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270080-bib-0002" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Camisasca et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270080-bib-0004" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Alho et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270080-bib-0001" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>; Wang et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270080-bib-0026" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>).</p><p>TSCC displays an aggressive nature, leading to significant disruptions in speech, mastication, and swallowing (Jemal et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270080-bib-0010" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Notably, TSCC has heightened rates of recurrence and metastasis, coupled with diminished survival rates, compared to SCC in other oral and head and neck regions (Jemal et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270080-bib-0009" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). The challenging prognosis of TSCC underscores the complexities associated with invasion and metastasis (Manning and Cantley&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270080-bib-0012" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). Although indications suggest a potential biological distinction for TSCC, this remains a subject of debate requiring extensive investigation (Kalluri and Zeisberg&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270080-bib-0011" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Rodrigues&#x02010;Lisoni et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270080-bib-0018" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>).</p><p>The primary treatment protocol for TSCC involves surgery and radiotherapy to eliminate malignant epithelial cells. Unfortunately, significant advancements in the treatment of TSCC patients have not taken place over the past four decades with this therapeutic approach, and the overall survival (OS) rate remains low, with a 50% 5&#x02010;year survival rate (Hiemer et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270080-bib-0007" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>).</p><p>An ideal prognostic factor for predicting TSCC recurrence has yet to be established. Some studies highlight the significance of surgical margin status, whereas others do not demonstrate a clear association between this factor and recurrence or survival rates (Yanamoto et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270080-bib-0028" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Brandwein&#x02010;Gensler et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270080-bib-0003" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>).</p><p>Among the cells playing a crucial role in the immune system's function against malignancies are Langerhans cells (LCs), which present internal or external antigens to T cells. CD1a, a membrane&#x02010;bound peptide expressed in LCs, facilitates the presentation of lipid and glycolipid antigens to T cells. Consequently, these cells represent a significant target for therapeutic and preventive processes in cancer (Stoitzner, Sparber, and Tripp&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270080-bib-0021" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Schuler, Schuler&#x02010;Thurner, and Steinman&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270080-bib-0019" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>).</p><p>In this study, we evaluated the relationship between the number of LCs (assessed through CD1a expression) in patients with TSCC compared to normal tissue. Additionally, we examined the correlation between these cells and patients' prognoses.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials" id="cre270080-sec-0060"><label>2</label><title>Methods and Materials</title><sec id="cre270080-sec-0070"><label>2.1</label><title>Patients</title><p>This study included patients diagnosed with TSCC whose medical records and pathological specimens were sourced from the Oncology Department of Omid Hospital and the Oral and Maxillofacial Pathology Department at Mashhad University of Medical Sciences, Iran. Convenience sampling was used to select cases from the pathology archives based on their availability and alignment with the study's inclusion and exclusion criteria. Inclusion criteria comprised patients with comprehensive clinical records, a follow&#x02010;up duration exceeding 2 years, and suitable pathological specimens for immunohistochemistry. Exclusion criteria included patients with incomplete medical records, inadequate pathological specimens for analysis, or significant co&#x02010;morbidities potentially influencing survival outcomes independently of TSCC progression, such as HPV infection. Relevant information and participant contact details were carefully extracted from the archives, including clinicopathological data such as age, gender, stage, histopathological grade, recurrence, and survival rate.</p></sec><sec id="cre270080-sec-0080"><label>2.2</label><title>Specimen Characteristics</title><p>Archived formalin&#x02010;fixed, paraffin&#x02010;embedded tissue blocks were retrieved for analysis. Two 4&#x02013;5&#x02009;&#x003bc;m&#x02010;thick sections were prepared from each block and validated for quality and quantity by two Oral and Maxillofacial Pathology professors (N.G. and N.S.).</p></sec><sec id="cre270080-sec-0090"><label>2.3</label><title>Assay Methods</title><p>Immunohistochemical staining was performed using the BOND Ready&#x02010;to&#x02010;Use Primary Antibody CD1a (MTB1) kit (Leica Biosystems Newcastle Ltd., United Kingdom) following the manufacturer's protocol. Sections were deparaffinized, rehydrated, and subjected to antigen retrieval using the automated Leica Bond&#x02010;Max system. Stained slides were subjected to quality control procedures to ensure reproducibility and reliability of results. CD1a&#x02010;positive dendritic cells (DCs) were identified and quantified. For each sample, three representative high&#x02010;cellularity &#x0201c;hot spot&#x0201d; fields within the invasive tumor component were identified under &#x000d7;100 magnification. The mean number of CD1a&#x02010;positive DCs across these fields was recorded for each sample (Minesaki et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270080-bib-0014" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>; Silva et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270080-bib-0020" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Immunohistochemical evaluations were conducted in a manner blinded to the study endpoints to prevent bias.</p></sec><sec id="cre270080-sec-0100"><label>2.4</label><title>Study Design</title><p>This biomarker retrospective study was conducted by examining medical records and archived pathological specimens from the Oncology Department of Omid Hospital and the Oral and Maxillofacial Pathology Department at Mashhad University of Medical Sciences, Iran. Cases were selected from a time period spanning from January 2008 to December 2018, with follow&#x02010;up data collected through December 2020.</p><p>Subsequently, a total of 36 samples were chosen from the pathology archives, divided into three groups: the control group, sourced from mucocele specimens, included epithelial and normal connective tissues without inflammation or with only mild inflammation and no epithelial dysplasia. There were 12 cases at Stage I or II and 12 cases at Stage III or IV based on the TNM classification. The early&#x02010;stage TSCC group included samples from Stages I and II TSCCs, whereas the advanced&#x02010;stage TSCC group comprised samples from Stages III and IV TSCCs (Mohtasham et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270080-bib-0016" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Additionally, TSCC samples were classified as low grade and high grade.</p><p>Matching criteria such as age and gender distribution were assessed to ensure comparability across groups. Moreover, disease&#x02010;free survival (DFS) was calculated from the time of pathological diagnosis to the first recurrence, whereas OS spanned from the time of pathological diagnosis to the last follow&#x02010;up or the date of death. The study protocol was approved by the Ethics Committee of Mashhad University of Medical Sciences under the code IR.MUMS.DENTISTRY.REC.1401.150.</p><p>Sample size calculation was based on the findings of Upadhyay et al. (<xref rid="cre270080-bib-0023" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). With a target power of 80% and a significance level of &#x003b1;&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.05, the minimum required sample size was determined to be 36 samples, with 12 samples allocated to each group. PASS software (version 2021; NCSS LLC, Kaysville, Utah, USA) was utilized for sample size determination.</p></sec><sec id="cre270080-sec-0110"><label>2.5</label><title>Statistical Analysis Methods</title><p>All statistical analyses were performed using SPSS software (version 23; SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, USA). Survival analyses, including Kaplan&#x02013;Meier and Cox regression analyses, were conducted. The chi&#x02010;square test was used for comparison between groups. Statistical significance was established at <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="cre270080-sec-0120"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><p>Among the 36 patients, the average age was 60.11&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;11.73 years, ranging from 32 to 78 years. Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270080-tbl-0001" ref-type="table">1</xref> shows an equal distribution of 50% females and 50% males across all three groups, indicating no significant gender difference among the groups (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.000). Similarly, no statistically significant difference in age was observed among the groups (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.236). Positive immunoreactivity was observed in 100% of the control group, 75% of the early&#x02010;stage group, and 41.7% of the advanced&#x02010;stage group, with a significant difference (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.002). Additionally, the average CD1a gene expression in the control, early&#x02010;stage, and advanced&#x02010;stage groups was 23.17, 20.11, and 3.20, respectively, indicating a significant difference among the groups (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001) (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270080-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="cre270080-tbl-0001" content-type="Table"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Chi&#x02010;square analysis examining differences in gender, age, immunoreactivity, and CD1a expression among three study groups.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="center" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="center" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="center" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="center" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="center" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><thead valign="bottom"><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" valign="bottom"><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="2" valign="bottom">Variables</th><th align="center" colspan="3" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">Groups</th><th rowspan="2" align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> value</th></tr><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" valign="bottom"><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Early Stage</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Advanced Stage</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">Gender (<italic toggle="yes">N/%</italic>)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6/50</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6/50</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6/50</td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top" colspan="1">1.000</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6/50</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6/50</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6/50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" valign="top" rowspan="1">Age, years (M&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.08&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;12.53</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.42&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;13.13</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.83&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;8.45</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.236</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">Immunoreactivity (<italic toggle="yes">N/%</italic>)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/25</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7/58.3</td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top" colspan="1">0.002*</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12/100</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9/75</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/41.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" valign="top" rowspan="1">CD1a expression (M&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.17&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.55</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.08&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;11.92</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.33&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.72</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000*</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="cre270080-tbl1-note-0001"><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Note:</italic> A significant difference between groups is indicated by an asterisk (*) (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). A 95% confidence interval of the mean was estimated in the analysis.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd.</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap><fig position="float" fig-type="Figure" id="cre270080-fig-0001"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>(a) High CD1a expression in Langerhans cells in the normal group (&#x000d7;40). (b) High expression of CD1a in Langerhans cells in the early&#x02010;stage group (&#x000d7;100). (c) Low expression of CD1a in Langerhans cells in the advanced&#x02010;stage group (&#x000d7;100).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="CRE2-11-e70080-g002" position="anchor" id="jats-graphic-1"/></fig><p>No statistically significant association was found between CD1a expression and patient age (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.471) or histopathological grade (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.457) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270080-tbl-0002" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Kaplan&#x02013;Meier survival analysis revealed a median OS of 61 months, with a 3&#x02010;year survival rate of 67.9%&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;11% and a 5&#x02010;year survival rate of 58.2%&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;13%. The median DFS was 22 months, with a 3&#x02010;year survival rate of 39.5%&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;10.3% and a 5&#x02010;year survival rate of 26.3%&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;10.2% (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270080-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="cre270080-tbl-0002" content-type="Table"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Chi&#x02010;square analysis investigating the difference in age and disease grade between two CD1a expression groups.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="center" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="center" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="center" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="left" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><thead valign="bottom"><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" valign="bottom"><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="2" valign="bottom">Variables</th><th align="center" colspan="2" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">CD1a expression</th><th rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> value</th></tr><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" valign="bottom"><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" valign="top" rowspan="1">Age, years (M&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;11.8</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;11.81</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.471</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">Grade (<italic toggle="yes">N/%</italic>)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/50</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9/64.3</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">0.457</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/50</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/35.7</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="cre270080-tbl2-note-0001"><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Note:</italic> A 95% confidence interval of the mean was estimated in the analysis.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd.</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap><fig position="float" fig-type="Figure" id="cre270080-fig-0002"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>(a) Overall survival (OS). (b) Disease&#x02010;free survival (DFS).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="CRE2-11-e70080-g003" position="anchor" id="jats-graphic-3"/></fig><p>An analysis of the effect of disease stage on OS revealed a 3&#x02010;year survival rate of 90%&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;9.5% in early&#x02010;stage patients compared to 18.8%&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;36.6% in advanced&#x02010;stage patients. The mean OS for early&#x02010; and advanced&#x02010;stage patients was 61 and 26 months, respectively, showing a significant impact of disease stage on OS (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.017). Regarding DFS, early&#x02010;stage patients had a 3&#x02010;year survival rate of 72.2%&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;13.8%, whereas advanced&#x02010;stage patients had a rate of 8.3%&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;8%. The mean DFS for these groups was 51 and 13 months, respectively, indicating a significant impact of disease stage on DFS (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001) (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270080-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref> and Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270080-tbl-0003" ref-type="table">3</xref>).</p><fig position="float" fig-type="Figure" id="cre270080-fig-0003"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>(a) Effect of disease stage on overall survival. (b) Effect of disease stage on disease&#x02010;free survival. (c) Effect of CD1a on overall survival. (d) Effect of CD1a on disease&#x02010;free survival.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="CRE2-11-e70080-g001" position="anchor" id="jats-graphic-5"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="cre270080-tbl-0003" content-type="Table"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Log&#x02010;rank Chi&#x02010;square analysis examining the influence of disease stage and CD1a expression on overall survival and disease&#x02010;free survival.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="center" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="center" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="center" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="center" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="center" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="center" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><thead valign="bottom"><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" valign="bottom"><th align="left" colspan="3" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">Variables</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median survival</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean survival</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Std. error</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">Overall survival</td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top" colspan="1">Stage</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Early</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.96</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.35</td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top" colspan="1">0.017*</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Advanced</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.73</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1">CD1a expression</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.54</td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top" colspan="1">0.049*</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.83</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">Disease&#x02010;free survival</td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top" colspan="1">Stage</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Early</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.88</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.15</td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top" colspan="1">0.000*</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Advanced</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.08</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.69</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1">CD1a expression</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.37</td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top" colspan="1">0.000*</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.51</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="cre270080-tbl3-note-0001"><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Note:</italic> A significant impact is indicated by an asterisk (*) (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). A 95% confidence interval of the mean was estimated in the analysis.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd.</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap><p>Furthermore, the median OS in the negative and positive CD1a expression groups was 22 and 61 months, respectively, demonstrating a significant effect of CD1a expression on OS (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.049). For DFS, the median survival was 7 months in the negative CD1a group and 49 months in the positive group, indicating a significant correlation between CD1a expression and DFS (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001) (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270080-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref> and Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270080-tbl-0003" ref-type="table">3</xref>).</p><p>As both disease stage and CD1a gene expression significantly influenced survival, Cox regression analysis was conducted to evaluate their relationship with survival outcomes. According to Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270080-tbl-0004" ref-type="table">4</xref>, neither disease stage nor CD1a expression significantly impacted OS (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.083 and <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.210, respectively). However, a significant correlation between both CD1a expression and disease stage with DFS was observed (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.006 and <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.002, respectively).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="cre270080-tbl-0004" content-type="Table"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Cox regression analysis examining the relationship between disease stage and CD1a expression, controlling for each other, and their impact on overall survival and disease&#x02010;free survival.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="center" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="center" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="center" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="center" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><thead valign="bottom"><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" valign="bottom"><th align="left" colspan="2" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">Variables</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Standard Deviation</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">Overall survival</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.959</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.130</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.083</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CD1a expression</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.215</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.969</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.210</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">Disease&#x02010;free survival</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2.032</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.739</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006*</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CD1a expression</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.993</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.968</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002*</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="cre270080-tbl4-note-0001"><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Note:</italic> A significant impact is indicated by an asterisk (*) (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). A 95% confidence interval of the mean was estimated in the analysis.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd.</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap><p>The staining pattern of LCs was observed in both the epithelial and stromal compartments. LC was distributed intraepithelially and within the connective tissues of the tumor microenvironment. For quantification, LCs with positive immunoreactivity were collectively counted in both the epithelial and stromal compartments to provide an overall representation of their presence. Differences in the distribution of LC between the epithelial and stromal compartments were noted, with a higher concentration generally observed in the epithelial regions compared to the stroma.</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="cre270080-sec-0130"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p>In this study, we conducted a quantitative analysis of LCs by assessing the expression of the CD1a marker in control, early&#x02010;stage, and advanced&#x02010;stage groups. Our statistical analyses revealed a significant reduction in CD1a expression in the advanced&#x02010;stage group compared to both the control and early&#x02010;stage groups. Furthermore, we evaluated the correlation between CD1a expression and clinical outcomes such as DFS and OS. The findings revealed a significant association, indicating that heightened CD1a expression corresponds to improved survival in TSCC patients.</p><p>No significant differences were observed between lesion grade and CD1a expression. This outcome was anticipated, as our study's primary focus was not on the relationship between marker expression and histopathological grade. Additionally, the study highlighted a nonsignificant relationship between marker expression and patient age or gender, indicating that these demographic variables had minimal influence on CD1a expression.</p><p>Our findings align with the research conducted by Jardim et al. (<xref rid="cre270080-bib-0008" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>), who explored the density of CD1a+ and CD83+ cells in patients with oral SCC. Their study demonstrated a strong correlation between reduced CD1a+ cell density in tumor&#x02010;adjacent tissues and adverse clinical outcomes, including DFS and OS. However, in our study, Cox regression analysis did not establish a significant association between the CD1a+ cell count and OS. This discrepancy could be attributed to differences in sample size and follow&#x02010;up duration between the two studies.</p><p>Similarly, Gomes et al. (<xref rid="cre270080-bib-0006" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>) observed a reduction in LC count in well&#x02010;differentiated lower lip SCC, attributing this decrease to prolonged UV exposure. Our findings corroborate this observation, emphasizing the pivotal role of the immune system in SCC pathogenesis.</p><p>Notably, the study carried out by Maraee et al. (<xref rid="cre270080-bib-0013" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>) focused on tumor&#x02010;infiltrating LCs in non&#x02010;melanotic skin cancers. Their results showed fewer LCs in larger tumors and in SCC compared to BCC, consistent with our findings and underscoring the critical role of LCs in tumor progression.</p><p>Contrasting results were reported by Minesaki et al. (<xref rid="cre270080-bib-0014" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>), who investigated the role of CD1a+, S100+, and CD8+ cells in advanced oropharyngeal cancer. They observed lower DSS and OS in groups with elevated LC counts. The authors suggested that these contradictions might stem from the diverse functions of LCs across different body organs. This highlights the need for further studies with larger sample sizes to provide more robust and conclusive evidence regarding the role of LCs in cancer prognosis.</p><p>CD1a, as a promising biomarker, has the potential to significantly impact the assessment of malignancy prognosis when used alongside established staging systems. This suggests that decisions regarding the extent of invasiveness during lesion excision, crucial for effective surgical interventions, can be informed by the presence of CD1a. Early evaluation of this biomarker could improve treatment strategies, reduce disease recurrence, and enhance overall patient survival.</p><p>In cancer research, numerous studies have explored the therapeutic or suppressive potential of DCs (Stoitzner, Sparber, and Tripp&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270080-bib-0021" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Schuler, Schuler&#x02010;Thurner, and Steinman&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270080-bib-0019" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>). Based on the findings of these studies and the present research, utilization of these cells could lead to remarkable advancements in cancer treatment and prevention.</p><p>Future studies should evaluate additional pathological parameters such as the degree of differentiation, tumor budding, and pattern of invasion, which are assessable on H&#x00026;E stainings and have proven prognostic value. Investigation of correlations between these features and LC distribution may provide deeper insights into the tumor microenvironment and its impact on survival outcomes.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="cre270080-sec-0140"><label>5</label><title>Conclusion</title><p>The significant association between decreased CD1a expression and reduced patient survival, as well as disease progression, highlights the potential of CD1a as an independent prognostic factor in the assessment of TSCC patients. Furthermore, considering the critical role of LCs in presenting tumor antigens and the adverse effects of their depletion on cancer cell invasion and malignancy, these cells present themselves as promising candidates for therapeutic interventions aimed at improving outcomes for affected patients.</p></sec><sec id="cre270080-sec-0150"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>
<bold>Narges Ghazi:</bold> conceptualization, methodology, resources, writing &#x02013; review and editing, and project administration. <bold>Nasrollah Saghravanian:</bold> conceptualization, methodology, validation, supervision, and project administration. <bold>Pooya Saeedi:</bold> investigation, visualization, and writing &#x02013; original draft and writing &#x02013; review and editing. <bold>Mohammad Mahdi Maboudinezhad:</bold> conceptualization, validation, investigation, writing &#x02013; review and editing, and visualization.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="cre270080-sec-0170"><title>Conflicts of Interest</title><p>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></sec></body><back><ack id="cre270080-sec-0160"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>The authors gratefully acknowledge the Vice Chancellor of Research at Mashhad University of Medical Sciences for providing financial support for this study.</p></ack><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="cre270080-sec-0190"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The data that support the findings of this study are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request.</p></sec><ref-list content-type="cited-references" id="cre270080-bibl-0001"><title>References</title><ref id="cre270080-bib-0001"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270080-cit-0001">
<string-name>
<surname>Alho</surname>, <given-names>O. P.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Kantola</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>U.</given-names>
<surname>Pirkola</surname>
</string-name>, et al. <year>1999</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Cancer of the Mobile Tongue in Finland&#x02014;Increasing Incidence, But Improved Survival</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Acta Oncologica</source>
<volume>38</volume>, no. <issue>8</issue>: <fpage>1021</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1024</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10665756</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270080-bib-0002"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270080-cit-0002">
<string-name>
<surname>Annertz</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
<surname>Anderson</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
<surname>Palm&#x000e9;r</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Wennerberg</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2012</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>The Increase in Incidence of Cancer of the Tongue in the Nordic Countries Continues Into the Twenty&#x02010;First Century</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Acta Oto&#x02010;laryngologica</source>
<volume>132</volume>, no. <issue>5</issue>: <fpage>552</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>557</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22339663</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270080-bib-0003"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270080-cit-0003">
<string-name>
<surname>Brandwein&#x02010;Gensler</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M. S.</given-names>
<surname>Teixeira</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>C. M.</given-names>
<surname>Lewis</surname>
</string-name>, et al. <year>2005</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Oral Squamous Cell Carcinoma: Histologic Risk Assessment, But Not Margin Status, Is Strongly Predictive of Local Disease&#x02010;Free and Overall Survival</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>American Journal of Surgical Pathology</source>
<volume>29</volume>, no. <issue>2</issue>: <fpage>167</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>178</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15644773</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270080-bib-0004"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270080-cit-0004">
<string-name>
<surname>Camisasca</surname>, <given-names>D. R.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M. A. N. C.</given-names>
<surname>Silami</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Honorato</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>F. L.</given-names>
<surname>Dias</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>P. A. S.</given-names>
<surname>Faria</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>S. Q. C.</given-names>
<surname>Louren&#x000e7;o</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2011</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Oral Squamous Cell Carcinoma: Clinicopathological Features in Patients With and Without Recurrence</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>ORL</source>
<volume>73</volume>, no. <issue>3</issue>: <fpage>170</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>176</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21625192</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270080-bib-0005"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270080-cit-0005">
<string-name>
<surname>Ganly</surname>, <given-names>I.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Patel</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Shah</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2012</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Early Stage Squamous Cell Cancer of the Oral Tongue&#x02014;Clinicopathologic Features Affecting Outcome</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Cancer</source>
<volume>118</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue>: <fpage>101</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>111</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21717431</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270080-bib-0006"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270080-cit-0006">
<string-name>
<surname>Gomes</surname>, <given-names>J. O.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>de Vasconcelos Carvalho</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>F. P.</given-names>
<surname>Fonseca</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>R. O.</given-names>
<surname>Gondak</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M. A.</given-names>
<surname>Lopes</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>P. A.</given-names>
<surname>Vargas</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2016</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>CD1a+ and CD83+ Langerhans Cells Are Reduced in Lower Lip Squamous Cell Carcinoma</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Journal of Oral Pathology &#x00026; Medicine</source>
<volume>45</volume>, no. <issue>6</issue>: <fpage>433</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>439</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26661374</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270080-bib-0007"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270080-cit-0007">
<string-name>
<surname>Hiemer</surname>, <given-names>S. E.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>V. K.</given-names>
<surname>Kartha</surname>
</string-name>, et al. <year>2015</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>A YAP/TAZ&#x02010;Regulated Molecular Signature Is Associated With Oral Squamous Cell Carcinoma</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Molecular Cancer Research</source>
<volume>13</volume>, no. <issue>6</issue>: <fpage>957</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>968</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25794680</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270080-bib-0008"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270080-cit-0008">
<string-name>
<surname>Jardim</surname>, <given-names>J. F.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
<surname>Gondak</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M. M.</given-names>
<surname>Galvis</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>C. A. L.</given-names>
<surname>Pinto</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>L. P.</given-names>
<surname>Kowalski</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2018</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>A Decreased Peritumoral CD1a+ Cell Number Predicts a Worse Prognosis in Oral Squamous Cell Carcinoma</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Histopathology</source>
<volume>72</volume>, no. <issue>6</issue>: <fpage>905</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>913</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29023924</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270080-bib-0009"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270080-cit-0009">
<string-name>
<surname>Jemal</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
<surname>Siegel</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Xu</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
<surname>Ward</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2010</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Cancer Statistics, 2010</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>CA: A Cancer Journal for Clinicians</source>
<volume>60</volume>, no. <issue>5</issue>: <fpage>277</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>300</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20610543</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270080-bib-0010"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270080-cit-0010">
<string-name>
<surname>Jemal</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>E. M.</given-names>
<surname>Ward</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>C. J.</given-names>
<surname>Johnson</surname>
</string-name>, et al. <year>2017</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Annual Report to the Nation on the Status of Cancer, 1975&#x02013;2014, Featuring Survival</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>JNCI: Journal of the National Cancer Institute</source>
<volume>109</volume>, no. <issue>9</issue>: <elocation-id>djx030</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jnci/djx030</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28376154</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270080-bib-0011"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270080-cit-0011">
<string-name>
<surname>Kalluri</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Zeisberg</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2006</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Fibroblasts in Cancer</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Nature Reviews Cancer</source>
<volume>6</volume>, no. <issue>5</issue>: <fpage>392</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>401</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16572188</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270080-bib-0012"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270080-cit-0012">
<string-name>
<surname>Manning</surname>, <given-names>B. D.</given-names>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>L. C.</given-names>
<surname>Cantley</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2007</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>AKT/PKB Signaling: Navigating Downstream</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Cell</source>
<volume>129</volume>, no. <issue>7</issue>: <fpage>1261</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1274</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17604717</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270080-bib-0013"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270080-cit-0013">
<string-name>
<surname>Maraee</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Gaber Farag Antar</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Mashhour Gadallah</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Gaber Abdou</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2020</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Tumour&#x02010;Infiltrating Langerhans Cells in Non&#x02010;Melanoma Skin Cancer, a Clinical and Immunohistochemical Study</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Ecancermedicalscience</source>
<volume>14</volume>: <fpage>1045</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32565898</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270080-bib-0014"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270080-cit-0014">
<string-name>
<surname>Minesaki</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
<surname>Kai</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
<surname>Kuratomi</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Aishima</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2021</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Infiltration of CD1a&#x02010;Positive Dendritic Cells in Advanced Laryngeal Cancer Correlates With Unfavorable Outcomes Post&#x02010;Laryngectomy</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>BMC Cancer</source>
<volume>21</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue>: <fpage>973</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12885-021-08715-6</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34461859</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270080-bib-0015"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270080-cit-0015">
<string-name>
<surname>Mirhashemi</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Sadeghi</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
<surname>Ghazi</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
<surname>Saghravanian</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Dehghani</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Aminian</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2023</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Prognostic Value of CD44 Expression in Oral Squamous Cell Carcinoma: A Meta&#x02010;Analysis</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Annals of Diagnostic Pathology</source>
<volume>67</volume>: <elocation-id>152213</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37856951</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270080-bib-0016"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270080-cit-0016">
<string-name>
<surname>Mohtasham</surname>, <given-names>N.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
<surname>Anvari</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
<surname>Memar</surname>
</string-name>, et al. <year>2014</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Expression of E&#x02010;Cadherin and Matrix metalloproteinase&#x02010;9 in Oral Squamous Cell Carcinoma and Histologically Negative Surgical Margins and Association With Clinicopathological Parameters</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Romanian Journal of Morphology and Embryology = Revue roumaine de morphologie et embryologie</source>
<volume>55</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue>: <fpage>117</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>121</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24715175</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270080-bib-0017"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270080-cit-0017">
<string-name>
<surname>Rethman</surname>, <given-names>M. P.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>W.</given-names>
<surname>Carpenter</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>E. E. W.</given-names>
<surname>Cohen</surname>
</string-name>, et al. <year>2010</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Evidence&#x02010;Based Clinical Recommendations Regarding Screening for Oral Squamous Cell Carcinomas</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Journal of the American Dental Association</source>
<volume>141</volume>, no. <issue>5</issue>: <fpage>509</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>520</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20436098</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270080-bib-0018"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270080-cit-0018">
<string-name>
<surname>Rodrigues&#x02010;Lisoni</surname>, <given-names>F. C.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
<surname>Peitl</surname>
<suffix>Jr.</suffix>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Vidotto</surname>
</string-name>, et al. <year>2010</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Genomics and Proteomics Approaches to the Study of Cancer&#x02010;Stroma Interactions</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>BMC Medical Genomics</source>
<volume>3</volume>: <fpage>14</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20441585</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270080-bib-0019"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270080-cit-0019">
<string-name>
<surname>Schuler</surname>, <given-names>G.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
<surname>Schuler&#x02010;Thurner</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>R. M.</given-names>
<surname>Steinman</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2003</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>The Use of Dendritic Cells in Cancer Immunotherapy</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Current Opinion in Immunology</source>
<volume>15</volume>, no. <issue>2</issue>: <fpage>138</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>147</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12633662</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270080-bib-0020"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270080-cit-0020">
<string-name>
<surname>Silva</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>F.</given-names>
<surname>Fonseca</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>O.</given-names>
<surname>Almeida</surname>
</string-name>, et al. <year>2020</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>CD1a+ and CD207+ Cells Are Reduced in Oral Submucous Fibrosis and Oral Squamous Cell Carcinoma</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Medicina Oral Patolog&#x000ed;a Oral y Cirugia Bucal</source>
<volume>25</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue>: <fpage>e49</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>e55</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4317/medoral.23177</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31880289</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270080-bib-0021"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270080-cit-0021">
<string-name>
<surname>Stoitzner</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>F.</given-names>
<surname>Sparber</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>C. H.</given-names>
<surname>Tripp</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2010</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Langerhans Cells as Targets for Immunotherapy Against Skin Cancer</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Immunology &#x00026; Cell Biology</source>
<volume>88</volume>, no. <issue>4</issue>: <fpage>431</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>437</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20351746</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270080-bib-0022"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270080-cit-0022">
<string-name>
<surname>Sung</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Ferlay</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>R. L.</given-names>
<surname>Siegel</surname>
</string-name>, et al. <year>2021</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Global Cancer Statistics 2020: GLOBOCAN Estimates of Incidence and Mortality Worldwide for 36 Cancers in 185 Countries</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>CA: A Cancer Journal for Clinicians</source>
<volume>71</volume>, no. <issue>3</issue>: <fpage>209</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>249</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33538338</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270080-bib-0023"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270080-cit-0023">
<string-name>
<surname>Upadhyay</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
<surname>Rao</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
<surname>Upadhyay</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2012</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>A Comparative Analysis of Langerhans Cell in Oral Epithelial Dysplasia and Oral Squamous Cell Carcinoma Using Antibody Cd&#x02010;1A</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Journal of Cancer Research and Therapeutics</source>
<volume>8</volume>, no. <issue>4</issue>: <fpage>591</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>597</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23361280</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270080-bib-0024"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270080-cit-0024">
<string-name>
<surname>Vered</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
<surname>Dayan</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
<surname>Salo</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2011</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>The Role of the Tumour Microenvironment in the Biology of Head and Neck Cancer: Lessons From Mobile Tongue Cancer</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Nature Reviews Cancer</source>
<volume>11</volume>, no. <issue>5</issue>: <fpage>382</fpage>; author reply.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270080-bib-0025"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270080-cit-0025">
<string-name>
<surname>Vered</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Shnaiderman&#x02010;Shapiro</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Zlotogorski&#x02010;Hurvitz</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
<surname>Salo</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
<surname>Yahalom</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2019</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Cancer&#x02010;Associated Fibroblasts in the Tumor Microenvironment of Tongue Carcinoma Is a Heterogeneous Cell Population</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Acta Histochemica</source>
<volume>121</volume>, no. <issue>8</issue>: <elocation-id>151446</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31604589</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270080-bib-0026"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270080-cit-0026">
<string-name>
<surname>Wang</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
<surname>Luo</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>F.</given-names>
<surname>Liu</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
<surname>Fu</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2013</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Quality of Life in Oral Cancer Patients&#x02010;Effects of Tongue Resection and Sociocultural Aspects</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Journal of Craniofacial Surgery</source>
<volume>24</volume>, no. <issue>5</issue>: <fpage>e493</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>e496</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24036827</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270080-bib-0027"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270080-cit-0027">
<string-name>
<surname>Warnakulasuriya</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>
<year>2009</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Global Epidemiology of Oral and Oropharyngeal Cancer</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Oral Oncology</source>
<volume>45</volume>, no. <issue>4&#x02013;5</issue>: <fpage>309</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>316</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18804401</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270080-bib-0028"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270080-cit-0028">
<string-name>
<surname>Yanamoto</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Yamada</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
<surname>Takahashi</surname>
</string-name>, et al. <year>2012</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Clinicopathological Risk Factors for Local Recurrence in Oral Squamous Cell Carcinoma</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>International Journal of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery</source>
<volume>41</volume>, no. <issue>10</issue>: <fpage>1195</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1200</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22901502</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>