<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Assoc Res Otolaryngol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Assoc Res Otolaryngol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>JARO: Journal of the Association for Research in Otolaryngology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1525-3961</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1438-7573</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer US</publisher-name><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39810072</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11861830</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">971</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10162-024-00971-0</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Dynamic X-ray Microtomography vs. Laser-Doppler Vibrometry: A Comparative Study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1322-3794</contrib-id><name><surname>Ivanovic</surname><given-names>Aleksandra</given-names></name><address><email>aleksandra.ivanovic@unibe.ch</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Jeffrey Tao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schmeltz</surname><given-names>Margaux</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wimmer</surname><given-names>Wilhelm</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schlepuetz</surname><given-names>Christian M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Remenschneider</surname><given-names>Aaron K.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bonnin</surname><given-names>Anne</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Anschuetz</surname><given-names>Lukas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff7">7</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff8">8</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/01q9sj412</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411656.1</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0479 0855</institution-id><institution>Department of Otorhinolaryngology, Head and Neck Surgery, Inselspital, </institution><institution>Bern University Hospital, University of Bern, </institution></institution-wrap>3010 Freiburgstrasse, Bern Switzerland </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/02k7v4d05</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5734.5</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0726 5157</institution-id><institution>Hearing Research Laboratory, </institution><institution>ARTORG Center for Biomedical Engineering Research, University of Bern, </institution></institution-wrap>Murtenstrasse 50, 3008 Bern, Switzerland </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/03eh3y714</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5991.4</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 1090 7501</institution-id><institution>Swiss Light Source, </institution><institution>Paul Scherrer Institut, </institution></institution-wrap>Villigen PSI, Switzerland </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/03vek6s52</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.38142.3c</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">000000041936754X</institution-id><institution>Eaton-Peabody Laboratories, </institution><institution>Massachusetts Eye and Ear, Harvard Medical School, </institution></institution-wrap>Boston, MA 02114 USA </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/03vek6s52</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.38142.3c</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">000000041936754X</institution-id><institution>Department of Otolaryngology Head and Neck Surgery, </institution><institution>Boston Children&#x02019;s Hospital, Harvard Medical School, </institution></institution-wrap>Boston, MA 02115 USA </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/04jc43x05</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.15474.33</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0477 2438</institution-id><institution>Department of Otorhinolaryngology, </institution><institution>TUM School of Medicine, Klinikum Rechts Der Isar, </institution></institution-wrap>Munich, Germany </aff><aff id="Aff7"><label>7</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/05a353079</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.8515.9</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0423 4662</institution-id><institution>Department of Otorhinolaryngology, Head and Neck Surgery, </institution><institution>CHUV Centre Hospitalier Universitaire Vaudois and University of Lausanne, </institution></institution-wrap>Lausanne, Switzerland </aff><aff id="Aff8"><label>8</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/01eas9a07</institution-id><institution>The Sense Innovation and Research Center, Lausanne and Sion, </institution></institution-wrap>Lausanne, Switzerland </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>14</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>2</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>26</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>63</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>6</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Purpose</title><p id="Par1">There are challenges in understanding the biomechanics of the human middle ear, and established methods for studying this system show significant limitations. In this study, we evaluate a novel dynamic imaging technique based on synchrotron X-ray microtomography designed to assess the biomechanical properties of the human middle ear by comparing it to laser-Doppler vibrometry (LDV).</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">We examined three fresh-frozen temporal bones (TB), two donated by white males and one by a Black female, using dynamic synchrotron-based X-ray microtomography for 256 and 512&#x000a0;Hz, stimulated at 110&#x000a0;dB and 120&#x000a0;dB sound pressure level (SPL). In addition, we performed measurements on these TBs using 1D LDV, a well-established method.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">The normalized displacement values (&#x000b5;m/Pa) at the umbo and the posterior crus of the stapes are consistent or within 5&#x02013;10&#x000a0;dB differences between all LDV and dynamic microtomography measurements and previously reported literature references. In general, the overall behavior is similar between the two measurement techniques.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par4">In conclusion, our results demonstrate the suitability of dynamic synchrotron-based X-ray microtomography in studying the middle ear&#x02019;s biomechanics. However, this study shows that better standardization regarding acoustic stimulation and measurement points is needed to better compare the two measurement techniques.</p></sec><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1007/s10162-024-00971-0.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Middle ear</kwd><kwd>Laser&#x000a0;Doppler vibrometry</kwd><kwd>Dynamic synchrotron-based X-ray microtomography</kwd><kwd>Phase-contrast&#x000a0;</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100001711</institution-id><institution>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds zur F&#x000f6;rderung der Wissenschaftlichen Forschung</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>320030\_192660</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Anschuetz</surname><given-names>Lukas</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>NIH</institution></funding-source><award-id>NIH R01 DC016079</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Jeffrey Tao</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>University of Bern</institution></funding-source></award-group><open-access><p>Open access funding provided by University of Bern</p></open-access></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Association for Research in Otolaryngology 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par5">The middle ear is a complicated and delicate biomechanical system that plays a vital role in hearing. It is located within the temporal bone and hosts the three auditory ossicles: malleus, incus, and stapes, which are connected to ligaments and attached to two muscles in the air-filled tympanic cavity. Over the past century, research has deepened our understanding of its mechanics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. The middle ear&#x02019;s primary function is to amplify and transmit air-borne sound waves to the fluid-filled cochlea. Impedance matching plays a crucial role: when sound waves strike the eardrum, the auditory ossicles work together to compensate for the impedance mismatch between air and inner ear fluid. This process results in a nearly 50-fold (<italic>&#x02248;</italic>34&#x000a0;dB increase) amplification of force transmitted to the inner ear. Additionally, the tensor tympani and stapedius muscles modulate the ossicles&#x02019; movement. Disruptions in the ossicular chain can lead to conductive hearing loss, while its total absence results in a hearing loss of approximately 60&#x000a0;dB sound pressure level (SPL) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>].</p><p id="Par6">However, studying the middle ear&#x02019;s biomechanics is challenging for several reasons: The middle ear is embedded into the temporal bone, and visual access to all three ossicles is limited. In addition, the movements are very tiny. The stapes footplate moves approximately 10&#x000a0;nm at a stimulus of 80&#x000a0;dB SPL [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>].</p><p id="Par7">Several measurement techniques have been proposed to study the dynamic behavior of the middle ear ossicles. Laser-Doppler vibrometry (LDV), which uses the Doppler effect to measure vibrations, has been employed as the gold standard. The interaction of two coherent laser beams, a reference, and a target beam, is used to calculate the beams&#x02019; movement toward the target structure. Displacements less than 10<sup>&#x002d8;8</sup>&#x000a0;mm and frequencies between 100&#x000a0;Hz and 100&#x000a0;kHz can be measured. The LDV measurements are single-point measurements, which provide information only in the direction of the beam. To evaluate the surface motion of an area, scanning LDV with multiple measurements at the selected location is conducted [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>].</p><p id="Par8">Nevertheless, this measurement approach comes with certain drawbacks. Firstly, LDV measurements require reflective beads to be placed manually in the region of interest, and the alignment of the laser beam to the beads can be tricky and impedes easy reproduction of the experimental results. Additionally, the experimental setup is complicated and requires continuous calibrations. Another point is the required direct microscopic sight of the area of interest. To access the stapes, one must remove some anatomical structures of the auditory system (opening of the facial recess and sectioning of the stapedius muscle) to get direct sight. However, this only allows access to limited parts of the crura, the neck, and the head of the stapes, excluding the footplate. In addition, a one-directional LDV is traditionally used to resolve stapes motions along its piston-like direction. However, 3D motions of the ossicles have gained more and more interest in recent years, which requires the adaption of a 3D LDV [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>].</p><p id="Par9">Various other measurement techniques, such as holography [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>] and optical coherence tomography [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>], have proven helpful in understanding the dynamic behavior of the tympanic membrane and the ossicular chain. However, both these techniques are only sensitive to the movement along the pathway of the optical beam. Thus, none of these measurement techniques allow us to simultaneously visualize and quantify the dynamic behavior of the ossicular chain in 3D. Another approach is the use of Digital Image Correlation (DIC). DIC is a non-contact optical imaging technique that allows the measurement of deformations. Compared to LDV, DIC can measure the displacement field of the entire visible surface. In addition, when using stereo-DIC, one can capture 3-dimensional displacement data. However, like LDV measurement, we need a direct line of sight of the structures we want to measure and a random speckle pattern on the surface to be measured. In addition, its accuracy depends on the camera resolution and the speckle pattern&#x02019;s quality [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>].</p><p id="Par10">An imaging method developed in recent years that can overcome some of the limitations mentioned above is dynamic synchrotron-based microtomography. In addition to laboratory or clinical micro-CT scanners [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>], static synchrotron-based X-ray microtomography has allowed new morphological studies of the inner and middle ear. By harnessing the unique properties of synchrotron radiation, this technique provides enhanced spatial resolution and soft tissue contrast by exploiting phase contrast in addition to absorption contrast, making it ideal for investigating delicate anatomical structures without destruction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. More recently, we were also able to perform dynamic synchrotron-based X-ray microtomography for the first time on unstained fresh-frozen human ear specimen and extract the three-dimensional information of the dynamic behavior of the auditory ossicles during sound stimulation of 110&#x000a0;dB and 120&#x000a0;dB SPL at 128&#x000a0;Hz [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. To correlate our recently proposed dynamic imaging method for evaluating the biomechanics of the human middle ear, we compared it to LDV measurements on the same temporal bone (TB) specimen. This paper presents a quantitative comparison of the two techniques.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Ethical Approval</title><p id="Par11">The study protocol was approved by the local ethical committee of Bern (Kantonale Ethikkommission Bern, KEK-BE 2016&#x02013;00887) and the local ethical committee of the Paul Scherrer Institute (Ethikkommission Nordwest-und Zentralschweiz, 2017&#x02013;00805), as well as the Mass General Brigham Institutional Review Board (#2022P001306).</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Dynamic Synchrotron-based X-ray Microtomography</title><p id="Par12">Three fresh-frozen human TBs anonymous donors were provided by the Eaton Peabody Laboratories, Mass Eye and Ear, Boston, MA, USA. The donor of TB1 was a 51-year-old white male (right ear), the donor of TB2 was an 89-year-old black female (right ear), and the donor of TB3 was a 58-year-old white male (left ear). They are stored as <italic>B-Fresh1</italic>, <italic>B-Fresh2</italic>, and <italic>B-Fresh3</italic> in the PSI petabyte archive system (a tape-based long-term storage system at the Swiss National Supercomputing Centre CSCS in Lugano, Switzerland). For simplicity, we have changed the naming of the samples in this article. TB1 corresponds to the raw data of <italic>B-Fresh1</italic>, TB2 corresponds to the raw data of <italic>B-Fresh2</italic>, and TB3 corresponds to the raw data of <italic>B-Fresh3</italic>. For better readability, we will refer to dynamic synchrotron-based-phase contrast X-ray microtomography simply as dynamic microtomography henceforth.</p><sec id="Sec5"><title>Sample Preparation</title><p id="Par13">The three fresh-frozen TBs were dissected as follows: Laterally, the concha was removed, conserving the bony and cartilaginous external auditory canal. Posteriorly and superiorly, the air cells of the mastoid portion were removed entirely until the tegmen tympani and the antrum. Inferiorly, the soft tissue was removed until the internal carotid artery, the jugular bulb, and the insertion of the Eustachian tube. The middle ear is, therefore, entirely open through its physiological ventilation routes. Medially, the petrous part of the temporal bone was removed until the bony capsule of the labyrinth. The semicircular canals and the internal auditory canal were skeletonized. Finally, the sample included an intact external auditory canal, middle and inner ear, and had a size of approximately 5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;2&#x000a0;cm. The surrounding temporal bone was reduced to a maximum thickness of 1&#x000a0;mm to minimize the X-ray absorption.</p><p id="Par14">An earplug was sewn into the external auditory canal. During the image acquisition, the specimen was placed in a custom-made cylindrical holder (diameter of 25&#x000a0;mm) and mounted on the rotation stage at the TOMCAT beamline. To prevent the samples from drying out during the acquisition, they were wrapped in neuro-patties soaked in a sterile saline solution, and the top of the holder was sealed with a plastic film (see Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Experimental setup at the TOMCAT beamline. The sample is wrapped in saline-soaked neuro-patties to keep it from drying, fixed in a custom-made sample holder, and mounted onto the rotation stage. The top is sealed with a plastic film, showing two tubes coming out (see zoom-in, bottom left of (<bold>a</bold>)). The black one is the tip of the earplug, which is sewn on one end to the external ear canal and connected over a silicone tube to the subwoofer (<bold>a</bold>) or to ER3C Insert Earphones from Etymotic coupled to an amplifier (<bold>b</bold>) on the other hand. The transparent tube with the red tip is inserted into the probe microphone during calibration. The sample is fixed onto the rotation stage. The X-ray beam comes from the left (indicated with a yellow arrow). The HR setup consists of the in-house built GigaFRoST camera [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>] and a 4&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;magnification high numerical aperture macroscope from Optique Peter [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10162_2024_971_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Sound Stimulation and Calibration</title><p id="Par15">Before scanning each sample, we calibrated the sound stimulation with a clinical probe microphone (ER7C, Etymotic Research) by measuring the exact voltage we needed to apply to the auditory canal to reach the desired dB SPL at a particular frequency. We measured at 256 and 512&#x000a0;Hz with 110&#x000a0;dB and 120&#x000a0;dB SPL. We used a sub-woofer with an inverted cone attached for 256&#x000a0;Hz and ER3C Insert Earphones from Etymotic coupled to an amplifier for 512&#x000a0;Hz and connected either of them to a sine wave generator (MeasComp USB daq Module MC1608 USB-1608G SKU: 6069&#x02013;410- 059). A silicon tube connected the sound stimulation unit to the earplug we sewed to the external auditory canal.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Image Acquisition and Reconstruction</title><p id="Par16">Dynamic synchrotron-based X-ray phase-contrast microtomography was conducted at the TOMCAT beamline (X02DA) within the Swiss Light Source (Paul Scherrer Institute, Switzerland). A multi-scale strategy was implemented to accommodate the dimensions of human TBs. Initially, a low-resolution (LR) setup was employed to capture overview scans of the sample, followed by local high-resolution (HR) scans of the middle ear. An in-house developed Fiji plugin, utilizing the 3D reconstructed LR dataset as input, facilitated the determination of spatial coordinates for regions of interest to be imaged with the HR setup [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. The LR overview scans covered a field-of-view (FOV) of approximately 29&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;12.5 mm<sup>2</sup>, using a half-acquisition technique, which entails a 360&#x000b0; rotation rather than the standard 180&#x000b0; in tomography acquisitions. The setup comprised a PCO 5.5 Edge camera coupled with a 1:1 microscope positioned 3&#x000a0;m from the sample, resulting in an effective pixel size of 5.8&#x000a0;&#x000b5;m. Scan parameters were adjusted to minimize radiation exposure, with a 30-ms exposure time and 1000 projections spanning 360&#x000b0;.</p><p id="Par17">The dynamic HR acquisitions were performed with a custom-made in-house fast read-out system consisting of the GigaFRoST camera [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>], a LuAg:Ce scintillator with a thickness of 150&#x000a0;&#x000b5;m, and a 4&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;magnification high numerical aperture macroscope from Optique Peter [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. These components were configured at a propagation distance of 250&#x000a0;mm, yielding an effective pixel size of 2.75&#x000a0;&#x000b5;m [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. The FOV achieved was approximately 11&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;3.3 mm<sup>2</sup> using the &#x0201c;half-acquisition&#x0201d; method. LR and HR acquisitions used a polychromatic beam filtered with a 5-mm Sigradur and a 4-mm glass filter. Additional filtration for LR acquisitions included a 15-mm Sigradur and a 75-&#x000b5;m Molybdean filter to minimize sample dose. The resulting average energy for both setups was approximately 24&#x000a0;keV.</p><p id="Par18">Given the assumption of periodic vibration in the middle ear, with a frequency matching that of the sound stimulation, each motion cycle occurs much more rapidly than the time required for a complete set of angular projections in tomography acquisition (which typically entails several thousand images). To accommodate this, dynamic tomograms were constructed by gathering a substantial number of projections across multiple consecutive motion cycles while the rotation stage slowly rotated. A total of 40,000 projections were captured during a single 360&#x000b0; rotation for each scan.</p><p id="Par19">With the maximum FOV in our HR setup (2016&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;1200 pixels), which was fit to the actual beam size, the maximum frame rate of the GigaFRoST camera is at 2&#x000a0;kHz before saturating the data transfer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. This corresponded to a minimum exposure period of 0.5&#x000a0;ms between consecutive image acquisitions. Consequently, the exposure period was always maintained above 0.5&#x000a0;ms to prevent saturation of the read-out system while maintaining a consistent FOV across all frequencies. The exposure time, i.e., the effective photon collection duration, was adjusted based on the frequency of sound stimulation. It always stayed within one-tenth of the sound stimulation period to prevent image blurring due to motion. Thus, exposure time decreased with increasing sound stimulation frequency, ranging from 0.3&#x000a0;ms for 256&#x000a0;Hz to 0.19&#x000a0;ms for 512&#x000a0;Hz. Due to the exposure time being shorter than the exposure period, there is a &#x0201c;dark time&#x0201d; between acquisitions where the camera does not collect photons. The total scan time corresponds to the number of projections times the exposure period. Exposure periods were set to 0.5&#x000a0;ms for 256&#x000a0;Hz and 0.7&#x000a0;ms for 512&#x000a0;Hz, resulting in overall scan times of 20&#x000a0;s at 256&#x000a0;Hz and 28&#x000a0;s at 512&#x000a0;Hz to collect the 40,000 projection images. The longer exposure periods for the faster oscillation experiments (512&#x000a0;Hz) are necessary to ensure the oscillations are sampled accurately.</p><p id="Par20">To correct for the X-ray beam inhomogeneities and dark current of the camera, the projections were first dark- and flat-field corrected. The sinograms were then computed for each set of projections and then reconstructed using the filtered back-projection Gridrec algorithm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>] and the Sarepy algorithm for ring removal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>].</p><p id="Par21">Two signals were collected during the image acquisition: the sinusoidal signal (or gating signal) transmitted from the signal generator to the sound unit and the camera exposure signal, giving the exact time of each image acquisition. These two signals allowed us to associate each image with a specific phase of the sine stimulation, corresponding to a specific phase of the vibration of the middle ear. The gating signal period was decomposed into ten different time windows called phases <italic>p</italic><sub><italic>j</italic></sub>, with <italic>p</italic><sub>0</sub> being the reference phase taken at the ascending zero-crossing point of the sinusoidal curve. A post-gating algorithm was applied to the 40,000 raw projections to sort them into the correct phases and build ten post-gated tomograms of approximately 4000 projections. These 4000 projections were evenly distributed over the full 360&#x000b0; rotation of the sample, so that each post-gated tomogram allowed to reconstruct in 3D each specific phase of the middle ear movement cycle.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Data Analysis</title><p id="Par22">A detailed description of the analysis pipeline is given by Schmeltz and Ivanovic et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Note that the pipeline developed to analyze the dynamic synchrotron-based X-ray microtomography data extracts the motion in all three directions. To allow for a more accurate comparison of the two techniques, we adapted the dynamic microtomography pipeline to also extract displacements in only one direction. We tried to match the direction in which the motion was extracted as closely as possible to the direction in which the LDV measurements were taken. For the umbo, this is along the direction perpendicular to the plane of the tympanic annulus. For the stapes, it is perpendicular to the stapes footplate. This allows for a more accurate comparison between the two measurement techniques.</p><p id="Par23">To assess the movement of the ossicular chain in response to sound stimulation, we assumed that the ossicles act as independent rigid bodies. According to this presumption, their three-dimensional motion over time can be characterized by rigid transformations composed of a rotation followed by a translation, i.e., all points within a given ossicle undergo identical transformations. Therefore, analyzing only a subset volume (SV) of an ossicle is sufficient to deduce the transformation of the entire ossicle. As previously mentioned, each motion cycle was divided into ten distinct time intervals anointed phases <italic>p</italic><sub><italic>j</italic></sub>. The intensity-based registration algorithm imregtform from MATLAB was employed to perform a 3D registration of the SV of an ossicle imaged at phase <italic>p</italic><sub>0</sub> with the corresponding SV imaged at the other phases <italic>p</italic><sub><italic>j</italic></sub>, where <italic>j&#x02009;&#x02208;&#x02009;</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>] to estimate the geometric transformation aligning the two phases without the need of segmentation or manual placement of landmarks. It effectively uses all available information by considering the unaltered intensity of every image pixel, thereby enabling sub-voxel registration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. Three SVs were manually selected for each ossicle. The transformations of all SVs were then averaged to obtain an average transformation per phase for each ossicle.</p><p id="Par24">After obtaining the mean transformations for all phases <italic>p</italic><sub><italic>j</italic></sub> across the three ossicles, the sinusoidal displacement of any region of interest (ROI) within an ossicle could be determined by calculating the projection of the displacement vector in <italic>z</italic>-direction applied to that point. To compare to the LDV measurement points, two ROIs (the umbo and the posterior crus of the stapes) were manually chosen using Fiji from the reconstructed data stack captured at phase <italic>p</italic><sub>0</sub>. To assess the precision of displacement computation compared to manual ROI selection, five points were selected around the ROI to compute the standard deviation of displacement estimations (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Direction of displacement extraction. The ossicles are displayed in yellow, surrounded by petrous bone, and the tympanic membrane, both in gold. White arrows indicate the directions of movement extraction from the dynamic microtomography data (in <italic>z</italic>-direction). Green arrows approximate the direction of the laser beam. As indicated in the figure, for this TB, we measured at the posterior crus of the stapes at an angle of 45&#x000b0;. We can then apply a cosine correction to derive the stapes motion along the <italic>z</italic>-direction, aligned with the stapes footplate. We cannot approximate the angle properly for the umbo; therefore, the direction difference between the LDV and dynamic microtomography seems to be more extensive</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10162_2024_971_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p><p id="Par25">To ensure that the extracted transformations corresponded to vibrations of the stimulated ossicles and not to vibrations of the entire sample in the sample holder, we applied the pipeline to a portion of the petrous bone. These values set the noise limit for our analyses.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Laser-Doppler Vibrometer</title><sec id="Sec10"><title>Sample Preparation</title><p id="Par26">The identical three specimens that underwent dynamic microtomography were refrozen and returned to Eaton Peabody Laboratories, Mass Eye and Ear, Boston, MA, USA. Further preparation of the temporal bones consisted of opening the facial recess to confirm the normality of the middle ear structures and to gain access to the stapes for laser-Doppler vibrometry (LDV) measurements [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. A small part of the anterior&#x02013;superior wall was opened and later replaced by a transparent plastic window to allow LDV measurement of umbo displacement (see Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Experimental LDV setup at the Eaton Peabody Laboratories. The sample is fixed on an air-isolation table within a soundproof booth. Part of the ear canal wall is replaced by a transparent plastic window that allows LDV measurement of the umbo. Reflective beads are placed at the area of interest (umbo, posterior crus of the stapes, and petrous bone). In addition, a probe microphone is inserted into the ear canal through a hole in the plastic window to monitor ear canal sound pressure (<italic>P</italic><sub><italic>ec</italic></sub>) levels near the tympanic membrane (TM). LDV measurement of the stapes displacement is performed through the glass-covered opening in the facial recess (see zoom-in, on the bottom right). We connected the sound stimulation to the yellow earplug, similar to the dynamic microtomography measurements. The laser beam (indicated with a yellow arrow) is manually focused on the reflective beads previously placed in the area of interest</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10162_2024_971_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Laser Measurements</title><p id="Par27">Small retro-reflective tape pieces (approximately 100&#x000a0;&#x000b5;m&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;100&#x000a0;&#x000b5;m&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;60&#x000a0;&#x000b5;m thick) were affixed to the lateral surface of the tympanic membrane (TM) at the umbo and to the posterior crus of the stapes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Each sample was securely positioned on an air-isolation table within a soundproof booth. LDV measurements were initially conducted at the umbo and then transitioned to the stapes without altering the setup. Additionally, vibrations of the petrous bone near the oval window were recorded to assess the noise floor and stimulus artifact in the measured displacements; all of the umbo and stapes motion measurements we report are at least 20&#x000a0;dB above the driven vibration of the petrous bone. For sound stimulation, a speaker (Radio Shack) equipped with a plastic tube was tightly sealed to the opening of the ear canal to deliver sound to the external ear. At the same time, a calibrated probe microphone (PCB 377C10) monitored sound pressures in the ear canal (<italic>P</italic><sub><italic>ec</italic></sub>) within a distance of less than 2&#x000a0;mm from the TM surface. The hardware of the stimulus and recording system, as well as its software control, have been detailed previously by Ravicz and Rosowski (2012) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. The primary stimulus was a sequence of 50 pure tones with frequencies logarithmically spaced between 200 and 20,000&#x000a0;Hz, during which the stimulus voltage to the loudspeaker remained constant at 0.5&#x000a0;V.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Data Analysis</title><p id="Par28">Fourier transforms of the recorded microphone and LDV time waveforms described the complex (magnitude and phase angle) sinusoidal sound pressure and velocity at the stimulus frequency. The velocities were converted into displacements by dividing the complex velocity by (2 <italic>&#x003c0;</italic>&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;frequency&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;i) and then normalized by the complex sound pressure at the stimulus frequency (<italic>P</italic><sub><italic>ec</italic></sub>). We report the normalized displacement magnitude by the sound pressure for a single stimulus of 0.5&#x000a0;V. In addition, we cosine corrected the displacement for the angle of the measuring beam to account for the expected piston-like stapes movement of the footplate.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Results</title><p id="Par29">Dynamic synchrotron-based X-ray microtomography scans were conducted on three fresh frozen temporal bones (TB1&#x02013;3) at two intensities, 110&#x000a0;dB and 120&#x000a0;dB SPL, and two frequencies, 256 and 512&#x000a0;Hz. The measurements were conducted at the TOMCAT beamline at the Swiss Light Source (Paul Scherrer Institute, Switzerland). After the dynamic imaging scans, the three TBs were shipped to the Eaton Peabody Laboratories, Mass Eye and Ear, Boston, MA, USA, where they underwent LDV measurements at the umbo, the posterior crus of the stapes, and the petrous bone. The acoustic stimulus of 0.5&#x000a0;V was sent to the speaker, which generated frequency-dependent sound between 80 and 100&#x000a0;dB SPL for a frequency range of approximately 200&#x02013;20000&#x000a0;Hz.</p><sec id="Sec14"><title>Dynamic Synchrotron-based X-ray Microtomography</title><p id="Par30">We normalized the unidirectional displacement amplitudes to the ear canal pressure <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>ec</italic></sub> (&#x000b5;m/Pa) to compare the two results quantitatively. Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> shows the raw displacement amplitudes (&#x000b5;m) and the normalized displacement amplitudes (&#x000b5;m/Pa) for the umbo and the posterior crus of the stapes for the three TBs at the two intensities and frequencies. For better comparison, 110&#x000a0;dB SPL is denoted as 6.89&#x000a0;Pa and 120&#x000a0;dB SPL as 21.79&#x000a0;Pa. We see that umbo and stapes displacement increase with increasing stimulus levels. However, the normalized displacement values decrease with increasing intensity except for TB1 and TB3 measured at the umbo at 256&#x000a0;Hz.
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Raw and normalized displacement amplitudes. Raw and normalized displacement amplitudes (in &#x000b5;m and &#x000b5;m/Pa, respectively) computed for the umbo and the posterior crus of the stapes, for 6.89 and 21.79&#x000a0;Pa, 256 and 512&#x000a0;Hz, and the three TBs. There is an increase in all raw displacement amplitudes from 6.89&#x000a0;Pa to 21.79&#x000a0;Pa. The normalized values show a more variable behavior. TB1 generally shows the highest raw displacements compared to TB2 and TB3, which show more similar values. All displacements values result from the analyzing pipeline and are not directly measured</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td align="left">ROI</td><td align="left" colspan="8">Umbo</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Pressure (Pa)</td><td align="left" colspan="4">6.89</td><td align="left" colspan="4">21.79</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Frequency (Hz)</td><td align="left" colspan="2">256</td><td align="left" colspan="2">512</td><td align="left" colspan="2">256</td><td align="left" colspan="2">512</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Computed displacement (&#x000b5;m)</td><td align="left">Raw disp</td><td align="left">Norm disp</td><td align="left">Raw disp</td><td align="left">Norm disp</td><td align="left">Raw disp</td><td align="left">Norm disp</td><td align="left">Raw disp</td><td align="left">Norm disp</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> TB1</td><td align="left">0.345</td><td align="left">0.050</td><td align="left">1.236</td><td align="left">0.179</td><td align="left">0.721</td><td align="left">0.720</td><td align="left">2.590</td><td align="left">0.033</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> TB2</td><td align="left">0.289</td><td align="left">0.042</td><td align="left">0.745</td><td align="left">0.108</td><td align="left">0.521</td><td align="left">0.024</td><td align="left">1.148</td><td align="left">0.053</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> TB3</td><td align="left">0.278</td><td align="left">0.040</td><td align="left">0.271</td><td align="left">0.039</td><td align="left">0.677</td><td align="left">0.310</td><td align="left">0.670</td><td align="left">0.031</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ROI</td><td align="left" colspan="8">Posterior crus stapes</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Pressure (Pa)</td><td align="left" colspan="4">6.89</td><td align="left" colspan="4">21.79</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Frequency (Hz)</td><td align="left" colspan="2">256</td><td align="left" colspan="2">512</td><td align="left" colspan="2">256</td><td align="left" colspan="2">512</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Computed displacement (&#x000b5;m)</td><td align="left">Raw disp</td><td align="left">Norm disp</td><td align="left">Raw disp</td><td align="left">Norm disp</td><td align="left">Raw disp</td><td align="left">Norm disp</td><td align="left">Raw disp</td><td align="left">Norm disp</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> TB1</td><td align="left">0.13</td><td align="left">0.019</td><td align="left">0.95</td><td align="left">0.138</td><td align="left">0.31</td><td align="left">0.014</td><td align="left">1.73</td><td align="left">0.080</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> TB2</td><td align="left">0.21</td><td align="left">0.030</td><td align="left">0.25</td><td align="left">0.036</td><td align="left">0.44</td><td align="left">0.020</td><td align="left">0.73</td><td align="left">0.034</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> TB3</td><td align="left">0.14</td><td align="left">0.020</td><td align="left">0.27</td><td align="left">0.039</td><td align="left">0.40</td><td align="left">0.018</td><td align="left">0.53</td><td align="left">0.024</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par31">For example, Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> shows the mean rotation angle and translation magnitude for TB1 stimulated at 512&#x000a0;Hz at sound levels of 110&#x000a0;dB SPL (a) and 120&#x000a0;dB SPL (b). In (a), we cannot identify a clear sine-like pattern in the rotation angle; instead, the movement detected appears to be noise from the background texture. Since the algorithm fails to detect any actual moving features, we observe an increased level of &#x0201c;artificial rotation.&#x0201d; Fortunately, this background movement does not have the periodicity of sound stimulation, as shown in (b), which helps us distinguish between the artificial and the actual movement. However, stimulated at a higher SPL, (b) confirms that the movement we extract for this malleus is sine-like and periodic. Similar behavior was found for TB2 and TB3 at 512&#x000a0;Hz and TB1 at 256&#x000a0;Hz, all stimulated at 110&#x000a0;dB SPL, which indicates that the actual movement (if any) is too small at this sound intensity stimulation to be detected by the algorithm. The displacements denoted in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> represent the average of the &#x0201c;artificial displacement&#x0201d; detected by the algorithm. The rotation angles and translation magnitudes for all measurements can be found in the supplementary.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Motion quantification for the malleus of TB1 stimulated at 512&#x000a0;Hz for the two intensities, 110&#x000a0;dB and 120&#x000a0;dB SPL. Panel <bold>a</bold> shows the mean rotation angle and the mean translation magnitude of TB1 stimulated at 512&#x000a0;Hz and 110&#x000a0;dB SPL computed for the umbo. We see the &#x0201c;artificial rotation&#x0201d; detected by the algorithm, caused by the moving textured background because the feature displaces no actual movement or a movement that is too small to be registered. Accordingly, the average displacement, averaged over 3 subvolumes (SVs), in 1D shows no sine-like behavior. Panel <bold>b</bold> shows the mean rotation angle and the mean translation magnitude for the same TB1 stimulated at 512&#x000a0;Hz and 120&#x000a0;dB SPL, computed for the umbo. The mean rotation and the mean translation follow a sine-like behavior. Similarly, the computed average displacement over 3 SVs in 1D shows the sine-like behavior</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10162_2024_971_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Laser-Doppler Vibrometry</title><p id="Par32">The TBs were measured with LDV at three points of interest (POI): the umbo, the posterior crus of the stapes, and the petrous bone, with pure tones at a constant stimulus level of 0.5&#x000a0;V delivered to the speaker, sweeping through frequencies between 200 and 20,000&#x000a0;Hz. Figures&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> and <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref> show the normalized displacement magnitude (&#x000b5;m/Pa) of the LDV measurements versus frequency at the umbo and posterior crus of the stapes, respectively. In addition, the normalized displacement values from the dynamic microtomography measurements at 120&#x000a0;dB SPL for the three TBs at 256 and 512&#x000a0;Hz are marked with green, blue, and pink crosses, respectively. As a reference, values from Gan et al. (2004) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>] and Goode et al. (1994)[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>] are plotted in red and black, respectively. At the umbo, we can observe a variance between the LDV measurements of the three TBs within the normal range [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. However, for the measurements taken at the posterior crus of the stapes, the LDV measurements are generally lower than the reference values from Gan et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. However, the values from the measurements taken at the synchrotron are much closer to the reference data values analyzed at the posterior crus of the stapes. In general, we can see that all values acquired at the synchrotron are within the normal range of previously reported LDV measurements and either consistent or within 5&#x02013;10&#x000a0;dB differences between all LDV measurements taken at the same samples.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;5</label><caption><p>Umbo normalized displacement magnitude (&#x000b5;m/Pa) vs frequency. Comparison of our LDV measurements at the umbo with dynamic microtomography measurements at 256 and 512&#x000a0;Hz, both stimulated at 120&#x000a0;dB SPL and previous literature. All measurements are within a normal range and comparable to previous literature values. There is a steeper slope in displacement between 256 and 512&#x000a0;Hz for the dynamic microtomography data of TB1 and TB2 compared to our LDV data, similar to the data from Gan et al. (2004). TB3 shows a similar plateau compared to our LDV data</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10162_2024_971_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig><fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;6</label><caption><p>Stapes posterior crus normalized displacement magnitude (&#x000b5;m/Pa) vs frequency. Comparison of our LDV measurements at the stapes posterior crus with dynamic microtomography measurements at 256 and 512&#x000a0;Hz, both stimulated at 120&#x000a0;dB SPL and previous literature. We can see an increase in displacement from 256 and 512&#x000a0;Hz for all TBs. TB1 shows the steepest increase, while TB2 and TB3 are flatter. All LDV measurements are notably lower than the literature reference and the dynamic microtomography measurements</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10162_2024_971_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par33">This study compared dynamic synchrotron-based X-ray microtomography to laser-Doppler vibrometry to assess middle ear biomechanics in three temporal bone samples. Our results showed either consistent or within 5&#x02013;10&#x000a0;dB differences between the normalized displacement values for the umbo and the posterior crus of the stapes in the LDV technique compared to those displacement values measured with dynamic synchrotron-based X-ray microtomography, as seen in Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> and <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>.</p><p id="Par34">During the dynamic microtomography scans, we stimulated the sample with a constant sound pressure of 110 and 120&#x000a0;dB SPL by adjusting the voltage to the corresponding frequency. In comparison, during the LDV scans, we sent a constant voltage of 0.5&#x000a0;V to the speaker, and therefore, the pressure in the ear canal changed depending on the frequency. Although the stimulation strategies used differ, we observe similar SPL values for the two frequencies we looked at. However, a difference of 5&#x02013;10&#x000a0;dB of overall displacements was observed between the two techniques. The discrepancy between the two measurement techniques is less likely caused by different stimulus levels. However, the dynamic microtomography scans were performed before the LDV. The samples underwent thawing, high radiation, and refreezing before they were shipped to Boston for the LDV measurements. This could have led to the drying of the soft tissue components in the bones, as previously suggested by [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. Moreover, opening the facial recess and sectioning of the stapedius muscle for the LDV measurements could have also affected the samples. Nevertheless, the general behavior for the umbo and the stapes is consistent between the dynamic microtomography and the LDV measurements, comparable with previously reported data, and within the measured frequency range.</p><p id="Par35">Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> shows a decrease in computed displacement amplitude from the umbo to the stapes, which is expected from previous literature. To ensure that the extracted transformations corresponded to vibrations of the stimulated ossicles and not to external motion (such as vibrations of the whole system), we applied the analysis pipeline to parts of the petrous bone. We found that the algorithm registers the textured, moving background (noise) when there is no detectable motion in the structure. This background noise varies between images, depending, among others, on the sample size, the exposure time (correlated to the frequency), the camera calibrations, and the scintillator used. This leads to different limits of our system to detect the smallest possible movement, depending on the acquisition. However, these movements do not show any sine-like behavior, which allows us to discriminate them from the stimuli-induced movement and, therefore, verify the transformations we extract on the ossicles.</p><p id="Par36">The normalized dynamic microtomography displacement amplitudes (&#x000b5;m/Pa) measured at 110&#x000a0;dB SPL (6.89&#x000a0;Pa) are generally higher than those measured at 120&#x000a0;dB SPL (21.79&#x000a0;Pa) for all TB and frequencies. This is indicated in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. An increase in 10&#x000a0;dB SPL in a linear regime corresponds to a displacement ratio of 3.16. However, we observe a maximum ratio of 2.47 at the umbo and 2.92 at the stapes, corresponding to an increase of 7.86&#x000a0;dB and 9.31&#x000a0;dB, respectively. This either suggests compressive growth &#x02014; a slower growth in displacement than the stimulus level &#x02014; for both the umbo and stapes, or it outlines our technical limitations for dynamic synchrotron X-ray microtomography mentioned above. There are several reports on nonlinear behavior in the middle ear for high sound pressure level stimulus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. Recently, Cheng et al. reported that the onset of nonlinear growth depends on the sample and can start at 110&#x000a0;dB SPL [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. They reported mainly expansive growth at the umbo for frequencies below 2&#x000a0;kHz and compressive growth at the stapes for frequencies below 2&#x000a0;kHz, which would only partially align with our findings. In addition, since we do not have measurements acquired with a stimulus below 110&#x000a0;dB SPL, we cannot state whether we are already in a nonlinear regime at 110&#x000a0;dB SPL (continuous exposition to 6.89&#x000a0;Pa). Another possible explanation would be the technical limit of our experimental imaging setup in resolving displacements at a sub-pixel level.</p><p id="Par37">Comparing two measurement techniques is not straightforward. With 1D LDV, we measure the velocity of a moving object in a single direction only along the laser beam. The laser is manually focused on the point of interest for each sample. However, the anatomy of each specimen is different. This makes it impossible to align the laser beam along the same axis between different TBs. However, laser focusing is usually done by the same experienced person for different samples during an experiment. Therefore, we can suggest that the setup and sample orientation are as similar as possible, considering the difference in the individual anatomy between the three TBs. Similarly, one person prepared all TBs for the dynamic microtomography measurements and placed them in the sample holder in the same orientation (external auditory canal facing upwards) (see Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). To mimic the 1D measurement from LDV, we extracted the displacement in <italic>z</italic>-direction only for the dynamic microtomography data analysis, as illustrated in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> for one sample. However, we recently showed that the movement of the umbo and the stapes is not just unidirectional and only piston-like [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>] but more complicated already at low frequencies, stimulated at 120&#x000a0;dB SPL. Unfortunately, we could not estimate the angle of the LDV measurements at the umbo compared to the direction we extracted from the dynamic microtomography because we did not have the images reconstructed when we acquired the LDV measurements. We do not have pictures of every sample from which we could estimate the laser beam exactly enough. Consequently, one can never capture the same direction along the movement in one direction only.</p><p id="Par38">In general, LDV offers the advantage of in vivo measurements (at the umbo) and the ability to assess a wide range of frequencies, making it highly versatile for dynamic studies. However, it requires extensive surgical preparation, which can be time-consuming and may alter the peripheral auditory system. In contrast, while limited to ex vivo applications and less practical for capturing broad frequency responses, dynamic microtomography provides the unique capability of simultaneously acquiring 3D volume displacements and morphological data.</p><p id="Par39">The most limiting factor in the dynamic microtomography measurements is the photon flux provided by the Swiss Light Source, which is required for a short exposure time while maintaining good image quality. The acquisition parameters are tied to the limited photon flux for dynamic microtomography: a trade-off between frame rate and FOV must be made to achieve sufficient acquisition speed. However, with the upgrade of the Swiss Light Source, the upgrade of the TOMCAT beamline, and the new generation of high-numerical aperture microscope, we can expect to reach a voxel size of at least 1.8&#x000a0;&#x000b5;m with better image quality, opening the door to measurements at higher stimulation frequencies.</p><p id="Par40">In the future, it would be interesting to compare the entire six degrees of freedom of the ossicles by comparing 3D LDV measurements with dynamic microtomography. Conducting the LDV measurements first, followed by the dynamic microtomography, might help reduce possible sample changes due to radiation. However, this would mean that the sample would no longer be intact for the dynamic microtomography scans. Also, the use of newer laser-Doppler systems would allow measurements without the use of reflective beads or tape. Further, one could consider keeping the sound stimulation during the dynamic microtomography at a constant voltage instead of a sound pressure level to have more comparable stimulation intensity values. In addition, with the ongoing upgrade of the Swiss Light Source, we will be able to increase the spatial and temporal resolution and, therefore, might be able to resolve movements at frequencies up to 2&#x000a0;kHz. This would allow a comparison on a broader frequency range.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par41">Upon assessing dynamic synchrotron-based X-ray microtomography and quantitatively comparing it to the gold standard technique, laser-Doppler vibrometry, we found that the former proves to be a suitable imaging technique for studying the middle ear&#x02019;s biomechanics. Despite its limitations in frequency response and in -vivo applicability, the dual capacity to combine structural and functional information makes dynamic microtomography a valuable tool.</p><p id="Par42">However, this study shows that better standardization is needed to compare the two measurement techniques. It is particularly challenging to compare the two methods quantitatively because, in 1D LDV, we look at single-point measurements, while with dynamic microtomography, we can extract the transformation matrix for each ossicle and apply it to any point of interest.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="10162_2024_971_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><caption><p>Supplementary file1 (DOCX 1023 KB)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="10162_2024_971_MOESM2_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Supplementary file2 (PDF 1414 KB)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors thank Philipp Zuppiger from the Paul Scherrer Institute for his technical support. The authors acknowledge the Paul Scherrer Institute, Villigen, Switzerland, for the provision of synchrotron radiation beamtime at the TOMCAT beamline X02DA of the SLS. No AI tools were used in the preparation of this manuscript or for research purposes.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author Contribution</title><p>A. I., J. T. C., M. S., A. R., A. B., and L. A. designed the study. A. I., M. S., A. B., and C. S. discussed the methodology of the dynamic microtomography experiments and image processing, while A. I., J. T. C., and A. R. discussed the methodology of the LDV experiments and data analysis. A. I., M. S., A. B., L. A., and W. W. developed the synchrotron-based microtomography experimental setup. L. A. and A. R. dissected and prepared the samples. A. I., M. S., A. B., C. S., and L. A. participated in the experimental beamtimes at PSI (TOMCAT, X02DA), and A. I., J. T. C., and A. R. participated in the LDV experiments at the Eaton-Peabody Laboratories, Mass. Eye and Ear, in Boston, MA, USA. A. I. reconstructed the dynamic microtomography data, and M. Sc. designed the dynamic microtomography analysis pipeline. A. I. analyzed the data from the LDV and dynamic microtomography experiments with constructive input from J. T. C., M. S., A. B., A. R., C. S., and L. A. A. I. created the figures and wrote the original draft. M. S., J. T. C., A. B., A. R., L. A., and C. S. provided constructive suggestions for the results and discussion. All the authors reviewed, edited, and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>Open access funding provided by University of Bern. The Swiss National Science Foundation (SNSF) funded this research (grant number 320030_192660) and the NIH R01 funding info: NIH R01 DC016079.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data Availability</title><p>The raw data supporting the conclusions of this article have been archived and published in agreement with the FAIR principles on the SciCat Data Catalog of PSI. They are available upon request.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Code Availability</title><p>The custom Python and Matlab codes supporting the analyses used in this article are available upon request.</p></notes><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Declarations</title><p id="Par43">The authors have no relevant financial or non-financial interests to disclose. The authors have no conflicts of interest to declare that are relevant to the content of this article. All the authors certify that they have no affiliations with or involvement in any organization or entity with any financial interest or non-financial interest in the subject matter or materials discussed in this manuscript. The authors have no financial or proprietary interests in any material discussed in this article.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Von B&#x000e9;k&#x000e9;sy G (1960) Experiments in hearing. McGraw-Hill, New York</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Decraemer</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name><name><surname>Khanna</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Funnell</surname><given-names>WRJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A method for determining three-dimensional vibration in the ear</article-title><source>Hear Res</source><year>1994</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>37</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0378-5955(94)90250-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7928731</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Decraemer WF, Khanna SM, Funnell WRJ (1994) A method for determining three-dimensional vibration in the ear. Hear Res 77:19&#x02013;37<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7928731</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vlaming</surname><given-names>MSMG</given-names></name><name><surname>Feenstra</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Studies on the mechanics of the normal human middle ear</article-title><source>Clin Otolaryngol Allied Sci</source><year>1986</year><volume>11</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>353</fpage><lpage>363</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2273.1986.tb02023.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3536194</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Vlaming MSMG, Feenstra L (1986) Studies on the mechanics of the normal human middle ear. Clin Otolaryngol Allied Sci 11(5):353&#x02013;363. 10.1111/j.1365-2273.1986.tb02023.x<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3536194</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Puria S, Allen JB (1998) Measurements and model of the cat middle ear: evidence of tympanic membrane acoustic delay. J Acoust Soc Am 104(6):3463&#x02013;81. 10.1121/1.423930</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peake</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosowski</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Middle-ear transmission: acoustic versus ossicular coupling in cat and human</article-title><source>Hear Res</source><year>1992</year><volume>57</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>245</fpage><lpage>268</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0378-5955(92)90155-G</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1733916</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Peake WT, Rosowski JJ, Lynch TJ (1992) Middle-ear transmission: acoustic versus ossicular coupling in cat and human. Hear Res 57(2):245&#x02013;268. 10.1016/0378-5955(92)90155-G<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1733916</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hato</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Stenfelt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Goode</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Three-dimensional stapes footplate motion in human temporal bones</article-title><source>Audiol Neuro-Otol</source><year>2003</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>140</fpage><lpage>152</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000069475</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Hato N, Stenfelt S, Goode RL (2003) Three-dimensional stapes footplate motion in human temporal bones. Audiol Neuro-Otol 8:140&#x02013;152. 10.1159/000069475</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ball GR, Huber A, Goode RL (1997) Scanning laser Doppler vibrometry of the middle ear ossicles. Ear Nose Throat J 76(4):213-8, 220, 222</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Dormer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Human middle ear transfer function measured by double laser interferometry system</article-title><source>Otol Neurotol</source><year>2004</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>423</fpage><lpage>435</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00129492-200407000-00005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15241216</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Gan Z, Wood W, Dormer J (2004) Human middle ear transfer function measured by double laser interferometry system. Otol Neurotol 25:423&#x02013;435<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15241216</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosowski</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakajima</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name><surname>Merchant</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical utility of laser-Doppler vibrometer measurements in live normal and pathologic human ears</article-title><source>Ear Hear</source><year>2008</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/AUD.0b013e31815d63a5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18091103</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Rosowski JJ, Nakajima HH, Merchant SN (2008) Clinical utility of laser-Doppler vibrometer measurements in live normal and pathologic human ears. Ear Hear 29:3&#x02013;19. 10.1097/AUD.0b013e31815d63a5<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18091103</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dobrev</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Ihrle</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>R&#x000f6;&#x000f6;sli</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerig</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Eiber</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sim</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A method to measure sound transmission via the malleus&#x02013;incus complex</article-title><source>Hear Res</source><year>2016</year><volume>340</volume><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>98</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.heares.2015.10.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26626362</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Dobrev I, Ihrle S, R&#x000f6;&#x000f6;sli C, Gerig R, Eiber A, Huber AM, Sim JH (2016) A method to measure sound transmission via the malleus&#x02013;incus complex. Hear Res 340:89&#x02013;98. 10.1016/j.heares.2015.10.016<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26626362</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Dobrev I, Farahmandi TS, R&#x000f6;&#x000f6;sli C (2020) Experimental investigation of the effect of middle ear in bone conduction.&#x000a0;Hear Res 395:108041. 10.1016/j.heares.2020.108041</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gottlieb</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaisbuch</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Puria</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Human ossicular-joint flexibility transforms the peak amplitude and width of impulsive acoustic stimuli</article-title><source>J Acoust Soc Am</source><year>2018</year><volume>143</volume><fpage>3418</fpage><lpage>3433</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1121/1.5039845</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29960477</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Gottlieb PK, Vaisbuch Y, Puria S (2018) Human ossicular-joint flexibility transforms the peak amplitude and width of impulsive acoustic stimuli. J Acoust Soc Am 143:3418&#x02013;3433. 10.1121/1.5039845<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29960477</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Powell RL, Stetson KA (1965) Interferometric vibration analysis by wavefront reconstruction.&#x000a0;J Opt Soc Am&#x000a0;55:1593&#x02013;1598. 10.1364/JOSA.55.001593</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Aarnisalo</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Harrington</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Socorro Hernandez-Montes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Furlong</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Merchant</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosowski</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Motion of the surface of the human tympanic membrane measured with stroboscopic holography</article-title><source>Hear Res</source><year>2010</year><volume>263</volume><fpage>66</fpage><lpage>77</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.heares.2009.12.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20034549</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Cheng JT, Aarnisalo AA, Harrington E, Socorro Hernandez-Montes M, Furlong C, Merchant SN, Rosowski JJ (2010) Motion of the surface of the human tympanic membrane measured with stroboscopic holography. Hear Res 263:66&#x02013;77. 10.1016/j.heares.2009.12.024<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20034549</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khaleghi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Dobrev</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Furlong</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosowski</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Digital holographic measurements of shape and three-dimensional sound-induced displacements of tympanic membrane</article-title><source>Opt Eng</source><year>2013</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>101916</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1117/1.oe.52.10.101916</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24790255</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Khaleghi M, Lu W, Dobrev I, Cheng JT, Furlong C, Rosowski JJ (2013) Digital holographic measurements of shape and three-dimensional sound-induced displacements of tympanic membrane. Opt Eng 52:101916. 10.1117/1.oe.52.10.101916<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24790255</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Rosowski JJ, Ramier A, Cheng JT, Yun SH (2020) Optical coherence tomographic measurements of the sound-induced motion of the ossicular chain in chinchillas: additional modes of ossicular motion enhance the mechanical response of the chinchilla middle ear at higher frequencies. Hear Res 396:108056. 10.1016/j.heares.2020.108056</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Oghalai</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Applegate</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Picometer scale vibrometry in the human middle ear using a surgical microscope based optical coherence tomography and vibrometry system</article-title><source>Biomed Opt Express</source><year>2019</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>4395</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1364/boe.10.004395</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31565497</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Kim W, Kim S, Huang S, Oghalai JS, Applegate BE (2019) Picometer scale vibrometry in the human middle ear using a surgical microscope based optical coherence tomography and vibrometry system. Biomed Opt Express 10:4395. 10.1364/boe.10.004395<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31565497</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>R&#x000f6;&#x000f6;sli</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobler</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosowski</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Simultaneous 3D imaging of sound-induced motions of the tympanic membrane and middle ear ossicles</article-title><source>Hear Res</source><year>2013</year><volume>304</volume><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>56</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.heares.2013.06.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23811181</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Chang EW, Cheng JT, R&#x000f6;&#x000f6;sli C, Kobler JB, Rosowski JJ, Yun SH (2013) Simultaneous 3D imaging of sound-induced motions of the tympanic membrane and middle ear ossicles. Hear Res 304:49&#x02013;56. 10.1016/j.heares.2013.06.006<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23811181</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>IW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Goh</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Extratympanic observation of middle and inner ear structures in rodents using optical coherence tomography</article-title><source>Clin Exp Otorhinolaryngol</source><year>2020</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>106</fpage><lpage>112</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21053/ceo.2019.00766</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31668054</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Oh SJ, Lee IW, Wang SG, Kong SK, Kim HK, Goh EK (2020) Extratympanic observation of middle and inner ear structures in rodents using optical coherence tomography. Clin Exp Otorhinolaryngol 13:106&#x02013;112. 10.21053/ceo.2019.00766<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31668054</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Livens</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ukshini</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Dirckx</surname><given-names>JJJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Measuring the motion of the eardrum using digital image correlation</article-title><source>J Phys: Conf Ser</source><year>2024</year><volume>2698</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>012024</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/1742-6596/2698/1/012024</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">Livens P, Ukshini E, Dirckx JJJ (2024) Measuring the motion of the eardrum using digital image correlation. J Phys: Conf Ser 2698(1):012024. 10.1088/1742-6596/2698/1/012024</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sim</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Puria</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Soft tissue morphometry of the malleus-incus complex from micro-ct imaging</article-title><source>JARO - J Assoc Res Otolaryngol</source><year>2008</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10162-007-0103-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18311579</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Sim JH, Puria S (2008) Soft tissue morphometry of the malleus-incus complex from micro-ct imaging. JARO - J Assoc Res Otolaryngol 9:5&#x02013;21. 10.1007/s10162-007-0103-x<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18311579</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kwacz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wysocki</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Krakowian</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reconstruction of the 3D geometry of the ossicular chain based on micro-ct imaging</article-title><source>Biocybernetics Biomed Eng</source><year>2012</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0208-5216(12)70030-X</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">Kwacz M, Wysocki J, Krakowian P (2012) Reconstruction of the 3D geometry of the ossicular chain based on micro-ct imaging. Biocybernetics Biomed Eng 32:27&#x02013;40. 10.1016/S0208-5216(12)70030-X</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elfarnawany</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohani</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghomashchi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Agrawal</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Ladak</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improved middle-ear soft-tissue visualization using synchrotron radiation phase-contrast imaging</article-title><source>Hear Res</source><year>2017</year><volume>354</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.heares.2017.08.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28822316</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Elfarnawany M, Rohani SA, Ghomashchi S, Allen DG, Zhu N, Agrawal SK, Ladak HM (2017) Improved middle-ear soft-tissue visualization using synchrotron radiation phase-contrast imaging. Hear Res 354:1&#x02013;8. 10.1016/j.heares.2017.08.001<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28822316</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anschuetz</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Dematt&#x000e8;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pica</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wimmer</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Caversaccio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonnin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synchrotron radiation imaging revealing the sub-micron structure of the auditory ossicles</article-title><source>Hear Res</source><year>2019</year><volume>383</volume><fpage>107806</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.heares.2019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31606582</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">Anschuetz L, Dematt&#x000e8; M, Pica A, Wimmer W, Caversaccio M, Bonnin A (2019) Synchrotron radiation imaging revealing the sub-micron structure of the auditory ossicles. Hear Res 383:107806. 10.1016/j.heares.2019<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31606582</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rohani</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gare</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Agrawal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ladak</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High-resolution imaging of the human incudostapedial joint using synchrotron-radiation phase- contrast imaging</article-title><source>J Microsc</source><year>2020</year><volume>277</volume><fpage>61</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jmi.12864</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31989597</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="journal">Rohani SA, Allen D, Gare B, Zhu N, Agrawal S, Ladak H (2020) High-resolution imaging of the human incudostapedial joint using synchrotron-radiation phase- contrast imaging. J Microsc 277:61&#x02013;70. 10.1111/jmi.12864<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31989597</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR26" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmeltz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ivanovic</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlep&#x000fc;tz</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wimmer</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>der Remenschnei-</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Caversaccio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Stampanoni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Anschuetz</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonnin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The human middle ear in motion: 3D visualization and quantification using dynamic synchrotron-based x-ray imaging</article-title><source>Commun Biol</source><year>2024</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>157</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s42003-023-05738-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38326549</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26" publication-type="journal">Schmeltz M, Ivanovic A, Schlep&#x000fc;tz CM, Wimmer W, der Remenschnei- AK, Caversaccio M, Stampanoni M, Anschuetz L, Bonnin A (2024) The human middle ear in motion: 3D visualization and quantification using dynamic synchrotron-based x-ray imaging. Commun Biol 7:157. 10.1038/s42003-023-05738-6<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38326549</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR27" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mokso</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlep&#x000fc;tz</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Theidel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Billich</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Celcer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mikuljan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Sala</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Marone</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlumpf</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Stampanoni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gigafrost: the gigabit fast readout system for tomography</article-title><source>J Synchrotron Radiat</source><year>2017</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>1250</fpage><lpage>1259</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S1600577517013522</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29091068</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27" publication-type="journal">Mokso R, Schlep&#x000fc;tz CM, Theidel G, Billich H, Schmid E, Celcer T, Mikuljan G, Sala L, Marone F, Schlumpf N, Stampanoni M (2017) Gigafrost: the gigabit fast readout system for tomography. J Synchrotron Radiat 24:1250&#x02013;1259. 10.1107/S1600577517013522<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29091068</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR28" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>B&#x000fc;hrer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Stampanoni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rochet</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x000fc;chi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Eller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Marone</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High-numerical-aperture macroscope optics for time-resolved experiments</article-title><source>J Synchrotron Radiat</source><year>2019</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>1161</fpage><lpage>1172</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S1600577519004119</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31274440</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28" publication-type="journal">B&#x000fc;hrer M, Stampanoni M, Rochet X, B&#x000fc;chi F, Eller J, Marone F (2019) High-numerical-aperture macroscope optics for time-resolved experiments. J Synchrotron Radiat 26:1161&#x02013;1172. 10.1107/S1600577519004119<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31274440</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Dejea H, Garcia-Canadilla P, Cook AC, Guasch E, Zamora M, Crispi F, Stampanoni M, Bijnens B, Bonnin A (2019) Comprehensive analysis of animal models of cardiovascular disease using multiscale x-ray phase contrast tomography. Sci Rep 9(1):6996. 10.1038/s41598-019-43407-z</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR30" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marone</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Stampanoni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regridding reconstruction algorithm for real-time tomographic imaging</article-title><source>J Synchrotron Radiat</source><year>2012</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1029</fpage><lpage>1037</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S0909049512032864</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23093766</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30" publication-type="journal">Marone F, Stampanoni M (2012) Regridding reconstruction algorithm for real-time tomographic imaging. J Synchrotron Radiat 19:1029&#x02013;1037. 10.1107/S0909049512032864<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23093766</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Vo NT, Atwood RC, Drakopoulos M (2018) Superior techniques for eliminating ring artifacts in X-ray micro-tomography. Opt Express 26(22):28396&#x02013;28412. 10.1364/oe.26.028396</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR32" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Huhns</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Algorithms for subpixel registration</article-title><source>Comput Vision, Graphics, Image Proc</source><year>1986</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>220</fpage><lpage>233</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0734-189X(86)90028-9</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32" publication-type="journal">Tian Q, Huhns MN (1986) Algorithms for subpixel registration. Comput Vision, Graphics, Image Proc 35:220&#x02013;233. 10.1016/0734-189X(86)90028-9</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR33" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Voss</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosowski</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Merchant</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Peake</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acoustic responses of the human middle ear</article-title><source>Hear Res</source><year>2000</year><volume>150</volume><issue>1-2</issue><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>69</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0378-5955(00)00177-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11077192</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR33" publication-type="journal">Voss SE, Rosowski JJ, Merchant SN, Peake WT (2000) Acoustic responses of the human middle ear. Hear Res 150(1&#x02013;2):43&#x02013;69. 10.1016/s0378-5955(00)00177-5<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11077192</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR34" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ravicz</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosowski</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chinchilla middle-ear admittance and sound power: high-frequency estimates and effects of inner-ear modifications</article-title><source>J Acoust Soc Am</source><year>2012</year><volume>132</volume><fpage>2437</fpage><lpage>2454</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1121/1.4750487</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23039439</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR34" publication-type="journal">Ravicz ME, Rosowski JJ (2012) Chinchilla middle-ear admittance and sound power: high-frequency estimates and effects of inner-ear modifications. J Acoust Soc Am 132:2437&#x02013;2454. 10.1121/1.4750487<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23039439</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Goode RL, Killion M, Nakamura K, Nishihara S (1994) New knowledge about the function of the human middle ear: development of an improved analog model.&#x000a0;Am J Otol 15(2):145&#x02013;54</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ravicz ME, Merchant SN, Rosowski JJ (2000) Effect of freezing and thawing on stapes-cochlear input impedance in human temporal bones. Hear Res 150(1&#x02013;2):215&#x02013;224.&#x000a0;10.1016/s0378-5955(00)00200-8</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR37" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name><name><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tollin</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Easter</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stapes displacement and intracochlear pressure in response to very high level, low frequency sounds</article-title><source>Hear Res</source><year>2017</year><volume>348</volume><fpage>16</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.heares.2017.02.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28189837</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR37" publication-type="journal">Greene NT, Jenkins HA, Tollin DJ, Easter JR (2017) Stapes displacement and intracochlear pressure in response to very high level, low frequency sounds. Hear Res 348:16&#x02013;30. 10.1016/j.heares.2017.02.002<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28189837</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Cheng JT, Ghanad I, Remenschneider A, Rosowski J (2021) The onset of nonlinear growth of middle-ear responses to high intensity sounds. Hear Res 405:108242.&#x000a0;10.1016/j.heares.2021.108242</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR39" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aerts</surname><given-names>JRM</given-names></name><name><surname>Dirckx</surname><given-names>JJJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nonlinearity in eardrum vibration as a function of frequency and sound pressure</article-title><source>Hear Res</source><year>2010</year><volume>263</volume><fpage>26</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.heares.2009.12.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20026266</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR39" publication-type="journal">Aerts JRM, Dirckx JJJ (2010) Nonlinearity in eardrum vibration as a function of frequency and sound pressure. Hear Res 263:26&#x02013;32. 10.1016/j.heares.2009.12.022<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20026266</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article>