<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="review-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Curr HIV/AIDS Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Curr HIV/AIDS Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Current HIV/AIDS Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1548-3568</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1548-3576</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer US</publisher-name><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40000537</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11861391</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">724</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11904-025-00724-5</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Review</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A Perspective on Home-Based Sexual Health Care: Evidence, Access, and Future Directions</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>(Hanneke) Goense</surname><given-names>Cornelia J.D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Evers</surname><given-names>Ymke J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hoebe</surname><given-names>Christian J.P.A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Dukers-Muijrers</surname><given-names>Nicole H.T.M.</given-names></name><address><email>Nicole.dukers@ggdzl.nl</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/04af0r679</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.491392.4</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0466 1148</institution-id><institution>Department of Sexual Health, Infectious Diseases and Environmental Health, Living Lab Public Health, </institution><institution>Public Health Service South Limburg, </institution></institution-wrap>P.O. Box 33, Heerlen, 6400 AA The Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/02jz4aj89</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5012.6</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0481 6099</institution-id><institution>Department of Health Promotion, Care and Public Health Research Institute (CAPHRI), </institution><institution>Maastricht University, </institution></institution-wrap>Maastricht, Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/02jz4aj89</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5012.6</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0481 6099</institution-id><institution>Department of Social Medicine, Care and Public Health Research Institute (CAPHRI), </institution><institution>Maastricht University, </institution></institution-wrap>Maastricht, Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/02d9ce178</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412966.e</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0480 1382</institution-id><institution>Department of Medical Microbiology, Infectious Diseases and Infection Prevention, Care and Public Health Research Institute (CAPHRI), </institution><institution>Maastricht University Medical Centre+ (MUMC+), </institution></institution-wrap>Maastricht, Netherlands </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>26</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>26</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>22</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>20</elocation-id><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>1</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Purpose</title><p id="Par1">This perspective explores the impact of home-based sexual health services on accessibility to STI and HIV testing for priority populations. This study evaluates home-based services as independent care options and as complementary components of traditional clinic-based care.</p></sec><sec><title>Recent Findings</title><p id="Par2">Challenges for persons to attend clinic-based sexual health care can be overcome by offering lower threshold home-based sexual health care. Implementing home-based services has successfully reached priority populations, including previously untested men who have sex with men (MSM) and individuals with a high exposure risk for sexually transmitted infections (STI) including human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), attending location-based sexual health care. A challenge in home-based services is to ensure equitable care, such as for individuals with limited access to digital resources or low health literacy.</p></sec><sec><title>Summary</title><p id="Par3">While home-based sexual health services enhance the accessibility of sexual healthcare, to ensure equitable care, research into the needs of still underserved populations and subsequent tailoring of the care offered, is needed. Continuous monitoring and evaluation of the implementation of home-based services may maximize the advantages of this promising type of care.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Home-based sexual health care</kwd><kwd>STI testing</kwd><kwd>HIV testing</kwd><kwd>Perspective</kwd><kwd>Implementation</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Aidsfonds Nederland</institution></funding-source><award-id>P-49903</award-id></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/501100004528</institution-id><institution>Maastricht Universitair Medisch Centrum</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>The Next Step</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Springer Science+Business Media, LLC, part of Springer Nature 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par4">In many global and national public health strategies, priority populations are identified for intervention and resource allocation for sexually transmitted infections (STI) including human immunodeficiency virus (HIV). Individuals in priority populations can benefit from targeted sexual health care interventions to make a significant impact on both individual and public health. Individuals from priority populations may encounter barriers to accessing location-based sexual health care, including feelings of shame, anticipated stigma from healthcare providers, and logistical difficulties such as distance to clinics and transportation costs, particularly in rural areas where such clinics are scarce [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Offering testing and care outside traditional clinics can help mitigate these barriers, making sexual health care more accessible. During public health crises like the COVID-19 pandemic, home-based sexual health services ensure the continuity of care [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Additionally, these services provide an accessible and cost-effective approach to regular STI and HIV testing, facilitating early diagnosis and treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. From an organizational perspective, implementing home-based care can alleviate the burden on clinic-based services by reducing the workload of healthcare providers and allowing resources to be redirected toward reaching vulnerable populations. This shift not only enhances service efficiency but also supports equitable access to sexual health care, location or home-based, for diverse patient groups [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>].</p><p id="Par5">Home-based sexual health care includes testing for either or both STI and HIV [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Furthermore, home-based sexual health care may present with diverse elements, for instance with self-sampling with laboratory testing or self-testing where the patient self assesses the results [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Stand-alone home-based sexual health care is widely available as paid or commercially available self-(sampling) tests to order online or buy in stores. Also, home-based care services were found to be integrated within existing location-based care. Main implementers then are health care providers of public health services, STI clinics, or general practitioners [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Some examples of home-based services with self-collection at home and laboratory analysis for STI testing are &#x0201c;I Want the Kit&#x0201d; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>], &#x02018;TakeMeHome&#x02019; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>], Project Caboodle [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]!, Preventx online postal self-sampling [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>], MemoDepistages [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>], and a Dutch regional home-based sexual health care service &#x0201c;Limburg4zero&#x0201d; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Other examples of home-based care services mostly use HIV self-testing options, where patients need to self-assess their results [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>].</p><p id="Par6">This perspective aimed to explore the evidence of home-based sexual health care regarding the accessibility of care for priority populations, and the benefits and challenges of home-based care. In addition, implementation possibilities and future developments of home-based sexual health care were explored.</p><sec id="Sec234443"><title>A Perspective on Home-Based Sexual Health Care</title><p id="Par7">Home-based sexual health care can be viewed as &#x0201c;comprehensive&#x0201d; when it consists of a combination of the key elements of home-based testing (self-testing or self-sampling testing) for STI or HIV, additional counseling through (tailored) online sexual health information or e-health services, and referral to obtaining treatment or further needed (medical) care [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Key elements of the implementation of home-based care include tailoring the care service and its dissemination to the priority population (formerly also referred to as &#x02018;key population&#x02019;), including ensuring the provision of clear and accessible instructions.</p><p id="Par8">Whereas in recent past, all priority populations who sought sexual health care had to attend location-based care, the option of home-based sexual health care now allows relocation of care to the home setting [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. Most reports evaluating home-based care and its implementation were focused on men who have sex with men (MSM) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>], including previously untested MSM at risk for STI and HIV exposure. Several studies confirm the successful reach of this population. A Dutch regional home-based sexual health care service for MSM demonstrated that approximately 40% of the users never had tested before [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Home-based STI and HIV testing services in Asian countries have also demonstrated success in reaching previously untested MSM [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. A recent randomized controlled trial among MSM in the US found that self-testing motivated frequent HIV testing among those who had never tested before, supported by the option of eHealth (eTest) follow-up and sexual health counselling [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. This study reported that home-based testing contributed to the diagnosis of new HIV cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Another home-based service in the US (TakeMeHome) identified new cases of STI and HIV [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>].</p><p id="Par9">In addition, home-based sexual health care is an acceptable alternative to location-based care for MSM who previously attended location-based care. A positive attitude and high intention to use home-based sexual health care were demonstrated among Dutch MSM who previously attended location-based care [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. A French home-based sexual health care service (MemoDepistages) also reached out to MSM who had a previous test experience [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. Uptake of self-sampling testing was particularly high among MSM who reported to have sex with multiple partners.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2333"><title>Evidence for Advantages and Challenges</title><p id="Par10">Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> shows an overview of the advantages and challenges of diverse forms of sexual health care, comparing location-based sexual health care, comprehensive home-based sexual health care integrated in routine (STI clinic) care, and home-based testing services offered commercially. A recent scoping review evaluated stand-alone STI tests that a person could order online across the US [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>], highlighting the value of this care-for in reaching patients who experience challenges in attending location-based care. The offered care services are usually found acceptable by its users. For example, a recent qualitative study among MSM in the US (Project Caboodle!) demonstrated a highly positive attitude towards using home-based sexual health care services. Home-based testing could lower barriers to STI and HIV testing for MSM who expected or experienced challenges (e.g., stigma, transportation) in attending location-based care [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Participants particularly praised the discretion and usability of the test kits [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Providing populations with various options for STI and HIV testing, to choose from, at home or at location, enhances their autonomy and self-control over their own sexual health [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. Another example is a qualitative study (TINY vial) among MSM in the UK, demonstrating an increased sense of independence and autonomy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. An example of a challenge experienced by home-based care users is that blood self-collection using a finger prick in home-based care, can be a complex procedure for some patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>].</p><p id="Par11">
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Advantages and challenges of different sexual health care services</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left">Advantages</th><th align="left">Challenges</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">
<bold>Location-based sexual health care at an STI clinic</bold>
</td><td align="left"><p>- Standard of care available</p><p>- Availability of prevention and counseling services</p><p>- Opportunity to immediately examine symptoms by a health care provider in person</p><p>- Referral to treatment or direct medication provision, and partner-management services</p></td><td align="left"><p>- May not be accessible for various populations who experience barriers to location-based care</p><p>- No show at the clinic</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><p>
<bold>Home-based comprehensive sexual health care offered by health care providers</bold>
</p><p>(this is a combination of self-(sampling) testing, additional counseling options, treatment, and referral)</p></td><td align="left"><p>- Standard of care available</p><p>- Accessible for priority populations for whom the service was designed</p><p>- Tailoring of direct online counseling and advice and opportunity for chat or webcam consultation</p><p>- Professional help (knowledge, skills, advice) (remotely) available regarding sexual health care</p></td><td align="left"><p>- Lost-to-follow-up</p><p>- Missing opportunities for further sexual health counseling</p><p>- May be less accessible for populations for which the service was not specifically designed</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><p>
<bold>Commercialized (stand-alone) home-based sexual health care</bold>
</p><p>(this is paid self-(sampling) testing services)</p></td><td align="left"><p>- Accessible for large group of people</p><p>- Higher return rate of (paid) self-sampling tests</p></td><td align="left"><p>- Lost-to-follow up</p><p>- Standard of care unknown</p><p>- Missing opportunities for further care and prevention</p><p>- May not be accessible for individuals with lower financial resource</p></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par12">An advantage of home-based care is its reach in populations that are underserved or at highest exposure risk. An Australian surveillance study assessed HIV test uptake following the introduction of commercial (paid) HIV self-tests [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. While the overall increase in home-based HIV testing was modest, the study indicated effective reach among priority populations, including MSM with irregular testing histories, migrants, and individuals at elevated risk for HIV exposure, who were more likely to test at home. This suggests that both care-integrated and commercially provided at-home testing may enhance the accessibility of sexual health care. However, when testing services are not administered by a health care provider, the quality and standard of care may not be assured [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. Concerns regarding commercially provided tests primarily focus on the accuracy of self-tests and the confidentiality of the testing process, and challenges in high testing costs for the patient. These challenges are typically absent in home-based care offered by public health care [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. </p></sec><sec id="Sec23566"><title>Improving Accessibility of Care for Underserved Priority Populations</title><p id="Par13">Individuals from priority populations may face barriers to accessing location-based sexual health care including stigma and logistical or other contextual challenges, particularly in rural areas. Home-based care offers an alternative that addresses these barriers by providing accessible testing and services outside traditional clinics. The specific tailoring of home-based care to underserved groups, could contribute to reduce inequity in access to healthcare. Nevertheless, a scoping review on outcomes for home-based testing by online postal service described the potential of growing inequity induced by this type of care [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. This occurs when the care service matches the needs, preferences, and skills of certain members of priority populations while being incongruent with those of other priority populations. The scoping review suggested that home-based sexual health care may be most suitable for individuals who already had used location-based care, but possibly less accessible for more vulnerable individuals who have sexual health concerns or who were unfamiliar with location-based care.</p><p id="Par14">The implementation evaluation of the Dutch &#x0201c;Limburg4zero&#x0201d; revealed that while the priority population of untested MSM was effectively reached, there was an underrepresentation of potentially vulnerable subgroups, such as MSM with less than a high school education and migrants of non-Western ethnicity, highlighting potential underlying inequities in access [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Continuous evaluation and enhancement of sexual healthcare accessibility for diverse underserved priority groups remains essential. A realist review revealed the importance of contextual elements herein [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Design of tailored communication messages, harmonized with the needs of the priority population, may enhance risk perception, self-control, and general STI and HIV knowledge [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>].</p><p id="Par15">To be able to tailor a service to the needs of the priority population, what is needed is an ongoing evaluation of the uptake and implementation of the service and its associated factors, including the dissemination and communication of the care service, and allowing for systematic adaptation of both the service and the implementation process. The high customizability of home-based care services should be fully utilized to optimize both the service itself for various priority populations and the implementation by health care providers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. For example, translating testing information to diverse languages enhances the accessibility of the service for MSM. A study in Cameroon demonstrated successful uptake of HIV self-testing when materials were available in regional languages [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. Additional consultation options with a health care provider can be built in (for instance via phone or by webcam), as reportedly favored by MSM on pre-exposure prophylaxis (PrEP) when they would use home-based testing rather than location-based care; these MSM valued face-to-face consultations with an health care provider when testing for STI and HIV [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. A previous RCT among male couples also suggested additional video counseling with an health care provider when STI testing at home (Project Nexus), especially when receiving positive results to improve linkage to care [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. A global systematic review supports the addition of digital counseling options, such as by webcam, specifically when self-testing and self-assessing the results [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Webcam consultations can be a digital alternative to or complement in-person contact at a clinic location. However, challenges may be encountered such as organizational limitations in (information or digital) technological possibilities, the financial resources for such innovations, and a lack of process management when tailoring a health care innovation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec37888"><title>The Role of Health Care Providers in Successful Implementation</title><p id="Par16">Public health care providers at an STI clinic can implement home-based sexual health care services in close collaboration with other health care providers, such as general practitioners or hospital-based specialists, and with community-based organizations and community-members [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Implementing home-based sexual healthcare can speed up care provision for priority populations, it may help reduce location-based patient load, and thereby reduce waiting times overall. Home-based caremay also allow health care providers to allocate time to other critical tasks, such as attending to more vulnerable individuals including persons with low health literacy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. Previous studies have reported health care provider task shifting and increased work efficiency when implementing home-based sexual health care [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>].</p><p id="Par17">A concern expressed by health care providers was the potential loss of direct patient contact in home-based care, regarding possible counseling advantages of in-person interaction. Although health care providers have generally expressed willingness to implement home-based care services, they were uncertain about patients&#x02019; follow-up on positive results and missed opportunities for prevention [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. This was also demonstrated in a Dutch implementation of home-based sexual health care, where nurses provided detailed examples of concerns about the quality of care such as a lack of direct contact with patients, which may result in missing (non-verbal) signals and, consequently, hinder the ability to deliver appropriate care and prevention [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>].</p><p id="Par18">For the care organization, the long-term cost-effectiveness of implementing home-based sexual health care is considered an advantage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. It is noted that initial implementation may require higher costs due to the expenses involved in starting process. These costs can include extra staffing, setting up collaborations with stakeholders, putting necessary systems in place, and establishing monitoring processes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>].</p><p id="Par19">A qualitative evaluation study among staff of an Australian sexual health care service outside a clinic (MyCheck) highlighted the value of allowing patients to decide on where to get tested [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. A US study concluded follow-up possibilities with eHealth services as a beneficial addition when, in this case, MSM used HIV self-testing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. MSM reportedly preferred home-based sexual health care as a complimentary option to location-based services [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. An American modeling study suggested that supplementing HIV self-testing with regular location-based sexual health care could contribute to reducing HIV incidence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec36777"><title>Implementation Opportunities</title><p id="Par20">An important and common concern associated with health care innovations is the risk of inadequate implementation. Also in home-based sexual health care, various elements of the intended implementation strategy (i.e., registration processes, communicational strategies, monitoring) are not always put into practice, preventing the intended advantages of the home-based service from being secured in real life care practice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. When implementating, it is crucial to have knowledge about the (determinants of) behavior of professionals in adopting, implementing, and continuing the intervention as intended, as well as knowledge about the various contextual factors, in order to optimize the implementation success of the home-based care innovation.</p><p id="Par21">A wide number of studies described the implementation of home-based sexual health care, but only a few studies to date reported using a systematic implementation framework. The Practical, Robust, Implementation and Sustainability Model (PRISM) is one such framework, and may be utilized to guide, optimize, and evaluate the implementation process systematically [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. A study on the implementation of HIV testing in a workplace (Test@Work) in the United Kingdom assessed that the RE-AIM framework aided in evaluating the intervention and assessed the challenges of implementing it [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. An Australian peer-led STI screening program (Deadly Liver Mob) highlighted that RE-AIM enabled a clear description of the implementation process in a real-world setting [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>].</p><p id="Par22">The PRISM framework addresses key outcomes of the implementation strategy which are: the Reach of the priority population, the Effectiveness of the intervention, Adoption of the intervention, Implementation fidelity, and long-term Maintenance (in short RE-AIM), brought together with contextual domains such as external environment and sustainability infrastructure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. A key feature of PRISM is that it includes the validation of the role of &#x02018;context&#x02019;. The importance of contextual domains for the understanding of implementation success is also stressed in a qualitative study on the use of the Consolidated Framework for Implementation Research (CFIR), which is another frequently used implementation framework [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>].</p><p id="Par23">Ideally, an implementation framework should be used before and also throughout implementation, in (1) selecting framework(s) and behavioral theories, (2) establishing and maintaining stakeholder engagement, (3) defining and developing evaluation questions, (4) developing an implementation mechanistic process model or logic model (i.e., visually linking resources and outcomes), (5) selecting evaluation methods (6) determining implementation factors, (7) selecting, tailoring, or developing, implementation strategy(s), (8) specifying implementation outcomes and evaluating implementation, (9) using the framework(s) on a limited scale (pilot) to tailor implementation, and (10) reporting [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. A challenge of the PRISM framework is its broad scope, which can complicate operationalization, and demand significant effort to assess the multiple interacting factors across diverse implementation contexts comprehensively.</p></sec><sec id="Sec366900"><title>Future Directions</title><p id="Par24">Future developments may be focused on the optimization of home-based sexual health care service itself and the optimization of implementation strategies. For example, improving the care service by enhancing serology sampling methods, such as easier high-volume blood self-collection (other than via finger-prick), and improving implementation by including digital developments, such as the use of artificial intelligence (AI). In recent years, advancements in home-based sexual health care have accelerated, offering more accessible and efficient solutions. Particularly since the global COVID-19 pandemic home-based sexual health care services have been increasingly optimized and implemented [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec34678"><title>Blood Sampling</title><p id="Par25">Home-based STI and HIV testing requires individuals to take samples at home. This may be challenging, especially for blood self-collection (regarding adequate volumes capillary) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. For syphilis and HIV laboratory testing on blood, a certain minimum of blood volume is required for valid diagnostics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. Sampling blood at home is usually done via finger-prick blood collection, though in recent years alternative methods have been developed. An example of innovative blood collection methodology is the use of a semi-automatic vacuum microneedle [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. The assessed at-home device (Tasso+) allowed the user to semi-automatically collect blood from the upper arm through a vacuum mechanism. This blood collection procedure was found highly acceptable and feasible for collecting larger volumes of blood enabling testing and including confirmation testing for various STIs including HIV. A US study showed promising results in testing such device on a larger scale, along with real-world logistic possibilities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>].</p><p id="Par26">A similar upper arm blood self-collection device, the TAP II device, has only been tested among patients with immune-mediated inflammatory rheumatic disease. In this study the upper-arm collection methods were usable, and half of the patients preferred the device compared to venous blood collection (by an health care provider) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. Another similar device (Onflow) reportedly provided painless blood collection from the upper arm. However, to date, this device has only been assessed under the supervision of health care providers, who were able to correctly apply the device [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. A potential limitation of these upper arm methods is their higher cost compared to finger-prick blood collection; however, no studies to date have evaluated this issue.</p></sec><sec id="Sec3268998"><title>Digital Communication and Services Provision Methods</title><p id="Par27">In a pre-implementation study among MSM, their preferences in types of interactions with an health care provider in future home-based sexual health care service were evaluated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. MSM reported a preference for telephone and webcam contact with an health care provider [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>], aligning with findings among PrEP using MSM [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>].</p><p id="Par28">Rather than contact with a &#x02018;real person&#x02019;, contact with a chatbot is increasingly used in sexual health care. An example of applying a chatbot in sexual health care is a pilot study among MSM in Malaysia which determined interaction with AI chatbots to be facilitating in accessing HIV testing and sexual health information [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]. In the Netherlands, an online chatbot (Advies.chat) is available to advise on cues to action that the individual should take based on answers to questions such as about specific symptoms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. In a recent narrative review, the advantages and challenges of chatbots for HIV prevention were assessed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]. For individuals who experienced challenges in contacting an health care provider, engaging with a chatbot may be a solution. It may be experienced as easy, not stigmatizing for those who seek sexual health care (information), potentially leading to the uptake of HIV testing. However, applying chatbots in sexual health care in counseling may raise concerns considering the safety and ethicality of data, as well as the correctness of medical advice given by chatbots when using AI algorithms.</p><p id="Par29">Another useful tool for accessing home-based sexual health care may be mobile applications (LYNX and MyChoice), where people can order their test and see their results via an app, as evaluated among young MSM in the US [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. In a qualitative study among young MSM from China the feasibility of app-based health care was confirmed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. Here again, confidentiality concerns regarding information security were expressed. Especially younger individuals may benefit from digital communication and services provision since they obtain most of their sexual health information through digital sources (i.e., internet, and mobile applications) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>].</p><p id="Par30">In previous research, online communication for the distribution of home-based sexual health care was the preferred communication mode [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>], but offline communication (i.e., posters, cards, and word-of-mouth communication) should be available for populations that have insufficient access to digital technology or otherwise have low (digital) health literacy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>]. &#x0201c;Limburg4zero&#x0201d; employed a broad and tailored communication strategy that used a mixed approach of online and offline channels to reach out to diverse groups of MSM [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Social media could be a mode to disseminate the care service. In-depth interviews with MSM from the US demonstrated a positive attitude toward advertisements about PrEP in dating apps and participants deemed the advertisements to be effective [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]. A strategy for online dissemination is by targeting. A recent case study (Open door Health) demonstrated the effectiveness of targeted search engine advertisements for increased use of STI and HIV testing services [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>].</p><p id="Par31">Recently the WHO released a technical briefing on using AI in sexual health, stating this as a facilitator of access to sexual health care [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>]. A review study from the US identified possible AI applications in preventing HIV. A key finding was the potential of AI in the early identification of individuals who were at high risk for HIV exposure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]. An Australian study evaluated an AI tool (<italic>MySTIRisk</italic>) that used machine learning to identify patients at elevated risk for STI and HIV from a public health center database [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>]. The machine learning tool was successful in determining the priority populations, who were at risk for HIV exposure. Consequently, identified priority populations could be offered early testing and preventive options including PrEP.</p><p id="Par32">Another AI development is to aid clinical diagnosis. For instance, the identification of STI by using images of the skin (HeHealth) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>]. Particularly for STI such as syphilis and mpox, this presents an opportunity for individuals to photograph their symptoms and perform self-assessments at home. Still, ethical questions are also raised about the privacy and security of data concerning a person&#x02019;s sexual health [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. The WHO called for AI applications as facilitators for accessing sexual health care while ensuring human rights and patients&#x02019; privacy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par33">Home-based sexual health overall increases the accessibility to sexual health care, STI, and HIV testing for previously untested MSM. It also offers an alternative to engage MSM that have attended location-based care, such as for PrEP. Home-based care can be a stand-alone service yet is also strong as a more comprehensive care offer that is offered as a complementary service integrated within location-based sexual health care. Implementing home-based strategies ultimately strives for achieving improved sexual health by an equitable healthcare offer. Nevertheless, ensuring equity is a continuous challenge not solved by the home-based services currently in place. Future research needs to specifically address accessibility of sexual health care for vulnerable individuals, still underserved by current care options. Therefore, low-threshold location-based care should remain an alternative, and developing secure digital sexual health solutions should be encouraged, specifically addressing priority populations&#x02019; health care needs. Continuous evaluation of (usage of) the home-based care-elements as well as the implementation of the care should be pursued where possible, to optimize home-based care and its accessibility and the seamless integration of this service into routine sexual health care.</p><sec id="Sec265677"><title>Recommendations for Practice Implications</title><p id="Par34">Our recommendations regarding the integration, implementation, and development of home-based sexual health care are as follows:</p><p id="Par35">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p id="Par36"><bold>Implement home-based sexual health care complementary to existing location-based sexual health care.</bold> Home-based sexual health care is highly acceptable for priority populations, and it should be integrated into existing location-based sexual health care. Doing so combines the advantages of both care forms such as supporting the self-autonomy of its users (since they may choose where and when they want to utilize sexual health care services) and health care providers can ensure the quality of care when the home-based care is offered by this highly skilled health care provider, who can also link the patient to location-based care when necessary.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par37"><bold>Tailoring of the care offer and its implementation is essential for improving the accessibility of home-based sexual health care.</bold> To address the preferences of the priority population and subgroups, it is necessary to tailor the home-based service to enhance its accessibility. For instance, by performing a needs assessment before implementation, a home-based sexual health care service may be customized to fit the preferences of the priority population. A systematic optimization of the intervention itself, for example by using the systematic Intervention Mapping framework [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>], and of its implementation strategies for maximal promotion of its use in various priority groups, is recommended.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par38"><bold>Follow an implementation science framework.</bold> To systematically implement a care intervention, specifically a home-based sexual health care service, we recommend adherence to an implementation science framework. The use of a systematic implementation framework to provide a certain level of detail and tailoring of the implementation strategies to optimally harness the benefits of the home-based care intervention in practice, is beneficial to use by health care providers and scientists, learn from, and work sequentially to progress the field. A systematic approach can facilitate a successful and structured implementation process, eventually leading to the desired outcome which is improved sexual health for all.</p></list-item></list>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec22222"><title>Key References</title><p id="Par39">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p id="Par40">Flowers P, Riddell J, Park C, Ahmed B, Young I, Frankis J, et al. Preparedness for use of the rapid result HIV self-test by gay men and other men who have sex with men (MSM): a mixed methods exploratory study among MSM and those involved in HIV prevention and care. HIV Med [Internet]. 2017;18:245&#x02013;55. Available from: https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/hiv.12420.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par41">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p id="Par42">This study shows the acceptability of home-based sexual health care services among health care providers.</p></list-item></list>
</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par43">Goense CJD, Doan THP, Kpokiri EE, Evers YJ, Estcourt CS, Crutzen R, et al. Understanding Practical, Robust Implementation and Sustainability of Home-based Comprehensive Sexual Health Care: A Realist Review. AIDS Behav. 2024.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par44">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p id="Par45">This realist review helps understand key elements that enhance the implementation of home-based sexual health care among priority populations.</p></list-item></list>
</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par46">Rapid Response Service. A review of internet-based testing services for HIV and sexually transmitted infections (STIs) [Internet]. Toronto, ON; 2022 Mar. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ohtn.on.ca/rapid-response-a-review-of-internet-based-testing-services-for-hiv-and-sexually-transmitted-infections-stis/">https://www.ohtn.on.ca/rapid-response-a-review-of-internet-based-testing-services-for-hiv-and-sexually-transmitted-infections-stis/</ext-link></p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par47">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p id="Par48">This source summarizes current, promising home-based testing services for STI.</p></list-item></list>
</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par49">Goense CJD, Evers YJ, Manait J, Hoebe CJ, van Loo IH, Posthouwer D, et al. Evaluating the Implementation of Home-based Sexual Health Care among Men Who Have Sex with Men: Limburg4zero. AIDSBehav 2025;</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par50">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p id="Par51">This study evaluates the implementation process of a regional home-based sexual health care service in the Netherlands.</p></list-item></list>
</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par52">Feldstein AC, Russell Glasgow ME. A Practical, Robust Implementation and Sustainability Model (PRISM) for Integrating Research Findings into Practice Research Methods. The Joint Commission Journal on Quality and Patient Safety [Internet]. 2008;34:228&#x02013;43. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ihi.org/IHI/Topics/Improvement/ImprovementMethods/HowToImprove/">http://www.ihi.org/IHI/Topics/Improvement/ImprovementMethods/HowToImprove/</ext-link>.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par53">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p id="Par54">This study explains the PRISM framework&#x02019;s usability for implementing complex health care innovations.</p></list-item></list>
</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par55">Cannon C, Holzhauer K, Golden M. Implementation and Evaluation of a Home-Based Pre-Exposure Prophylaxis Monitoring Option: Protocol for a Randomized Controlled Trial. JMIR Res Protoc [Internet]. 2024;13:e56587. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.researchprotocols.org/2024/1/e56587">https://www.researchprotocols.org/2024/1/e56587</ext-link>.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par56">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p id="Par57">This study describes an RCT protocol for testing an innovative health care innovation considering self-blood collection in a real-life larger-scale setting.</p></list-item></list>
</p></list-item></list>
</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>CG wrote the first draft of the paper, supervised by YE, CH, and ND. All authors approved the final draft before submission.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This study is part of &#x0201c;Limburg4Zero: An integrated approach to reduce the number of HIV and sexually transmitted diseases in Limburg&#x0201d;. Limburg4Zero received funding from Aidsfonds Nederland; P-49903, P-2374, and by Maastricht University Medical Center&#x02009;+&#x02009;within &#x02018;the Next Step&#x02019; funding scheme.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data Availability</title><p>No datasets were generated or analysed during the current study.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethical Approval</title><p id="Par58">This article does not contain any studies with human or animal subjects performed by any of the authors.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing Interests</title><p id="Par59">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deblonde</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>De Koker</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamers</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></name><name><surname>Fontaine</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Luchters</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Temmerman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Barriers to HIV testing in Europe: A systematic review</article-title><source>Eur J Public Health</source><year>2010</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>422</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/eurpub/ckp231</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20123683</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Deblonde J, De Koker P, Hamers FF, Fontaine J, Luchters S, Temmerman M. Barriers to HIV testing in Europe: A systematic review. Eur J Public Health. 2010;20:422&#x02013;32.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20123683</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Denison</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bromhead</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Grainger</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Dennison</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jutel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Barriers to sexually transmitted infection testing in new Zealand: a qualitative study</article-title><source>Aust N Z J Public Health</source><year>2017</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>432</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1753-6405.12680</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28664644</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Denison HJ, Bromhead C, Grainger R, Dennison EM, Jutel A. Barriers to sexually transmitted infection testing in new Zealand: a qualitative study. Aust N Z J Public Health. 2017;41:432&#x02013;7.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28664644</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Leenen J, Hoebe CJPA, Bos AER, Wolffs PFG, van Loo IHM, de Wit JBF et al. Systematic development of an intervention to promote Self-Sampling for HIV and sexually transmitted infections for men who have sex with men: an intervention mapping approach. Front Reproductive Health. 2021;3.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carnevale</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohall</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Choe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zitaner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>At-Home testing for sexually transmitted infections during the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title><source>Sex Transm Dis</source><year>2021</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/OLQ.0000000000001313</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Carnevale C, Richards P, Cohall R, Choe J, Zitaner J, Hall N, et al. At-Home testing for sexually transmitted infections during the COVID-19 pandemic. Sex Transm Dis. 2021;48:11&#x02013;4.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stephenson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Chavanduka</surname><given-names>TMD</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosso</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Pitter</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sex in the time of COVID-19: results of an online survey of gay, bisexual and other men who have sex with men&#x02019;s experience of sex and HIV prevention during the US COVID-19 epidemic</article-title><source>AIDS Behav</source><year>2021</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>40</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10461-020-03024-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32876905</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Stephenson R, Chavanduka TMD, Rosso MT, Sullivan SP, Pitter RA, Hunter AS, et al. Sex in the time of COVID-19: results of an online survey of gay, bisexual and other men who have sex with men&#x02019;s experience of sex and HIV prevention during the US COVID-19 epidemic. AIDS Behav. 2021;25:40&#x02013;8.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32876905</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sanders GD, Bayoumi AM, Sundaram V, Bilir SP, Neukermans CP, Rydzak CE et al. Cost-Effectiveness of Screening for HIV in the Era of Highly Active Antiretroviral Therapy [Internet]. N Engl J Med. 2005. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nejm.org">www.nejm.org</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Seguin M, Dodds C, Mugweni E, McDaid L, Flowers P, Wayal S et al. Self-sampling kits to increase HIV testing among black Africans in the UK: the HAUS mixed-methods study. Health Technol Assess [Internet]. 2018;22:1&#x02013;158. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/29717978">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/29717978</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Agust&#x000ed; C, Mu&#x000f1;oz R, Gonz&#x000e1;lez V, Villegas L, Fibla J, Mero&#x000f1;o M et al. Outreach HIV testing using oral fluid and online consultation of the results: pilot intervention in Catalonia. Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin. 2021;39.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Flowers P, Riddell J, Park C, Ahmed B, Young I, Frankis J et al. Preparedness for use of the rapid result HIV self-test by gay men and other men who have sex with men (MSM): a mixed methods exploratory study among MSM and those involved in HIV prevention and care. HIV Med [Internet]. 2017;18:245&#x02013;55. Available from: 10.1111/hiv.12420</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Goense CJD, Doan THP, Kpokiri EE, Evers YJ, Estcourt CS, Crutzen R et al. Understanding practical, robust implementation and sustainability of Home-based comprehensive sexual health care: A realist review. AIDS Behav. 2024.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harding-Esch</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hollis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohammed</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Saunders</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Self-sampling and self-testing for stis and HIV: the case for consistent nomenclature</article-title><source>Sex Transm Infect Month</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>10</fpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Harding-Esch EM, Hollis E, Mohammed H, Saunders JM. Self-sampling and self-testing for stis and HIV: the case for consistent nomenclature. Sex Transm Infect Month. 2015;5:10.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Rapid Response Service. A review of internet-based testing services for HIV and sexually transmitted infections (STIs) [Internet], Toronto ON. 2022 Mar. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ohtn.on.ca/rapid-response-a-review-of-internet-based-testing-services-for-hiv-and-sexually-transmitted-infections-stis/">https://www.ohtn.on.ca/rapid-response-a-review-of-internet-based-testing-services-for-hiv-and-sexually-transmitted-infections-stis/</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hogenson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Jett-Goheen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaydos</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An analysis of user survey data for an internet program for testing for sexually transmitted infections, i want the kit, in Maryland and Washington, DC</article-title><source>Sex Transm Dis</source><year>2019</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>768</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/OLQ.0000000000001061</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31663978</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Hogenson E, Jett-Goheen M, Gaydos CA. An analysis of user survey data for an internet program for testing for sexually transmitted infections, i want the kit, in Maryland and Washington, DC. Sex Transm Dis. 2019;46:768&#x02013;70.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31663978</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hecht J, Facente SN, Cohen S, Menza T, Trainor N, Heumann C et al. TakeMeHome: A novel method for reaching previously untested people through online ordering and self-collect HIV and STI testing. Sex Transm Dis [Internet]. 2024; Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://journals.lww.com/">https://journals.lww.com/</ext-link>10.1097/OLQ.0000000000002058</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sallabank G, Stephenson R, Gandhi M, Merrill L, Sharma A. Lessons learned from the implementation of a pilot study on Self-collected specimen return by sexual minority men (Project Caboodle!): Qualitative Exploration. JMIR Form Res. 2023;7.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Spence T, Howarth A, Reid D, Sheringham J, Apea V, Crundwell D et al. How does online postal self-sampling (OPSS) shape access to testing for sexually transmitted infections (STIs)? A qualitative study of service users. BMC Public Health. 2024;24.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Rahib D, Bercot B, Delagreverie H, Gabassi A, Delaugerre C, Salord H et al. Online self-sampling kits for human immunodeficiency virus and other sexually transmitted infections: feasibility, positivity rates, and factors associated with infections in France. Int J STD AIDS. 2022;33.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Goense CJD, Evers YJ, Manait J, Hoebe CJPA, van Loo IHM, Posthouwer D et al. Evaluating the Implementation of Home-Based Sexual Health Care Among Men Who Have Sex with Men: Limburg4zero. AIDS Behav [Internet]. 2025; Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://link.springer.com/">https://link.springer.com/</ext-link>10.1007/s10461-024-04579-6</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Jin X, Xu J, Smith MK, Xiao D, Rapheal ER, Xiu X et al. An internet-based self-testing model (easy test): Cross-sectional survey targeting men who have sex with men who never tested for HIV in 14 provinces of China. J Med Internet Res. 2019;21.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wray TB, Chan PA, Klausner JD, Ward LM, Ocean EMS, Carr DJ et al. The effects of regular home delivery of HIV self-testing and follow-up counselling on HIV testing and prevention outcomes in men who have sex with men who test infrequently in the United States: a pragmatic, virtual randomized controlled trial. J Int AIDS Soc [Internet]. 2024;27:26318. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/jia2.26318/full">http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/https://doi.org/10.1002/jia2.26318/full</ext-link>|10.1002/jia2.26318</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Manabe</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Highlighting and addressing barriers to widespread adaptation of HIV self-testing in the united States</article-title><source>Expert Rev Mol Diagn</source><year>2023</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>191</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14737159.2023.2187291</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36891583</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Ma S, Manabe YC. Highlighting and addressing barriers to widespread adaptation of HIV self-testing in the united States. Expert Rev Mol Diagn. 2023;23:191&#x02013;8.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36891583</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Rosadi&#x000f1;o JDT, Pagtakhan RG, Bri&#x000f1;es MT, Dinglasan JLG, Cruz DP, Corciega JOL et al. Implementation of unassisted and community-based HIV Self-Testing (HIVST) during the COVID-19 pandemic among Men-who-have-sex-with-Men (MSM) and transgender women (TGW): A demonstration study in metro Manila, Philippines. PLoS ONE. 2023;18.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gupta-Wright A, Barnabas RV, Ingold H, Duneton P, Abubakar I. HIV self-testing: lessons learnt and priorities for adaptation in a shifting landscape. BMJ Glob Health. 2021;6.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Yeh PT, Kennedy CE, Minamitani A, Baggaley R, Shah P, Verster A et al. Web-Based service provision of HIV, viral hepatitis, and sexually transmitted infection prevention, testing, linkage, and treatment for key populations: systematic review and Meta-analysis. J Med Internet Res. 2022;24.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Phanuphak N, Jantarapakde J, Himmad L, Sungsing T, Meksena R, Phomthong S et al. Linkages to HIV confirmatory testing and antiretroviral therapy after online, supervised, HIV self-testing among Thai men who have sex with men and transgender women. J Int AIDS Soc [Internet]. 2020;23. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/">http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/</ext-link>10.1002/jia2.25448/full</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Goense CJ, Evers YJ, Hoebe Christian JPA, Crutzen Rik, Dukers-Muijrers NH. Intention to use and acceptability of home-based sexual health care among men who have sex with men who previously attended clinic-based sexual health care. Front Reproductive Health. 2022.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Rahib D, Delagreverie H, Gabassi A, Le Thi T, Vassel E, Vodosin P et al. Online self-sampling kits to screen multipartner MSM for HIV and other STIs: Participant characteristics and factors associated with kit use in the first three months of the MemoDepistages program, France, 2018. Sex Transm Infect. 2021;97:134&#x02013;40.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR28" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manca</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Der Pol</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Exten</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinto</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A review of the scope of Direct-to-Consumer sexually transmitted infection testing services offered on the internet</article-title><source>Sex Transm Dis</source><year>2023</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>323</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36807311</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28" publication-type="journal">Manca E, Van Der Pol B, Exten C, Pinto CN. A review of the scope of Direct-to-Consumer sexually transmitted infection testing services offered on the internet. Sex Transm Dis. 2023;50:323&#x02013;8.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36807311</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Spence T, Kander I, Walsh J, Griffiths F, Ross J. Perceptions and experiences of internet-based testing for sexually transmitted infections: systematic review and synthesis of qualitative research. J Med Internet Res. 2020;22.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Dodds C, Mugweni E, Phillips G, Park C, Young I, Fakoya F et al. Acceptability of HIV self-sampling kits (TINY vial) among people of black African ethnicity in the UK: A qualitative study. BMC Public Health. 2018;18.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Goense CJD, Evers YJ, van Loo IHM, Heuts RJM, Hoebe CJPA, Cannon CA et al. Using an innovative method for self-collection of capillary blood for HIV and syphilis testing among men who have sex with men who use PrEP in the Netherlands; Limburg4zero. Sex Transm Dis. 2024.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Leenen J, Hoebe CJPA, Ackens RP, Posthouwer D, van Loo IHM, Wolffs PFG et al. Pilot implementation of a home-care programme with chlamydia, gonorrhoea, hepatitis B, and syphilis self-sampling in HIV-positive men who have sex with men. BMC Infect Dis. 2020;20.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Baraitser P, Black A, Amos-Gibbs S, Holdsworth G, Ardines E, Courtenay M et al. User preference for HIV self-testing or self-sampling within a free online sexual health service: a service evaluation. Int J STD AIDS. 2019;30.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR34" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sumray</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lloyd</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Estcourt</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Burns</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibbs</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Access to, usage and clinical outcomes of, online postal sexually transmitted infection services: a scoping review</article-title><source>Sex Transm Infect</source><year>2022</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>528</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/sextrans-2021-055376</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35701146</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR34" publication-type="journal">Sumray K, Lloyd KC, Estcourt CS, Burns F, Gibbs J. Access to, usage and clinical outcomes of, online postal sexually transmitted infection services: a scoping review. Sex Transm Infect. 2022;98:528&#x02013;35.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35701146</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Norelli J, Zlotorzynska M, Sanchez T, Sullivan PS. Scaling up carekit: lessons learned from expansion of a centralized home HIV and sexually transmitted infection testing program. Sex Transm Dis. 2021;48.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR36" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mbopi-K&#x000e9;ou</surname><given-names>F-X</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalla</surname><given-names>GCM</given-names></name><name><surname>Anakeu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pondi</surname><given-names>J-E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Launching HIV self-testing in a multicultural setting in Cameroon</article-title><source>Lancet Infect Dis</source><year>2020</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>286</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(20)30050-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32112761</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR36" publication-type="journal">Mbopi-K&#x000e9;ou F-X, Kalla GCM, Anakeu P, Pondi J-E. Launching HIV self-testing in a multicultural setting in Cameroon. Lancet Infect Dis. 2020;20:286&#x02013;7.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32112761</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Stephenson R, Freeland R, Sullivan SP, Riley E, Johnson BA, Mitchell J et al. Home-based HIV testing and counseling for male couples (project nexus): A protocol for a randomized controlled trial. JMIR Res Protoc. 2017;6.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">McGuire M, de Waal A, Karellis A, Janssen R, Engel N, Sampath R et al. HIV self-testing with digital supports as the new paradigm: A systematic review of global evidence (2010&#x02013;2021). EClinicalMedicine. 2021;39.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR39" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Habel</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Aral</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Remote health: optimizing the delivery of sexual health care</article-title><source>Sex Transm Dis</source><year>2022</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>S1</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/OLQ.0000000000001618</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35312660</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR39" publication-type="journal">Habel MA, Sullivan P, Hall C, Aral S. Remote health: optimizing the delivery of sexual health care. Sex Transm Dis. 2022;49:S1&#x02013;6.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35312660</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Shrestha RK, Chavez PR, Noble M, Sansom SL, Sullivan PS, Mermin JH et al. Estimating the costs and cost-effectiveness of HIV self-testing among men who have sex with men, United States. Journal of the Internation AIDS Society [Internet]. 2020;23. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/">http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/</ext-link>10.1002/jia2.25445/full</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR41" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blake</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Spielberg</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Lensing</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolff</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Venkatasubramanian</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Could home sexually transmitted infection specimen collection with e-prescription be a cost-effective strategy for clinical trials and clinical care?</article-title><source>Sex Transm Dis</source><year>2015</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/OLQ.0000000000000221</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25504295</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR41" publication-type="journal">Blake DR, Spielberg F, Levy V, Lensing S, Wolff PA, Venkatasubramanian L, et al. Could home sexually transmitted infection specimen collection with e-prescription be a cost-effective strategy for clinical trials and clinical care? Sex Transm Dis. 2015;42:13&#x02013;9.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25504295</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lafferty L, Rautenbach C, McNulty A, Ryder N, Slattery C, Houghton R et al. Client and staff perceptions of acceptability of mycheck: a direct-to-pathology telehealth and e-testing service for comprehensive bloodborne virus and sexually transmissible infection screening. Sex Health. 2024;21.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hamilton DT, Katz DA, Luo W, Stekler JD, Rosenberg ES, Sullivan PS et al. Effective strategies to promote HIV self-testing for men who have sex with men: evidence from a mathematical model. Epidemics. 2021;100518.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR44" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bolarinwa</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Adebisi</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ajayi</surname><given-names>KV</given-names></name><name><surname>Boutahar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sexual and reproductive health rights in the era of artificial intelligence</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2024</year><volume>404</volume><fpage>120</fpage><lpage>1</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(24)00696-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39002985</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR44" publication-type="journal">Bolarinwa O, Adebisi YA, Ajayi KV, Boutahar R. Sexual and reproductive health rights in the era of artificial intelligence. Lancet. 2024;404:120&#x02013;1.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39002985</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Feldstein AC, Russell Glasgow MEA, Practical R, Implementation, and Sustainability Model (PRISM) for Integrating Research Findings into Practice Research Methods. The Joint Commission Journal on QualityPatient Safety [Internet]. 2008;34:228&#x02013;43. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ihi.org/IHI/Topics/Improvement/ImprovementMethods/HowToImprove/">http://www.ihi.org/IHI/Topics/Improvement/ImprovementMethods/HowToImprove/</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR46" publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group><source>Diffusion of innovations</source><year>1995</year><edition>4</edition><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Free</publisher-name></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR46" publication-type="book">Rogers EM. Diffusion of innovations. 4th ed. New York: Free; 1995.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Glasgow RE, Harden SM, Gaglio B, Rabin B, Smith ML, Porter GC et al. RE-AIM planning and evaluation framework: adapting to new science and practice with a 20-year review. Front Public Health. 2019;7.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Moullin JC, Dickson KS, Stadnick NA, Albers B, Nilsen P, Broder-Fingert S et al. Ten recommendations for using implementation frameworks in research and practice. Implement Sci Commun. 2020;1.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Cannon CA, Ramchandani MS, Golden MR. Feasibility of a novel self-collection method for blood samples and its acceptability for future home-based PrEP monitoring. BMC Infect Dis. 2022;22.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Cannon C, Holzhauer K, Golden M. Implementation and Evaluation of a Home-Based Pre-Exposure Prophylaxis Monitoring Option: Protocol for a Randomized Controlled Trial. JMIR Res Protoc [Internet]. 2024;13:e56587. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.researchprotocols.org/2024/1/e56587">https://www.researchprotocols.org/2024/1/e56587</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zarbl J, Eimer E, Gigg C, Bendzuck G, Korinth M, Elling-Audersch C et al. Remote self-collection of capillary blood using upper arm devices for autoantibody analysis in patients with immune-mediated inflammatory rheumatic diseases. RMD Open. 2022;8.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Noble LD, Dixon C, Moran A, Trottet C, Majam M, Ismail S et al. Painless capillary blood collection: A rapid evaluation of the onflow device. Diagnostics. 2023;13.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Cheah MH, Gan YN, Altice FL, Wickersham JA, Shrestha R, Salleh NAM et al. Testing the feasibility and acceptability of using an artificial intelligence chatbot to promote HIV testing and Pre-Exposure prophylaxis in Malaysia: mixed methods study. JMIR Hum Factors. 2024;11.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Vermey K, Daas C, Den, Zweers W, Bergen J, Van, Bos H. P046 ensuring quality-assured and personalized online self-testing within a market-driven context. BMJ; 2019. pp. A991&#x02013;99.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR55" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Heerden</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bosman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Swendeman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Comulada</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chatbots for HIV prevention and care: a narrative review</article-title><source>Curr HIV/AIDS Rep</source><year>2023</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>481</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11904-023-00681-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38010467</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR55" publication-type="journal">van Heerden A, Bosman S, Swendeman D, Comulada WS. Chatbots for HIV prevention and care: a narrative review. Curr HIV/AIDS Rep. 2023;20:481&#x02013;6.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38010467</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Biello KB, Horvitz C, Mullin S, Mayer KH, Scott H, Coleman K et al. HIV self-testing and STI self-collection via mobile apps: experiences from two pilot randomized controlled trials of young men who have sex with men. Mhealth [Internet]. 2021;7:26&#x02013;26. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://mhealth.amegroups.com/article/view/50249/html">https://mhealth.amegroups.com/article/view/50249/html</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zhao T, Cao Z, Jiang Z, Bulloch G, Qiu Y, Liu L et al. Providing HIV testing in men who have sex with men through a gay social networking app in China: A qualitative interview study with multisectoral service providers. Front Public Health. 2022.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR58" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hightow-Weidman</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name><surname>Muessig</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bauermeister</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>LeGrand</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Youth, technology, and HIV: recent advances and future directions</article-title><source>Curr HIV/AIDS Rep</source><year>2015</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>500</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11904-015-0280-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26385582</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR58" publication-type="journal">Hightow-Weidman LB, Muessig KE, Bauermeister J, Zhang C, LeGrand S. Youth, technology, and HIV: recent advances and future directions. Curr HIV/AIDS Rep. 2015;12:500&#x02013;15.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26385582</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wulandari LPL, Kaldor J, Guy R. Uptake and acceptability of assisted and unassisted HIV self-testing among men who purchase sex in brothels in Indonesia: A pilot intervention study. BMC Public Health. 2020;20.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR60" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adan</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Psaros</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Chamberlin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Zionts</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Iyer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Platt</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Swiping right on PrEP: a qualitative study of MSM preferences for PrEP public health messaging on dating apps</article-title><source>AIDS Care</source><year>2024</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>1135</fpage><lpage>47</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09540121.2024.2343761</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38648528</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR60" publication-type="journal">Adan MA, Psaros C, Chamberlin G, Zionts D, Iyer S, Platt L, et al. Swiping right on PrEP: a qualitative study of MSM preferences for PrEP public health messaging on dating apps. AIDS Care. 2024;36:1135&#x02013;47.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38648528</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Chambers LC, Malyuta Y, Goedel WC, Chan PA, Sutten Coats C, Allen K et al. Identifying Effective Components of a Social Marketing Campaign to Improve Engagement With Express Sexual Health Services Among Gay, Bisexual, and Other Men Who Have Sex With Men: Case Study. JMIR Public Health Surveill [Internet]. 2024;10:e50944&#x02013;e50944. Available from: https://publichealth.jmir.org/2024/1/e50944.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">World Health Organization. The role of artificial intelligence in sexual and reproductive health and rights [Internet]. 2024 Mar. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789240090705">https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789240090705</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR63" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marcus</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Sewell</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name><surname>Balzer</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name><surname>Krakower</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Artificial intelligence and machine learning for HIV prevention: emerging approaches to ending the epidemic</article-title><source>Curr HIV/AIDS Rep</source><year>2020</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11904-020-00490-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32347446</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR63" publication-type="journal">Marcus JL, Sewell WC, Balzer LB, Krakower DS. Artificial intelligence and machine learning for HIV prevention: emerging approaches to ending the epidemic. Curr HIV/AIDS Rep. 2020;17:171&#x02013;9.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32347446</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Latt PM, Soe NN, Xu X, Ong JJ, Chow EPF, Fairley CK et al. Identifying individuals at high risk for HIV and sexually transmitted infections with an artificial Intelligence-Based risk assessment tool. Open Forum Infect Dis. 2024;11.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Soe NN, Yu Z, Latt PM, Lee D, Ong JJ, Ge Z et al. Evaluation of artificial intelligence-powered screening for sexually transmitted infections-related skin lesions using clinical images and metadata. BMC Med. 2024;22.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">O&#x02019;Cathain A, Croot L, Sworn K, Duncan E, Rousseau N, Turner K et al. Taxonomy of approaches to developing interventions to improve health: A systematic methods overview. Pilot Feasibility Stud. 2019;5.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>