<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PeerJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PeerJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">peerj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PeerJ</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2167-8359</issn><publisher><publisher-name>PeerJ Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Diego, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40191755</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11972562</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">19076</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19076</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Orthopedics</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Sports Medicine</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A retrospective study on safety and clinical outcomes of unilateral biportal endoscopic technique for spinal degenerative diseases</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="author-1" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Haitao</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Qi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Kehan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Zihuan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-5" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Dongjie</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-6" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Shaohui</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-7" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Jilu</given-names></name><email>liujilu0717@163.com</email><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-8" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Haifeng</given-names></name><email>weihfspine@126.com</email><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><aff id="aff-1"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Spinal Tumor, Changzheng Hospital, Naval Medical University CN</institution>, <city>Shanghai</city>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff-2"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Spinal Surgery, Naval Hospital of Eastern Theater</institution>, <city>Zhoushan</city>, <country>China</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Jimenez-Cebrian</surname><given-names>Ana Maria</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>3</day><month>4</month><year iso-8601-date="2025">2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>13</volume><elocation-id>e19076</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="2024-09-23"><day>23</day><month>9</month><year iso-8601-date="2024">2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="2025-02-10"><day>10</day><month>2</month><year iso-8601-date="2025">2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9;2025 Sun et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Sun et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, reproduction and adaptation in any medium and for any purpose provided that it is properly attributed. For attribution, the original author(s), title, publication source (PeerJ) and either DOI or URL of the article must be cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/19076"/><abstract><sec><title>Background and Objective</title><p>Unilateral biportal endoscopy (UBE) has been developing rapidly in coincidence with the popularization of minimally invasive spine surgery (MISS). However, the clinical outcome and invasiveness of UBE-assisted spinal surgery (UBESS) are undefined. The aim of the present study was to summarize the clinical outcome and surgical invasiveness of UBE for the treatment of various spinal degenerative diseases in a single center to validate the safety and application value of UBESS.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>Included in this study were 105 patients who received UBESS from November 2021 to June 2022 in our center. All patients were followed up postoperatively for at least 12 months. All basic information was recorded to depict the demographic and surgical variables. Clinical outcomes were assessed in terms of the operation time, complications, days of hospital stay, total blood loss, intraoperative blood loss, postoperative drainage volume, hidden blood loss, biochemical changes associated with surgical injury, comparison of the visual analogue scale (VAS) for back and leg pain, Japanese Orthopedic Association (JOA) scores for cervical diseases at preoperative and postoperative stage, as well as Oswetry Disability Index (ODI), and modified MacNab scores one year after treatment.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Of the 105 included patients, 68 patients were with single-level lumbar degenerative diseases, 22 with two-level diseases, two with three-level diseases, 10 with single-level isthmic spondylolisthesis, and three with single-level cervical spondylotic radiculopathy. UBE was performed by using five surgical approaches. The operation time, days of hospital stay, blood loss, postoperative immobilization time and prognosis were all estimated in consideration of the surgical approaches and the number of operated segments. The mean operation time ranged from 80 min to 214 min for single-level spinal diseases, and 112 min to 330 min for two-level ones. Total blood loss was higher in multilevel spinal surgery and single-level UBE-assisted lumbar interbody fusion+discectomy (ULIFD). The postoperative immobilization duration was between 0.5 and 2 days for single level spinal diseases, 1 and 3 days for 2-level diseases, fewer than 2 days for three-level diseases, and 1.5&#x02013;12 days for isthmic spondylolisthesis (IS). The VAS and ODI for lumbar diseases decreased significantly and the JOA scores for cervical diseases improved after operation. The satisfaction rate was 89.70%, 85.71%, 90.00%, 66.67%, and 90.00% for the five surgical approaches respectively.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>UBESS has proved to be a safe, reliable and minimally invasive option for spinal degenerative diseases, with significant benefits of pain control, rapid functional recovery, short hospitalization, and early rehabilitation. However, postoperative hidden blood loss should be put under the careful management when performing UBESS.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>Unilateral biportal endoscopy</kwd><kwd>Minimally invasive spine surgery</kwd><kwd>Hidden blood loss</kwd><kwd>Complications</kwd><kwd>Hospital stay</kwd><kwd>Clinical outcomes</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="fund-1"><funding-source>National Natural Science Foundation of China (NSFC)</funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>The authors received no funding for this work. The APC was funded by a National Natural Science Foundation of China (NSFC) project titled &#x0201c;UGP-2 Integrin Glycosylation Signaling Axis-Mediated Mechanism of Malignant Behavior in Chondrosarcoma&#x0201d; led by Professor Haifeng Wei. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Spinal degenerative disorders (SDD), including intervertebral disc herniation/protrusion, spinal canal stenosis, spondylolisthesis and spondylosis, are one of the leading causes of chronic pain and radiculopathy, and a frequent indication for spinal surgery. Given the aging population, a more sedentary lifestyle, overall improvement of public health, and the evolution from contagious diseases to chronic diseases, the incidence of SDD is on the increase as expected (<xref rid="ref-19" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2019</xref>). The ascending trend renders more SDD patients as surgical candidates and more spinal surgeries in the past decades (<xref rid="ref-29" ref-type="bibr">Tetreault et al., 2015</xref>). Fenestration, laminectomy and lumbar fusion are common conventional open surgical options for SDD. However, they are disadvantaged by the high risk of infection, great damage to paravertebral soft tissues and the possibility of spinal instability. With the rapid evolvement of endoscopic platforms and techniques, minimally invasive surgery has emerged as an alternative surgical approach for SDD. Although minimally invasive spinal surgery reduces the surgical exposure and lowers the damage, the narrow working space limits the visualization and surgical performance.</p><p>Recently, unilateral biportal endoscopic spinal surgery (UBESS) has attracted increasing attention, for the instrumental channel and visual channel are independent of each other. Thus, unilateral biportal endoscopy (UBE) has the advantages of unrestricted instrument use and a wider visual field (<xref rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr">Heo et al., 2017</xref>). Compared with percutaneous uniportal endoscopy, the improvement of operational flexibility enables surgeons to perform more precise and safer operations under indirect visualization. Some previous clinical studies have reported the application of UBE in single-level lumbar disc herniation, lumbar spondylolisthesis and cervical spondylopathy, but there is limited knowledge about its surgical invasiveness (<xref rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr">Jiang et al., 2022</xref>; <xref rid="ref-25" ref-type="bibr">Park et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr">Kang et al., 2021</xref>). Generally, total blood loss (TBL) is regarded as an indicator for surgical invasiveness. But it is admitted that overt blood loss, including intraoperative blood loss (IBL) and drainage volume, is inadequate to estimate TBL (<xref rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr">Lin et al., 2022</xref>). Residual blood in the dead space and extravasation, which are referred to as hidden blood loss (HBL), are reported to significantly increase TBL and inversely decrease postoperative hemoglobin (Hb) (<xref rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr">Kang et al., 2021</xref>). However, HBL is often overlooked in clinical practice, and continuous saline irrigation makes the estimation of blood loss difficult. Therefore, serological markers, creatine kinase (CK) and C-reactive protein (CRP) are introduced as objective indicators to assess surgical invasiveness simultaneously.</p><p>To the best of our knowledge, few studies have comprehensively described the clinical efficacy and surgical invasiveness of UBESS for single-level SDD, and there remains one significant gap in multilevel SDD. In the present study, we performed a detailed analysis with respect to the comparison of perioperative parameters and prognoses to evaluate the clinical outcomes of this technique in a large cohort of patients who were subjected to follow-up observations.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Patient population and study design</title><p>Patients with clinically and radiographically confirmed SDD in our center from November 2021 to April 2022 were retrospectively reviewed. Pain intensity and functional disability were assessed to evaluate the pathological degree. Preoperative MRI and CT data were obtained for all candidates to confirm the surgical indications and select surgical strategies. The inclusion criteria were preoperative back/leg pain intensity &#x02265;5 on Visual Analogue Score (VAS), intervertebral disc herniation/protrusion, spinal canal stenosis, spondylolisthesis and spondylosis undergoing UBESS, request of minimally invasive therapy, and follow-up with sufficient clinical data. Patients were excluded from the studies for the following reasons: lost to follow-up, contraindications, refusal of surgery, incomplete clinical data, and conservative treatment. Finally, a total of 105 patients were included in this retrospective study.</p><p>This research was approved by the Naval Hospital of Eastern Theater ethics committee (number: DHL202105), and informed consent was obtained from all participating patients or their delegated guardians. We adopted the method of having participating patients or their delegated guardians fill out informed consent forms and collected all the consent forms.</p></sec><sec><title>Surgical technique</title><p>After general anesthesia, the patient was placed in a prone position on the radiolucent table to ensure that the target pathological region was perpendicular to the ground under C-arm fluoroscopy. The initial target anatomical site was the junction of the spinal process and lamina, and the inferior margin of the upper lamina was then confirmed under fluoroscopy and marked with a horizontal line. Two skin incisions were made roughly on the medial margin of the upper and lower pedicles, 1&#x02212;1.5 cm cranial or caudal to the marked line. The lower incision was for the working portal, and the upper one was for the endoscopic portal. The core dilators were inserted from the working and endoscopic portal through interfascicular space to the junction of the spinal process and lamina. Serial dilators and periosteal strippers were used to expand the corridor and space. Once the triangulation for observation and instrument channel was made, the endoscope combined with the irrigation system and radiofrequency was placed within the established corridor and space. The soft tissue on the lamina and facet was peeled off to expose the inferior margin of the upper lamina and articular process. Sustained hemostasis by radiofrequency was conducted during operation to maintain a clear view. Next, partial laminectomy was performed to remove part of the inferior lamina of the upper lamina until the upper free margin of the ligamentum favum was exposed. The lower margin of the ligamentum favum was detached from the lower lamina with pituitary forceps. Part of the articular process was resected with an electrical drill, Kerrison punch and osteotome, which is necessary for nerve protection (<xref rid="fig-1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig-1"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19076/fig-1</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>An intraoperative view of unilateral biportal endoscopy spinal surgery (UBESS).</title><p>(A) The specific position for UBESS. (B). Skin marks for the left approach in lumbar surgery. The instrumental portal (red box) is cranial to the horizontal line, and endoscopic portal (green box) is caudal to the line. (C) The instrumental and endoscopic portals are confirmed over the junction of the spinal process and lamina. (D). Exposure of the inferior margin of the lamina and articular process. (E) Partial laminectomy was performed to dissociate the initial origin of the ligamentum favum. The dural sac and nerve root were confirmed after sufficient flavectomy. (F) Partial articular process resection. It is necessary to protect the nerve and decompress the transverse nerve root.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-13-19076-g001" position="float"/></fig><p>For patients with lateral recess stenosis, the lateral recess and nerve root canal were decompressed by ipsilateral flavectomy. For patients with bilateral stenosis, it is necessary to remove the lamina sufficiently to the contralateral side, and the ligamentum flavum to expose the contralateral facet joint and lateral recess for contralateral decompression (<xref rid="fig-2" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig-2"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19076/fig-2</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Additional midline laminectomy was performed over the ligamentum favum midline.</title><p>It is necessary to remove the lamina sufficiently to the contralateral foramen and the ligamentum favum for the sake of enlarging the canal volume, thus achieving bilateral decompression.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-13-19076-g002" position="float"/></fig><p>For patients with lumbar/cervical disc herniation, the ruptured disc was removed routinely, the soft disc particle was removed with pituitary forceps, and the calcified disc material was removed with a Kerrison punch. Internal disc decompression was recommended to reduce the risk of recurrence and chemical inflammation. After discectomy, annuloplasty was performed with a disposable fiber loop suture device (Jinxinxing, Inc., Beijing, China) for a certain group (<xref rid="fig-3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig-3"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19076/fig-3</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Resect the ruptured disc and suture the disrupted fibrous annulus.</title><p>(A) Starting from the origin of the transverse root, dissection was proceeded between the nerve and the disc. (B) The ruptured disc was removed through the ipsilateral axillary corridor. Further internal decompression was accomplished with the use of pituitary forceps; (C) Annuloplasty, namely, disrupted fibrous annulus was sutured with a disposable fiber loop suture device.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-13-19076-g003" position="float"/></fig><p>For patients with lumbar spondylolisthesis, the intervertebral space was processed with a reamer and pituitary forceps after discectomy. Then the cartilage endplate was curetted for interbody bone grafting through an infundibular bone graft device. Autologous bone, or allografts were used to promote bony fusion. An interbody cage of appropriate size was placed under endoscopic visualization. After that, the percutaneous screws were implanted into bilateral pedicles under C-arm fluoroscopy. Finally, the pedicle screw position was confirmed and the drainage tube was indwelled before closure (<xref rid="fig-4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig-4"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19076/fig-4</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>An interbody cage was placed.</title><p>(A) The cartilage endplate was processed for interbody bone grafting through an infundibular bone graft device. An interbody cage of appropriate size was placed under endoscopic visualization. (B) Percutaneous pedicle screws were implanted after cage insertion and confirmed. Postoperative CT showing UBE-assisted lumbar interbody fusion+discectomy.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-13-19076-g004" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Data collection</title><p>The data were collected from the hospital admission records up to May 2023. The general information included gender, age, height, weight, body mass index (BMI), symptom duration, cardinal symptom, and follow-up duration. Perioperative data included diagnosis, operative approaches, the number of operative segments, operative level, operation time, postoperative immobilization time, drainage tube indwelling time, postoperative hospital stay, complications, postoperative blood loss (PBL), TBL, IBL, HBL, hematocrit (Hct), Hb, CK and CRP.</p><p>Laboratory testing was regularly performed. Preoperative Hb, Hct, CK and CRP were recorded at admission. Postoperative Hb, Hct, CK and CRP were detected on the 2nd day after operation. No blood transfusion was required during or after operation, and thus TBL was calculated based on the perioperative change of Hct (<xref rid="ref-23" ref-type="bibr">Nash et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr">Gross, 1983</xref>). <disp-formula id="NONUM-d2e321">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-13-19076-e001.jpg" position="float"/><tex-math id="tex-NONUM-d2e321">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
\begin{eqnarray*}\mathrm{TBL}(\mathrm{ml})=\text{Patient blood volume}(\mathrm{PBV},\mathrm{ml})\times \frac{(\text{Hctpre}-\text{Hctpost})}{(\text{Hctpre}+\text{Hctpost})} \times 2. \end{eqnarray*}\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="mml-NONUM-d2e321" overflow="scroll"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">TBL</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="" open="(" close=")"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">ml</mml:mi></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Patient blood volume</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="" open="(" close=")"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">PBV</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">ml</mml:mi></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="" open="(" close=")"><mml:mtext>Hctpre</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Hctpost</mml:mtext></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="" open="(" close=")"><mml:mtext>Hctpre</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Hctpost</mml:mtext></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mstyle></mml:math></alternatives>
</disp-formula>In this calculation, Hct<sub>pre</sub> and Hct<sub>post</sub> are short for pre- and postoperative Hct, respectively.</p><p><inline-formula><alternatives><inline-graphic xlink:href="peerj-13-19076-i001.jpg"/><tex-math id="tex-ieqn-5">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
$\mathrm{PBV} \left( \mathrm{ml} \right) =(\mathrm{k}1\times \text{height}{ \left( \mathrm{m} \right) }^{3}+\mathrm{k}2\times \text{weight}(\mathrm{Kg})+\mathrm{k}3)\times 1000$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="mml-ieqn-5" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">PBV</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="" open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">ml</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="" open="(" close=")"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">k</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>height</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="" open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">k</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>weight</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="" open="(" close=")"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Kg</mml:mi></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">k</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1000</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>. (k1= 0.3561, k2= 0.03308, and k3= 0.1833, for women; k1= 0.3669, k2= 0.03219, and k3= 0.6041, for men) (<xref rid="ref-22" ref-type="bibr">Nadler, Hidalgo &#x00026; Bloch, 1962</xref>).</p><p>IBL was determined by the sum of volume differences between suction fluid and irrigation liquid, and the amount of blood absorbed by gauze and towels using visual estimation (<xref rid="ref-2" ref-type="bibr">Ali Algadiem et al., 2016</xref>). PBL comprised the drainage flow and the blood loss visually estimated by soaked gauze. The drainage tube was removed when the drainage flow was less than 50 ml. HBL was calculated by Sehat&#x02019;s method (<xref rid="ref-28" ref-type="bibr">Sehat, Evans &#x00026; Newman, 2004</xref>). Therefore, HBL=TBL-IBL-PBL.</p><p>Clinical outcomes, such as pain control, functional modification and patient satisfaction, were evaluated by VAS, Oswestry Disability Index (ODI), Japanese Orthopedic Association scores (JOA) and modified MacNab Score, respectively. Back and leg VAS (0&#x02013;10), and ODI (0&#x02013;100%) for lumbar disorders were investigated at admission, 1 month, 6 months and 1 year after operation. The improvement rate (%) of JOA (0&#x02013;17) for cervical diseases was calculated at the final follow-up [improvement rate (%) = (postoperative score &#x02013;preoperative score)/(17- preoperative score)]. Plain radiography and CT were conducted 1 year after ULIFD. Interbody fusion was assessed <italic toggle="yes">via</italic> radiographical imaging at the final follow-up. Grade I and Grade II were identified as spinal fusion according to the Bridwell grading system (<xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr">Bridwell et al., 1995</xref>). Patient satisfaction was rated according to the modified MacNab score at the final follow-up, with excellent and good defined as clinically satisfactory.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Basic demographics and perioperative information</title><p>Demographic information of the 105 patients who underwent UBESS in our center is shown in <xref rid="table-1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. They included 64 males (60.95%) and 41 females ranging in age from 20 to 79 years, with a mean of 50.57 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;17.04 (median 51) years. 17.1% of the patients were younger than 30 years, and 12.4% of the patients were older than 70 years. The height and weight of the patients were collected routinely as basic admission information. The mean height was 1.69 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.08&#x000a0;m, and the mean weight was 68.55 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;9.78 kg. Forty-four patients (41.9%) with the complaints of pain and weakness were admitted as inpatients; 35 patients (33.33%) complained of pain and paresthesia and 26 patients (24.76%) with pain were outpatients of our hospital. The mean symptom duration was 4.03 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;5.66 years. All the patients with progressive symptoms sought further treatment owing to the failure of conservative treatment.</p><p>The surgical information was obtained from the medical records. Of the 105 included patients, 77 (73.33%) were affected by lumbar disc herniation (LDH), 12 (11.43%) with spinal stenosis (SS), 10 (9.53%) with lumbar isthmic spondylolisthesis (LIS), three (2.86%) with cervical spondylotic radiculopathy (CSR), two (1.90%) with lumbar spinal stenosis (LSS), and one (0.95%) with recurrent LDH (RLDH) (<xref rid="table-2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). In consideration of the operative site and disease type, LDH, LDH with SS, LSS and RLDH were considered as the lumbar degenerative disorder (LDD) group. CSR and LIS were classified as an independent group. There were 68 patients with single-level LDD, 22 with two-level LDD, two with three-level LDD, 10 with single-level LIS, and three with single-level CSR. Five operative approaches were employed, including UBE-assisted lumbar discectomy+laminectomy+syndesmectomy (UDLS-L), UBE-assisted lumbar discectomy+laminectomy+syndesmectomy+annuloplasty (ULSA), UBE-assisted laminectomy+syndesmectomy (ULS), UBE-assisted cervical discectomy+laminectomy+syndesmectomy (UDLS-C), and UBE-assisted lumbar interbody fusion+discectomy (ULIFD), of which three (UDLS-L, ULSA and ULS) were applied for LDD, and two (UDLS-C and ULIFD) were used for CSR and LIS.</p><p>Compared with single-level LDD, the mean operation time (mOT) was shorter for multilevel LDD with UDLS-L or ULS, and longer for single-level LDD with ULSA than UDLS-L or ULS. All UBESSs were performed by an experienced spinal surgeon.</p><p>Regarding complications, pleural effusion occurred in one patient, small dural tear in one patient, and lateral femoral cutaneous nerve injury in one patient in LDD group, the complication rate being 3/92. All the patients with complications in this group received non-surgical treatment for the symptoms, and close follow-up was warranted. In the LIS group, cerebrospinal fluid leakage, wound infection, nerve root compression and pedicle penetration by screws were found in three patients, the complication rate being 3/10. Potent antibiotic, 3rd generation cephalosporin, was given for incision infection after bacterial culture and antimicrobial susceptibility tests. Revision surgery by UBE was performed to adjust pedicle screws and decompression. The complications occurred in the early period when UBESS was firstly carried out. All patients were discharged from our center after recovery. The detailed information is listed in <xref rid="table-3" ref-type="table">Tables 3</xref>, <xref rid="table-4" ref-type="table">4</xref> and <xref rid="table-5" ref-type="table">5</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="table-1"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19076/table-1</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Demographics of patients receiving UBESS.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-13-19076-g005" position="float"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Demographics</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">UBESS</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender, Male/Female (Male %)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64/41 (60.95%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (ys)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.57 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;17.04</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weight (kg)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.55 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;9.78</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Height (m)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.69 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.08</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.94 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.23</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cardinal symptom</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pain only</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (24.76%)</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pain and paresthesia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (33.33%)</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pain and weakness</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44 (41.9%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Symptom duration (years)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.03 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;5.66</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="table-2"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19076/table-2</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Perioperative diagnosis of patients receiving UBESS.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-13-19076-g006" position="float"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Perioperative diagnosis</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">UBESS</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LDH</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77 (73.33%)</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LDH+SS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (11.43%)</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LIS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (9.53%)</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CSR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (2.86%)</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LSS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (1.90%)</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RLDH</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.95%)</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="table-3"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19076/table-3</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Surgical information of patients receiving UBESS.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-13-19076-g007" position="float"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">UBESS</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">LDD (LDH/LDH+SS/LSS/RLDH)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Operative approach</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UDLS-L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UDLSA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ULS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Operative segment</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">single-level LDD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">two-level LDD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">three-level LDD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Operative level</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L1/2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L2/3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L3/4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L4/5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L5/S1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L1/2, L5/S1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L2/3, L4/5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L3/4, L4/5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L4/5, L5/S1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L3/4, L4/5, L5/S1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Operation time (mins)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UDLS-L (single/double/triple segments)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">110.88 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;13.75/150.31 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;18.50/254.50</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UDLSA (single segment)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">129.40 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;7.35</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ULS (single/double/triple segments)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.71 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;4.64/130.83 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;8.34/205.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Postoperative immobilization time(days)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UDLS-L (single/double/triple segments)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.36 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.76/1.44 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.31/2.00</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UDLSA (single segment)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.35 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.34</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ULS (single/double/triple segments)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.36 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.48/1.42 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.38/1.50</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drainage tube indwelling duration(days)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UDLS-L (single/double/triple segments)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.30/0.84 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.30/1.00</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UDLSA (single segment)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.26</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ULS (single/double/triple segments)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.26/0.83 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.41/1.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Postoperative hospital stay (days)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UDLS-L (single/double/triple segments)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.49 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.19/3.84 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.77/5.00</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UDLSA (single segment)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.45 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.93</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ULS (single/double/triple segments)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.43 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.53/3.83 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.75/5.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Complications</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pleural effusion</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cerebrospinal fluid leakage</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lateral femoral cutaneous nerve injury</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="table-4"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19076/table-4</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Surgical information of patients receiving UBESS.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-13-19076-g008" position="float"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Surgical information</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">UBESS</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">LIS</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Operative approach</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ULIFD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Operative segment</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Operative level</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L4/5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L5/S1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Operation time (mins)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">193.80 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;14.13</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Postoperative immobilization time (days)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.80 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.78</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drainage tube indwelling duration (days)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.32</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Postoperative hospital stay (days)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.30 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.05</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Complications</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1. Cerebrospinal fluid leakage</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2. Pedicle penetration by screws</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nerve root compression</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wound infection</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Postoperative hospital stay (days)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.42 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.38</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="table-5"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19076/table-5</object-id><label>Table 5</label><caption><title>Surgical information of patients receiving UBESS.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-13-19076-g009" position="float"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Surgical information</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">UBESS</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">CSR</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Operative approach</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UDLS-C</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Operative segment</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Operative level</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C4/5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C5/6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Operation time (mins)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">136.33 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;16.62</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Postoperative immobilization time (days)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.33 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.29</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drainage tube indwelling duration (days)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.29</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Postoperative hospital stay (days)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.42 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.38</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Comparisons of perioperative serology and blood loss</title><p>Overall, serological changes and blood loss in multilevel LDD were significantly higher than those in single-level LDD, and the serological parameters and blood loss were increased in the treatment of LIS with ULIFD as compared with UDLS-L, ULS, UDLSA and UDLS-C (<xref rid="table-6" ref-type="table">Tables 6</xref> and <xref rid="table-7" ref-type="table">7</xref>). There were approximate mean CK and CRP level changes in CSR and single-level LDD except ULS. The perioperative Hb and Hct differences were slightly obvious in LDD with UDLSA, but similar change was found between LDD with UDLS-L and with ULS. The mean TBL in ULS was 273.98 &#x000b1;&#x000a0; 42.59 ml, suggesting that it may be least invasive surgical approach for single-level LDD. The discrepancy was also observed in multilevel LDD. HBL was the major component to be reckoned with, which accounted for more than 70% of TBL in each group. The results of perioperative serology and blood loss are listed in <xref rid="table-6" ref-type="table">Tables 6</xref> and <xref rid="table-7" ref-type="table">7</xref>, respectively.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="table-6"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19076/table-6</object-id><label>Table 6</label><caption><title>Changes of perioperative laboratory indices.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-13-19076-g010" position="float"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</th><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Operative segment</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single segment</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Double segment</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Triple segment</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hct loss (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UDLS-L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.31 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.99 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.00</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ULS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.71 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.90 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.20</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UDLSA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.12 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UDLS-C</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.10 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ULIFD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.81 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hb loss (g/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UDLS-L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.83 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;8.83</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.25 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;7.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.00</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ULS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.86 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;5.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.50 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;6.72</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.00</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UDLSA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.86 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UDLS-C</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.33 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ULIFD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.90 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;5.24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CK change (1d, U/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UDLS-L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">161.07 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;75.69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">239.38 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;46.82</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.00/327.00</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ULS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">127.86 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;14.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">205.33 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;16.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.00/310.00</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UDLSA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">160.80 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;69.36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UDLS-C</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">166.67 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;27.54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ULIFD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">392.50 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;54.43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRP changes (mg/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UDLS-L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.19 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;4.70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.26 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;4.37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00/25.30</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ULS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.67 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.87 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.86/25.28</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UDLSA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.06 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UDLS-C</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.67 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;4.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ULIFD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.19 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;12.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="table-7" orientation="landscape"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19076/table-7</object-id><label>Table 7</label><caption><title>Perioperative blood loss.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-13-19076-g011" position="float"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Estimated total blood loss (ml)</th><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Intraoperative blood loss (ml)</th><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Postoperative blood loss (ml)</th><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Hidden blood loss (ml)</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single seg</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Double seg</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Triple seg</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single seg</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Double seg</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Triple seg</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single seg</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Double seg</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Triple seg</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single seg</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Double seg</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Triple seg</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">UDLS-L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">333.70 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;180.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">575.69 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;170.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">603.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.75 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;30.70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.25 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;16.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.72 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;34.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.94 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;22.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">257.23 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;163.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">448.50 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;162.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">463.11</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ULS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">273.98 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;42.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">434.28 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;33.51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">427.60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.57 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;20.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.33 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;9.83</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.57 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;8.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.67 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;12.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">221.84 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;56.43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">329.28 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;41.98</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">317.60</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">UDLSA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">359.10 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;68.67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.50 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;11.36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.50 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;10.66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">282.10 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;77.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">UDLS-C</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">255.96 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;36.54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.67 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;5.77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.00 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;5.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">197.63 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;42.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ULIFD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">672.56 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;136.90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">113.00 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;24.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.00 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;31.69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">473.56 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;108.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Clinical outcomes of UBESS</title><p>The clinical outcomes and patient satisfaction are shown in <xref rid="table-8" ref-type="table">Table 8</xref>. The mean follow-up duration of the series available was 13.14 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.90 months. Postoperative back and leg VAS, ODI and JOA were significantly improved in each disease group. Improvements in pain intensity and lumbar dysfunction one month after operation were remarkable. The improvement rate was 100%, 100% and 66.67% for the three CSR patients at the final follow-up. Evaluation of interbody fusion using the Bridwell grading system showed a fusion rate of 100%. At the last follow-up, the clinical satisfaction rate according to modified MacNab Score was 91.18% for UDLS-L, 92.85% for ULS, 90.00% for UDLSA, 66.67% for UDLS-C, and 90.00% for UDLIF.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="table-8" orientation="landscape"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19076/table-8</object-id><label>Table 8</label><caption><title>Clinical outcomes of UBESS.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-13-19076-g012" position="float"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" colspan="5" rowspan="1">UBESS (operative segment)</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">UDLS-L <break/>(Single/Double/Triple)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ULS <break/>(Single/Double/Triple)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">UDLSA <break/>(Single)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">UDLS-C <break/>(Single)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ULIFD <break/>(Single)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Preoperative ODI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.78 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;12.63/60.25 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;9.50/63.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.43 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;6.27/59.83 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.66/77.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.80 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;10.93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.40 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;6.88</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Postoperative ODI (1 month)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.29 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;10.00/29.38 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;4.01/47.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.57 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.07/ 30.17 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;4.44/57.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.70 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;8.37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.20 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;9.22</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Postoperative ODI (3 months)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.51 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;6.94/18.75 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.06/28.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.88 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.79/19.17 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.17/38.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.30 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;7.51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.40 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;10.76</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Postoperative ODI (1 year)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.43 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;4.47/10.25 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.94/12.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.71 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.98/10.83 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.47/20.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.30 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.60 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.40</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Preoperative JOA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15/14/14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Postoperative JOA (1 year)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17/17/16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Improvement rate (1 year, %)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100/100/66.67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Preoperative VAS back</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.08 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.89/7.88 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.72/7.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.14 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.07/7.67 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.82/8.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.90 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.10 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.88</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Postoperative VAS back (1 month)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.98 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.05/2.56 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.73/5.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.86 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.90/2.16 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.75/5.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.90 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.60 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.17</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Postoperative VAS back (3 months)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.58/1.25 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.45/3.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.69/1.33 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.52/3.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.60 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.52</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Postoperative VAS back (1 year)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.43/0.62 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.50/1.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.49/0.67 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.52/2.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.48</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Preoperative VAS leg</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.04 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.94/6.94 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.77/4.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.28 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.76/6.83 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.75/5.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.90 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.99</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.30 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.77</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Postoperative VAS leg (1 month)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.96 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.87/2.31 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.95/2.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.82/2.33 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.52/3.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.47</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.90 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.88</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Postoperative VAS leg (3 months)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.52/1.31 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.60/1.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.49/1.17 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.41/1.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.42</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Postoperative VAS leg (1 year)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.50/0.94 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.57/1.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.53/0.67 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.52/1.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.53</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fusion rate (grade I, II)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grade I</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grade II</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Follow-up duration (months)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.41 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.55/13.69 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.25/13.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.14 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.90/14.33 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.63/15.60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.70 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.67 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.58</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.40 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.24</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Modified MacNab score <break/>(excellent/good/fair/poor)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49/13/6/0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10/3/1/0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/1/1/0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/1/1/0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/4/1/0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Excellent/good rate (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.00</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>In this study, we explored the clinical efficacy and surgical invasiveness of various UBE-assisted surgical approaches in a large cohort of SDD patients who were subjected to follow-up observations, and for the first time presented the clinical outcomes of UBESS in patients with multilevel SDD. In addition, we also provided the experience of revision surgery after the failure of ULIFD (<xref rid="fig-4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>).</p><p>As a form of MISS, UBESS offers excellent performance with high operative flexibility and versatility (<xref rid="ref-25" ref-type="bibr">Park et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="ref-6" ref-type="bibr">Gao et al., 2022</xref>; <xref rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2019</xref>). Consistent with these reports, we have used UBE-assisted surgical approaches of UDLS-L, ULS, UDLSA, UDLS-C and UDLIF for the treatment of LDD, CSR and LIS in our center, and our experience and practice have demonstrated several advantages of UBESS.</p><p>Firstly, it offers rapid pain control and functional recovery. It was found in this study that postoperative ODI, back and leg VAS and JOA all improved significantly at each designated time point as compared with the preoperative conditions, as evidenced by short-term ODI and VAS pain scores for single level LDD and long-term JOA for single level CSR after operation, which is consistent with some recent studies (<xref rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr">Jiang et al., 2022</xref>; <xref rid="ref-11" ref-type="bibr">Huang et al., 2023</xref>). <xref rid="ref-6" ref-type="bibr">Gao et al. (2022)</xref> reported that ODI decreased from 54.18 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;10.42 to 36.89 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;9.13, and the VAS score for back pain decreased from 5.71 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.62 to 2.2 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;30.68 in one week after ULIFD. In contrast, the clinical improvements in one month would be better in consideration of some factors such as ischemia reperfusion injury and complications. The clinical outcome of multilevel SDD with different operative approaches was comparable to that of single-level LDD. The similar improvement was also observed between single- and double- level diseases in patients using the same surgical approach. This may be attributed to multiple factors. Integrity of the spinal structure by directly reaching the target lesions, and safe and complete decompression under amplified visualization may be factors contributing to the rapid recovery. In addition, with minimal dissection and retraction of the muscles, muscle trophy and denervation could be avoided, which reduced the postoperative early pain (<xref rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr">Heemskerk et al., 2021</xref>).</p><p>Secondly, it offers minimal invasiveness with considerable HBL. CK and CRP are commonly assumed to reflect muscle damage (<xref rid="ref-30" ref-type="bibr">Thelander &#x00026; Larsson, 1992</xref>; <xref rid="ref-18" ref-type="bibr">Kumbhare, Parkinson &#x00026; Dunlop, 2008</xref>). In our study, the CK level in multilevel LDD group was higher than that in the single-level LDD group. We found a dose&#x02013;response relationship between CK and surgical invasiveness, which is consistent with the previous study (<xref rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr">Arts et al., 2007</xref>). The ULIFD approach with more incisions and pedicle screw implantation in the confined working space may cause greater damage. Additionally, the pressure exerted on the paraspinal muscle may increase the CK level (<xref rid="ref-18" ref-type="bibr">Kumbhare, Parkinson &#x00026; Dunlop, 2008</xref>). In the absence of infection, the trend of CRP change was found similar to CK, suggesting that the tissue damage was minimal, which is also evidenced by the lower level of both CK and CRP in LDD group with UL, because shorter OT of ULS and less surgical manipulation on the paraspinal structure in each group lowered the muscular exposure and trauma.</p><p>In spinal surgery, HBL is by no means negligible, because it constitutes a large percentage of TBL cases in this series (<xref rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr">Jiang et al., 2022</xref>; <xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr">Peng et al., 2023</xref>). It was also reported that HBL was the most important contributor to TBL in minimally invasive transforaminal lumbar interbody fusion (<xref rid="ref-33" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2017</xref>).</p><p>Our finding that HBL accounted for over 70% of TBL in each group is consistent with their findings. We also found HBL differences between groups with different surgical approaches for the same level SDD. The OT of different surgical approaches is classified as the risk factor of HBL, coupled with paraspinal muscle thickness (<xref rid="ref-8" ref-type="bibr">Guo et al., 2022</xref>). On the other hand, the HBL of ULIFD varies significantly, being 473.56 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;108.35 ml. The variation of HBL of ULIFD ranged from 227.86 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;221.75 ml to 472.19 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;64.44 ml in previous studies (<xref rid="ref-11" ref-type="bibr">Huang et al., 2023</xref>; <xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr">Peng et al., 2023</xref>; <xref rid="ref-8" ref-type="bibr">Guo et al., 2022</xref>). Our experience showed that HBL was much higher in the early learning period. But with the number of cases increasing, HBL will gradually decrease. <xref rid="ref-17" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al. (2020b)</xref> proposed that the caseloads for mastering this approach might be 34. However, <xref rid="ref-31" ref-type="bibr">Xu et al. (2022)</xref> advised 54 cases for proficiency. Therefore, the argument over the learning curve remains undefined.</p><p>Thirdly, it offers a low incidence of complication. Although complications occurred throughout hospitalization, it seemed acceptable clinically. All the complications occurred in the mastery phase. <xref rid="ref-5" ref-type="bibr">Choi et al. (2016)</xref> reported that the complication rate in the early learning period was about 30.8%. In the present study, the complication rate with UBESS for LDD was 3.26%, which is lower than the mean 6.7% (0%-13.8%) reported in a systemic review (<xref rid="ref-20" ref-type="bibr">Lin et al., 2019</xref>). Furthermore, symptomatic treatment is effective and associated with minimal damage to the surrounding tissues due to the high-resolution endoscopic technique. The complication rate of ULIFD for LIS was higher than that of UDLS-L, UDLSA and ULS for LDD in the early learning period, but there were only 10 LIS cases in our series. The more casse there are, the richer the content of the learning curve, which would help shorten the learning time for new learners who have never contacted this technique, which can be reflected by the steepness of the learning curve (<xref rid="ref-31" ref-type="bibr">Xu et al., 2022</xref>; <xref rid="ref-1" ref-type="bibr">Ahn et al., 2022</xref>). Besides, quality and safety of medical care should also be emphasized for the sake of achieving a stable success rate.</p><p>Dural tearing is the most common complication, as evidenced by the occurrence in previous studies (<xref rid="ref-20" ref-type="bibr">Lin et al., 2019</xref>). In our series, dural tearing occurred in two cases during the meningo-veterabral ligament dissection in the early learning period. The absorbable gelatin sponge was applied on the dural breaks intraoperatively and conservative treatment was given postoperatively. Both patients spontaneously restored to health without headache after removing the drainage tube. We consider that dural sac adhesion to the spinal canal is the main reason of causing damage by radiofrequency or instruments. Furthermore, operational proficiency in the early learning period, disc fragments and loosened dura should also be considered (<xref rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr">Pan et al., 2020</xref>). The debate on the appropriate treatment for dural tearing is still ongoing. Some studies recommend absolute bed stay and simple observation for minor tears of less than four mm, while open repair might be safe and effective for defects larger than 10 mm (<xref rid="ref-26" ref-type="bibr">Park et al., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2020a</xref>). But the repair technique under endoscopy requires further development. Thus, the detailed treatment regime for dural tearing by UBESS remains to be improved.</p><p>Several drawbacks of this study should be acknowledged. Firstly, the primary limitation of this study is the absence of a comparison group, which significantly affects the ability to draw definitive conclusions about the efficacy and safety of the operational technique being evaluated. Without a control group, it is challenging to determine whether the observed outcomes are genuinely attributable to the technique itself or if they could be influenced by other factors. Consequently, to provide a more robust assessment and validate the findings, prospective randomized controlled trials are necessary. Such studies would allow for a direct comparison, enhancing the reliability of the results and supporting evidence-based practice.</p><p>Secondly, a notable limitation of this study stems from its dependence on data sourced from a single center, which ultimately constrains the generalizability of its findings to a wider population. The lack of multi-center data support introduces potential biases that could arise from specific institutional practices, variations in patient demographics, and localized treatment methodologies. Consequently, the conclusions derived from this research may not adequately reflect the experiences or outcomes encountered in other clinical environments. To bolster the evidence and improve the reliability of the results, future investigations should focus on incorporating multi-center data with larger sample sizes. This approach would yield a more comprehensive understanding of the operational technique and its effectiveness across a diverse spectrum of patient populations.</p><p>Thirdly, the relatively brief follow-up period in this study constitutes a significant limitation, as it may impede the comprehensive assessment of postoperative patients&#x02019; functional recovery, along with the identification of complications and long-term prognosis. Insufficient follow-up duration can lead to a deficiency in critical data concerning the progression of patients over time, which is vital for accurately evaluating the effectiveness of the surgical intervention. Moreover, important late-onset complications may go undetected within such a constrained timeframe. To rectify this concern, future research should emphasize extending the follow-up duration, thereby facilitating a more in-depth exploration of the enduring outcomes and the overall impact of the treatment on patients&#x02019; quality of life.</p><p>In addition, as this case series is dependent on retrospective observations, the inherent selection and measurement bias are unavoidable. Finally, a previous study reported that the lowest hematorit value appeared 3&#x02013;5 days post-operation (<xref rid="ref-32" ref-type="bibr">Yang et al., 2017</xref>), and therefore estimation of blood loss by hematorit measured in the 2nd day after operation may be underestimated or overestimated.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Our experience and practice demonstrate that treatment of spinal degenerative diseases with UBESS can offer excellent clinical, radiographic and functional outcomes. High operational flexibility and multi-scenario application with minimal invasiveness may contribute to the consideration of being the next generation of spinal endoscopic development following conventional endoscopic spinal surgery with one portal. It appears that UBESS is a rapid and curative treatment with a low incidence of complications for SDD. Nevertheless, HBL accounts for a large percentage of TBL in UBESS group. As controllable factors, lower HBL and TBL in UBESS group are conducive to the rapid recovery and shorter hospital stay.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="supplemental-information"><title> Supplemental Information</title><supplementary-material id="supp-1" position="float" content-type="local-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19076/supp-1</object-id><label>Supplemental Information 1</label><caption><title>Raw data</title></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-13-19076-s001.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><glossary content-type="abbreviations" id="glossary-1"><title>Abbreviation</title><def-list id="dl1"><def-item><term> UBESS</term><def><p>Unilateral biportal endoscopic spinal surgery</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> BMI</term><def><p>Body mass index</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> Seg</term><def><p>Segment/segments</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> CSR</term><def><p>Cervical spondylotic radiculopathy</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> LDH</term><def><p>Lumbar disc herniation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> RLDH</term><def><p>Recurrent LDH</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> IS</term><def><p>Isthmic spondylolisthesis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> SS</term><def><p>Spinal stenosis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> UDLS-L</term><def><p>UBE-assisted lumbar discectomy+laminectomy+syndesmectomy</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> UDLS-C</term><def><p>UBE-assisted cervical discectomy+laminectomy+syndesmectomy</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> UDLSA</term><def><p>UBE-assisted lumbar discectomy+laminectomy+syndesmectomy+annulus fibrosus suture</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> ULS</term><def><p>UBE-assisted laminectomy+syndesmectomy</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> ULIFD</term><def><p>UBE-assisted lumbar interbody fusion+discectomy</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><sec sec-type="additional-information"><title>Additional Information and Declarations</title><fn-group content-type="competing-interests"><title>Competing Interests</title><fn id="conflict-1" fn-type="COI-statement"><p>The authors declare there are no competing interests.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="author-contributions"><title>Author Contributions</title><fn id="contribution-1" fn-type="con"><p><xref rid="author-1" ref-type="contrib">Haitao Sun</xref> conceived and designed the experiments, performed the experiments, analyzed the data, prepared figures and/or tables, authored or reviewed drafts of the article, and approved the final draft.</p></fn><fn id="contribution-2" fn-type="con"><p><xref rid="author-2" ref-type="contrib">Qi Zhang</xref> conceived and designed the experiments, performed the experiments, analyzed the data, prepared figures and/or tables, authored or reviewed drafts of the article, and approved the final draft.</p></fn><fn id="contribution-3" fn-type="con"><p><xref rid="author-3" ref-type="contrib">Kehan Xu</xref> conceived and designed the experiments, performed the experiments, authored or reviewed drafts of the article, and approved the final draft.</p></fn><fn id="contribution-4" fn-type="con"><p><xref rid="author-4" ref-type="contrib">Zihuan Zhou</xref> performed the experiments, authored or reviewed drafts of the article, and approved the final draft.</p></fn><fn id="contribution-5" fn-type="con"><p><xref rid="author-5" ref-type="contrib">Dongjie Jiang</xref> performed the experiments, authored or reviewed drafts of the article, and approved the final draft.</p></fn><fn id="contribution-6" fn-type="con"><p><xref rid="author-6" ref-type="contrib">Shaohui He</xref> performed the experiments, authored or reviewed drafts of the article, and approved the final draft.</p></fn><fn id="contribution-7" fn-type="con"><p><xref rid="author-7" ref-type="contrib">Jilu Liu</xref> conceived and designed the experiments, performed the experiments, authored or reviewed drafts of the article, and approved the final draft.</p></fn><fn id="contribution-8" fn-type="con"><p><xref rid="author-8" ref-type="contrib">Haifeng Wei</xref> conceived and designed the experiments, performed the experiments, authored or reviewed drafts of the article, and approved the final draft.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="other"><title>Human Ethics</title><fn id="addinfo-1"><p>The following information was supplied relating to ethical approvals (i.e., approving body and any reference numbers):</p><p>The Naval Hospital of Eastern Theater ethics committee.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="other"><title>Data Availability</title><fn id="addinfo-2"><p>The following information was supplied regarding data availability:</p><p>The raw data is available in the <xref rid="supplemental-information" ref-type="sec">Supplementary File</xref>.</p></fn></fn-group></sec><ref-list content-type="authoryear"><title>References</title><ref id="ref-1"><label>Ahn et al. (2022)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S-G</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year><article-title>Learning curve for minimally invasive transforaminal lumbar interbody fusion: a systematic review</article-title><source>European Spine Journal</source><volume>31</volume><fpage>3551</fpage><lpage>3559</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00586-022-07397-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36178548</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-2"><label>Ali Algadiem et al. (2016)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ali Algadiem</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aleisa</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alsubaie</surname><given-names>HI</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alsneini</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Blood loss estimation using gauze visual analogue</article-title><source>Trauma Monthly</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>e34131</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27626017</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-3"><label>Arts et al. (2007)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Arts</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nieborg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brand</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Peul</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Serum creatine phosphokinase as an indicator of muscle injury after various spinal and nonspinal surgical procedures</article-title><source>Journal of Neurosurgery Spine</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>282</fpage><lpage>286</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3171/spi-07/09/282</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17877261</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-4"><label>Bridwell et al. (1995)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bridwell</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lenke</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McEnery</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baldus</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Blanke</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="1995">1995</year><article-title>Anterior fresh frozen structural allografts in the thoracic and lumbar spine. Do they work if combined with posterior fusion and instrumentation in adult patients with kyphosis or anterior column defects?</article-title><source>Spine</source><volume>20</volume><fpage>1410</fpage><lpage>1418</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00007632-199506020-00014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7676341</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-5"><label>Choi et al. (2016)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S-J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y-S</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Learning curve associated with complications in biportal endoscopic spinal surgery: challenges and strategies</article-title><source>Asian Spine Journal</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>624</fpage><lpage>629</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4184/asj.2016.10.4.624</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27559440</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-6"><label>Gao et al. (2022)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hui</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>He</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year><article-title>Case series of unilateral biportal endoscopic-assisted transforaminal lumbar interbody fusion in the treatment of recurrent lumbar disc herniation</article-title><source>American Journal of Translational Research</source><volume>14</volume><fpage>2383</fpage><lpage>2392</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35559367</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-7"><label>Gross (1983)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="1983">1983</year><article-title>Estimating allowable blood loss: corrected for dilution</article-title><source>Anesthesiology</source><volume>58</volume><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>280</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00000542-198303000-00016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6829965</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-8"><label>Guo et al. (2022)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>An</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fei</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year><article-title>Risk factors for hidden blood loss in unilateral biportal endoscopic lumbar spine surgery</article-title><source>Frontiers in Surgery</source><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>966197</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fsurg.2022.966197</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36046261</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-9"><label>Heemskerk et al. (2021)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Heemskerk</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oluwadara Akinduro</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Clifton</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Qui&#x000f1;ones-Hinojosa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Abode-Iyamah</surname><given-names>KO</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year><article-title>Long-term clinical outcome of minimally invasive versus open single-level transforaminal lumbar interbody fusion for degenerative lumbar diseases: a meta-analysis</article-title><source>The Spine Journal</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>2049</fpage><lpage>2065</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.spinee.2021.07.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34273567</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-10"><label>Heo et al. (2017)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Heo</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Son</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eum</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Fully endoscopic lumbar interbody fusion using a percutaneous unilateral biportal endoscopic technique: technical note and preliminary clinical results</article-title><source>Neurosurgical Focus</source><volume>43</volume><fpage>E8</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3171/2017.5.focus17146</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-11"><label>Huang et al. (2023)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2023">2023</year><article-title>Comparison of surgical invasiveness, hidden blood loss, and clinical outcome between unilateral biportal endoscopic and minimally invasive transforaminal lumbar interbody fusion for lumbar degenerative disease: a retrospective cohort study</article-title><source>BMC Musculoskeletal Disorders</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>274</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12891-023-06374-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37038129</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-12"><label>Jiang et al. (2022)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhan</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y-L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>X-S</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year><article-title>Unilateral biportal endoscopic discectomy versus percutaneous endoscopic lumbar discectomy in the treatment of lumbar disc herniation: a retrospective study</article-title><source>Journal of Orthopaedic Surgery and Research</source><volume>17</volume><fpage>30</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13018-022-02929-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35033143</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-13"><label>Kang et al. (2021)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>You</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Heo</surname><given-names>D-H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>H-J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>H-J</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year><article-title>Minimally invasive transforaminal lumbar interbody fusion using the biportal endoscopic techniques versus microscopic tubular technique</article-title><source>The Spine Journal: Official Journal of the North American Spine Society</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>2066</fpage><lpage>2077</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.spinee.2021.06.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34171465</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-14"><label>Kim et al. (2019)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>EJJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H-J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>J-H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>M-C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>J-S</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>Biportal endoscopic spinal surgery for lumbar spinal stenosis</article-title><source>Asian Spine Journal</source><volume>13</volume><fpage>334</fpage><lpage>342</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.31616/asj.2018.0210</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30959588</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-15"><label>Kim et al. (2018)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>S-W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S-C</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Clinical comparison of unilateral biportal endoscopic technique versus open microdiscectomy for single-level lumbar discectomy: a multicenter, retrospective analysis</article-title><source>Journal of Orthopaedic Surgery and Research</source><volume>13</volume><fpage>22</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13018-018-0725-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29386033</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-16"><label>Kim et al. (2020a)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Raorane</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Heo</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>I-T</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020a</year><article-title>Incidental durotomy during endoscopic stenosis lumbar decompression: incidence, classification, and proposed management strategies</article-title><source>World Neurosurgery</source><volume>139</volume><fpage>e13</fpage><lpage>e22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.wneu.2020.01.242</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32059965</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-17"><label>Kim et al. (2020b)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>J-H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020b</year><article-title>Learning curve and clinical outcome of biportal endoscopic-assisted lumbar interbody fusion</article-title><source>BioMed Research International</source><volume>2020</volume><elocation-id>8815432</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2020/8815432</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33381586</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-18"><label>Kumbhare, Parkinson &#x00026; Dunlop (2008)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kumbhare</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Parkinson</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dunlop</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>Validity of serum creatine kinase as a measure of muscle injury produced by lumbar surgery</article-title><source>Journal of Spinal Disorders &#x00026; Techniques</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/BSD.0b013e31805777fb</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18418137</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-19"><label>Li et al. (2019)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>Trends of surgical treatment for spinal degenerative disease in China: a cohort of 37,897 inpatients from 2003 to 2016</article-title><source>Clinical Interventions in Aging</source><volume>14</volume><fpage>361</fpage><lpage>366</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/cia.s191449</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30863029</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-20"><label>Lin et al. (2019)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>GX</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kotheeranurak</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>C-W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Heo</surname><given-names>D-H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>C-K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J-Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J-S</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>A systematic review of unilateral biportal endoscopic spinal surgery: preliminary clinical results and complications</article-title><source>World Neurosurgery</source><volume>125</volume><fpage>425</fpage><lpage>432</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.wneu.2019.02.038</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30797907</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-21"><label>Lin et al. (2022)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>GX</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>ZK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C-M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rui</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>B-S</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year><article-title>Evaluation of the outcomes of biportal endoscopic lumbar interbody fusion compared with conventional fusion operations: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>World Neurosurgery</source><volume>160</volume><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>66</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.wneu.2022.01.071</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35085805</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-22"><label>Nadler, Hidalgo &#x00026; Bloch (1962)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nadler</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hidalgo</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bloch</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="1962">1962</year><article-title>Prediction of blood volume in normal human adults</article-title><source>Surgery</source><volume>51</volume><fpage>224</fpage><lpage>232</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21936146</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-23"><label>Nash et al. (2016)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nash</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tractenberg</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mendez</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>David</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ljungberg</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tinsley</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Burns-Drecq</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Betancourt</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Groah</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Cardiometabolic syndrome in people with spinal cord injury/disease: guideline-derived and nonguideline risk components in a pooled sample</article-title><source>Archives of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation</source><volume>97</volume><fpage>1696</fpage><lpage>1705</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apmr.2016.07.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27465752</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-24"><label>Pan et al. (2020)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><article-title>Percutaneous endoscopic lumbar discectomy: indications and complications</article-title><source>Pain Physician</source><volume>23</volume><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>56</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32013278</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-25"><label>Park et al. (2017)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jun</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Posterior percutaneous endoscopic cervical foraminotomy and diskectomy with unilateral biportal endoscopy</article-title><source>Orthopedics</source><volume>40</volume><fpage>e779</fpage><lpage>e783</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3928/01477447-20170531-02</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28585996</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-26"><label>Park et al. (2020)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>S-S</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><article-title>Dural tears in percutaneous biportal endoscopic spine surgery: anatomical location and management</article-title><source>World Neurosurgery</source><volume>136</volume><fpage>e578</fpage><lpage>e585</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.wneu.2020.01.080</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31958589</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-27"><label>Peng et al. (2023)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>QL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q-Z-Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>J-Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X-F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2023">2023</year><article-title>Comparison of the total and hidden blood loss in patients undergoing single-level open and unilateral biportal endoscopic transforaminal lumbar interbody fusion: a retrospective case control study</article-title><source>BMC Musculoskeletal Disorders</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>295</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12891-023-06393-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37060012</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-28"><label>Sehat, Evans &#x00026; Newman (2004)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sehat</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year><article-title>Hidden blood loss following hip and knee arthroplasty. Correct management of blood loss should take hidden loss into account</article-title><source>The Journal of Bone and Joint Surgery British Volume</source><volume>86</volume><fpage>561</fpage><lpage>565</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2106/00004623-200403000-00015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15174554</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-29"><label>Tetreault et al. (2015)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tetreault</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Harrop</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hilibrand</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nouri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fehlings</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Degenerative cervical myelopathy: a spectrum of related disorders affecting the aging spine</article-title><source>Neurosurgery</source><volume>77</volume><issue>Suppl 4</issue><fpage>S51</fpage><lpage>S67</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1227/neu.0000000000000951</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26378358</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-30"><label>Thelander &#x00026; Larsson (1992)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Thelander</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Larsson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="1992">1992</year><article-title>Quantitation of C-reactive protein levels and erythrocyte sedimentation rate after spinal surgery</article-title><source>Spine</source><volume>17</volume><fpage>400</fpage><lpage>404</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00007632-199204000-00004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1579874</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-31"><label>Xu et al. (2022)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year><article-title>Learning curve and complications of unilateral biportal endoscopy: cumulative sum and risk-adjusted cumulative sum analysis</article-title><source>Neurospine</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>792</fpage><lpage>804</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14245/ns.2143116.558</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35996762</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-32"><label>Yang et al. (2017)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Hidden and overall haemorrhage following minimally invasive and open transforaminal lumbar interbody fusion</article-title><source>Journal of Orthopaedics and Traumatology</source><volume>18</volume><fpage>395</fpage><lpage>400</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10195-017-0464-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28741030</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-33"><label>Zhang et al. (2017)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>ZX</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>ZM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>W-F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y-S</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Comparison of the total and hidden blood loss in patients undergoing open and minimally invasive transforaminal lumbar interbody fusion</article-title><source>World Neurosurgery</source><volume>107</volume><fpage>739</fpage><lpage>743</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.wneu.2017.08.113</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28844914</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>