<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Psychon Bull Rev</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Psychon Bull Rev</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Psychonomic Bulletin &#x00026; Review</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1069-9384</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1531-5320</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer US</publisher-name><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38743215</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11680657</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2517</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3758/s13423-024-02517-0</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Brief Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Surprise!&#x02014;Clarifying the link between insight and prediction error</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-9430-4077</contrib-id><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>Maxi</given-names></name><address><email>maxi_becker@gmx.net</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Xinhao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cabeza</surname><given-names>Roberto</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/01hcx6992</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.7468.d</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2248 7639</institution-id><institution>Department of Psychology, </institution><institution>Humboldt University Berlin, </institution></institution-wrap>Berlin, Germany </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/00py81415</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.26009.3d</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 7961</institution-id><institution>Center for Cognitive Neuroscience, </institution><institution>Duke University, </institution></institution-wrap>Durham, NC 27708 USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>5</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>14</day><month>5</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>31</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>2714</fpage><lpage>2723</lpage><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>4</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2024</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">The AHA experience, a moment of deep understanding during insightful problem-solving involving feelings of certainty, pleasure, and surprise, has captivated psychologists for more than a century. Recently, a new theoretical framework has proposed a link between the AHA experience and prediction error (PE), a popular concept in decision-making and reinforcement learning. This framework suggests that participants maintain a meta-cognitive prediction about the time it takes to solve a problem and the AHA experience arises when the problem is solved earlier than expected, resulting in a <italic>meta-cognitive PE</italic>. In our preregistered online study, we delved deeper into this idea, investigating whether prediction errors also pertain to participants&#x02019; predictions regarding the solvability of the problem itself, and which dimension of the AHA experience aligns with the meta-cognitive PE. Utilizing verbal insight problems, we found a positive association between the AHA experience and the meta-cognitive PE, specifically in regards to problem solvability. Specifically, the element of <italic>surprise,</italic> a critical AHA dimension, emerged as a key indicator of the meta-cognitive PE, while other dimensions&#x02014;such as pleasure, certainty, and suddenness&#x02014;showed no signs for similar relationships, with suddenness exhibiting a negative correlation with meta-cognitive PE. This new finding provides further evidence that aspects of the AHA experience, <italic>surprise</italic> in particular, correspond to a meta-cognitive PE. The finding also underscores the multifaceted nature of this phenomenon, linking insights with learning theories and enhancing our understanding of this intriguing phenomenon.</p><sec><title>Supplementary information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.3758/s13423-024-02517-0.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Insight</kwd><kwd>Prediction error</kwd><kwd>Aha experience</kwd><kwd>Surprise</kwd><kwd>Compound remote associates</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Humboldt-Universit&#x000e4;t zu Berlin (1034)</institution></funding-source></award-group><open-access><p>Open Access funding enabled and organized by Projekt DEAL.</p></open-access></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Psychonomic Society, Inc. 2024</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Many scientific discoveries and groundbreaking innovations have been the result of insights that have been described as thrilling moments of clarity and understanding. Those sudden understandings of a nonobvious problem involve connecting seemingly unrelated ideas or concepts and are usually accompanied by an &#x0201c;AHA!&#x0201d; experience (Danek et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2020</xref>; Dietrich &#x00026; Kanso, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2010</xref>). People do not always experience insight or an AHA moment when they come up with new ideas or solve problems. But when they do, the idea or solution feels discontinuous, internally rewarding and surprising, including the subjective experience that it appeared suddenly and is certainly correct (Danek &#x00026; Wiley, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2017</xref>; Kizilirmak et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2019</xref>; Metcalfe &#x00026; Wiebe, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">1987</xref>; Topolinski &#x00026; Reber, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2010</xref>).</p><sec id="Sec2"><title>AHA experience as (meta-cognitive) prediction error</title><p id="Par3">What explains this fundamental difference in subjective phenomenology between insight and noninsight solutions? For more than a century, psychology has held an interest in understanding the essence of the AHA experience, leading to an extensive body of literature exploring both the behavioural and neurocognitive aspects of this phenomenon (for a review, see Becker et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2023</xref>), alongside theories about its phenomenology (Topolinski &#x00026; Reber, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2010</xref>). For example, the AHA experience has been related to internal reward signals of having found the solution involving classical reward regions like the ventral striatum (Becker et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2023</xref>; Kizilirmak et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2016</xref>; Kizilirmak &#x00026; Becker, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2023</xref>; Oh et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2020</xref>; Tik et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2018</xref>). However, this only explains the reward aspect, which is only one of the several dimensions of the AHA experience. In contrast, a new account attempts to connect the phenomenology of the AHA experience to the concept of <italic>prediction error</italic> (Becker &#x00026; Cabeza, in press; Danek et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2015</xref>; Dubey et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2021</xref>; Friston et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2017</xref>; Savinova &#x00026; Korovkin, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2022</xref>). This concept is widely known in decision-making and reinforcement learning (Sutton &#x00026; Barto, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2018</xref>), due to its close conceptual proximity to surprise, reward and novelty. A prediction error (PE) generally describes a mismatch between a predicted outcome (i.e. prior experience derived from statistical regularities) and an actual outcome (i.e. sensory inputs or current thoughts; Rouhani et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2023</xref>). PEs may be classified into (1) perceptual/cognitive PEs, which refer to the size of the surprise of a perceptual/cognitive outcome, and (2) motivational PEs, which refer to the valence of the outcome&#x02014;that is, whether an outcome is better or worse than expected (Den Ouden et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2012</xref>).</p><p id="Par4">In the context of problem-solving, Dubey and colleagues (2021) argue that subjects are assumed to maintain a meta-cognitive model of their ability and prediction of when to solve a problem. Consequently, a PE arises when the solution is solved faster than expected, creating this sense of suddenness, surprise and internal reward (Dubey et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2021</xref>). As support for their assumptions, they conducted a large-scale online experiment, along with several simulation studies, where subjects were briefly presented with anagrams of varying difficulty for one second. They were then prompted to estimate how long it would take them to solve the anagram (ranging from 0 to 3 minutes). Subsequently, participants were asked to solve the anagrams and rate their AHA experience (scale of 1 to 7). The time PE was calculated by subtracting the actual solution time from the estimated solution time, which was then compared with the reported AHA experience. Their analysis revealed a significant positive correlation between participants&#x02019; time PE and their subjective AHA experiences (but note, the PE&#x02013;AHA relationship may have been confounded by the varying difficulty of the anagrams).</p><p id="Par5">Considering the AHA experience through the lens of a (meta-cognitive) PE is a promising approach not only because it has the potential to explain its distinct dimensions, such as pleasure and surprise, but also because it connects insight to a more general theory of (reinforcement) learning in psychology, potentially providing a more unifying account of this phenomenon (Dubey et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2021</xref>; Friston et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2017</xref>). When solving a problem via insight, the solution itself often seems to be completely unexpected (Kizilirmak et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2018</xref>; Metcalfe &#x00026; Wiebe, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">1987</xref>). Therefore, it is plausible that the AHA experience is associated not solely with a PE regarding the solution timing (Dubey et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2021</xref>), but also with several PEs concerning different aspects of the solution process, such as its general solvability or the content of the solution. What Dubey et al.&#x02019;s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2021</xref>) study leaves further open is which aspects of the AHA experience (positive emotions, suddenness, certainty and surprise, amongst others; Danek &#x00026; Wiley, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2017</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2020</xref>; Webb et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2016</xref>) best represent a meta-cognitive PE.</p><p id="Par6">Savinova and Korovkin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2022</xref>) did not directly examine metacognitive PEs but explored the impact of solution expectancy on different dimensions of the AHA experience (pleasure, surprise, suddenness, and certainty) by manipulating subjects&#x02019; expectations across different problem sets. They compared a control group where solution approaches varied for each of the eight problems, with two experimental groups where the approach remained consistent except for the last problem. One experimental group had additionally similar problem structures. Results showed that as solutions became more expected (from problem 1&#x02013;7 in experimental groups), surprise and (less consistently) pleasure decreased. Furthermore, in the experimental group with similar problem structures, pleasure and surprise additionally increased from the penultimate to the last problem. These results suggest a first link between solution expectancy and AHA experience, particularly with surprise and pleasure (no consistent relationship was found with suddenness and certainty). Yet, it remains unclear whether these particular dimensions of the AHA experience or others are linked to a metacognitive PE on a trial by trial level, as suggested by Dubey et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2021</xref>) and whether this relationship generalizes to other tasks.</p></sec><sec id="Sec3"><title>Current research and hypotheses</title><p id="Par7">To further investigate those questions, we set up a pre-registered online study utilising verbal problems&#x02014;compound remote associates (CRAs)&#x02014;whose solution is often accompanied by an AHA experience (Bowden &#x00026; Jung-Beeman, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2003</xref>). To estimate participants&#x02019; solution expectation, we first briefly presented them with the individual CRAs and asked them to evaluate the solvability of those problems (solution expectation). Subsequently, we had them solve the CRAs and rate their AHA experience. Importantly, similar to Savinova and Korovkin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2022</xref>), the AHA experience was divided into four different dimensions (internal <italic>pleasure</italic> of having found the solution and feeling that it appeared <italic>suddenly</italic>, <italic>certainty</italic> that the solution is correct and <italic>surprise</italic> about the solution result).</p><p id="Par8">Under the assumption that some AHA experience dimensions represent a (meta-cognitive) PE of the problem&#x02019;s solvability, we assumed that the difference between the solution expectation and the actual solution outcome should directly scale with the size of those AHA experience dimensions on a trial by trial basis. As we exclusively examine solved problems, where the solution outcome is inherently equal to or better than the expected outcome, we hypothesized a positive correlation between the meta-cognitive PE and the corresponding dimension of the AHA experience (see Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Although not explicitly preregistered, we expect this positive correlation to be stronger in correctly solved trials, as only they are reliably interpreted as indicative of genuine insight.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>Experimental design and hypotheses. <italic>Note.</italic> CRA = Compound Remote Associates. AHA<sub>dim</sub> = AHA experience dimensions; Acc. = Accuracy; Acc.0 = incorrectly solved trial; Acc.1 = correctly solved trial; PE<sub>meta</sub> = meta-cognitive prediction error. Hypotheses: We expect a positive relationship between PE<sub>meta</sub> and any of the AHA dimensions and this relationship should be modulated by accuracy. PE<sub>meta</sub> is calculated as the difference between the actual solution and expected solution likelihood. The participant&#x02019;s expected solution likelihood was measured via the Rating task. (Color figure online)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13423_2024_2517_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec5"><title>Participants</title><p id="Par9">The study was preregistered (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://aspredicted.org/ce7hu.pdf">https://aspredicted.org/ce7hu.pdf</ext-link>). Relying on the effect size from a study investigating the AHA experience as a prediction error (Dubey et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2021</xref>), we estimated a minimal sample size of <italic>n</italic> = 27 (&#x000df; = 95%, &#x003b1; = 5%). The study was conducted as an online format for an English-speaking population in MechanicalTurk, recruiting 45 participants. The local ethics committee of the Humboldt University Berlin approved the study. All participants received monetary compensation for their time on task. The only inclusion criterion was English-language proficiency because the task required high knowledge of English. For this, we adopted the Mill Hill vocabulary scale (Raven,&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">1960</xref>). Participants were excluded from further analyses if (1) they did not manage to choose the correct synonym for 5 out of 18 words from the Mill Hill vocabulary scale (<italic>n</italic> = 6), (2) showed no variance in their AHA rating (<italic>n</italic> = 0), or (3) in their solution likelihood rating (<italic>n</italic> = 0). Six participants were excluded from the study based on those criteria resulting in a final sample of <italic>n</italic> = 39 [age (in years): <italic>M</italic> = 43.2, <italic>median</italic> = 44; <italic>SD</italic> = 11.2; range: 27&#x02013;65, 48.7% females.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Materials and procedure</title><sec id="FPar1" sec-type="materials"><title>Materials</title><p id="Par10">The stimulus material consisted of 60 normed Compound Remote Associates (CRA) published elsewhere (Bowden &#x00026; Jung-Beeman, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2003</xref>). Those verbal tasks consist of three presented target words (e.g., <italic>reading, service, stick</italic>), and the goal is to find a solution word (<italic>lip</italic>) that can be appended in front or in the back of every one of the target words building a meaningful compound, respectively (<italic>lip reading, lip service, lip stick</italic>). Based on the norms, mean accuracy was 51.0% (<italic>SD</italic> = 24.4%; max = 97%; min = 10%) and solution time was 10.5 sec (<italic>SD</italic> = 3.49 sec, min = 4.12 sec; max = 18.69 sec). A list with all CRAs selected for this study in the experiment can be found in the Supplement (Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Procedure</title><p id="Par11">The online experiment was programmed in Inquisit (Version 4.0; Inquisit, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2012</xref>), took approx. 45 minutes and was divided into four different tasks. To be eligible for participation in the experiment, participants first completed the Mill Hill task, followed by the execution of the Rating task, Word fluency task, and finally CRA task (explained in more detail as follows).</p></sec><sec id="FPar3"><title>Rating task</title><p id="Par12">After task instructions, participants first received nine practice trials to get used to the task. For the test trials, they received all 60 CRAs in a randomized order for 2 seconds and were subsequently asked about their solution expectation: &#x0201c;How likely do you think you can solve the problem on a scale between 1 (<italic>very unlikely</italic>) and 5 (<italic>very likely</italic>)?&#x0201d; After explaining the goal of the task to them, they were specifically instructed not to solve the individual items but to provide a personal or subjective estimate (&#x0201c;gut feeling&#x0201d;) of how likely they think they could solve the task. To enforce that participants do not overthink their respective estimate or try to solve the CRA, response time for every rating was limited to max 5 seconds (excluding the 2 seconds stimulus presentation). Average response time was 0.96 sec (<italic>SD</italic> = 0.74 sec). Trials where participants did not provide a rating within a 5-second time window were timed out and excluded from all further analyses (0.3% of all trials). Participants could also indicate whether they had already solved the trial within this 2-second time window; those trials were excluded from all further analyses (8.2% of all trials).</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Word fluency task</title><p id="Par13">In this short task, participants were asked to write down as many animals and plants as they can think of in one minute each. This short task was included primarily to distract the participants from thinking about the previously shown CRAs and their solutions as this might bias the results.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Compound Remote Associates (CRAs)</title><p id="Par14">After a short task instruction including two practice trials, participants received the same 60 CRAs in a randomized order again that they had already seen in the Rating task. This time they were asked to solve them within max 45 seconds and if they failed to do so a new trial would start. They were instructed to press their solution button as soon as they found the answer and type in their respective solution word. Subsequently, they were asked to rate how they experienced their solution in relation to (1) <italic>suddenness</italic>, (2) <italic>pleasure</italic>, (3) <italic>certainty,</italic> and (4) <italic>surprise</italic> (see next paragraph) without a time limit. After providing all responses, a new trial would start.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Insight assessment</title><p id="Par15">Insight is typically assessed using self-ratings of the AHA experience, previously quantified as a binary variable denoting its presence or absence (Jung-Beeman et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2004</xref>; Kounios &#x00026; Beeman, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2014</xref>). However, more recent investigations have revealed that the AHA experience actually constitutes a continuous phenomenon comprising several dimensions. These dimensions include (1) the extent of positive emotional response upon discovering the solution, (2) the perceived suddenness of the solution&#x02019;s emergence, (3) the level of certainty regarding the correctness of the solution, and (4) the degree of surprise elicited by the solution, among other dimensions (Danek et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2014</xref>; Danek &#x00026; Wiley, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2017</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2020</xref>; Webb et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2016</xref>). Therefore, we assessed insight via the AHA experience on a continuous scale and split it into those four main components (positive emotion/pleasure, certainty, suddenness, surprise). Note, however, there is still no consensus about which components make up the AHA experience, resulting in some researchers focussing more on the suddenness or emotional/pleasure component (Kounios &#x00026; Beeman, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2014</xref>; Tik et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2018</xref>) and others on the surprise component (Gick &#x00026; Lockhart, 1995) reducing comparability between studies. The different concepts were described to the participants as follows:</p><p id="Par16">
<disp-quote><p id="Par17">&#x0201c;Consequently, you are asked HOW you experienced finding the solution: Here, we ask about four different aspects of the AHA experience: suddenness, pleasure, certainty, &#x00026; surprise that can, but don&#x02019;t always, have to coincide.&#x0201d;</p><p id="Par18"><bold><italic>Suddenness:</italic></bold>&#x000a0;&#x0201c;Did the solution come to you suddenly, or did you increasingly approach the solution in a stepwise manner? (scale: 1 [<italic>stepwise</italic>]&#x02013;7 [<italic>sudden solution</italic>]).&#x0201d;</p><p id="Par19"><bold><italic>Pleasure:</italic></bold>&#x000a0;&#x0201c;Did you experience a positive emotion (pleasure) upon finding the solution? yes/no.&#x0201d;&#x000a0;</p><p id="Par20"><bold><italic>Certainty:</italic></bold>&#x000a0;&#x0201c;When the solution first appeared to you (before evaluation), how certain were you that the solution is correct? (scale 1&#x02013;7).&#x0201d;</p><p id="Par21"><bold><italic>Surprise:</italic></bold>&#x000a0;&#x0201c;How surprising does the solution result seem to you? (scale 1&#x02013;7).&#x0201d;</p></disp-quote>
</p><p id="Par22">Note, participants might be surprised not only by the moment of insight but also by the solution&#x02019;s content. For example, they might not have expected that the solution, like &#x0201c;dog,&#x0201d; falls within the semantic category of mammals/animals when first given the task. To account for this, we allowed participants to interpret the nature of their surprise and simply referred to it as &#x0201c;surprise about the solution result&#x0201d; in the instruction and during the rating. In order to prevent participants from forgetting each dimension&#x02019;s meaning, we also provided them with descriptions for each dimension during each individual rating. However, the possibility of idiosyncratic interpretations of these other dimensions cannot be entirely ruled out.</p><sec id="FPar10"><title>Measurement model for AHA experience</title><p id="Par23">To demonstrate that those four dimensions form part of the AHA experience for the current data set, we calculated a measurement model for a latent AHA experience factor from those four dimensions (<italic>suddenness, pleasure, certainty, surprise</italic>) for correctly solved CRA items. The latent factor was estimated within a confirmatory factor analysis (CFA) in R using the lavaan package and its default settings (Version 0.6-15; Rosseel, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2012</xref>). In order to ensure that the relationships among the AHA dimensions in the measurement model remain unbiased by factors such as difficulty or individual differences between subjects or items, we utilized residualized data in the confirmatory factor analysis (CFA). That is to say, we first calculated a (general) linear mixed model for every AHA dimension controlling for solution time, trial number, as well as random subject and item effects (following this formula: AHA<sub>dimensions</sub> ~ RT + trial# + (1|subject) + (1|item) + &#x00190;). The resulting residuals were entered into the CFA. The measurement model was estimated via the robust maximum likelihood estimator and the resulting fit was evaluated via the exact chi-squared goodness-of-fit statistic as well as comparative fit indices such as Bentler&#x02019;s comparative fit index (CFI), root-mean-square error of approximation (RMSEA), and standardized root-mean-square residual (SRMR). Accepted thresholds indicating good model fit are RMSEA &#x02264; .05, SRMR &#x0003c; 0.1, and CFI &#x02265; = .95 (Hu &#x00026; Bentler, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">1999</xref>; Schermelleh-Engel et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2014</xref>). To improve the model fit, we additionally specified covariances between the variables <italic>pleasure</italic> and <italic>surprise</italic> (see Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Measurement model: Latent AHA Experience factor loading onto four different AHA dimensions. <italic>Note</italic>. Asterisk indicates significant factor loading at <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; .001</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13423_2024_2517_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="FPar11"><title><bold>Calculation of meta-cognitive prediction error (PE</bold><sub><bold>meta</bold></sub><bold>)</bold></title><p id="Par24">We defined the PE<sub>meta</sub> related to the solvability of a problem as the difference between the actual and expected solution outcome consistent with previous work (Den Ouden et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2012</xref>). The expected solution outcome was measured via the solution likelihood rating in the Rating task and the resulting values (1 = <italic>very unlikely solvable</italic> to 5 = <italic>very likely solvable</italic>) were normed between 0 and 1. The actual solution outcome (i.e., participants pressing the solution button under the belief they had found a solution regardless of its accuracy) was set to 1 (<italic>very likely solvable</italic>) as this relates to the highest possible solution likelihood and subtracted from the expected solution outcome (solution likelihood).<disp-formula id="Equa"><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${PE}_{meta}= {1 -"expected\;solution\;likelihood"}_{{\text{normed}}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M2" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">PE</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">meta</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mo>"</mml:mo><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>"</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>normed</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13423_2024_2517_Article_Equa.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p>Note, in this problem-solving context, the actual solution outcome can only be better or as good as the expected solution outcome, but never worse, because we only consider solutions.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Data analyses</title><p id="Par26">For statistical analysis, three general linear mixed-effects models (Baayen et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2008</xref>) were applied predicting variance in s<italic>uddenness, pleasure, certainty,</italic> and <italic>surprise</italic> (dependent variable) with PE<sub><italic>meta</italic></sub> (independent variable) on a trial-by-trial basis (see equations, below). We assumed a positive relationship between at least one of the AHA experience&#x02019;s main dimensions and PE<sub><italic>meta</italic></sub> if those components reflect internal errors in predicting the solution. Because insight refers to correctly solved trials (Salvi et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2016</xref>), we assumed that the positive relationship between PE<sub>meta</sub> and the AHA dimensions should be more strongly pronounced for correctly than for incorrectly solved trials indicative of a genuine insight (see Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Therefore, we additionally estimated an interaction between PE<sub>meta</sub> and accuracy in predicting dimensions of the AHA experience. We further corrected for solution time to account for task difficulty and trial order to account for signs of fatigue or habituation. Subjects and items were modelled as random intercepts.<list list-type="order"><list-item><p id="Par27">AHA<sub>dimensions</sub> ~ Acc. + RT + trial# + (1|subject) + (1|item) + &#x00190;</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par28">AHA<sub>dimensions</sub> ~ PE<sub>meta</sub> + Acc. + RT + trial# + (1|subject) + (1|item) + &#x00190;</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par29">AHA<sub>dimensions</sub> ~ PE<sub>meta</sub> * Acc. + RT + trial# + (1|subject) + (1|item) + &#x00190;</p></list-item></list></p><p id="Par30"><italic>Note</italic>. AHA dimensions are <italic>pleasure</italic>, <italic>suddenness</italic>, <italic>certainty,</italic> and <italic>surprise</italic>. RT = solution time. PE<sub>meta</sub> = meta-cognitive prediction error; acc.= accuracy.</p><p id="Par31">Pop-out solutions (&#x0003c;2 sec) were excluded from all analyses as they do not count as insight solutions (Becker et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2021</xref>). Note however, as this resulted in an exclusion of 42.5% of all trials, we additionally repeated the analyses including trials that were solved in &#x0003c;2 sec. Importantly, the main results did not change significantly. Because pleasure was measured in a binary style, we modelled this variable via a binomial model (logit link function). All other models were modelled assuming a Gaussian link function. The <italic>p</italic> values were calculated via likelihood-ratio tests testing the baseline model (1) without PE<sub><italic>meta</italic></sub> against the full model (2) with PE<sub><italic>meta</italic></sub> and the full model (2) against the interaction model (PE<sub><italic>meta</italic></sub> * accuracy) (3). For exploratory purposes, we additionally modelled a three-way interaction (PE<sub><italic>meta</italic></sub> * accuracy * solution time) for <italic>suddenness</italic> to investigate whether solution time (i.e., task difficulty) modulated the unexpected negative relationship with PE<sub><italic>meta.</italic></sub> Importantly, because we did not know which dimension of the AHA experience may relate to PE<sub><italic>meta</italic></sub>, all respective resulting <italic>p</italic> values were corrected for multiple comparison (Holm, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">1979</xref>). Only the best model fit is being reported. All mixed-effects analyses were conducted in R (Version 4.2.0) using the glmmTMB package (Version 1.1.7; Brooks et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2017</xref>). The data as well as the analysis code have been made publicly available online (github.com/MaxiBecker/AHA_as_Prediction-Error).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Results</title><p id="Par32">On average, participants pressed the solution button in 85.3% (<italic>SD</italic> = 16.2%) of all CRAs and they solved 64.5% (<italic>SD</italic> = 16.9%) of all trials correctly. Median solution time for all trials was 7.63 sec (<italic>SD</italic> = 2.8 sec) and 6.3 sec (<italic>SD</italic> = 2.6 sec) for correctly solved trials. The CRA solutions were rated as <italic>pleasing</italic> in 57% (<italic>SD</italic> = 31%) of all cases and on a scale from 1 to 7 they were perceived as <italic>certain</italic> (<italic>M</italic> = 4.8; <italic>SD</italic> = .96), <italic>sudden</italic> (<italic>M</italic> = 4.62; <italic>SD</italic> = .95), and <italic>surprising</italic> (<italic>M</italic> = 3.08; <italic>SD</italic> = 1.08). Furthermore, participants were able to predict whether they would be able to correctly solve a CRA problem or not, &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>(1) = 5.46, <italic>p</italic> = .019; odds ratio = 1.20.</p><sec id="Sec10"><title>Latent AHA experience factor loads onto AHA dimensions</title><p id="Par33">The model converged normally after 26 iterations. The chi-squared goodness-of-fit statistic, &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>(1) = .629, <italic>p</italic> = .428, was not significant suggesting no significant difference between the measurement model and the data. Practical fit indices confirmed a good fit of the model to the data (CFI = 1.00; RSMEA = .000; SRMR =.007). The latent insight factor loaded significantly positively onto <italic>Certainty</italic> (<italic>&#x003bb;</italic> = .755, <italic>z</italic> = 11.79; <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; .001), <italic>Suddenness</italic> (<italic>&#x003bb;</italic> = .492, <italic>z</italic> = 10.79; <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; .001), and <italic>Pleasure</italic> (<italic>&#x003bb;</italic> = .344, <italic>z</italic> = 6.75; <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; .001), and significantly negatively onto <italic>Surprise</italic> (<italic>&#x003bb;</italic> = &#x02212;.313, <italic>z</italic> = &#x02212;5.922; <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; .001) suggesting that all four variables contribute significantly to the latent AHA experience factor (see Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). In sum, those results confirm that all four AHA dimensions explain relevant variance of a latent AHA experience factor.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Relationship between meta-cognitive prediction error and AHA dimensions</title><sec id="FPar12"><title>Certainty</title><p id="Par34">Accuracy, &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>(1) = 495.97, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; .001, <italic>&#x000df;</italic> = .57, CI [.53, .62], predicted the amount of certainty about the correctness of the solution. However, there was no evidence for PE<sub>meta</sub>, &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>(1) = 1.84, <italic>p</italic> = .17, &#x000df; = &#x02212;.03, CI [&#x02212;.07, .01], nor for an interaction between PE<sub>meta</sub> and accuracy, &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>(1) = 0.35, <italic>p</italic> = .55 &#x000df; = .01, CI [&#x02212;.03, .05], to predict variance in the amount of certainty about the solution (see Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>, Table S2 in the Supplement).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Meta-cognitive prediction error predicting AHA experience dimension <italic>surprise. Note.</italic> Values represent estimated marginal means. Error bars are 95% confidence intervals; likel. = likelihood; Accuracy 0 = incorrect solution; Accuracy 1 = correct solution</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13423_2024_2517_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="FPar13"><title>Pleasure</title><p id="Par35">Accuracy, &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>(1) = 276.85, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; .001, odds ratio = 24.60, CI [15.65, 38.68], predicted the amount of perceived pleasure upon finding the solution. However, there was no evidence for PE<sub>meta</sub>, &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>(1) = 1.88, <italic>p</italic> = .17, odds ratio = .70, CI [.42, 1.17], nor for an interaction between PE<sub>meta</sub> and accuracy, &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>(1) = 1.38, <italic>p</italic> = .24, odds ratio = 2.0, CI [.63, 6.40], to predict variance in the amount of perceived pleasure (see Fig<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">.3</xref>, Table S2 in the Supplement).</p></sec><sec id="FPar14"><title>Suddenness</title><p id="Par36">Both PE<sub>meta</sub>, &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>(1) = 6.52, <italic>p</italic>-Bonferroni = .043, &#x000df; = &#x02212;.06 CI [&#x02212;.11, .01], and accuracy, &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>(1) = 71.20, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; .001, &#x000df; = .23, CI [.18, .28], predicted the amount of perceived suddenness upon finding the solution (see Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). However, the relationship between PE<sub>meta</sub> and suddenness was negative and therefore in the opposite than hypothesized direction. No evidence for a significant interaction between PE<sub>meta</sub> and accuracy in predicting <italic>suddenness</italic> was observed, &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>(1) = 0.15, <italic>p</italic> = .69, &#x000df; = .01, CI [&#x02212;.04, .06], hence, correctly and incorrectly solved trials contributed to this negative relationship (see Table S3 in the Supplement).</p><p id="Par37">Given the unexpected negative relationship between <italic>suddenness</italic> and PE<sub>meta</sub>, we further explored whether this relationship is modulated by task difficulty (i.e., solution time). In fact, we found a three-way interaction between PE<sub>meta</sub> * Accuracy * Solution Time, &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>(1) = 4.20, <italic>p</italic> = .04, &#x000df; = .05, CI [.00,.10]. A visual inspection of the interaction demonstrates that the negative relationship between PE<sub>meta</sub> and <italic>suddenness</italic> for correctly solved trials is driven by quickly solved CRA items (~ 2.4 sec; see Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref> in the Supplement).</p></sec><sec id="FPar15"><title>Surprise</title><p id="Par38">The amount of perceived surprise upon solution finding was significantly negatively predicted by accuracy, &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup> = 11.24, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; .001, &#x000df; = &#x02212;.16 CI [&#x02212;.21, &#x02212;.11], and significantly positively predicted by PE<sub>meta</sub>, &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>(1) = 18.88, <italic>p</italic>-Bonferroni &#x0003c; .001, &#x000df; = .12, CI [.07, .27]. There was furthermore a trend for significance for a PE<sub>meta</sub> * Accuracy interaction, &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>(1) = 3.68, <italic>p</italic> = .055, &#x000df; = &#x02212;.12 CI [&#x02212;.27, &#x02212;.07]). A visual inspection of the interaction demonstrates that the positive relationship between PE<sub>meta</sub> and <italic>surprise</italic> was mostly driven by correct solutions (see Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>, Table S3 in the Supplement).</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par39">The AHA experience, an indicator of insight, is a complex construct with multiple dimensions, including pleasure, certainty, suddenness, and surprise about the solution. Recent suggestions propose a link between the AHA experience and meta-cognitive prediction errors (PE<sub>meta</sub>), reflecting the temporal difference between the expected and actual solution (Dubey et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2021</xref>). In this study, we further explored this link investigating whether PE<sub>meta</sub> also relates to the expected solvability of the problem and which AHA dimension might reflect this aspect. We hypothesized a positive correlation between PE<sub>meta</sub> and at least one AHA dimension, with a stronger effect for correct solutions, indicative of genuine insight (Danek &#x00026; Salvi, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2020</xref>). As hypothesized, we found evidence that <italic>surprise</italic> was significantly predicted by PE<sub>meta</sub>, particularly for correct solutions. No other AHA dimension exhibited a significant relationship in the expected direction. Moreover, we observed a negative correlation between PE<sub>meta</sub> and suddenness, contingent upon solution time and accuracy, as will be elaborated upon in the subsequent discussion.</p><sec id="Sec13"><title>Relationships between different AHA dimensions and PE<sub>meta</sub></title><p id="Par40">The positive correlation between PE<sub>meta</sub> and <italic>surprise</italic> is consistent with Savinova and Korovkin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2022</xref>) who found <italic>surprise</italic> to be most consistently related to solution expectancy. This relationship is further consistent with Dubey et al.&#x02019;s, (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2021</xref>) reinforcement learning account of insight suggesting that the AHA experience involves monitoring predictions about one&#x02019;s interactions with the problem and &#x0201c;sudden insight surprises individuals about their own problem-solving ability,&#x0201d; leading to the AHA experience (Dubey et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2021</xref>, p. 14). This positive correlation further aligns with Friston et al.&#x02019;s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2017</xref>) active inference framework by suggesting that the AHA moment represents a reduction in prediction error, as individuals update their beliefs about problem solvability. The positive correlation indicates that greater surprise during the AHA moment is linked to larger discrepancies between initial predictions and the actual solution, reflecting a significant revision of prior beliefs (Friston et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2017</xref>). Note, that albeit related, PE<sub>meta</sub> and <italic>surprise</italic> are independent measures. PE<sub>meta</sub> refers to the estimated <italic>solvability</italic> of the problem before the problem is solved, measured via the rating task. In contrast, <italic>surprise</italic> relates to the emotional evaluation of how unexpected the moment of solution or the solution <italic>content</italic> is perceived once the solution was found in the CRA task.</p><p id="Par41">Finally, our results align with an fMRI study by Danek et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2015</xref>), demonstrating a connection between expectation violation in magic tricks and heightened activity in the anterior cingulate cortex. This brain region is frequently associated with prediction errors (Alexander &#x00026; Brown, 2019) and commonly activated during insight (Becker et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2021</xref>; Dietrich &#x00026; Kanso, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2010</xref>).</p><p id="Par42">As assumed (albeit not explicitly preregistered), the assumed positive relationship between <italic>surprise</italic> and PE<sub>meta</sub> was much more pronounced for correctly solved CRA items indicative of a genuine insight (see Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>), although the interaction between accuracy and PE<sub>meta</sub> only reached a trend for significance (<italic>p</italic> = .055). In contrast, <italic>surprise</italic> remained consistently high for inaccurately solved CRA problems as has been observed before (Danek &#x00026; Wiley, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2017</xref>). This likely reflects the fact that for incorrectly solved problems, the solver was generally unable to make predictions about the solution content resulting in high surprise upon (incorrect) solution.</p><p id="Par43">Our study found no evidence of a connection between PE<sub>meta</sub> and the <italic>pleasure</italic> and <italic>certainty</italic> dimensions of AHA. While the null finding for the certainty dimension is consistent with the null finding for this dimension in Savinova and Korovkin&#x02019;s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2022</xref>) study, they did observe a negative correlation between the level of solution expectation with (not only surprise but also) pleasure, although pleasure showed less consistent results. This also contrasts with Dubey et al.&#x02019;s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2021</xref>) suggestion that the AHA experience is analog to a reward prediction error. However, their assessment treated the AHA experience as a composite measure, making it impossible to determine which AHA dimension drove the positive link with their PE<sub>meta</sub> measure. Our null findings may stem from insufficient statistical power, due to significant interindividual differences related to trait reward sensitivity (Oh et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2020</xref>), despite our efforts to account for random subject effects in our analyses. Alternatively, PE<sub>meta</sub> may be primarily associated with the <italic>surprise</italic> element of the AHA experience and less with <italic>pleasure</italic> and <italic>certainty</italic>. In contrast, <italic>pleasure</italic> and <italic>certainty</italic> may be more reflective of reward towards having found the solution irrespective of prior expectations (Kizilirmak &#x00026; Becker, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2023</xref>; Oh et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2020</xref>) and how well the new solution fits into the solver&#x02019;s existing knowledge base (Laukkonen et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2022</xref>). Consistently, we found that <italic>pleasure</italic> and <italic>certainty</italic> were influenced by accuracy, implying both dimensions were elicited from the discovery of the correct solution. This aligns with past research showing that <italic>pleasure</italic> and <italic>certainty</italic> are better predictors of accuracy than <italic>surprise</italic> (Webb et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2018</xref>).</p><p id="Par44">Finally, PE<sub>meta</sub> negatively predicted <italic>suddenness</italic>, indicating that participants who expected to solve the CRA problem were more likely to perceive the solution as sudden. While this finding may appear counterintuitive, it can be explained by considering the influence of task difficulty on both <italic>suddenness</italic> and expected solution likelihood, as we found an effect of task difficulty (here measured via solution time) on participants&#x02019; expected solution likelihood and <italic>suddenness</italic> ratings. According to spreading activation accounts of insightful problem solving (Becker et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2022</xref>; Bowers et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">1990</xref>), simple CRA problems possess strong cue associations (e.g., drop, forest, cape) with the solution word (rain), leading to automatic preactivation of the solution upon cue presentation, thereby enhancing the sense of solvability (increased expected solution likelihood). At the same time, a solution may be perceived as <italic>sudden</italic> when the solution word was automatically activated including less controlled search processes indicative of simple problems (Becker et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2022</xref>). This is consistent with our finding that the negative relationship for <italic>suddenness</italic> and predictions of problem solving ability was mainly driven by simple problems solved in less than 4 seconds whereas the relationship ceases for (more difficult) problems solved later than that (see Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref> in the Supplements).</p><p id="Par45">Note, all four AHA dimensions were related to task difficulty but not in the same direction. While <italic>suddenness</italic>, <italic>certainty</italic> and <italic>pleasure</italic> were particularly high for easy problems, <italic>surprise</italic> increased with task difficulty, which probably explains the opposite factor loading on the latent AHA variable. Hence, to avoid a possible confound with task difficulty and understand the AHA experience&#x02019;s diverse functions, it is important to assess its different dimensions, particularly <italic>surprise</italic>. In sum, all results combined suggest that the AHA experience is a multifaceted complex construct that reflects various cognitive functions, with <italic>surprise</italic> being positively associated with a PE<sub>meta</sub> as previously suggested (Dubey et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2021</xref>). However, our results also suggest that PE<sub>meta</sub> is likely not the only factor driving the AHA experience.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Open questions</title><p id="Par46">Numerous questions remain unanswered, presenting future avenues for exploration. For example, PE<sub>meta</sub> has been observed to encompass various elements of the solution process, such as estimates regarding the timing of solution derivation (Dubey et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2021</xref>), as well as the general solvability of the solution (current study). To what extent do participants engage in meta-cognitive predictions concerning other aspects of the solution process depending on the type of problem, and how do these predictions interconnect with different AHA dimensions? Furthermore, certain dimensions of the AHA experience, such as <italic>relief, drive to act</italic>, and <italic>impasse</italic>, were not investigated in this study (Danek &#x00026; Wiley, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2017</xref>; Webb et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2016</xref>). This begs the question of whether any of these dimensions might bear associations with PE<sub>meta</sub>. Moreover, participants likely lack awareness of all their various predictions concerning the solution process. Therefore, assessing implicit solution expectations of subjects (ideally integrating objective measures via ERP studies to quantify surprise) and comparing them with the AHA experience could enhance our understanding of how prediction errors manifest in the surprise dimension of the AHA experience. Further research is warranted to address these open questions.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par47">In current insight research, efforts are underway to make this phenomenon more compatible with existing learning theories by associating the AHA experience with (meta-cognitive) PEs commonly known in reinforcement learning (Dubey et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2021</xref>; Friston et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2017</xref>). This is an important step towards a more comprehensive explanation of the insight phenomenon. The present study fills an important gap in this endeavour and again stresses the fact that the AHA experience is a complex and heterogeneous subjective phenomenon signalling different cognitive functions about the phenomenon (Danek &#x00026; Wiley, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2017</xref>; Webb et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2016</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec16" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary information</title><p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="13423_2024_2517_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><caption><p>Supplementary file1 (DOCX 180 KB)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This work was funded by the Einstein Foundation Berlin (EPP-2017-423), and M.B. was additionally funded by the Sonophilia Foundation. We thank Luise Oehler for her help in data acquisition and Paola Gega for useful discussions.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>M.B., X.W., &#x00026; R.C. conceived of the study. M.B. collected, analyzed the data, and wrote the manuscript. M.B., X.W., and R.C. contributed to revising the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>Open Access funding enabled and organized by Projekt DEAL. Einstein Stiftung Berlin, EPP-2017-423.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data Availability</title><p> The data for both experiments are available online (github.com/MaxiBecker/AHA_as_Prediction-Error), and the main experiment was preregistered (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://aspredicted.org/ce7hu.pdf">https://aspredicted.org/ce7hu.pdf</ext-link>).</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar16" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflicts of interest</title><p id="Par48">All authors report no financial interests or conflicts of interest.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baayen</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mixed-effects modeling with crossed random effects for subjects and items</article-title><source>Journal of Memory and Language</source><year>2008</year><volume>59</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>390</fpage><lpage>412</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jml.2007.12.005</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Baayen, R. H., Davidson, D. J., &#x00026; Bates, D. M. (2008). Mixed-effects modeling with crossed random effects for subjects and items. <italic>Journal of Memory and Language,</italic><italic>59</italic>(4), 390&#x02013;412.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cabeza</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Between automatic and control processes: How relationships between problem elements interact to facilitate or impede insight</article-title><source>Memory &#x00026; Cognition</source><year>2022</year><volume>50</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1719</fpage><lpage>1734</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3758/s13421-022-01277-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35260990</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Becker, M., Davis, S., &#x00026; Cabeza, R. (2022). Between automatic and control processes: How relationships between problem elements interact to facilitate or impede insight. <italic>Memory &#x00026; Cognition,</italic><italic>50</italic>(8), 1719&#x02013;1734.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35260990</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#x000fc;hn</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sommer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Verbal insight revisited&#x02014;Dissociable neurocognitive processes underlying solutions accompanied by an AHA! experience with and without prior restructuring</article-title><source>Journal of Cognitive Psychology</source><year>2021</year><volume>33</volume><issue>6/7</issue><fpage>659</fpage><lpage>684</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/20445911.2020.1819297</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Becker, M., K&#x000fc;hn, S., &#x00026; Sommer, T. (2021). Verbal insight revisited&#x02014;Dissociable neurocognitive processes underlying solutions accompanied by an AHA! experience with and without prior restructuring. <italic>Journal of Cognitive Psychology,</italic><italic>33</italic>(6/7), 659&#x02013;684.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Cabeza</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The influence of insight on risky decision making and nucleus accumbens activation</article-title><source>Scientific Reports</source><year>2023</year><volume>13</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>17159</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-023-44293-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37821507</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Becker, M., Yu, Y., &#x00026; Cabeza, R. (2023). The influence of insight on risky decision making and nucleus accumbens activation. <italic>Scientific Reports,</italic><italic>13</italic>(1), 17159.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37821507</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bowden</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jung-Beeman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Normative data for 144 compound remote associate problems</article-title><source>Behavior Research Methods, Instruments, &#x00026; Computers</source><year>2003</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>634</fpage><lpage>639</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3758/BF03195543</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Bowden, E. M., &#x00026; Jung-Beeman, M. (2003). Normative data for 144 compound remote associate problems. <italic>Behavior Research Methods, Instruments, &#x00026; Computers,</italic><italic>35</italic>, 634&#x02013;639.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bowers</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Regehr</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Balthazard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intuition in the context of discovery</article-title><source>Cognitive Psychology</source><year>1990</year><volume>22</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>72</fpage><lpage>110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0010-0285(90)90004-N</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Bowers, K. S., Regehr, G., Balthazard, C., &#x00026; Parker, K. (1990). Intuition in the context of discovery. <italic>Cognitive Psychology,</italic><italic>22</italic>(1), 72&#x02013;110.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Kristensen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Benthem</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Magnusson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Skaug</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Machler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bolker</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>glmmTMB balances speed and flexibility among packages for zero-inflated generalized linear mixed modeling</article-title><source>The R Journal</source><year>2017</year><volume>9</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>378</fpage><lpage>400</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.32614/RJ-2017-066</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Brooks, M. E., Kristensen, K., Van Benthem, K. J., Magnusson, A., Berg, C. W., Nielsen, A., Skaug, H. J., Machler, M., &#x00026; Bolker, B. M. (2017). glmmTMB balances speed and flexibility among packages for zero-inflated generalized linear mixed modeling. <italic>The R Journal,</italic><italic>9</italic>(2), 378&#x02013;400.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Danek</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Salvi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Moment of truth: Why Aha! Experiences are correct</article-title><source>The Journal of Creative Behavior</source><year>2020</year><volume>54</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>484</fpage><lpage>486</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jocb.380</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Danek, A. H., &#x00026; Salvi, C. (2020). Moment of truth: Why Aha! Experiences are correct. <italic>The Journal of Creative Behavior,</italic><italic>54</italic>(2), 484&#x02013;486.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Danek, A. H., &#x00026; Wiley, J. (2017). What about false insights? Deconstructing the Aha! Experience along its multiple dimensions for correct and incorrect solutions separately. <italic>Frontiers in Psychology</italic>, <italic>7</italic>, 2077. 10.3389/fpsyg.2016.02077</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Danek, A. H., &#x00026; Wiley, J. (2020). What causes the insight memory advantage? <italic>Cognition</italic>, <italic>205</italic>, 104411. 10.1016/j.cognition.2020.104411</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Danek, A. H., Fraps, T., von M&#x000fc;ller, A., Grothe, B., &#x00026; &#x000d6;llinger, M. (2014). It&#x02019;s a kind of magic&#x02014;What self-reports can reveal about the phenomenology of insight problem solving. <italic>Frontiers in Psychology</italic>, <italic>5</italic>, 1408. 10.3389/fpsyg.2014.01408</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Danek, A. H., &#x000d6;llinger, M., Fraps, T., Grothe, B., &#x00026; Flanagin, V. L. (2015). An fMRI investigation of expectation violation in magic tricks. <italic>Frontiers in Psychology,</italic><italic>6</italic>, 120976.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Danek</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Closing the gap: Connecting sudden representational change to the subjective Aha! Experience in insightful problem solving</article-title><source>Psychological Research</source><year>2020</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>119</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00426-018-0977-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29349507</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Danek, A. H., Williams, J., &#x00026; Wiley, J. (2020). Closing the gap: Connecting sudden representational change to the subjective Aha! Experience in insightful problem solving. <italic>Psychological Research,</italic><italic>84</italic>, 111&#x02013;119.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29349507</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Den Ouden, H. E., Kok, P., &#x00026; De Lange, F. P. (2012). How prediction errors shape perception, attention, and motivation. <italic>Frontiers in Psychology</italic>, <italic>3</italic>. 10.3389/fpsyg.2012.00548</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dietrich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanso</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A review of EEG, ERP, and neuroimaging studies of creativity and insight</article-title><source>Psychological Bulletin</source><year>2010</year><volume>136</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>822</fpage><lpage>848</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/a0019749</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20804237</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Dietrich, A., &#x00026; Kanso, R. (2010). A review of EEG, ERP, and neuroimaging studies of creativity and insight. <italic>Psychological Bulletin,</italic><italic>136</italic>(5), 822&#x02013;848.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20804237</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Dubey, R., Ho, M. K., Mehta, H., &#x00026; Griffiths, T. (2021). Aha! Moments correspond to meta-cognitive prediction errors. <italic>PsyArXiv Preprints.</italic>10.31234/osf.io/c5v42</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Friston</surname><given-names>Lin</given-names></name><name><surname>M., Frith, C. D., Pezzulo, G., Hobson, J. A., &#x00026; Ondobaka, S. </surname></name></person-group><article-title>Active inference, curiosity and insight</article-title><source>Neural Computation</source><year>2017</year><volume>29</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>2633</fpage><lpage>2683</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1162/neco_a_00999</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28777724</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Friston, Lin, &#x00026; M., Frith, C. D., Pezzulo, G., Hobson, J. A., &#x00026; Ondobaka, S. (2017). Active inference, curiosity and insight. <italic>Neural Computation,</italic><italic>29</italic>(10), 2633&#x02013;2683.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28777724</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holm</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A simple sequentially rejective multiple test procedure</article-title><source>Scandinavian Journal of Statistics</source><year>1979</year><volume>6</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>70</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Holm, S. (1979). A simple sequentially rejective multiple test procedure. <italic>Scandinavian Journal of Statistics,</italic><italic>6</italic>(2), 65&#x02013;70.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bentler</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fit indices in covariance structure modeling: Sensitivity to underparameterized model misspecification</article-title><source>Psychological Methods</source><year>1998</year><volume>3</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>424</fpage><lpage>453</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/1082-989X.3.4.424</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Hu, L., &#x00026; Bentler, P. M. (1998). Fit indices in covariance structure modeling: Sensitivity to underparameterized model misspecification. <italic>Psychological Methods,</italic><italic>3</italic>(4), 424&#x02013;453. 10.1037/1082-989X.3.4.424</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bentler</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cutoff criteria for fit indexes in covariance structure analysis: Conventional criteria versus new alternatives</article-title><source>Structural Equation Modeling: A Multidisciplinary Journal</source><year>1999</year><volume>6</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10705519909540118</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">Hu, L., &#x00026; Bentler, P. M. (1999). Cutoff criteria for fit indexes in covariance structure analysis: Conventional criteria versus new alternatives. <italic>Structural Equation Modeling: A Multidisciplinary Journal,</italic><italic>6</italic>(1), 1&#x02013;55.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Inquisit. (2012). <italic>Millisecond Software 4.0</italic> [Computer software]<italic>.</italic> Millisecond Software.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Jung-Beeman, M., Bowden, E. M., Haberman, J., Frymiare, J. L., Arambel-Liu, S., Greenblatt, R., Reber, P. J., &#x00026; Kounios, J. (2004). Neural activity when people solve verbal problems with insight. <italic>PLOS Biology</italic>, <italic>2</italic>(4), e97. 10.1371/journal.pbio.0020097</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kizilirmak, J. M., &#x00026; Becker, M. (2023). A cognitive neuroscience perspective on insight as a memory process: Encoding the solution. In <italic>The Routledge international handbook of creative cognition</italic> (p. 17). Routledge. 10.31234/osf.io/bevjm</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kizilirmak</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Schott</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Thuerich</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sweeney-Reed</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Richter</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Folta-Schoofs</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Richardson-Klavehn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Learning of novel semantic relationships via sudden comprehension is associated with a hippocampus-independent network</article-title><source>Consciousness and Cognition</source><year>2019</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>132</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.concog.2019.01.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30763808</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">Kizilirmak, J. M., Schott, B. H., Thuerich, H., Sweeney-Reed, C. M., Richter, A., Folta-Schoofs, K., &#x00026; Richardson-Klavehn, A. (2019). Learning of novel semantic relationships via sudden comprehension is associated with a hippocampus-independent network. <italic>Consciousness and Cognition,</italic><italic>69</italic>, 113&#x02013;132.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30763808</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kizilirmak, J. M., Serger, V., Kehl, J., &#x000d6;llinger, M., Folta-Schoofs, K., &#x00026; Richardson-Klavehn, A. (2018). Feelings-of-warmth increase more abruptly for verbal riddles solved with in contrast to without Aha! Experience. <italic>Frontiers in Psychology</italic>, <italic>9</italic>,&#x000a0;1404. 10.3389/fpsyg.2018.01404</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kizilirmak, J. M., Thuerich, H., Folta-Schoofs, K., Schott, B. H., &#x00026; Richardson-Klavehn, A. (2016). Neural correlates of learning from induced insight: A case for reward-based episodic encoding. <italic>Frontiers in Psychology</italic>, <italic>7</italic>, 1693. 10.3389/fpsyg.2016.01693</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR27" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kounios</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Beeman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The cognitive neuroscience of insight</article-title><source>Annual Review of Psychology</source><year>2014</year><volume>65</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-psych-010213-115154</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24405359</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27" publication-type="journal">Kounios, J., &#x00026; Beeman, M. (2014). The cognitive neuroscience of insight. <italic>Annual Review of Psychology,</italic><italic>65</italic>(1), 71&#x02013;93. 10.1146/annurev-psych-010213-115154<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24405359</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR28"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Laukkonen, R. E., Webb, M., Salvi, C., Tangen, J. M., Slagter, H. A., &#x00026; Schooler, J. W. (2023). Insight and the selection of ideas. <italic>Neuroscience &#x00026; Biobehavioral Reviews, 153</italic>, 105363. 10.1016/j.neubiorev.2023.105363</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR29" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Metcalfe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiebe</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intuition in insight and noninsight problem solving</article-title><source>Memory &#x00026; Cognition</source><year>1987</year><volume>15</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>238</fpage><lpage>246</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3758/BF03197722</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3600264</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29" publication-type="journal">Metcalfe, J., &#x00026; Wiebe, D. (1987). Intuition in insight and noninsight problem solving. <italic>Memory &#x00026; Cognition,</italic><italic>15</italic>(3), 238&#x02013;246.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3600264</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR30"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Oh, Y., Chesebrough, C., Erickson, B., Zhang, F., &#x00026; Kounios, J. (2020). An insight-related neural reward signal. <italic>NeuroImage</italic>, <italic>214</italic>,&#x000a0;116757. 10.1016/j.neuroimage.2020.116757</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Raven, J. C. (1960).&#x000a0;<italic>Guide to the standard progressive matrices: Sets A, B, C D and E</italic>. HK Lewis.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR32" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosseel</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>lavaan: An R package for structural equation modeling</article-title><source>Journal of Statistical Software</source><year>2012</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18637/jss.v048.i02</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32" publication-type="journal">Rosseel, Y. (2012). lavaan: An R package for structural equation modeling. <italic>Journal of Statistical Software,</italic><italic>48</italic>, 1&#x02013;36.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR33"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR33" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rouhani</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Niv</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwabe</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiple routes to enhanced memory for emotionally relevant events</article-title><source>Trends in Cognitive Sciences</source><year>2023</year><volume>27</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>867</fpage><lpage>882</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tics.2023.06.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37479601</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR33" publication-type="journal">Rouhani, N., Niv, Y., Frank, M. J., &#x00026; Schwabe, L. (2023). Multiple routes to enhanced memory for emotionally relevant events. <italic>Trends in Cognitive Sciences,</italic><italic>27</italic>(9), 867&#x02013;882.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37479601</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR34"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR34" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salvi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bricolo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kounios</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowden</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Beeman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Insight solutions are correct more often than analytic solutions</article-title><source>Thinking &#x00026; Reasoning</source><year>2016</year><volume>22</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>443</fpage><lpage>460</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13546783.2016.1141798</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27667960</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR34" publication-type="journal">Salvi, C., Bricolo, E., Kounios, J., Bowden, E., &#x00026; Beeman, M. (2016). Insight solutions are correct more often than analytic solutions. <italic>Thinking &#x00026; Reasoning,</italic><italic>22</italic>(4), 443&#x02013;460.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27667960</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR35"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR35" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Savinova</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Korovkin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Surprise! Why insightful solution is pleasurable</article-title><source>Journal of Intelligence</source><year>2022</year><volume>10</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>98</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jintelligence10040098</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36412778</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR35" publication-type="journal">Savinova, A., &#x00026; Korovkin, S. (2022). Surprise! Why insightful solution is pleasurable. <italic>Journal of Intelligence,</italic><italic>10</italic>(4), 98.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36412778</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR36"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Schermelleh-Engel, K., Kerwer, M., &#x00026; Klein, A. G. (2014). Evaluation of model fit in nonlinear multilevel structural equation modeling. <italic>Frontiers in Psychology</italic>, <italic>5</italic>,&#x000a0;181. 10.3389/fpsyg.2014.00181</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sutton, R. S., &#x00026; Barto, A. G. (2018). <italic>Reinforcement learning: An introduction</italic>. MIT press.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR38" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sladky</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Luft</surname><given-names>CDB</given-names></name><name><surname>Willinger</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Banissy</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhattacharya</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Windischberger</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ultra-high-field fMRI insights on insight: Neural correlates of the Aha!-moment</article-title><source>Human Brain Mapping</source><year>2018</year><volume>39</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>3241</fpage><lpage>3252</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hbm.24073</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29665228</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR38" publication-type="journal">Tik, M., Sladky, R., Luft, C. D. B., Willinger, D., Hoffmann, A., Banissy, M. J., Bhattacharya, J., &#x00026; Windischberger, C. (2018). Ultra-high-field fMRI insights on insight: Neural correlates of the Aha!-moment. <italic>Human Brain Mapping,</italic><italic>39</italic>(8), 3241&#x02013;3252.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29665228</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR39"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR39" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Topolinski</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Reber</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gaining insight into the &#x0201c;Aha&#x0201d; experience</article-title><source>Current Directions in Psychological Science</source><year>2010</year><volume>19</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>402</fpage><lpage>405</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0963721410388803</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR39" publication-type="journal">Topolinski, S., &#x00026; Reber, R. (2010). Gaining insight into the &#x0201c;Aha&#x0201d; experience. <italic>Current Directions in Psychological Science,</italic><italic>19</italic>(6), 402&#x02013;405.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR40"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Webb, M. E., Little, D. R., &#x00026; Cropper, S. J. (2016). Insight is not in the problem: Investigating insight in problem solving across task types. <italic>Frontiers in Psychology</italic>, <italic>7</italic>. 10.3389/fpsyg.2016.01424</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR41" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Little</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Cropper</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Once more with feeling: Normative data for the aha experience in insight and noninsight problems</article-title><source>Behavior Research Methods</source><year>2018</year><volume>50</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>2035</fpage><lpage>2056</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3758/s13428-017-0972-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29052169</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR41" publication-type="journal">Webb, M. E., Little, D. R., Cropper, Simon, &#x00026; J. (2018). Once more with feeling: Normative data for the aha experience in insight and noninsight problems. <italic>Behavior Research Methods,</italic><italic>50</italic>(5), 2035&#x02013;2056. 10.3758/s13428-017-0972-9<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29052169</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article>