<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="abstract"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Eur Psychiatry</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Eur Psychiatry</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">EPA</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>European Psychiatry</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0924-9338</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1778-3585</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11862524</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1192/j.eurpsy.2024.1276</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="other">EPV0611</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S0924933824012768</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Abstract</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="section"><subject>e-Poster Viewing</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Between Delusions and Borders: Diagnosing Delusional Disorder in Migratory Contexts</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Carrasqueira</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2858" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor1130" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2859" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Marques</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2858" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2858" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Laureano</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2858" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff2858"><sup>1</sup>Psychiatry and Mental Health Department, <institution>Hospital Centre of Leiria</institution>, <city>Leiria</city></aff><aff id="aff2859"><sup>2</sup>Child and adolescent psychiatry, <institution>Coimbra Hospital and University Centre</institution>, <city>Coimbra</city>, <country>Portugal</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1130"><label>*</label>Corresponding author.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="collection" iso-8601-date="2024-04"><month>4</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>67</volume><issue seq="1251">Suppl 1</issue><issue-title content-type="special_issue">Abstracts of the 32nd European Congress of Psychiatry</issue-title><fpage>S613</fpage><lpage>S613</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2024</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Author(s)</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article, distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution licence (<uri xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</uri>), which permits unrestricted re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="S0924933824012768a.pdf"/><abstract><sec id="sec6793"><title>Introduction</title><p>
The mental health of immigrants is a significant, yet often overlooked, aspect of public health. This case study highlights the intersection of migration and mental health, focusing on a patient with delusional disorder. It is particularly relevant for psychiatrists due to the unique challenges in diagnosing and treating mental health conditions in migrant populations, who often face cultural, linguistic, and systemic barriers in accessing care.</p></sec><sec id="sec6794"><title>Objectives</title><p>The primary objective of this case study is to elucidate the diagnostic and clinical challenges encountered in managing delusional disorder in a migrant patient. The case study presented aims to provide insights into how delusional beliefs can precipitate and perpetuate the process of migration.</p></sec><sec id="sec6795"><title>Methods</title><p>
The case study was developed through comprehensive psychiatric interviews during the patient&#x02019;s stay in a Psychiatric Inpatient Unit, supplemented by a targeted literature review on PubMed using &#x0201c;delusion disorder&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;immigration&#x0201d; as keywords.</p></sec><sec id="sec6796"><title>Results</title><p>
The patient, a 44-year-old Indian male, was a functional young adult until 2007 when he began exhibiting symptoms of delusional disorder. His delusions progressively evolved from local scenarios to national and eventually to a global scale. The initial delusions were focused on personal and professional conspiracies within his home country, leading to his first internal migration. As the condition worsened, his delusions expanded, fueling a belief in a widespread conspiracy that transcended national borders. This escalation of delusional beliefs became the primary motivation for the patient&#x02019;s international migration. He changed countries four times, each move driven by an attempt to escape the perceived threats and conspiracies associated with his delusional disorder. The patient&#x02019;s journey through various countries was a direct result of the intensifying nature of his condition.</p></sec><sec id="sec6797"><title>Conclusions</title><p>This case study accentuates the profound impact that a delusional disorder can have as a driver and catalyst of international migration, influencing the individual&#x02019;s decision-making process and shaping the migratory experiences. It emphasizes the necessity for psychiatrists to consider the unique socio-cultural contexts of migrant patients in diagnosis and treatment. The case study advocates for a comprehensive treatment approach, integrating psychiatric care with a nuanced understanding of the migrant&#x02019;s experiences and challenges. This multifaceted approach is crucial in addressing the complex needs of patients with delusional disorder in migrant populations.</p></sec><sec id="sec6798"><title>Disclosure of Interest</title><p>None Declared</p></sec></abstract><counts><page-count count="1"/></counts></article-meta></front></article>