<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Public Health</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Public Health</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2296-2565</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40401054</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12092466</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2025.1549830</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Public Health</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Long-term PM2.5 exposure and new-onset lung diseases among middle-aged and older adults in China: a retrospective cohort study from CHARLS</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Xiaojun</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/formal-analysis/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Kai</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/formal-analysis/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Daihua</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/124423/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Jingjing</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2929880/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/formal-analysis/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/methodology/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Department of General Surgery, Xi&#x02019;an No.3 Hospital, The Affiliated Hospital of Northwest University</institution>, <addr-line>Xi&#x02019;an</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Department of Intensive Care Unit, Xi&#x02019;an No.3 Hospital, The Affiliated Hospital of Northwest University</institution>, <addr-line>Xi&#x02019;an</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by" id="fn0002"><p>Edited by: Nurzawani Md. Sofwan, Universiti Teknologi MARA Sarawak Branch, Malaysia</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by" id="fn0003"><p>Reviewed by: Richa Mishra, Washington University in St. Louis, United States</p><p>Mohd Faiz Ibrahim, Ministry of Health, Malaysia</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Jingjing Li, <email>15389273312@163.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>07</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>13</volume><elocation-id>1549830</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2025 Wu, Zhang, Yu and Li.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Wu, Zhang, Yu and Li</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec id="sec1"><title>Background</title><p>Air pollution caused by ambient fine particulate matter (&#x02264; 2.5&#x0202f;&#x003bc;m) adversely affects human health. Previous studies have shown that PM2.5 exposure increases the risk of lung diseases. However, the relationship between long-term PM2.5 exposure and new-onset lung diseases among middle-aged and older adults in China is still unclear.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>Methods</title><p>We conducted a retrospective cohort study through the China Health and Retirement Longitudinal Study (CHARLS) and Science Data Bank (ScienceDB). The logistic regression model and restricted cubic spline (RCS) were used to explore the relationship between long-term PM2.5 exposure and new-onset lung diseases. To further increase the robustness of the results, we performed sensitivity and subgroup analyses.</p></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>Results</title><p>A total of 10,707 patients were included in this study. The 10,707 patients were divided into two groups: without new-onset lung diseases (<italic>n</italic>&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;9,019) and with new-onset lung diseases (<italic>n</italic>&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;1,688). The results of multivariate analysis showed that per 1 ug/m<sup>3</sup> increase in annual PM2.5 concentration, the risk of new lung diseases increased by 0.3%. The results of the RCS showed that PM2.5 exposure increased the risk of new-onset lung diseases more significantly when the annual PM2.5 concentration was greater than 48.5 ug/m<sup>3</sup>. Sensitivity analysis and subgroup analysis also confirmed the reliability of the results.</p></sec><sec id="sec4"><title>Conclusion</title><p>PM2.5 exposure increases the risk of new-onset lung diseases among middle-aged and old adults in China, especially when the concentration of PM2.5&#x0202f;&#x0003e;&#x0202f;48.5 ug/m<sup>3</sup>. Our study established an empirical foundation for refining PM2.5 emission regulations, developing age-stratified screening protocols for incident pulmonary diseases, and advancing mechanistic investigations into PM2.5-induced lung pathology.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>long-term</kwd><kwd>PM2.5 exposure</kwd><kwd>new-onset lung diseases</kwd><kwd>middle-aged and older adults</kwd><kwd>China</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><funding-statement>The author(s) declare that no financial support was received for the research and/or publication of this article.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="4"/><table-count count="4"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="34"/><page-count count="8"/><word-count count="4890"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>section-at-acceptance</meta-name><meta-value>Environmental Health and Exposome</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec5"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p>Air pollution caused by ambient fine particulate matter (PM2.5) has been widely recognized as a critical threat to global public health, with well-documented sources including industrial emissions, vehicle exhaust, and fossil fuel combustion (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1&#x02013;3</xref>). Epidemiological evidence consistently demonstrates that PM2.5 exposure elevates risks of various pulmonary pathologies. For instance, longitudinal data from Wang et al. (<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>) revealed an 11% increased emphysema risk per 2&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/m<sup>3</sup> PM2.5 increment over a decade, while Nakhjirgan et al.&#x02019;s (<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>) cohort study identified a significant association between PM2.5 exposure and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) development [HR&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;1.032, 95% CI: 1.004&#x02013;1.061] &#x02013; a leading contributor to PM2.5-related mortality worldwide (<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5&#x02013;7</xref>). Furthermore, emerging evidence links PM2.5 exposure to asthma exacerbation, lung carcinogenesis, and accelerated progression of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis (<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8&#x02013;10</xref>). Importantly, longitudinal declines in pulmonary function parameters such as forced vital capacity (FVC) and forced expiratory volume in 1&#x0202f;s (FEV&#x02081;) have been observed across all age groups exposed to chronic PM2.5 pollution (<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). Middle-aged and older adults represent a vulnerable population due to cumulative lifetime exposure and age-related physiological decline, including diminished pulmonary reserve and impaired pollutant clearance (<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). This susceptibility is particularly concerning in China, where severe PM2.5 pollution intersects with a substantial aging population (<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>).</p><p>The China Health and Retirement Longitudinal Study (CHARLS) is a nationwide study that started in 2011. It includes data from more than 17,000 people nationwide and makes the data public after every 2&#x02013;3&#x0202f;years of follow-up (<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). CHARLS has now been updated to 2020 (<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). The Science Data Bank (ScienceDB), developed by the computer network information center of the Chinese Academy of Science, can provide scientific data-sharing services to researchers (<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). This study aimed to explore the relationship between long-term PM2.5 exposure and new-onset lung disease among middle-aged and older adults in China through CHARLS and ScienceDB. This study investigated age-specific risks of new-onset lung diseases associated with varying levels of PM2.5 exposure, providing critical evidence to inform air quality management policies, offering references for developing age-specific screening protocols for emerging pulmonary conditions, and supporting empirical foundations for mechanistic investigations into PM2.5-related pulmonary pathogenesis.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="sec6"><label>2</label><title>Methods</title><sec id="sec7"><label>2.1</label><title>Study design and inclusion of patients</title><p>We conducted this study using the CHARLS. Since most cities in China began the detection of PM2.5 in 2013, this study started with CHARLS 2013. This retrospective cohort study enrolled participants meeting strict inclusion/exclusion criteria, categorizing them into Patients with new-onset lung diseases and without new-onset lung diseases groups. Risk factor analysis for new-onset lung disease was performed after baseline data comparison (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Schematic outline of this study.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpubh-13-1549830-g001" position="float"/></fig><p>Inclusion criteria of patients were as follows: (1) age &#x02265; 45&#x0202f;years, (2) patients without lung diseases in 2013, (3) patients with PM2.5 and follow-up data until 2020.</p><p>Exclusion criteria of patients were as follows: (1) age &#x0003c; 45&#x0202f;years, (2) patients with lung diseases in 2013, (3) patients without other related data (gender, insurance, etc.), (4) patients without follow-up data until 2020, and (5) patients without PM2.5 data.</p></sec><sec id="sec8"><label>2.2</label><title>Variable extraction</title><p>CHARLS provides several questionnaires from which we can obtain relevant data. The demographic background questionnaire included age, marital status, education level, and location data. The health status and functioning questionnaire provides data on gender, lung diseases (chronic bronchitis, emphysema, and pulmonary heart disease, but not lung cancer), chronic diseases (defined as one or more of hypertension, diabetes, coronary heart disease, asthma, arthritis, stroke, liver disease, kidney disease, etc.), smoking, and drinking. Insurance questionnaires provide data on insurance (Participation in insurance is defined as enrollment in at least one type of coverage, including but not limited to medical insurance, commercial insurance, or other analogous insurance schemes). The exit questionnaire provides data on follow-up information. New-onset lung diseases (chronic bronchitis, emphysema, and pulmonary heart disease, et.al, but not lung cancer) were defined as cases newly diagnosed during follow-up among participants without a prior history of lung disease. New-onset lung diseases and chronic diseases were diagnosed based on clinic visits and doctor-diagnosed conditions.</p></sec><sec id="sec9"><label>2.3</label><title>PM2.5 data</title><p>We obtained PM2.5 data from the Science Data Bank (ScienceDB).<xref rid="fn0001" ref-type="fn"><sup>1</sup></xref> Liu et al. (<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>) collected global ground-based PM2.5 concentration data at Washington University. The annual average PM2.5 concentration data set of 342 administrative units in China can be obtained through ArcGIS software. The dataset was linearly correlated with the data published by the Chinese government, and the goodness of fit (R<sup>2</sup>) was above 0.8.</p></sec><sec id="sec10"><label>2.4</label><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>In this study, count data were described using numbers and percentages. A baseline comparison of counting data was performed using the chi-square test, and grade data was performed using the Mann&#x02013;Whitney U test. The logistic regression model was used for univariate and multivariate analysis, with PM2.5 as the measurement data. Restricted cubic spline (RCS) was used to further explore the relationship between PM2.5 exposure and new-onset lung diseases. We performed sensitivity analysis through three models and subgroup analysis of age and chronic disease variables to further increase the robustness of the results. Statistical analyses were performed using SPSS 23.0 (SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, USA) and R package (version 4.2.1).&#x0201d;rms&#x0201d; package was used to perform RCS in R Studio. <italic>p</italic>&#x0202f;&#x0003c;&#x0202f;0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec11"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><sec id="sec12"><label>3.1</label><title>Inclusion of patients</title><p>CHARLS included a total of 18,612 individuals in 2013. We excluded 1,881 individuals who had lung disease in 2013. After combining the data from the ScienceDB through address information, 3,810 individuals without PM2.5 information were excluded. Then, we excluded 1,227 individuals without related information, and the remaining 11,654 patients were followed up. The endpoint of follow-up was the occurrence of new-onset lung diseases, and the follow-up period was from the time of inclusion to the occurrence of the endpoint event. After excluding 987 patients lost to follow-up, we finally included 10,707 patients in 2020. The 10,707 patients were divided into two groups based on whether the endpoint event occurred: without new-onset lung diseases (n&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;9,019) and with new-onset lung diseases (<italic>n</italic>&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;1,688) (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Flow chart of patient inclusion in this study.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpubh-13-1549830-g002" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec13"><label>3.2</label><title>Comparison of baseline data</title><p>Patients with new-onset lung diseases had a higher proportion of age &#x02265; 65 (35.2% vs. 29.3%, <italic>p</italic>&#x0202f;&#x0003c;&#x0202f;0.001), more male (51.3% vs. 45.7%, <italic>p</italic>&#x0202f;&#x0003c;&#x0202f;0.001), more single (14.5% vs. 12.0%, <italic>p</italic>&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.005), more illiteracy (49.9% vs. 45.9%, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c;&#x0202f;0.001), more smokers (51.0% vs. 42.0%, <italic>p</italic>&#x0202f;&#x0003c;&#x0202f;0.001), and more drinkers (49.8% vs. 44.4%, <italic>p</italic>&#x0202f;&#x0003c;&#x0202f;0.001), more chronic diseases (80.7% vs. 67.2%, <italic>p</italic>&#x0202f;&#x0003c;&#x0202f;0.001) (<xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Basic information in the baseline.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristics</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Without lung diseases</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">With lung diseases</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>p</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number (%)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,707 (100%)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9,019 (84.2%)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,688 (15.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (<italic>n</italic>, %)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;65</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7,473 (69.8%)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,380 (70.7%)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,093 (64.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;65</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,234 (30.2%)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,639 (29.3%)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">595 (35.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender (<italic>n</italic>, %)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,984 (46.5%)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,118 (45.7%)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">866 (51.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,723 (53.5%)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,901 (54.3%)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">822 (48.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Marital status (<italic>n</italic>, %)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,325 (12.4%)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,081 (12.0%)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">244 (14.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Married</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9,382 (87.6%)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7,938 (88.0%)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,444 (85.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Residence (<italic>n</italic>, %)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.052</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rural</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,933 (64.8%)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,805 (64.4%)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,128 (66.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urban</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,774 (35.2%)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,214 (35.6%)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">560 (33.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Educational level (<italic>n</italic>, %)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Illiteracy</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,981 (46.5%)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,139 (45.9%)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">842 (49.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primary school</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,298 (21.5%)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,906 (21.1%)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">392 (23.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Middle school</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,244 (21.0%)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,943 (21.5%)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">301 (17.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High school and above</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,184 (11.1%)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,031 (11.4%)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">153 (9.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking (yes, <italic>n</italic>, %)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,662 (43.5%)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,786 (42.0%)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">876 (51.9%)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drinking (yes, <italic>n</italic>, %)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,846 (45.3%)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,006 (44.4%)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">840 (49.8%)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insurance (yes, <italic>n</italic>, %)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,483 (97.9%)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8,832 (97.9%)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,651 (97.8%)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.755</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chronic diseases (yes, <italic>n</italic>, %)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7,426 (69.4%)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,063 (67.2%)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,363 (80.7%)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec14"><label>3.3</label><title>Univariate and multivariate analysis</title><p>The results of univariate analysis showed that there were statistical differences in age, gender, marital status, educational level, smoking, drinking, and chronic diseases (<italic>p</italic>-values lower than 0.05). However, there was no statistical difference in PM2.5 exposure (measurement data) (OR&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;1.003, 95% CI: 0.999&#x02013;1.006, <italic>p</italic>&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.104). Even if it was not statistically significant, we conducted a multivariate analysis of the PM2.5 variables using measurement data (<xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). The results of multivariate analysis showed that age &#x02265; 65&#x0202f;years (OR: 1.130, 95% CI: 1.004&#x02013;1.2772, <italic>p</italic>&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.042), smoking (OR: 1.583, 95% CI: 1.351&#x02013;1.855, <italic>p</italic>&#x0202f;&#x0003c;&#x0202f;0.001), chronic diseases (OR: 2.028, 95% CI: 1.781&#x02013;2.309, <italic>p</italic>&#x0202f;&#x0003c;&#x0202f;0.001), PM2.5 exposure (OR: 1.003, 95% CI: 1.000&#x02013;1.007, <italic>p</italic>&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.037) increased risks of new-onset lung diseases and more educational levels decreased risk of new-onset lung diseases: middle school (OR:0.741, 95%CI: 0.637&#x02013;0.863, <italic>p</italic>&#x0202f;&#x0003c;&#x0202f;0.001), high school and above (OR:0.706, 95%CI:0.581&#x02013;0.858, <italic>p</italic>&#x0202f;&#x0003c;&#x0202f;0.001) (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Univariate and Multivariate logistic regression analysis.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristics</th><th align="center" valign="top" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Univariate</th><th align="center" valign="top" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Multivariate</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95% CI)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>p</italic>
</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95% CI)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>p</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (vs. &#x0003c;65)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.316 (1.179&#x02013;1.469)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.130 (1.004&#x02013;1.272)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.042</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender (vs. Female)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.798 (0.719&#x02013;0.885)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.052 (0.886&#x02013;1.249)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.561</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Marital status (vs. Single)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.806 (0.694&#x02013;0.936)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.886 (0.755&#x02013;1.040)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.138</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Residence (vs. Rural)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.897 (0.803&#x02013;1.001)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.052</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Educational level (vs. Illiteracy)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primary school</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.011 (0.886&#x02013;1.153)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.871</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.946 (0.825&#x02013;1.085)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.428</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Middle school</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.762 (0.661&#x02013;0.878)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.741 (0.637&#x02013;0.863)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High school and above</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.729 (0.606&#x02013;0.878)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.706 (0.581&#x02013;0.858)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking (vs. No)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.491 (1.344&#x02013;1.655)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.583 (1.351&#x02013;1.855)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drinking (vs. No)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.240 (1.117&#x02013;1.376)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.111 (0.983&#x02013;1.256)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.093</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insurance (vs. No)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.945 (0.661&#x02013;1.350)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.755</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chronic diseases (vs. No)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.045 (1.798&#x02013;2.326)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.028 (1.781&#x02013;2.309)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PM2.5</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.003 (0.999&#x02013;1.006)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.104</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.003 (1.000&#x02013;1.007)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.037</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>OR, odd ratio; CI, confidence interval.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Forest plot of multivariate analysis. OR, odd ratio; CI, confidence interval.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpubh-13-1549830-g003" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec15"><label>3.4</label><title>Results of RCS</title><p>RCS balance flexibility and stability by constraining tail linearity, avoid overfitting through low-degree polynomials, enable intuitive visualization, and support statistical inference, enhancing clinical interpretability. Then we used the RCS model to further explore the relationship between PM2.5 exposure and new-onset lung diseases. After adjusting for multiple variables, the results of RCS showed a positive association between PM2.5 exposure and new-onset lung diseases when the concentration of PM2.5&#x0202f;&#x0003e;&#x0202f;48.5 ug/m<sup>3</sup> (P of non-linearity&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.004) (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Restricted cubic spline of relationship between PM2.5 and new-onset lung diseases. Adjusting by age, gender, marital status, residence, educational level, smoking, drinking, insurance and chronic diseases. OR, odd ratio; CI, confidence interval.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpubh-13-1549830-g004" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec16"><label>3.5</label><title>Results of the sensitivity analysis</title><p>We explored the relationship between PM2.5 exposure and new-onset lung diseases through multiple models in the form of measurement data and count data (Q1: PM2.5&#x0202f;&#x0003c;&#x0202f;48.5 ug/m<sup>3</sup>; Q2: PM2.5&#x0202f;&#x02265;&#x0202f;48.5 ug/m<sup>3</sup>), respectively to further increase the robustness of the results (<xref rid="tab3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Model 1: adjusted by age, gender, marital status, residence, educational level; Model 2: additional adjusted by smoking and drinking; Model 3: additional adjusted by insurance and chronic diseases.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Association between PM2.5 and new-onset lung diseases in different model.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Characteristics</th><th align="center" valign="top" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Model 1</th><th align="center" valign="top" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Model 2</th><th align="center" valign="top" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Model 3</th></tr><tr><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95%CI)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>p</italic>
</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95%CI)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>p</italic>
</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95%CI)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>p</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PM2.5</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.004 (1.000&#x02013;1.007)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.031</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.003 (1.000&#x02013;1.007)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.038</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.003 (1.000&#x02013;1.007)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.037</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PM2.5 (vs.Q1)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.232 (1.109&#x02013;1.369)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.228 (1.104&#x02013;1.364)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.227 (1.103&#x02013;1.365)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>OR, odd ratio; CI, confidence interval. Model 1: adjusted by age, gender, marital status, residence, educational level; Model 2: additional adjusted by smoking and drinking; Model 3: additional adjusted by insurance and chronic diseases (Q1: PM2.5 &#x0003c; 48.5ug/m<sup>3</sup>; Q2:PM2.5 &#x02265; 48.5ug/m<sup>3</sup>).</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>All models showed that PM2.5 exposure increased the risk of new-onset lung diseases when PM2.5 was used as measurement data. Model 1 (OR: 1.004, 95% CI: 1.000&#x02013;1.007, <italic>p</italic>&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.031). Model 2 (OR: 1.003, 95% CI: 1.000&#x02013;1.007, <italic>p</italic>&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.038). Model 3 (OR: 1.003, 95% CI: 1.000&#x02013;1.007, <italic>p</italic>&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.037).</p><p>All models also showed that PM2.5 exposure increased the risk of new-onset lung diseases when PM2.5 was used as count data (Q1 as reference). Model 1 (OR: 1.232, 95% CI: 1.109&#x02013;1.369, <italic>p</italic>&#x0202f;&#x0003c;&#x0202f;0.001). Model 2 (OR: 1.228, 95% CI: 1.104&#x02013;1.364, <italic>p</italic>&#x0202f;&#x0003c;&#x0202f;0.001). Model 3 (OR: 1.227, 95% CI: 1.103&#x02013;1.365, <italic>p</italic>&#x0202f;&#x0003c;&#x0202f;0.001).</p></sec><sec id="sec17"><label>3.6</label><title>Results of the subgroup analysis</title><p>We also used three models for subgroup analysis in age and smoking variables, with PM2.5 as the measurement and count data (Q1: PM2.5&#x0202f;&#x0003c;&#x0202f;48.5 ug/m<sup>3</sup>; Q2: PM2.5&#x0202f;&#x02265;&#x0202f;48.5 ug/m<sup>3</sup>), respectively (<xref rid="tab4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). The P results for interaction showed no interaction (<italic>p</italic>&#x0202f;&#x0003e;&#x0202f;0.05).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Subgroup analysis of the association between PM2.5 and new-onset lung diseases by different models.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristics</th><th align="center" valign="top" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Model 1</th><th align="center" valign="top" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Model 2</th><th align="center" valign="top" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Model 3</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95%CI)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>p</italic>
</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95%CI)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>p</italic>
</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95%CI)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>p</italic>
</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P for interaction</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="8" rowspan="1">PM2.5 (Measurement)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.090</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;65</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.002 (0.998&#x02013;1.006)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.382</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.002 (0.998&#x02013;1.006)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.382</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.002 (0.998&#x02013;1.006)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.302</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;65</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.007 (1.002&#x02013;1.013)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.012</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.007 (1.001&#x02013;1.013)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.017</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.007 (1.001&#x02013;1.012)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.021</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.071</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000 (0.995&#x02013;1.005)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.986</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000 (0.996&#x02013;1.005)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.897</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000 (0.996&#x02013;1.005)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.874</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.006 (1.002&#x02013;1.011)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.006 (1.002&#x02013;1.011)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.006 (1.002&#x02013;1.011)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="8" rowspan="1">PM2.5 (vs.Q1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.222</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;65</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.180 (1.036&#x02013;1.344)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.186 (1.040&#x02013;1.351)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.198 (1.050&#x02013;1.366)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;65</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.342 (1.120&#x02013;1.607)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.322 (1.103&#x02013;1.585)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.310 (1.092&#x02013;1.571)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.451</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.173 (1.010&#x02013;1.363)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.037</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.190 (1.023&#x02013;1.383)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.024</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.188 (1.020&#x02013;1.382)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.026</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.279 (1.101&#x02013;1.485)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.278 (1.101&#x02013;1.484)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.283 (1.104&#x02013;1.491)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>OR, odd ratio; CI, confidence interval. Model 1: adjusted by age, gender, marital status, residence, educational level; Model 2: additional adjusted by smoking and drinking; Model 3: additional adjusted by insurance and chronic diseases (Q1: PM2.5 &#x0003c; 48.5ug/m<sup>3</sup>; Q2:PM2.5 &#x02265; 48.5ug/m<sup>3</sup>).</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>PM2.5 as measurement data: when age &#x02265; 65&#x0202f;years, PM2.5 exposure increases the risks of new-onset lung diseases (<italic>p</italic>&#x0202f;&#x0003c;&#x0202f;0.05). In subgroups without smoking, PM2.5 exposure increased the risks of new-onset lung diseases (<italic>p</italic>&#x0202f;&#x0003c;&#x0202f;0.05).</p><p>PM2.5 as count data: PM2.5 exposure increased the risks of new-onset lung diseases (Q1 as a reference) in both subgroups of age &#x0003c; 65&#x0202f;years (<italic>p</italic>&#x0202f;&#x0003c;&#x0202f;0.05) and age &#x02265; 65&#x0202f;years (<italic>p</italic>&#x0202f;&#x0003c;&#x0202f;0.05). In subgroups with and without smoking, PM2.5 exposure increased the risks of new-onset lung diseases (Q1 as a reference) (<italic>p</italic>&#x0202f;&#x0003c;&#x0202f;0.05).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec18"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p>PM2.5 exposure increases the risks of chronic lung diseases, which has been widely reported in high-income countries (<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20&#x02013;22</xref>). However, PM2.5 detection in China starts late, and the relationship between PM2.5 exposure and new-onset lung diseases among middle-aged and older adults remains unclear.</p><p>Our findings demonstrated a significant association between long-term PM2.5 exposure and the incidence of new-onset lung diseases among middle-aged and older adults. The results of univariate analysis showed PM2.5 exposure did not increase the risk of new-onset lung diseases (<italic>p</italic>&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.104). The results of multivariate analysis showed that per 1 ug/m<sup>3</sup> increase in annual PM2.5 concentration, the risk of new lung diseases increased by 0.3%(<italic>p</italic>&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.037). This phenomenon may occur because the effect of PM2.5 was masked by age. As age increased, cumulative exposure to PM2.5 became longer. When age and PM2.5 were included together in a multivariate analysis, the OR for age decreased, and the effect of PM2.5 was no longer obscured by age. The results of the RCS showed that PM2.5 exposure increased the risk of new-onset lung diseases more significantly when the annual PM2.5 concentration was greater than 48.5 ug/m<sup>3</sup>. Sensitivity analysis and subgroup analysis also confirmed the reliability of the results.</p><p>Our results were consistent with previous research (<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>): PM2.5 exposure elevated the risk of respiratory diseases such as asthma. Our study delved deeper into the dose&#x02013;response relationship between PM2.5 exposure levels and pulmonary outcomes, proposing a threshold of 48.5&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/m<sup>3</sup> as a critical upper limit for targeted air quality regulation. While current annual PM2.5 levels in high-income countries generally remain below 48.5&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/m<sup>3</sup>, our findings hold particular relevance for informing region-specific policy formulation in low-and middle-income countries (LMICs). China&#x02019;s national standards (annual: 35&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/m<sup>3</sup>, 24-h: 75&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/m<sup>3</sup>) reflect substantial progress in air quality governance (<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). However, persistent disparities in regional development within China necessitate flexibility. This study provides evidence-based phased implementation strategies for provinces facing challenges in achieving national targets, supporting the implementation of regionally adaptable interim standards during transitional phases.</p><p>Some mechanism studies may explain the results: According to Fan et al. (<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>), PM2.5 exposure enhanced mitophagy via triphosphopyridine nucleotide oxidase 4 (NOX4)/ transcription factor nuclear factor erythroid 2-related factor 2 (Nrf2) redox imbalance, further increasing susceptibility to acute exacerbation of COPD (AECOPD). Research by Guo et al. (<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>) showed PM2.5 exposure up-regulated the expression of methyltransferase-like protein 16 (METTL16), subsequently altered N6-methyladenosine (m6A) modification, and finally microvascular injury in COPD. According to Zhang et al. (<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>), PM2.5 exposure induced lung injury in Wistar rats via activating AMP-activated protein kinase (AMPK)&#x02014;sirtuin 1 (SIRT1)&#x02014;peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor-<italic>&#x003b3;</italic> coactivator 1&#x003b1; (PGC-1&#x003b1;) pathway. In conclusion, PM2.5 plays an important role in accelerating the progression of lung diseases by activating reactive oxygen species (ROS) and inflammation (<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29&#x02013;31</xref>). Therefore, previous studies have provided new ideas for treating lung diseases through the anti-inflammatory and antioxidant effects of Resveratrol, Biochanin A Polyphenols, etc. (<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32&#x02013;34</xref>).</p><p>This study advanced environmental epidemiology by establishing a novel age-stratified exposure-response framework. Particularly, the identification of differential susceptibility patterns across age deciles provided granular evidence for refining air quality standards, (b) necessitated age-optimized early detection strategies in clinical practice, and (c) pinpointed critical windows for molecular epidemiological research on PM2.5-induced pulmonary damage.</p><p>There were some drawbacks to this study. First, this study was retrospective, and there were inevitable biases in the data collection process. Second, we explored only the effect of outdoor PM2.5 exposure on new-onset lung diseases. However, the impact of indoor PM2.5 could not be investigated because the data could not be obtained. The relationship between indoor PM2.5 exposure and new-onset lung diseases warrants further investigation in future studies. Finally, the PM2.5 data used in this study may not fully reflect the true PM2.5 exposure of an individual, as the location of an individual may vary. Nevertheless, our findings provided critical evidence-based insights to inform the formulation of regionally adaptable PM2.5 emission standards.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec19"><label>5</label><title>Conclusion</title><p>Our study identifies a critical PM2.5 threshold of 48.5&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/m<sup>3</sup> for incident pulmonary diseases in Chinese middle-aged and older adults. This threshold aligns with regional pollution disparities and aging-specific vulnerabilities, suggesting its utility as a transitional target for provinces struggling to meet China&#x02019;s current national standard (35&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/m<sup>3</sup>). Implementing regionally adaptive policies. Mechanistic research associated with PM2.5 exposure and new-onset lung diseases also should be performed to guide clinical prevention and treatment.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors would like to thank the China Health and Retirement Longitudinal Study team and Science Data Bank team for providing the data.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="fn0001"><p>
<sup>1</sup>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.scidb.cn/en" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.scidb.cn/en</ext-link>
</p></fn></fn-group><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="sec20"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>The original contributions presented in the study are included in the article/supplementary material, further inquiries can be directed to the corresponding author.</p></sec><sec sec-type="ethics-statement" id="sec21"><title>Ethics statement</title><p>The studies involving humans were approved by Institutional Review Board (IRB) of Peking University. The IRB approval number for the main household survey including anthropometrics is 00001052-11015. The studies were conducted in accordance with the local legislation and institutional requirements. Written informed consent for participation was not required from the participants or the participants&#x02019; legal guardians/next of kin because the data we used in this manuscript can be obtained from a public and available dataset. The manuscript presents research on animals that do not require ethical approval for their study.</p></sec><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="sec22"><title>Author contributions</title><p>XW: Formal analysis, Writing &#x02013; original draft. KZ: Formal analysis, Writing &#x02013; original draft. DY: Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing. JL: Data curation, Formal analysis, Methodology, Writing &#x02013; original draft, Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="sec24"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="ai-statement" id="sec25"><title>Generative AI statement</title><p>The author(s) declare that no Gen AI was used in the creation of this manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="sec26"><title>Publisher&#x02019;s note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rojas-Rueda</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Alsufyani</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Herbst</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>AlBalawi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Alsukait</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Alomran</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Ambient particulate matter burden of disease in the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia</article-title>. <source>Environ Res</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>197</volume>:<fpage>111036</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2021.111036</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33775683</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Brauer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Burnett</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The effect of air pollution on deaths, disease burden, and life expectancy across China and its provinces, 1990-2017: an analysis for the global burden of disease study 2017</article-title>. <source>Lancet Planet Health</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>e386</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>98</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2542-5196(20)30161-3</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32818429</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Busch</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Cifuentes</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cabrera</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Chronic exposure to fine particles (PM2.5) and mortality: evidence from Chile</article-title>. <source>Environ Epidemiol</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>e253</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/EE9.0000000000000253</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37545809</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Aaron</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Madrigano</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Angelini</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Association between long-term exposure to ambient air pollution and change in quantitatively assessed emphysema and lung function</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>322</volume>:<fpage>546</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>56</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2019.10255</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31408135</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakhjirgan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kashani</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kermani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Exposure to outdoor particulate matter and risk of respiratory diseases: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Environ Geochem Health</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>46</volume>:<fpage>20</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10653-023-01807-1</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38153542</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>UW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kyung</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Adverse effects of air pollution on pulmonary diseases</article-title>. <source>Tuberc Respir Dis (Seoul)</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>85</volume>:<fpage>313</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4046/trd.2022.0116</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36097730</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The global burden of disease attributable to ambient fine particulate matter in 204 countries and territories, 1990-2019: a systematic analysis of the global burden of disease study 2019</article-title>. <source>Ecotoxicol Environ Saf</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>238</volume>:<fpage>113588</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecoenv.2022.113588</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35525115</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Fermoyle</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Troy</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name><surname>Knibbs</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Corte</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The impact of air pollution on interstitial lung disease: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Front Med (Lausanne)</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>1321038</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmed.2023.1321038</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38298511</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Behinaein</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hutchings</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Knapp</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Okereke</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The growing impact of air quality on lung-related illness: a narrative review</article-title>. <source>J Thorac Dis</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>5055</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>63</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21037/jtd-23-544</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37868892</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ciabattini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rizzello</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucaroni</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Palombi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Boffetta</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Systematic review and meta-analysis of recent high-quality studies on exposure to particulate matter and risk of lung cancer</article-title>. <source>Environ Res</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>196</volume>:<fpage>110440</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2020.110440</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33181136</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Long-term exposure to PM2.5 and Children's lung function: a dose-based association analysis</article-title>. <source>J Thorac Dis</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>6379</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>95</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21037/jtd-19-crh-aq-007</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33209476</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Putri Anis Syahira</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Karmegam</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nur Athirah Diyana</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name><surname>Irniza</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Shamsul Bahri</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Vivien</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Impacts of PM2.5 on respiratory system among traffic policemen</article-title>. <source>Work</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>66</volume>:<fpage>25</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3233/WOR-203147</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32417810</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Long-term PM2.5 exposure and peak expiratory flow in middle-aged and older people in China: a quasi-experimental study</article-title>. <source>Am J Epidemiol</source>. (<year>2025</year>) <volume>194</volume>:<fpage>738</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>45</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aje/kwae146</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38907335</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Yue</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The challenge of population aging for mitigating deaths from PM2.5 air pollution in China</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>5222</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-023-40908-4</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37633954</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The impact of living environmental factors on cognitive function and mild cognitive impairment: evidence from the Chinese elderly population</article-title>. <source>BMC Public Health</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>24</volume>:<fpage>2814</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-024-20197-2</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39402570</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Strauss</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cohort profile: the China health and retirement longitudinal study (CHARLS)</article-title>. <source>Int J Epidemiol</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <volume>43</volume>:<fpage>61</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ije/dys203</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23243115</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Association between cognitive function and ambient particulate matters in middle-aged and elderly Chinese adults: evidence from the China health and retirement longitudinal study (CHARLS)</article-title>. <source>Sci Total Environ</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>828</volume>:<fpage>154297</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2022.154297</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35288137</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Nowcasting and forecasting the care needs of the older population in China: analysis of data from the China health and retirement longitudinal study (CHARLS)</article-title>. <source>Lancet Public Health</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>e1005</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>13</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2468-2667(22)00203-1</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36423656</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Checklist of vascular plant species in Huangshui River basin of Qinghai Province</article-title>. <source>China Biodivers Data J</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>e123002</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/BDJ.12.e123002</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38817271</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <source>Assessing the evolution of PM2. 5 and related health impacts resulting from air quality policies in China. Environmental Impact Assessment Review</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>93</volume>:<fpage>106727</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eiar.2021.106727</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37056681</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goobie</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlsten</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Johannson</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Khalil</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Marcoux</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Assayag</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Association of particulate matter exposure with lung function and mortality among patients with fibrotic interstitial lung disease</article-title>. <source>JAMA Intern Med</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>182</volume>:<fpage>1248</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>59</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamainternmed.2022.4696</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36251286</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kerr</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>van Donkelaar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name><name><surname>Brauer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bukart</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wozniak</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Increasing racial and ethnic disparities in ambient air pollution-attributable morbidity and mortality in the United States</article-title>. <source>Environ Health Perspect</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>132</volume>:<fpage>37002</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1289/EHP11900</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38445892</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qibin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Yacan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Minli</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Meixi</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Chengye</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuping</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The impact of PM2.5 on lung function in adults with asthma</article-title>. <source>Int J Tuberc Lung Dis</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>24</volume>:<fpage>570</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5588/ijtld.19.0394</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32552993</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>D'Souza</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Senthilkumar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Scovronick</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Acute effects of ambient air pollution on asthma emergency department visits in ten U.S. States</article-title>. <source>Environ Health Perspect</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>131</volume>:<fpage>47003</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1289/EHP11661</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37011135</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The effect of living environmental factors on cardiovascular diseases in Chinese adults: results from a cross-sectional and longitudinal study</article-title>. <source>Eur J Prev Cardiol</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>1063</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>73</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/eurjpc/zwac304</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36537654</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ci</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>PM2.5 increases susceptibility to acute exacerbation of COPD via NOX4/Nrf2 redox imbalance-mediated mitophagy</article-title>. <source>Redox Biol</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>59</volume>:<fpage>102587</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.redox.2022.102587</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36608590</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>PM2.5 induces pulmonary microvascular injury in COPD via METTL16-mediated m6A modification</article-title>. <source>Environ Pollut</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>303</volume>:<fpage>119115</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2022.119115</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35259473</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Shuo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ping</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>IL-10 ameliorates PM2.5-induced lung injury by activating the AMPK/SIRT1/PGC-1&#x003b1; pathway</article-title>. <source>Environ Toxicol Pharmacol</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>86</volume>:<fpage>103659</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.etap.2021.103659</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33862202</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Oxidative stress is the pivot for PM2.5-induced lung injury</article-title>. <source>Food Chem Toxicol</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>184</volume>:<fpage>114362</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fct.2023.114362</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38101601</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The health effects of ambient PM2.5 and potential mechanisms</article-title>. <source>Ecotoxicol Environ Saf</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>128</volume>:<fpage>67</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>74</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecoenv.2016.01.030</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26896893</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khoshnamvand</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Azizi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Naddafi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hassanvand</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The effect of size distribution of ambient air particulate matter on oxidative potential by acellular method Dithiothreitol; a systematic review</article-title>. <source>J Environ Health Sci Eng</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>579</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>88</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40201-021-00768-w</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35669811</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>XJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Resveratrol extracted from Chinese herbal medicines: a novel therapeutic strategy for lung diseases</article-title>. <source>Chin Herb Med</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>349</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>58</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chmed.2020.07.003</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32963508</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Mechanisms of Biochanin a alleviating PM2.5 organic extracts-induced EMT of A549 cells through the PI3K/Akt pathway</article-title>. <source>J Nat Prod</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>85</volume>:<fpage>2290</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>301</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jnatprod.2c00457</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36181478</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Phytochemical reduces toxicity of PM2.5: a review of research progress</article-title>. <source>Nutr Rev</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>82</volume>:<fpage>654</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>63</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nutrit/nuad077</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37587082</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>