<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="issn">2168-8184</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cureus</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2168-8184</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cureus</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Palo Alto (CA)</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12103062</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7759/cureus.82897</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Emergency Medicine</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>General Surgery</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Preventive Medicine</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Gastric Perforation After Liquid Nitrogen Cocktail Ingestion: A Case Report</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Muacevic</surname><given-names>Alexander</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>John R</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Zaldo Arredondo</surname><given-names>Carlos I</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Abarca Magall&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>Alfredo S</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Damacio Breton</surname><given-names>Roberto E</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-3" ref-type="aff">3</xref><xref rid="aff-4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Estrada Gonzales</surname><given-names>Jose A</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-5" ref-type="aff">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Leal Isla Flores</surname><given-names>Valeria</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-6" ref-type="aff">6</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff-1">
<label>1</label>
General Surgery, Hospital General de Le&#x000f3;n, Le&#x000f3;n, MEX </aff><aff id="aff-2">
<label>2</label>
General and Colorectal Surgery, Hospital Regional Lic. Adolfo L&#x000f3;pez Mateos, Mexico City, MEX </aff><aff id="aff-3">
<label>3</label>
General Surgery, Hospital de Especialidades 5 de Mayo, Puebla, MEX </aff><aff id="aff-4">
<label>4</label>
Medicine, Benem&#x000e9;rita Universidad Aut&#x000f3;noma de Puebla, Puebla, MEX </aff><aff id="aff-5">
<label>5</label>
General Surgery, Cancun General Hospital "Jesus Kumate Rodriguez", Canc&#x000fa;n, MEX </aff><aff id="aff-6">
<label>6</label>
General Surgery, Hospital Regional Lic. Adolfo L&#x000f3;pez Mateos, Mexico City, MEX </aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">
Carlos I. Zaldo Arredondo <email>iskyam.zaldo@gmail.com</email>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>24</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic"><month>4</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>17</volume><issue>4</issue><elocation-id>e82897</elocation-id><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2025, Zaldo Arredondo et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Zaldo Arredondo et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License CC-BY 4.0., which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="https://www.cureus.com/articles/363966-gastric-perforation-after-liquid-nitrogen-cocktail-ingestion-a-case-report">This article is available from https://www.cureus.com/articles/363966-gastric-perforation-after-liquid-nitrogen-cocktail-ingestion-a-case-report</self-uri><abstract><p>Liquid nitrogen is a compound widely used in the food industry, and in recent years, it has gained popularity in the preparation of beverages and cocktails. However, it is not an innocuous substance. Although reported cases of gastrointestinal tract injuries associated with its ingestion are few, awareness of its potential harmful effects is crucial to reach a timely diagnosis and treatment. This article aims to present the case of a 34-year-old male patient who, following the consumption of a beverage prepared with liquid nitrogen, suffered a gastric perforation and massive pneumoperitoneum, as evidenced by a plain abdominal CT scan. He required emergency surgical intervention, which was successfully performed via a laparoscopic approach. The patient was discharged on the third postoperative day after tolerating a liquid diet.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>barotrauma-induced pneumoperitoneum</kwd><kwd>gastric perforation</kwd><kwd>liquid nitrogen</kwd><kwd>massive pneumoperitoneum</kwd><kwd>minimally invasive laparoscopy</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Liquid nitrogen is a compound widely used in the food industry due to its ability to cool and preserve products through rapid freezing [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. However, its recreational use in the preparation of food and beverages has also become popular, owing to the smoke effect it generates upon evaporation [<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>].</p><p>Inappropriate ingestion of liquid nitrogen can cause severe effects in the gastrointestinal tract, primarily due to direct contact with tissues, given its approximate temperature of -195&#x000b0;C (-319&#x000b0;F) [<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Furthermore, its rapid expansion upon transitioning to a gaseous state can lead to gastrointestinal perforations and pneumoperitoneum secondary to barotrauma [<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Although reported cases of digestive tract perforation associated with liquid nitrogen ingestion are rare, all have necessitated emergency surgical management [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>-<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>].</p><p>Gastric perforation is suspected based on the patient's clinical presentation, which may include tachycardia, tachypnea, fever, generalized abdominal pain, and rebound tenderness as key symptoms [<xref rid="REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. The diagnosis is confirmed by evidence of free air in the abdominal cavity via imaging studies, among which computed tomography (CT) of the abdomen is the most useful [<xref rid="REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Patients who undergo timely surgical intervention for gastric perforation tend to exhibit a favorable clinical course and can be discharged once they tolerate oral intake [<xref rid="REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>].</p><p>In the present report, we describe the case of a patient who presented with a gastric perforation associated with the recreational ingestion of liquid nitrogen, detailing the clinical evolution, surgical management, and subsequent postoperative course.</p></sec><sec sec-type="cases"><title>Case presentation</title><p>A 34-year-old male patient, with no significant past medical history or prior surgical interventions, presented to the emergency department with acutely developing generalized abdominal pain after consuming a liquid nitrogen-infused alcoholic beverage at a bar.</p><p>Upon admission, the patient was diaphoretic and exhibited the following vital signs: tachycardia 124 beats per minute, blood pressure of 82/60 mmHg, a temperature of 35.4 &#x000b0;C, and a respiratory rate of 30 breaths per minute. On examination, he was lethargic, with notable generalized abdominal distension, rigidity, tender to palpation in all quadrants, tympanic to percussion, and demonstrated a loss of hepatic dullness. Relevant laboratory findings from the emergency department are summarized in Table <xref rid="TAB1" ref-type="table">1</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Laboratory test results</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patient values</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal range</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glucose</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77 mg/dl</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74 &#x02013; 106 mg/dl</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urea</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 mg/dl</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 &#x02013; 43 mg/dl</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Creatinine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1 mg/dl</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66 &#x02013; 1.25 mg/dl</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C-Reactive Protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">134 mg/l</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;5 mg/l</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leukocytes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.46 x 10<sup>3</sup>/&#x000b5;L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 &#x02013; 10 x 10<sup>3</sup>/&#x000b5;L</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hemoglobin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.60 g/dl</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 &#x02013; 16 g/dl</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Platelets</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">250 x 10<sup>3</sup>/&#x000b5;L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13-400 x 10<sup>3</sup>/&#x000b5;L</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sodium</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">139 mmol/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">137 &#x02013; 145 mmol/L</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Potassium</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.3 mmol/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5 &#x02013; 5.1 mmol/L</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloride</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">108 mmol/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">98 &#x02013; 107 mmol/L</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prothrombin Time</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.4 seconds</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 &#x02013; 15 seconds</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Partial Thromboplastin Time</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 seconds</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 &#x02013; 36 seconds</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">International Normalized Ratio (INR)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Based on the clinical presentation and initial findings, an abdominal CT scan was immediately performed, revealing a massive pneumoperitoneum suggestive of hollow viscus perforation (Figure <xref rid="FIG1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). This prompted a request for immediate diagnostic laparoscopy.</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Abdominal CT scan showing pneumoperitoneum (yellow arrows)</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0017-00000082897-i01" position="float"/></fig><p>Laparoscopic exploration revealed abundant free air in the abdominal cavity and a 3 cm perforation on the anterior aspect of the stomach (Figure <xref rid="FIG2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>), which was repaired laparoscopically with Monocryl 3-0 (Ethicon, Inc., Raritan, New Jersey, United States) and reinforced with an omental patch (Figure <xref rid="FIG3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Exploratory laparoscopy revealing gastric perforation secondary to the ingestion of liquid nitrogen</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0017-00000082897-i02" position="float"/></fig><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Repair of gastric perforation via laparoscopic approach with placement of an omental patch</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0017-00000082897-i03" position="float"/></fig><p>Postoperatively, the patient was transferred to recovery in stable condition and did not require mechanical ventilation. The patient progressed well, tolerating a liquid diet by postoperative day 2, and was discharged on postoperative day 3.</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>The etiology of gastric perforations can be diverse; however, the majority necessitate emergency surgical management&#x000a0;due to the risk of peritonitis and abdominal sepsis [<xref rid="REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Both clinical assessment and imaging studies are critical for timely diagnosis, with abdominal CT being the preferred modality due to its high sensitivity and specificity [<xref rid="REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>].</p><p>Surgical intervention can be performed via open surgery or laparoscopy, with the latter generally favored due to its minimally invasive nature. In most instances, management involves primary closure of the perforation site using absorbable suture material, with or without the application of an omental patch [<xref rid="REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>-<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].</p><p>Reported cases of gastric perforation associated with liquid nitrogen ingestion are rare. These cases typically involve two primary mechanisms: cryogenic injury resulting from direct contact with mucous membranes and skin, and barotrauma occurring when liquid nitrogen transitions to a gaseous state within the gastric cavity [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>-<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>].</p><p>The Leidenfrost effect describes the formation of an insulating vapor layer around a liquid when it encounters a surface with a temperature significantly exceeding its boiling point, thereby impeding heat transfer. This phenomenon explains how liquid nitrogen reaches the gastric cavity, where it undergoes rapid expansion as it vaporizes, with barotrauma serving as the primary mechanism of injury [<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>].</p><p>Irrespective of the etiology of gastric perforation and massive pneumoperitoneum, prompt diagnosis and surgical intervention are essential for achieving favorable patient outcomes [<xref rid="REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Surgical management and subsequent follow-up do not differ significantly from other causes of gastric perforation [<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>-<xref rid="REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. The early initiation of enteral nutrition with good patient tolerance is a positive prognostic indicator for hospital discharge [<xref rid="REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].&#x000a0;</p><p>In this particular case, the minimally invasive laparoscopic approach, coupled with the accurate identification of pneumoperitoneum via CT imaging, played a pivotal role in the successful management of the patient.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>This report presents a case of gastric perforation resulting from liquid nitrogen ingestion. Prompt identification of the perforation was paramount in facilitating immediate surgical intervention, which led to the timely repair of the defect via a laparoscopic approach and a subsequent successful recovery for the patient. This case underscores the importance of raising awareness regarding the risks associated with the ingestion of cryogenic substances and emphasizes the critical role of healthcare professionals in recognizing atypical gastrointestinal injuries and cautioning the community about the possible damage that these can have on the digestive tract.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group content-type="conflict"><title>Disclosures</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Human subjects:</bold> Consent for treatment and open access publication was obtained or waived by all participants in this study.</p><p><bold>Conflicts of interest:</bold> In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following:</p><p><bold>Payment/services info:</bold> All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work.</p><p><bold>Financial relationships:</bold> All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work.</p><p><bold>Other relationships:</bold> All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="other"><title>Author Contributions</title><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Concept and design:</bold>&#x000a0; Carlos I. Zaldo Arredondo, Alfredo S. Abarca Magall&#x000f3;n, Roberto E. Damacio Breton, Jose A. Estrada Gonzales, Valeria Leal Isla Flores</p><p><bold>Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data:</bold>&#x000a0; Carlos I. Zaldo Arredondo, Alfredo S. Abarca Magall&#x000f3;n, Roberto E. Damacio Breton, Jose A. Estrada Gonzales, Valeria Leal Isla Flores</p><p><bold>Drafting of the manuscript:</bold>&#x000a0; Carlos I. Zaldo Arredondo, Alfredo S. Abarca Magall&#x000f3;n, Roberto E. Damacio Breton, Valeria Leal Isla Flores</p><p><bold>Critical review of the manuscript for important intellectual content:</bold>&#x000a0; Carlos I. Zaldo Arredondo, Alfredo S. Abarca Magall&#x000f3;n, Jose A. Estrada Gonzales</p><p><bold>Supervision:</bold>&#x000a0; Carlos I. Zaldo Arredondo</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="REF1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Liquid nitrogen ingestion leading to massive pneumoperitoneum without identifiable gastrointestinal perforation</article-title><source>J Emerg Med</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tharratt</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Offerman</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>607</fpage><lpage>609</lpage><volume>38</volume><year>2010</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18790587</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Stomach perforation caused by ingesting liquid nitrogen: a case report on the effect of a dangerous snack</article-title><source>Clin Endosc</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>381</fpage><lpage>383</lpage><volume>51</volume><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29502381</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Gastric perforation associated with the intake of ice cream with liquid nitrogen [Article in Spanish]</article-title><source>Rev Gastroenterol Peru</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Guzm&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McBrown</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Montoya</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rincon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Concha</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Iba&#x000f1;ez</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>364</fpage><lpage>366</lpage><volume>39</volume><year>2019</year><uri xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/32097398/">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/32097398/</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32097398</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Liquid nitrogen ingestion followed by gastric perforation</article-title><source>Pediatr Emerg Care</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Berrizbeitia</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Calello</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dhir</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>O'Reilly</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marcus</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>48</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><volume>26</volume><year>2010</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20065833</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Barotrauma after liquid nitrogen ingestion: a case report and literature review</article-title><source>Postgrad Med</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>511</fpage><lpage>514</lpage><volume>130</volume><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29999439</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>A lethal cocktail: gastric perforation following liquid nitrogen ingestion</article-title><source>BMJ Case Rep</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Pollard</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bukhari</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name>
</person-group><volume>2013</volume><year>2013</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><article-title>Gastric perforation</article-title><source>StatPearls [Internet]</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Sigmon</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tuma</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kamel</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cassaro</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><publisher-loc>Treasure Island (FL)</publisher-loc><publisher-name>StatPearls Publishing</publisher-name><year>2023</year><uri xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK519554/">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK519554/</uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Gastric rupture following multiple blunt trauma</article-title><source>Radiol Case Rep</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Hue</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hung</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Minh</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Anh</surname><given-names>TV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Anh</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Duc</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>1380</fpage><lpage>1383</lpage><volume>17</volume><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35251422</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Pneumoperitoneum from acute gastric dilation and perforation</article-title><source>BMJ Case Rep</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Azevedo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Canhoto</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>0</fpage><volume>12</volume><year>2019</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Acute gastric dilatation: a retrospective case series from a single institution</article-title><source>Case Rep Gastroenterol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Bathobakae</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bashir</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Venero</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yuridullah</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cavanagh</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baddoura</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>439</fpage><lpage>448</lpage><volume>18</volume><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39474155</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>