<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Geriatr</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Geriatr</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Geriatrics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2318</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11786471</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">5707</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12877-025-05707-0</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Using CT imaging to identify sarcopenia as a risk factor for severe falls in older adults</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fries</surname><given-names>Nadja</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-4473-1046</contrib-id><name><surname>Kotti</surname><given-names>Angeliki</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-0066-4985</contrib-id><name><surname>Woisetschl&#x000e4;ger</surname><given-names>Mischa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-7130-9158</contrib-id><name><surname>Sp&#x000e5;ngeus</surname><given-names>Anna</given-names></name><address><email>anna.spangeus@liu.se</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/05ynxx418</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5640.7</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2162 9922</institution-id><institution>Division of Diagnostics and Specialist Medicine, Department of Health, Medicine and Caring Sciences, </institution><institution>Link&#x000f6;ping University, </institution></institution-wrap>Link&#x000f6;ping, Sweden </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/05h1aye87</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411384.b</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9309 6304</institution-id><institution>Department of Radiology, </institution><institution>Link&#x000f6;ping University Hospital, </institution></institution-wrap>Link&#x000f6;ping, Sweden </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/05ynxx418</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5640.7</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2162 9922</institution-id><institution>Department of Biomedical and Clinical Sciences, </institution><institution>Link&#x000f6;ping University, </institution></institution-wrap>Link&#x000f6;ping, Sweden </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/05ynxx418</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5640.7</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2162 9922</institution-id><institution>Center for Medical Image Science and Vizualization (CMIV), </institution><institution>Link&#x000f6;ping University, </institution></institution-wrap>Link&#x000f6;ping, Sweden </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/05h1aye87</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411384.b</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9309 6304</institution-id><institution>Department of Acute Internal Medicine and Geriatrics, </institution><institution>Link&#x000f6;ping University Hospital, </institution></institution-wrap>Link&#x000f6;ping, Sweden </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>1</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>1</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>25</volume><elocation-id>72</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>6</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Sarcopenia is a skeletal muscle disease primarily associated with ageing and progressive muscle decline and increases the risk of falls. The purpose of the present study was to investigate risk factors, including sarcopenia, for severe falls compared to non-severe falls. In addition, we wanted to explore possible associations between sarcopenia, bone mineral density (BMD), adipose tissue as well as clinical scores assessing frailty, nutritional status, and fall risk.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">This retrospective cohort study included 101 older patients that had experienced a fall incident during in-patient care at a geriatric ward between 2018 and 2020. The fall incidents were categorized into severe or non-severe falls. Clinical data, including risk assessment scores were retrospectively obtained from the participants&#x02019; medical records. Body composition, including skeletal muscle quantity (SKM), adipose tissues, and BMD were assessed from abdominal CT-scans performed for any reason maximal 6 months before or after the fall. Skeletal muscle index ratio (SMI-ratio) was calculated using SKM cm<sup>2</sup>/height m<sup>2</sup> and divided with previous described cut off values for sarcopenia. An SMI ratio&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;100% indicated sarcopenia.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">The severe fall group showed higher grade of sarcopenia compared to the non-severe fall group (SMI ratio of 71% vs. 83%, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.041) as well as lower, though statistically non-significant, BMI and subcutaneous adipose tissue (SAT) (BMI 22 [20&#x02013;24] vs. 24 [22&#x02013;27] kg/m<sup>2</sup>, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.108, and SAT 95&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;70&#x000a0;cm&#x000b2; vs. 141&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;94&#x000a0;cm&#x000b2;, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.124). Overweight was more common in non-severe than severe fall group (43% vs. 14%, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.048). SMI ratio correlated negatively with frailty and positive with BMI and the following body composition measurements: intramuscular-, subcutaneous, and visceral adipose tissue (IMAT, SAT and VAT). No correlation with other clinical risk assessment scores nor spine T-score was found. In the multivariate analysis, higher level of frailty, male sex as well as lower BMI, VAT and SAT remained as risk factors for low SMI ratio.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par4">These results underscore the importance of addressing sarcopenia and related risk factors, including malnutrition, in the management and prevention of severe falls in the elderly population. Body composition analyzed in CT-scans could add value in this risk assessment. This analysis could be conducted opportunistically during CT scans performed for other purposes.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Sarcopenia</kwd><kwd>Osteoporosis</kwd><kwd>Osteosarcopenia</kwd><kwd>Fall</kwd><kwd>Body composition</kwd><kwd>Frailty</kwd><kwd>Geriatric</kwd><kwd>Computed tomography</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Link&#x000f6;ping University</institution></funding-source></award-group><open-access><p>Open access funding provided by Link&#x000f6;ping University.</p></open-access></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; BioMed Central Ltd., part of Springer Nature 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par5">Sarcopenia is a progressive skeletal muscle disease that impairs muscle quantity and quality leading to low muscle strength. While primarily associated with ageing and muscle changes that happen over a long period of time, sarcopenia can also occur secondary to e.g. inflammatory processes such as malignancy or organ failure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>].</p><p id="Par6">Today low muscle strength measured with functional tests, is considered to be the main finding in sarcopenic patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. The diagnosis could be further assessed radiologically by the presence of low muscle quantity. A recommended radiological method for assessing lean mass is dual-energy X-ray absorptiometry (DXA) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. DXA is advantageous due to its very low radiation dose, which permits multiple reassessments over time without health concerns. However, it necessitates a dedicated machine and a separate visit. Alternatively, sarcopenia and other body composition measures can be identified using CT scans [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>], which can be analyzed opportunistically during scans performed for any reason. Given the frequency of performed CT scans nowadays, particularly among the aging population, opportunistic body composition analysis offers a readily available and valuable method for screening sarcopenia in high-risk groups. Compared to DXA, CT provides three-dimensional images and higher resolution, potentially enhancing the accuracy of the analysis.</p><p id="Par7">Previous studies have shown that tissue measurements at the level of lumbar L3 strongly relates to whole body composition and thus one established method is to use the L3 level in computer tomography (CT)-scans as a landmark to calculate muscle cross-sectional area and to predict whole body composition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. It thereby enables rapid quantification of different types of tissues such as SKM (skeletal muscle), intramuscular adipose tissue (IMAT), visceral adipose tissue (VAT) and subcutaneous adipose tissue (SAT). This is an easily applicable method as abdominal CT-scans done for other reasons are often available in the patients&#x02019; medical records [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Therefore, if deemed valuable for assessing the risk of severe falls, body composition analysis can be conveniently conducted on routine CT scans (opportunistically) or even in dedicated low-dose CT scans. If an increased risk is identified, appropriate measures can be implemented.</p><p id="Par8">Sarcopenia and osteoporosis share many risk factors as well as negative clinical outcomes such as an increased risk of falls and fractures, frailty, hospitalization and mortality [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Frailty is a condition with impaired function of multiple physiological systems which consequently predisposes an individual to decreased capacity in maintaining balance and coordination. It also increases the risk for inability to recover from falls [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Frailty can be estimated with the Clinical Frailty Scale (CFS) ranging from 1 (very fit) to 9 (terminally ill) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Poor nutrition status is known to fasten the process of developing sarcopenia, and malnutrition with vitamin D deficiency was also shown to be related to balance dysfunction, increasing the risk of falling [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. A way to estimate nutrition status is by the mini nutritional assessment short-form (SF-MNA) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Poor nutrition status is also a risk factor for developing pressure ulcers. The risk assessment pressure sore (RAPS) scale rates risk factors with an assumption that a lower score generates a greater risk of developing pressure sores [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>] .</p><p id="Par9">To clinically identify patients with high risk of falling, the Downton Fall Risk Index (DRFI) is a valuable screening instrument with a score range of 0&#x02013;11 where 3 or more is considered as a high risk of falls [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. And lastly the modified elderly mobility scale (M-EMS) is an instrument designed to evaluate mobility and is specially addressed to the older persons. It generates a maximum of 20 points where higher points indicate a more safe and independent movement [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>].</p><p id="Par10">Previous studies have shown that same-level falls (low-energy trauma) account for close to half of all traumas in the older persons population and that these patients also pose a higher risk for severe injury compared to the younger population (e.g. head- and neck injuries and fractures) as well as death related to falls [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Moreover, osteoporosis combined with sarcopenia is associated with an even higher risk for fracture, but little is known about whether the outcome of a fall can be predicted with the degree of sarcopenia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>].</p><p id="Par11">Compared to non-injurious falls, severe falls pose a significant risk of causing long-term disabilities, such as after fractures and brain injuries. They often necessitate more intensive medical interventions, including hospitalization, surgery, and rehabilitation, and are therefore associated with substantial healthcare costs. Additionally, severe falls can have psychological impacts, such as fear of falling, which may limit patients&#x02019; activities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Therefore, a better understanding of the risk factors for severe falls and the identification of protective factors are essential to safeguard the geriatric population.</p><p id="Par12">The aim of this study was to investigate risk factors for severe falls compared to non-severe falls in older persons. In addition, we wanted to explore possible associations between sarcopenia, body composition (bone mineral density [BMD] and adipose tissue) as well as clinical risk assessment scores assessing frailty, nutritional status, and fall risk.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Study design and study cohort</title><p id="Par13">In the present retrospective cohort study, we included all patients at the geriatric acute ward with a fall-incident during an inpatient stay between 1st January 2018 to 31st December 2020 (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;159). Of these patients, only patients with an abdominal CT scan performed within 6 months before or after the fall incident were included (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;101). The fall-incidents were identified through the department&#x02019;s event tracking system (Synergi). We excluded patients with falls secondary to other clinical events such as stroke, or arrhythmia. Data collected from the patients&#x02019; medical record was used to categorize falls into two groups depending on the outcome of the fall, i.e. severe falls and non-severe falls. Severe falls included falls that resulted in fracture, need of opioid prescription, major head injury, internal bleeding, or death, while non-severe falls resulted in no or minor medical conditions (e.g. bruises or laceration with/or without mild analgesics for pain management).</p><p id="Par14">Background data, clinical measures and clinical risk assessment scores were extracted from the medical records. Clinical risk assessment instruments included in the study were CFS, SF-MNA-, DRFI-, M-EMS- as well as RAPS- score. The CFS is an instrument assessing frailty on a 9-point-scale ranging from 1 (very fit) to 9 (terminally ill) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. The SF-MNA consists of six questions that cover key areas related to nutritional status and estimates patient&#x02019;s nutrition status on a 0&#x02013;14-point scale, where 0&#x02013;7 point is considered malnourished, and 8&#x02013;11 at risk of malnutrition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. The DRFI is a tool used to assess the risk of falls in patients. Risk is assessed from five modules with a higher score suggesting a greater risk of fall. A score of 3 or more is considered as a high risk of falls [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. The M-EMS is an instrument designed to evaluate mobility and is specially addressed to older people. It generates a maximum of 20 points where higher points indicate a more safe and independent movement [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. The RAPS assesses risk factors for pressure ulcers with lower score indicating a higher risk of developing pressure sores [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. A score&#x02009;<italic>&#x02264;</italic>&#x02009;29 is considered an increased risk of pressure ulcers.</p><p id="Par15">For the body composition measurements all abdominal CT-scans performed for any clinical reasons 6 months before or after the reported fall were retrospectively identified using Picture Archiving and Communication System (PACS) (Sectra Imtec AB, Link&#x000f6;ping, Sweden, version 25.1) which resulted in 101 unique patients with at least one CT abdominal scan. In the SKM assessment, lumbar spine CT-scans (i.e. scans made with spine protocol) were excluded due to incomplete field of view (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;30). Our final CT cohort consisted of 71 patients with CT-scans available for analysis as shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. There were no significant differences between patients analyzed with DAFS and those not analyzed, in terms of age (84&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;8 vs. 84&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;7 years, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.933), sex (46% female vs. 44% female, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.873), and the percentage with severe fall trauma (16% vs. 14%, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.821). CT scans utilized in the SKM analysis were conducted on average 11 days prior to the fall event (with a median of 6 days). 10% of the scans were performed 3 months or longer after the fall, and 3% were conducted 4 months or longer post-fall.</p><p id="Par16">
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Flow chart of the patient inclusion process for skeletal muscle (SKM) assessment. A total of 101 CT scans were available; however, 30 could not be analyzed due to technical issues, such as incomplete coverage of the abdominal area</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12877_2025_5707_Fig3_HTML" id="d33e402"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par17">For BMD assessment, lumbar spine CT-scans and scans with missing calibration data were excluded as they were not possible to analyze in the software (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;44). This resulted in 57 unique patients with CT-scans available for BMD analysis. There were no significant differences between patients analyzed for BMD and those not analyzed, in terms of age (84&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;8 vs. 85&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;7 years, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.428), sex (47% female vs. 43% female, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.622), and the percentage with severe fall trauma (16% vs. 14%, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.815).</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Body composition measurements</title><sec id="Sec41"><title>Skeletal muscle</title><p id="Par18">In each patient&#x000b4;s CT-scan, body composition measurements were obtained by using Data Analysis Facilitation Suite (DAFS) (Voronoi Health Analytics, Inc., Vancouver, Canada). DAFS allows automated single slice as well as multi-slice extraction from CT scans which generates organ segmentation and body composition measurements. For our cohort, single slice SKM, SAT, VAT and IMAT measurements across mid-L3 were calculated and quantified as cross-sectional area in cm<sup>2</sup> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).</p><p id="Par19">
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Single-slice body composition measurement with Data Analysis Facilitation Suite (DAFS) (Voronoi Health Analytics, Inc., Vancouver, Canada). The various tissues were automatically identified and analyzed, including skeletal muscles (red) and adipose tissues, which were further sub-categorized into subcutaneous (blue), visceral (yellow), and intramuscular (green)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12877_2025_5707_Fig1_HTML" id="d33e437"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec42"><title>Bone mineral density</title><p id="Par20">BMD and T-score were assessed by the Mindways qCT PRO software (version 2, Mindways, Austin, TX, USA). Regions of interest (ROIs) are automatically placed with 7&#x02013;9&#x000a0;mm thickness depending on how much the shape of the vertebrae allows analysis without distortion of BMD (e.g. compression fracture, posterior venous plexus, cortical bone) in the trabecular part of the lumbar L1-L3 vertebrae and can manually be adjusted if needed. From this, a mean BMD and T-score was calculated. In case T-score varied&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1 SD between vertebrae, we excluded the vertebrae with the highest T-score.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Defining cut off measurements</title><sec id="Sec51"><title>Skeletal muscle</title><p id="Par21">For the sarcopenia analyses, we calculated the skeletal muscle index (SMI, cm<sup>2</sup>/ m<sup>2</sup>) using the formula: cross-sectional area of SKM divided by the square of body height. Cut off measurements were obtained from a previous study on a healthy Caucasian population with sarcopenia defined as &#x0003c;&#x02009;41.6 cm<sup>2</sup>/ m<sup>2</sup> for men and &#x0003c;&#x02009;32 cm<sup>2</sup>/ m<sup>2</sup> for women [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Each patient&#x02019;s SMI was divided with these cut off values, resulting in a sex-neutral ratio that represents the participants percent of the cut off value for sarcopenia and is called SMI ratio. In tables and figures SMI ratio is presented in percent.</p></sec><sec id="Sec52"><title>Bone mineral density</title><p id="Par22">T-scores both from the hip and spine (average spine T-score) were used for the analysis.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par23">Descriptives were presented in mean and standard deviation (SD) or median and interquartile range (IQR) for continuous variables according to normal distribution or not, and frequency for categorical variables. For continuous data, group comparisons were made with T-test and Mann-Whitney U according to normality and for categorical data Chi2-test was used.</p><p id="Par24">Possible correlation between sarcopenia with clinical measures and adipose tissue measurements was examined according to normality by Pearson or Spearman.</p><p id="Par25">Univariate linear regression was conducted on variables considered to possibly have an impact on the level of sarcopenia, and statistically significant variables were further analyzed with multiple regression analysis. In the multivariate regression analysis three different models were used; Model (1) sex, outcome of fall, CFS, and BMI; Model (2) sex, outcome of fall, CFS, and SAT; and Model (3) sex, outcome of fall, CFS, and VAT. The models were created due to collinearity between BMI, SAT, and VAT.</p><p id="Par26">All statistical calculations were conducted using SPSS Statistics (version 28.0, IBM Corp., Armonk, NY, USA) and a <italic>p</italic> value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 was considered significant.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec8"><title>Characteristics of the study participants</title><p id="Par27">Cohort characteristics are described in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. Of the 101 participants, 59 were male and 42 female, with a mean age of 84 years (range 62&#x02013;103 years). In the chosen period a total of 14 (14%) patients had a fall categorized as severe. 84% of the patients were defined as sarcopenic (SMI ratio&#x02009;<italic>&#x02264;</italic>&#x02009;100%). Nearly half of the patients (48%) had sustained previous fractures before the documented fall-incident. The total numbers of fall events during the inpatient stay varied between one and three. Most patients (79%) had only one fall event, 18% had two fall events, and 3% had three fall events. There was no statistical difference in the number of falls between patients categorized as having severe (71% one fall, 29% two falls, and 0% three falls) or non-severe falls (81% one fall, 16% two falls, and 3% three falls).</p><p id="Par29">
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Cohort descriptives and group comparisons between non-severe- and severe falls</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Variable</th><th align="left">All</th><th align="left"/><th align="left">Non-severe falls</th><th align="left">Severe falls</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="2"><italic>P</italic>-value<break/>severe vs. non-severe falls</th></tr><tr><th align="left"><italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;101</th><th align="left"/><th align="left"><italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;87</th><th align="left"><italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;14</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">
<bold>Clinical risk factors</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"/><td align="left" rowspan="2"/><td align="left" rowspan="2"/><td align="left" rowspan="2"/><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="2">0.287</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Sex</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;male</td><td align="left"><italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;58</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">83%</td><td align="left">17%</td><td align="left" colspan="2"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;female</td><td align="left"><italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;42</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">91%</td><td align="left">9%</td><td align="left" colspan="2"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Age (years)<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">84 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;7)</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">84 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;7)</td><td align="left">85 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;9)</td><td align="left" colspan="2">
<italic>0.631</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Height (cm)<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">170 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;10)</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">170 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;11)</td><td align="left">170 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;6)</td><td align="left" colspan="2">
<italic>0.800</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Weight (kg)<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">70 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;17)</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">71 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;18)</td><td align="left">66 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;12)</td><td align="left" colspan="2">
<italic>0.344</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">24 (21&#x02013;27)</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">24 (22&#x02013;27)</td><td align="left">22 (20&#x02013;24)</td><td align="left" colspan="2">
<italic>0.108</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<bold>Medical treatment</bold>
</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left" colspan="2"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Blood thinners</td><td align="left">63%</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">68%</td><td align="left">79%</td><td align="left" colspan="2">
<italic>0.183</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Antihypertensives</td><td align="left">69%</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">68%</td><td align="left">71%</td><td align="left" colspan="2">
<italic>0.787</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Statins</td><td align="left">21%</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">22%</td><td align="left">14%</td><td align="left" colspan="2">
<italic>0.518</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Osteoporosis treatment</td><td align="left">10%</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">9%</td><td align="left">14%</td><td align="left" colspan="2">
<italic>0.554</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;FRID-classified medication</td><td align="left">93%</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">92%</td><td align="left">100%</td><td align="left" colspan="2">
<italic>0.262</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Opioids</td><td align="left">39%</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">40%</td><td align="left">29%</td><td align="left" colspan="2">
<italic>0.695</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<bold>Medical history before admission</bold>
</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left" colspan="2"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Cardiovascular disease</td><td align="left">56%</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">55%</td><td align="left">71%</td><td align="left" colspan="2">
<italic>0.240</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Diabetes mellitus</td><td align="left">27%</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">26%</td><td align="left">29%</td><td align="left" colspan="2">
<italic>1.000</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Cognitive Disease</td><td align="left">31%</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">30%</td><td align="left">36%</td><td align="left" colspan="2">
<italic>0.661</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Parkinson&#x02019;s disease</td><td align="left">13%</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">12%</td><td align="left">21%</td><td align="left" colspan="2">
<italic>0.383</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Osteoporosis</td><td align="left">20%</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">21%</td><td align="left">14%</td><td align="left" colspan="2">
<italic>0.577</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Previous fractures</td><td align="left">48%</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">47%</td><td align="left">50%</td><td align="left" colspan="2">
<italic>0.842</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<bold>Living situation before admission</bold>
</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left" colspan="2">
<italic>0.618</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Own home</td><td align="left">31%</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">29%</td><td align="left">43%</td><td align="left" colspan="2"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Own home but need of municipal service</td><td align="left">56%</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">59%</td><td align="left">43%</td><td align="left" colspan="2"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Rehabilitation facility</td><td align="left">4%</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">3%</td><td align="left">7%</td><td align="left" colspan="2"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Nursing home</td><td align="left">9%</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">9%</td><td align="left">7%</td><td align="left" colspan="2"/></tr><tr><td align="left">
<bold>Physical function before admission</bold>
</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left" colspan="2">
<italic>0.309</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Independent</td><td align="left">18%</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">20%</td><td align="left">7%</td><td align="left" colspan="2"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Walking aids</td><td align="left">65%</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">65%</td><td align="left">64%</td><td align="left" colspan="2"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Dependent (personal assistance needed)</td><td align="left">17%</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">15%</td><td align="left">29%</td><td align="left" colspan="2"/></tr><tr><td align="left">
<bold>Radiologic assessments</bold>
</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left" colspan="2"/></tr><tr><td align="left">T-score spine<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">-3.9 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.3)</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">-3.9 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.2)</td><td align="left">-3.6 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="2">
<italic>0.419</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">T-score femoral neck<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">-2.7 (-3.2- -1.9)</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">-2.7 (-3.3 &#x02013; -2.2)</td><td align="left">-1.9 (-3.2&#x02013; -1.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="2">
<italic>0.378</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SMI ratio in %<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">81 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;17)</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">83 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;17)</td><td align="left">71 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;14)</td><td align="left" colspan="2">
<bold><italic>0.041</italic></bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">IMAT (cm<sup>2</sup>)<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">18 (13&#x02013;23)</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">18 (7&#x02013;29)</td><td align="left">16 (7&#x02013;25)</td><td align="left" colspan="2">
<italic>0.269</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SAT (cm<sup>2</sup>)<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">134 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;91)</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">141 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;94)</td><td align="left">95 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;70)</td><td align="left" colspan="2">
<italic>0.124</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">VAT (cm<sup>2</sup>)<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">94 (49&#x02013;220)</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">96 (54&#x02013;218)</td><td align="left">92 (34&#x02013;237)</td><td align="left" colspan="2">
<italic>0.891</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<bold>Risk assessment score</bold>
</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left" colspan="2"/></tr><tr><td align="left">CFS<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">6 (5&#x02013;7)</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">6 (5&#x02013;7)</td><td align="left">6 (6&#x02013;7)</td><td align="left" colspan="2">
<italic>0.183</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SF-MNA<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">8 (6&#x02013;10)</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">8 (5&#x02013;10)</td><td align="left">6 (6&#x02013;8)</td><td align="left" colspan="2">
<italic>0.196</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">DFRI<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">5 (4&#x02013;6)</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">5 (4&#x02013;6)</td><td align="left">4 (4&#x02013;6)</td><td align="left" colspan="2">
<italic>0.967</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">RAPS<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">31 (28&#x02013;32)</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">31 (28&#x02013;32)</td><td align="left">31 (27&#x02013;32)</td><td align="left" colspan="2">
<italic>0.905</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">M-EMS<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">9 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;5)</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">9 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;5)</td><td align="left">10 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;5)</td><td align="left" colspan="2">
<italic>0.258</italic>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Variables presented according to normality, <sup>a</sup>=mean (SD), <sup>b</sup>=median (IQR) and categorical in frequency distributions (%); SMI, skeletal muscle index; SKM, skeletal muscle; IMAT, intramuscular adipose tissue; SAT, subcutaneous adipose tissue; VAT, visceral adipose tissue; CFS, clinical frailty score; SF-MNA, Mini Nutritional Assessment - short form; DFRI, Downton Fall Risk Index; RAPS, Risk assessment Pressure Sore scale; M-EMS, Modified Elderly mobility Scale. FRID, fall risk inducing drugs. Blood thinners include both anti-coagulant and platelet inhibitors. Antihypertensives include all classes of antihypertensives. Diabetes mellitus, including type 1- and 2 diabetes mellitus; cardiovascular disease; including coronary heart disease, cerebrovascular disease and peripheral arterial disease; Cognitive Disease, including Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease, vascular dementia, Lewy body disease, unspecified dementia</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par28">Regarding clinical risk assessment scores, 94% of the participants had a high risk of falling according to DFRI (<italic>&#x02265;</italic>&#x02009;3) with a moderate mobility limitation (M-EMS mean score 9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5). 58% were at least moderately frail (CFS&#x02009;<italic>&#x02265;</italic>&#x02009;6). Only 8% of the participants were considered having a normal nutritional status according to the SF-MNA but were at no current risk to develop pressure sores (RAPS median score 31 [28&#x02013;32]).</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Severe versus non-severe falls</title><p id="Par31">As shown in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, patients with severe falls had significantly lower SMI ratio than patients with non-severe falls (SMI ratio 71% vs. 83%, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.041) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Median BMI was lower, though statistically non-significant, in patients who suffered a severe fall compared to the non-severe fall (22 [20&#x02013;24] vs. 24 [22&#x02013;27] kg/m<sup>2</sup>, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.108). Furthermore, when analyzing BMI categories (underweight&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;18.5&#x000a0;kg/m&#x000b2;, normal weight 18.5&#x02013;24.9&#x000a0;kg/m&#x000b2;, and overweight&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;25&#x000a0;kg/m&#x000b2;), a higher percentage of overweight individuals was observed in the non-severely injured group compared to the severely injured group (43% vs. 14%, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.048), reinforcing the protective effect of higher weight. Similarly, subcutaneous adipose tissue (SAT) was nearly 150% higher in non-severe falls compared to severe falls, although this difference was not statistically significant (141&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;94&#x000a0;cm&#x000b2; vs. 95&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;70&#x000a0;cm&#x000b2;, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.124). No statistical difference was seen regarding spine- and femoral neck T-score, body composition measures IMAT and VAT, as well as clinical estimation of frailty (CFS), fall-risk (DFRI), pressure sore (RAPS), mobility (M-EMS) and malnutrition (SF-MNA).</p><p id="Par32">
<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Group comparison between non-severe- and severe falls and skeletal muscle index divided by the cut off measure of sarcopenia, shown in percent (SMI ratio in %). Below 100% is considered sarcopenic</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12877_2025_5707_Fig2_HTML" id="d33e1272"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Associations between Sarcopenia, clinical measures, clinical risk assessment scores and body composition</title><p id="Par34">As shown in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, SMI ratio correlated positively with BMI (rho&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.438) and adipose tissues (IMAT, SAT and VAT, rho&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.280, 0.478, and 0.269, respectively), and negative with frailty (CFS, rho = -0.288). There was no significant correlation between SMI ratio with the other clinical measuring scales.</p><p id="Par35">
<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Correlation between Sarcopenia (SMI ratio) and clinical measures, as well as clinical risk assessment scores</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Variable</th><th align="left">SMI ratio</th><th align="left"><italic>P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Age<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">-0.150 [-0.384-0.101]</td><td align="left">
<italic>0.240</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">0.438 [0.206&#x02013;0.623]</td><td align="left">
<bold><italic>&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</italic></bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Previous fracture<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">0.152 [-0.107-0.392]</td><td align="left">
<italic>0.234</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<bold>Body composition</bold>
</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">T-score spine<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">0.053 [-0.223-0.321]</td><td align="left">
<italic>0.710</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">T-score femoral neck<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">-0.032 [-0.345-0.287]</td><td align="left">
<italic>0.841</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">IMAT (cm<sup>2</sup>)<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">0.280 [0.027&#x02013;0.499]</td><td align="left">
<bold><italic>0.026</italic></bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SAT (cm<sup>2</sup>)<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">0.478 [0.261&#x02013;0.649]</td><td align="left">
<bold><italic>&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</italic></bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">VAT (cm<sup>2</sup>)<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">0.269 [0.015&#x02013;0.490]</td><td align="left">
<bold><italic>0.033</italic></bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<bold>Clinical risk assessment scores</bold>
</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">CFS<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">-0.288 [-0.509 - -0.032]</td><td align="left">
<bold><italic>0.024</italic></bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SF-MNA<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">0.227 [-0.057-0.477]</td><td align="left">
<italic>0.106</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">DFRI<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">0.028 [-0.252-0.303]</td><td align="left">
<italic>0.844</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">RAPS<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">0.104 [-0.188-0.379]</td><td align="left">
<italic>0.473</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MEMS<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">0.059 [-0.205-0.314]</td><td align="left">
<italic>0.665</italic>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>= Pearson&#x02019;s correlation analysis; <sup>b</sup>= Spearman&#x02019;s correlation analysis; previous fractures with no coded as 0 and yes coded as 1; SMI, skeletal muscle index; IMAT, intramuscular adipose tissue; SAT, subcutaneous adipose tissue; VAT, visceral adipose tissue; CFS, Clinical Frailty Score; SF-MNA, Mini Nutritional Assessment &#x02013; short form; DFRI, Downton Fall Risk Index; RAPS, Risk assessment Pressure Sore scale; M-EMS, Modified Elderly Mobility Scale</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par37">Univariate- and multivariate regression analyses are presented with SMI ratio as the dependent variable in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>. Collinearity was found between weight and height and was therefore presented as BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>). Femoral neck T-score was excluded as collinearity was found between spine- and femoral neck T-score. The multivariate regression included all clinical measurements that were significant in the univariate regression but as collinearity was found between BMI, SAT and VAT we analyzed data in three different regression models, as described in methods. Thus, BMI was included in model 1, SAT in model 2, and VAT in model 3.</p><p id="Par38">In the univariate analyses, male sex, severe fall, lower BMI, lower SAT, lower VAT and a higher degree of frailty (CFS) were associated with worse sarcopenia (i.e. lower SMI ratio). In the multivariate analysis, male sex, lower BMI, lower VAT, lower SAT and a higher degree of frailty remained significant risk factors for low SMI ratio.</p><p id="Par39">
<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Predictive factors of muscle mass (SMI ratio in %), analyzed with univariate- and multivariate linear regression</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2"/><th align="left" rowspan="2">Univariate</th><th align="left" colspan="3">Multivariate</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Model 1<break/><italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.470</th><th align="left">Model 2<break/><italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.382</th><th align="left">Model 3<break/><italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.481</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Sex</td><td align="left">-10.22 [-18.60- -1.84]*</td><td align="left">-12.26 [-19.14- -5.38]*</td><td align="left">-8.44 [-15.73- -1.16]*</td><td align="left">-16.33 [-23.58- -9.08]*</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Age</td><td align="left">-0.33 [-0.90-0.23]</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">BMI</td><td align="left">1.48 [0.83&#x02013;2.14]*</td><td align="left">1.56 [0.97&#x02013;2.14]*</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Outcome of the fall</td><td align="left">-11.61 [-22.71- -0.51]*</td><td align="left">-4.72 [-13.65-4.22]</td><td align="left">-4.88 [-14.59-4.83]</td><td align="left">-5.93 [-14.71-2.85]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Previous fracture</td><td align="left">4.27 [-4.40-12.93]</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">T-score spine</td><td align="left">0.68 [-2.95-4.30]</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">IMAT (cm<sup>2</sup>)</td><td align="left">0.37 [-0.07-0.81]</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">SAT (cm<sup>2</sup>)</td><td align="left">0.09 [0.05&#x02013;0.13]*</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">0.08 [0.04&#x02013;0.12]*</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">VAT (cm<sup>2</sup>)</td><td align="left">0.05 [0.02&#x02013;0.09]*</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">0.08 [0.05&#x02013;0.11]*</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CFS</td><td align="left">-3.82 [-7.17- -0.48]*</td><td align="left">-3.20 [-5.83&#x02013;0.57]*</td><td align="left">-3.42 [-6.25- -0.58]*</td><td align="left">-3.20 [-5.80- -0.60]*</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SF-MNA</td><td align="left">1.56 [-0.20-3.32]</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">DFRI</td><td align="left">0.39 [-3.15-3.93]</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">RAPS</td><td align="left">0.55 [-0.94-2.04]</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">MEMS</td><td align="left">0.20 [-0.72-1.11]</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05; SMI, skeletal muscle index; outcome off the fall with non-severe fall coded as 0 and severe fall coded as 1; sex with female coded as 0 and male coded as 1; previous fractures with no coded as 0 and yes coded as 1; IMAT, intramuscular adipose tissue; SAT, subcutaneous adipose tissue; VAT, visceral adipose tissue; CFS, Clinical Frailty Score; SF-MNA, Mini Nutritional Assessment &#x02013; Short form; DFRI, Downton Fall Risk Index; RAPS, Risk assessment Pressure Sore Scale; M-EMS, Modified Elderly Mobility Scale</p><p>All three multivariate models included sex&#x02009;+&#x02009;outcome of fall&#x02009;+&#x02009;CFS. In addition to this model 1 included BMI, model 2 included SAT, and model 3 included VAT</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par42">In the present study, we showed that patients who experienced severe falls exhibit more pronounced sarcopenia compared to non-severe fallers. Additionally, there was a trend indicating that severe fallers had lower BMI and reduced subcutaneous adipose tissue. A greater severity of sarcopenia was associated with male sex, lower adipose tissue levels, lower BMI, and frailty.</p><p id="Par43">A previous Italian study with a similar cohort as ours with a mean age of 86 years suggested that sarcopenia increases the risk of falling up to three times in two years follow up, yet little is known whether the outcome of the fall was associated with the degree of sarcopenia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>].</p><p id="Par44">In our study, participants were on average moderately frail with a median of 6 on the CFS and had all sustained a fall during their stay at the geriatric ward. Most patients (84%) had a SMI ratio below 100%, indicating sarcopenia. SMI ratio differed significantly between the groups where those who sustained a severe fall had more severe sarcopenia compared to the non-severe fall group (SMI ratio of 71% vs. 83%, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.041). In contrast to our finding, a study on Swedish women aged 75&#x02013;80 years reported that sarcopenia based on definitions including low muscle mass, i.e. lean mass assessed by DXA (European Working Group on Sarcopenia in Older People [EWGSOP2] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>], and Asian Working Group for Sarcopenia [AWGS] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]) was not associated to severe falls, whereas sarcopenia defined using only functional tests (Sarcopenia Definitions and Outcomes Consortium, SDOC) was [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. The discrepancies between our study and the other study may be attributed to several factors. Firstly, the patient cohorts differ in terms of age (our cohort had a higher mean age, 84 years compared to 78 years), sex (our study included both sexes, whereas the other study included only women), and functional status (only 18% of our participants could walk without assistance, compared to all participants in the other study). Furthermore, the study designs differ: our study uses case reports to define and categorize the severity of each fall, comparing severe to non-severe falls, and utilizes CT scan data from a near time frame, i.e., within six months of the fall, for sarcopenia assessment. In contrast, the other study defines fall injuries based on ICD-coded fall events over a seven-year follow-up period post-sarcopenia assessment. The methodologies also differ in terms of technique; our study employed 3-D CT scans, while the other used 2-D DXA.</p><p id="Par45">A low BMI is associated with a higher risk of sustaining a fall (non-injurious or not) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Little is known about the risk of severe falls. In our study, we saw a trend towards protective effect regarding fall severity with higher amount of adipose tissue, especially SAT, with a mean of 95&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;70 cm<sup>2</sup> in the severe fall group compared to 141&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;94 cm<sup>2</sup> in the non-severe fall group. Although both groups are considered normal weight on average according to BMI, BMI was higher in the non-severe fall group (BMI 22&#x000a0;kg/m<sup>2</sup> vs. 24&#x000a0;kg/m<sup>2</sup> in the non-severe fall group) as was the percentage of overweight patients (43% vs. 14%). Collectively, these findings suggest a protective role of adipose tissue, underscoring the importance of nutritional interventions in this population to prevent severe injurious falls. Consistent with our results, Ek et al. identified underweight as a risk factor for injurious falls [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>].</p><p id="Par46">Measurement of body composition using CT-scans could provide an easy and valuable method for assessing sarcopenia and nutritional status in the geriatric population. An automated software solution, like the one used in the present study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>], could offer a rapid and accurate tool for assessing body composition even from opportunistic CT scans, i.e. CT scans performed for any reason. In this case, no additional visits or scans are required, thereby keeping the assessment costs low. Considering that CT investigations are frequently performed in aging populations, they could offer an excellent opportunity to evaluate body composition, including muscle, adipose tissue, and bone in a large-scale screening.</p><p id="Par47">In our study, two different software solutions were used that both are reliable tools providing trustworthy body composition measurements. Until now radiological methods are mainly used for research [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>].</p><p id="Par48">In our study, males exhibited a higher risk of developing sarcopenia compared to females. This finding remained significant even after adjusting for nutritional status (BMI, SAT, and VAT). Several previous studies have reported similar results, indicating a higher prevalence of sarcopenia in males than in females [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. The underlying reasons are unclear and likely multifactorial, potentially involving hormonal differences between the sexes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. Regarding sex differences in severe falls, a previous study by Aryee et al. found a higher risk of severe falls in males than in females [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. Similarly, in our study, nearly twice as many males as females experienced a severe fall (17% vs. 9%).</p><p id="Par49">Interventions to improve skeletal muscle function to treat sarcopenia may also treat frailty as they both seem to lead to reduced muscle strength. Studies also suggest that sarcopenia is a risk factor for developing frailty [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Interestingly, no difference was seen regarding frailty (CFS) between severe and non-sever falls, but CFS correlated with SMI ratio (<italic>r</italic>=-0.288, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). The univariate regression analysis showed similar results where every step up on the clinical frailty scale led to a significant decrease of SMI ratio of 3.8%. CFS remained significant even when adjusted for other variables in the three multivariate models, suggesting frailty as an independent risk factor for sarcopenia or vice versa.</p><p id="Par50">Poor nutrition status is known to fasten the process of developing sarcopenia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. In our study, however, no association was found regarding sarcopenia and SF-MNA or RAPS. Similarly, those risk assessment scores did not differ between severe and non-severe falls.</p><p id="Par51">Even though DRFI is a valuable screening instrument for fall, it does not consider the severity of a fall. In accordance, our study showed no association between DFRI score and risk of severe falls.</p><p id="Par52">The European Working Group on Sarcopenia in Older People (EWGSOP) recommends the use of SARC-F questionnaire (acronym for strength, assistance walking, rise from a chair, climb stairs, and falls) as a first step to screen for sarcopenia in health care as it has a high specificity to predict low muscle strength [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Unfortunately, this questionnaire was not used in our clinic. Similarly, no functional tests, such as grip strength or low gait speed, were used regularly in clinical routine.</p><p id="Par53">A guideline published 2018 from the task force of the International Conference on Sarcopenia and Frailty Research (ICSFR) advocate that the treatment of sarcopenia should consist of physical activity as well as a protein-rich diet or protein supplementation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>].</p><p id="Par54">Even so, sarcopenia is not always equal to low fat mass, it can also present itself as sarcopenic obesity and this is more common in the geriatric population [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. In this phenotype fat infiltration usually can be found in muscles, leading to a poorer muscle function. This is contrary to the case of malnutrition where low adipose tissue is often present [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. In our cohort there was a small difference in IMAT between the severe fall- and the non-severe fall group, however non-significant. Increased adipose tissue correlated well with increased muscle mass where SAT was prominent which is in accordance with the assumption that our cohort is at risk of malnutrition with a median of 8 on the SF-MNA.</p><sec id="Sec12"><title>Limitations</title><p id="Par55">There are some limitations in our study. The number of observations in this study is low, with risk of underpower and falsely non-significant results. Many patients were lost due to CT scans that were not compatible with the DAFS software.</p><p id="Par56">As a retrospective cohort study design, it&#x02019;s at risk for several research biases. Even though the clinical assessment scales are well validated and reliable tools there may be risks of observer bias. Furthermore, there is a risk that some fall events were poorly or vaguely described in the case records, potentially leading to misclassification in the study. To address this, we conducted a comprehensive evaluation of each patient case, utilizing all available case record data including input from all professionals in the ward.</p><p id="Par57">Although most CT scans were conducted shortly before the fall event (with a median of 6 days before the fall), some patients had their CT scans several weeks post-incident. In these cases, low muscle mass could have resulted from immobilization following the fall, rather than pre-existing low muscle mass that increased the risk of a severe fall. However, the number of CT scans performed more than three months after the fall was low (7 scans, or 10%), likely having low impact on the overall data. Strengths of the study included the design that all data was collected from the same ward, with routines for reporting clinical assessment scores for all patients, and well-defined reporting system regarding fall incidents and severity.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par58">The conclusion of this study is that older patients who suffer a severe fall have less skeletal muscle quantity measured by CT-scan compared to patients that get mildly injured in the fall. Adipose tissue appears to have a protective effect in the event of a fall and in preventing sarcopenia, with subcutaneous adipose tissue providing the most significant protection. Therefore, diagnosing and treating sarcopenia and malnutrition may be crucial in reducing the severity of fall-related injuries in geriatric patients. An integrated assessment of muscle and adipose tissue in CT scans, e.g. in opportunistic screening or dedicated low dose CT scans, should thus be considered for future geriatric assessment. Once identified, preventive measures should be implemented to improve muscle and nutritional status.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We would like to thank Voronoi Health Analytics Inc. (Vancouver, Canada) for their kind support including the usage of analysis software in this study.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>NF, data collection, data analysis, manuscript writing; AS, data collection, data analysis, review and editing manuscript; AK, data analysis, review and editing manuscript; MW, data collection, data analysis, review and editing manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>Open access funding provided by Link&#x000f6;ping University.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The datasets generated and analyzed during the current study are not publicly available but are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par59">Ethical application was reviewed and approved by the Swedish Ethical Review Authority (2021&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;01425) as well as a supplementary application to use AI algorithms for the body composition measurements (2022-02053-02). The study was conducted according to the ethical standards of the institutional and/or national research committee and with the 1964 Helsinki declaration and its later amendments or comparable ethical standards. The requirement for informed consent was waived by the Swedish Ethical Review Authority.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par60">Not Applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par61">AS has received lecturer fees from UCB, AMGEN, and Tromp (within the field of osteoporosis).NF, AK and MW have no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>BMD</term><def><p id="Par62">Bone mineral density</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SKM</term><def><p id="Par63">Skeletal muscle</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CT</term><def><p id="Par64">Computed tomography</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SMI</term><def><p id="Par65">Skeletal muscle index</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CFS</term><def><p id="Par66">Clinical frailty score</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BMI</term><def><p id="Par67">Body mass index</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IMAT</term><def><p id="Par68">Intramuscular adipose tissue</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SAT</term><def><p id="Par69">Subcutaneous adipose tissue</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>VAT</term><def><p id="Par70">Visceral adipose tissue</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SARC-F</term><def><p id="Par71">Acronym for strength, assistance walking, rise from a chair, climb stairs, and falls)</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DXA</term><def><p id="Par72">Dual energy x-ray</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MRI</term><def><p id="Par73">Magnetic resonance imaging</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SD</term><def><p id="Par74">Standard deviations</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SF-MNA</term><def><p id="Par75">Mini nutritional assessment - short form</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RAPS</term><def><p id="Par76">Risk assessment pressure sore</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DFRI</term><def><p id="Par77">Downton fall risk index</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>M-EMS</term><def><p id="Par78">Modified elderly mobility scale</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PACS</term><def><p id="Par79">Picture archiving and communication system</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DAFS</term><def><p id="Par80">Data analysis facilitation suite</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ROI</term><def><p id="Par81">Regions of interest</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IQR</term><def><p id="Par82">Interquartile range</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>EWGSOP</term><def><p id="Par83">The european working group on sarcopenia in older people</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ICSFS</term><def><p id="Par84">International conference on sarcopenia and frailty research</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cruz-Jentoft</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bahat</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Boirie</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruy&#x000e8;re</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Cederholm</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sarcopenia: revised European consensus on definition and diagnosis</article-title><source>Age Ageing</source><year>2019</year><volume>48</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>16</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ageing/afy169</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30312372</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Cruz-Jentoft AJ, Bahat G, Bauer J, Boirie Y, Bruy&#x000e8;re O, Cederholm T, et al. Sarcopenia: revised European consensus on definition and diagnosis. Age Ageing. 2019;48(1):16&#x02013;31.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30312372</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anyene</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Caan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Popuri</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenchik</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Giri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Body composition from single versus multi-slice abdominal computed tomography: concordance and associations with colorectal cancer survival</article-title><source>J Cachexia Sarcopenia Muscle</source><year>2022</year><volume>13</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>2974</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jcsm.13080</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36052755</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Anyene I, Caan B, Williams GR, Popuri K, Lenchik L, Giri S, et al. Body composition from single versus multi-slice abdominal computed tomography: concordance and associations with colorectal cancer survival. J Cachexia Sarcopenia Muscle. 2022;13(6):2974&#x02013;84.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36052755</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mourtzakis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Prado</surname><given-names>CMM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lieffers</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Reiman</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>McCargar</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Baracos</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A practical and precise approach to quantification of body composition in cancer patients using computed tomography images acquired during routine care</article-title><source>Appl Physiol Nutr Metab</source><year>2008</year><volume>33</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>997</fpage><lpage>1006</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/H08-075</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18923576</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Mourtzakis M, Prado CMM, Lieffers JR, Reiman T, McCargar LJ, Baracos VE. A practical and precise approach to quantification of body composition in cancer patients using computed tomography images acquired during routine care. Appl Physiol Nutr Metab. 2008;33(5):997&#x02013;1006.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18923576</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shimada</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Doi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakakubo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Makino</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Impact of osteosarcopenia on disability and mortality among Japanese older adults</article-title><source>J Cachexia Sarcopenia Muscle</source><year>2023</year><volume>14</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>1107</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jcsm.13209</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36858820</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Shimada H, Suzuki T, Doi T, Lee S, Nakakubo S, Makino K, et al. Impact of osteosarcopenia on disability and mortality among Japanese older adults. J Cachexia Sarcopenia Muscle. 2023;14(2):1107&#x02013;16.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36858820</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chalhoub</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Cawthon</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ensrud</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Stefanick</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Kado</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Boudreau</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Risk of nonspine fractures in older adults with Sarcopenia, low bone mass, or both</article-title><source>J Am Geriatr Soc</source><year>2015</year><volume>63</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1733</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jgs.13605</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26310882</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Chalhoub D, Cawthon PM, Ensrud KE, Stefanick ML, Kado DM, Boudreau R, et al. Risk of nonspine fractures in older adults with Sarcopenia, low bone mass, or both. J Am Geriatr Soc. 2015;63(9):1733&#x02013;40.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26310882</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herrmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Engelke</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ebert</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000fc;ller-Deubert</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rudert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziouti</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Interactions between muscle and bone&#x02014;where physics meets biology</article-title><source>Biomolecules</source><year>2020</year><volume>10</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/biom10030432</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Herrmann M, Engelke K, Ebert R, M&#x000fc;ller-Deubert S, Rudert M, Ziouti F, et al. Interactions between muscle and bone&#x02014;where physics meets biology. Biomolecules. 2020;10(3):1&#x02013;30.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greco</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pietschmann</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Migliaccio</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Osteoporosis and sarcopenia increase frailty syndrome in the elderly</article-title><source>Front Endocrinol (Lausanne)</source><year>2019</year><volume>10</volume><issue>APR</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30723457</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Greco EA, Pietschmann P, Migliaccio S. Osteoporosis and sarcopenia increase frailty syndrome in the elderly. Front Endocrinol (Lausanne). 2019;10(APR):1&#x02013;10.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30723457</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Church</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Rockwood</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Theou</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A scoping review of the clinical Frailty Scale</article-title><source>BMC Geriatr</source><year>2020</year><volume>20</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12877-020-01801-7</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Church S, Rogers E, Rockwood K, Theou O. A scoping review of the clinical Frailty Scale. BMC Geriatr. 2020;20(1):1&#x02013;18.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zhang X, Huang P, Dou Q, Wang C, Zhang W, Yang Y et al. Falls among older adults with sarcopenia dwelling in nursing home or community: A meta-analysis. Clin Nutr [Internet]. 2020;39(1):33&#x02013;9. Available from: 10.1016/j.clnu.2019.01.002</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kaiser MJ, Bauer JM, Ramsch C, Uter W, Guigoz Y, Cederholm T et al. Validation of the Mini Nutritional Assessment short-form (MNA<sup>&#x000ae;</sup>-SF): A practical tool for identification of nutritional status. J Nutr Heal Aging [Internet]. 2009;13(9):782&#x02013;8. Available from: 10.1007/s12603-009-0214-7</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lindgren</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Unosson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Krantz</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ek</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A risk assessment scale for the prediction of pressure sore development: reliability and validity</article-title><source>J Adv Nurs</source><year>2002</year><volume>38</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>190</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2648.2002.02163.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11940132</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Lindgren M, Unosson M, Krantz AM, Ek AC. A risk assessment scale for the prediction of pressure sore development: reliability and validity. J Adv Nurs. 2002;38(2):190&#x02013;9.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11940132</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosendahl</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lundin-olsson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kallin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gustafson</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurtis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prediction of falls among older people in residential care facilities by the Downton index</article-title><source>Aging Clin Exp Res</source><year>2003</year><volume>15</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>142</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF03324492</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12889846</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Rosendahl E, Lundin-olsson L, Kallin K, Jensen J, Gustafson Y, Kurtis E. Prediction of falls among older people in residential care facilities by the Downton index. Aging Clin Exp Res. 2003;15(2):142&#x02013;7.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12889846</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Linder</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Winkvist</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sernert</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of the Swedish version of the Modified Elderly mobility scale (Swe-M-EMS) in patients with acute stroke</article-title><source>Clin Rehabil</source><year>2006</year><volume>20</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>584</fpage><lpage>97</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1191/0269215506cr972oa</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16894801</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Linder A, Winkvist L, Nilsson L, Sernert N. Evaluation of the Swedish version of the Modified Elderly mobility scale (Swe-M-EMS) in patients with acute stroke. Clin Rehabil. 2006;20(7):584&#x02013;97.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16894801</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sterling</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Connor</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonadies</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Geriatric falls: Injury severity is high and disproportionate to mechanism</article-title><source>J Trauma - Inj Infect Crit Care</source><year>2001</year><volume>50</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>116</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00005373-200101000-00021</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Sterling DA, O&#x02019;Connor JA, Bonadies J. Geriatric falls: Injury severity is high and disproportionate to mechanism. J Trauma - Inj Infect Crit Care. 2001;50(1):116&#x02013;9.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ye L, Liang R, Liu X, Li J, Yue J, Zhang X. Frailty and sarcopenia: A bibliometric analysis of their association and potential targets for intervention. Ageing Res Rev [Internet]. 2023;92(June):102111. Available from: 10.1016/j.arr.2023.102111</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gandham A, Gregori G, Johansson L, Larsson BAM, Johansson H, Harvey NC et al. Sarcopenia definitions and their association with injurious falls in older Swedish women from the Sahlgrenska University Hospital Prospective Evaluation of Risk of Bone fractures (SUPERB) study. Osteoporos Int [Internet]. 2024;35(11):1963&#x02013;72. Available from: 10.1007/s00198-024-07196-0</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">World Health Organization. WHO global report on falls. 2007;1&#x02013;47.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Landi F, Liperoti R, Russo A, Giovannini S, Tosato M, Capoluongo E et al. Sarcopenia as a risk factor for falls in elderly individuals: Results from the ilSIRENTE study. Clin Nutr [Internet]. 2012;31(5):652&#x02013;8. Available from: 10.1016/j.clnu.2012.02.007</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name><surname>Woo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Assantachai</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Auyeung</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name><surname>Iijima</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Asian Working Group for Sarcopenia: 2019 Consensus Update on Sarcopenia diagnosis and treatment</article-title><source>J Am Med Dir Assoc</source><year>2020</year><volume>21</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>300</fpage><lpage>e3072</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jamda.2019.12.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32033882</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Chen LK, Woo J, Assantachai P, Auyeung TW, Chou MY, Iijima K, et al. Asian Working Group for Sarcopenia: 2019 Consensus Update on Sarcopenia diagnosis and treatment. J Am Med Dir Assoc. 2020;21(3):300&#x02013;e3072.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32033882</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trevisan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Crippa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ek</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Welmer</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Sergi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Maggi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Nutritional status, body Mass Index, and the risk of Falls in Community-Dwelling older adults: a systematic review and Meta-analysis</article-title><source>J Am Med Dir Assoc</source><year>2019</year><volume>20</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>569</fpage><lpage>e5827</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jamda.2018.10.027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30554987</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">Trevisan C, Crippa A, Ek S, Welmer AK, Sergi G, Maggi S, et al. Nutritional status, body Mass Index, and the risk of Falls in Community-Dwelling older adults: a systematic review and Meta-analysis. J Am Med Dir Assoc. 2019;20(5):569&#x02013;e5827.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30554987</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ek</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rizzuto</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Fratiglioni</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Calder&#x000f3;n-Larra&#x000f1;aga</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnell</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sj&#x000f6;berg</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Risk factors for Injurious Falls in older adults: the role of sex and length of Follow-Up</article-title><source>J Am Geriatr Soc</source><year>2019</year><volume>67</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>246</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jgs.15657</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30496601</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Ek S, Rizzuto D, Fratiglioni L, Calder&#x000f3;n-Larra&#x000f1;aga A, Johnell K, Sj&#x000f6;berg L, et al. Risk factors for Injurious Falls in older adults: the role of sex and length of Follow-Up. J Am Geriatr Soc. 2019;67(2):246&#x02013;53.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30496601</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Dietz MV, Popuri K, Janssen L, Salehin M, Ma D, Chow VTY et al. Evaluation of a fully automated computed tomography image segmentation method for fast and accurate body composition measurements. Nutrition. 2025;129.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koitka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kroll</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Malamutmann</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Oezcelik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nensa</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fully automated body composition analysis in routine CT imaging using 3D semantic segmentation convolutional neural networks</article-title><source>Eur Radiol</source><year>2021</year><volume>31</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1795</fpage><lpage>804</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00330-020-07147-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32945971</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Koitka S, Kroll L, Malamutmann E, Oezcelik A, Nensa F. Fully automated body composition analysis in routine CT imaging using 3D semantic segmentation convolutional neural networks. Eur Radiol. 2021;31(4):1795&#x02013;804.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32945971</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Huang YF, Liu SP, Muo CH, Lai CY, Chang CT. Male sex and ageing are independent risk factors for Sarcopenia Stage in patients with chronic kidney Disease not yet on Dialysis. J Cachexia Sarcopenia Muscle. 2024;2684&#x02013;92.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sex differences in the prevalence and adverse outcomes of Sarcopenia and sarcopenic obesity in community dwelling elderly in East China using the AWGS criteria</article-title><source>BMC Endocr Disord</source><year>2019</year><volume>19</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12902-019-0432-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30606164</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="journal">Du Y, Wang X, Xie H, Zheng S, Wu X, Zhu X, et al. Sex differences in the prevalence and adverse outcomes of Sarcopenia and sarcopenic obesity in community dwelling elderly in East China using the AWGS criteria. BMC Endocr Disord. 2019;19(1):1&#x02013;11.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30606164</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Jiang Y, Xu B, Zhang K, Zhu W, Lian X, Xu Y et al. The association of lipid metabolism and sarcopenia among older patients: a cross-sectional study. Sci Rep [Internet]. 2023;13(1):1&#x02013;10. Available from: 10.1038/s41598-023-44704-4</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Aryee E, James SL, Hunt GM, Ryder HF. Identifying protective and risk factors for injurious falls in patients hospitalized for acute care: a retrospective case-control study. 2017;1&#x02013;9.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR28" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dent</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Morley</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Cruz-Jentoft</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Arai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kritchevsky</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Guralnik</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>International Clinical Practice guidelines for Sarcopenia (ICFSR): screening, diagnosis and management</article-title><source>J Nutr Heal Aging</source><year>2018</year><volume>22</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1148</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12603-018-1139-9</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28" publication-type="journal">Dent E, Morley JE, Cruz-Jentoft AJ, Arai H, Kritchevsky SB, Guralnik J, et al. International Clinical Practice guidelines for Sarcopenia (ICFSR): screening, diagnosis and management. J Nutr Heal Aging. 2018;22(10):1148&#x02013;61.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article>