<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Lancet Reg Health Eur</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Lancet Reg Health Eur</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Lancet Regional Health - Europe</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2666-7762</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11681880</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2666-7762(24)00341-7</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.lanepe.2024.101172</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">101172</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>HBV and HCV testing outcomes among marginalized communities in Italy, 2019&#x02013;2024: a prospective study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name><surname>Monti</surname><given-names>Monica</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name><surname>Caruso</surname><given-names>Teresita</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name><surname>Castellaccio</surname><given-names>Alice</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4"><name><surname>De Giorgi</surname><given-names>Irene</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5"><name><surname>Cavallini</surname><given-names>Gabriella</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au6"><name><surname>Manca</surname><given-names>Maria Laura</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au7"><name><surname>Lorini</surname><given-names>Serena</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au8"><name><surname>Marri</surname><given-names>Silvia</given-names></name><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">e</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au9"><name><surname>Petraccia</surname><given-names>Luisa</given-names></name><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">f</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au10"><name><surname>Madia</surname><given-names>Francesco</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au11"><name><surname>Stasi</surname><given-names>Cristina</given-names></name><xref rid="aff7" ref-type="aff">g</xref><xref rid="aff8" ref-type="aff">h</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au12"><name><surname>Carraresi</surname><given-names>Laura</given-names></name><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">e</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au13"><name><surname>Lorefice</surname><given-names>Elisabetta</given-names></name><xref rid="aff9" ref-type="aff">i</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au14"><name><surname>Bonelli</surname><given-names>Sara Irene</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au15"><name><surname>Nerli</surname><given-names>Alessandro</given-names></name><xref rid="aff11" ref-type="aff">j</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au16"><name><surname>Mudalal</surname><given-names>Mouheb M.A.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au17"><name><surname>Martini</surname><given-names>Lorenzo</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au18"><name><surname>Gitto</surname><given-names>Stefano</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au19"><name><surname>Carradori</surname><given-names>Eleonora</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au20"><name><surname>Xheka</surname><given-names>Adela</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au21"><name><surname>Bendini</surname><given-names>Irene</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au22"><name><surname>Lukolic&#x02019;</surname><given-names>Samuele</given-names></name><xref rid="aff10" ref-type="aff">k</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au23"><name><surname>Latella</surname><given-names>Lorenzo</given-names></name><xref rid="aff10" ref-type="aff">k</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au24"><name><surname>Aquilini</surname><given-names>Donatella</given-names></name><xref rid="aff11" ref-type="aff">j</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au25"><name><surname>Blanc</surname><given-names>Pierluigi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au26"><name><surname>Zignego</surname><given-names>Anna Linda</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">l</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au27"><name><surname>Gragnani</surname><given-names>Laura</given-names></name><email>laura.gragnani@unipi.it</email><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">l</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#x02217;</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>MASVE Interdepartmental Hepatology Center, Department of Experimental and Clinical Medicine, University of Florence, Center for Research and Innovation CRIA-MASVE, Firenze, Italy</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Department of Translational Research and of New Surgical and Medical Technologies, University of Pisa, Pisa, Italy</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>San Jacopo Hospital, Infectious Disease Unit, Pistoia, Italy</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>Department of Clinical and Experimental Medicine and Department of Mathematics, University of Pisa and University Hospital of Pisa, Pisa, Italy</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>e</label>Department of Neuroscience, Psychology, Drug Research and Child Health (NEUROFARBA), Section of Pharmacology, University of Florence, Florence, Italy</aff><aff id="aff6"><label>f</label>Poison Control Center Unit, Department of Emergency, Anesthesia and Critical Care Medicine, Policlinico Umberto I Hospital - Sapienza, University of Rome, Rome, Italy</aff><aff id="aff7"><label>g</label>Regional Health Agency of Tuscany, Florence, Italy</aff><aff id="aff8"><label>h</label>Department of Life Science, Health, and Health Professions - Link Campus University, Roma, Italy</aff><aff id="aff9"><label>i</label>San Giuseppe Hospital, Gastroenterology Unit, Empoli, Italy</aff><aff id="aff11"><label>j</label>Santo Stefano Hospital, Infectious Disease Unit, Prato, Italy</aff><aff id="aff10"><label>k</label>Department of Health Sciences, University of Florence, Florence, Italy</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x02217;</label>Corresponding author. Department of Translational Research and of New Surgical and Medical Technologies, University of Pisa, Pisa 56126, Italy. <email>laura.gragnani@unipi.it</email></corresp><fn id="fn1"><label>l</label><p id="ntpara0010">LG and ALZ equally contributed.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>09</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>2</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>09</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>49</volume><elocation-id>101172</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>3</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>25</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>26</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2024 The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="abs0010"><title>Summary</title><sec><title>Background</title><p>The health of the marginalized populations is crucial for public health and inequalities. The World Health Organization (WHO) Global Hepatitis Report 2024 stated that over 304 million people were living with Hepatitis B Virus (HBV)/Hepatitis C Virus (HCV) infection in 2022. We performed HBV/HCV screenings among marginalized communities to reveal hidden infections and link-to-care positive participants.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>From January 2019 to May 2024, finger-prick tests were used to conduct on-site screenings at non-profit organizations in Tuscany, Italy. Positive participants were referred to the closest outpatient clinic.</p></sec><sec><title>Findings</title><p>Eighty/1812 (4.4%) participants were Hepatitis B surface Antigen (HBsAg)+, mostly men (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;<italic>0.001</italic>) and non-Italian natives compared to those HBsAg- (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;<italic>0.001</italic>). Fifty-two/1812 (2.9%) were anti-HCV+ with a higher proportion of Italians (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;<italic>0.001</italic>) and lower education level (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.01) compared to the anti-HCV-. Intravenous drug use was an independent factor for being anti-HCV+ (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;<italic>0.0001</italic>). Among the HBsAg&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;individuals, 66.3% (53/80) were linked and 90.4% (48/53) retained in care (treated/monitored). Of the anti-HCV participants requiring clinical evaluation, 37.8% (14/37) were linked to care, and all the 11/14 (88.6%) viremic patients were successfully treated.</p></sec><sec><title>Interpretation</title><p>We found higher HBV/HCV positivity compared to national prevalences. Participation and linkage to care were successful. The young mean age (33.6&#x000a0;yrs) of HBsAg&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;individuals, primarily from regions with low vaccinal adherence, indicated geographical origin as a key risk factor. HCV positivity was associated with extreme marginality. The results stress the need to implement marginalized groups screening to target HBV/HCV hidden infections, reducing disparities in healthcare and advancing towards the WHO 2030 elimination goal.</p></sec><sec><title>Funding</title><p><funding-source id="gs5">Gilead Sciences</funding-source>; <funding-source id="gs6"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100007387</institution-id><institution>Fondazione Cassa di Risparmio di Pistoia e Pescia</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source>; <funding-source id="gs1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100009888</institution-id><institution>Regione Toscana</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source>.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Hepatitis B virus</kwd><kwd>Hepatitis C virus</kwd><kwd>Marginalized populations</kwd><kwd>Healthcare disparities</kwd><kwd>World Health Organization</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p id="p0010">
<boxed-text id="dtbox1"><caption><title>Research in context</title></caption><sec id="dtbox1sec1"><title>Evidence before this study</title><p id="p0015">As of May 2024, a PubMed search was conducted using the queries &#x0201c;Hepatitis B Virus (HBV) screening or testing&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;Hepatitis C Virus (HCV) screening or testing&#x0201d; &#x0201c;marginalized/underprivileged/vulnerable populations&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;viral hepatitis elimination&#x0201d;. The search revealed several studies focused on marginalized populations, predominantly conducted in the USA. Those performed in Europe often included small sample sizes or were conducted before the COVID-19 pandemic. Studies carried out in Italy primarily employed testing strategies targeting specific settings (mainly migrants) and usually did not address marginalized Italian natives.</p><p id="p0020">Overall, as previous reports have shown, the typical HBV and HCV screening strategies adopted in Europe to meet the World Health Organization&#x02019;s (WHO) goal of eliminating HBV and HCV as a public health threat by 2030 often do not include disadvantaged populations due to challenges in outreach, linkage to care, and low compliance. This exclusion hampers the viral hepatitis elimination plan and exemplifies health inequality, particularly among marginalized groups such as migrants and homeless people, a topic of growing concern for the public health community.</p></sec><sec id="dtbox1sec2"><title>Added value of this study</title><p id="p0025">The higher HBV/HCV prevalence we found in marginalized settings compared to the general Italian population highlights the need to expand screening efforts to vulnerable groups to target residual/hidden infections. This would reduce disparities in access to treatment and help progress toward the WHO&#x02019;s goal to end viral hepatitis as a public health threat by 2030. Our findings suggest that an integrated on-site testing strategy, involving navigators and social workers, is likely the key to achieving high adherence, linkage, and retention in the care of positive cases, even without financial incentives for participation. The results also indicate a difference between HBV and HCV positive subgroups: while HBV is more prevalent among economic migrants and refugees temporarily living in shelters, who do not typically experience social exclusion in their home countries, the profile of the HCV-positive individual is one marked by extreme marginalization, risky behaviors, and a lack of health-related priorities. These insights could help in better targeting testing interventions.</p></sec><sec id="dtbox1sec3"><title>Implications of all the available evidence</title><p id="p0030">Our study demonstrates that the integrated on-site testing model we adopted could serve as a useful framework for policymakers tasked with reassessing existing health policies and systems related to viral hepatitis elimination at national and European levels. Additionally, Italy is a first port of call for many migrants seeking to reach the European Union. The provision of prompt HBV/HCV screening interventions could facilitate clinical management in their final destination countries enhancing individual health and social status. To achieve global HBV and HCV elimination, it is essential to develop strategies that improve healthcare accessibility while building trust and engagement with marginalized communities.</p></sec></boxed-text>
</p><sec id="sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0035">Hepatitis B Virus (HBV) and Hepatitis C Virus (HCV) are the most common causes of chronic liver disease worldwide.<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> The Global Hepatitis Report 2024, recently released by the World Health Organization (WHO), states that over 304 million of people were living with HCV or HBV infection in 2022,<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> making HBV and HCV two of the top ten &#x0201c;infectious killers&#x0201d; globally.<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> Almost 1.3 million people die every year, due to chronic diseases caused by HBV and HCV.<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> Furthermore, viral hepatitis is responsible for liver cancer (hepatocellular carcinoma- HCC), that is the most common primary liver cancer and the third leading cause of cancer-related mortality worldwide.<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref></p><p id="p0040">Because chronic liver disease is asymptomatic until the late stages, estimates suggest that 40&#x02013;80% of affected people are not aware that they are infected.<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> Due to the high prevalence of chronic liver disease in developing countries, they bear a higher burden of morbidity and mortality for hepatic causes.<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> For instance, it is estimated that 5&#x02013;10% of adults in East Asia and Sub Saharan Africa may be infected with chronic HBV infection.<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> In 2016, the WHO announced the goal to eliminate viral hepatitis as a public health threat by 2030.<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> As stated by the last report, this important accomplishment requires a global action although, currently, there are still several gaps in HBV and HCV elimination policies adopted by the countries.<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref></p><p id="p0045">An effective strategy for HCV elimination is leveraging the concept of &#x0201c;micro-elimination&#x0201d;.<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> Micro-elimination is a targeted approach aimed at reducing HCV infection rates within specific high-risk groups, geographic areas, or settings rather than attempting to eliminate the virus across entire populations at once. These focused interventions are designed to address each group's unique challenges and needs, ultimately contributing to the broader global HCV elimination goals set by WHO.<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> Micro-elimination approaches should adhere to specific criteria, although these may need adjustment based on epidemiological contexts and geographic locations.<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> While this strategy was successfully used for HCV infection, there are few examples of micro-elimination studies regarding HBV.<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref></p><p id="p0050">In addition, disparities in care and outcomes among underserved populations such as the homeless, marginalized people, and migrants are of growing interest to public health. The prevention, identification, and timely management of infections caused by HBV and HCV, are necessary health interventions to provide health care that is accessible to all. These interventions are essential in improving the living conditions of the vulnerable people. It will aid in ceasing the spread of diseases due to HBV and HCV that are intended to be eliminated in the future, in accordance with the WHO directives.<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref></p><p id="p0055">Here, we report results from a screening project aimed at the identification and linkage to care of Hepatitis B surface Antigen (HBsAg) and anti-HCV positive individuals. The project was conducted in the metropolitan areas of Florence, Prato, and Pistoia, three cities in Tuscany, a central Italian region. Testing campaigns were performed on-site in different local charities, such as meal centers, shelters for migrants, and help centers for marginalized people.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>Methods</title><p id="p0060">A prospective study to identify and, when necessary, treat HBV and HCV infection was carried out by performing on-site screening sessions at different charities and shelters operating in the metropolitan areas of Firenze, Prato and Pistoia, Tuscany, Italy. The sites included non-profit organizations providing support to those in need (charities), such as meal centers, shelters for migrants, food banks, Italian language schools for foreigners, and religious gathering places. The charities operating in the area covered by the study were first contacted by phone or email to schedule an in-person or online meeting to explain the objectives and methods of the screening project in detail. Community navigators at the non-profit organizations that agreed to host the testing sessions, received specialized training to provide charity users with accurate information about the testing. Posters and leaflets announcing the upcoming sessions were available throughout the charities at least two weeks before the screenings.</p><p id="p0065">All the charity users &#x02265;18 years of age were eligible for testing unless the presence of psychiatric disorders or language barriers that would prevent from correctly understanding of the testing aims, consenting or participation in the study. Cultural mediators were recruited for the sessions at shelters for immigrants (mostly Urdu, Arabic and Bengali speakers, depending on the geographical origin of the individuals attending the charity). Healthcare personnel involved in the screening could speak French, English, Albanian and Levantine Arabic. The number of cultural mediators and navigators depended on the number of users/charity.</p><p id="p0070">The healthcare personnel team included a physician, three researchers and a nurse. After a short interview to collect a brief medical history and inform the participants about the screening&#x02019;s aim, those who agreed to be tested signed an informed consent form. The form was available in different languages (Italian, English, French, Chinese, Albanian, Arabic and Spanish).</p><p id="p0075">The interview was useful in determining possible risk factors for HBV and HCV infection such as previous or current use of intravenous (IV) injected drugs, unprotected sex, familial exposure, previous surgeries or blood transfusions. Questions about comorbidities and education level were also included in the survey.</p><p id="p0080">Rapid Diagnostic tests (RDT) for HBsAg (Abbott Rapid Diagnostics, USA; sensitivity: 97.2% [95% CI: 93.1, 99.2]; specificity: 98.5% [95% CI: 95.7, 99.7])<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref> and anti-HCV positivity (Hangzhou All Test Biotech Co., Ltd, China, distributed by ScreenItalia, Italy; sensitivity: 100% ([95% CI:99:4%&#x02013;100%]; specificity: 100% [95% CI:99: 8%&#x02013;100%]) were performed on whole blood obtained via a finger prick.</p><p id="p0085">HBsAg and anti-HCV positive participants were advised to attend a further evaluation appointment at the nearest outpatient clinic that had previously agreed to participate in the study. The healthcare personnel were able to make appointments immediately after communicating the test results or, at the latest, the day after, to provide easy and quick access to care. Positive participants were referred to the following outpatient clinics of the centers participating in the study: MaSVE Interdepartmental Hepatology Center, University of Florence, Florence; Infectious Disease Unit, &#x0201c;San Jacopo&#x0201d; Hospital, Pistoia; Infectious Disease Unit, &#x0201c;Santo Stefano&#x0201d; Hospital, Prato; Gastroenterology Unit, &#x0201c;San Giuseppe&#x0201d; Hospital, Empoli.</p><p id="p0090">Linkage to care consisted of clinic appointments, assessment of viremia, liver function tests and where possible, a liver FibroScan (Echosens, Paris, France). An abdomen ultrasound was also performed at the initial appointment. According to a previous study,<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref> two different linkages to care outcomes were assessed: linked to care (attended one clinic appointment) and retained in care (attended &#x0003e;1 clinic appointment), meaning that patients were monitored or received therapy, based on the evaluation of clinicians. HBV and HCV treatments offered were in accordance with the European guidelines.<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref></p><p id="p0095">HBsAg negative participants were referred to the local disease control and prevention center to assess whether they were susceptible to HBV vaccination.</p><p id="p0100">The Ethical Committee of Area Vasta Centro provided ethical approval for this study (evaluation code: 17886_bio, updated after the COVID-19 pandemic -10/18/2022- with the new code 22562_spe). All research was conducted in accordance with both the Declarations of Helsinki and Istanbul. All participants gave written consent.</p><sec id="sec2.1"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="p0105">The primary endpoints, i.e., the prevalence of HBsAg and anti-HCV, were detected by rapid tests. Missing data (regarding unprotected sex and education level) were excluded from the analysis. Categorical variables were presented using frequencies and percentages. Continuous variables were summarized as mean (SD) if normally distributed (assessed by Shapiro&#x02013;Wilk test) or median (IQR) otherwise.</p><p id="p0110">Differences in continuous variables were assessed using Student t-tests or Mann&#x02013;Whitney U tests, as appropriate, while categorical variables were compared using &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup> or Fisher's exact tests. In the case of more than 2 categories and <italic>p</italic> was significant on the &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup> test, the residuals were analyzed to see which categories contributed to significance.</p><p id="p0115">Two multivariate logistic regression models were fitted, one for HBV positivity and one for HCV positivity. Independent variables included sex, age, comorbidities (e.g., diabetes, hypertension), and risk factors (e.g., intravenous drug use, blood transfusion). Odds ratios (ORs) and 95% confidence intervals (CIs) were calculated to assess the strength of the associations.</p><p id="p0120">If necessary, the <italic>p</italic> level was set at 0.05, adjusted for multiple comparison. Statistical analyzes were performed using Stata/SE version 17.0 (StataCorp, College Station, TX, USA) and R version 4.4.1.</p><p id="p0125">World regions were classified according to the United Nation Geoscheme.<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref></p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><title>Role of the funding sources</title><p id="p0130">Gilead Sciences; Fondazione Cassa di Risparmio di Pistoia e Pescia; Regione Toscana gave their unconditioned contribution to the study and did not have any role in study design, in collection, analysis, and interpretation of data, in the writing of the report, and in the decision to submit the paper for publication.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>Results</title><p id="p0135">From January 2019 to May 2024, a total of 75 testing sessions were performed. The testing activity was stopped during the COVID-19 pandemic from March 2020 to January 2022. Considering the average number of daily users for each charity hosting the sessions, 2203 individuals were approached and invited to participate. Among them, 1812 (82.4%) agreed to HBV and HCV testing as shown in the flow chart reported in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>.<fig id="fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Flow chart summarizing the study outcomes.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig></p><p id="p0140">The main characteristics of participants, overall and by HBsAg and anti-HCV status, are reported in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;1</xref>. The participants were mostly males (75%), mean age was 38&#x000a0;<bold>&#x000b1;</bold>&#x000a0;14.9 years and Italy was the most represented country of origin (13.5%), followed by Bangladesh (13.1%) and Morocco (11%). The heatmap in panel A of <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref> visually represents the geographical origin of the total population, while the geographical origin of the HBsAg+ and anti-HCV&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;participants is shown in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>, panels B and C respectively.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Characteristics of the study population, overall, and by HBsAg and anti-HCV status.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Characteristic</th><th>Total (1812)</th><th>HBsAg&#x02212; (1732)</th><th>HBsAg+ (80)</th><th><italic>p</italic></th><th>Anti-HCV&#x02212; (1760)</th><th>Anti-HCV+ (52)</th><th><italic>p</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Age, years, mean &#x000b1; SD</td><td>38&#x000a0;<bold>&#x000b1;</bold>&#x000a0;14.9</td><td>38.5&#x000a0;<bold>&#x000b1;</bold>&#x000a0;14.93</td><td>33.6&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;12.4</td><td align="char"><italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;<italic>0.001</italic></td><td>38.6&#x000a0;<bold>&#x000b1;</bold>&#x000a0;14.9</td><td>49.2&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;12.6</td><td align="char"><italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;<italic>0.0001</italic></td></tr><tr><td>Sex</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Males</td><td>1365</td><td>1292 (74.6%)</td><td>73 (91%)</td><td align="char"><italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;<italic>0.001</italic></td><td>1322 (75%)</td><td>43 (82.7%)</td><td align="char"><italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;<italic>0.4003</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Females</td><td>447</td><td>440 (25.4%)</td><td>7 (9%)</td><td/><td>438 (25%)</td><td>9 (17.3%)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Country of origin</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Italy</td><td>245</td><td>244 (14%)</td><td>1 (1.3%)</td><td align="char"><italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;<italic>0.001</italic></td><td>218 (12.4%)</td><td>27 (51.9%)</td><td align="char"><italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;<italic>0.0001</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Others</td><td>1567</td><td>1488 (86%)</td><td>79 (98.7%)</td><td/><td>1542 (87.6%)</td><td>25 (48.1%)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Type of charity</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td align="char"><italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;<italic>0.001</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Shelters for immigrants</td><td>708</td><td>668 (38.5%)</td><td>40 (50%)</td><td align="char"><italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;<italic>0.05</italic></td><td>701 (39.8%)</td><td>7 (13.5%)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Meal centers</td><td>592</td><td>564 (32.6%)</td><td>28 (35%)</td><td/><td>560 (31.8%)</td><td>32 (61.5%)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Food banks</td><td>141</td><td>140 (8.1%)</td><td>1 (1.3%)</td><td/><td>135 (7.7%)</td><td>6 (11.5%)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Schools for foreigners</td><td>184</td><td>177 (10.2%)</td><td>7 (8.8%)</td><td/><td>182 (10.3%)</td><td>2 (3.8%)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Religious gathering center</td><td>93</td><td>92 (5.3%)</td><td>1 (1.3%)</td><td/><td>91 (5.2%)</td><td>2 (3.8%)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Other</td><td>94</td><td>91 (5.3%)</td><td>3 (3.8%)</td><td/><td>91 (5.2%)</td><td>3 (5.8%)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Comorbidity</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Hypertension</td><td>95</td><td>91 (5.3%)</td><td>4 (5%)</td><td align="char"><italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;<italic>0.3626</italic></td><td>92 (5.2%)</td><td>3 (5.8%)</td><td align="char"><italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;<italic>0.7417</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Diabetes</td><td>79</td><td>76 (4.4%)</td><td>3 (3.8%)</td><td align="char"><italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003e;&#x000a0;<italic>0.999</italic></td><td>76 (4.3%)</td><td>3 (5.8%)</td><td align="char"><italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;<italic>0.4705</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Dyslipidemia</td><td>9</td><td>8 (0.5%)</td><td>1 (1.3%)</td><td align="char"><italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;<italic>0.3346</italic></td><td>9 (0.5%)</td><td>0</td><td align="char"><italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003e;&#x000a0;<italic>0.999</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Other</td><td>316</td><td>307 (17.7%)</td><td>9 (11.3%)</td><td align="char"><italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;<italic>0.1737</italic></td><td>290 (16.5%)</td><td>26 (50%)</td><td align="char"><italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;<italic>0.0001</italic></td></tr><tr><td>Risk factors</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;IV drugs</td><td>174</td><td>169 (9.8%)</td><td>5 (6.3%)</td><td align="char"><italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;<italic>0.4324</italic></td><td>143 (8.1%)</td><td>31 (59.6%)</td><td align="char"><italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;<italic>0.0001</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Surgeries</td><td>220</td><td>214 (12.4%)</td><td>6 (7.5%)</td><td align="char"><italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;<italic>0.2866</italic></td><td>213 (12.1%)</td><td>7 (13.5%)</td><td align="char"><italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;<italic>0.4949</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Blood transfusions</td><td>45</td><td>42 (2.4%)</td><td>3 (3.8%)</td><td align="char"><italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;<italic>0.4328</italic></td><td>43 (2.4%)</td><td>2 (3.8%)</td><td align="char"><italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;<italic>0.3186</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Unprotected sex<xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td>510/1361</td><td>495/1308 (37.8%)</td><td>15/53 (28.3%)</td><td align="char"><italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;<italic>0.1927</italic></td><td>493/1323 (38.3%)</td><td>17/38 (44.7%)</td><td align="char"><italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;<italic>0.3961</italic></td></tr><tr><td>Education<xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;None</td><td>147/1256</td><td>136/1210 (11.2%)</td><td>11/46 (23.9%)</td><td align="char"><italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;<italic>0.087</italic></td><td>146/1211 (11.9%)</td><td>1/35 (2.9%)</td><td align="char"><italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;<italic>0.01</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Less than high school</td><td>534/1256</td><td>516/1210 (42.6%)</td><td>18/46 (39.1%)</td><td/><td>510/1211 (41.8%)</td><td>24/35 (68.6%)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;High school</td><td>464/1256</td><td>449/1210 (37.1%)</td><td>15/46 (32.6%)</td><td/><td>454/1211 (37.2%)</td><td>10/35 (28.6%)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;More than high school</td><td>111/1256</td><td>109/1210 (9%)</td><td>2/46 (4.3%)</td><td/><td>111/1211 (9.1%)</td><td>0</td><td/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>HBsAg&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;hepatitis B virus surface antigen; HCV&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;hepatitis C virus.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl1fna"><label>a</label><p id="ntpara0015">Data are available for a subgroup of participants as detailed in the table.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="fig2"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Geographical origin of participants.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig></p><p id="p0145">Eighty/1812 (4.4%) participants were found to be positive (+) for HBsAg and 52/1812 (2.9%) for the anti-HCV. Two individuals were both HBsAg+ and anti-HCV+.</p><sec id="sec3.1"><title>HBsAg positivity related outcomes</title><p id="p0150">A higher proportion of those who were HBsAg+ were men (91% vs 74.6%; <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;<italic>0.001</italic>), and non-Italian natives compared to those who were HBsAg- (98.7% vs 86%; <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;<italic>0.001</italic>). Moreover, HBsAg&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;individuals had a significantly younger mean age (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;<italic>0.001</italic>) (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;1</xref>). The &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup> test showed an association with the geographical origins of the participants,<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref> as reported in <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;3</xref> (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;<italic>0.05</italic>). The analysis of residual showed a significant difference regarding HBsAg positivity (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;<italic>0.001</italic>) between participants coming from Eastern Asia (12%) and those coming from Western Asia (no HBsAg&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;individuals).<fig id="fig3"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Geographical origin of the HBsAg positive and anti-HCV-positive individuals, based on World regions classified according to the United Nation Geoscheme.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr3"/></fig></p><p id="p0155">Details about the type of charity that hosted the testing sessions, the presence of comorbidity, risk factors and education levels were also reported in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;1</xref>. Overall, 50% of the HBsAg&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;participants were recent immigrants living in shelters. A significant association between location and HBV positivity (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;<italic>0.05</italic>) emerged from a &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup> test performed on the hosting charities and test positivity. The analysis of residuals showed higher HBV positivity in &#x0201c;shelters for immigrants&#x0201d; (5.6%, 40/708) and &#x0201c;meal centers&#x0201d; (4.7%, 28/592) compared to &#x0201c;food banks&#x0201d; (0.7%, 1/141) (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;<italic>0.01</italic> for both comparisons).</p><p id="p0160">The male sex was found to be the only predictive variable of HBsAg positivity (OR&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3.55, 95% CI: 1.62&#x02013;7.77, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;<italic>0.01</italic>), at regression analysis.</p><p id="p0165">HBsAg&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;individuals were referred to the closest outpatient clinics. Linkage to care uptake for the HBsAg&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;participants was 66.3% (53/80), considering that 2 individuals were aware of the infection and already on treatment (2/80, 2.5%) (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>). The retention in care outcome was reached for 48/53 (90.6%) patients, as 5/53 (9.4%) were lost after the initial clinical assessment visit. The main liver and viral parameters of the retained in care group are reported in <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;2</xref>. Fibroscan evaluation was available for 38/48 (79%) and showed overall mild liver damage (<xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;2</xref>). Twelve/48 (25%) participants were eligible for treatment and started on Entecavir (<xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;2</xref>), while regular monitoring appointments were scheduled for the remaining patients. All linked-to-care HBsAg&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;individuals were tested for Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV) and Hepatitis D Virus (HDV) infection markers, and no coinfections were found.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2"><label>Table&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Characteristics of the linked to care HBsAg and anti-HCV positive patients.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Complementary test and administered treatment</th><th>HBsAg+ (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;48)</th><th>Anti-HCV+ (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;14)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Analytical parameter, median (IQR)</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;AST, U/L</td><td>25 (11&#x02013;35)</td><td>32 (21&#x02013;34)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;ALT, U/L</td><td>25 (18&#x02013;36)</td><td>41 (34&#x02013;59)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;GGT, U/L</td><td>22 (19&#x02013;32)</td><td>37 (20&#x02013;92)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Alkaline phosphatase, U/L</td><td>57 (55&#x02013;76)</td><td>67 (57&#x02013;69)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Platelets, 10<sup>3</sup> U/&#x003bc;L</td><td>218 (186&#x02013;246)</td><td>230 (151&#x02013;260)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Albumin g/dL, mean&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;SD</td><td>4.4&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.4</td><td>4.3&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.3</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Bilirubin (mg/dL), mean&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;SD</td><td>0.7&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.3</td><td>0.5&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.3</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;INR, mean&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;SD</td><td>1.05&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.1</td><td>0.93&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.1</td></tr><tr><td>HBV DNA, IU/mL, median (IQR)</td><td>2105 (589&#x02013;9638)</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>HCV-RNA, IU/mL, median (IQR)</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>2,380,000 (931,750&#x02013;2,655,000)</td></tr><tr><td>HCV genotype, n (%)</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>7 (50%)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;1a</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>3 (43%)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;1b</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>1 (14%)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;3</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>3 (43%)</td></tr><tr><td>HBV/HCV positivity, n (%)</td><td>2 (4%)</td><td>2 (14%)</td></tr><tr><td>Fibrosis grade (FibroScan&#x000ae;), n (%)</td><td>38 (48%)</td><td>10 (19%)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;F<sub>0</sub>&#x02013;F<sub>1</sub></td><td>33 (87%)</td><td>7 (70%)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;F<sub>2</sub></td><td>4 (10%)</td><td>1 (10%)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;F<sub>3</sub></td><td>1 (3%)</td><td>0</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;F<sub>4</sub></td><td>0</td><td>2 (20%)</td></tr><tr><td>Anti-HBV treatment, n (%)</td><td>12 (25%)</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Entecavir</td><td>12 (100%)</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Anti-HCV treatment, n (%)</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>11 (79%)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Epclusa</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>6 (55%)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Maviret</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>5 (45%)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;SVR, n (%)</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>11 (100%)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>HBV&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;hepatitis B virus; HCV&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;hepatitis C virus; IQR&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;interquartile range; AST&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;aspartate aminotransferase (normal range&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;5&#x02013;45 U/L); ALT&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;alanine aminotransferase (normal range&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;5&#x02013;45 U/L); GGT&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;gamma-glutamyl transferase (normal range&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;7&#x02013;55 U/L); AP=Alkaline phosphatase (normal range&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;45&#x02013;115 U/L); Platelets (normal range&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;140&#x02013;450&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>3</sup>); Albumin (normal range&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3.6&#x02013;4.9&#x000a0;g/dL); Bilirubin (normal range&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.1&#x02013;1.1&#x000a0;mg/dL); SD&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;standard deviation; INR&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;international normalized ratio; SVR&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;sustained virological response. The distribution of continuous variables was assessed using the Shapiro&#x02013;Wilk normality test. Continuous variables were reported as mean (SD) if normally distributed, while for not normally distributed variables, data were presented as median (IQR) otherwise.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><title>Anti-HCV positivity related outcomes</title><p id="p0170">A higher proportion of Italian natives was present among the anti-HCV&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;participants compared to the anti-HCV- (51.9% vs 12.4%; <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;<italic>0.001</italic>) (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;1</xref>). Results of &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup> test on the geographical origins of the participants<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref> as reported in <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>, showed a significant association with anti-HCV+ (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;<italic>0.05</italic>). The analysis of residuals demonstrated a significantly higher HCV positivity rate (11%, 27/245) among participants born in Italy compared to those from Southern Asia (0%, 0/6) and North Africa (2.2%, 7/313) (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;<italic>0.05</italic> in both comparisons).</p><p id="p0175">Anti-HCV&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;individuals had a mean age of 49.2&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;12.6 years, and 37/52 (71.2%) were younger than baby-boomers (born between 1946 and 1964), a high-risk birth cohort for HCV exposure.</p><p id="p0180">Details about the type of charity that hosted the testing sessions, the presence of comorbidity, risk factors and education levels were also reported in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;1</xref>. The anti-HCV&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;participants were most likely meal center users. The &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup> test indicated a significant association between the location where individuals were contacted and their HCV positivity status (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;<italic>0.05</italic>). The analysis of residuals revealed that the proportion of HCV-positive individuals was significantly higher in &#x0201c;meal centers&#x0201d; (5.4%, 32/592) and &#x0201c;food banks&#x0201d; (4.4%, 6/141) compared to &#x0201c;shelters for immigrants&#x0201d; (1%, 7/708) (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;<italic>0.05</italic> for both the comparisons).</p><p id="p0185">A previous or current intravenous (IV) drug use significantly correlated with the anti-HCV positivity (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;<italic>0.001</italic>) (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;1</xref>). A multivariate logistic regression analysis identified the use of IV drugs as an independent factor for being anti-HCV+ (OR&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;16.52, 95% CI: 9.25&#x02013;29.49, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;<italic>0.0001</italic>).</p><p id="p0190">Among the anti-HCV&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;participants, most individuals had an education level lower than high school (68.6%; <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;<italic>0.01</italic>) (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;1</xref>). Fifteen/52 (28.8%) were previously treated.</p><p id="p0195">The 37/52 (71.2%) anti-HCV&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;individuals requiring linkage to care were referred to the closest outpatient clinics but 23/37 (62.2%) refused or did not attend the first clinic appointment. Fourteen/37 (37.8%) patients were linked and further retained in care (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>). Of the 14 anti-HCV individuals, 3/14 (21.4%) had negative viremia and 11/14 (88.6%) patients had an active infection; all the viremic individuals underwent an antiviral treatment and reached an SVR (<xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;2</xref>). No HIV coinfections were found in the linked to care anti-HCV&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;patients.</p><p id="p0200">The major liver and viral data of the 14 anti-HCV&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;participants are detailed in <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;2</xref>. Liver damage evaluated by Fibroscan was available for 10/14 (71.4%) patients and 2/10 (20%) were cirrhotic. Three patients were admitted to a rehabilitation program to treat alcohol addiction (data not shown).</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec4"><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0205">Compared to the general population, marginalized individuals are at higher risk of infectious diseases and may encounter unique barriers in the receipt of health care. Usual screening strategies adopted to reach the WHO goal to eliminate viral hepatitis as a public health threat by 2030, generally do not include disadvantaged people due to problems in the approach, linkage to care, and low compliance. Initiatives focused on underserved populations employing a micro-elimination approach are reported mostly for HCV.<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref> As stated by Lazarus and coworkers, micro-elimination approaches should adhere to specific criteria, although these may need adjustment based on epidemiological contexts and geographic locations.<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> Despite our study does not meet&#x000a0;all the criteria to be defined as a micro-elimination intervention according to Lazarus and colleagues,<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> the sample size, on-site strategy, and results in terms of participation, prevalence found, and linkage to care could serve as an important model for stakeholders, paving the way for future micro-elimination projects targeting similar populations.</p><p id="p0210">The health inequity of groups of the population, such as migrants and homeless people is a theme of growing interest for the public health community. Screening interventions, such as HBV and HCV testing campaigns, are essential in improving the living conditions of marginalized populations and could help in reducing the high incidence of liver cancer recently reported among people living in economically disadvantaged areas of Europe.<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref></p><p id="p0215">One of the key points to ensure the success of the testing campaign is the method of recruitment as barriers can increase hesitancy regarding testing. Studies analyzing different aspects of this issue can be very useful in repeating successful strategies and improving possible biases. Nevertheless, we have to take into account that every geographical area has a different social context, and screening campaign strategies as well as health needs and barriers in linkage to care and management of the clinical path. This may require an adjustment to the local social environment.</p><p id="p0220">Our study had a high success in terms participation with an 82.4% rate of acceptance to get tested. We chose the onsite strategy: a team of healthcare personnel performed the testing directly at the charity and communicated the result within a short amount of time (usually 10&#x02013;15&#x000a0;min). Previous studies reported different acceptance rates for screening, depending on the category of the screened population and the strategies employed. A very satisfactory response rate (97.6%) was reported by Sahajian and colleague in Lyon, France.<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref> However, the study sample mostly included participants who consulted health centers of their own accord.<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref> Another successful strategy employed a voucher system of reimbursement for agreeing to undergo testing or completing a survey<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> that is especially effective since a major problem for marginalized people is often the lack of money.<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref> Gelberg and colleagues reported an 83% response rate to an HCV exposure testing campaign among homeless adults in Los Angeles, USA where the participants received cash incentives for their involvement.<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref></p><p id="p0225">Overall, despite the fact that we did not offer any reimbursements as the Italian law does not allow it, the participation response to our screening campaign was more than satisfactory. This is likely due to the large number of meals distributed daily by the centers running free meal programs, resulting in a high number of potential participants who can be screened in a short amount of time. Also, recent immigrants who are still not employed, spend most of their time in the shelters where they live and are easily approachable.</p><p id="p0230">In addition, we obtained higher participation percentages in the smaller settings where the volunteers and the director had an established relationship with the majority of users. Previous analyses reported that, in some cases, the relationship with health and social care professionals was a barrier because they treated people experiencing homelessness without empathy.<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr"><sup>26</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref> On the other hand, the improvement of shelter service and staff collaborations in the dissemination of information about infectious disease could assist higher numbers of people to link to health care.<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28</sup></xref> One of the reasons marginalized people avoid tests and treatment is mistrust: in some cases, they perceive that they are not a priority for a shelter&#x02019;s staff, healthcare providers and social workers.<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr"><sup>29</sup></xref></p><p id="p0235">The HBsAg 4.4% prevalence we reported in the setting of vulnerable individuals is higher than those recorded at national levels on the general population. In fact, Sagnelli et&#x000a0;al. stated that only 0.8% of individuals born in Italy were HBsAg+ in 2022<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr"><sup>30</sup></xref> and the Global Health Observatory of the WHO reports a 2022 prevalence of 0.51% in Italy.<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr"><sup>31</sup></xref></p><p id="p0240">Only 1/80 (1.3%) of the HBsAg&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;participants was born in Italy. This is in line with the progressive reduction of HBV endemicity in our country over the last 50 years due to the universal HBV vaccination since 1991.<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr"><sup>30</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr"><sup>32</sup></xref> Therefore, the 4.4% prevalence of HBsAg we found is due mainly to immigrants who are not vaccinated against HBV as already reported and discussed by Sagnelli et&#x000a0;al..<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr"><sup>30</sup></xref> In this regard, the WHO Regional Office for Europe urged the host countries to set up HBV vaccination policies for all unvaccinated migrants. In Italy, the vaccination is accessible and free for anyone who requests it. For this reason, according to the Italian guidelines,<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr"><sup>33</sup></xref> we referred all the HBsAg- individuals to the local disease control and prevention centers to assess if they were susceptible to vaccination and receive the shots if needed.</p><p id="p0245">A very alarming finding is the young age of the HBsAg&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;participants. This is concerning for the patient liver health as, in this setting, other risk factors for liver damage are frequently concomitant (i.e., alcohol abuse, especially for homeless people), making the hepatic disease rapidly evolving. In addition, it is conceivable that young adults potentially have more opportunities to spread the infection, due to their lifestyle. Since many countries have free vaccination programs, the young age of HBV&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;confirms, as already discussed, the low compliance to the recommended HBV-immunization, in line with previous results regarding similar settings<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> and this further stresses the need for dedicated immunization plans.</p><p id="p0250">According to previous reports,<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr"><sup>38</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr"><sup>39</sup></xref> our results showed that HBsAg positivity was more frequent in males.</p><p id="p0255">We could not determine any risk factor associated with HBV infection; thus, the geographical origin from endemic areas with low vaccination compliance emerged as the main cause of HBsAg positivity.</p><p id="p0260">The anti-HCV positivity showed a significant association with Italian nationality. Interestingly, the Italian native sub-population showed a higher prevalence than the one we found in sub-populations of participants coming from high endemicity areas such as North Africa.<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr"><sup>40</sup></xref> Since the vulnerable people are usually unaware of the treatment options, they are not often referred to official healthcare services. The prevalence we observed is even slightly higher than the one of the pre-direct-acting-antivirals era in Italy (2.9% vs 2.3% reported by Sagnelli et&#x000a0;al.).<xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr"><sup>41</sup></xref> Among the Italian participants, the prevalence of anti-HCV was 11%, nearly five times higher than the percentage reported by Sagnelli and colleagues for the general Italian population,<xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr"><sup>41</sup></xref> making the marginalized Italian citizens an ideal target for micro-elimination interventions.</p><p id="p0265">The majority of the anti-HCV&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;participants were younger than baby boomers, which is the birth cohort with the highest risk for HCV.<xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr"><sup>42</sup></xref> This finding supports the National Plan initiated in 2021, which consists of a free-of-charge HCV screening focused on key populations, including current IV drug users attending public drug addiction services, people in prison, and individuals born between 1969 and 1989.<xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr"><sup>43</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr"><sup>44</sup></xref> Our results confirm that screening the 1969&#x02013;1989 birth cohort could effectively discover undiagnosed HCV cases and suggest expanding the screening to include new key populations, such as marginalized people and migrants living in shelters.</p><p id="p0270">The risk factor analysis confirmed that IV drug use was significantly associated with HCV exposure, consistently with previous data.<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, <xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, <xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>, <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref> The majority of anti-HCV&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;individuals were approached in the meal centers. This is due to the fact that users of free meal centers often experience social exclusion and have risky behaviors in addition to poverty. In other words, in this sub-setting, the higher risk of HCV exposure is due to extremely marginalizing living conditions such as homelessness. This is also corroborated by the significant association of HCV positivity to the use of IV drugs, a habit correlating with advanced marginality.<xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr"><sup>49</sup></xref></p><p id="p0275">The linkage to care uptake and retention in care for the HBsAg&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;participants were successful, even considering the two individuals were already aware of the infection and on treatment. Most of the HBsAg&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;patients were recruited from shelters for migrants, where they often developed a trusting relationship with navigators. As previously discussed, collaboration with social workers operating in charities is likely the major key to the success of the screening campaigns and subsequent linkage to care. The results of our study, in terms of linkage and retention in care outcomes, reflect this point.</p><p id="p0280">The outcome of linkage to care for anti-HCV&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;patients needs improvement. Only 14 out of 23 (61%) anti-HCV-positive participants were linked to care, indicating that some individuals with active HCV infection may have been prevented from accessing antiviral therapy. The composition of the anti-HCV&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;subset explains the reluctance that prevented healthcare access: these individuals, mostly Italians, experienced social exclusion. While recent immigrants perceive their health as an important issue, this is not a priority for extremely marginalized people, for whom social exclusion is a multidimensional phenomenon, not limited to material deprivation.</p><p id="p0285">Therefore, since the definition of marginality is broad and reflects that marginalization is an umbrella term, we can state that HBsAg and anti-HCV positivity are associated with two different subsets among the participants in the testing sessions.</p><p id="p0290">The main hepatic parameters of the retained in care groups showed overall mild liver damage in the HBsAg&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;participants.</p><p id="p0295">Liver damage evaluation in the anti-HCV individuals showed 2 cirrhotic patients (one with HCC), that were both successfully treated with antiviral therapy. Again, the presence of advanced liver damage among the anti-HCV&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;patients could be linked to the particular features of this sub-group characterized by habits linked not only to the infection risk but also to a faster evolution of liver damage such as alcohol consumption.</p><p id="p0300">The higher HBV/HCV prevalences we found in marginalized settings compared to the Italian general population, stress the need to implement the screening of vulnerable groups to target residual/hidden infections. Thus, reducing disparities in access to cure and advancing towards the WHO plan to end viral hepatitis as a public health threat by 2030. Results highlighted a difference between HBV and HCV positive sub-settings: while HBV is highly prevalent in economic migrants and refugees temporarily living in shelters and that usually do not experience social exclusion in their countries; the profile of the HCV&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;individual is that of a person experiencing extreme marginalization, who engages in risky behaviors, and whose priorities do not include their health.</p><p id="p0305">This study has some limitations. Concerning risk factor assessment, 25% of participants declined to respond to the question about &#x0201c;unprotected sex&#x0201d;. Furthermore, the survey regarding education level was introduced later during the study. Thus, data is available for 69% of the participants. Hence missing data was not included in the statistical analysis.</p><p id="p0310">Reasons for non-testing and data on individuals who declined participation were not recorded, which not only prevented analysis of refusal factors but also limited efforts to enhance adherence and compare participants with non-participants.</p><p id="p0315">We detected HCV infection with an RDT which assesses anti-HCV positivity and therefore requires a second test to diagnose an active infection. Conversely, the reflex test assessing viremia has the potential to increase the uptake of HCV testing and linkage to HCV care.</p><p id="p0320">The data about the HCV active infection rate was partial since 9/23 anti-HCV&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;individuals were not linked to care. This accounts for using tests that reveal the presence of the anti-HCV instead of the reflex care test that detects viral RNA.</p><p id="p0325">Overall, this study found that an on-site HBV and HCV screening strategy can be successful among marginalized communities in Italy, particularly in facilities providing various forms of assistance and support to migrants, homeless individuals, and other vulnerable groups.</p><p id="p0330">Thus, the on-site testing could be a helpful model for European policymakers when reassessing existing health policies and systems regarding viral hepatitis elimination plans. It is essential to develop strategies that enhance healthcare accessibility while fostering trust and engagement with marginalized communities. As demonstrated by the high rate of success we obtained when navigators actively took part in the screening sessions and to the further clinical path, this is only possible through integrated care models. In other words, in this context, successful strategies not only meet medical needs but also address social determinants of health, including housing, employment, and mental health services. Thus, this offers a more comprehensive approach to healthcare by tackling the underlying causes of disparities.</p></sec><sec id="sec5"><title>Contributors</title><p id="p0335">Study design: LG, MM and ALZ. Data collection: LG, MM, TC, AC, IDG, GC, SL, SM, FM, CS, LP, LC, MMA M, LM, EC, AX, IB, SL, LL, SIB, AN, SG, DA, PB. Data analysis: LG, MM, ALZ, MLM. Drafting and revising: LG, MM, GC, ALZ, MLM, SG. All authors have read and approved the final version of the manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="sec6"><title>Data sharing statement</title><p id="p0340">MM and LG have full access to all of the data in the study and take responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis. All data used in the study are available upon request to the corresponding author.</p></sec><sec id="sec7"><title>Editor note</title><p id="p0345">The Lancet Group takes a neutral position with respect to territorial claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Declaration of interests</title><p id="p0350">Stefano Gitto: Gilead, speaker honoraria (2, year 2024), consultant fee (1, year 2024). All other authors declare no competing interests.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carballo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Feld</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Janssen</surname><given-names>H.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immigration and viral hepatitis</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Hepatol</source><volume>63</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>515</fpage><lpage>522</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhep.2015.04.026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25962882</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burki</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>WHO's 2024 global hepatitis report</article-title><source>Lancet Infect Dis</source><volume>24</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2024</year><fpage>e362</fpage><lpage>e363</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(24)00307-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38795729</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sapisochin</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salem</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saborowski</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title><source>Lancet</source><volume>400</volume><issue>10360</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>1345</fpage><lpage>1362</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(22)01200-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36084663</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perz</surname><given-names>J.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>G.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Farrington</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hutin</surname><given-names>Y.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>B.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The contributions of hepatitis B virus and hepatitis C virus infections to cirrhosis and primary liver cancer worldwide</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Hepatol</source><volume>45</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2006</year><fpage>529</fpage><lpage>538</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhep.2006.05.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16879891</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Harmanci</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hutin</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Global progress on the elimination of viral hepatitis as a major public health threat: an analysis of WHO Member State responses 2017</article-title><source>JHEP Rep</source><volume>1</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>89</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhepr.2019.04.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32039355</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lazarus</surname><given-names>J.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Safreed-Harmon</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thursz</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The micro-elimination approach to eliminating hepatitis C: strategic and operational considerations</article-title><source>Semin Liver Dis</source><volume>38</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>192</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0038-1666841</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29986353</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lazarus</surname><given-names>J.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiktor</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Colombo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thursz</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Foundation</surname><given-names>E.I.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Micro-elimination - a path to global elimination of hepatitis C</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Hepatol</source><volume>67</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>665</fpage><lpage>666</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhep.2017.06.033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28760329</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lazarus</surname><given-names>J.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Picchio</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Byrne</surname><given-names>C.J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A&#x000a0;global systematic review of hepatitis C elimination efforts through micro-elimination</article-title><source>Semin Liver Dis</source><volume>42</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>159</fpage><lpage>172</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/a-1777-6112</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35189667</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cooke</surname><given-names>G.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrieux-Meyer</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Applegate</surname><given-names>T.L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Accelerating the elimination of viral hepatitis: a Lancet Gastroenterology &#x00026; Hepatology commission</article-title><source>Lancet Gastroenterol Hepatol</source><volume>4</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>135</fpage><lpage>184</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2468-1253(18)30270-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30647010</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cooke</surname><given-names>G.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Flower</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Progress towards elimination of viral hepatitis: a Lancet Gastroenterology &#x00026; Hepatology commission update</article-title><source>Lancet Gastroenterol Hepatol</source><volume>9</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2024</year><fpage>346</fpage><lpage>365</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2468-1253(23)00321-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38367629</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pham</surname><given-names>T.N.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Le</surname><given-names>D.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dao</surname><given-names>D.V.B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Establishing baseline framework for hepatitis B virus micro-elimination in Ho Chi Minh City, Vietnam - a community-based seroprevalence study</article-title><source>Lancet Reg Health West Pac</source><volume>30</volume><year>2023</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100620</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.lanwpc.2022.100620</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Colucci</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Uceda Renteria</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lunghi</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Italian migrants study: an HCV and HBV micro-elimination pilot project</article-title><source>Clin Res Hepatol Gastroenterol</source><volume>46</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2022</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">101852</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clinre.2021.101852</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Avellon</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ala</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Diaz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clinical performance of Determine HBsAg 2 rapid test for Hepatitis B detection</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Med Virol</source><volume>92</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>3403</fpage><lpage>3411</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jmv.25862</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32270883</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Balasegaram</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Douthwaite</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>An innovative approach to increase viral hepatitis diagnoses and linkage to care using opt-out testing and an integrated care pathway in a London Emergency Department</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>13</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2018</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e0198520</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0198520</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>European Association for the Study of the Liver. Electronic address: easloffice@easloffice.eu</collab><collab>Clinical Practice Guidelines Panel: Chair:</collab><collab>EASL Governing Board Representative:</collab><collab>Panel Members:</collab></person-group><article-title>EASL recommendations on treatment of hepatitis C: final update of the series</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Hepatol</source><volume>73</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>1170</fpage><lpage>1218</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhep.2020.08.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32956768</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>European Association for the Study of the Liver. Electronic address: easloffice@easloffice.eu</collab><collab>European Association for the Study of the Liver</collab></person-group><article-title>EASL 2017 Clinical Practice Guidelines on the management of hepatitis B virus infection</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Hepatol</source><volume>67</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>370</fpage><lpage>398</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhep.2017.03.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28427875</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="other" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>United Nation Geoscheme</collab></person-group><article-title>M49 Standard Version, Geneva</article-title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://unstats.un.org/unsd/methodology/m49/" id="intref0021">https://unstats.un.org/unsd/methodology/m49/</ext-link><year>2023</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kondili</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lazarus</surname><given-names>J.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jepsen</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Inequities in primary liver cancer in Europe: the state of play</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Hepatol</source><volume>80</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2024</year><fpage>645</fpage><lpage>660</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhep.2023.12.031</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38237866</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sahajian</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanhems</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bailly</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fabry</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Trepo</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sepetjan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Screening campaign of hepatitis C among underprivileged people consulting in health centers of Lyon area, France</article-title><source>Eur J Public Health</source><volume>17</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2007</year><fpage>263</fpage><lpage>271</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/eurpub/ckl233</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17068003</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sherriff</surname><given-names>L.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayon-White</surname><given-names>R.T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A&#x000a0;survey of hepatitis C prevalence amongst the homeless community of Oxford</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Public Health Med</source><volume>25</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2003</year><fpage>358</fpage><lpage>361</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pubmed/fdg088</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14747596</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Page</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shumway</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Riley</surname><given-names>E.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>HCV screening in a cohort of HIV infected and uninfected homeless and marginally housed women in San Francisco, California</article-title><source>BMC Publ Health</source><volume>17</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>171</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-017-4102-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nyamathi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Correlates of hepatitis C virus infection in homeless men: a latent variable approach</article-title><source>Drug Alcohol Depend</source><volume>75</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2004</year><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>95</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2004.02.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15225892</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Laere</surname><given-names>I.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Wit</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klazinga</surname><given-names>N.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pathways into homelessness: recently homeless adults problems and service use before and after becoming homeless in Amsterdam</article-title><source>BMC Publ Health</source><volume>9</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>3</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2458-9-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref24"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baggett</surname><given-names>T.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Connell</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singer</surname><given-names>D.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rigotti</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The unmet health care needs of homeless adults: a national study</article-title><source>Am J Public Health</source><volume>100</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>1326</fpage><lpage>1333</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2105/AJPH.2009.180109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20466953</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gelberg</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arangua</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prevalence, distribution, and correlates of hepatitis C virus infection among homeless adults in Los Angeles</article-title><source>Public Health Rep</source><volume>127</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>407</fpage><lpage>421</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/003335491212700409</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22753984</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref26"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parylo</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of health services received by homeless families in Leicester</article-title><source>Community Pract</source><volume>84</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>24</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref27"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>D.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Experiences of homeless people in the health care delivery system: a descriptive phenomenological study</article-title><source>Public Health Nurs</source><volume>25</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2008</year><fpage>420</fpage><lpage>430</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1525-1446.2008.00726.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18816359</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref28"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fuster</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gelberg</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Community screening, identification, and referral to primary care, for hepatitis C, B, and HIV among homeless persons in Los Angeles</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Community Health</source><volume>44</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>1044</fpage><lpage>1054</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10900-019-00679-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31127412</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref29"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Masson</surname><given-names>C.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fokuo</surname><given-names>J.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clients' perceptions of barriers and facilitators to implementing hepatitis C virus care in homeless shelters</article-title><source>BMC Infect Dis</source><volume>20</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>386</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12879-020-05103-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32471376</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sagnelli</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sica</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Creta</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Calogero</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ciccozzi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sagnelli</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiological and clinical aspects of hepatitis B virus infection in Italy over the last 50 years</article-title><source>World J Gastroenterol</source><volume>28</volume><issue>26</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>3081</fpage><lpage>3091</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3748/wjg.v28.i26.3081</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36051347</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="other" id="sref31"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/data/gho/data/indicators/indicator-details/GHO/hepatitis---prevalence-of-chronic-hepatitis-among-the-general-population" id="intref0010">https://www.who.int/data/gho/data/indicators/indicator-details/GHO/hepatitis---prevalence-of-chronic-hepatitis-among-the-general-population</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref32"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stroffolini</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stroffolini</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vaccination campaign against hepatitis B virus in Italy: a history of successful achievements</article-title><source>Vaccines</source><volume>11</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2023</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1531</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/vaccines11101531</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref33"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tosti</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marceca</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eugeni</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Health assessment for migrants and asylum seekers upon arrival and while hosted in reception centers: Italian guidelines</article-title><source>Health Pol</source><volume>125</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>393</fpage><lpage>405</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.healthpol.2020.12.010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref34"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>J.E.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Surey</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>MacLellan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abubakar</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stagg</surname><given-names>H.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hepatitis B vaccination uptake in hard-to-reach populations in London: a cross-sectional study</article-title><source>BMC Infect Dis</source><volume>19</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>372</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12879-019-3926-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31046683</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref35"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>P.M.R.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Matos</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>R.M.B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prevalence, risk factors and hepatitis B immunization: helping fill the gap on hepatitis B epidemiology among homeless people, Goi&#x000e2;nia, Central Brazil</article-title><source>Cad Sa&#x000fa;de P&#x000fa;blica</source><volume>33</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2017</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e00109216</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/0102-311X00109216</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref36"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>P.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Byrd</surname><given-names>K.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>T.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinbaum</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hepatitis B vaccination coverage among high-risk adults 18-49 years, U.S., 2009</article-title><source>Vaccine</source><volume>29</volume><issue>40</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>7049</fpage><lpage>7057</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2011.07.030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21782873</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref37"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alagna</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Santangelo</surname><given-names>O.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Raia</surname><given-names>D.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gianfredi</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Provenzano</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Firenze</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Health status, diseases and vaccinations of the homeless in the city of Palermo, Italy</article-title><source>Ann Ig</source><volume>31</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7416/ai.2019.2255</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30554236</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref38"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>P.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeh</surname><given-names>S.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gender disparity in chronic hepatitis B: mechanisms of sex hormones</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Gastroenterol Hepatol</source><volume>30</volume><issue>8</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>1237</fpage><lpage>1245</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jgh.12934</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25708186</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref39"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>S.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Changchien</surname><given-names>C.S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Age, gender, and local geographic variations of viral etiology of hepatocellular carcinoma in a hyperendemic area for hepatitis B virus infection</article-title><source>Cancer</source><volume>86</volume><issue>7</issue><year>1999</year><fpage>1143</fpage><lpage>1150</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(sici)1097-0142(19991001)86:7&#x0003c;1143::aid-cncr7&#x0003e;3.0.co;2-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10506697</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref40"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Daw</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Bouzedi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>M.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dau</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Agnan</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hepatitis C virus in North Africa: an emerging threat</article-title><source>Sci World J</source><volume>2016</volume><year>2016</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">7370524</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2016/7370524</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref41"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andriulli</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stroffolini</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mariano</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Declining prevalence and increasing awareness of HCV infection in Italy: a population-based survey in five metropolitan areas</article-title><source>Eur J Intern Med</source><volume>53</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>79</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejim.2018.02.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29475770</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref42"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>B.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beckett</surname><given-names>G.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Falck-Ytter</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Holtzman</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>J.W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hepatitis C virus testing of persons born during 1945-1965: recommendations from the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</article-title><source>Ann Intern Med</source><volume>157</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>817</fpage><lpage>822</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/0003-4819-157-9-201211060-00529</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22910836</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref43"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kondili</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aghemo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Andreoni</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Milestones to reach Hepatitis C Virus (HCV) elimination in Italy: from free-of-charge screening to regional roadmaps for an HCV-free nation</article-title><source>Dig Liver Dis</source><volume>54</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>237</fpage><lpage>242</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.dld.2021.03.026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33926816</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref44"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Decree</surname><given-names>I.L.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Decreto legislativo 30 dicembre 2019, n. 162 conversione in legge 28 febbraio 2020, n. 8. Screening nazionale gratuito per eliminazione del virus HCV a norma dell&#x02019;articolo</source><year>2019</year><fpage>25</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref45"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Strehlow</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zerger</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hepatitis C among clients of health care for the homeless primary care clinics</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Health Care Poor Underserv</source><volume>23</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>811</fpage><lpage>833</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1353/hpu.2012.0047</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref46"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>K.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Garrett</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alter</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Strathdee</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Seroprevalence of HCV infection in homeless Baltimore families</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Health Care Poor Underserv</source><volume>19</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2008</year><fpage>580</fpage><lpage>587</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1353/hpu.0.0023</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref47"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pinazo-Bandera</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aranda</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a-Garc&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hepatitis C virus point-of-care microelimination approach in a vulnerable population in the South of Spain</article-title><source>Gastroenterol Rep (Oxf)</source><volume>12</volume><year>2024</year><fpage>goad077</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gastro/goad077</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38264764</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref48"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khalili</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>H.H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Shelter-based integrated model is effective in scaling up hepatitis C testing and treatment in persons experiencing homelessness</article-title><source>Hepatol Commun</source><volume>6</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>50</fpage><lpage>64</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hep4.1791</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34628726</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref49"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kreek</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Extreme marginalization: addiction and other mental health disorders, stigma, and imprisonment</article-title><source>Ann N Y Acad Sci</source><volume>1231</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1749-6632.2011.06152.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21884162</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref></ref-list><ack id="ack0010"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p id="p0355">Authors would like to thank Ms. Nora Slonim (American English) and Ms. Ysabella Grasso (British English) for their kind language editing. Thanks should also go to all the Charities that hosted the screening events and to all the participants. A special acknowledgement goes to Mr. Renato Brunetti and Ms. Elena Boninsegna who supported the healthcare professional team and to Ms. Elena Pieralli, director of Meal Center La Pira, Prato, Italy, who hosted the first screening session and helped in set up the best strategies to conduct further testing. SL was supported by the &#x0201c;Prof. Claudio Puoti 2021&#x0201d; AISF fellowship. The authors thank Gilead Sciences, Fondazione Cassa di Risparmio di Pistoia e Pescia, and Regione Toscana for their unconditioned contributions.</p></ack></back></article>