<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Medicine (Baltimore)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Medicine (Baltimore)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MD</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0025-7974</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1536-5964</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Lippincott Williams &#x00026; Wilkins</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Hagerstown, MD</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40388790</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12091608</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">MD-D-25-00916</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="art-access-id">00071</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000042411</article-id><article-version vocab="JAV" vocab-identifier="http://www.niso.org/publications/rp/RP-8-2008.pdf" article-version-type="Version of Record">3</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>6200</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Research Article</subject><subject>Observational Study</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Identification of therapeutic targets for neonatal respiratory distress: A systematic druggable genome-wide Mendelian randomization</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0009-0001-7245-2300</contrib-id><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Hang</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><email>ditianvs20@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Feng</given-names></name><degrees>BD</degrees><email>ditianvs@163.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>HongLi</given-names></name><degrees>BD</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="c1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Department of Neonatal Intensive Care Center (NICU), Henan Provincial Key Medicine Laboratory of Nursing, Henan Provincial People&#x02019;s Hospital, People&#x02019;s Hospital of Zhengzhou University, Zhengzhou, Henan, China.</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1"><label>*</label>Correspondence: HongLi Wang, Department of Neonatal Intensive Care Center (NICU), Henan Provincial Key Medicine Laboratory of Nursing, Henan Provincial People&#x02019;s Hospital, People&#x02019;s Hospital of Zhengzhou University, Zhengzhou 450003, Henan, China (e-mail: <email xlink:href="136615609@qq.com">136615609@qq.com</email>).</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>16</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>104</volume><issue>20</issue><elocation-id>e42411</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2025 the Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License 4.0 (CCBY)</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="medi-104-e42411.pdf"/><abstract><p>Currently, there remains a significant gap in effective pharmacologic interventions for neonatal respiratory distress syndrome (NRDS). To address this critical unmet medical need, we aimed to systematically identify novel therapeutic targets and preventive strategies through comprehensive integration and analysis of multiple publicly accessible datasets. In this study, we employed an integrative approach combining druggable genome data, cis-expression quantitative trait loci (cis-eQTL) from human blood and lung tissues, and genome-wide association study summary statistics for neonatal respiratory distress. We performed two-sample Mendelian randomization (TSMR) analysis to investigate potential causal relationships between druggable genes and neonatal respiratory distress. To strengthen causal inference, we performed Bayesian co-localization analyses. Furthermore, we conducted phenome-wide Mendelian randomization (Phe-MR) to systematically evaluate potential side effects and alternative therapeutic indications associated with the identified candidate drug targets. Finally, we interrogated existing drug databases to identify actionable pharmacological agents targeting the identified genes. All 3 genes (LTBR, NAAA, CSNK1G2) were analyzed by Bayesian co-localization (PH4&#x02005;&#x0003e;&#x02005;75%). CSNK1G2 (lung eQTL, odds ratio [OR]: 0.419, 95% CI: 0.185&#x02013;0.948, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02005;=&#x02005;.037; blood eQTL, OR: 4.255, 95% CI: 1.346&#x02013;13.455, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02005;=&#x02005;.014; Gtex whole blood eQTL, OR: 4.966, 95% CI: 1.104&#x02013;22.332, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02005;=&#x02005;.037). LTBR (lung eQTL, OR: 0.550, 95% CI: 0.354&#x02013;0.856, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02005;=&#x02005;.008; blood eQTL, OR: 0.347, 95% CI: 0.179&#x02013;0.671, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02005;=&#x02005;.002; Gtex whole blood eQTL, OR: 0.059, 95% CI: 0.0.007&#x02013;0.478, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02005;=&#x02005;.008). NAAA (lung eQTL, OR: 0.717, 95% CI: 0.555&#x02013;0.925, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02005;=&#x02005;.011; Gtex whole blood eQTL, OR: 0.660, 95% CI: 0.476&#x02013;0.913, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02005;=&#x02005;.012). Drug repurposing analyses support the possibility that etanercept and asciminib hydrochloride may treat neonatal respiratory distress by activating LTBR. This study demonstrated that LTBR, NAAA, and CSNK1G2 may serve as promising biomarkers and therapeutic targets for NRDS.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>cis-eQTL</kwd><kwd>colocalization</kwd><kwd>Mendelian randomization</kwd><kwd>neonatal respiratory distress</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="ID0E5YAE141204"><funding-source>the provincial Medical Science and Technology PR Program Joint Co-construction Project of Henan</funding-source><award-id>LHGJ20240094</award-id><principal-award-recipient>Hang Yuan</principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name><meta-value>TRUE</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>SDC</meta-name><meta-value>T</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>
1. Introduction</title><p>Neonatal respiratory distress syndrome (NRDS) is characterized by progressive dyspnea and respiratory failure in newborns shortly after birth, primarily attributed to insufficient alveolar surfactant production.<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</sup> This condition can lead to severe complications including respiratory failure, cardiac dysfunction, and life-threatening infections.<sup>[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]</sup> While alveolar surfactant replacement therapy has been established as the primary preventive and therapeutic approach for NRDS, its clinical efficacy remains limited.<sup>[<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]</sup> Furthermore, there is a notable paucity of research investigating potential preventive or therapeutic targets for NRDS. Consequently, elucidating the underlying pathogenesis of this condition and identifying novel therapeutic targets represent crucial areas of research interest.</p><p>In recent years, the rapid advancement of biotechnology has significantly propelled the development of multi-omics research, an interdisciplinary field that integrates large-scale data from diverse biological domains, including transcriptomics and metabolomics. This integrative approach has provided robust evidence and sophisticated tools for identifying potential disease biomarkers and therapeutic targets.<sup>[<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]</sup> Among various research methodologies, Genome-Wide Association Studies (GWAS) have emerged as a powerful approach for investigating genetic factors underlying complex diseases. By conducting genome-wide typing of high-density genetic markers (e.g., SNPs) across large-scale population DNA samples, GWAS enables comprehensive identification of genes associated with disease onset, progression, and therapeutic response.<sup>[<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]</sup> Furthermore, the integration of expression quantitative trait loci (eQTL) analysis with GWAS datasets has proven particularly valuable in elucidating genetic variations that influence gene expression patterns related to disease phenotypes.<sup>[<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]</sup> Notably, cis variants, which are located on the same chromosome and in close proximity to the transcribed gene unit, have demonstrated greater utility than trans variants in identifying functionally relevant phenotypic changes. This characteristic makes cis variants particularly valuable for exploring the genetic mechanisms underlying gene expression regulation.<sup>[<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]</sup></p><p>There has been a surge in reports highlighting the successful development of novel therapeutic agents, with the identification of disease-specific drug targets serving as a critical prerequisite. To streamline the exploration of potential drug targets, researchers have introduced the concept of &#x0201c;druggable genomes,&#x0201d; which has significantly accelerated the discovery of new therapeutic targets.<sup>[<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]</sup> As an integral component of genomics research, the druggable genome comprises genes encoding proteins with inherent potential to serve as drug targets, primarily due to their capacity to bind therapeutic compounds effectively. The application of druggable genome analysis has markedly enhanced both the efficiency and success rate of novel drug target identification.<sup>[<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]</sup> Furthermore, Mendelian randomization (MR), an innovative methodological approach that utilizes genetic variants strongly associated with exposure factors as instrumental variables (IVs) to assess causal relationships between exposures and outcomes, has provided robust evidence in causal inference studies.<sup>[<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]</sup> The integration of druggable genome analysis with cis-expression quantitative trait loci (cis-eQTL) MR has emerged as a powerful research strategy, successfully identifying potential therapeutic targets for various complex diseases, including amyotrophic lateral sclerosis, idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis, and type 2 diabetes mellitus.<sup>[<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]</sup></p><p>In this study, we systematically integrated druggable genomic data, transcriptomic profiles, and GWAS data of NRDS to identify potential preventive and therapeutic targets for this condition.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>
2. Methods</title><p>The schematic representation of the research framework is illustrated in Figure <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. The analysis was conducted using aggregated datasets, with all necessary informed consent and ethical approvals having been secured in the original studies from which the data were derived.</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>We curated a comprehensive set of 2532 known druggable genes from the DGIdb database, following the methodology established by Finan et al to construct eQTL tools for these druggable genes, we integrated eQTL data derived from human blood (eQTLGen), whole blood (GTEx), and lung tissues (GTEx). Through this process, we identified independent genetic variants significantly associated with druggable gene expression, which served as instrumental variables (IVs). These IVs were specifically located within 1&#x02009;Mb upstream (cis) and downstream of the coding sequence. In our MR analysis, these IVs were employed to identify potential causal genetic variants associated with neonatal respiratory distress. Furthermore, we implemented a Bayesian co-localization approach to detect shared causal genetic variants across traits. To evaluate the clinical relevance of our findings, we conducted phenome-wide MR (Phe-MR) analyses using UK Biobank GWAS data to assess potential side effects and additional therapeutic indications of the prioritized druggable genes. Finally, we systematically investigated the availability and clinical development status of these genes through comprehensive database searches and website evaluations. eQTL = expression quantitative trait loci, eQTLGen consortium = expression quantitative trait locus generating consortium, DGIdb = drug-gene interaction database, GTEx = genotype-tissue expression project, GWAS = genome-wide association study, IV = instrumental variable, MR = Mendelian randomization, Phe-MR = whole-phenomenon Mendelian randomization analysis.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="medi-104-e42411-g001" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec><title>
3. Data sources</title><sec><title>
3.1. druggable genes</title><p>We retrieved druggable genes from 2 primary sources: the drug-gene interaction database (DGIdb v5.0.8, <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dgidb.org/downloads" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.dgidb.org/downloads</ext-link>)<sup>[<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]</sup> and and the seminal work of Finan et al.<sup>[<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]</sup> DGIdb represents a comprehensive repository specializing in drug-gene interactions, integrating diverse data sources encompassing drug mechanisms of action, gene mutations, clinical trial outcomes, and other relevant information. This database serves as an essential resource for researchers and healthcare professionals, facilitating advancements in personalized medicine and drug discovery. Specifically, we accessed the February 2022 release of DGIdb, which contains curated drug-gene interaction data mapped to Entrez gene identifiers.<sup>[<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]</sup> Furthermore, Finan et al groundbreaking study established critical connections between GWAS-identified loci associated with complex diseases and druggable genes, thereby providing a robust framework for drug target identification and validation.<sup>[<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]</sup> The integration of these 2 complementary data sources significantly enhances the reliability and comprehensiveness of our analysis.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>
4. eQTL dataset</title><p>We obtained blood cis-eQTL data encompassing 19,250 gene transcripts from 31,684 individuals through the eQTLGen consortium.<sup>[<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]</sup> Furthermore, we acquired comprehensive cis-eQTL data from both lung tissue and whole blood samples through the Genotype-Tissue Expression (GTEx) Consortium, comprising a cohort of 715 individuals (Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Data sources for the MR analysis in the current study.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type of dataset</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Data subtype</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Source</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sample size</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Population</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Download site</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Druggable genome</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DGIdb</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Freshour.SL, et al 2020</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dgidb.org/downloads" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.dgidb.org/downloads</ext-link>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prior druggable gene</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Finan.C et al 2017</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Finan C, et al PMID: 28356508.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">QTL datasets</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lung cis&#x02010;eQTL</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GTEx Consortium 2020 Science</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">715</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xlink:href="https://gtexportal.org/home/datasets" ext-link-type="uri">https://gtexportal.org/home/datasets</ext-link>.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Whole blood cis&#x02010;eQTL</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GTEx Consortium 2020 Science</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">715</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xlink:href="https://gtexportal.org/home/datasets" ext-link-type="uri">https://gtexportal.org/home/datasets</ext-link>.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blood<break/>cis&#x02010;eQTL</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">eQTLGen Consortium (V&#x000f5;sa U, et al 2021)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 684</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.eqtlgen.org/cis-eqtls.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.eqtlgen.org/cis-eqtls.html</ext-link>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">GWAS summary</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Respiratory distress<break/>of newborn</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FinnGen</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cases: 171, Controls: 218,527.</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.finngen.fi/en" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.finngen.fi/en</ext-link> GWAS ID (finn-b-P16_RESPI_DISTR_NEWBO)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1419<break/>Phenotypes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UK Biobank (Zhou, et al 2018)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">408 961</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.leelabsg.org/resources" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.leelabsg.org/resources</ext-link>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other"><p>cis&#x02010;eQTL&#x02005;=&#x02005;cis-expression quantitative trait loci, DGIdb&#x02005;=&#x02005;drug-gene interaction database, eQTLGen&#x02005;=&#x02005;expression quantitative trait locus generating consortium, GWAS&#x02005;=&#x02005;genome-wide association study, GTEx&#x02005;=&#x02005;genotype-tissue expression.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>
5. GWAS datasets for neonatal respiratory distress</title><p>We retrieved genome-wide association study (GWAS) summary statistics for NRDS from the FinnGen database, comprising 171 cases and 218,527 controls (Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>
6. Instrument selection</title><p>Mendelian randomization methods employ single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) that exhibit strong associations with the exposure of interest as IVs to evaluate the causal relationship between exposure and outcomes. These IVs must satisfy 3 fundamental assumptions: the IV demonstrates a direct association with the exposure; the IV remains independent of potential confounding factors; and the IVs are independent of the outcome variable.<sup>[<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]</sup> To ensure the robustness of our analysis while minimizing potential pleiotropic effects and maintaining the integrity of the 3 core MR assumptions (specifically, that IVs influence outcomes exclusively through their effect on exposure without alternative pathways), we implemented stringent selection criteria. These included applying a genome-wide significance threshold (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02005;&#x0003c;&#x02005;5&#x02005;&#x000d7;&#x02005;10<sup>&#x02212;8</sup>) and requiring an <italic toggle="yes">F</italic>-statistic&#x02005;&#x02265;&#x02005;10 to identify strong IVs.<sup>[<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]</sup></p></sec><sec><title>
7. Two-sample Mendelian randomization</title><p>Following the identification of candidate druggable gene IV, we extracted corresponding variants from the GWAS dataset for neonatal respiratory distress. To evaluate the exposure-outcome association, we employed both the Wald ratio and inverse variance weighting methods. The <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-values of the available genes were corrected by Bonferroni (Bonferroni threshold: Lung eQTL at 0.05/334, blood eQTL at 0.05/1531, and whole blood eQTL at 0.05/312). Comprehensive sensitivity analyses were conducted using MR-Egger, weighted mode, and weighted median approaches, complemented by multidirectionality assessment through MR-Egger intercept analysis.<sup>[<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]</sup> Potential outliers were identified using the MR-PRESSO global test, with significant SNP outliers being systematically excluded from subsequent analyses.<sup>[<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]</sup> Statistical significance thresholds were set at <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02005;&#x0003c;&#x02005;.05 for both heterogeneity and multidirectionality analyses. To establish causal directionality, we implemented Steiger analysis using the &#x0201c;TwoSampleMR&#x0201d; R software package, effectively mitigating potential reverse causality bias. The causal direction was determined as follows: true (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02005;&#x0003c;&#x02005;.05) for exposure-to-outcome effects, false (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02005;&#x0003c;&#x02005;.05) for reversed effects, and inconclusive (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02005;&#x02265;&#x02005;.05).<sup>[<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]</sup> All statistical analyses were performed using R software (version 4.1.2) with specialized packages including TwoSampleMR, MR-PRESSO, ensuring methodological rigor and reproducibility.</p></sec><sec><title>
8. Bayesian colocalization</title><p>Bayesian colocalization is a robust statistical approach designed to assess whether the observed association signals between 2 traits originate from the same underlying genetic variants. This methodology evaluates 5 distinct hypotheses through posterior probability calculations: PPH0, indicating no association between the traits; PPH1, where only trait 1 shows genetic association; PPH2, where only trait 2 demonstrates genetic association; PPH3, where both traits exhibit genetic associations but through distinct variants; and PPH4, where both traits share the same causal genetic variant. In our analysis, we considered potentially druggable genes and neonatal respiratory distress to share the same genetic variant when the posterior probability of PPH4 exceeded 75%.<sup>[<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]</sup> The Bayesian co-localization analysis was conducted using the &#x0201c;coloc&#x0201d; package (version 5.1.0) in R (<ext-link xlink:href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/coloc/" ext-link-type="uri">https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/coloc/</ext-link>), following standard implementation protocols.</p></sec><sec><title>
9. Phenome&#x02010;wide MR analysis</title><p>To comprehensively investigate the causal relationships between the identified druggable genes and various disease traits, we conducted a phenome-wide MR (Phe-MR) analysis. This systematic approach aimed to maximize the identification of potential causal associations and provide robust evidence to facilitate novel drug development. In this study, we utilized GWAS data comprising 1419 phenotypes derived from 408,961 White British participants of European ancestry in the UK Biobank. The phenotypic data were processed using the scalable and accurate implementation of generalized mixed models (SAIGE) method, as previously described by Zhou et al, which enabled the analysis of more than 1400 binary phenotypic samples. The GWAS summary statistics were obtained from the SAIGE database (<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.leelabsg.org" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.leelabsg.org</ext-link>) to ensure statistical reliability, with detailed phenotypic information presented in Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>.</p></sec><sec><title>
10. Actionable drugs for candidate genes</title><p>We conducted a comprehensive assessment of the identified druggable genes for potential drug development by leveraging 3 major biomedical databases: DrugBank (<ext-link xlink:href="https://go.drugbank.com" ext-link-type="uri">https://go.drugbank.com</ext-link>), ChEMBL (<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.ebi.ac.uk/chembl" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ebi.ac.uk/chembl</ext-link>), and ClinicalTrials.gov (<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.clinicaltrials.gov" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.clinicaltrials.gov</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>
11. Results</title><sec><title>
11.1. Druggable genome</title><p>To identify potential drug targets, we initially extracted 3953 potentially druggable genes from the DGIdb database (Table S1, Supplemental Digital Content, <ext-link xlink:href="https://links.lww.com/MD/O869" ext-link-type="uri">https://links.lww.com/MD/O869</ext-link>) and obtained an additional 4463 druggable genes from the comprehensive study conducted by Finan et al (Table S2, Supplemental Digital Content, <ext-link xlink:href="https://links.lww.com/MD/O869" ext-link-type="uri">https://links.lww.com/MD/O869</ext-link>). To enhance the reliability and validity of our target selection, we performed a rigorous comparative analysis of these 2 datasets. This analysis resulted in the identification of 2532 high-confidence druggable genes that were consistently validated by both sources and had been officially annotated by the Human Genome Nomenclature Committee (Table S3, Supplemental Digital Content, <ext-link xlink:href="https://links.lww.com/MD/O869" ext-link-type="uri">https://links.lww.com/MD/O869</ext-link>).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>
12. Candidate druggable genes for neonatal respiratory distress</title><p>We overlapped 2532 potentially druggable genes with genes in the human blood, whole blood, and lung eQTL datasets, and then extracted genetic variation within a 1&#x02009;Mb range on either side of the coding sequences of the overlapping druggable genes. We obtained 334 SNPs associated with 334 druggable genes in the human lung tissue cis-eQTL, 3378 SNPs associated with 1531 druggable genes in the human blood cis-eQTL, and 312 SNPs associated with 312 druggable genes in the human whole blood cis-eQTL as representative of the IVs exposed to MR analysis (Fig. <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Next, we performed MR analysis of exposure using the GWAS Abstract dataset for neonatal respiratory distress. And after correction, we found that 3 druggable genes simultaneously present in at least 2 eQTL databases (Bonferroni corrected <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02005;&#x0003c;&#x02005;.05) were causally associated with neonatal respiratory distress (Figs. <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> and <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Summary of druggable genes for neonatal respiratory distress identified by MR and Bayesian co-localization analysis. In order to make IV more effective and to reduce pleiotropy at the same time, this study mainly used single SNPs as exposure tools. A Steiger <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value&#x02005;&#x0003c;&#x02005;.05 is considered true, which indicates that IV causes outcome. Figure <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> shows that the 3 druggable genes passed Mendelian randomization and Bayesian co-localization analysis. The eQTL dataset and neonatal respiratory distress were considered to have the same variant if the posterior probability of PPH4 was&#x02005;&#x0003e;&#x02005;75%. The strength of the association between exposure and outcome is showed by OR. OR is defined as: if OR&#x02005;&#x0003e;&#x02005;1, exposure may promote the outcome; if OR&#x02005;&#x0003c;&#x02005;1, exposure may suppress the outcome. OR = odds ratio.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="medi-104-e42411-g002" position="float"/></fig><p>To identify potential drug targets sharing genetic variants with NRDS, we employed Bayesian co-localization analysis to determine whether the causal signals identified in our MR study originated from identical genetic variants. Our findings revealed 3 promising druggable genes (LTBR, NAAA, CSNK1G2) that demonstrated consistent co-localization across multiple quantitative trait locus (QTL) datasets. Notably, while the NAAA gene failed to show co-localization in the blood expression quantitative trait loci (eQTL) dataset, it exhibited shared genetic variants with NRDS in both lung and whole blood eQTL datasets (Fig. <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> and Table S4, Supplemental Digital Content, <ext-link xlink:href="https://links.lww.com/MD/O869" ext-link-type="uri">https://links.lww.com/MD/O869</ext-link>). The analysis of transcript levels revealed tissue-specific associations with NRDS risk. In lung tissue, each standard deviation (SD) increase in CSNK1G2 expression was associated with a reduced risk of NRDS (odds ratio [OR]: 0.419, 95% CI: 0.185&#x02013;0.948, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02005;=&#x02005;.037). Conversely, elevated CSNK1G2 transcript levels in blood samples from eQTLGen (OR: 4.255, 95% CI: 1.346&#x02013;13.455, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02005;=&#x02005;.014) and whole blood samples from GTEx (OR: 4.966, 95% CI: 1.104&#x02013;22.332, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02005;=&#x02005;.037) were associated with increased NRDS risk, highlighting the complex tissue-specific regulatory mechanisms underlying this condition.</p><p>The analysis of transcript levels from multiple databases revealed significant associations with neonatal respiratory distress. In the eQTLGen Blood database, each 1 SD increase in LTBR transcript levels was associated with a reduced risk of neonatal respiratory distress (OR: 0.347, 95% CI: 0.179&#x02013;0.671, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02005;=&#x02005;.002). Similar protective associations were observed in GTEx databases, with LTBR transcript levels showing reduced risk in both lung tissue (OR: 0.550, 95% CI: 0.354&#x02013;0.856, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02005;=&#x02005;.008) and whole blood (OR: 0.059, 95% CI: 0.007&#x02013;0.478, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02005;=&#x02005;.008). For NAAA transcript levels, a 1 SD increase was associated with lower neonatal respiratory distress in lung tissue (OR: 0.717, 95% CI: 0.555&#x02013;0.925, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02005;=&#x02005;.011) and GTEx whole blood (OR: 0.660, 95% CI: 0.476&#x02013;0.913, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02005;=&#x02005;.012). However, NAAA transcript levels in blood from the eQTLGen database did not reach statistical significance (OR: 0.559, 95% CI: 0.302&#x02013;1.033, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02005;=&#x02005;.063). Importantly, our findings passed the Steiger filter test, providing robust support for our hypothesis that the IVs directly influence the outcome variable (Fig. <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> and Table S4, Supplemental Digital Content, <ext-link xlink:href="https://links.lww.com/MD/O869" ext-link-type="uri">https://links.lww.com/MD/O869</ext-link>). These results collectively suggest a protective role of LTBR and NAAA transcript levels against neonatal respiratory distress.</p></sec><sec><title>
13. Phe&#x02010;MR analysis of neonatal respiratory distress&#x02010;associated candidate druggable genes</title><p>We conducted PheWAS-MR analyses on 1149 diseases and traits from the UK Biobank, using IVs consistent with previously identified druggable genes associated with neonatal respiratory distress (6 SNPs in 3 genes, excluding those with nonsignificant Bayesian colocalization). Causal effects were considered statistically significant at <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02005;&#x02264;&#x02005;1&#x02005;&#x000d7;&#x02005;10&#x0207b;<sup>4</sup>. Increased LTBR transcript levels were associated with a reduced risk of urinary incontinence (OR: 1.074, 95% CI: 1.036&#x02013;1.112, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02005;=&#x02005;8.9&#x02005;&#x000d7;&#x02005;10&#x0207b;&#x02075;). However, no associations were found between CSNK1G2 and NAAA and any of the 1419 diseases, suggesting that drugs targeting these genes may not have significant adverse effects (Table S4, Supplemental Digital Content, <ext-link xlink:href="https://links.lww.com/MD/O869" ext-link-type="uri">https://links.lww.com/MD/O869</ext-link> and Fig S1, Supplemental Digital Content, <ext-link xlink:href="https://links.lww.com/MD/O870" ext-link-type="uri">https://links.lww.com/MD/O870</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec><title>
14. Actionable drugs for target genes</title><p>We have genetically evaluated 3 drug candidates for neonatal respiratory distress to assess their preclinical and clinical developmental potential (Table <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). While agents targeting CSNK1G2 have been specifically investigated, compounds related to the other 2 genes have been evaluated in clinical trials for other indications but have not been explored for neonatal respiratory distress treatment. Notably, Etanercept<sup>[<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]</sup> and Asciminib hydrochloride,<sup>[<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]</sup> which function as LTBR gene activators and maintain normal LTBR gene expression, emerge as promising therapeutic candidates for neonatal respiratory distress through their LTBR activation mechanism. In contrast, Nabiximols<sup>[<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]</sup> and Cannabidiol,<sup>[<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]</sup> which act as NAAA inhibitors, appear less suitable due to their potentially adverse effects on neonatal respiratory distress.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Finding actionable drugs for target genes.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Molecule type</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Compounds</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Action type</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical development activities</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene molecular function</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">NAAA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Small Molecule</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nabiximols</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inhibitor</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Investigational. treatment of neuropathic pain from multiple sclerosis and for cancer pain.</td><td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">DNA-binding transcription factor binding/hydrolase activity.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Small Molecule</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cannabidiol</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inhibitor</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Approved/investigational. treatment of Lennox-Gastaut syndrome and Dravet syndrome.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CSNK1G2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATP binding/histone H2AS1 kinase activity/protein serine kinase activity</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">LTBR</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Small Molecule</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Etanercept</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Agonist</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Approved/ investigational. Treatment of severe rheumatoid arthritis and moderate to severe plaque psoriasis</td><td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Cytokine activity/signaling receptor binding/tumor necrosis factor receptor binding</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Small Molecule</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asciminib hydrochloride</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Agonist</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Approved/investigational. Treatment of CGL</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other"><p>CGL = chronic granulocytic leukemia, LTBR = lymphotoxin beta receptor.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>
15. Discussion</title><p>Based on the comprehensive datasets analyzed in this study, we have identified robust evidence supporting the genetic co-localization of 3 promising drug target genes (LTBR, NAAA, and CSNK1G2). Through systematic evaluation of their clinical development potential, we demonstrate that Etanercept and Asciminib hydrochloride may represent effective therapeutic agents for NRDS through their activation of LTBR. Furthermore, our findings suggest that the expression profiles of these 3 genes could potentially serve as valuable biomarkers for the prevention and management of neonatal respiratory distress.</p><p>The lymphotoxin beta receptor gene (LTBR ) encodes a member of the tumor necrosis factor receptor superfamily, known as the lymphotoxin beta receptor. This receptor plays a pivotal role in immune system regulation, particularly in the development and maintenance of lymphoid tissues and intercellular signaling pathways, primarily through its interaction with lymphotoxin beta.<sup>[<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]</sup> Functionally, LTBR mediates critical cellular processes including apoptosis and proliferation, thereby contributing significantly to both adaptive and innate immune responses.<sup>[<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]</sup> Notably, recent studies have revealed an additional role of LTBR in regulating the expression of leucine and tryptophan biosynthetic genes in Corynebacterium glutamicum, an important amino acid-producing bacterium.<sup>[<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]</sup> Our MR study indicates that elevated LTBR gene transcription levels may confer protection against NRDS. While the precise mechanistic link between LTBR and NRDS remains to be fully elucidated, existing evidence suggests that both maternal antenatal systemic inflammatory indices<sup>[<xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]</sup> and neonatal airway inflammatory manifestations<sup>[<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]</sup> are significant contributors to NRDS development. These findings suggest that modulation of inflammatory responses and enhancement of immune system functionality may represent promising therapeutic strategies for NRDS management. The primary pharmacological activators of LTBR currently identified are Etanercept and Asciminib hydrochloride. However, our MR analyses were unable to establish optimal therapeutic parameters, including dosage regimens and treatment durations, for these agents. These critical clinical considerations warrant further investigation through well-designed prospective studies and randomized controlled trials to establish evidence-based therapeutic protocols.</p><p>The CSNK1G2 gene has been identified as one of the key genes demonstrating common genetic co-localization associated with NRDS. Notably, increased transcript levels of CSNK1G1 have been established as a significant risk factor for NRDS. CSNK1G2 encodes a protein that belongs to the protein tyrosine kinase family, specifically within the cell cycle protein-dependent kinase 1 family, which is crucial for various biological processes. Recent studies have revealed a novel function of CSNK1G2 in regulating oxidative stress response and modulating reactive oxygen species levels.<sup>[<xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]</sup> Additionally, CSNK1G2 has been shown to play a pivotal role in sensitizing breast cancer cells to tamoxifen (TAM) toxicity by differentially regulating the PI3K/AKT/mTOR/S6K and ERK signaling pathways.<sup>[<xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]</sup> Despite these advancements, the association between CSNK1G2 and neonatal respiratory distress remains unexplored. Furthermore, the development of effective CSNK1G2 inhibitors for clinical applications remains an unmet need, highlighting a critical gap in current research and therapeutic strategies.</p><p>N-Acetylethanolamine acid hydrolase (NAAA) is predominantly localized within the endochromosome-lysosome compartment of both innate and adaptive immune cells. NAAA-targeted pharmacological agents demonstrate significant therapeutic potential in the management of human inflammatory diseases.<sup>[<xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]</sup> Emerging research has revealed that N-acyl-ethanolamine amidase (NAAA) plays a crucial role in mitigating intestinal fibrosis through the modulation of macrophage activity.<sup>[<xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]</sup> Furthermore, empirical evidence indicates that NAAA expression is markedly elevated in rat alveolar macrophages.<sup>[<xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]</sup> Our investigation has identified a correlation between upregulated NAAA transcript levels and decreased susceptibility to neonatal respiratory distress. While NAAA-related compounds, such as Nabiximols and Cannabidiol, have received clinical approval, these agents primarily function as NAAA inhibitors. Consequently, there is a compelling need to explore and develop NAAA agonists as potential therapeutic interventions for neonatal respiratory distress.</p><p>This study demonstrates several notable strengths that enhance its scientific value and practical implications. Primarily, our approach incorporated comprehensive druggable gene databases for initial screening, ensuring that the identified candidate genes were directly associated with drug targets. This strategic selection significantly improves the potential success rate of future drug development while reinforcing the reliability of our findings. Secondly, our methodology integrated cis-acting variants of gene expression with GWAS data on neonatal respiratory distress, followed by rigorous Bayesian co-localization analysis. The cross-validation of results using independent datasets from different sources further strengthens the accuracy and credibility of our analytical outcomes. Thirdly, through systematic exploration of online databases, we successfully identified clinical drug information corresponding to candidate pharmacogenetic genes, providing valuable insights into their potential therapeutic applications for neonatal respiratory distress.</p><p>However, certain limitations should be acknowledged. First, the scarcity of comprehensive eQTL and pQTL data specific to neonatal blood in public databases presents a significant constraint, potentially limiting our ability to fully elucidate the pathogenesis of neonatal respiratory distress. Second, the exclusive reliance on GWAS data from European populations in this study may affect the generalizability of our findings. Inclusion of diverse ethnic groups in future research would enhance the robustness and applicability of the results across different populations.</p></sec><sec><title>
16. Conclusion</title><p>Our findings unveil promising therapeutic targets for NRDS, with 3 potential druggable genes (LTBR, NAAA, and CSNK1G2) emerging as candidates for further investigation. However, the translational potential of these targets derived from MR analyses requires rigorous validation through well-designed clinical trials. Future studies should systematically evaluate both the therapeutic efficacy and safety profiles of these molecular targets, while considering the inherent limitations of MR-based approaches in clinical translation.</p></sec><sec><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We are sincerely grateful to the researchers who made the GWAS data publicly available.</p></sec><sec><title>Author contributions</title><p><bold>Conceptualization:</bold> Hang Yuan.</p><p><bold>Data curation:</bold> Hang Yuan.</p><p><bold>Formal analysis:</bold> Hang Yuan.</p><p><bold>Funding acquisition:</bold> Hang Yuan.</p><p><bold>Investigation:</bold> Hang Yuan.</p><p><bold>Methodology:</bold> Hang Yuan.</p><p><bold>Project administration:</bold> Hang Yuan.</p><p><bold>Resources:</bold> Hang Yuan.</p><p><bold>Software:</bold> Hang Yuan.</p><p><bold>Validation:</bold> Hang Yuan.</p><p><bold>Visualization:</bold> Hang Yuan.</p><p><bold>Writing &#x02013; original draft:</bold> Hang Yuan.</p><p><bold>Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing:</bold> Hang Yuan, Feng Gao, HongLi Wang.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><fig id="s001" position="anchor"><media xlink:href="medi-104-e42411-s001.xlsx"/></fig><fig id="s002" position="anchor"><media xlink:href="medi-104-e42411-s002.pdf"/></fig></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="abbr"><p>
<def-list><title>Abbreviations:</title><def-item><term>Cis-eQTL</term><def><p>cis-expression quantitative trait loci</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GTEx</term><def><p>genotype-tissue expression</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GWAS</term><def><p>genome-wide association study</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IVs</term><def><p>instrumental variables</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IVW</term><def><p>inverse variance weighting</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NRDS</term><def><p>neonatal respiratory distress syndrome</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Phe-MR</term><def><p>phenome-wide Mendelian randomization</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SAIGE</term><def><p>scalable and accurate implementation of generalized mixed models</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TSMR</term><def><p>two-sample Mendelian randomization</p></def></def-item></def-list>
</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p>This work was funded by the provincial Medical Science and Technology PR Program Joint Co-construction Project of Henan (No. LHGJ20240094).</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>The authors have no conflicts of interest to disclose.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>All data generated or analyzed during this study are included in this published article [and its supplementary information files].</p></fn><fn fn-type="supplementary-material"><p>Supplemental Digital Content is available for this article.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>How to cite this article: Yuan H, Gao F, Wang H. Identification of therapeutic targets for neonatal respiratory distress: A systematic druggable genome-wide Mendelian randomization. Medicine 2025;104:20(e42411).</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>[1]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>IL</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>New developments in neonatal respiratory management.</article-title>
<source>Pediatr Neonatol</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>63</volume>:<fpage>341</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35382987</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>[2]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mei</surname><given-names>YB</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>ZC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>[A review on neonatal acute respiratory distress syndrome].</article-title>
<source>Zhongguo Dang Dai Er Ke Za Zhi</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>724</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30210023</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>[3]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><name><surname>Kotecha</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kotecha</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Respiratory distress of the term newborn infant.</article-title>
<source>Paediatr Respir Rev</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>29</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>36; quiz 36</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23347658</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>[4]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mwita</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jande</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Katabalo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamala</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Dewey</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Reducing neonatal mortality and respiratory distress syndrome associated with preterm birth: a scoping review on the impact of antenatal corticosteroids in low- and middle-income countries.</article-title>
<source>World J Pediatr</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>131</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>40</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33389692</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>[5]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Edmond</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bahl</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Target product profile: aerosolized surfactant for neonatal respiratory distress.</article-title>
<source>Bull World Health Organ</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>101</volume>:<fpage>341</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37131945</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>[6]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Polin</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlo</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name></person-group>; <collab>Committee on Fetus and Newborn</collab>. <article-title>Surfactant replacement therapy for preterm and term neonates with respiratory distress.</article-title>
<source>Pediatrics</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>133</volume>:<fpage>156</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>63</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24379227</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>[7]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>YV</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Integrative analysis of multi-omics data for discovery and functional studies of complex human diseases.</article-title>
<source>Adv Genet</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>93</volume>:<fpage>147</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>90</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26915271</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>[8]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akiyama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Multi-omics study for interpretation of genome-wide association study.</article-title>
<source>J Hum Genet</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>66</volume>:<fpage>3</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32948838</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>[9]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Integration of summary data from GWAS and eQTL studies predicts complex trait gene targets.</article-title>
<source>Nat Genet</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>48</volume>:<fpage>481</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27019110</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>[10]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Cis-eQTL analysis and functional validation of candidate genes for carcass yield traits in beef cattle.</article-title>
<source>Int J Mol Sci</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>15055</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36499383</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>[11]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>TIVAN: tissue-specific cis-eQTL single nucleotide variant annotation and prediction.</article-title>
<source>Bioinformatics</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>1573</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30304335</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>[12]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hopkins</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Groom</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The druggable genome.</article-title>
<source>Nat Rev Drug Discov</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>727</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>30</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12209152</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>[13]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Finan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaulton</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kruger</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The druggable genome and support for target identification and validation in drug development.</article-title>
<source>Sci Transl Med</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>eaag1166</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28356508</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>[14]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Systematic illumination of druggable genes in cancer genomes.</article-title>
<source>Cell Rep</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>110400</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35196490</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>[15]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Evolutionary survey of druggable protein targets with respect to their subcellular localizations.</article-title>
<source>Genome Biol Evol</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>1291</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23749117</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>[16]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Larsson</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Butterworth</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Burgess</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Mendelian randomization for cardiovascular diseases: principles and applications.</article-title>
<source>Eur Heart J</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>44</volume>:<fpage>4913</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>24</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37935836</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>[17]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>QQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>TBK1, a prioritized drug repurposing target for amyotrophic lateral sclerosis: evidence from druggable genome Mendelian randomization and pharmacological verification in vitro.</article-title>
<source>BMC Med</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>96</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38443977</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>[18]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Identifying potential drug targets for idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis: a mendelian randomization study based on the druggable genes.</article-title>
<source>Respir Res</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>217</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38783236</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>[19]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Integrating Mendelian randomization and single-cell RNA sequencing to identify therapeutic targets of baicalin for type 2 diabetes mellitus.</article-title>
<source>Front Pharmacol</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>1403943</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39130628</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>[20]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Freshour</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiwala</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cotto</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Integration of the Drug-Gene Interaction Database (DGIdb 4.0) with open crowdsource efforts.</article-title>
<source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>49</volume>:<fpage>D1144</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>51</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33237278</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>[21]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>V&#x000f5;sa</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Claringbould</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Westra</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>; <collab>BIOS Consortium</collab>. <article-title>Large-scale cis- and trans-eQTL analyses identify thousands of genetic loci and polygenic scores that regulate blood gene expression.</article-title>
<source>Nat Genet</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>53</volume>:<fpage>1300</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34475573</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>[22]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name><surname>Richmond</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>North</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>An integrative approach to detect epigenetic mechanisms that putatively mediate the influence of lifestyle exposures on disease susceptibility.</article-title>
<source>Int J Epidemiol</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>48</volume>:<fpage>887</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>98</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31257439</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>[23]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Plasma pQTL and brain eQTL integration identifies PNKP as a therapeutic target and reveals mechanistic insights into migraine pathophysiology.</article-title>
<source>J Headache Pain</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>202</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39578729</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>[24]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rees</surname><given-names>JMB</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Burgess</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Extending the MR-Egger method for multivariable Mendelian randomization to correct for both measured and unmeasured pleiotropy.</article-title>
<source>Stat Med</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>36</volume>:<fpage>4705</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>18</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28960498</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>[25]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Causal relationship between physical activity, leisure sedentary behaviors and COVID-19 risk: a Mendelian randomization study.</article-title>
<source>J Transl Med</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>216</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35562752</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>[26]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Identification of prospective aging drug targets via Mendelian randomization analysis.</article-title>
<source>Aging Cell</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>e14171</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38572516</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>[27]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoijtink</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Moerbeek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Sample-size determination for the Bayesian t test and Welch&#x02019;s test using the approximate adjusted fractional Bayes factor.</article-title>
<source>Behav Res Methods</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>53</volume>:<fpage>139</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>52</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32632740</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>[28]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mysler</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Moots</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Etanercept for the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis.</article-title>
<source>Immunotherapy</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>433</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>45</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29482402</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>[29]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>R&#x000e9;a</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Development of asciminib, a novel allosteric inhibitor of BCR-ABL1.</article-title>
<source>Crit Rev Oncol Hematol</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>171</volume>:<fpage>103580</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35021069</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>[30]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kleiner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Horv&#x000e1;th</surname><given-names>IL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bunduc</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Nabiximols is efficient as add-on treatment for patients with multiple sclerosis spasticity refractory to standard treatment: a systematic review and meta-analysis of randomised clinical trials.</article-title>
<source>Curr Neuropharmacol</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>2505</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>15</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37519000</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>[31]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Britch</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Babalonis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cannabidiol: pharmacology and therapeutic targets.</article-title>
<source>Psychopharmacology (Berl)</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>238</volume>:<fpage>9</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>28</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33221931</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>[32]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Comprehensive analysis reveals that LTBR is a immune-related biomarker for glioma.</article-title>
<source>Comput Biol Med</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>174</volume>:<fpage>108457</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38599071</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>[33]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Systematic analysis of the prognostic value and immunological function of LTBR in human cancer.</article-title>
<source>Aging (Albany NY)</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>129</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>52</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38175686</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>[34]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>YQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Silencing of TRAF5 enhances necroptosis in hepatocellular carcinoma by inhibiting LTBR-mediated NF-&#x003ba;B signaling.</article-title>
<source>PeerJ</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>e15551</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37366426</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>[35]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brune</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Jochmann</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Brinkrolf</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The IclR-type transcriptional repressor LtbR regulates the expression of leucine and tryptophan biosynthesis genes in the amino acid producer <italic toggle="yes">Corynebacterium glutamicum</italic>.</article-title>
<source>J Bacteriol</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>189</volume>:<fpage>2720</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>33</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17259312</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>[36]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weng</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Maternal prenatal systemic inflammation indexes predicts premature neonatal respiratory distress syndrome.</article-title>
<source>Sci Rep</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>18129</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39103465</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>[37]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Man</surname><given-names>OM</given-names></name><name><surname>Azamor</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Cambou</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Respiratory distress in SARS-CoV-2 exposed uninfected neonates followed in the COVID Outcomes in Mother-Infant Pairs (COMP) Study.</article-title>
<source>Nat Commun</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>399</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38267411</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>[38]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Casein kinase 1 gamma regulates oxidative stress response via interacting with the NADPH dual oxidase complex.</article-title>
<source>PLoS Genet</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>e1010740</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37099597</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>[39]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nguyen Hoang</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoe</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>CSNK1G2 differently sensitizes tamoxifen-induced decrease in PI3K/AKT/mTOR/S6K and ERK signaling according to the estrogen receptor existence in breast cancer cells.</article-title>
<source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>e0246264</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33861751</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>[40]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Piomelli</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Scalvini</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Fotio</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>N-Acylethanolamine acid amidase (NAAA): structure, function, and inhibition.</article-title>
<source>J Med Chem</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>63</volume>:<fpage>7475</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>90</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32191459</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>[41]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nan&#x000ec;</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Pagano</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>De Cicco</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Pharmacological inhibition of N-Acylethanolamine acid amidase (NAAA) mitigates intestinal fibrosis through modulation of macrophage activity.</article-title>
<source>J Crohns Colitis</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>jjae132</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>[42]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsuboi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Takezaki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueda</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The N-acylethanolamine-hydrolyzing acid amidase (NAAA).</article-title>
<source>Chem Biodivers</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>1914</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>25</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17712833</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>