<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Microbiol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Microbiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2180</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12093770</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">4024</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12866-025-04024-1</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Impact of heavy metals on antibiotic resistance of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> from slum wastewater in Kawempe division, Kampala district, Uganda: a case study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Byarugaba</surname><given-names>Isaac</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Nabatanzi</surname><given-names>Alice</given-names></name><address><email>alice2nabatanzi@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Muhumuza</surname><given-names>Emmanuel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kyambadde</surname><given-names>Joseph</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/03dmz0111</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.11194.3c</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0620 0548</institution-id><institution>Department of Biochemistry and Systems Biology, School of Biosciences, College of Natural Sciences, </institution><institution>Makerere University, </institution></institution-wrap>P. O. Box 7062, Kampala, 00256 Uganda </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/03dmz0111</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.11194.3c</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0620 0548</institution-id><institution>Department of Plant Sciences, Microbiology and Biotechnology, School of Biosciences, College of Natural Sciences, </institution><institution>Makerere University, </institution></institution-wrap>P. O. Box 7062, Kampala, 00256 Uganda </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>21</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>25</volume><elocation-id>310</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>8</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>5</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Slum dwellers face significant infrastructure and public health challenges like poor housing and drainage, inadequate sanitation, and limited access to clean water, leading to increased disease transmission and resistance to antibiotic treatments. This study evaluated the impact of heavy metals on antibiotic resistance patterns of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> in wastewater from slums of Bwaise II, Bwaise III, Kazo, and Makerere III in Kawempe division, Kampala.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">Levels of heavy metals (lead, mercury, cadmium, chromium, and arsenic) in wastewater were determined using inductively coupled plasma mass spectroscopy. <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> were isolated from wastewater using MacConkey agar and their susceptibility to 50&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l of stock antibiotics (tetracycline, amoxicillin, ceftriaxone at 30&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml, and ciprofloxacin at 5&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml) determined. The potential of heavy metals to induce antibiotic resistance in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> was determined by culturing susceptible isolates in 200&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l of Luria-Bertina broth containing stock antibiotics (10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l), or stock antibiotics (10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l) and stock heavy metals (10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l). Stock heavy metals were prepared from the average concentration of heavy metals detected in wastewater.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">Detectable levels of heavy metals were reported in wastewater from Bwaise II, Kazo and Makerere III only. Lead, cadmium and arsenic, mercury and chromium, were highest in Bwaise II, Kazo, and Makerere III, respectively. The occurrence of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> resistant to at least an antibiotic was 72.8% (169 of 232) and resistance to tetracycline, ceftriaxone, amoxicillin, and ciprofloxacin were 34.1%, 28.9%, 35.3%, and 34.5%, respectively. Study findings further revealed a positive correlation (R<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.371&#x02013;0.985) between the presence of heavy metals in wastewater and antibiotic resistance patterns of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>. Also, heavy metals; lead (77.41&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml), mercury (1.44&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml), and cadmium (10.21&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml) significantly (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) induced antibiotic resistance in susceptible <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par4">Wastewater in Kawempe slums is polluted with heavy metals and high prevalence of antibiotic-resistant <italic>Escherichia coli.</italic> Inadequate infrastructure in slums facilitate discharge of wastewater polluted with heavy metals, which in turn play a role in increasing antibiotic resistance. There is need for proper wastewater management to contain the prevalence of antibiotic resistance.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Antibiotic resistance</kwd><kwd><italic>Escherichia coli</italic></kwd><kwd>Heavy metals</kwd><kwd>Slums</kwd><kwd>Wastewater</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>The Government of Uganda funded this work through the Makerere University Research Innovations Fund (MAK-RIF)</institution></funding-source><award-id>MAKRIF/CH/02/21</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; BioMed Central Ltd., part of Springer Nature 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par5">Population growth and rural-urban migration in pursuit of employment opportunities, better living standards and services have resulted in urban sprawl [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. This has contributed to the increase in slum residents [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. About 863&#x000a0;million people of the global population and over half of the urban population in lower-income countries are residents of slums [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Approximately 53.6% of the people in Uganda&#x02019;s capital city Kampala are living in slum communities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Slum dwellers face significant infrastructure and public health challenges such as inadequate sanitation, poor housing and drainage, limited access to clean water, which in turn lead to increased disease transmission and resistance to antibiotic treatments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Consequently, residents are at risk of suffering from life-threatening waterborne and soil-hosted diseases such as diarrhea, typhoid, and cholera [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. In developing countries, about 88% of diarrhea cases are attributed to inadequate hygiene and the use of contaminated water [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Moreover, <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> (<italic>E. coli</italic>) a member of fecal coliforms, yet an important pathogen for diarrhea is most prevalent in such environmental conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>].</p><p id="Par6">Water contamination is caused by industrial, domestic, agricultural and radioactive wastes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. These wastes enter the water system through leaking sewers, urban and agricultural runoffs, industrial and household wastewater, often contaminated with various bacteria and unquantifiable quantities of antibiotic resistance driving agents such as residual antibiotics, disinfectants, heavy metals and other toxic chemicals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. These in turn favor microbial growth and establish antibiotic selection pressure which drives the proliferation of antibiotic resistance in pathogenic microorganisms, such as <italic>E. coli</italic>, leading to a rise in the prevalence of antibiotic-resistant bacteria in water systems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Antibiotic resistance is associated with reduced treatment efficacy and options, high medical costs, recurring health complications, and prolonged hospital stays, hence increased mortality rate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. As a matter of concern, the World Health organization (WHO) has recognized antibiotic resistance as one of the top environmental health challenges facing humanity to date with the global mortality rate estimated at 700,000 deaths per year [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. Antibiotic resistance occurs when bacteria develop mechanisms to evade antibiotic effects allowing them to persist and spread despite treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. These mechanisms include; chromosomal mutations in genes coding for the antibiotic targets, over-expression of efflux pumps, physical blocking of the antibiotic targets, and enzymatic modification of the antibiotics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>].</p><p id="Par7">Studies by [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>], reported a correlation between heavy metals and antibiotic resistance in point sources of contamination, i.e., wastewater treatment plants, animal farms, solid waste dump sites, and health facilities, respectively. Studies on determining the levels of heavy metal in non-point sources of contamination such as in slum communities and their effects on microbial communities are still limited. In addition, majority of studies aimed at understanding the causes of antimicrobial resistance were limited to the misuse of antibiotics which is associated with increased antibiotic residue pollution. However, it is possible that chemical contaminants discharged in the environment could have a significant effect on the abundance of resistance genes and proliferation of antibiotic selection pressure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>].</p><p id="Par8">In Uganda, no studies have been conducted to determine the effect of heavy metal contamination on antibiotic resistance in wastewater discharged in slums. Therefore, the objectives of this study were; to determine the levels of heavy metals and antibiotic resistance patterns of <italic>E. coli</italic> in wastewater discharged in selected slums of Kawempe division, Kampala, and determine the effect of heavy metals on the antibiotic resistance patterns of <italic>E. coli.</italic> The study findings provide information on the current status of heavy metal contamination and antibiotic resistance patterns in wastewater discharged in slums of Kawempe division, Kampala. The findings also indicate the role of heavy metals on the prevalence of antibiotic resistance in wastewater.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Study area</title><p id="Par9">The study was conducted in Kawempe which constitutes one of the five administrative divisions of Kampala the capital city of Uganda. Kawempe division is a peri-urban setting located at 00<sup>O</sup>22&#x02019;45&#x0201d; N 32<sup>O</sup>33&#x02019;27&#x0201d; E in the northwestern corner of Kampala city, bordered by Wakiso district in the west, Nakawa division in the southeast, Central division in the south and Rubaga division in the southwest (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Kawempe is characterized by poor waste management and drainage systems, poor housing conditions and limited access to clean water, as well as numerous fuel stations and motor workshops [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. It has a population of 338,665 with 52% as women and about 94,202 households. Its climate is tropical rainforest featuring wet and dry seasons with average rainfall&#x02009;~&#x02009;1200&#x000a0;mm/year [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>].</p><p id="Par10">Kawempe has about 15 informal settlements (slums) accounting for about 85.8% (290,500 of 338,665) of its population, and majority of the unlined pit latrines (38%) of the total pit latrines a predominant sanitation technology in Kampala [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>].</p><p id="Par11">
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Wastewater sampling points in Kawempe division, Kampala</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12866_2025_4024_Fig1_HTML" id="d33e363"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Study design</title><p id="Par12">The study design was both experimental and a case study. Kawempe division was selected because of the highest unimproved sanitation incidences where excreta are not hygienically separated from human contact compared to other divisions of Kampala. Slums of Bwaise II, Bwaise III, Kazo, and Makerere III were purposively sampled because of their highest levels of unimproved sanitation compared to other parishes in Kawempe division [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Wastewater sampling points were purposively sampled at the intersection points of wastewater emerging from at least two households, near the walkway, waste dumping sites, and feeding points of the free-range domestic animals (hens, ducks).</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Pilot survey</title><p id="Par13">A pilot survey was conducted for four days in the slums of Bwaise II, Bwaise III, Kazo, and Makerere III to identify wastewater sampling points. The GPS coordinates and photos of the selected sites were captured using the Kobo Collect data collection tool (Additional file 1).</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Collection of wastewater samples</title><p id="Par14">Wastewater samples were collected in duplicate from 22 identified sources in slums of Bwaise II (7), Bwaise III (2), Kazo (9), and Makerere III (4) potentially contaminated with heavy metals and <italic>E. coli</italic>. The samples were collected early morning (6:30 am-8:00 am) because of the more stabilized pH and temperature pronounced at that time of the day. Samples were collected in well-labeled sterile 50&#x000a0;ml and 500&#x000a0;ml screw-capped plastic bottles, transported to the laboratory in ice-cooled boxes at 4 <sup>O</sup>C, and stored in a refrigerator at 4 <sup>O</sup>C prior analysis. Before analysis, the duplicate wastewater samples from each sampling point were mixed to form a composite sample. The 50&#x000a0;ml samples were used to isolate <italic>E. coli</italic> in the Microbiology laboratory at the Department of Plant Sciences, Microbiology and Biotechnology, Makerere University while the 500&#x000a0;ml samples were used to determine the levels of heavy metals at the Government Analytical Laboratory in Wandegeya, Kampala-Uganda.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Determination of the levels of heavy metals</title><p id="Par15">The levels of heavy metals lead (Pb), mercury (Hg), cadmium (Cd), chromium (Cr), and arsenic (As) were analyzed by the inductively coupled plasma mass spectroscopy (ICP-MS, Agilent 7700, USA) following the HJ776-2015 method and the ISO/IEC 17025:2017 requirements. The composite wastewater samples were filtered using a 0.45&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m pore filter membrane. To 25&#x000a0;ml of the filtrates, 1&#x000a0;ml of 30% hydrogen peroxide was added followed by 1&#x000a0;ml of concentrated nitric acid. The mixture was then digested at 180 <sup>O</sup>C for 15&#x000a0;min. The digests were diluted by addition of 50&#x000a0;ml of de-ionized water and the concentrations (ppb) determined using inductively coupled plasma mass spectroscopy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. This was replicated 10 times to determine the levels of heavy metals in the wastewater filtrates from each sampling point. A mixed standard solution including all the heavy metals (Pb, Hg, Cd, Cr, As) and reagent blanks was carried out through digestion and analyzed as part of the quality control protocol.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Isolation of <italic>E. coli</italic> from wastewater</title><p id="Par16">Ten-fold serial dilution was performed on wastewater samples using distilled water. For every sample, 100&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l of the 10<sup>&#x02212;&#x02009;5</sup> serial dilution was surface plated on MacConkey agar (Jijan Babio Biotechnology Co. Ltd.) and incubated at 37 <sup>O</sup>C for 48&#x000a0;h. A reference strain (<italic>E. coli</italic> ATCC 25922) was surface plated as a positive control, and MacConkey agar with no inoculum as a negative control. <italic>E. coli</italic> colonies were identified by their morphological similarity to the reference strain which grow as pink colonies surrounded by an area of precipitated bile salts on MacConkey agar [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. The selected <italic>E. coli</italic> colonies were sub-cultured in Luria-Bertani broth (Scharlab, Spain) at 37 <sup>O</sup>C for 24&#x000a0;h in an orbital shaker at 125&#x000a0;rpm to obtain pure cultures, and later stored at 4 <sup>O</sup>C prior to screening for antibiotic resistance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Determination of antibiotic resistance patterns</title><p id="Par17">Agar well diffusion method was used to test for the susceptibility of <italic>E. coli</italic> to antibiotics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. The antibiotic stock solutions of tetracycline (TET, 30&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml), amoxicillin (AMX, 30&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml), ceftriaxone (CFT, 30&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml), and ciprofloxacin (CIP, 5&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml) were prepared. Pure cultures of <italic>E. coli</italic> were standardized by dilution using freshly prepared Luria-Bertani (LB) broth until a consistent OD<sub>600</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.5 equivalent to 3&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;1000<sup>8</sup> CFU/mL was obtained. LB agar plates were prepared and 100&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l of the pure culture surface plated. This was followed by creating wells on the agar plates using a sterile micropipette tip, addition of 50&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l of the stock antibiotics, and incubation at 37 <sup>O</sup>C for 24&#x000a0;h. The diameter (mm) of zone of inhibition was measured and interpreted as resistant, intermediate, or susceptible according to the Clinical Laboratory Standard Institute (CLSI) guidelines for Enterobacterales [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. During this study, all isolates that showed intermediate zone of inhibition were considered resistant. The multiple antibiotic resistance index (MARI) was also determined for each isolate as described by [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>] using the formula below.</p><p id="Par18">
<disp-formula id="Equ1"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e462">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\rm{MARI}}\&#x0003e;{\rm{ = }}\&#x0003e;{{{\rm{No}}{\rm{.}}\&#x0003e;{\rm{of}}\&#x0003e;{\rm{antibiotics}}\&#x0003e;{\rm{the}}\&#x0003e;{\rm{isolate}}\&#x0003e;{\rm{is}}\&#x0003e;{\rm{resistant\,to}}} \over {{\rm{Total}}\&#x0003e;{\rm{number}}\&#x0003e;{\rm{of}}\&#x0003e;{\rm{antibiotics}}\&#x0003e;{\rm{tested}}\&#x0003e;{\rm{against}}}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xlink:href="12866_2025_4024_Article_Equ1.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Determination of the effect of heavy metals on antibiotic resistance patterns</title><p id="Par19">This included assessing the relationship between the presence of heavy metals and prevalence of antibiotic resistance in the collected wastewater samples, and determining the potential of heavy metals to induce antibiotic resistance in <italic>E. coli</italic> by the microdilution method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. In the latter case, the antibiotic susceptible <italic>E. coli</italic> isolates from the sampling points where no heavy metals were detected were used in this study. These were re-cultured in freshly prepared LB broth at 37 <sup>O</sup>C for 24&#x000a0;h with shaking at 200&#x000a0;rpm, and later standardized by dilution using freshly prepared broth until a consistent OD<sub>600</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.5 equivalent to 3&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;1000<sup>8</sup> CFU/ml was obtained. Stock solutions of heavy metals (Pb, Cd, Hg) were prepared from salts of Pb(NO3)<sub>2</sub> (Scharlab, Spain), CdCl<sub>2</sub> (BDH Chemicals Ltd Poole, England), and Hg(NO3)<sub>2</sub> (BDH Chemicals Ltd Poole, England), respectively. The molecular weight of the salt and the atomic weight of the heavy metal was used to calculate the weight composition (P) of the heavy metal in the respective salt. This was used to determine the amount of the salt (Y) needed to prepare a stock solution with the desired amount of the heavy metal (M) using the formula below [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>].</p><p id="Par20">
<disp-formula id="Equ2"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e499">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:\left(P\right)\:X\:\left(Y\right)\:=\:\left(M\right)$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xlink:href="12866_2025_4024_Article_Equ2.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>
</p><p id="Par21">
<disp-formula id="Equ3"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e507">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\&#x0003e;{\rm{Y}}\&#x0003e;{\rm{ = }}\&#x0003e;{{\left( {\rm{M}} \right)} \over {\left( {\rm{P}} \right)}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xlink:href="12866_2025_4024_Article_Equ3.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>
</p><p id="Par22">The &#x000b5;g equivalent of the salt weighed was dissolved in 1&#x000a0;ml of distilled water to make a one-time (1X) stock solution of the heavy metal salt. The stock solutions were prepared from the average amount of the heavy metals detected in wastewater samples. The antibiotic susceptible isolates were cultured in 200&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l of LB broth containing 10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l of stock antibiotics (tetracycline, amoxicillin, ceftriaxone at 30&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml; and ciprofloxacin at 5&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml), or a combination of stock antibiotics (10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l) and stock heavy metals (10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l). The plates were then incubated at 37 <sup>O</sup>C for 48&#x000a0;h. The growth of each isolate exposed to either antibiotics or a combination of antibiotics and heavy metals was assessed by measuring their OD<sub>600</sub> using the iMark microplate absorbance reader (Bio-Rad, USA). A negative control excluded exposure of isolates to either the antibiotics or heavy metals. The resultant microbial growth patterns were used to determine the effect of heavy metals on antibiotic resistance in <italic>E. coli</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Data analysis</title><p id="Par23">Raw data sorting and descriptive statistics were performed using MS Excel 2019. The antibiotic resistance patterns of <italic>E. coli</italic> isolates were compared using chi-square tests. Linear regression was used to assess the relationship between heavy metals and antibiotic resistance patterns. T-test was used to compare the resistance patterns of <italic>E. coli</italic> on exposure to antibiotics against a combination of antibiotics and heavy metals. Comparisons were considered significantly different at a level of 95% CI (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.05). The linear regression, T-test, chi-square test, and the graphical presentation of the data were performed using GraphPad Prism 8.0.1.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec13"><title>Levels of heavy metals in wastewater</title><p id="Par24">The pollution levels of heavy metals in wastewater from slums of Bwaise II, Bwaise III, Kazo and Makerere III are presented in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. Results showed that at least one heavy metal was detected in 50% (11 of 22) of the wastewater samples collected. Detectable levels of heavy metals were reported at sampling points A1, A2, A4 and A6 in Bwaise II; C1, C2, C3, C4 and C9 in Kazo; and D2 and D4 in Makerere III. The highest levels of Pb were detected in Bwaise II at sampling point A4, while Cd and As were highest in Kazo at sampling points C1 and C2, respectively. Levels of Hg and Cr were highest in Makerere III at sampling points D2 and D4, respectively.</p><p id="Par25">
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>The mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;sd levels of heavy metals (ppb) detected in wastewater samples from slums of Bwaise II, Bwaise III, Kazo and Makerere III</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Sampling area</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">Sampling point</th><th align="left" colspan="5">Heavy metals (LOD)</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Hg (0.54)</th><th align="left">Pb (0.35)</th><th align="left">Cd (0.15)</th><th align="left">Cr (0.5)</th><th align="left">As (0.5)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="7">Bwaise II</td><td align="left">A1</td><td align="left">4.21&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.56</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">12.70&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.04</td></tr><tr><td align="left">A2</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">34.14&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.21</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left">A3</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left">A4</td><td align="left">2.03&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.09</td><td align="left">783.84&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.22</td><td align="left">45.05&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.08</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left">A5</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left">A6</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">5.11&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.92</td><td align="left">8.05&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.14</td></tr><tr><td align="left">A7</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Bwaise III</td><td align="left">B1</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left">B2</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="9">Kazo</td><td align="left">C1</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">61.03&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.21</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C2</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">2.16&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.11</td><td align="left">647.58&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.94</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C3</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">13.22&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.17</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">4.39&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.22</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C4</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">15.92&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.03</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C5</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C6</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C7</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C8</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C9</td><td align="left">1.06&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">3.06&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.11</td><td align="left">2.04&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4">Makerere III</td><td align="left">D1</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left">D2</td><td align="left">12.39&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.07</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left">D3</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left">D4</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">274.12&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.06</td><td align="left">26.36&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.33</td><td align="left">73.93&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.17</td><td align="left">16.02&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.03</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>LOD; Level of detection, SD; Standard Deviation, (-); no detectable heavy metals</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Antibiotic resistance patterns of <italic>E. coli</italic> in wastewater samples</title><p id="Par26">Results for <italic>E. coli</italic> isolates in wastewater are presented in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>. Wastewater samples from all sampling points showed growth of <italic>E. coli</italic> on MacConkey agar plates. A total of 232 out of 769 isolates were identified as <italic>E. coli</italic> based on their morphological similarity with a reference strain.</p><p id="Par27">
<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Number of isolates identified as <italic>E. coli</italic> from wastewater samples</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Sampling area (<italic>n</italic>)</th><th align="left">Total isolates</th><th align="left">E. coli isolates</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Bwaise II (7)</td><td align="left">274</td><td align="left">93</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Bwaise III (2)</td><td align="left">67</td><td align="left">16</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Kazo (9)</td><td align="left">324</td><td align="left">82</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Makerere III (4)</td><td align="left">104</td><td align="left">41</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<bold>Total</bold>
</td><td align="left">
<bold>769</bold>
</td><td align="left">
<bold>232</bold>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>n&#x02009;=&#x02009;number of wastewater samples</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par28">Results for the susceptibility tests of <italic>E. coli</italic> isolates from the different slum areas under this study are presented as Additional file 2. Overall, 72.8% (169 out of 232) of the <italic>E. coli</italic> isolates from the different slum areas were resistant to at least one of the four antibiotics (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).</p><p id="Par29">
<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Percentage antibiotic resistance and the multiple antibiotics resistance index (MARI) of <italic>E. coli</italic> isolated from wastewater from the slums of Kawempe</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Sampling Area</th><th align="left">Resistant E. coli isolates (<italic>n</italic>)</th><th align="left">% Resistance</th><th align="left">MARI</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Bwaise II</td><td align="left">67(93)</td><td align="left">72.0</td><td align="left">0.28</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Bwaise III</td><td align="left">8(16)</td><td align="left">50.0</td><td align="left">0.23</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Kazo</td><td align="left">58(82)</td><td align="left">70.7</td><td align="left">0.32</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Makerere III</td><td align="left">36(41)</td><td align="left">87.8</td><td align="left">0.45</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>n&#x02009;=&#x02009;number of isolates screened for resistance</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par30">The resistance pattern for each antibiotic varied significantly (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.000) for all <italic>E. coli</italic> isolates from the different slum areas. The proportions of <italic>E. coli</italic> resistant to tetracycline, ceftriaxone, amoxicillin, and ciprofloxacin were 34.1%, 28.9%, 35.3%, and 34.5%, respectively. The trends of resistance patterns for <italic>E. coli</italic> isolates from Bwaise II, Bwaise III, Kazo, and Makerere III were TET&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;AMX&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;CIP&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;CFT; CIP&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;AMX&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;TET&#x02009;=&#x02009;CFT; CFT&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;TET&#x02009;=&#x02009;AMX&#x02009;=&#x02009;CIP; and CFT&#x02009;=&#x02009;CIP&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;AMX&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;TET, respectively (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).</p><p id="Par31">
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Antibiotic resistance patterns of <italic>E. coli i</italic>solated from wastewater samples</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12866_2025_4024_Fig2_HTML" id="d33e1085"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Effect of heavy metals on antibiotic resistance patterns</title><p id="Par32">Results showed positive correlation between the presence of heavy metals namely; Pb (R<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.985), Hg (R<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.672), Cd (R<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.853), Cr (R<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.371), As (R<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.672) and the antibiotic resistance patterns of <italic>E. coli</italic> from sampling points at the different slum areas investigated (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Results for OD<sub>600</sub> showing growth of <italic>E. coli</italic> in media supplemented with a combination of antibiotics (tetracycline, amoxicillin, ceftriaxone, ciprofloxacin) and heavy metals; Pb (77.41&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml), Hg (1.44&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml), and Cd (10.21&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml), and growth supplemented with antibiotics only are presented as Additional file 3. There was a significant increase (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) in the growth of <italic>E. coli</italic> isolates (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;12) cultured in media supplemented with a combination of antibiotics and heavy metals compared to growth supplemented with antibiotics only (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>).</p><p id="Par33">
<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Relationship between the presence of heavy metals and antibiotic resistance patterns of <italic>E. coli</italic> in wastewater</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12866_2025_4024_Fig3_HTML" id="d33e1138"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par34">
<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Growth of <italic>E. coli</italic> in LB broth supplemented with antibiotics only and a combination of antibiotics with heavy metals at OD<sub>600nm</sub></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12866_2025_4024_Fig4_HTML" id="d33e1153"/></fig>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par35">Slum dwellers face significant infrastructure and public health challenges like poor housing and drainage, inadequate sanitation, and limited access to clean water [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. This study revealed that heavy metals were present and the magnitude of their levels in wastewater collected from the different slum areas of Kawempe division varied. The variations could have been due to differences in soil components and wastewater generated at the different sampling sites.</p><p id="Par36">Lead was recorded highest in Bwaise II at sampling point A4, located downstream of the dumping site of wastes generated from the market in Jambula cell, which suggest the possible source of the high Pb levels detected in wastewater. Moreover [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>], in their studies reported that the source of Pb pollution in the environment is usually from electronic and battery wastes, corrosion of old buildings with lead paints, and runoffs from bituminous paving on roads. The highest levels of Cd and As were reported in wastewater samples from Kazo at sampling points C1 and C2, respectively. At the upstream end of sampling point C1 in Kazo-Angola cell, there is an Agri-processing factory, and household solid waste dumping site which could be the source of high Cd levels detected in wastewater at the sampling point. At the upstream end of sampling point C2 in Kazo-Angola cell, brick making activities, and household wastes burning spots were observed near the drainage systems. In addition to runoffs from a water spring and garden near the sampling point, these could have served as the sources of arsenic. The observed potential sources of As and Cd are in line with what [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>] reported in their study as the source of arsenic and cadmium pollution, i.e., combustion of fossil fuel, incineration of municipal and industrial wastes, human activities such as mining, land application of sewage sludge, and fertilizer EPA. Levels of Hg and Cr were highest in wastewater from Makerere III at sampling points D2 in Kibbe cell and D4 in Sebina cell, respectively. The runoffs through metallic case and carpentry workshops, and waste dumping sites in the neighboring areas of the sampling points could be the potential sources of the high Cr and Hg levels detected. Moreover [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>], in their study reported metal coating, dyes production for painting, wood protection materials, textile industry, chemical production, fluorescent light lamps, and fungicides as sources of Hg and Cr pollution in the environment.</p><p id="Par37">The levels of Pb detected in Bwaise II and Makerere III at sampling points A4 and D4, respectively were higher than permissible limits by WHO (10 ppb) and NEMA (100 ppb), whereas at sampling point C3 in Kazo they were higher than the limits by WHO only. The levels of Cd in Bwaise II, Kazo, and Makerere III at sampling points A4, C1 and C9, and D4, respectively exceeded the permissible limits by the WHO (3 ppb). Only Cr levels detected in Makerere III at sampling point D4 exceeded the permissible limits by WHO (50 ppb) and NEMA (50 ppb), whereas Hg exceeded the permissible levels by WHO (1 ppb) in wastewater samples from Bwaise II, Kazo, and Makerere III at sampling points A1 and A4, C9, and D2, respectively. Heaps of wastes were observed at all wastewater sampling points or at the upstream ends where the levels exceeded the permissible limits. These suggest spill offs from the wastes as the potential source of heavy metal pollution in slums of Kawempe division.</p><p id="Par38">In this study, 72.8% of <italic>E. coli</italic> isolates were resistant to at least one of the four antibiotics tested. This was in agreement with findings by [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>] who reported resistance patterns of <italic>E. coli</italic> to at least one of the 16 antimicrobial agents screened in Africa between 2005 and 2018 that ranged from 33.3 to 100%. Worth noting is that 43% of people living in slums do self-medication using antibiotics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]. In addition, 30&#x02013;90% of the ingested antibiotics are excreted unchanged [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>] which end up in wastewater. Moreover, antibiotics and various personal care products used, as well as anthropogenic activities contribute to a build-up of antibiotic selection pressure in wastewaters [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>].</p><p id="Par39">A study by [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>] described the average multiple antibiotic resistance index (MARI) value as an indicator of the level of contaminants in the environment where the bacteria are isolated. This study revealed that the average MARI value of isolates varied amongst slums. Moreover, wastewater samples from Bwaise III with heavy metals below the level of detection had isolates with the lowest MARI value compared to the other slums with detectable levels. This finding relates with findings by [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>] and [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>] who reported differences in the MARI values for isolates from hospital wastewater and non-hospital wastewater. In addition, there was a positive correlation between the presence of heavy metals in wastewater and antibiotic resistance patterns (R<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.371&#x02013;0.985) across the slums, signifying the role of heavy metals in the build-up of antibiotic selection pressure.</p><p id="Par40">Some heavy metals at low concentrations are reported to be essential elements in different biochemical processes and may become toxic at high concentrations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>]. In addition, prolonged exposure to heavy metals has been reported to have effects on the composition and activity of microbial communities by selecting for metal resistance as well as co-selection for resistance to antibiotics through activation of efflux pumps, enzyme detoxification, and alteration of cellular targets [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>].</p><p id="Par41">During this study, supplementing the growth media with a combination of heavy metals and antibiotics significantly (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) counteracted the antibiotic effects on <italic>E. coli</italic> leading to an increase in their growth. This relates well with findings by [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>] who reported a significant increase (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) in the minimum inhibitory concentrations of ampicillin against pathogenic bacteria collected from sites close to metal mining activities compared to the control sites, and [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>] who reported a significant increase in bacterial growth in heavy metal plus antibiotics supplemented media. The exposure to Pb, Cd, and Hg could have activated cross resistance mechanism leading to mutations in the ribosomes which in turn change the configuration of the binding sites for tetracycline [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]. Also, this exposure could have activated the co-resistance mechanism inducing the expression of beta-lactam genes that code for beta-lactamase enzyme which hydrolyze the beta-lactam ring in ceftriaxone and amoxicillin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>]. Besides, resistance to ciprofloxacin was only increased with exposure to Cd which could have resulted from the higher interaction capacity with the gyrase enzyme unlike Pb and Hg or the high concentration of Cd that interfered with Mg<sup>2+</sup> co-factor functions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>]. Co-resistance occurs when two or more resistance genes are present on the same mobile genetic element, such as plasmids, transposons hence inducing multiple resistance mechanisms. Moreover, heavy metal resistance genes and antibiotic resistance genes have been reported to co-occur on the same mobile genetic elements [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Cross-resistance on the other hand occurs when a single mechanism such as mutation in the target sites simultaneously induces resistance to different stress agents. This is supported by findings of [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>] who reported that more than 75% of the bacteria isolates with high tolerance to heavy metals were resistant to some antibiotics yet very few tested positive for antibiotic resistance genes; and findings of [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>] who reported an association between tetracycline and heavy metal resistance.</p><p id="Par42">Our study findings, therefore, elaborated the role of heavy metal pollution with regard to the prevalence of antibiotic resistance in <italic>E. coli</italic>. With more than 80% of the world&#x02019;s wastewater generated being discharged into the environment without treatment, the public health is at risk of increased antibiotic resistant infections [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>]. Surface water sources such as rivers, lakes, and wells being major sinks for the wastewater discharged into the environment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>], water quality will increasingly be compromised by antibiotic resistant bacteria. In addition, wastewater is also used in agriculture for irrigation farming [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>] which predisposes plants to contamination with antibiotic resistant pathogenic bacteria.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par43">The present study highlights the presence of heavy metals in wastewater collected from slums of Kawempe Division, Kampala with Pb, Hg, and Cd at levels higher than permissible limits set by WHO. The study further reported high resistance patterns (72.8%) of <italic>E. coli</italic> isolated from wastewater samples to tetracycline, amoxicillin, ceftriaxone, and ciprofloxacin. The findings also reported the significant role of Pb, Cd, and Hg in inducing resistance of <italic>E. coli</italic> to different classes of antibiotics, which represent a major public health concern. This therefore calls for proper wastewater management to contain the prevalence of antibiotic resistance in pathogenic microorganisms.</p><p id="Par44">This study recommends more research involving larger sample size and seasonal variations as well as other divisions of Kampala to obtain more data regarding heavy metal pollution, and antibiotic resistance. Future studies may also focus on the long-term exposure of pathogenic bacteria to heavy metals and how it affects the biochemical pathways to ascertain their AMR mechanisms.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>Osbert Nuwahereza designed the map of the study area, and Chris Bima assisted in wastewater sample collection. Department of Plant Sciences, Microbiology, and Biotechnology provided the Microbiology Laboratory, and DGAL provided the heavy metal analysis services.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>JK, AN, BI developed the study design; BI, EM collected, and processed samples; BI analyzed samples; AN, JK, BI, and EM prepared, read, and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was funded by the Government of Uganda through the Makerere University Research Innovations Fund (MAK-RIF) grant number MAKRIF/CH/02/21.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>All relevant data are reported in the manuscript.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par45">This study did not use human subject samples or data, so no Institutional Review Board (IRB) approval or participants&#x02019; consent was needed.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par46">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par47">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>AMR</term><def><p id="Par48">Antimicrobial resistance</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>AMX</term><def><p id="Par49">Amoxicillin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CFT</term><def><p id="Par50">Ceftriaxone</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CFU</term><def><p id="Par51">Colony-Forming Unit</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CIP</term><def><p id="Par52">Ciprofloxacin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DGAL</term><def><p id="Par53">Directorate of the Government Analytical Laboratory</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DNA</term><def><p id="Par54">Deoxyribonucleic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GPS</term><def><p id="Par55">Global Positioning System</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ICP-MS</term><def><p id="Par56">Inductively Coupled Mass spectroscopy</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>KCCA</term><def><p id="Par57">Kampala Capital City Authority</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MARI</term><def><p id="Par58">Multiple Antibiotic Resistance Index</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NEMA</term><def><p id="Par59">National Environment Management Authority</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RPM</term><def><p id="Par60">Revolutions Per Minute</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TET</term><def><p id="Par61">Tetracycline</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>UBOS</term><def><p id="Par62">Uganda Bureau of Statistics</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>WHO</term><def><p id="Par63">World Health Organization</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Tumwesigye S, Hemerijckx L, marie, Opio A, Poesen J, Vanmaercke M, Twongyirwe R et al. Who and Why? Understanding Rural Out-Migration in Uganda. 2021;104&#x02013;23.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mafabi M. Graduate School Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering Investigating the Occurrence of Contaminants of Emerging Concern in Urban Slum Areas: a Case Study of Bwaise, Kawempe Division, Kampala-Uganda. 2021;(May).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kayaga S, Fisher J, Goodall S, Kanyesigye C, Kaggwa R, Nambiro M et al. Enhancing livelihoods of the urban poor through productive uses of utility- supplied water services &#x02013; Evidence from Kampala, Uganda. Cities [Internet]. 2020;102(March):102721. Available from: 10.1016/j.cities.2020.102721</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Niva</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Taka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Varis</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rural-urban migration and the growth of informal settlements: A socio-ecological system conceptualization with insights through a water lens</article-title><source>Sustain</source><year>2019</year><volume>11</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>10</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Niva V, Taka M, Varis O. Rural-urban migration and the growth of informal settlements: A socio-ecological system conceptualization with insights through a water lens. Sustain. 2019;11(12):7&#x02013;10.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ssemugabo C, Nalinya S, Biyinzika Lubega G, Ndejjo R, Musoke D. Health Risks in Our Environment: Urban Slum Youth&#x02019; Perspectives Using Photovoice in Kampala, Uganda. 2020;13(1).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Musoke D, Ndejjo R, Halage AA, Kasasa S, Ssempebwa JC, Carpenter DO. Drinking Water Supply, Sanitation, and Hygiene Promotion Interventions in Two Slum Communities in Central Uganda. J Environ Public Health. 2018;2018.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Vane CH, Kim AW, Lopes dos Santos RA, Gill JC, Moss-Hayes V, Mulu JK et al. Impact of organic pollutants from urban slum informal settlements on sustainable development goals and river sediment quality, Nairobi, Kenya, Africa. Appl Geochem. 2022;105468. 10.1016/j.apgeochem.2022.105468</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Odetoyin B, Ogundipe O, Onanuga A. Prevalence, diversity of diarrhoeagenic Escherichia coli and associated risk factors in well water in Ile-Ife, Southwestern Nigeria. One Heal Outlook [Internet]. 2022; Available from: 10.1186/s42522-021-00057-4</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cabral</surname><given-names>JPS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Water microbiology. Bacterial pathogens and water</article-title><source>Int J Environ Res Public Health</source><year>2010</year><volume>7</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>3657</fpage><lpage>703</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph7103657</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21139855</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Cabral JPS. Water microbiology. Bacterial pathogens and water. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2010;7(10):3657&#x02013;703.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21139855</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bashir I, Lone FA, Bhat RA, Mir SA, Dar ZA, Dar SA. Concerns and Threats of Contamination on Aquatic Ecosystems. In: Bioremediation and Biotechnology [Internet]. Springer, Cham; 2020. pp. 1&#x02013;26. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://link.springer.com/chapter/">https://link.springer.com/chapter/</ext-link>10.1007/978-3-030-35691-0_1</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Rathi BS, Kumar PS. Application of adsorption process for effective removal of emerging contaminants from water and wastewater *. Environ Pollut [Internet]. 2021;280:116995. Available from: 10.1016/j.envpol.2021.116995</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Giek S, Saeidi N, Gu X, Gabrielle G, Vergara R, Gin KY. hoong. Occurrence of microbial indicators, pathogenic bacteria and viruses in tropical surface waters subject to contrasting land use. Water Res [Internet]. 2019;150:200&#x02013;15. Available from: 10.1016/j.watres.2018.11.058</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Yusuf I, Muhammad ZD, Amin BM, Shuaibu MD, Hamza N, Isah HD et al. Detection of clinically relevant antibiotic- &#x000ad; resistant bacteria in shared fomites, waste water and municipal solid wastes disposed near residential areas of a Nigerian city. 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Edokpayi JN, Odiyo JO, Edokpayi N, Odiyo JO, Durowoju OS. In. Household hazardous waste management in &#x000ad; impact of wastewater on surface water quality in sub-Saharan Africa developing countries: A case study of South Africa. InTech. 2017. 10.5772/66561</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Fouz N, Pangesti KNA, Yasir M, Al-malki AL. The contribution of wastewater to the transmission of antimicrobial resistance in the environment. Implications of Mass Gathering Settings; 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Komijani M, Eghbalpour F, Lari E, Baygloo NS. Developing erythromycin resistance gene by heavy metals, Pb, Zn, and Co, in aquatic ecosystems. Sci Rep [Internet]. 2022;(0123456789):1&#x02013;8. Available from: 10.1038/s41598-022-25272-5</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Shaharoona B, Al-ismaily S, Al-mayahi A, Al-harrasi N. Heliyon The role of urbanization in soil and groundwater contamination by heavy metals and pathogenic bacteria: A case study from Oman. Heliyon [Internet]. 2019;5(April):e01771. Available from: 10.1016/j.heliyon.2019.e01771</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Osi A, Korzeniewska E, Harnisz M, Niest S. The prevalence and characterization of antibiotic-resistant and virulent Escherichia coli strains in the municipal wastewater system and their environmental fate. Sci Total Environ. 2016;577:367&#x02013;375. 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2016.10.203</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Pulingam T, Parumasivam T, Gazzali AM, Sulaiman AM, Chee JY, Lakshmanan M et al. Antimicrobial resistance: Prevalence, economic burden, mechanisms of resistance and strategies to overcome. Eur J Pharm Sci [Internet]. 2022;170:106103. Available from: 10.1016/j.ejps.2021.106103</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kumar SB, Arnipalli SR, Ziouzenkova O. Antibiotics in food chain: the consequences for antibiotic resistance. Antibiotics. 2020; 9(10):688. 10.3390/antibiotics9100688</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">WHO. Antimicrobial Resistance [Internet]. 2023. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/antimicrobial-resistance">https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/antimicrobial-resistance</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Niegowska M, Sanseverino I, Navarro A, Lettieri T. Knowledge gaps in the assessment of antimicrobial resistance in surface waters. 2021;(July):1&#x02013;17.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kariuki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kering</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wairimu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Onsare</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Mbae</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial resistance rates and surveillance in Sub-Saharan Africa: where are we now??</article-title><source>Infect Drug Resist</source><year>2022</year><volume>15</volume><issue>June</issue><fpage>3589</fpage><lpage>609</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/IDR.S342753</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35837538</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Kariuki S, Kering K, Wairimu C, Onsare R, Mbae C. Antimicrobial resistance rates and surveillance in Sub-Saharan Africa: where are we now?? Infect Drug Resist. 2022;15(June):3589&#x02013;609.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35837538</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Suge T, Magu D, Wanzala P. Correlation between Escherichia coli resistant gene isolated from stool samples of children under five years and that from consumed water. Sci African [Internet]. 2023;22(October):e01937. Available from: 10.1016/j.sciaf.2023.e01937</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Christaki E, Marcou M, Tofarides A. Antimicrobial Resistance in Bacteria: Mechanisms, Evolution, and Persistence. J Mol Evol [Internet]. 2019;(0123456789). Available from: 10.1007/s00239-019-09914-3</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Morrison L, Zembower TR. A n t i m i c ro b i a l R e s i s t a n c e. Gastrointest Endosc Clin NA [Internet]. 2020;30(4):619&#x02013;35. Available from: 10.1016/j.giec.2020.06.004</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Putten BCL, Van Der, Remondini D, Pasquini G, Janes VA, Schultsz C. Quantifying the contribution of four resistance mechanisms to Ciprofloxacin MIC in Escherichia coli: a systematic review 1,2. 2018;(October 2018):298&#x02013;310.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Razieh Pourahmad J, Seyed Mohammad L, Hoda A, Maryam T. The role of some transcription factors in expression of GyrA and Gyr B following exposure to Ciprofloxacin. Jundishapur J Microbiol. 2020;13(6) In Press. 10.5812/jjm.100654</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zhao Q, Shen Y, Chen G, Luo Y, Cui S, Tian Y. Prevalence and molecular characterization of Fluoroquinolone- resistant Escherichia coli in healthy <italic>Escherichia coli </italic>in Healthy Children. Front Cell Infect Microbiol Sec Molecular Bacterial Pathogenesis. 2021;11. 10.3389/fcimb.2021.743390</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gupta S, Sreekrishnan TR, Ahammad SZ. Effects of heavy metals on the development and proliferation of antibiotic resistance in urban sewage treatment plants. Environ Pollut. 2022; 308:119649. 10.1016/j.envpol.2022.119649</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mazhar SH, Li X, Rashid A, Su JM, Xu J, Brejnrod AD et al. Co-selection of antibiotic resistance genes, and mobile genetic elements in the presence of heavy metals in poultry farm environments. Sci Total Environ [Internet]. 2021;755:142702. Available from: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.142702</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Edet UO, Bassey IU, Joseph AP. Heavy metal co-resistance with antibiotics amongst bacteria isolates from an open dumpsite soil. Heliyon [Internet]. 2023;9(2):e13457. Available from: 10.1016/j.heliyon.2023.e13457</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ahmed N, Tahir K, Aslam S, Cheema SM, Rabaan AA, Turkistani SA et al. Heavy metal (Arsenic) induced antibiotic resistance among Extended-Spectrum &#x003b2;-Lactamase (ESBL) producing Bacteria of nosocomial origin. Pharmaceuticals. 2022;15(11):1426. 10.3390/ph15111426</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lu Xming, Lu Pzhen. Science of the Total Environment Distribution of antibiotic resistance genes in soil amended using Azolla imbricata and its driving mechanisms. Sci Total Environ [Internet]. 2019;692:422&#x02013;31. Available from: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.07.285</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">KCCA. Kampala City Sanitation profile [Internet]. Kampala. 2017. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.kcca.go.ug">https://www.kcca.go.ug</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Christopher MJ. Municipal waste management in Kawempe division. (April; 2013.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">UBOS. National Population and Housing Cencus 2014. 2014; Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ubos.org/">https://www.ubos.org/</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">KCCA. Statistical Abstract for Kampala City. 2019.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Milos R. Fast and [internet]obust analysis of various [internet]ypes of waters by [internet]CP-OES following method HJ 776&#x02013;2015 using smart [internet]ools [internet]o facilitate [internet]he analytical [Internet]. USA; 2021. Available from: www.agilent.com/chem.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Allen ME. MacConkey Agar Plates Protocols 2016;(September 2005):1&#x02013;4.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR41" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Son</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group><source>HHS Public Access</source><year>2022</year><volume>1</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>13</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR41" publication-type="journal">Son MS, Taylor RK. HHS Public Access. 2022;1(1):1&#x02013;13.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR42" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhat</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name><surname>Nalawade</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial activity of endodontic medicaments and vehicles using agar well diffusion method on facultative and obligate anaerobes</article-title><source>Int J Clin Pediatr Dent</source><year>2016</year><volume>9</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>335</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5005/jp-journals-10005-1388</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28127166</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR42" publication-type="journal">Bhat KG, Nalawade TM. Antimicrobial activity of endodontic medicaments and vehicles using agar well diffusion method on facultative and obligate anaerobes. Int J Clin Pediatr Dent. 2016;9(4):335&#x02013;41.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28127166</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR43" publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Clinical Laboratory Standard Institute</collab></person-group><source>M100 performance standards for antimicrobial</source><year>2020</year><edition>30</edition><publisher-loc>Wayne, PA</publisher-loc><publisher-name>CLSI supplement M100</publisher-name></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR43" publication-type="book">Clinical Laboratory Standard Institute. M100 performance standards for antimicrobial. 30th ed. Wayne, PA: CLSI supplement M100; 2020.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR44" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krumperman</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiple antibiotic resistance indexing of Escherichia coli to identify high-risk sources of fecal contamination of foods</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>1983</year><volume>46</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>165</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/aem.46.1.165-170.1983</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6351743</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR44" publication-type="journal">Krumperman PH. Multiple antibiotic resistance indexing of Escherichia coli to identify high-risk sources of fecal contamination of foods. Appl Environ Microbiol. 1983;46(1):165&#x02013;70.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6351743</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR45" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Golus</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sawicki</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Widelski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ginalska</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The agar microdilution method &#x02013; a new method for antimicrobial susceptibility testing for essential oils and plant extracts</article-title><source>J Appl Microbiol</source><year>2016</year><volume>121</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1291</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jam.13253</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27501239</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR45" publication-type="journal">Golus J, Sawicki R, Widelski J, Ginalska G. The agar microdilution method &#x02013; a new method for antimicrobial susceptibility testing for essential oils and plant extracts. J Appl Microbiol. 2016;121(5):1291&#x02013;9.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27501239</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Perkin WH, Kipping FS. Organic Chemistry [Internet]. London [etc] W., Chambers R. limited; 1922. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://archive.org/details/organicchemistry00perkrich/page/n35/mode/2up">https://archive.org/details/organicchemistry00perkrich/page/n35/mode/2up</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR47" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kyayesimira</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ssemaganda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Muhwezi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Andama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of cadmium and lead in dried sewage sludge from lubigi Feacal sludge and wastewater treatment plant in Uganda</article-title><source>J Water Resour Prot</source><year>2019</year><volume>11</volume><issue>06</issue><fpage>690</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4236/jwarp.2019.116040</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR47" publication-type="journal">Kyayesimira J, Ssemaganda A, Muhwezi G, Andama M. Assessment of cadmium and lead in dried sewage sludge from lubigi Feacal sludge and wastewater treatment plant in Uganda. J Water Resour Prot. 2019;11(06):690&#x02013;9.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR48" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lopes</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Albuquerque</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fael</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dinis- Almeida</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of metals leaching in permeable asphalt pavement and conventional asphalt pavement</article-title><source>KnE Eng</source><year>2020</year><volume>2020</volume><fpage>166</fpage><lpage>76</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR48" publication-type="journal">Lopes AM, Albuquerque A, Fael C, Dinis- Almeida M. Evaluation of metals leaching in permeable asphalt pavement and conventional asphalt pavement. KnE Eng. 2020;2020:166&#x02013;76.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR49" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sevak</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pushkar</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Arsenic pollution cycle, toxicity and sustainable remediation technologies: A comprehensive review and bibliometric analysis</article-title><source>J Environ Manage</source><year>2024</year><volume>349</volume><issue>January</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>7</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR49" publication-type="journal">Sevak P, Pushkar B. Arsenic pollution cycle, toxicity and sustainable remediation technologies: A comprehensive review and bibliometric analysis. J Environ Manage. 2024;349(January):1&#x02013;7.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Obasi PN, Akudinobi BB. Potential health risk and levels of heavy metals in water resources of lead&#x02013;zinc mining communities of Abakaliki, southeast Nigeria. Appl Water Sci [Internet]. 2020;10(7):1&#x02013;23. Available from: 10.1007/s13201-020-01233-z</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR51" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jadaa</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohammed</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Heavy Metals &#x02013; Definition, natural and anthropogenic sources of releasing into ecosystems, toxicity, and removal Methods &#x02013; An overview study</article-title><source>J Ecol Eng</source><year>2023</year><volume>24</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>249</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12911/22998993/162955</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR51" publication-type="journal">Jadaa W, Mohammed H. Heavy Metals &#x02013; Definition, natural and anthropogenic sources of releasing into ecosystems, toxicity, and removal Methods &#x02013; An overview study. J Ecol Eng. 2023;24(6):249&#x02013;71.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kimera ZI, Mgaya FX, Mshana SE, Karimuribo ED, Matee MIN. Occurrence of extended spectrum beta lactamase (ESBL) producers, quinolone and carbapenem resistant Enterobacteriaceae isolated from environmental samples along Msimbazi river basin ecosystem in Tanzania. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2021;18(16):8264. 10.3390/ijerph1816826</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Id KJK, Id EN, Ahmad A, Duse AG, Olago D, Ndwigah SN et al. Contamination of groundwater with sulfamethoxazole and antibiotic resistant Escherichia coli in informal settlements in. 2023;(49):1&#x02013;15. Available from: 10.1371/journal.pwat.0000076</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gillings MR, Gaze WH, Pruden A, Smalla K, Tiedje JM, Ku J. Using the class 1 integron-integrase gene as a proxy for anthropogenic pollution. ISME J [Internet]. 2014;9(6):1269&#x02013;79. Available from: 10.1038/ismej.2014.226</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR55" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khalid</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdollah</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Environmental distribution of personal care products and their effects on human health</article-title><source>Iran J Pharm Res</source><year>2021</year><volume>20</volume><issue>January</issue><fpage>216</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34400954</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR55" publication-type="journal">Khalid M, Abdollah M. Environmental distribution of personal care products and their effects on human health. Iran J Pharm Res. 2021;20(January):216&#x02013;53.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34400954</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Akbar A, Sinegani S, Younessi N. Antibiotic resistance of bacteria isolated from heavy metal-polluted soils with different land uses. Integr Med Res [Internet]. 2017;(2010). Available from: 10.1016/j.jgar.2017.05.012</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Teshome A, Alemayehu T, Deriba W, Ayele Y. Antibiotic Resistance Profile of Bacteria Isolated from Wastewater Systems in Eastern Ethiopia. 2020;2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR58" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moges</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Mengistu</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeshambel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Walelegn</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation and characterization of multi drug resistance bacterial pathogens from wastewater in hospital and non-hospital environments, Northwest Ethiopia</article-title><source>BMC Res Notes</source><year>2014</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1756-0500-7-215</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24382056</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR58" publication-type="journal">Moges F, Mengistu E, Yeshambel B, Walelegn W. Isolation and characterization of multi drug resistance bacterial pathogens from wastewater in hospital and non-hospital environments, Northwest Ethiopia. BMC Res Notes. 2014;7:1&#x02013;6.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24382056</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Pitondo-Silva A, Goncalves GB, Stehling EG. Heavy metal resistance and virulence profile in Pseudomonas aeruginosa isolated from Brazilian soils. 2016;124(8):681&#x02013;8. 10.1111/apm.12553</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Dickinson AW, Power A, Hansen MG, Brandt KK, Piliposian G, Appleby P et al. Heavy metal pollution and co-selection for antibiotic resistance: A microbial palaeontology approach. Environ Int [Internet]. 2019;132(May):105117. Available from: 10.1016/j.envint.2019.105117</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Qing W, Xu Y, Liu L, Li Lyun, Lin H, Wu X et al. yan,. The prevalence of ampicillin-resistant opportunistic pathogenic bacteria undergoing selective stress of heavy metal pollutants in the Xiangjiang River, China. Environ Pollut [Internet]. 2020;115362. Available from: 10.1016/j.envpol.2020.115362</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Yang K, Zhang Y. Reversal of heavy metal- &#x000ad; induced antibiotic resistance by dandelion root extracts and taraxasterol. APMIS. 2016;124(8):681&#x02013;8. 10.1111/apm.12553</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Perewari DO, Otokunefor K, Agbagwa OE. Tetracycline-Resistant Genes in Escherichia coli from Clinical and Nonclinical Sources in Rivers State, Nigeria. Int J Microbiol. 2022;2022.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Haberecht HB, Nealon NJ, Gilliland JR, Holder AV, Runyan C, Oppel RC et al. Antimicrobial-Resistant Escherichia coli from Environmental Waters in Northern Colorado. 2019;2019.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR65" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sissi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Perdon&#x000e0;</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Domenici</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Feriani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Howells</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Maxwell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ciprofloxacin affects conformational equilibria of DNA gyrase A in the presence of magnesium ions</article-title><source>J Mol Biol</source><year>2001</year><volume>311</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>203</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/jmbi.2001.4838</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11469868</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR65" publication-type="journal">Sissi C, Perdon&#x000e0; E, Domenici E, Feriani A, Howells AJ, Maxwell A, et al. Ciprofloxacin affects conformational equilibria of DNA gyrase A in the presence of magnesium ions. J Mol Biol. 2001;311(1):195&#x02013;203.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11469868</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sissi C, Marangon E, Chemello A, Noble CG, Maxwell A, Palumbo M. The effects of metal ions on the structure and stability of the DNA gyrase. B Protein. J Mol Biol. 2005. 11;353(5):1152-60. doi: 10.1016/j.jmb.2005.09.043. 2005;1152 &#x02013; 60.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR67" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Virulence and antibiotic and heavy metal resistance of Vibrio parahaemolyticus isolated from crustaceans and shellfish in Shanghai</article-title><source>China</source><year>2016</year><volume>79</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1371</fpage><lpage>7</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR67" publication-type="journal">Hu Q, Chen L. Virulence and antibiotic and heavy metal resistance of Vibrio parahaemolyticus isolated from crustaceans and shellfish in Shanghai. China. 2016;79(8):1371&#x02013;7.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Martins VV, Ol&#x000ed;via M, Zanetti B. Aquatic environments polluted with antibiotics and heavy metals: a human health hazard. Environ Sci Pollut Res Int. 2014;21(9):5873&#x02013;8. 10.1007/s11356-014-2509-4</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kinuthia GK, Ngure V, Beti D, Lugalia R, Wangila A. Levels of heavy metals in wastewater and soil samples from open drainage channels in Nairobi. Kenya: Community Health Implication. 2020;10:8434. 10.1038/s41598-020-65359-5</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ahogle AMA, Korir NK, Houngnandan P, Abu-Ghunmi L, Letema S. Bacterial hazards in urban stream irrigation in peri-urban interface of Nairobi-Machakos counties, Kenya. Int J Environ Stud [Internet]. 2023;00(00):1&#x02013;17. Available from: 10.1080/00207233.2023.2216605</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>