<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="review-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sports Med Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sports Med Open</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Sports Medicine - Open</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2199-1170</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2198-9761</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer International Publishing</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Cham</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40402402</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12098250</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">860</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40798-025-00860-7</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Systematic Review</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The Effect of Probiotic Supplementation on Cytokine Modulation in Athletes After a Bout of Exercise: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Aparicio-Pascual</surname><given-names>Diego</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Clemente-Su&#x000e1;rez</surname><given-names>Vicente Javier</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tornero-Aguilera</surname><given-names>Jos&#x000e9; Francisco</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3616-7799</contrib-id><name><surname>Rubio-Zarapuz</surname><given-names>Alejandro</given-names></name><address><email>Alejandro.rubio@universidadeuropea.es</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/04dp46240</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.119375.8</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2173 8416</institution-id><institution>Department of Sports Sciences. Faculty of Medicine, Health and Sports, </institution><institution>Universidad Europea de Madrid, </institution></institution-wrap>28670 Villaviciosa de Od&#x000f3;n, Madrid, Spain </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/01v5nhr20</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.441867.8</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0486 085X</institution-id><institution>Grupo de Investigaci&#x000f3;n en Cultura, Educaci&#x000f3;n y Sociedad, </institution><institution>Universidad de La Costa, </institution></institution-wrap>080002 Barranquilla, Colombia </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>22</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>12</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>58</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>3</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Exercise-induced inflammation, especially after intense or prolonged physical activity, can hinder recovery in athletes. Probiotic supplementation has been suggested as a potential method to modulate this inflammatory response by influencing the gut microbiota. However, the effects of probiotics on cytokine profiles following exercise remain unclear. This systematic review and meta-analysis aimed to assess the impact of probiotic supplementation on cytokine modulation in athletes aged 18&#x02013;50&#x000a0;years following exercise.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">Randomized controlled trials (RCTs) that administered probiotic supplementation for at least one week to athletes were included. Studies comparing probiotics to a placebo or no supplementation, with post-exercise cytokine levels as the primary outcome, were analyzed. A systematic search was conducted across four databases (PubMed (Medline), Scopus, Web of Science (WOS) and Cochrane), up to June 2024. Risk of bias was assessed using the McMaster Critical Review Form, and random-effects meta-analyses were performed to determine the impact of probiotic supplementation.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">A total of 19 studies involving 526 athletes from various endurance disciplines were included in the review. Probiotic supplementation significantly increased the anti-inflammatory cytokine interleukin-10 (IL-10) (SMD&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.43; 95% CI 0.25&#x02013;0.61; I<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0%). However, no significant effects were observed for other cytokines, including IL-1&#x003b2;, IL-6, IL-8, TNF-&#x003b1;, or IFN-&#x003b3;. Subgroup analyses supported the consistency of IL-10 findings across different exercise protocols, though substantial heterogeneity was observed for some cytokines. The variability in study designs, probiotic strains, dosages, and exercise modalities contributed to the mixed results.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par4">Probiotic supplementation appears to enhance anti-inflammatory responses post-exercise, particularly by increasing IL-10 levels, which may aid recovery in athletes. However, the evidence regarding its effects on pro-inflammatory cytokines remains inconclusive. Further well-designed RCTs are needed to clarify these effects and establish standardized protocols for supplementation.</p></sec><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1186/s40798-025-00860-7.</p></sec></abstract><abstract id="Abs2" abstract-type="Key Message"><title>Key Points</title><p id="Par5">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p id="Par6">Probiotic supplementation enhances anti-inflammatory responses post-exercise, particularly by increasing IL-10 levels, suggesting a potential benefit for athletes in terms of recovery. This effect may be mediated through modulation of the intestinal microbiota, which plays a critical role in immune regulation.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par7">Despite the observed increase in IL-10, probiotics did not significantly alter the levels of pro-inflammatory cytokines such as IL-1&#x003b2;, IL-6, IL-8, TNF-&#x003b1;, or IFN-&#x003b3;. This indicates that the immunomodulatory effects of probiotics may be selective, primarily enhancing anti-inflammatory responses rather than suppressing inflammation directly.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par8">Differences in probiotic strains, dosages, exercise modalities, and study designs contributed to variability in results. Future research should aim to establish standardized supplementation protocols to clarify the role of probiotics in cytokine modulation and athletic recovery.</p></list-item></list></p><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1186/s40798-025-00860-7.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Probiotic supplementation</kwd><kwd>Cytokine modulation</kwd><kwd>Exercise-induced inflammation</kwd><kwd>Athletes</kwd><kwd>Systematic review</kwd><kwd>Meta-analysis</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Springer Nature Switzerland AG 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec2"><title>Background</title><p id="Par26">Probiotic supplementation has garnered significant attention in the realm of sports nutrition, particularly due to its potential role in modulating immune responses following exercise. They are defined as living microorganisms that can confer health benefits to the host when administered in adequate amounts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. These living microorganisms typically consist of several strains, with the most significant being bacteria from the genera <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> and <italic>Bifidobacterium</italic>, as well as yeasts from the genus <italic>Saccharomyces</italic>. It is important to note that probiotic supplements can be composed of either a single strain or multiple strains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Currently, they are used to alleviate GI problems and overtraining issues which appear frequently in endurance sports [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Additionally, they appear to improve nutrient absorption and digestion capacity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Their mechanisms of action include enhancing intestinal barrier function, regulating the production of antimicrobial peptides and antioxidant compounds/enzymes, involving SCFAs in balancing regulatory T lymphocytes and modifying cytokine secretion by macrophages and lymphocytes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. However, these mechanisms are profoundly affected by the composition of the gut microbiota, which notably influences how probiotics exert their effects [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>].</p><p id="Par27">A central component of immune regulation, particularly in response to exercise, involves cytokines, small signaling proteins that facilitate communication between immune cells. Cytokines coordinate the body&#x02019;s inflammatory and anti-inflammatory responses, ensuring a proper balance between necessary immune activation and the resolution of inflammation. For readers less familiar with these biomarkers, cytokines are typically classified into pro-inflammatory and anti-inflammatory categories, each with distinct roles in immune regulation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>].</p><p id="Par28">Pro-inflammatory cytokines, are primarily responsible for initiating the inflammatory response, mobilizing immune cells to sites of tissue damage, and promoting repair mechanisms. such as interleukin-6 (IL-6) and tumor necrosis factor-alpha (TNF-&#x003b1;), are essential in the initial response to infection, injury, or exercise. These cytokines serve to mobilize immune cells to sites of tissue damage and promote repair mechanisms essential for recovery. IL-6, produced by contracting muscles during exercise, is known to stimulate acute-phase protein production and influence immune cell differentiation, facilitating the body&#x02019;s initial response to stress. TNF-&#x003b1;, a potent mediator of systemic inflammation, can induce fever, trigger apoptosis in damaged cells, and stimulate the production of additional pro-inflammatory cytokines. This cascade of responses ensures the repair and adaptation processes are activated but can contribute to muscle soreness and delayed recovery when elevated excessively or for prolonged periods [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Anti-inflammatory cytokines, particularly interleukin-10 (IL-10), counterbalance the effects of pro-inflammatory cytokines, promoting the resolution of inflammation once the initial threat has been addressed. This balance between pro-inflammatory and anti-inflammatory cytokines is crucial for maintaining immune homeostasis and preventing chronic or excessive inflammation. IL-10 plays a central role in deactivating immune responses that could potentially harm healthy tissues. The interplay between these cytokine types is particularly relevant during and after physical exercise, where the body experiences a transient inflammatory response that is essential for the normal physiological adaptation process. This response is characterized by an increase in pro-inflammatory cytokines, which help initiate tissue repair and facilitate adaptation to physical stressors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. This balance is particularly crucial during and after physical exercise, when the body experiences a transient inflammatory response essential for physiological adaptation. Pro-inflammatory cytokines increase during exercise, initiating repair processes and supporting adaptations to physical stress. Understanding cytokine dynamics is key to developing effective recovery strategies for athletes and active individuals. Elevated levels of these cytokines reflect the body&#x02019;s natural response to stress, playing a dual role in healing and adaptation. However, managing this response can be challenging, especially when targeting cytokine modulation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> summarizes the key roles of cytokines in relation to exercise, highlighting their involvement in the pro or anti- inflammatory response and physiological adaptations.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Summary of the roles of key cytokines in relation to exercise</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Cytokine</th><th align="left">Actions</th><th align="left">Change with exercise</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="3">&#x0201c;Pro-inflammatory&#x0201d;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">IL-1&#x003b2;</td><td align="left">Induce synthesis of NO, prostaglandins and leukotrienes</td><td align="left">&#x02191;&#x02009;&#x02194;&#x02009;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">IL-8</td><td align="left"><p>Neutrophils chemotaxis</p><p>Induction of angiogenesis</p></td><td align="left">&#x02191;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">IL-15</td><td align="left">Activation of adaptative immune system (B cells and T cells)</td><td align="left">&#x02009;=&#x02009;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">TNF-&#x003b1;</td><td align="left"><p>Immune cell activation</p><p>Stimulation of prostaglandins synthesis</p></td><td align="left">&#x02191;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3">&#x0201c;Anti-inflammatory&#x0201d;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">IL-1Ra</td><td align="left">Inhibition of signaling through IL-1 receptor</td><td align="left">&#x02191;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">IL-4 &#x00026; IL-13</td><td align="left"><p>Inhibition of Th1 cells</p><p>Reduction of plasma IL-1&#x003b2;</p><p>Upregulation of IL-1Ra expression</p></td><td align="left">&#x02191;&#x02009;&#x02194;&#x02009;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">IL-6</td><td align="left"><p>Induces upregulation of IL-10 and Il-1Ra</p><p>&#x0201c;Pro-inflammatory&#x0201d; cytokine inhibition</p></td><td align="left">&#x02191;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">IL-10</td><td align="left">Inhibition of &#x0201c;pro-inflammatory&#x0201d; cytokines including IL-1&#x003b2; and TNF-&#x003b1;</td><td align="left">&#x02191;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Adapted from [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. NO: Nitric oxide; IL-1&#x003b2;: Interleukin 1-&#x003b2;; IL-8: Interleukin 8; IL-15: Interleukin 15; TNF-&#x003b1;: Tumor necrosis factor &#x003b1;; IL-1Ra: Interleukin 1-Ra; IL-4: Interleukin 4; IL-13: Interleukin 13; Th1 cells: T helper 1 cells; IL-6: Interleukin 6; IL-10: Interleukin 10; &#x02191;: upregulated after exercise;&#x02009;=&#x02009;: no change with exercise; &#x02191;&#x02009;&#x02194;&#x02009;: inconsistent findings</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par29">In this context, sports nutrition offers various approaches to support recovery, reduce injury risk, and enhance overall performance. As abovementioned probiotic supplementation, has emerged as a promising strategy, some meta-analyses suggest that probiotics not only modulate inflammation but also contribute to aerobic performance improvements in athletes, presenting an innovative tool for optimizing training and recovery outcomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Related with these roles, they are widely recognized for their role in reducing the incidence of upper respiratory tract infections (URTIs) by enhancing immune responses through T- and B-lymphocyte activation and dampening intestinal inflammation. This immunomodulatory effect promotes the secretion of key cytokines, including interferon-gamma (IFN-&#x003b3;), immunoglobulin A (IgA), and IL-10, while concurrently downregulating pro-inflammatory cytokines such as IL-6, IL-8, and TNF-&#x003b1;. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. As highlighted by J&#x000e4;ger et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>], achieving these potential benefits require a minimum dosage of 1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10&#x02079; colony-forming units (CFU), during at least 3&#x000a0;weeks for most bacterial species. Despite research highlighting the benefits of probiotics in reducing URTIs and gastrointestinal symptoms, studies examining their effects on cytokine modulation in athletes remain limited. Only two meta-analyses have specifically examined probiotics' effects on cytokine responses in this population, each encompassing fewer than ten studies, which constrains the robustness of the conclusions drawn [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. While these reviews have identified positive outcomes for certain cytokines, the findings remain inconsistent, underscoring the need for a comprehensive meta-analysis that synthesizes current evidence on cytokine modulation following exercise. Consequently, a comprehensive meta-analysis is crucial to assess the effectiveness of probiotics in modulating cytokine responses following exercise. The current literature is limited and inconsistent, undermining the reliability of existing conclusions. This meta-analysis seeks to synthesize available data to enhance our understanding of probiotics' role in improving immune function and recovery in athletes.</p><p id="Par30">This meta-analysis evaluates the effects of probiotic supplementation on cytokine modulation in athlete&#x02019;s post-exercise. By synthesizing existing research, it aims to clarify the role of probiotics in managing inflammation and supporting recovery.</p></sec><sec id="Sec3"><title>Methods</title><p id="Par31">Following the guidelines of the PRISMA&#x000ae; statement (Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>], a systematic review of the scientific literature was conducted to examine the impact of probiotic supplementation on cytokine modulation after a bout of exercise in different types of athletes.</p><sec id="Sec4"><title>Search Strategy</title><p id="Par32">Records were identified through extensive searches of the scientific databases PubMed (Medline), Scopus, Web of Science (WOS) and Cochrane on June 28th, 2024. The key terms, along with the Boolean algorithms and wildcards used in the search string, were as follows:<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p id="Par33">PubMed (Medline): ("probiotic*" [TIAB] OR "probiotic*" [TW] OR "microbiota*" [TIAB] OR "microbiota*" [TW] OR "postbiotic*" [TIAB] OR "postbiotic*" [TW]) AND ("cytokine?" [TIAB] OR "cytokine?" [TW] OR "inflamm*" [TIAB] OR "inflamm*" [TW] OR "immune*" [TIAB] OR "immune*" [TW]) AND ("exercise" [TIAB] OR "exercise" [TW] OR "athletes" [TIAB] OR "athletes" [TW] OR "endurance athletes" [TIAB] OR "endurance athletes" [TW])</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par34">Scopus, Web of Science (WOS) and Cochrane: ("probiotic*" OR "microbiota*" OR "postbiotic*") AND ("cytokine?" OR "inflamm*" OR "inmune*") AND ("exercise" OR "athletes" OR "endurance athletes")</p></list-item></list></p><p id="Par35">Only English-language peer-reviewed scientific articles published from 2010 to June 28, 2024, were included, independently of risk of bias assessment scores. Grey literature, such as government reports and unpublished theses, were not specifically screened. All steps in the record screening process were managed using Zotero&#x000ae; version 6.0. Additionally, references from the included records were manually searched for potential additional sources. Therefore, screening process is summarized in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>PRISMA 2020 flow diagram for new systematic reviews which included searches of databases and registers only</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40798_2025_860_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Eligibility Criteria</title><p id="Par36">A total of 2358 records were identified across the four databases used. Additionally, a review of the reference lists from the articles revealed one additional record, which was included in the final review. The selection process was conducted by two authors (DAP and ARZ), with a third author (VJCS) consulted to resolve any discrepancies and provide the final decision. Duplicate entries were manually removed, resulting in 1355 records for further screening. After eliminating 1285 records based on title and abstract, 70 records were assessed for full text. Ultimately, 17 records were included, with one being obtained through citation searches.</p><p id="Par37">Out of these, 17 records were included in the qualitative and quantitative synthesis (meta-analysis), while the analyses encompassed a total of 19 articles. The discrepancies occurred because the study by Huang et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>] involved two distinct populations, and the study by West et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>] presented results separated by gender. Consequently, a specific citation approach was adopted for each group. Participants from the first intervention were referenced as "1" (Huang et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]), while those from the second intervention were labeled as "2" (Huang et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]). A similar strategy was employed to differentiate between female and male participants in the West et al., 2011 study, with females cited as (West et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]) and males as (West et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]). This citation strategy ensured a clear distinction between the populations within the meta-analysis framework, facilitating the interpretation of the findings.</p><p id="Par38">The eligibility criteria for record screening were established based on the following PICOS framework:<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p id="Par39">Participants: athletes, ranging from 18 to 50&#x000a0;years of age.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par40">Intervention: Probiotic supplementation for at least one week.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par41">Comparator: age-matched athletes.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par42">Outcomes: post exercise circulating levels of cytokines, acute phase proteins, tumor necrosis factor &#x003b1; (TNF-&#x003b1;), interferon-&#x001b4; (IFN-&#x001b4;) and C-reactive protein (CRP).</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par43">Study design: Randomized trials reporting inflammatory marker values measured after a bout of exercise following a probiotic or placebo intervention.</p></list-item></list></p><p id="Par44">Prior to full-text screening, all systematic and narrative reviews were excluded based on title and abstract. Exclusion criteria for articles not included in the meta-analysis were as follows: studies published before 2010 were excluded, along with those where the supplementation protocol included did not exclusively involved probiotics. Additionally, research was excluded if it did not measure cytokine levels or only assessed them at baseline. Studies involving non-athletes or sedentary individuals were also not considered. Finally, any studies without accessible full-text articles were excluded from the review.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Risk of Bias Assessment</title><p id="Par45">The risk of bias in the included studies was evaluated using the Critical Review Form-Quantitative Studies, also known as the McMaster Scale [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>], as shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>. The lead author (DAP) conducted the initial risk of bias assessment, which was then reviewed for accuracy by all co-authors. This evaluation incorporated 16 criteria instead of the standard 15, with an additional criterion specifically addressing study limitations. Special attention was given to the randomization process: studies that did not report the randomization procedure, allocation process, or provide a CONSORT diagram were marked as "no" for that criterion. Based on the critical appraisal results, an overall methodological quality score was assigned: studies were classified as having "very low" quality, indicated by black, if fewer than 25% of criteria were met; "low" quality, indicated by red, if 25&#x02013;50% of criteria were met; "moderate" quality, indicated by yellow, if 50&#x02013;75% of criteria were met; and "high" quality, indicated by blue, if 75% or more of the criteria were met.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Summary of bias assessment with mcmaster scale</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40798_2025_860_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Data Extraction</title><p id="Par46">Data extraction was conducted by the lead author (DAP) and independently reviewed by (ARZ) and (JFTA) to ensure accuracy and reliability. To facilitate comparisons between study groups, effect measures for continuous outcomes were collected, including mean and standard deviation (mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD), mean and standard error (mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SE), median and interquartile range (median [IQR]), and log-transformed values of circulating inflammatory markers at baseline. Prior to analysis, data using the formula SD&#x02009;=&#x02009;SE x <inline-formula id="IEq1"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e561">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\sqrt{n}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="d33e566"><mml:msqrt><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msqrt></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="40798_2025_860_Article_IEq1.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, in which n is the sample size for each group. Mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD values were also estimated from median (IQR) data using the method proposed by Wan et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. It is important to note that in the study by West et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>], data is reported as log-transformed values. However, conversion of this data was not necessary, as the supplementary material of the study provides the raw data. Also, estimated values from graphical representations (bar, line chart&#x02026;) were extracted using WebPlotDigitizer&#x000ae; version 4.8.</p><p id="Par47">Once extracted, these values were added to a template in Microsoft Excel&#x000ae;, which included the following fields: citation, supplementation period, participants, participants divided by the supplementation groups (probiotic/placebo), method of data extraction, reported values (pg/ml), data reported values ((Mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD), (Mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SE) and (Median&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;Interquartile range)), bout of exercise and the data of the cytokines already transformed to (Mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD).</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p id="Par48">The analysis was conducted using Jamovi&#x000ae; version 2.6.13, utilizing the standardized mean difference as the outcome measure and applying a random-effects model to fit the data. The heterogeneity (tau<sup>2</sup>) was estimated using Hedges' estimator [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Alongside the tau<sup>2</sup> estimate, the Q-test for heterogeneity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>] and the I<sup>2</sup> statistic were reported. When any heterogeneity was detected (tau<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0), regardless of the Q-test results, a prediction interval for the true outcomes was provided. To identify potential outliers and influential studies within the model, studentized residuals and Cook's distances were examined. Studies with studentized residuals exceeding the 100 x (1&#x02014;0.05/(2&#x000a0;k))<sup>th</sup> percentile of a standard normal distribution were flagged as potential outliers, applying a Bonferroni correction with a two-sided alpha of 0.05 for k included studies. Studies were considered influential if their Cook's distance was greater than the median plus six times the interquartile range of all Cook's distances. Funnel plot asymmetry was assessed using both the rank correlation test and the regression test, with the standard error of the observed outcomes serving as the predictor. However, this was only assessed when a minimum of 10 studies were available, this was done according to the guidelines implemented by Godavitarne et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. In which, due to the low formal power of the analysis, it is unable to distinguish between chance and true asymmetry. In other words, despite ruling out asymmetry, bias cannot be excluded. Although Jamovi reported heterogeneity with three different measurements tau<sup>2</sup>, Q and I<sup>2</sup> values heterogeneity in this study it was opted for I<sup>2</sup> for heterogeneity assessment. Which is a reliable, scale-independent measure in meta-analysis that effectively quantifies variability arising from differences among studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. However, it may be biased when fewer than seven studies are included in the analysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. As so, to address this potential bias, the analysis was only conducted when at least seven distinct studies reported on the same cytokine, following the previously mentioned criteria. Therefore, heterogeneity is considered low for values less than 30%, moderate for values greater than 30%, substantial for values greater than 50%, and considerable for values greater than 75% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Finally, regarding subgroup analyses they were conducted to account for overly influential studies, when they were identified through studentized residuals and Cook&#x02019;s distances. Furthermore, the studies were categorized based on exercise bout, specifically differentiating between VO2max tests and marathon/triathlon events and if applicable overly influential studies were again eliminated. But it is important to note that these analyses were performed only when a minimum of seven studies as it is mentioned previously.</p><p id="Par49">A multivariate random-effects meta-regression was conducted to evaluate whether specific covariates, number of probiotic strains, exercise type, and intervention duration, could predict the effects of probiotics on cytokine modulation in athletes. The meta-regression analysis was performed using Open Meta-Analyst software&#x000ae; when heterogeneity exceeded 75% and at least 15 studies were available, following the recommendations of Thompson and Higgins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>].</p><p id="Par50">The covariates were categorized as follows: the probiotic strains were classified based on the specific number of strains used in each study protocol, the intervention duration was categorized according to the number of weeks each study lasted, and the type of exercise was assigned a binary classification, studies involving prolonged endurance activities such as marathons and triathlons were coded as 0, whereas those incorporating VO&#x02082; max tests were coded as 1. These categorizations allowed for a structured analysis of how different probiotic interventions and exercise modalities influence cytokine responses in athletes.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Results</title><p id="Par51">A total of 526 athletes were documented in the included studies, with 240 participating in probiotic supplementation and 247 in placebo supplementation, in addition to 39 athletes included in various crossover designs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. These athletes were further categorized into various endurance sports disciplines (runners, marathoners, cyclists and triathletes), except for those in the study by J&#x000e4;ger et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>], which involved resistance-trained athletes, and the study by Mazani et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>], which did not specify the sport discipline of the athletes. The age range of the athletes spanned from a minimum of 18 to a maximum of 50&#x000a0;years. While most studies reported VO2max, it was not consistently documented across all investigations. Regarding sex, the studies by (West et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]) included only male athletes. However, the studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>], included both sexes, while the studies by (West et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]) included only female athletes. Finally, the sex of the athletes was not specified in the studies by (Huang et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]; Huang et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]). It is worth noting that several Lactobacillus species were reclassified in 2020 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]; however, this study used the names reported in the original studies to minimize bias.</p><p id="Par52">Additional information about this data can be found in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, which details the study design, sample size, posology, bacterial species used, exercise bout conducted before the cytokine&#x02019;s extraction and study outcomes (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Characteristics of included studies</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Study</th><th align="left">Design</th><th align="left">Sample</th><th align="left">Posology</th><th align="left">Bacterial species</th><th align="left">Bout of exercise</th><th align="left">Outcomes</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Axelrod et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]</td><td align="left">Double-blind randomized, placebo-controlled trial</td><td align="left">Seven endurance trained athletes, sex not reported; aged 18&#x02013;45&#x000a0;years; VO2max&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;50&#x000a0;ml/kg/min</td><td align="left">One capsule per day, for a duration of 4&#x000a0;weeks</td><td align="left"><italic>Lactobacillus salivarius UCC118</italic> (2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>8</sup>&#x000a0;CFU/capsule)</td><td align="left">Two hours of continuous aerobic exercise at 60% of VO2 max</td><td align="left"><p>PRO VS PLA:</p><p>&#x02009;=&#x02009;IL-6</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Batatinha et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]</td><td align="left">Double-blind randomized trial</td><td align="left">Twenty-seven marathonists, males; aged 30&#x02013;45&#x000a0;years; VO2max not reported</td><td align="left">One sachet per day, for a duration of 30&#x000a0;days</td><td align="left"><italic>Bifidobacterium animalis. subsp. Lactis</italic> (10&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>9</sup>&#x000a0;CFU/sachet) and <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic> (10&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>9</sup>&#x000a0;CFU/sachet)</td><td align="left">Marathon race (42.195&#x000a0;km)</td><td align="left"><p>PRO VS PLA:</p><p>&#x02009;=&#x02009;IL-1&#x003b2;, IL-2,</p><p>IL-4, IL-6, IL-8,</p><p>IL-10, IL-15,</p><p>TNF-&#x003b1; and</p><p>IFN-&#x001b4;</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Engel et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]</td><td align="left">Double-blind randomized, two-armed, placebo-controlled trial</td><td align="left">One-hundred and twenty-six endurance athletes, sex not reported; aged 18&#x02013;50&#x000a0;years; VO2max&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;40&#x000a0;ml/kg/min</td><td align="left">Two capsules per day, one with breakfast, for a duration of 6&#x000a0;weeks</td><td align="left"><italic>Bifidobacterium breve Bif195</italic> (2.5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>10</sup>&#x000a0;CFU/capsule)</td><td align="left">One hour of continuous aerobic exercise at 80% of VO2 max</td><td align="left"><p>PRO VS PLA:</p><p>&#x02009;=&#x02009;IL-1&#x003b2;, IL-2,</p><p>IL-4, IL-6, IL-8,</p><p>IL-10, IL-12p70, IL-13, TNF-&#x003b1; and IFN-&#x001b4;;</p><p>&#x02191; CRP</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Gill et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]</td><td align="left">Blinded randomized and counterbalanced order trial</td><td align="left">Eight non-heat acclimatized healthy endurance athletes, males; aged 26&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6&#x000a0;years; VO2max 59&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5&#x000a0;ml/kg/min (Mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD)</td><td align="left">One beverage per day, for a duration of 7&#x000a0;days</td><td align="left"><italic>Lactobacillus casei</italic> (1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>11</sup>&#x000a0;CFU/beverage)</td><td align="left">Two hours of continuous aerobic exercise at 60% of VO2 max, with ambient conditions of 34&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0,4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C and 32&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2% relative humidity</td><td align="left"><p>PRO VS PLA:</p><p>&#x02009;=&#x02009;IL-1&#x003b2;, IL-6,</p><p>IL-8, IL-10,</p><p>TNF-&#x003b1; and</p><p>IFN-&#x001b4;</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Huang et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]</td><td align="left">Double-blind randomized trail</td><td align="left">Nineteen triathletes, sex not reported; aged 20.65&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.1&#x000a0;years; VO2max not reported (Mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD)</td><td align="left">Two capsules per day, for a duration of 4&#x000a0;weeks</td><td align="left"><italic>Lactobacillus plantarum PS128</italic> (1.5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>10</sup>&#x000a0;CFU/capsule)</td><td align="left">Sprint Triathlon (750&#x000a0;m swimming, 20&#x000a0;km biking and 5&#x000a0;km running)</td><td align="left"><p>PRO VS PLA:</p><p>&#x02009;=&#x02009;IL-4 and IL-10;</p><p>&#x02193; IL-6, IL-8 and TNF-&#x003b1;;</p><p>&#x02191; IFN-&#x001b4;</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Huang et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]</td><td align="left">Double-blind randomized trial</td><td align="left">Eighteen triathletes, sex not reported; aged 21.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.75&#x000a0;years; VO2max 60.95&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.85&#x000a0;ml/kg/min (Mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD)</td><td align="left">Two capsules per day, for a duration of 3&#x000a0;weeks</td><td align="left"><italic>Lactobacillus plantarum PS128</italic> (1.5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>10</sup>&#x000a0;CFU/capsule)</td><td align="left">Official competition of Triathlon (1.5&#x000a0;km swimming, 40&#x000a0;km biking and 10&#x000a0;km running)</td><td align="left"><p>PRO VS PLA:</p><p>&#x02193; IL-6, IL-8 and TNF-&#x003b1; and</p><p>IFN-&#x001b4;;</p><p>&#x02191; IL-4 and</p><p>IL-10</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">J&#x000e4;ger et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]</td><td align="left">Double-blind, randomized, placebo-controlled, crossover trial</td><td align="left">Fifteen resistance-trained, males; aged 25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4&#x000a0;years; VO2max not reported (Mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD)</td><td align="left">One capsule per day, for a duration of 21&#x000a0;days</td><td align="left"><italic>Bifidobacterium Breve BR03</italic> (5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>9</sup>&#x000a0;CFU/capsule) and <italic>Streptococcus thermophilus FP4</italic> (5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>9</sup>&#x000a0;CFU/capsule)</td><td align="left">5 sets of 10 maximal eccentric (forced lengthening) contractions at a speed pf 30&#x000b0;/s</td><td align="left"><p>PRO VS PLA:</p><p>&#x02009;=&#x02009;IL-6</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Lamprecht et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]</td><td align="left">Double-blind randomized, placebo-controlled trial</td><td align="left">Twenty-three endurance trained, males; aged 30&#x02013;45&#x000a0;years; VO2max&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;45&#x000a0;mL/kg/min</td><td align="left">Two sachets per day, with 100&#x02013;125&#x000a0;ml of plain water for a duration of 14&#x000a0;weeks</td><td align="left"><italic>Bifidobacterium bifidum W23, Bifidobacterium lactis W51, Enterococcus faecium W54, Lactobacillus acidophilus W22, Lactobacillus brevis W63,</italic> and <italic>Lactococcus lactis W58</italic>; with a minimal concentration of 2.5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>9</sup>&#x000a0;CFU/sachet</td><td align="left">Test to exhaustion in a cycle ergometer work started at 60 Watts (W) for three minutes and was increased 20 W every minute until voluntary exhaustion. It lasted around 15 to 18&#x000a0;min</td><td align="left"><p>PRO VS PLA:</p><p>&#x02009;=&#x02009;IL-6 and</p><p>TNF-&#x003b1;</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Lennon et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]</td><td align="left">Double-blind randomized, placebo-controlled cross-over study</td><td align="left">Sixteen runners, males and females; 32.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;8&#x000a0;years; VO2max not reported (Mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD)</td><td align="left">One capsule per day for a duration of 4&#x000a0;weeks</td><td align="left"><italic>Pediococcus acidilactici</italic> and two <italic>Lactobacillus plantarum strains</italic> maintaining an equal ratio of 1:1:1; with a minimal concentration of 3.0&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>9</sup>&#x000a0;CFU/capsule</td><td align="left">90&#x000a0;min of test to exhaustion in a treadmill, where participants ran at 65&#x02013;70% VO2max</td><td align="left"><p>PRO VS PLA:</p><p>&#x02009;=&#x02009;IL-1&#x003b2;, IL-6,</p><p>IL-8, IL-10 and TNF-&#x003b1;</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mazani et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]</td><td align="left">Blind randomized trial</td><td align="left">Twenty-seven athletes, females; aged 18&#x02013;25&#x000a0;years; VO2max not reported</td><td align="left">Two cups of probiotic yoghurt (450&#x000a0;g) per day, for a duration of 2&#x000a0;weeks</td><td align="left">Not addressed</td><td align="left">Test to exhaustion according to Bruce test</td><td align="left"><p>PRO VS PLA:</p><p>&#x02009;=&#x02009;IL-6 and</p><p>TNF-&#x003b1;</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mazur-Kurach et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]</td><td align="left">Double-blind randomized trial</td><td align="left">Twenty-six elite road cyclist, males; aged 18&#x02013;26&#x000a0;years; VO2max 61.66&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.26&#x000a0;ml/kg/min (Mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD)</td><td align="left">One capsule per day, for 16&#x000a0;weeks</td><td align="left"><italic>Lactobacillus plantarum</italic>, <italic>Lactobacillus casei</italic>, <italic>Lactobacillus rhamnosus</italic>, <italic>Bifidobacterium breve</italic>, <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic>, <italic>Bifidobacterium longum</italic>, <italic>Bifidobacterium bifidum</italic>, <italic>Bifidobacterium infantis</italic>, <italic>Lactobacillus helveticus</italic>, <italic>Lactobacillus fermentum</italic>, <italic>Lactobacillus bulgaricus, Lactococcus lactis</italic>, and <italic>Streptococcus thermophilus</italic>; with a minimal concentration of 1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>11</sup>&#x000a0;CFU/capsule</td><td align="left">Cycle ergometer, test started with a load of 100 W; then every two minutes the resistance was increased by 35 W. The pedaling rhythm was constant at 90&#x000a0;rpm till exhaustion</td><td align="left"><p>PRO VS PLA:</p><p>&#x02009;=&#x02009;IL-1&#x003b2;, IL-6 and IL-8</p><p>&#x02193; TNF-&#x003b1;;</p><p>&#x02191; IL-10</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Pugh et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]</td><td align="left">Double-blind randomized, matched-pairs trial</td><td align="left">Twenty runners, males and females; aged 35.45&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;7.2&#x000a0;years; VO2max 57&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;8.3&#x000a0;ml/kg/min (Mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD)</td><td align="left">One capsule per day, for a duration of 28&#x000a0;days and an extra one two hours prior to the race</td><td align="left"><italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus (CUL60), Lactobacillus acidophilus (CUL21), Bifidobacterium bifidum (CUL20),</italic> and <italic>Bifidobacterium animalis subsp. lactis</italic> (CUL34); with a minimal concentration of 2.5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>10</sup>&#x000a0;CFU/capsule</td><td align="left">Marathon race (42.195&#x000a0;km)</td><td align="left"><p>PRO VS PLA:</p><p>&#x02009;=&#x02009;IL-6, IL-8 and IL-10</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Pugh et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]</td><td align="left">Double-blind randomized, placebo-controlled crossover trial</td><td align="left">Seven trained cyclists, sex not reported; aged 23&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4&#x000a0;years; VO2max 64&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.2&#x000a0;ml/kg/min (Mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD)</td><td align="left">One capsule per day, for a duration of 28&#x000a0;days</td><td align="left"><italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus (CUL60), Lactobacillus acidophilus (CUL21), Bifidobacterium bifidum (CUL20), and Bifidobacterium animalis subsp. lactis (CUL34);</italic> with a minimal concentration of 2.5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>10</sup>&#x000a0;CFU/capsule</td><td align="left">Two hours in a cycle ergometer at 55% Wmax and a cadence dependent linear output of 100&#x000a0;kJ of work</td><td align="left"><p>PRO VS PLA:</p><p>&#x02009;=&#x02009;IL-1a, IL-8 and IL-10</p><p>&#x02193; IL-6</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Shing et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]</td><td align="left">Double-blind randomized, placebo-controlled and counterbalanced crossover trial</td><td align="left">Ten trained runners, males; aged 27&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2&#x000a0;years; VO2max 62.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.1&#x000a0;ml/kg/min (Mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD)</td><td align="left">One capsule per day, for a duration of 4&#x000a0;weeks</td><td align="left"><italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic> (7.4&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>9</sup>&#x000a0;CFU/capsule); <italic>L. rhamnosus</italic> (15.55&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>9</sup>&#x000a0;CFU/capsule); <italic>L. casei</italic> (9.45&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>9</sup>&#x000a0;CFU/capsule); <italic>L. plantarum</italic> (3.15&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>9</sup>&#x000a0;CFU/capsule); <italic>L. fermentum</italic> (1.35&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>9</sup>&#x000a0;CFU/capsule); <italic>Bifidobacterium lactis</italic> (4.05&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>9</sup>&#x000a0;CFU/capsule); <italic>B. breve</italic> (1.35&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>9</sup>&#x000a0;CFU/capsule); <italic>B. bifidum</italic> (0.45&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>9</sup>&#x000a0;CFU/capsule); <italic>Streptococcus thermophilus</italic> (2.25&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>9</sup>&#x000a0;CFU/capsule); with a minimal concentration of 45&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>9</sup>&#x000a0;CFU/capsule</td><td align="left">Time to fatigue run was assessed during a treadmill run set at 80% of ventilatory threshold, conducted in a climate chamber set at 35&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C and 40% relative humidity</td><td align="left"><p>PRO VS PLA:</p><p>&#x02009;=&#x02009;IL-1ra, IL-6,</p><p>IL-10 and</p><p>TNF-&#x003b1;</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Tavares-Silva et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]</td><td align="left">Double-blind randomized trial</td><td align="left">Fourteen marathon runners, males; aged 39.92&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.47&#x000a0;years; VO2max 55.72&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;7.46&#x000a0;ml/kg/min (Mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD)</td><td align="left">One gelatinous capsule per day during nighttime, for a duration of 30&#x000a0;days</td><td align="left"><italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus-LB-G80</italic> (1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>9</sup>&#x000a0;CFU/capsule); <italic>Lactobacillus paracasei-LPc-G110</italic> (1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>9</sup>&#x000a0;CFU/capsule); <italic>Lactococcus subp. lactis-LLL-G25</italic> (1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>9</sup>&#x000a0;CFU/capsule); <italic>Bifidobacterium animalis subp. lactis-BL-G101</italic> (1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>9</sup>&#x000a0;CFU/capsule); <italic>Bifidobacterium bifidum-BB-G90</italic> (1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>9</sup>&#x000a0;CFU/capsule); with a minimal concentration of 5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>9</sup>&#x000a0;CFU/capsule</td><td align="left">International S&#x000e3;o Paulo Marathon (42.195&#x000a0;km)</td><td align="left"><p>PRO VS PLA:</p><p>&#x02009;=&#x02009;IL-2, IL-4,</p><p>IL-10 and</p><p>TNF-&#x003b1;</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Tavares-Silva et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]</td><td align="left">Double-blind randomized, controlled trial</td><td align="left">Twenty-seven marathoners, males; aged 25&#x02013;45&#x000a0;years; VO2max not reported</td><td align="left">One sachet per day, for a duration of 30&#x000a0;days</td><td align="left"><italic>Lactobacillus acidophillus</italic> (1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>10</sup>&#x000a0;CFU/capsule) and <italic>Bifidobacterium bifidum subsp. Lactis</italic> (1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>10</sup>&#x000a0;CFU/capsule)</td><td align="left">International S&#x000e3;o Paulo Marathon (42.195&#x000a0;km)</td><td align="left"><p>PRO VS PLA:</p><p>&#x02009;=&#x02009;L-1&#x003b2;, IL-6,</p><p>IL-10 and</p><p>TNF-&#x003b1;;</p><p>&#x02193; IL-15;</p><p>&#x02191; IL-8</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Vaisberg et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]</td><td align="left">Blind randomized trial</td><td align="left">Forty-two amateur marathon runners, males; aged 39.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;9.4&#x000a0;years; VO2max 57.75&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.87 (Mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD)</td><td align="left">One bottle of fermented milk (80&#x000a0;g) per day, for a duration of 30&#x000a0;days</td><td align="left"><italic>Lactobacillus casei Shirota</italic> (40&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>9</sup>&#x000a0;CFU/beverage)</td><td align="left">Marathon race (42.195&#x000a0;km)</td><td align="left"><p>PRO VS PLA:</p><p>&#x02009;=&#x02009;IL-1ra, IL-1&#x003b2;,</p><p>IL-4, IL-6, IL-10, IL-12p70 and</p><p>IL-13;</p><p>&#x02193; TNF-&#x003b1;</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">West et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]</td><td align="left">Double-blind randomized, placebo-controlled parallel-groups trial</td><td align="left">Thirty-five cyclist and triathletes, females; aged 36.05&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;9.4&#x000a0;years; VO2max&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;45&#x000a0;ml/kg/min</td><td align="left">One capsule per day, for a duration of 11&#x000a0;weeks</td><td align="left"><italic>Lactobacillus fermentum VRI-003</italic> (1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>9</sup>&#x000a0;CFU/capsule)</td><td align="left">Incremental performance test in a cycle ergometer</td><td align="left"><p>PRO VS PLA:</p><p>&#x02009;=&#x02009;IL-8, IL-10 and IFN-&#x001b4;;</p><p>&#x02193; IL-1ra, IL-6 and TNF-&#x003b1;</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">West et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]</td><td align="left">Double-blind randomized, placebo-controlled parallel-groups trial</td><td align="left">Sixty-two cyclist and triathletes, males; aged 35.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;9.6&#x000a0;years; VO2max&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;50&#x000a0;ml/kg/min (Mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD)</td><td align="left">One capsule per day, for a duration of 11&#x000a0;weeks</td><td align="left"><italic>Lactobacillus fermentum VRI-003</italic> (1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>9</sup>&#x000a0;CFU/capsule)</td><td align="left">Incremental performance test in a cycle ergometer</td><td align="left"><p>PRO VS PLA:</p><p>&#x02009;=&#x02009;IL-6, IL-8,</p><p>TNF-&#x003b1; and</p><p>IFN-&#x001b4;;</p><p>&#x02193; IL-1ra and</p><p>IL-10</p></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>VO2max: Maximum Oxygen Intake; CFU: Colony-Forming Units; PRO: Probiotics; PLA: Placebo; IL: Interleukin; TNF: Tumor Necrosis Factor; IFN: Interferon; CRP: C Reactive Protein; W: Watts; RPM: Revolutions Per Minute, kJ: Kilojoules;&#x02009;=&#x02009;there was no statistical significance difference; &#x02193;: there was statistical significance difference and the concentration decreased; &#x02191;: there was statistical significance difference and the concentration increased</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Summary of statistics of all cytokines</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Cytokine</th><th align="left">Number of studies (k)</th><th align="left">Effect size (Mean, 95% CI)</th><th align="left"><italic>p</italic>-value</th><th align="left">Heterogeneity (I<sup>2</sup>) (%)</th><th align="left">Q-test (Q, <italic>p</italic>-value)</th><th align="left">Prediction interval</th><th align="left">Potential outliers</th><th align="left">Influential studies</th><th align="left">Funnel plot asymmetry</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">IL-1&#x003b2;</td><td align="left">7</td><td align="left">0.065 (&#x02212;&#x02009;0.467 to 0.598)</td><td char="." align="char">0.810</td><td char="." align="char">73.12</td><td align="left">27.031 (0.0001)</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x02009;1.209 to 1.340</td><td align="left">Batatinha et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]</td><td align="left">Batatinha et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]</td><td align="left">NA</td></tr><tr><td align="left">IL-6</td><td align="left">18</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x02009;0.124 (&#x02212;&#x02009;0.331 to 0.083)</td><td char="." align="char">0.239</td><td char="." align="char">25.11</td><td align="left">25.841 (0.077)</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x02009;0.597 to 0.349</td><td align="left">None</td><td align="left">None</td><td align="left">Yes (p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.028, regression test)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">IL-8</td><td align="left">12</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x02009;0.156 (&#x02212;&#x02009;0.502 to 0.190)</td><td char="." align="char">0.376</td><td char="." align="char">58.98</td><td align="left">24.346 (0.0113)</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x02009;1.094 to 0.781</td><td align="left">Batatinha et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]</td><td align="left">Batatinha et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]</td><td align="left">No</td></tr><tr><td align="left">IL-10</td><td align="left">15</td><td align="left">0.434 (0.252 to 0.617)</td><td char="." align="char">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001</td><td char="." align="char">0.00</td><td align="left">9.605 (0.791)</td><td align="left">N/A</td><td align="left">None</td><td align="left">Engel et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]</td><td align="left">No</td></tr><tr><td align="left">TNF-&#x003b1;</td><td align="left">15</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x02009;0.283 (&#x02212;&#x02009;0.733 to 0.167)</td><td char="." align="char">0.218</td><td char="." align="char">80.57</td><td align="left">93.474 (&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001)</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x02009;1.870 to 1.304</td><td align="left">West et al. M [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]</td><td align="left">West et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]</td><td align="left">No</td></tr><tr><td align="left">IFN- &#x001b4;</td><td align="left">7</td><td align="left">0.972 (&#x02212;&#x02009;1.077 to 3.022)</td><td char="." align="char">0.352</td><td char="." align="char">97.65</td><td align="left">135.650 (&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001)</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x02009;4.727 to 6.671</td><td align="left">West et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]</td><td align="left">None</td><td align="left">NA</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>NA: Not Addressed</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><sec id="Sec10"><title>IL-1&#x003b2;</title><p id="Par53">Seven studies were analyzed, with effects ranging from &#x02212;&#x02009;1.527 to 0.840. Most studies (86%) showed positive effects. The overall effect, estimated using a random-effects model, was 0.065 (95% CI &#x02212;&#x02009;0.467 to 0.598), meaning there was no significant difference from zero (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.810). There was considerable variation across studies (I<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;73.12%, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0001), suggesting inconsistent findings. The prediction interval ranged from &#x02212;&#x02009;1.209 to 1.340, indicating that while the average effect was positive, some studies showed negative results. One study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>] appeared to be an outlier due to a large residual and high Cook&#x02019;s distance, suggesting it may have strongly influenced the overall results (Figs. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>, <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>, <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>, <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>, <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref> and <xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>IL-1&#x003b2; forest plot</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40798_2025_860_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig><fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>IL-6 forest plot</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40798_2025_860_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig><fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;5</label><caption><p>IL-8 forest plot</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40798_2025_860_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig><fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;6</label><caption><p>IL-10 forest plot</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40798_2025_860_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig><fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;7</label><caption><p>TNF-&#x003b1; forest plot</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40798_2025_860_Fig7_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig><fig id="Fig8"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;8</label><caption><p>TNF-&#x003b1; Meta-Regression based on the bout of exercise</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40798_2025_860_Fig8_HTML" id="MO8"/></fig><fig id="Fig9"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;9</label><caption><p>IFN-&#x001b4; forest plot</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40798_2025_860_Fig9_HTML" id="MO9"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>IL-6</title><p id="Par54">Eighteen studies were analyzed, with standardized mean differences ranging from &#x02212;&#x02009;1.036 to 0.541. Most estimates (56%) were negative. The average standardized mean difference, calculated using a random-effects model, was &#x02212;&#x02009;0.124 (95% CI &#x02212;&#x02009;0.331 to 0.083), showing no significant difference from zero (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.239). Although the test for heterogeneity was not significant (I<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;25.11%, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.077), some variation across studies may still be present. The prediction interval ranged from &#x02212;&#x02009;0.597 to 0.349, suggesting that while the average effect was negative, some studies showed positive results. No studies were identified as outliers based on studentized residuals, and Cook&#x02019;s distances indicated that none had an excessive influence on the results. The regression test suggested possible funnel plot asymmetry (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.028), but this was not confirmed by the rank correlation test (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.081).</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>IL-8</title><p id="Par55">Twelve studies were included in the analysis, with standardized mean differences ranging from &#x02212;&#x02009;1.545 to 0.318. Most estimates (42%) were negative. The average standardized mean difference, based on a random-effects model, was &#x02212;&#x02009;0.156 (95% CI &#x02212;&#x02009;0.502 to 0.190), showing no significant difference from zero (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.376). The Q-test indicated considerable variability between studies (I<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;58.98%, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0113), suggesting heterogeneous outcomes. The prediction interval ranged from &#x02212;&#x02009;1.094 to 0.781, meaning that while the average effect was negative, some studies reported positive results. One study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>] had a high studentized residual, suggesting it might be an outlier. Additionally, its Cook&#x02019;s distance indicated a potentially strong influence on the results. However, tests for publication bias did not suggest funnel plot asymmetry (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.153 and <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.287).</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>IL-10</title><p id="Par56">Fifteen studies were included in the analysis, with standardized mean differences ranging from &#x02212;&#x02009;0.137 to 1.577. Most estimates (87%) were positive. The average standardized mean difference, based on a random-effects model, was 0.434 (95% CI 0.252 to 0.617), showing a significant effect (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001). The Q-test indicated no significant variability between studies (I<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.00%, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.791), suggesting consistent outcomes. One study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>] had a much larger weight compared to the others, potentially influencing the results. However, no studies were identified as outliers based on studentized residuals. Cook&#x02019;s distances, suggested [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>] might have a strong influence on the findings. Tests for publication bias did not indicate funnel plot asymmetry (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.623 and <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.434).</p><p id="Par57">Due to its well-known anti-inflammatory profile the scale of the forest plot is inverted to mitigate the interpretation bias.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>TNF-&#x003b1;</title><p id="Par58">Fifteen studies were analyzed, with standardized mean differences ranging from &#x02212;&#x02009;1.754 to 1.856. Most estimates (60%) were negative. The average standardized mean difference, based on a random-effects model, was &#x02212;&#x02009;0.283 (95% CI &#x02212;&#x02009;0.733 to 0.167), showing no significant effect (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.218). The Q-test indicated substantial variability among studies (I<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;80.57%, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001), suggesting inconsistent results. The prediction interval (&#x02212;&#x02009;1.870&#x02013;1.304) shows that while the average effect is negative, some studies reported positive outcomes. One study (West et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]) had a high studentized residual and might be an outlier. Cook&#x02019;s distance also suggested this study could strongly influence the results. However, tests for publication bias did not indicate funnel plot asymmetry (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.495 and <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.208).</p><p id="Par59">Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref> presents the meta-regression statistics for TNF-&#x003b1;, assessing the potential influence of various covariates on its response to intervention. The intercept value (&#x02212;&#x02009;0.519, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.231) suggests no significant overall effect. The duration of the intervention in weeks (&#x02212;&#x02009;0.004, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.957) does not appear to significantly impact TNF-&#x003b1; levels, indicating that the length of the study is not a determining factor in its modulation. Similarly, the number of strains used (&#x02212;&#x02009;0.018, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.815) shows no meaningful association, suggesting that variations in strain diversity do not substantially influence TNF-&#x003b1; changes. Although the bout of exercise (0.516, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.331) presents a positive coefficient, it does not reach statistical significance. Moreover, the omnibus <italic>p</italic>-value (0.783) indicates that the overall model does not explain a significant proportion of the variance in TNF-&#x003b1; outcomes. These findings suggest that the examined covariates may not be strong predictors of TNF-&#x003b1; modulation in this meta-analysis.<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>TNF-&#x003b1; meta-regression statistics</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Covariate</th><th align="left">Coefficients</th><th align="left">Lower bound</th><th align="left">Upper bound</th><th align="left">Std. error</th><th align="left"><italic>p</italic>-Value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Intercept</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x02009;0.519</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x02009;1.370</td><td align="left">0.331</td><td align="left">0.434</td><td align="left">0.231</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Duration in weeks</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x02009;0.004</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x02009;0.137</td><td align="left">0.130</td><td align="left">0.068</td><td align="left">0.957</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Bout of exercise</td><td align="left">0.516</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x02009;0.526</td><td align="left">1.559</td><td align="left">0.532</td><td align="left">0.331</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Number of strains</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x02009;0.018</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x02009;0.169</td><td align="left">0.133</td><td align="left">0.077</td><td align="left">0.815</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3">Omnibus <italic>p</italic>-Value</td><td align="left" colspan="3">0.783</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>IFN-&#x001b4;</title><p id="Par60">Seven studies were included in the analysis, with standardized mean differences ranging from &#x02212;&#x02009;1.302 to 5.933. Most estimates (57%) were positive. The average standardized mean difference, based on a random-effects model, was 0.972 (95% CI &#x02212;&#x02009;1.077 to 3.022), which did not significantly differ from zero (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.352). The Q-test showed considerable variability among studies (I<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;97.65%, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001), suggesting the results were inconsistent. The prediction interval (&#x02212;&#x02009;4.727&#x02013;6.671) indicates that although the average outcome is positive, some studies showed negative results. One study (West et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]) had a high studentized residual, potentially marking it as an outlier. However, no study appeared to have an overly strong influence on the overall results according to Cook's distances.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par61">The primary objective of this meta-analysis was to evaluate the impact of probiotic supplementation on cytokine modulation following a bout of exercise in athletes. Analysis of 19 studies demonstrated that probiotic supplementation did not significantly influence most cytokine responses, including IL-1&#x003b2;, IL-6, IL-8, TNF-&#x003b1; and IFN-&#x001b4;. However, a significant effect was noted in the upregulation of IL-10. The analysis was further stratified by exercise type, comparing VO2max tests and endurance events such as marathons and triathlons independently. Despite these distinctions, levels of IL-6, IL-8, and TNF-&#x003b1; remained statistically insignificant. And IL-10 remained statistically significant in all subgroup analyses. Importantly, after excluding potential outliers and highly influential studies, a significant reduction in TNF-&#x003b1; concentration was observed. Nevertheless, no differences were found in IL-8 levels. Additionally, TNF-&#x003b1; levels did not achieve statistical significance in studies focused on VO2max exercise bouts, even after accounting for outliers and highly influential studies<bold>.</bold></p><p id="Par62">While these results do not indicate a consistent effect across all cytokines, they suggest that probiotics may play a role in modulating immune responses and supporting recovery after exercise. Notably, the findings of this meta-analysis differ from those reported in previous meta-analyses on the same topic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Earlier analyses identified significant reductions in IL-6, a trend not observed in the present study. Some alignment was found regarding TNF-&#x003b1; modulation, yet no significant effects were reported for IL-10 in those previous meta-analyses. These discrepancies may be attributed to differences in study design, probiotic strains and dosages, exercise protocols, and participant characteristics. Additionally, a key distinction is that previous meta-analyses included studies that measured cytokine levels both at baseline and post-exercise, whereas our analysis focused on cytokine responses specifically in the context of exercise recovery. This difference in measurement timing could have influenced the observed outcomes.</p><p id="Par63">It is important to highlight that both [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>] and [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>] included a relatively small number of studies, which may have limited the generalizability of their findings. In contrast, an umbrella review conducted by [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>] examined the effects of probiotics primarily in clinical populations, such as individuals with diabetes or autoimmune diseases. In that review, no significant alignments with our results were found regarding IL-6 and TNF-&#x003b1;. However, another meta-analysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>] did report a clear upregulation of IL-10, while failing to observe significant effects on IL-6 and TNF-&#x003b1;. This suggests that while probiotic supplementation may enhance anti-inflammatory responses in certain populations, its effects on specific cytokines can vary depending on health status, exercise intensity, probiotic formulation, and whether cytokines are measured at rest or in response to exercise.</p><p id="Par64">As so, the highlighted biological mechanisms through which probiotics modulate cytokine responses are complex and diverse. Probiotics influence immune function and inflammation via several pathways: they alter the gut microbiota by increasing beneficial bacteria and decreasing harmful species, which strengthens gut barrier function and reduces systemic inflammation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. They also enhance the production of short-chain fatty acids (SCFAs) like butyrate, which are known for their anti-inflammatory effects. It has been shown to influence immune function and inflammation through multiple mechanisms, particularly by modulating the gut microbiota. By increasing beneficial bacterial populations and reducing the abundance of harmful species, probiotics help strengthen the gut barrier and lower systemic inflammation. They also enhance the production of short-chain fatty acids (SCFAs), such as butyrate, which have recognized anti-inflammatory effects. Notably, the impact of probiotics on SCFA production can vary depending on the specific probiotic strain used and the baseline microbial composition of the individual. Studies have indicated that probiotics such as <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> and <italic>Bifidobacterium</italic> strains can significantly increase fecal concentrations of SCFAs, including butyrate, acetate, and propionate, which are associated with improved gut health and reduced inflammation. Moreover, the production of these metabolites may also help restore microbial balance and support immune function, suggesting that individual responses to probiotics may depend on initial gut microbiota conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Thus, probiotic supplementation could be a potential strategy to modulate inflammatory processes and improve immune responses, particularly in individuals with altered or compromised microbiota. The mechanism of probiotic modulation of immune function and inflammation is illustrated in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>, adapted from [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>].<fig id="Fig10"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;10</label><caption><p>Potential Effects of Probiotics on the Modulation of SCFAs in Humans</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40798_2025_860_Fig10_HTML" id="MO10"/></fig></p><p id="Par65">Figure <xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref> Adapted from [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>] Potential effects of SCFAs in humans; AMPK: AMP kinase; ANGPTL: angiopoietin-like; GLP1: glucagon-like peptide 1; GPR: G protein-coupled receptor; HSL: hormone-sensitive lipase; LPL: lipoprotein lipase; PPAR- &#x001b4;: peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor-&#x001b4;; PYY: polypeptide YY</p><p id="Par66">They also interact directly with immune cells, such as dendritic cells and macrophages, to boost anti-inflammatory cytokines like IL-10 while reducing pro-inflammatory cytokines such as TNF-&#x003b1; and IL-6 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Additionally, probiotics may affect the gut-brain axis, potentially modulating stress responses and inflammation associated with exercise-induced stress and recovery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. These combined effects contribute to reduced systemic inflammation, evident in altered cytokine profiles [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>].</p><p id="Par67">Getting in-depth with the results and their interpretation here are the most remarkable insights:</p><p id="Par68">IL-1&#x003b2; is a well-known pro-inflammatory cytokine released in response to cellular damage, behaving similarly to TNF-&#x003b1; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. While estimates suggested that IL-1&#x003b2; concentrations were higher in the placebo group compared to the probiotic group, the clinical implications of these differences remain unclear due to the lack of statistical significance and high variability across studies. Despite this, the potential for probiotic supplementation to influence IL-1&#x003b2; levels warrants further exploration, particularly considering its role in modulating inflammation in response to cellular stress.</p><p id="Par69">Similarly, IL-6, a cytokine with both pro-inflammatory and anti-inflammatory properties, plays a crucial role in the inflammatory response to exercise. IL-6 promotes the production of anti-inflammatory cytokines like IL-10 and IL-1Ra, which can help mitigate the harmful effects of inflammation. Probiotics may contribute to reducing systemic inflammation by enhancing gut barrier function and modulating immune cell activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. In previous meta-analysis a reduction in the concentration of IL-6 was observed when pooling studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. But, although estimates showed lower IL-6 concentrations in the probiotic group, the clinical relevance of this finding remains uncertain. The variability observed suggests that while probiotics may have a role in influencing IL-6, more research is needed to confirm their consistent impact on exercise-induced inflammation. However, is important to mention that the regression test for funnel plot asymmetry suggested a potential publication bias, indicating possible asymmetry in the distribution of studies. Conversely, the rank correlation test did not show a statistically significant relationship between effect sizes and study size, implying that systematic bias in effect size reporting may be less likely. These varying findings highlight the challenges in detecting publication bias, suggesting that while funnel plot asymmetry might be present, it is not consistently supported by all analyses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>].</p><p id="Par70">IL-8, a cytokine involved in muscle recovery and angiogenesis, has a minimal systemic response following intense exercise, especially when eccentric movements are involved [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Most estimates indicated that IL-8 concentrations were lower in the probiotic group compared to the placebo group, although this difference did not reach clinical significance. Despite the variability across studies, probiotics could still have a role in moderating IL-8 levels, potentially aiding recovery by influencing localized inflammation following intense physical exertion.</p><p id="Par71">IL-10 is widely acknowledged as a prominent anti-inflammatory cytokine, is produced by a wide range of leukocytes, IL-10 is essential for suppressing macrophage activation and the subsequent release of proinflammatory cytokines, such as IL-6 and TNF-&#x003b1; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. Additionally, research has shown that probiotics can increase IL-10 concentrations by the modulation of dendritic cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>] Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig">11</xref>. When comparing to other meta-analysis, Compared to previous meta-analyses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>], which included fewer studies and assessed cytokine levels primarily before and after exercise bouts, our analysis provides a more comprehensive evaluation. Additionally, while an umbrella review by [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>] reported IL-10 upregulation, its findings were based on populations with clinical illnesses, limiting their applicability to athletes. Our meta-analysis not only demonstrates a statistically significant increase in IL-10 levels but also underscores the clinical relevance of probiotic supplementation in enhancing recovery. The observed benefits across various subgroups, including VO2max, marathon, and triathlon participants, suggest probiotics may be effective across different exercise intensities and modalities. Although some variability was noted in the subgroup analysis for marathon and triathlon participants, the overall trend of improved IL-10 levels remains clinically significant. Given IL-10&#x02019;s crucial role in modulating inflammation and supporting recovery, these findings highlight probiotics as a potential strategy to optimize post-exercise recovery in athletes.<fig id="Fig11"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;11</label><caption><p>Potential Impact of Probiotics on the Upregulation of IL-10</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40798_2025_860_Fig11_HTML" id="MO11"/></fig></p><p id="Par72">The modulation of TNF-&#x003b1; in response to probiotic supplementation follows a similar pattern to that of IL-1&#x003b2;, with evidence suggesting that probiotics can influence TNF-&#x003b1; levels by reducing intestinal inflammation. This effect is thought to occur through the downregulation of TLR expression and the secretion of metabolites that prevent TNF-&#x003b1; from entering blood mononuclear cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Despite these mechanisms, our analysis did not find a statistically significant reduction in TNF-&#x003b1; concentrations. Significant heterogeneity was noted across the included studies, and excluding the potential outlier study by (West et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]) indicated a possible trend towards lower TNF-&#x003b1; levels in the probiotic group compared to placebo, although heterogeneity remained substantial. Furthermore, no single study was found to have a disproportionate influence on the overall results, and funnel plot asymmetry was not indicated by rank correlation or regression tests. It is important to note that in most studies, the prediction interval crossed zero, suggesting that previously identified effects may have been suppressed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. While subgroup analyses suggested potential reductions in TNF-&#x003b1; levels following probiotic supplementation, these findings did not reach statistical significance in either subgroup. Understanding the precise mechanisms by which probiotics may modulate TNF-&#x003b1; remains an area of interest, particularly in the context of inflammatory responses and recovery strategies.</p><p id="Par73">The meta-regression analysis suggests that the examined covariates may not be strong predictors of TNF-&#x003b1; modulation in response to probiotic interventions. While neither intervention duration nor strain diversity showed a meaningful influence, exercise type emerged as a potential factor of interest. Although it did not reach statistical significance in this analysis, its role could become clearer with a larger number of studies and more standardized methodologies. Future research should focus on ensuring balanced study designs across different exercise modalities to better assess their impact on TNF-&#x003b1; regulation.</p><p id="Par74">The modulation of IFN-&#x003b3; in response to exercise remains controversial, as evidence on its regulation is inconsistent [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. While some studies suggest that probiotic supplementation may help modulate IFN-&#x003b3; levels, our analysis did not find a significant difference between groups. Higher concentrations were generally observed in the placebo group, which could indicate a heightened inflammatory response in the absence of probiotics. However, this trend was not consistent across all studies. Given IFN-&#x003b3;&#x02019;s role in immune regulation and inflammation, understanding its response to exercise and probiotic supplementation remains crucial for optimizing recovery strategies in athletes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Strengths and Limitations</title><p id="Par75">Several factors may contribute to these discrepancies. Differences in the bouts of exercise (e.g., VO2max test vs. marathons), the design, the intensity, duration of the exercise bout, and the timing of probiotic supplementation relative to exercise are critical considerations. Additionally, the specific strains of probiotics used, their viability, and their ability to colonize the gut microbiota can significantly influence outcomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Understanding these variables is essential for interpreting the diverse results reported in the literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>].</p><p id="Par76">A notable strength of this meta-analysis is the rigorous methodology employed, including a comprehensive literature search, stringent inclusion criteria, and the use of advanced statistical techniques to address heterogeneity among studies.</p><p id="Par77">The inclusion of a diverse range of studies enhances the generalizability of our findings. Moreover, the focus on cytokine modulation provides valuable insights into the immune-regulatory effects of probiotics in the context of exercise.</p><p id="Par78">However, several limitations must be acknowledged. First, the potential for publication bias exists, as studies with positive findings are more likely to be published. To mitigate this, funnel plots and Egger's regression tests were employed, but some bias may still be present [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. Regarding IL-6, potential publication bias was suggested by the Egger's regression (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.028), indicating possible asymmetry in the funnel plot. This raises concerns about the influence of unpublished small or null-effect studies on the results, which has been acknowledged in the discussion. Heterogeneity among studies was significant, influenced by variations in study design, participant characteristics, probiotic types and dosages, and exercise protocols. To address this, analyses were conducted with at least seven studies, and subgroup analyses explored sources of heterogeneity. However, some residual heterogeneity remained, highlighting the complexity of interpreting these findings and suggesting the need for further research.</p><p id="Par79">Additionally, the quality of included studies varied, with some studies having small sample sizes and short follow-up periods. The lack of standardized protocols for probiotic administration and cytokine measurement further complicates comparisons across studies. Future research should prioritize standardized methodologies to enhance the reliability and comparability of findings. Future research should focus on standardizing methodologies to improve the reliability and comparability of results. Additionally, more effective implementation of washout periods tailored to different study characteristics is recommended.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Clinical and Practical Implications</title><p id="Par80">The findings of this meta-analysis have significant clinical and practical implications for athletes and those engaged in regular physical activity. Probiotic supplementation shows promise in managing inflammation and enhancing recovery by modulating immune responses. By reducing pro-inflammatory cytokines and increasing anti-inflammatory cytokines, probiotics can mitigate exercise-induced inflammation and muscle damage, leading to faster recovery, improved performance, reduced fatigue, and a lower risk of overtraining. Additionally, probiotics may bolster immune resilience by supporting gut health, which is particularly beneficial during intense training periods [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Based on these findings, incorporating probiotic supplementation into exercise recovery strategies could be highly beneficial. But this approach requires careful selection of probiotic strains, along with tailored dosage and timing, to meet individual needs and training schedules, effectively mitigating potential issues.</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Future Research Directions</title><p id="Par81">While this meta-analysis provides valuable insights, several areas require further investigation. Long-term studies are needed to assess the sustained impact of probiotics on cytokine modulation and overall health outcomes, as some of the included studies focused on short-term effects (&#x0003c;&#x02009;4&#x000a0;weeks). Additionally, future studies should consider that a minimum dosage of 1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10&#x02079; CFU, administered for at least 3&#x000a0;weeks, is required to achieve the aforementioned effects, as suggested by J&#x000e4;ger et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Future research should also explore the role of the bout of exercise as a key factor influencing TNF-&#x003b1; and other cytokine modulation in response to probiotic supplementation. The type and intensity of exercise can significantly affect the inflammatory response, and understanding how these factors interact with probiotics could provide valuable insights. If future studies focus on similar populations with consistent characteristics, such as comparable baseline inflammation levels, exercise dosages, and other relevant factors, the effect of different exercise bouts (e.g., endurance versus VO&#x02082; max tests) on TNF-&#x003b1; and other cytokines could be more clearly defined. This approach could advance our understanding of how probiotics influence the broader cytokine profile, particularly in terms of pro-inflammatory and anti-inflammatory cytokines, and help establish more targeted and effective protocols for probiotic supplementation based on the nature of the exercise and individual athlete profiles. Also, extending it to older adults, individuals with chronic inflammatory conditions, and different athletic populations will help understand the broader applicability of probiotics. Detailed mechanistic studies are necessary to explore the interactions between probiotics, gut microbiota, and the immune system at the molecular level. However, within this meta-analysis, only two studies (West et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>] and West et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]) have addressed this approach.</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par82">In conclusion, this meta-analysis offers strong evidence that probiotic supplementation can effectively modulate cytokine responses after exercise. By decreasing pro-inflammatory cytokines and increasing anti-inflammatory cytokines, probiotics show potential as a strategy to improve recovery and manage exercise-induced inflammation, particularly in relation to IL-10 levels. While the findings are encouraging, further research is needed to fully elucidate the long-term effects, strain-specific benefits, and mechanisms of action of probiotics in different populations. Integrating probiotics into exercise recovery protocols represents a promising avenue for improving athletic performance, reducing fatigue, and supporting immune health. Continued investigation in this field will pave the way for more personalized and effective strategies for managing exercise-induced inflammation and optimizing overall health.</p></sec><sec id="Sec21" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="40798_2025_860_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><caption><p>Supplementary Material 1.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="40798_2025_860_MOESM2_ESM.xlsx"><caption><p>Supplementary Material 2.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></p></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>RCTs</term><def><p id="Par9">Randomized controlled trials</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GI</term><def><p id="Par10">Gastrointestinal</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SCFAs</term><def><p id="Par11">Short-chain fatty acids</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IL</term><def><p id="Par12">Interleukin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TNF-&#x003b1;</term><def><p id="Par13">Tumor necrosis factor alpha</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IL-1Ra</term><def><p id="Par14">Interleukin 1 receptor antagonist</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Th1 cells</term><def><p id="Par15">T helper 1 cells</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IFN-&#x003b3;</term><def><p id="Par16">Interferon-gamma</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IgA</term><def><p id="Par17">Immunoglobulin A</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CFU</term><def><p id="Par18">Colony-forming units</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CRP</term><def><p id="Par19">C-Reactive protein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PRISMA&#x000ae;</term><def><p id="Par20">Preferred reporting items for systematic reviews and meta-analyses</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>WOS</term><def><p id="Par21">Web of science</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>VO2max</term><def><p id="Par22">Maximum oxygen uptake</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RPM</term><def><p id="Par23">Revolutions per minute</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>kJ</term><def><p id="Par24">Kilojoules</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Q-test</term><def><p id="Par25">Cochran's Q test for heterogeneity</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>I would like to express my heartfelt gratitude to my family, friends, and colleagues for their unwavering support and encouragement throughout this journey. And a special thanks to Dr. Alejandro Rubio-Zarapuz for his invaluable guidance and expertise throughout this research.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>Conceptualization: Diego Aparicio Pascual, Alejandro Rubio-Zarapuz; Methodology: Diego Aparicio Pascual, Alejandro Rubio-Zarapuz, Vicente Javier Clemente-Su&#x000e1;rez, Jos&#x000e9; Francisco Tornero-Aguilera; Formal analysis and investigation: Diego Aparicio Pascual, Jos&#x000e9; Francisco Tornero-Aguilera; Writing&#x02014;original draft preparation: Diego Aparicio Pascual, Alejandro Rubio-Zarapuz, Vicente Javier Clemente-Su&#x000e1;rez, Jos&#x000e9; Francisco Tornero-Aguilera; Writing&#x02014;review and editing: Diego Aparicio Pascual, Jos&#x000e9; Francisco Tornero-Aguilera; Supervision: Alejandro Rubio-Zarapuz, Vicente Javier Clemente-Su&#x000e1;rez.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>No funding was required for the present research.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of Data and Material</title><p>All data and materials obtained from this research are present in this manuscript and its supplementary material and raw data can be obtained upon reasonable request.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics Approval and Consent to Participate</title><p id="Par83">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for Publication</title><p id="Par84">All authors have reviewed and consent to the publication of this manuscript.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par85">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>J&#x000e4;ger</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohr</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Carpenter</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerksick</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Purpura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Moussa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>International society of sports nutrition position stand: probiotics</article-title><source>J Int Soc Sports Nutr</source><year>2019</year><volume>16</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>62</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12970-019-0329-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31864419</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">J&#x000e4;ger R, Mohr AE, Carpenter KC, Kerksick CM, Purpura M, Moussa A, et al. International society of sports nutrition position stand: probiotics. J Int Soc Sports Nutr. 2019;16(1):62. 10.1186/s12970-019-0329-0.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31864419</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>P&#x000e9;rez-Castillo</surname><given-names>&#x000cd;M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sabag-Daigle</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x000f3;pez-Chicharro</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mihic</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Rueda</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouzamondo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The athlete gut microbiota: state of the art and practical guidance</article-title><source>Benef Microbes</source><year>2024</year><volume>15</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>126</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1163/18762891-bja00007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38659188</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">P&#x000e9;rez-Castillo &#x000cd;M, Sabag-Daigle A, L&#x000f3;pez-Chicharro J, Mihic N, Rueda R, Bouzamondo H. The athlete gut microbiota: state of the art and practical guidance. Benef Microbes. 2024;15(2):97&#x02013;126. 10.1163/18762891-bja00007.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38659188</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rauch</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Mika</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>McCubbin</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Huschtscha</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>RJS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of prebiotics, probiotics, and synbiotics on gastrointestinal outcomes in healthy adults and active adults at rest and in response to exercise&#x02014;A systematic literature review</article-title><source>Front Nutr</source><year>2022</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1003620</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnut.2022.1003620</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36570133</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Rauch CE, Mika AS, McCubbin AJ, Huschtscha Z, Costa RJS. Effect of prebiotics, probiotics, and synbiotics on gastrointestinal outcomes in healthy adults and active adults at rest and in response to exercise&#x02014;A systematic literature review. Front Nutr. 2022;9:1003620. 10.3389/fnut.2022.1003620.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36570133</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>D&#x000ed;az-Jim&#x000e9;nez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#x000e1;nchez-S&#x000e1;nchez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ordo&#x000f1;ez</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosety</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x000ed;az</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosety-Rodriguez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Impact of probiotics on the performance of endurance athletes: a systematic review</article-title><source>IJERPH</source><year>2021</year><volume>18</volume><issue>21</issue><fpage>11576</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph182111576</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34770090</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">D&#x000ed;az-Jim&#x000e9;nez J, S&#x000e1;nchez-S&#x000e1;nchez E, Ordo&#x000f1;ez FJ, Rosety I, D&#x000ed;az AJ, Rosety-Rodriguez M, et al. Impact of probiotics on the performance of endurance athletes: a systematic review. IJERPH. 2021;18(21):11576. 10.3390/ijerph182111576.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34770090</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Santiba&#x000f1;ez-Gutierrez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez-Landa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Calleja-Gonz&#x000e1;lez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Delextrat</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mielgo-Ayuso</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of probiotic supplementation on exercise with predominance of aerobic metabolism in trained population: a systematic review, meta-analysis and meta-regression</article-title><source>Nutrients</source><year>2022</year><volume>14</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>622</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/nu14030622</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35276980</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Santiba&#x000f1;ez-Gutierrez A, Fern&#x000e1;ndez-Landa J, Calleja-Gonz&#x000e1;lez J, Delextrat A, Mielgo-Ayuso J. Effects of probiotic supplementation on exercise with predominance of aerobic metabolism in trained population: a systematic review, meta-analysis and meta-regression. Nutrients. 2022;14(3):622. 10.3390/nu14030622.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35276980</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prajapati</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bisani</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Prajapati</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Prajapati</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Agrawal</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Advances in probiotics research: mechanisms of action, health benefits, and limitations in applications</article-title><source>Syst Microbiol and Biomanuf</source><year>2024</year><volume>4</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>386</fpage><lpage>406</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s43393-023-00208-w</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Prajapati K, Bisani K, Prajapati H, Prajapati S, Agrawal D, Singh S, et al. Advances in probiotics research: mechanisms of action, health benefits, and limitations in applications. Syst Microbiol and Biomanuf. 2024;4(2):386&#x02013;406. 10.1007/s43393-023-00208-w.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Docherty</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Harley</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>McAuley</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Crowe</surname><given-names>LAN</given-names></name><name><surname>Pedret</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirwan</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The effect of exercise on cytokines: implications for musculoskeletal health: a narrative review</article-title><source>BMC Sports Sci Med Rehabil</source><year>2022</year><volume>14</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>5</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13102-022-00397-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34991697</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Docherty S, Harley R, McAuley JJ, Crowe LAN, Pedret C, Kirwan PD, et al. The effect of exercise on cytokines: implications for musculoskeletal health: a narrative review. BMC Sports Sci Med Rehabil. 2022;14(1):5. 10.1186/s13102-022-00397-2.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34991697</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ma&#x00142;kowska</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sawczuk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cytokines as biomarkers for evaluating physical exercise in trained and non-trained individuals: a narrative review</article-title><source>IJMS</source><year>2023</year><volume>24</volume><issue>13</issue><fpage>11156</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms241311156</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37446334</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Ma&#x00142;kowska P, Sawczuk M. Cytokines as biomarkers for evaluating physical exercise in trained and non-trained individuals: a narrative review. IJMS. 2023;24(13):11156. 10.3390/ijms241311156.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37446334</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>&#x00141;agowska</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bajerska</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Probiotic supplementation and respiratory infection and immune function in athletes: systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials</article-title><source>J Athl Train</source><year>2021</year><volume>56</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1213</fpage><lpage>1223</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4085/592-20</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33481001</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">&#x00141;agowska K, Bajerska J. Probiotic supplementation and respiratory infection and immune function in athletes: systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials. J Athl Train. 2021;56(11):1213&#x02013;23. 10.4085/592-20.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33481001</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nazari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Faghfoori</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>As&#x02019;Habi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Arab</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hajianfar</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Probiotic consumption and inflammatory markers in athletes: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Int J Food Propert</source><year>2020</year><volume>23</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1402</fpage><lpage>1415</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10942912.2020.1807566</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Nazari M, Faghfoori Z, As&#x02019;Habi A, Arab A, Hajianfar H. Probiotic consumption and inflammatory markers in athletes: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Int J Food Propert. 2020;23(1):1402&#x02013;15. 10.1080/10942912.2020.1807566.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Plaza-Diaz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruiz-Ojeda</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gil-Campos</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gil</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>mechanisms of action of probiotics</article-title><source>Adv Nutr</source><year>2019</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>S49</fpage><lpage>66</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/advances/nmy063</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30721959</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Plaza-Diaz J, Ruiz-Ojeda FJ, Gil-Campos M, Gil A. mechanisms of action of probiotics. Adv Nutr. 2019;10:S49-66. 10.1093/advances/nmy063.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30721959</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Page</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>McKenzie</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bossuyt</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Boutron</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Mulrow</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The PRISMA 2020 statement: an updated guideline for reporting systematic reviews</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>2021</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>n71</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.n71</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Page MJ, McKenzie JE, Bossuyt PM, Boutron I, Hoffmann TC, Mulrow CD, et al. The PRISMA 2020 statement: an updated guideline for reporting systematic reviews. BMJ. 2021;29: n71. 10.1136/bmj.n71.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The beneficial effects of lactobacillus plantarum PS128 on high-intensity, exercise-induced oxidative stress, inflammation, and performance in triathletes</article-title><source>Nutrients</source><year>2019</year><volume>11</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>353</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/nu11020353</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30736479</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Huang WC, Wei CC, Huang CC, Chen WL, Huang HY. The beneficial effects of lactobacillus plantarum PS128 on high-intensity, exercise-induced oxidative stress, inflammation, and performance in triathletes. Nutrients. 2019;11(2):353. 10.3390/nu11020353.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30736479</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>West</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><name><surname>Pyne</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Cripps</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Hopkins</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name><name><surname>Eskesen</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Jairath</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Lactobacillus fermentum (PCC&#x000ae;) supplementation and gastrointestinal and respiratory-tract illness symptoms: a randomised control trial in athletes</article-title><source>Nutr J</source><year>2011</year><volume>10</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>30</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1475-2891-10-30</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21477383</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">West NP, Pyne DB, Cripps AW, Hopkins WG, Eskesen DC, Jairath A, et al. Lactobacillus fermentum (PCC&#x000ae;) supplementation and gastrointestinal and respiratory-tract illness symptoms: a randomised control trial in athletes. Nutr J. 2011;10(1):30. 10.1186/1475-2891-10-30.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21477383</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Scanlan C, Law M, Stewart D, Pollock N, Letts L, Bosch J, et al. Critical Review Form &#x02013; Quantitative Studies.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimating the sample mean and standard deviation from the sample size, median, range and/or interquartile range</article-title><source>BMC Med Res Methodol</source><year>2014</year><volume>14</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>135</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2288-14-135</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25524443</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Wan X, Wang W, Liu J, Tong T. Estimating the sample mean and standard deviation from the sample size, median, range and/or interquartile range. BMC Med Res Methodol. 2014;14(1):135. 10.1186/1471-2288-14-135.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25524443</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hedges</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name><name><surname>Olkin</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><source>Statistical methods for meta-analysis</source><year>1985</year><publisher-loc>INC.</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="book">Hedges LV, Olkin I. Statistical methods for meta-analysis. INC.: Academic Press; 1985.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cochran</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The combination of estimates from different experiments</article-title><source>Biometrics</source><year>1954</year><volume>10</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>101</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/3001666</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Cochran WG. The combination of estimates from different experiments. Biometrics. 1954;10(1):101. 10.2307/3001666.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Godavitarne</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ricketts</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Understanding and interpreting funnel plots for the clinician</article-title><source>Br J Hosp Med</source><year>2018</year><volume>79</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>578</fpage><lpage>583</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12968/hmed.2018.79.10.578</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Godavitarne C, Robertson A, Ricketts DM, Rogers BA. Understanding and interpreting funnel plots for the clinician. Br J Hosp Med. 2018;79(10):578&#x02013;83. 10.12968/hmed.2018.79.10.578.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pathak</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dwivedi</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Deo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sreenivas</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Thakur</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Which is the preferred measure of heterogeneity in meta-analysis and why? A revisit</article-title><source>BBOAJ</source><year>2017</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.19080/BBOAJ.2017.01.555555</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">Pathak M, Dwivedi SN, Deo S, Sreenivas V, Thakur B. Which is the preferred measure of heterogeneity in meta-analysis and why? A revisit. BBOAJ. 2017. 10.19080/BBOAJ.2017.01.555555.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Von Hippel</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The heterogeneity statistic I2 can be biased in small meta-analyses</article-title><source>BMC Med Res Methodol</source><year>2015</year><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>35</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12874-015-0024-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25880989</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Von Hippel PT. The heterogeneity statistic I2 can be biased in small meta-analyses. BMC Med Res Methodol. 2015;15(1):35. 10.1186/s12874-015-0024-z.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25880989</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Higgins JPT, Thomas J, Chandler J, Cumpston M, Li T, Page MJ, et al., editors. Front Matter. In: Cochrane Handbook for Systematic Reviews of Interventions. 1st ed. Wiley; 2019. 10.1002/9781119536604.fmatter</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>JPT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How should meta-regression analyses be undertaken and interpreted?</article-title><source>Stat Med</source><year>2002</year><volume>21</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1559</fpage><lpage>1573</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/sim.1187</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12111920</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Thompson SG, Higgins JPT. How should meta-regression analyses be undertaken and interpreted? Stat Med. 2002;21(11):1559&#x02013;73. 10.1002/sim.1187.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12111920</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Axelrod</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Brennan</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cresci</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hull</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fealy</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>UCC118 supplementation reduces exercise-induced gastrointestinal permeability and remodels the gut microbiome in healthy humans</article-title><source>Physiol Rep</source><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14814/phy2.14276</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31758610</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">Axelrod CL, Brennan CJ, Cresci G, Paul D, Hull M, Fealy CE, et al. UCC118 supplementation reduces exercise-induced gastrointestinal permeability and remodels the gut microbiome in healthy humans. Physiol Rep. 2019. 10.14814/phy2.14276.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31758610</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>J&#x000e4;ger</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Purpura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Anzalone</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Eimerbrink</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Probiotic Streptococcus thermophilus FP4 and bifidobacterium breve br03 supplementation attenuates performance and range-of-motion decrements following muscle damaging exercise</article-title><source>Nutrients</source><year>2016</year><volume>8</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>642</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/nu8100642</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27754427</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="journal">J&#x000e4;ger R, Purpura M, Stone J, Turner S, Anzalone A, Eimerbrink M, et al. Probiotic Streptococcus thermophilus FP4 and bifidobacterium breve br03 supplementation attenuates performance and range-of-motion decrements following muscle damaging exercise. Nutrients. 2016;8(10):642. 10.3390/nu8100642.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27754427</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR26" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pugh</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagenmakers</surname><given-names>AJM</given-names></name><name><surname>Doran</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fleming</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Fielding</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Morton</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Probiotic supplementation increases carbohydrate metabolism in trained male cyclists: a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled crossover trial</article-title><source>Am J Physiol Endocrinol Metab</source><year>2020</year><volume>318</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>E504</fpage><lpage>E513</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpendo.00452.2019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32069071</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26" publication-type="journal">Pugh JN, Wagenmakers AJM, Doran DA, Fleming SC, Fielding BA, Morton JP, et al. Probiotic supplementation increases carbohydrate metabolism in trained male cyclists: a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled crossover trial. Am J Physiol Endocrinol Metab. 2020;318(4):E504&#x02013;13. 10.1152/ajpendo.00452.2019.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32069071</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR27" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shing</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Peake</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Briskey</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><name><surname>Fortes</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effects of probiotics supplementation on gastrointestinal permeability, inflammation and exercise performance in the heat</article-title><source>Eur J Appl Physiol</source><year>2014</year><volume>114</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>103</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00421-013-2748-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24150782</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27" publication-type="journal">Shing CM, Peake JM, Lim CL, Briskey D, Walsh NP, Fortes MB, et al. Effects of probiotics supplementation on gastrointestinal permeability, inflammation and exercise performance in the heat. Eur J Appl Physiol. 2014;114(1):93&#x02013;103. 10.1007/s00421-013-2748-y.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24150782</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR28" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mazani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nemati</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Baghi</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Amani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Haedari</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Alipanah-Mogadam</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of probiotic yoghurt consumption on oxidative stress and inflammatory factors in young females after exhaustive exercise</article-title><source>J Pak Med Assoc</source><year>2018</year><volume>68</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1748</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30504936</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28" publication-type="journal">Mazani M, Nemati A, Baghi AN, Amani M, Haedari K, Alipanah-Mogadam R. The effect of probiotic yoghurt consumption on oxidative stress and inflammatory factors in young females after exhaustive exercise. J Pak Med Assoc. 2018;68(12):1748.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30504936</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR29" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Batatinha</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tavares-Silva</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Leite</surname><given-names>GSF</given-names></name><name><surname>Resende</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Albuquerque</surname><given-names>JAT</given-names></name><name><surname>Arslanian</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Probiotic supplementation in marathonists and its impact on lymphocyte population and function after a marathon: a randomized placebo-controlled double-blind study</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2020</year><volume>10</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>18777</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-75464-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33139757</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29" publication-type="journal">Batatinha H, Tavares-Silva E, Leite GSF, Resende AS, Albuquerque JAT, Arslanian C, et al. Probiotic supplementation in marathonists and its impact on lymphocyte population and function after a marathon: a randomized placebo-controlled double-blind study. Sci Rep. 2020;10(1):18777. 10.1038/s41598-020-75464-0.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33139757</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR30" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Allerton</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ansley-Robson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hemmings</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>RJS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>does short-term high dose probiotic supplementation containing lactobacillus casei attenuate exertional-heat stress induced endotoxaemia and cytokinaemia?</article-title><source>Int J Sport Nutr Exerc Metab</source><year>2016</year><volume>26</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>268</fpage><lpage>275</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1123/ijsnem.2015-0186</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26568577</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30" publication-type="journal">Gill SK, Allerton DM, Ansley-Robson P, Hemmings K, Cox M, Costa RJS. does short-term high dose probiotic supplementation containing lactobacillus casei attenuate exertional-heat stress induced endotoxaemia and cytokinaemia? Int J Sport Nutr Exerc Metab. 2016;26(3):268&#x02013;75. 10.1123/ijsnem.2015-0186.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26568577</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR31" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lamprecht</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bogner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Schippinger</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Steinbauer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Fankhauser</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Hallstroem</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Probiotic supplementation affects markers of intestinal barrier, oxidation, and inflammation in trained men; a randomized, double-blinded, placebo-controlled trial</article-title><source>J Int Soc Sports Nutr</source><year>2012</year><volume>9</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>45</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1550-2783-9-45</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22992437</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR31" publication-type="journal">Lamprecht M, Bogner S, Schippinger G, Steinbauer K, Fankhauser F, Hallstroem S, et al. Probiotic supplementation affects markers of intestinal barrier, oxidation, and inflammation in trained men; a randomized, double-blinded, placebo-controlled trial. J Int Soc Sports Nutr. 2012;9(1):45. 10.1186/1550-2783-9-45.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22992437</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR32" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mazur-Kurach</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Fr&#x00105;czek</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Klimek</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Does multi-strain probiotic supplementation impact the effort capacity of competitive road cyclists?</article-title><source>IJERPH</source><year>2022</year><volume>19</volume><issue>19</issue><fpage>12205</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph191912205</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36231510</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32" publication-type="journal">Mazur-Kurach P, Fr&#x00105;czek B, Klimek AT. Does multi-strain probiotic supplementation impact the effort capacity of competitive road cyclists? IJERPH. 2022;19(19):12205. 10.3390/ijerph191912205.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36231510</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR33" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pugh</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Sparks</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Doran</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fleming</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Langan-Evans</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirk</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Four weeks of probiotic supplementation reduces GI symptoms during a marathon race</article-title><source>Eur J Appl Physiol</source><year>2019</year><volume>119</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1491</fpage><lpage>1501</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00421-019-04136-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30982100</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR33" publication-type="journal">Pugh JN, Sparks AS, Doran DA, Fleming SC, Langan-Evans C, Kirk B, et al. Four weeks of probiotic supplementation reduces GI symptoms during a marathon race. Eur J Appl Physiol. 2019;119(7):1491&#x02013;501. 10.1007/s00421-019-04136-3.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30982100</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR34" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tavares-Silva</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Caris</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ravacci</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomatieli-Santos</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of multi-strain probiotic supplementation on URTI symptoms and cytokine production by monocytes after a marathon race: a randomized, double-blind, placebo study</article-title><source>Nutrients</source><year>2021</year><volume>13</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1478</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/nu13051478</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33925633</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR34" publication-type="journal">Tavares-Silva E, Caris AV, Santos SA, Ravacci GR, Thomatieli-Santos RV. Effect of multi-strain probiotic supplementation on URTI symptoms and cytokine production by monocytes after a marathon race: a randomized, double-blind, placebo study. Nutrients. 2021;13(5):1478. 10.3390/nu13051478.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33925633</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR35" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tavares-Silva</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Leite</surname><given-names>GSF</given-names></name><name><surname>Batatinha</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Resende</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemos</surname><given-names>VDA</given-names></name><name><surname>Marques</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Thirty days of double-strain probiotic supplementation increases monocyte phagocytosis in marathon runners</article-title><source>Br J Nutr</source><year>2024</year><volume>132</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>298</fpage><lpage>308</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0007114524001259</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38826085</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR35" publication-type="journal">Tavares-Silva E, Leite GSF, Batatinha H, Resende A, Lemos VDA, Marques CG, et al. Thirty days of double-strain probiotic supplementation increases monocyte phagocytosis in marathon runners. Br J Nutr. 2024;132(3):298&#x02013;308. 10.1017/S0007114524001259.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38826085</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR36" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vaisberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Paix&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Almeida</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Daily intake of fermented milk containing lactobacillus casei Shirota (Lcs) modulates systemic and upper airways immune/inflammatory responses in marathon runners</article-title><source>Nutrients</source><year>2019</year><volume>11</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1678</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/nu11071678</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31336570</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR36" publication-type="journal">Vaisberg M, Paix&#x000e3;o V, Almeida E, Santos J, Foster R, Rossi M, et al. Daily intake of fermented milk containing lactobacillus casei Shirota (Lcs) modulates systemic and upper airways immune/inflammatory responses in marathon runners. Nutrients. 2019;11(7):1678. 10.3390/nu11071678.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31336570</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR37" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lennon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lackie</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Miltko</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kearns</surname><given-names>ZC</given-names></name><name><surname>Paquette</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Bloomer</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Safety and efficacy of a probiotic cocktail containing <italic>P</italic>. <italic>acidilactici</italic> and <italic>L</italic>. <italic>plantarum</italic> for gastrointestinal discomfort in endurance runners: randomized double-blinded crossover clinical trial</article-title><source>Appl Physiol Nutr Metab</source><year>2024</year><volume>49</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>890</fpage><lpage>903</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/apnm-2023-0449</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38427981</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR37" publication-type="journal">Lennon S, Lackie T, Miltko A, Kearns ZC, Paquette MR, Bloomer RJ, et al. Safety and efficacy of a probiotic cocktail containing <italic>P</italic>. <italic>acidilactici</italic> and <italic>L</italic>. <italic>plantarum</italic> for gastrointestinal discomfort in endurance runners: randomized double-blinded crossover clinical trial. Appl Physiol Nutr Metab. 2024;49(7):890&#x02013;903. 10.1139/apnm-2023-0449.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38427981</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR38" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Engel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mortensen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wellejus</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vera-Jimenez</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Struve</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Brummer</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Safety of Bifidobacterium breve, Bif195, employing a human exercise-induced intestinal permeability model: a randomised, double-blinded, placebo-controlled, parallel group trial</article-title><source>BM</source><year>2022</year><volume>13</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>243</fpage><lpage>252</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3920/BM2021.0173</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR38" publication-type="journal">Engel S, Mortensen B, Wellejus A, Vera-Jimenez N, Struve C, Brummer RJ, et al. Safety of Bifidobacterium breve, Bif195, employing a human exercise-induced intestinal permeability model: a randomised, double-blinded, placebo-controlled, parallel group trial. BM. 2022;13(3):243&#x02013;52. 10.3920/BM2021.0173.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR39" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Faghfouri</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Afrakoti</surname><given-names>LGMP</given-names></name><name><surname>Kavyani</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Nogourani</surname><given-names>ZS</given-names></name><name><surname>Musazadeh</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Jafarlou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dehghan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of probiotic supplementation in inflammatory biomarkers in adults: an umbrella meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials</article-title><source>Inflammopharmacology</source><year>2023</year><volume>31</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>2253</fpage><lpage>2268</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10787-023-01332-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37698776</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR39" publication-type="journal">Faghfouri AH, Afrakoti LGMP, Kavyani Z, Nogourani ZS, Musazadeh V, Jafarlou M, Dehghan P. The role of probiotic supplementation in inflammatory biomarkers in adults: an umbrella meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials. Inflammopharmacology. 2023;31(5):2253&#x02013;68. 10.1007/s10787-023-01332-8.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37698776</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR40" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Milajerdi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mousavi</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sadeghi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Salari-Moghaddam</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Parohan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Larijani</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Esmaillzadeh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of probiotics on inflammatory biomarkers: A meta-analysis of randomized clinical trials</article-title><source>Eur J Nutr</source><year>2020</year><volume>59</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>633</fpage><lpage>649</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00394-019-01931-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30854594</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR40" publication-type="journal">Milajerdi A, Mousavi SM, Sadeghi A, Salari-Moghaddam A, Parohan M, Larijani B, Esmaillzadeh A. The effect of probiotics on inflammatory biomarkers: A meta-analysis of randomized clinical trials. Eur J Nutr. 2020;59(2):633&#x02013;49. 10.1007/s00394-019-01931-8.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30854594</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR41" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kepes</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Cortina</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessing publication bias: a 7-step user&#x02019;s guide with best-practice recommendations</article-title><source>J Bus Psychol</source><year>2023</year><volume>38</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>957</fpage><lpage>982</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10869-022-09840-0</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR41" publication-type="journal">Kepes S, Wang W, Cortina JM. Assessing publication bias: a 7-step user&#x02019;s guide with best-practice recommendations. J Bus Psychol. 2023;38(5):957&#x02013;82. 10.1007/s10869-022-09840-0.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR42" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>P&#x000e9;rez-Castillo</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rueda</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouzamondo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Aparicio-Pascual</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Vali&#x000f1;o-Marques</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x000f3;pez-Chicharro</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Segura-Ortiz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Does lifelong exercise counteract low-grade inflammation associated with aging? A systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Sports Med</source><year>2025</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40279-024-02152-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39792347</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR42" publication-type="journal">P&#x000e9;rez-Castillo IM, Rueda R, Bouzamondo H, Aparicio-Pascual D, Vali&#x000f1;o-Marques A, L&#x000f3;pez-Chicharro J, Segura-Ortiz F. Does lifelong exercise counteract low-grade inflammation associated with aging? A systematic review and meta-analysis. Sports Med. 2025. 10.1007/s40279-024-02152-8.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39792347</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR43" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saraiva</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vieira</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Garra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biology and therapeutic potential of interleukin-10</article-title><source>J Exp Med</source><year>2020</year><volume>217</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>e20190418</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.20190418</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31611251</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR43" publication-type="journal">Saraiva M, Vieira P, O&#x02019;Garra A. Biology and therapeutic potential of interleukin-10. J Exp Med. 2020;217(1): e20190418. 10.1084/jem.20190418.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31611251</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR44" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wittouck</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Salvetti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Franz</surname><given-names>CMAP</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>HMB</given-names></name><name><surname>Mattarelli</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A taxonomic note on the genus Lactobacillus: description of 23 novel genera, emended description of the genus Lactobacillus Beijerinck 1901, and union of Lactobacillaceae and Leuconostocaceae</article-title><source>Int J Syst Evol Microbiol</source><year>2020</year><volume>70</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>2782</fpage><lpage>2858</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/ijsem.0.004107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32293557</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR44" publication-type="journal">Zheng J, Wittouck S, Salvetti E, Franz CMAP, Harris HMB, Mattarelli P, et al. A taxonomic note on the genus Lactobacillus: description of 23 novel genera, emended description of the genus Lactobacillus Beijerinck 1901, and union of Lactobacillaceae and Leuconostocaceae. Int J Syst Evol Microbiol. 2020;70(4):2782&#x02013;858. 10.1099/ijsem.0.004107.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32293557</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article>