<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="review-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mol Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Mol Med</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Molecular Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1076-1551</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1528-3658</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40410732</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12101010</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1268</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s10020-025-01268-5</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Review</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Regulation of placental development and function by ubiquitination</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Xue</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Xiaoqing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Shanshan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>Zhiju</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>An</surname><given-names>Zihao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Qiang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Bin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Yanhua</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Chao</given-names></name><address><email>chtang@zju.edu.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/025fyfd20</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411360.1</institution-id><institution>National Clinical Research Center for Child Health, Children&#x02019;s Hospital Zhejiang University School of Medicine, </institution></institution-wrap>Hangzhou, China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/013q1eq08</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.8547.e</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0125 2443</institution-id><institution>Institute of Developmental Biology and Molecular Medicine, </institution><institution>Fudan University, </institution></institution-wrap>Shanghai, China </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/02afcvw97</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.260483.b</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9530 8833</institution-id><institution>Department of Pathophysiology, </institution><institution>Medical School of Nantong University, </institution></institution-wrap>Nantong, 226001 China </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/0220qvk04</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.16821.3c</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0368 8293</institution-id><institution>Xinhua Hospital Affiliated to Shanghai JiaoTong University School of Medicine, </institution></institution-wrap>Shanghai, China </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/03f015z81</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.433871.a</institution-id><institution>Zhejiang Provincial Center for Disease Control and Prevention, </institution></institution-wrap>Hangzhou, China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>23</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>23</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>31</volume><elocation-id>202</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>7</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">The proper distribution of nutrients and metabolites between the mother and fetus is one important factor for successful pregnancy. As a bridge, the placenta plays a key role in sensing the nutritional needs of the fetus, coordinating the maternal nutrition supply, and enhancing its nutritional transport capabilities. Imperfect placental development can lead to pregnancy-related disorders such as preeclampsia, recurrent miscarriage, and/or fetal growth restriction, posing risks to both mother and child in the short and long term. However, current understanding of the human placenta remains as a "black box", and its developmental control mechanisms for adaptive pregnant regulation still needs to be elucidated. As one form of post-translational modification (PTM), ubiquitination plays an important role in regulating cellular functions and is regarded as a valuable drug target. Particularly, ubiquitination related to placenta development has been discovered in recent years. Placental development processes closely associated with pregnant complications, such as blastocyst implantation, syncytiotrophoblast cell differentiation, and immune barrier maintenance, have been reported to be affected by ubiquitination. However, the diagnosis and intervention of pregnancy diseases also urgently need to be improved. Thus, aiming to comprehensive summarize and further exploring the molecular mechanism, target and regulatory mechanism of pregnancy complications, we have herein reviewed genes and pathways regulating pregnancy progress and diseases and focusing on ubiquitin-related physiological process in placenta.</p><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1186/s10020-025-01268-5.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Placenta</kwd><kwd>Ubiquitination</kwd><kwd>Pregnancy diseases</kwd><kwd>Cellular functions</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Foundation for The Top-Notch Youth Talent Cultivation Project of Independent Design Project of National Clinical Research Center for Child Health</institution></funding-source><award-id>Q21A0006</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Feinstein Institute for Medical Research 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Brief introduction and backgrounds</title><p id="Par2">The placenta is a transient organ that serves as a crucial interface between the fetus and the mother, making it indispensable for maintaining the health and well-being of both parties. The formation of the human placenta comprises a series of processes, including embryo implantation, invasion, migration, proliferation, and differentiation of trophoblast cells. The outer wall of the blastocyst is made up of trophoblast cells, which form the earliest and outermost embryonic cell layer. During implantation, the blastocyst invades the endometrial stroma and causes decidualization of the endometrium. At this point, the stromal cells become decidual cells that are larger in size and rich in glycogen and lipids, and surround the blastocyst. The decidua further differentiates into the decidua capsularis that covers the blastocyst, the decidua basalis that lies between the blastocyst and the muscular layer of the uterine wall, and the decidua parietalis (Gellersen and Brosens <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2014</xref>). The decidua capsularis and decidua parietalis may fuse as the uterine cavity is obliterated. Among them, the orderly arranged ectoderm, mesoderm, and endoderm cells derived from the epiblast constitute the embryonic germ layer, which has a lower degree of differentiation, has mitotic capability, and participates in the fusion of the blastoderm (Gordeev et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2024</xref>). The outer cells fuse with each other evolved into syncytiotrophoblast, playing a powerful endocrine role. Syncytiotrophoblast is also known spongio-trophoblast, as it forms spongy cavity with villus structure for absorbing the maternal tissue decomposition and transport nutrients to the fetus in its adjacent cavity. The inner has clear boundaries and is composed of a single layer of cubic cells, known as cytotrophoblast, which continuously divides and replenishes into the syncytiotrophoblast. The trophoblast gradually expands outward, eroding the decidua and remodeling the vascular, causing maternal blood to flow through the spongy cavity formed by the fusion of the trophoblast formed by the fusion of the trophoblast (Sharma et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">2016</xref>). While eroding outward, the trophoblast and its derivatives combine with the ectodermal cavity where it covers to form a local papilla that protrudes into the cavity and becomes the primitive villi. Later, the extraembryonic mesoderm grows and stretches into the primary villus, forming the secondary villus structure. Within this structure, the mesoderm differentiates into blood vessels and connective tissues as the middle layer structure, and the projections develop into villi. Finally, the trophoblast layers, which consist of both cytotrophoblast and syncytiotrophoblast, form the villous tree. When the embryo develops the allantois, it outpunches from the hindgut, contributing to the umbilical cord and bringing blood supply (Gauster et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2022</xref>). This allows the villous trophoblast cells in the allantoic contact area to continue to develop. Subsequently, the placenta progresses into the maternal and fetal compartments, which are delineated by a plentiful vascular network. The rest of the non-contact area's villi stagnate and gradually shrink, forming a smooth villous membrane. The blood vessels of the allantois stalk grow into the umbilical artery and umbilical vein (Arora and Papaioannou <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2012</xref>). The densely growing villi near the decidua basal area form chorion frondosum, which are clustered into several clusters to form cotyledons with a septum between them, and each cotyledon comprises a network of villous trees. A placenta has 10&#x02013;20 villous lobes, together these form a series of 30&#x02013;50 complex three-dimensional villous trees, each centered over the opening of a maternal spiral artery and representing an individual maternal&#x02013;fetal exchange unit (Jin, et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2022</xref>). The normal architecture and elaboration of the villous trees plays a pivotal role across gestation, and villous mal-development plays a critical role in pathological pregnancies.</p><p id="Par3">Ubiquitination refers to the process by which ubiquitin, a small molecule (8.5 kDa) composed of 76 amino acids (Chau et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">1989</xref>), acts as an enzyme to select target proteins from intracellular proteins and specifically modify and dispose of them. Ubiquitin is widely present in all eukaryotic cells, and its sequence is highly conserved, with only three amino acids differences from yeast to humans. It is process of a covalent binding of ubiquitin to target and degrading proteins via catalysis of E1 Ubiquitin-activating enzyme, E2 Ubiquitin-conjugating enzymes, and E3 Ubiquitin-ligase enzymes. Briefly, in the presence of ATP, which provides the required energy, the ubiquitin-activating enzyme E1 activates the ubiquitin molecule; Afterwards, the ubiquitin-activating enzyme E1 transfers the activated ubiquitin molecule to the ubiquitin-binding enzyme E2; Finally, ubiquitin ligase E3 attaches the E2-bound ubiquitin to target proteins (Millar et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">2019</xref>), thereby intervening and affecting the fate of the target proteins and regulating intracellular signaling responses. Ubiquitination not only participates in the regulation of protein quantity, but also plays a crucial regulatory role in protein activity, protein&#x02013;protein interactions, and protein subcellular localization through different lengths of ubiquitin chains (single ubiquitination, multiple ubiquitination, and poly-ubiquitination) and various types of ubiquitin chains (linked through Met1, Lys6, Lys11, Lys27, Lys29, Lys33, Lys48, and Lys63) (Chen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2021a</xref>). Due to its diversity and multivalency, ubiquitination is widely involved in various physiological processes, including cell proliferation, apoptosis, autophagy, endocytosis, DNA damage repair, and immune response. And 80&#x02013;90% of the proteins in the cell are degraded through the ubiquitin pathway (Pickart and Fushman <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">2004</xref>). The classical ubiquitin-controlled protein degradation process involves K48 ubiquitin chain labeling and proteasome (primarily 26S proteasome) specifically recognizing and degrading K48 ubiquitin chain labeling. This degradation system is called the ubiquitin&#x02013;proteasome system (UPS), which also plays important role in kinds of gestational disorders.</p><p id="Par4">Recent studies have shown that ubiquitination plays a crucial role in placental development, and its disruption may contribute to pregnancy-related disorders. For instance, the classical ubiquitination protein degradation process involves K48 ubiquitin chain labeling and proteasome (primarily 26S proteasome) specifically recognizing and degrading K48 ubiquitin chain labeling. This degradation system, known as the ubiquitin&#x02013;proteasome system (UPS), plays a significant role in various gestational disorders (Pickart and Fushman <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">2004</xref>). Ubiquitination has important physiological significance. It not only eliminates faulty proteins, but also plays an important regulatory role in the cell growth cycle, DNA replication, and chromosome structure (Benanti <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2012</xref>; Martin-Rufo et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">2022</xref>; Feng et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2022</xref>). Therefore, they are involved in the development and progression of many diseases and are potential therapeutic targets in modern medicine. To better understand the regulation of the functional activity of the placenta, a"black box"that influences pregnancy outcomes, we have reviewed ubiquitination-related physiological processes in placenta and summarized related genes and pathways. This review aims to provide a deeper understanding of ubiquitination and its implications for maternal&#x02013;fetal health. By synthesizing emerging evidence and leveraging new technologies, we explore how ubiquitination influences placental function, offering insights that underscore the importance of this PTM in the biology of pregnancy.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Ubiquitination regulates the physiological function of placenta</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Nutrients and substances exchange related ubiquitination</title><p id="Par5">The placenta is the primary interface and the essential organ responsible for nutrient and substance exchange between the mother and fetus. The oxygen, free fatty acids, glucose, amino acids, vitamins, and electrolytes needed for fetal growth and development can be transported through the placenta into the fetal blood by simple diffusion and active transport (Jin et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2021</xref>). The placenta provides metabolic support rather than directly breaking down complex structures enzymatically for fetal nutrition. On one hand, it produces various enzymes that can decompose complex structures into simple substances, or synthesize glycogen, protein, and cholesterol from simple structures, providing nutrients for the fetus. On the other hand, fetal metabolites, such as carbon dioxide, uric acid, and urea, are also transported into the maternal blood through the placenta and are consequently eliminated from the body along with the mother&#x02019;s.</p><p id="Par6">The ubiquitination of proteins plays a key role in the aforementioned physiological processes (Summarized in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). For example, murine trophoblasts-derived exosome-enriched extracellular vesicles (ExoE-EVs) are associated with pregnancy and orchestrate physiological processes in the placenta. The ExoE-EVs facilitate intercellular communication by carrie X-chromosome miRNAs, which target ubiquitin-mediated proteolysis and are predicted to affect maternal&#x02013;fetal immune interactions and the differentiation of syncytial-like cells (Stefanski et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">2019</xref>). Sodium-coupled neutral amino acid transporter 2 (SNAT-2), a target of rapamycin (mTOR) signaling, regulates system amino acid transport. In placentas with fetal growth restriction (FGR), the ubiquitin ligase, Neural precursor cell-Expressed Developmentally Down-regulated protein 4&#x02013;2 (NEDD4-2), up-regulates the ubiquitination of SNAT2, resulting in the suppressed activity of mTORC1/2 (Chen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2015</xref>). On the other hand, epigenomic modifications, which are chemical alterations on chromosomal DNA and proteins, can regulate the exchange of metabolites in the placenta. This, in turn, can influence ubiquitination of associated proteins, ultimately impacting fetal development. For instance, SIAH3, a member of the E3 ubiquitin protein ligase family, experiences hypomethylation in placentas with elevated cadmium (Cd) levels, consequently impacting protein ubiquitination in the placenta and subsequently influencing maternal health and fetal development (Mohanty et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">2015</xref>). PKA treatment increases GCMa acetylation and protects it from ubiquitination with a concomitant increase in transcriptional activity (Chang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2005</xref>). During chronic hypoglycemia, the fetus of sheep exhibits increased rates of lysine flux and oxidative metabolism, accompanied by elevated muscle-specific ubiquitin ligases FBXO32 and RFP28, as well as greater concentrations of 4E-BP1 (Limesand et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2009</xref>), which supports the finding that hypoglycemia does not cause changes in fetal protein accumulation or synthesis.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Ubiquitination regulation related to placental function of transport, immunity and endocrine homeostasis</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Gene, PTMs, or gene family</th><th align="left">Regulate target</th><th align="left">Pathological features of placenta</th><th align="left">Species/Function</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">SNAT-2</td><td align="left">mTOR signaling regulated&#x000a0;ubiquitination</td><td align="left">Placental amino acid transport is decreased; intrauterine growth restriction</td><td align="left">Human/Transport</td></tr><tr><td align="left">X-chromosome miRNAs</td><td align="left">Predicted to target ubiquitin-mediated proteolysis and intracellular signaling pathways</td><td align="left">Carried by exsome, plays vitrol role ExoE-EVs, particularly from the X chromosome cluster</td><td align="left">Mice/Transport</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SIAH3</td><td align="left">Hypomethylated in high Cd placentas</td><td align="left">Infant sex-specific associations of placental Cd with genome-wide DNA methylation in the placenta</td><td align="left">Human/Transport</td></tr><tr><td align="left">GCMa</td><td align="left">PKA protect GCMa from ubiquitination and increases the TAD stability</td><td align="left">Regulates trophoblastic fusion</td><td align="left">Human/Transport</td></tr><tr><td align="left">FAU</td><td align="left">A gene encoding MNSF-&#x003b2;, ubiquitously expressed ubiquitin-like protein&#x000a0;interacting with RC3H1</td><td align="left">Regulates TNF&#x003b1; production in decidual macrophages; RSA</td><td align="left">Human/Immunity balance</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MAGE-A3</td><td align="left">Acts as a cellular master regulator by stimulating E3 ubiquitin ligase TRIM28</td><td align="left">Regulation of various cellular targets and&#x000a0;an attractive target for vaccine-based immune therapy</td><td align="left">Human/Immunity balance</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Pellino (Peli)1</td><td align="left">E3 Ubiquitin Protein Ligase 1, which mediated cytokine and chemokine responses and</td><td align="left">Induced cell death in placental trophoblasts and human neural stem cells</td><td align="left">Mice/Immunity balance</td></tr><tr><td align="left">UHRF1</td><td align="left">Mediate histone ubiquitination,&#x000a0;and activating the MyD88/NF-&#x003ba;B signaling pathway</td><td align="left">Increasing the CXCL2/IL-1&#x003b2; in the trophoblasts, promoting the polarization of decidual macrophage differentiation to M1 phenotype; RSA</td><td align="left">Human, Mice/Immunity balance</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ISG15</td><td align="left">Functional ubiquitin homologue gene</td><td align="left">Regulated by mononucleate cells and IFNT and affect endometrial stroma; Implantation failure</td><td align="left">Sheep/Immunity balance</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SOX4</td><td align="left">SOX4-PGR-HERC4 axis mediated degradation</td><td align="left">Regulated WNT5 A, WNT4, IL-11, BMP2, and so on; human endometrial decidualization; Implatation failure</td><td align="left">Human/Endocrine homeostasis</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><p>phospho-CREB</p><p>(p-CREB)</p></td><td align="left">Interacts with p-CREB to prevent its ubiquitination via FOXO1</td><td align="left">Aldosterone biosynthesized in endometrial gland during mid-secretory phase promotes decidualization</td><td align="left">Human/Endocrine homeostasis</td></tr><tr><td align="left">RGS2</td><td align="left">Suppressing USP14 mediated deubiquitination of HAND1</td><td align="left">Estradiol was increased by regulated HAND1; Pre-eclampsia</td><td align="left">Human/Endocrine homeostasis</td></tr><tr><td align="left">BAP1</td><td align="left">BAP1/ASXL complex; form the polycomb repressive deubiquitinase (PR-DUB) complex</td><td align="left">EMT progression; early placentation</td><td align="left">Human/Endocrine homeostasis</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Immune defense function related ubiquitination</title><p id="Par7">The placental barrier separates fetal blood from maternal blood to avoid or reduce the impact of harmful factors on the fetus. The defensive function of the placenta can prevent macromolecules in the maternal blood from entering the fetal blood circulation. On one hand, since the second trimester, immunoglobulin G (IgG) antibodies contained in the maternal blood increased, through term, most antibodies being acquired during the third trimester through the placenta (Simister <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">2003</xref>). On the other hand, it prevents large molecules such as bacteria and pathogens in the maternal blood from penetrating the placenta directly into the fetal blood circulation (Brett et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2014</xref>). However, certain pathogens may cross the placenta in cases of placental barrier damage or infection (Chenge, et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2023</xref>). Additionally, the placenta's ability to resist barbiturates (Browne et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2014</xref>), morphine (Lyu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">2024</xref>), and various foreign viruses such as toxoplasma gondii (Hubal et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2025</xref>) and mycoplasma (Pan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">2025</xref>) is delicate.</p><p id="Par8">Many proteins are ubiquitinated to participate in immune response, triggering and/or assisting in the normal function of placenta protection (Goor et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97">2020</xref>) (See Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). For example, the expression of monoclonal nonspecific suppressor factor-&#x003b2; (MNSF-&#x003b2;), a ubiquitously expressed ubiquitin-like protein, is significantly increased in decidual macrophages of recurrent spontaneous abortion (RSA) patient. RSA is a pregnancy complication usually defined as three or more spontaneous abortions prior to 20&#x02013;28 weeks gestation. The etiology of RSA is complex and diverse. In addition to genetic factors, autoimmune abnormalities, thrombophilia, and endocrine factors may be the causes of RSA. The aberrantly increased MNSF&#x003b2; expression in decidual macrophages promotes TNF&#x003b1; production via its interaction with RC3H1 (Zhen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR121">2021</xref>), ultimately leading to immune dysfunction in the maternal&#x02013;fetal interface and resulting in pregnancy loss. Melanoma Associated Antigen A3 (MAGE-A3), a protein exclusively expressed in testes and placenta, has been found to stimulate E3 ubiquitin ligase Tripartite Motif-containing protein 28 (TRIM28). It regulates the cellular energy sensor AMP-activated protein kinase and has consequently been regarded as a promising target for vaccine-based immune therapy (Schafer et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">2021</xref>). Ubiquitination may also play a role in the disruption of placental function caused by infection or immune dysregulation. For instance, Pellino (Peli), an E3 ubiquitin ligase found in placental trophoblasts, mediates inflammatory cytokine and chemokine responses, as well as induce cell death, in placental trophoblasts and human Neural Stem Cells. Pregnant mice infected with the Zika virus and lacking Peli1 signaling display reduced placental inflammation and tissue damage, ultimately leading to a milder manifestation of congenital abnormalities (Luo et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">2020</xref>). Ubiquitin like with PHD and ring finger domains 1 (UHRF1) is proved to be as a key regulator on the trophoblasts and their cross-talk with local immune cells, has been demonstrated as a potential approach for RSA intervention (Liu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">2022a</xref>). Similarly, Interferon-stimulated gene 15 (ISG15) is regulated by mononucleate cells and IFNT, affecting endometrial stroma and contributing to implantation failure (Joyce et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2005</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Pathological features and ubiquitination related gene involved in embryo implantation</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Gene Name</th><th align="left">Mechanism</th><th align="left">Pathological features of placenta</th><th align="left">Species</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Sox4</td><td align="left">Repressing E3 ubiquitin ligase HERC4</td><td align="left">Dysregulated decidualization of stromal cells; Implantation failure</td><td align="left">Sheep</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SKP2</td><td align="left">A key component of the SCF-type E3 ubiquitin ligase complex</td><td align="left">Reduced in the decidual tissues and down-regulated GLUT1; RSA</td><td align="left">Human</td></tr><tr><td align="left">USP7</td><td align="left">Deubiquitinating directly interacted with the EZH2 and regulated the Wnt/&#x003b2;-catenin signaling pathway</td><td align="left">Regulate trophoblast proliferation, apoptosis, migration, and invasion; Downregulated in the placental villous tissues, RSA</td><td align="left">Human</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Smurf2</td><td align="left">An E3 ubiquitin ligase</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">Rhesus monkey endometrium</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SPOP</td><td align="left">An adapter of E3 ligases of ubiquitination</td><td align="left">Regulates endometrial stromal cell decidualization and affected by hormones</td><td align="left">Mice</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MAP3 K4</td><td align="left">Promotes HDAC6 ubiquitination and degradation</td><td align="left">Maintaining the epithelial state, deacetylating histones on epithelial gene promoters, promoting the dissolution of tight junctions; epithelial-to-mesenchymal transition</td><td align="left">Mice</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ISG15</td><td align="left">Functional ubiquitin homologue gene</td><td align="left">Regulated by mononucleate cells and IFNT and affect endometrial stroma; Implantation failure</td><td align="left">Sheep</td></tr><tr><td align="left">FAU</td><td align="left">A gene encoding MNSF-&#x003b2;, a ubiquitously expressed ubiquitin-like protein promote TNF&#x003b1; production via its interaction with RC3H1</td><td align="left">Significantly increased in decidual macrophages (dM&#x003d5;); RSA patient</td><td align="left">Human</td></tr><tr><td align="left">UHRF1</td><td align="left">Mediate histone ubiquitination,&#x000a0;and activating the MyD88/NF-&#x003ba;B signaling pathway</td><td align="left">Increasing the pro-inflammatory TH-1 type chemokine/cytokines CXCL2/IL-1&#x003b2; in the trophoblasts, promoting the polarization to M1 phenotype; RSA</td><td align="left">Human, Mice</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par9">In conclusion, the contribution of ubiquitination to the placental immune defense primarily relies on the anatomical characteristics of the decidua and the intercellular communication mechanism of immune cells. To further understand the role of ubiquitination, investigating its involvement in the following physiological processes of placental immune development is necessary. A successful pregnancy enables the embryo and fetus to develop within the uterus while keeping the mother's immune system. Uterine natural killer cells, immature dendritic cells, T cells, and macrophages contribute to creating a favorable uterine environment for a successful pregnancy (Andreescu, et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2025</xref>). By studying the role of ubiquitin in the communication and activation of immune cells, we can uncover related pathological mechanisms, thereby laying a scientific foundation for clinical diagnosis and treatment.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Endocrine homeostasis-related ubiquitination</title><p id="Par10">The placenta is an endocrine organ that secretes various hormones, cytokines, and neurotransmitters, which play an important role in maintaining normal pregnancy and regulating fetal development. In the early stages of pregnancy, human chorionic gonadotropin and prolactin secreted between the second and eighth weeks, promoting fetal growth and development while also participating in enhancing the secondary growth and development of the mother's mammary glands. In addition, the synthesis and secretion of cytokines such as epidermal growth factor, nerve growth factor, and interleukins by the placenta not only contribute to the healthy growth of the fetus, but also can play an irreplaceable role in early trophoblast cells'invasion, proliferation and differentiation of cytotrophoblast, as well as in maternal tolerance and non-rejection of the fetus through ubiquitination. As an instance, SOX4, acting as a pivotal regulator, regulates the stability of progesterone receptor (PGR) by suppressing the degradation mechanism of E3 ubiquitin ligase HERC4. Furthermore, several genes associated with secretion, fetal development, and stem cell differentiation (such as WNT5 A, WNT4, IL-11, and BMP2) have been found to be down-regulated significantly following the silencing of SOX4 (Huang, et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2022</xref>). In another case, in order to maintain early pregnancy and provide crucial nutrients and an immune environment for placental formation, the endometrium must undergo decidualization. Aldosterone biosynthesized in endometrial gland during mid-secretory phase promotes decidualization via activating MR/LKB1/p-AMPK/PDK4/p-CREB/FOXO1 signaling pathway, in which PDK4 interacts with p-CREB to prevent its ubiquitination and facilitate decidualization via FOXO1 (Li et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">2020</xref>). Ubiquitination related endocrine gene also associated to pregnancy diseases. For example, RGS2 inhibits the deubiquitination of HAND1 by ubiquitin-specific protease 14 (USP14), leading to the restoration of HAND1-induced trans-inactivation of the <italic>aromatase</italic> gene and subsequent elevations in estradiol levels, which may contribute to pre-eclampsia (Tang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">2023</xref>). Several pregnancy complications such as miscarriage, pre-eclampsia, placenta accreta, and FGR are underpinned by a primary defect in epithelial-mesenchymal transition (EMT) progression. BAP1, a catalytic subunit of a deubiquitinase complex, suppressed EMT progression dependent on the binding to additional sex comb-like (ASXL1/2) proteins to form the polycomb repressive deubiquitinase (PR-DUB) complex in mouse trophoblasts. While its dependency on additional sex comb-like (ASXL1/2) proteins binding is not directly relevant, BAP1 has been associated with pregnancy complications and its protein levels significantly down-regulated during EMT (Perez-Garcia, et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">2021</xref>).</p><p id="Par11">In conclusion, ubiquitination plays a crucial role in the network of fetal, maternal, and placental. However, despite the importance of this process, relevant research is still limited. In addition to gene functions, we were surprised to discover that metabolites, PTMs, and certain non-coding RNAs can regulate the processing of the placenta through ubiquitination. As metabolomics and epigenomics continue to advance, we anticipate that more physiological processes related to ubiquitination will be identified. Meanwhile, it should be noted that due to the differences between the human placenta and those of other organisms, the ubiquitination mechanisms may also vary. From this perspective, as research on pregnancy-related ubiquitination deepens, it can also reveal scientific theories related to species evolution, which is also very meaningful.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Ubiquitination regulated pregnancy maintenance and diseases</title><p id="Par12">Early defects and dysfunction in placental development are the primary causes of various common pregnancy-related diseases, such as recurrent miscarriage, fetal intrauterine growth restriction, preeclampsia, and preterm birth (Vishnyakova et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101">2019</xref>; Vishnyakova et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR102">2021</xref>). Mammalian placental cells are vulnerable to mitochondrial dysfunction, oxidative damage, and the buildup of cross-linked ubiquitinated proteins, which are frequent causes of placental dysfunction. The ubiquitin&#x02013;proteasome degradation pathway plays a crucial regulatory role in preserving the dynamic equilibrium of proteins and cellular function within the body. We herein have summarized the ubiquitin-related genes and mechanisms involved in the progress of pregnancy and various diseases (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>A schema chart showing the relationship between the ubiquitin-related genes and human placenta</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10020_2025_1268_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><sec id="Sec7"><title>Implantation failure</title><p id="Par13">Placental invasion is the initial step after embryo implantation, including sequential pre-contact, apposition, adhesion, invasion and penetration of the decidua, followed by the formation of chorionic villi (Ochoa-Bernal and Fazleabas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">2020</xref>). Implantation causes the secretory-phase endometrium to become thicker and more abundant for blood supply. The stromal fibroblasts further expand and accumulate glycogen, preparing to differentiate into decidual cells with specialized secretory functions (Gellersen and Brosens <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2014</xref>). During this process, differentiation of endometrial stromal cells for pregnancy present morphological and physiological changes to adapt to pregnancy. Ubiquitination plays a critical role in regulating cell differentiation and signaling pathways. Dysregulated decidualization is always associated with failure of pregnancy. Recent evidence has shown that dysregulated SOX4-HERC4-PGR axis is a potential cause of defective decidualization and recurrent implantation failure in in vitro fertilization patients (Huang, et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2022</xref>). The F-box protein S-phase kinase associated protein 2 (SKP2) is a key component of the SCF-type E3 ubiquitin ligase complex, which is significantly reduced in the decidual tissues of RSA patients and suppresses the expression of its downstream target, GLUT1 (Lv et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">2021</xref>). The expression of SPOP, an adapter of E3 ligases of ubiquitination, in mouse uteri during early pregnancy could be controlled by hormones and regulates endometrial stromal cell decidualization, indicating the role of ubiquitination in embryonic implantation.</p><p id="Par14">Trophoblasts are placental stem cells and play crucial roles in maternal&#x02013;fetal crosstalk. The first developmental EMT occurs in trophoblast cells during implantation, where epithelial trophoblast cells in the trophectoderm transition into invasive giant cells (Thiery et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93">2009</xref>). Adequate trophoblast migration and invasion are essential for successful placental development and implantation (Vento-Tormo et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98">2018</xref>). The expression of ubiquitin-specific protease 7 (USP7), a member of the deubiquitinating enzyme family, is downregulated in the placental villous tissues of RSA patients. Recent studies have revealed that USP7-related deubiquitination directly interacts with the enhancer of zeste homolog 2 (EZH2) and regulates trophoblast proliferation, apoptosis, migration, and invasion through the Wnt/&#x003b2;-catenin signaling pathway in trophoblasts in the maternal&#x02013;fetal interface (Zhou et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR122">2023</xref>; Yang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR112">2007</xref>). Smad ubiquitin regulatory factor 2 (Smurf2) is an E3 ubiquitin ligase that triggers the ubiquitin-dependent degradation of the SMAD7-mediated transforming growth factor beta (TGF-beta) receptor (Kavsak et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">2000</xref>). In hesus monkey endometrium and placenta, Smurf2 may play specific roles in glandular secretion, trophoblastic cell invasion, and placentation through TGF-beta signaling pathway during early pregnancy (Yang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR112">2007</xref>). Importantly, the first epithelial-to-mesenchymal transition (EMT) occurs in trophoblast stem cells during implantation. Mobley et al<italic>.</italic> find that HDAC6 is regulated by MAP3 K4 during trophoblast stem cell differentiation and EMT. They prove that MAP3 K4 promotes HDAC6 ubiquitination and degradation, maintaining the epithelial state, and HDAC6 directly deacetylates histones on epithelial gene promoters such as <italic>claudin6</italic> and <italic>occludin</italic>, promoting the dissolution of tight junctions (Mobley et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">2017</xref>). Ubiquitination of immune cells also plays critical roles in implantation. For example, interferon stimulated gene 15 (ISG15) is a ubiquitin-like protein whose expression and conjugation to targets (ISGylation) is induced by multiple factors such as infection, DNA damage, and ischemia. ISG15 conjugation/ISGylation in decidua is involved in one or more of physiological function of decidual. The mononuclear cells of the trophectoderm secrete IFNT, which can stimulate the expression of functional ubiquitin homologue gene <italic>ISG15</italic> in the endometrial stroma of sheep (Joyce et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2005</xref>). The disruption of aforementioned MNSF-&#x003b2; and UHRF1 related to the immune balance also contribute to implantation failure and pregnancy loss (Zhen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR121">2021</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Vascularization of the placenta and eclampsia or preeclampsia</title><p id="Par15">Vascularization of the placenta is a critical developmental process that ensures fetal viability. Preeclampsia (PE) is a complication of pregnancy that occurs after 20 weeks of gestation and is highly related to placental vascularization. PE patients exhibit symptoms of high blood pressure, high levels of protein in urine that indicate kidney damage (proteinuria), or other signs of organ damage. In severe cases, PE can progress to eclampsia, accompanied by convulsions, posing a threat to the lives of both the mother and the fetus. Most ubiquitylation studies on the pathogenesis of PE or eclamptic placenta and ubiquitination have been reported (Summarized in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). The ubiquitin ligase Ankyrin repeat SOCS box-containing 4 (ASB4) promotes embryonic stem cell differentiation to vascular lineages and is highly expressed early in placental development. The transcriptional regulator inhibitor of DNA binding 2 (ID2) negatively regulates vascular differentiation during development and is a target of many ubiquitin ligases. ASB4 mediates vascular differentiation in the placenta by degrading ID2, and deletion of <italic>Asb4</italic> in mice induces a pathology that phenocopies human pre-eclampsia, including hypertension and proteinuria (Townley-Tilson et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">2014</xref>). The Cullin 4-RING E3 ubiquitin ligase (CRL4) complex ubiquitinates and degrades substrates, while DDB1 and CUL4-associated factor 13 (DCAF13) is a component and substrate receptor of this complex, which recognizes and recruits the complex different substrates. The DCAF13 levels in the decidua of PE patients are significantly lower than that of normal pregnant women, and <italic>Dcaf13</italic> knockout mice fails to undergo decidualization (Yan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR111">2022</xref>). USP5 is lowly expressed in the placentas of PE patients as well as in hypoxia/reoxygenation-induced trophoblast cells. USP5 promotes the proliferation of trophoblast cells via activating Wnt/&#x003b2;-catenin signaling pathway (Zhang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR118">2021</xref>), and the downstream signals, such as c-Myc and Cyclin D1. A more recent report shows that RGS2 contributes to PE via USP14/HAND1-regulated estradiol biosynthesis (Tang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">2023</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Ubiquitination related gene involved in pregnant diseases</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Gene, gene family, or protein complex</th><th align="left">Mechanism</th><th align="left">Pathological features of placenta</th><th align="left">Species/Disorder</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">ASB4</td><td align="left">Activate ubiquitin ligases and degradation of ID2 (negative vascular differentiation)</td><td align="left">Promoted embryonic stem cell differentiation to vascular lineages and highly expressed during early placental development</td><td align="left">Mice/PE</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CRL4</td><td align="left">E3 ubiquitin ligase</td><td align="left">DDB1 and CUL4-associated factor 13 (DCAF13) complex levels in the decidua of PE patients is significantly lower; knocking-out of DCAF13 causese decidualization falure</td><td align="left">Human;Mice/PE</td></tr><tr><td align="left">USP5</td><td align="left">A deubiquitinase</td><td align="left">Lowly expressed in the placentas of PE patients as well as in hypoxia/reoxygenation-induced trophoblast cells</td><td align="left">Human/PEa</td></tr><tr><td align="left">RGS2</td><td align="left">Suppressing USP14 mediated deubiquitination of HAND1</td><td align="left">Estradiol was increased by regulated HAND1; Pre-eclampsia</td><td align="left">Human/PE</td></tr><tr><td align="left">miR-135a-5p</td><td align="left">Target E3 ubiquitin protein ligase &#x003b2;-TrCP</td><td align="left">Regulates EMT of trophoblast cells</td><td align="left">Human/PE</td></tr><tr><td align="left">X-chromosome miRNAs</td><td align="left">Predicted to target ubiquitin-mediated proteolysis and intracellular signaling pathways</td><td align="left">Carried by exsome, plays vitrol role ExoE-EVs, particularly from the X chromosome cluster</td><td align="left">Mice/PE</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SNAT-2</td><td align="left">mTOR signaling regulated&#x000a0;ubiquitination</td><td align="left">Placental amino acid transport is decreased; intrauterine growth restriction</td><td align="left">Human/PE</td></tr><tr><td align="left">A20</td><td align="left">A ubiquitin modifying enzyme</td><td align="left">IUGR can reduce the expression of A20 protein in lung tissue of newborn rats</td><td align="left">Mice/IUGR</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CUL7</td><td align="left">Participating ubiquitin&#x02013;proteasome system</td><td align="left">Up-regulated up to 10 times in IUGR and 15 times in preeclampsia associated with IUGR</td><td align="left">Human/IUGR&#x00026;PE</td></tr><tr><td align="left">UBE variants</td><td align="left">The ubiquitin-conjugating enzymes</td><td align="left">Differentially expressed and associated with GDM</td><td align="left">Human/GDM</td></tr><tr><td align="left">UBE2E2</td><td align="left">The ubiquitin-conjugating enzymes</td><td align="left">UBE2E2 single-nucleotide polymorphisms rs7612463 showed a significant association with GDM</td><td align="left">Human/GDM</td></tr><tr><td align="left">G&#x003b2;L</td><td align="left">A ubiquitination-dependent mammalian target of rapamycin</td><td align="left">Maternal hyperglycemia inhibits pulmonary vasculogenesis during fetal lung development by promoting G&#x003b2;L-ubiquitination-dependent mTORC1 assembly</td><td align="left">Mice/GDM</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par16">MicroRNAs can also regulate the ubiquitination in placenta and thus contributes to PE. For example, miR-135a-5p is targeted and regulated by &#x003b2;-transducin repeat containing E3 ubiquitin protein ligase (&#x003b2;-TrCP) in the placental of PE patients (Wu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR108">2020</xref>). In molecular biological experiments, down-regulated E-cadherin levels and increased N-cadherin, Vimentin, and &#x003b2;-catenin levels that are induced by miR-135a-5p overexpression are attenuated by &#x003b2;-TrCP overexpression. In addition, X-chromosome miRNAs carried by ExoE-EVs are predicted to target ubiquitin-mediated proteolysis and intracellular signaling pathways (Stefanski et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">2019</xref>), however, their functions and the correlation with PE remain to be studied.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Other pregnant diseases</title><p id="Par17">Some other common pregnancy complications have also been reported to be related to ubiquitination. Intrauterine growth restriction (IUGR), also known as FGR as previously mentioned, is when the fetal weight is estimated to be below the 10 th percentile for its gestational age. The pathogenesis of IUGR is complex, with most patients experiencing placental hypoperfusion and hypoplasia, which are closely linked to ubiquitination. For example, the activity of mTORC1 and mTORC2 is decreased whereas the protein expression of the ubiquitin ligase NEDD4-2 (+ 72%, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c; 0.0001) and the ubiquitination of SNAT-2 (+ 180%, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c; 0.05) are increased in homogenates of FGR placentas (Gascoin-Lachambre et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2010</xref>). Cullins constitute a family of seven proteins involved in cell scaffold and in selective proteolysis via the ubiquitin&#x02013;proteasome system, the <italic>CUL7</italic> gene is up-regulated up to 10 times in FGR and 15 times in preeclampsia associated with FGR (Bari et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2016</xref>). Gestational diabetes mellitus (GDM) is a condition in which a hormone made by the placenta prevents the body from using insulin effectively. Glucose builds up in the blood instead of being absorbed by the cells. A transcriptomic profiling analysis of trophoblast isolated from gestational diabetes mellitus (GDM) defined 8 ubiquitin-conjugating enzymes (UBE) splice variants (UBE2D3 variants 1, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 9 and UBE2V1 variant 4) are associated with increased maternal fasting plasma glucose (Kim et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">2013</xref>). In another research, the genetic variants of ubiquitin-conjugating enzyme UBE2E2 are also reported to be associated with GDM (Xu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR110">2023</xref>). Ubiquitination may also trigger other complications from pregnancy disorders. For example, the decreased ubiquitin modifying enzyme A20 is associated with hyper-responsiveness to ovalbumin challenge following FGR (Luo et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">2023</xref>). The maternal hyperglycemia inhibits pulmonary vasculogenesis during mouse fetal lung development by promoting G protein beta subunit-like protein (G&#x003b2;L) ubiquitination-dependent mammalian target of rapamycin assembly (Gascoin-Lachambre et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2010</xref>). With the advancement of omics technology, an increasing number of ubiquitination mechanisms associated with pregnancy complications will be discovered, holding great promise for the development of therapeutic approaches for these diseases.</p><p id="Par18">Our review summarizes many ubiquitination processes related to pregnancy complications, potentially providing new insights for drug development. The placenta is a complex tissue composed of various cells and structures, making it a crucial component. Therefore, studying the ubiquitination processes on the development of a specific group of cells during a particular period by utilizing spatial omics methods may provide more insight in to explanation of diseases. In addition, The ubiquitin mechanism can be harnessed for targeted protein degradation techniques, such as molecular glue (Schreiber <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">2021</xref>) and proteolysis-targeting chimeras (Yang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR113">2019</xref>), which are key focuses in the pharmaceutical industry.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Identification of ubiquitination-associated protein regulation in gestational disorders by Mendelian randomization analysis</title><p id="Par19">To additionally figure out the ubiquitination-associated protein regulation in gestational disorders, we carried out the Mendelian randomization analysis by using database when ubiquitination related plasma proteins as outcome and pregnant diseases as exposure. 85 ubiquitination related plasma proteins were screened (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>), which were used as expose factors in subsequent Mendelian randomization analysis. Four major pregnancy related diseases from a Finnish database were set as outcomes to explore the potential ubiquitination related molecular mechanisms of action in perinatal diseases. The specific information and download links for the outcomes can be found in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>. The positive results obtained from the screening were presented in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref>, and the corresponding single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) used for the exposure factors in the positive results are summarized in Table S1.<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Information regarding the ubiquitination related plasma proteins utilized as exposures in Mendelian randomization analysis</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Expose data (Seq id)</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">Protein name</th><th align="left" colspan="5">Paticipated pathway related to ubiquitination</th></tr><tr><th align="left"><bold>Deubiquitination</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Ub-specific processing proteases</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Protein ubiquitination</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Ubiquitination Cascade</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Regulation of FZD by ubiquitination</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">16825_20</td><td align="left">ATXN3</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">12925_105</td><td align="left">AXIN2</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">13977_28</td><td align="left">BARD1</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">13032_1</td><td align="left">BECN1</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">10046_55</td><td align="left">BIRC2</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">15319_226</td><td align="left">CCNA1</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">15574_37</td><td align="left">CCNA2</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">13089_6</td><td align="left">HIF1 A</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">3197_70</td><td align="left">IDE</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">12551_3</td><td align="left">ITCH</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">16304_6</td><td align="left">LGR4</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">16296_43</td><td align="left">LGR5</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">18392_19</td><td align="left">MAT2B</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">13228_75</td><td align="left">MDM2</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">13229_20</td><td align="left">MDM4</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">9315_16</td><td align="left">MUL1</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">11536_9</td><td align="left">MYSM1</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">12493_42</td><td align="left">OTUB2</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">12480_9</td><td align="left">OTUD5</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">19364_163</td><td align="left">PCNA</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">8300_82</td><td align="left">PEX14</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">7880_9</td><td align="left">PSMA1</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">4280_47</td><td align="left">PSMA2</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">18925_24</td><td align="left">PSMA5</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">12460_18</td><td align="left">PSMA7</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">12612_37</td><td align="left">PSMB1</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">18339_207</td><td align="left">PSMB3</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">18340_2</td><td align="left">PSMB4</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">12580_7</td><td align="left">PSMB5</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">10530_8</td><td align="left">PSMB6</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">18942_11</td><td align="left">PSMB9</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">18385_4</td><td align="left">PSMD10</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">13572_43</td><td align="left">PSMD11</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">13568_30</td><td align="left">PSMD4</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">10716_35</td><td align="left">PSMD5</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">3898_5</td><td align="left">PSMD7</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">5918_5</td><td align="left">PSME1</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">17694_32</td><td align="left">PSME2</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">16887_29</td><td align="left">PTRH2</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">12522_6</td><td align="left">RAD23B</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">8970_9</td><td align="left">RIPK2</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">6510_56</td><td align="left">RNF128</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">11401_181</td><td align="left">RNF146</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">14120_2</td><td align="left">RNF43</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">16614_27</td><td align="left">RSPO1</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">8409_3</td><td align="left">RSPO2</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">13094_75</td><td align="left">RSPO3</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">8464_31</td><td align="left">RSPO4</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">9838_4</td><td align="left">SMAD1</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">10364_6</td><td align="left">SMAD2</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">10363_13</td><td align="left">SMAD3</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">12022_12</td><td align="left">SMAD4</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">13985_12</td><td align="left">SMURF2</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">19187_21</td><td align="left">STAMBP</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">12401_3</td><td align="left">STAMBPL1</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">11350_30</td><td align="left">STUB1</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">10703_203</td><td align="left">SUDS3</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">18270_10</td><td align="left">TAF10</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">2333_72</td><td align="left">TGFB1</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">5133_17</td><td align="left">TGFBR2</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">14009_65</td><td align="left">TNFAIP3</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">9907_216</td><td align="left">TNKS</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">6123_69</td><td align="left">TP53</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">6651_74</td><td align="left">UBB</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">17743_14</td><td align="left">UBE2A</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">9865_40</td><td align="left">UBE2B</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">12556_7</td><td align="left">UBE2C</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">19247_1</td><td align="left">UBE2D1</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">18842_24</td><td align="left">UBE2D2</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">19280_29</td><td align="left">UBE2D3</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">14326_4</td><td align="left">UBE2E1</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">18213_30</td><td align="left">UBE2F</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">9199_6</td><td align="left">UBE2G2</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">3874_8</td><td align="left">UBE2L3</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">19190_4</td><td align="left">UBE2L6</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">19111_10</td><td align="left">UBE2M</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">12400_25</td><td align="left">UBE2T</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">11226_16</td><td align="left">UBE3 A</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">5019_16</td><td align="left">UCHL1</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">19161_1</td><td align="left">USP15</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">12681_63</td><td align="left">USP21</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">9215_117</td><td align="left">USP25</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">13450_49</td><td align="left">USP8</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">13236_25</td><td align="left">WNT3 A</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">14122_132</td><td align="left">ZNRF3</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x026ab;</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Information regarding the pregnant diseases utilized as outcomes in Mendelian randomization analysis</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">GWAS id</th><th align="left">Pregnant disease</th><th align="left">Number of cases</th><th align="left">Number of controls</th><th align="left">Download linkage</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">finn-b-O15_PRE_OR_ECLAMPSIA</td><td align="left">Pre-eclampsia (PE)</td><td align="left">8818</td><td align="left">234034</td><td align="left"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://storage.googleapis.com/finngen-public-data-r11/summary_stats/finngen_R11_O15_PRE_OR_ECLAMPSIA.gz">https://storage.googleapis.com/finngen-public-data-r11/summary_stats/finngen_R11_O15_PRE_OR_ECLAMPSIA.gz</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td align="left">finn-b-GEST_DIABETES</td><td align="left">Gestational diabetes mellitus (GDM)</td><td align="left">16802</td><td align="left">237816</td><td align="left"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://storage.googleapis.com/finngen-public-data-r11/summary_stats/finngen_R11_GEST_DIABETES.gz">https://storage.googleapis.com/finngen-public-data-r11/summary_stats/finngen_R11_GEST_DIABETES.gz</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td align="left">finn-b-O15_POOR_FETGRO</td><td align="left">Fetal growth restriction (FGR)</td><td align="left">4617</td><td align="left">250001</td><td align="left"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://storage.googleapis.com/finngen-public-data-r11/summary_stats/finngen_R11_O15_POOR_FETGRO.gz">https://storage.googleapis.com/finngen-public-data-r11/summary_stats/finngen_R11_O15_POOR_FETGRO.gz</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td align="left">finn-b-O15_PRETERM</td><td align="left">Preterm birth (PTB)</td><td align="left">10350</td><td align="left">194563</td><td align="left"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://storage.googleapis.com/finngen-public-data-r11/summary_stats/finngen_R11_O15_PRETERM.gz">https://storage.googleapis.com/finngen-public-data-r11/summary_stats/finngen_R11_O15_PRETERM.gz</ext-link></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab6"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Mendelian randomization estimates of the effect of ubiquitination related plasma proteins on pregnant diseases</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Expose/Plasma protein</th><th align="left">Indexs</th><th align="left">Analyze methods</th><th align="left">P or <underline>Q</underline> valuse</th><th align="left">Outcome/Pregnant disease</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="9">ATXN3</td><td align="left" rowspan="5">Mendelian Randomization result</td><td align="left">MR Egger</td><td align="left">0.271</td><td align="left" rowspan="9">GDM</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Weighted median</td><td align="left">0.042</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Inverse variance weighted</td><td align="left">0.027</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Simple mode</td><td align="left">0.383</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Weighted mode</td><td align="left">0.122</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Heterogeneity tests</td><td align="left">MR Egger</td><td align="left">0.649</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Inverse variance weighted</td><td align="left">0.798</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Horizontal Pleiotropy</td><td align="left">MR-Egger regression intercept</td><td align="left">0.907</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MR-PRESSO global test</td><td align="left">0.904</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="9">BARD1</td><td align="left" rowspan="5">Mendelian Randomization result</td><td align="left">MR Egger</td><td align="left">0.950</td><td align="left" rowspan="9">GDM</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Weighted median</td><td align="left">0.258</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Inverse variance weighted</td><td align="left">0.035</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Simple mode</td><td align="left">0.148</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Weighted mode</td><td align="left">0.583</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Heterogeneity tests</td><td align="left">MR Egger</td><td align="left">0.072</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Inverse variance weighted</td><td align="left">0.136</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Horizontal Pleiotropy</td><td align="left">MR Egger regression intercept</td><td align="left">0.773</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MR-PRESSO global test</td><td align="left">0.296</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="9">CCNA2</td><td align="left" rowspan="5">Mendelian Randomization result</td><td align="left">MR Egger</td><td align="left">0.680</td><td align="left" rowspan="9">FGR</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Weighted median</td><td align="left">0.071</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Inverse variance weighted</td><td align="left">0.042</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Simple mode</td><td align="left">0.307</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Weighted mode</td><td align="left">0.256</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Heterogeneity tests</td><td align="left">MR Egger</td><td align="left">0.755</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Inverse variance weighted</td><td align="left">0.946</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Horizontal Pleiotropy</td><td align="left">MR Egger regression intercept</td><td align="left">0.927</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MR-PRESSO global test</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="9">MDM4</td><td align="left" rowspan="5">Mendelian Randomization result</td><td align="left">MR Egger</td><td align="left">0.799</td><td align="left" rowspan="9">PTB</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Weighted median</td><td align="left">0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Inverse variance weighted</td><td align="left">0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Simple mode</td><td align="left">0.093</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Weighted mode</td><td align="left">0.083</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Heterogeneity tests</td><td align="left">MR Egger</td><td align="left">0.846</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Inverse variance weighted</td><td align="left">0.980</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Horizontal Pleiotropy</td><td align="left">MR Egger regression intercept</td><td align="left">0.973</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MR-PRESSO global test</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="9">PSMA7</td><td align="left" rowspan="5">Mendelian Randomization result</td><td align="left">MR Egger</td><td align="left">0.206</td><td align="left" rowspan="9">FGR</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Weighted median</td><td align="left">0.027</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Inverse variance weighted</td><td align="left">0.035</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Simple mode</td><td align="left">0.173</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Weighted mode</td><td align="left">0.109</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Heterogeneity tests</td><td align="left">MR Egger</td><td align="left">0.673</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Inverse variance weighted</td><td align="left">0.718</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Horizontal Pleiotropy</td><td align="left">MR Egger regression intercept</td><td align="left">0.503</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MR-PRESSO global test</td><td align="left">0.781</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="9">PSMB6</td><td align="left" rowspan="5">Mendelian Randomization result</td><td align="left">MR Egger</td><td align="left">0.818</td><td align="left" rowspan="9">PE</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Weighted median</td><td align="left">0.106</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Inverse variance weighted</td><td align="left">0.049</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Simple mode</td><td align="left">0.339</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Weighted mode</td><td align="left">0.255</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Heterogeneity tests</td><td align="left">MR Egger</td><td align="left">0.736</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Inverse variance weighted</td><td align="left">0.855</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Horizontal Pleiotropy</td><td align="left">MR Egger regression intercept</td><td align="left">0.732</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MR-PRESSO global test</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="9">RSPO1</td><td align="left" rowspan="5">Mendelian Randomization result</td><td align="left">MR Egger</td><td align="left">0.097</td><td align="left" rowspan="9">GDM</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Weighted median</td><td align="left">0.012</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Inverse variance weighted</td><td align="left">0.047</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Simple mode</td><td align="left">0.097</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Weighted mode</td><td align="left">0.049</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Heterogeneity tests</td><td align="left">MR Egger</td><td align="left">0.304</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Inverse variance weighted</td><td align="left">0.311</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Horizontal Pleiotropy</td><td align="left">MR-Egger regression intercept</td><td align="left">0.386</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MR-PRESSO global test</td><td align="left">0.434</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="9">RSPO3</td><td align="left" rowspan="5">Mendelian Randomization result</td><td align="left">MR Egger</td><td align="left">0.515</td><td align="left" rowspan="9">FGR</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Weighted median</td><td align="left">0.078</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Inverse variance weighted</td><td align="left">0.048</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Simple mode</td><td align="left">0.220</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Weighted mode</td><td align="left">0.168</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Heterogeneity tests</td><td align="left">MR Egger</td><td align="left">0.702</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Inverse variance weighted</td><td align="left">0.810</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Horizontal Pleiotropy</td><td align="left">MR Egger regression intercept</td><td align="left">0.698</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MR-PRESSO global test</td><td align="left">0.829</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="18">STAMBPL1</td><td align="left" rowspan="5">Mendelian Randomization result</td><td align="left">MR Egger</td><td align="left">0.815</td><td align="left" rowspan="9">GDM</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Weighted median</td><td align="left">0.056</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Inverse variance weighted</td><td align="left">0.012</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Simple mode</td><td align="left">0.191</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Weighted mode</td><td align="left">0.157</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Heterogeneity tests</td><td align="left">MR Egger</td><td align="left">0.570</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Inverse variance weighted</td><td align="left">0.569</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Horizontal Pleiotropy</td><td align="left">MR Egger regression intercept</td><td align="left">0.445</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MR-PRESSO global test</td><td align="left">0.670</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5">Mendelian Randomization result</td><td align="left">MR Egger</td><td align="left">0.910</td><td align="left" rowspan="9">FGR</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Weighted median</td><td align="left">0.212</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Inverse variance weighted</td><td align="left">0.048</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Simple mode</td><td align="left">0.497</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Weighted mode</td><td align="left">0.336</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Heterogeneity tests</td><td align="left">MR Egger</td><td align="left">0.261</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Inverse variance weighted</td><td align="left">0.367</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Horizontal Pleiotropy</td><td align="left">MR Egger regression intercept</td><td align="left">0.612</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MR-PRESSO global test</td><td align="left">0.496</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="9">TGFB1</td><td align="left" rowspan="5">Mendelian Randomization result</td><td align="left">MR Egger</td><td align="left">0.465</td><td align="left" rowspan="9">FGR</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Weighted median</td><td align="left">0.060</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Inverse variance weighted</td><td align="left">0.011</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Simple mode</td><td align="left">0.179</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Weighted mode</td><td align="left">0.248</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Heterogeneity tests</td><td align="left">MR Egger</td><td align="left">0.228</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Inverse variance weighted</td><td align="left">0.357</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Horizontal Pleiotropy</td><td align="left">MR Egger regression intercept</td><td align="left">0.708</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MR-PRESSO global test</td><td align="left">0.455</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="18">TNFAIP3</td><td align="left" rowspan="5">Mendelian Randomization result</td><td align="left">MR Egger</td><td align="left">0.532</td><td align="left" rowspan="9">PE</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Weighted median</td><td align="left">0.092</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Inverse variance weighted</td><td align="left">0.043</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Simple mode</td><td align="left">0.110</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Weighted mode</td><td align="left">0.343</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Heterogeneity tests</td><td align="left">MR Egger</td><td align="left">0.780</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Inverse variance weighted</td><td align="left">0.791</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Horizontal Pleiotropy</td><td align="left">MR Egger regression intercept</td><td align="left">0.536</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MR-PRESSO global test</td><td align="left">0.796</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5">Mendelian Randomization result</td><td align="left">MR Egger</td><td align="left">0.241</td><td align="left" rowspan="9">FGR</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Weighted median</td><td align="left">0.008</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Inverse variance weighted</td><td align="left">0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Simple mode</td><td align="left">0.171</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Weighted mode</td><td align="left">0.115</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Heterogeneity tests</td><td align="left">MR Egger</td><td align="left">0.841</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Inverse variance weighted</td><td align="left">0.854</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Horizontal Pleiotropy</td><td align="left">MR Egger regression intercept</td><td align="left">0.576</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MR-PRESSO global test</td><td align="left">0.845</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="9">TP53</td><td align="left" rowspan="5">Mendelian Randomization result</td><td align="left">MR Egger</td><td align="left">0.290</td><td align="left" rowspan="9">PTB</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Weighted median</td><td align="left">0.043</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Inverse variance weighted</td><td align="left">0.027</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Simple mode</td><td align="left">0.204</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Weighted mode</td><td align="left">0.187</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Heterogeneity tests</td><td align="left">MR Egger</td><td align="left">0.840</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Inverse variance weighted</td><td align="left">0.832</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Horizontal Pleiotropy</td><td align="left">MR Egger regression intercept</td><td align="left">0.625</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MR-PRESSO global test</td><td align="left">0.554</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="9">UBE2C</td><td align="left" rowspan="5">Mendelian Randomization result</td><td align="left">MR Egger</td><td align="left">0.580</td><td align="left" rowspan="9">FGR</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Weighted median</td><td align="left">0.005</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Inverse variance weighted</td><td align="left">0.010</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Simple mode</td><td align="left">0.147</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Weighted mode</td><td align="left">0.133</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Heterogeneity tests</td><td align="left">MR Egger</td><td align="left">0.103</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Inverse variance weighted</td><td align="left">0.262</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Horizontal Pleiotropy</td><td align="left">MR Egger regression intercept</td><td align="left">0.937</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MR-PRESSO global test</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="9">UBE2G2</td><td align="left" rowspan="5">Mendelian Randomization result</td><td align="left">MR Egger</td><td align="left">0.586</td><td align="left" rowspan="9">GDM</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Weighted median</td><td align="left">0.197</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Inverse variance weighted</td><td align="left">0.038</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Simple mode</td><td align="left">0.604</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Weighted mode</td><td align="left">0.666</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Heterogeneity tests</td><td align="left">MR Egger</td><td align="left">0.598</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Inverse variance weighted</td><td align="left">0.747</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Horizontal Pleiotropy</td><td align="left">MR Egger regression intercept</td><td align="left">0.821</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MR-PRESSO global test</td><td align="left">0.672</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="9">UBE3 A</td><td align="left" rowspan="5">Mendelian Randomization result</td><td align="left">MR Egger</td><td align="left">0.587</td><td align="left" rowspan="9">PTB</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Weighted median</td><td align="left">0.107</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Inverse variance weighted</td><td align="left">0.045</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Simple mode</td><td align="left">0.377</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Weighted mode</td><td align="left">0.370</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Heterogeneity tests</td><td align="left">MR Egger</td><td align="left">0.840</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Inverse variance weighted</td><td align="left">0.832</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Horizontal Pleiotropy</td><td align="left">MR Egger regression intercept</td><td align="left">0.670</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MR-PRESSO global test</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="9">USP21</td><td align="left" rowspan="5">Mendelian Randomization result</td><td align="left">MR Egger</td><td align="left">0.610</td><td align="left" rowspan="9">PTB</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Weighted median</td><td align="left">0.116</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Inverse variance weighted</td><td align="left">0.049</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Simple mode</td><td align="left">0.643</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Weighted mode</td><td align="left">0.179</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Heterogeneity tests</td><td align="left">MR Egger</td><td align="left">0.434</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Inverse variance weighted</td><td align="left">0.600</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Horizontal Pleiotropy</td><td align="left">MR Egger regression intercept</td><td align="left">0.919</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MR-PRESSO global test</td><td align="left">0.648</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par20">Collectively, a total of four diseases with 18 proteins were found to be correlated with ubiquitination-associated protein regulation (summarized in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>), including:<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p id="Par21">&#x02460;PE: PSMB6, and TNFAIP3;</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par22">&#x02461;GDM: ATXN3, BARD1, RSPO1, STAMBPL1, and UBE2G2;</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par23">&#x02462;FGR: CCNA2, PSMA7, RSPO3, STAMBPL1, TGFB1, TNFAIP3, and UBE2C;</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par24">&#x02463;premature birth (PTB): MDM4, TP53, UBE3 A, and USP21.</p></list-item></list><fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Results of MR analysis when ubiquitination related plasma proteins as outcome and pregnant diseases as exposure</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10020_2025_1268_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p><sec id="Sec11"><title>PE</title><p id="Par25">Proteasome subunit Y (PSMB6) is a component of the 20S core proteasome complex and participates in ubiquitin-dependent protein degradation within the 26S proteasome (Lichter et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2012</xref>). This complex maintains protein homeostasis by eliminating misfolded or unnecessary proteins. The expression of PSMB6 was found to be decreased in preeclamptic placentas (Bennani-Baiti et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2015</xref>), linking the ubiquitin-dependent protein degradation with PE. Our data of Mendelian randomization analysis showed that, PSMB6 is identified to be associated with PE, with 3 SNPs and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c; 0.05 (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;= 0.049) using IVW method (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>A).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Identification of ubiquitination-associated protein regulation in PE by Mendelian randomization analysis</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10020_2025_1268_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p><p id="Par26">TNFAIP3 (TNF alpha induced protein 3) was identified as a tumor necrosis factor (TNF)-related gene whose expression is rapidly induced by TNF. A recent study reported that the transcription regulation region (TRR) of TNFAIP3 showed a hypomethylation with induction of 5-aza-CdR, which facilitated CREB recruitment and thereby participated in regulating trophoblast fusion (Yang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR114">2024</xref>), suggesting TNFAIP3 may be involved in syncytiotrophoblast stress, the first stage of the two-stage model of PE. Our data of Mendelian randomization analysis showed that, TNFAIP3 is identified to be associated with PE, with 4 SNPs and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c; 0.05 (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;= 0.043) using IVW method (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>B).</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>GDM</title><p id="Par27">The ubiquitin-specific peptidase Ataxin-3 (ATXN3), belonging to the Josephin family of deubiquitinases, is highly conserved and ubiquitously expressed in mammals (Wang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR104">2023</xref>). Physiological functions of ATXN3 presumably include ubiquitin protease and transcriptional corepressor activity, while inactivation of <italic>Atxn3</italic> gene increases protein ubiquitination in mice (Schmitt et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">2007</xref>). A recent study showed that ATXN3 deubiquitinates and stabilizes the transcription coactivator Yes-associated protein (YAP) in a proteasome-dependent manner (Wu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR109">2023</xref>), while YAP influences &#x003b2; cell proliferation and diabetes (Nambiar et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">2023</xref>), suggesting the potential role of ATXN3 in GDM. Our data of Mendelian randomization analysis showed that, ATXN3 is identified to be associated with GDM, with 5 SNPs and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c; 0.05 (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;= 0.027) using IVW method and 5 SNPs and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c; 0.05 (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;= 0.042) using weighted median method (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>A).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Identification of ubiquitination-associated protein regulation in GDM by Mendelian randomization analysis</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10020_2025_1268_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p><p id="Par28">The BReast CAncer type 1 susceptibility protein (BRCA1)-associated RING domain 1 (<italic>BARD1</italic>) gene encodes a 777-aa protein (Hawsawi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2022</xref>; Witus et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR107">2021</xref>), which usually functions by forming a complex with its heterodimeric binding partner BRCA1. The BRCA1/BARD1 complex localizes to damaged chromatin after DNA replication and catalyzes the ubiquitylation of histone H2 A and other cellular targets (Hu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2021</xref>). The sole enzymatic function of the BRCA1/BARD1 complex is as a RING-type E3 ubiquitin (Ub) ligase, leading to the deposition of Ub signals onto a variety of substrate proteins. For example, ubiquitination of NF2 by the BRCA1/BARD1 complex in proliferating cells inhibits NF2/LATS association and Hippo signaling, resulting in the up-regulated stability of YAP protein that correlates positively with cell proliferation (Verma et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99">2019</xref>). Similarly, ubiquitin&#x02013;proteasome degradation pathway plays a significant role in the coordinated protein stability of BRCA1 and its partner BARD1 in the female-specific ovarian granulosa cells. The proteasome-mediated degradation of BRCA1/BARD1 also occurs during the cAMP-dependent steroidogenic process, indicating the dynamic changes of BRCA1/BARD1 protein stability in ovarian granulosa cells provide an excellent paradigm for investigating the regulation of this protein complex under physiological conditions (Lu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">2007</xref>). A recent study reported that miR-210-3p was overexpressed in the pancreas of a GDM mouse model, where miR-210-3p negatively regulated BARD1 expression to exert protective effects on endometrial stromal cells against oxidative stress damage (Cao et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2022</xref>), suggesting the involvement of BARD1 in GDM. Our data of Mendelian randomization analysis showed that, BARD1 is identified to be associated with GDM, with 4 SNPs and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c; 0.05 (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;= 0.035) using IVW method (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>B).</p><p id="Par29">R-spondin1 (RSPO1), belonging to the R-spondin family, is expressed during early ovary development and has recently emerged as an important mediator of ovary development through activating the Wnt/&#x003b2;-catenin signaling, leading to suppression of testis formation (Tomaselli et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94">2011</xref>). Given the hormones secreted by female&#x02019;s ovaries are pivotal for placentation and subsequently pregnant maintenance, it can be hypothesized that RSPO1 plays an important role during pregnancy. Wnt signaling downstream mutations have been implicated to be associated with fat distribution, and a recent study identifies that 12 obese patients harbor the same mutations in RSPO1 (p.R219 W/Q) predisposing to human obesity by screening all Wnt-related paracrine factors in 1994 obese cases and 2161 controls using whole-exome sequencing (WES) (Sun et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">2023</xref>). Consistently, in another study by Kang et al<italic>.</italic>, it is reported that circulating RSPO1 levels are increased to a greater extent in the obese group than in the lean group, and serum levels of RSPO1 are higher in the insulin-resistant group than in the insulin-sensitive group (Kang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">2019</xref>), indicating that gain-of-function mutations and excessive expression of RSPO1 in a pregnant woman could be a risk factor contributing to obesity and GDM. Our data of Mendelian randomization analysis showed that, RSPO1 is identified to be associated with GDM, with 7 SNPs and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c; 0.05 (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;= 0.047) using IVW method, 7 SNPs and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c; 0.05 (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;= 0.012) using weighted median method, and 7 SNPs and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c; 0.05 (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;= 0.049) using weighted mode method (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>C).</p><p id="Par30">STAMBPL1, a deubiquitinating enzyme that cleaves Lys63 ubiquitin linkage (McCullough et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">2004</xref>), is also associated with GDM. STAMBPL1 protein harbors nuclear localization signal (NLS), MPN (Mprl/Padl N-terminal) and JAMM (Jab1/MPN domain metalloenzyme) domains, thus belonging to the JAMM deubiquitinating enzyme family. It is found that STAMBPL1-E292 A (a mutant without deubiquitinating activity) significantly suppressed MKP1 protein polyubiquitination (Liu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">2022b</xref>), indicating the function of STAMBPL1 as a deubiquitinating enzyme (DUB) is dependent on its E292 aa residue. Our data of Mendelian randomization analysis showed that, STAMBPL1 is identified to be associated with GDM, with 4 SNPs and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c; 0.05 (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;= 0.012) using IVW method (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>D).</p><p id="Par31">E2 Ubiquitin Conjugase G2 (UBE2G2), acting as an E2 enzyme, functions as part of the endoplasmic reticulum (ER)-associated degradation (ERAD) pathway responsible for identification and degradation of misfolded proteins in the ER (Ju et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">2010</xref>). UBE2G2 is found to be involved in proinsulin degradation and subsequent presentation of the PPIB10-18 autoantigen, which is involved in the generation of insulin-derived peptides, emphasizing the importance of proinsulin processing in the ER to Type 1 diabetes (T1D) pathogenesis and identify novel targets for future T1D therapies (Cremer et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2024</xref>). Given T1D is caused by destruction of pancreatic beta cells, it can be hypothesized that pregnant women with T1D would have similar clinical symptoms to GDM during gestation. Our data of Mendelian randomization analysis showed that, UBE2G2 is identified to be associated with GDM, with 5 SNPs and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c; 0.05 (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;= 0.038) using IVW method (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>E).</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>FGR</title><p id="Par32">Cyclin A2 (CCNA2, also known as CCNA, encoded by human <italic>CCNA2</italic> gene), belongs to the highly conserved cyclin family, whose members oscillate to regulate the cell cycle, and regulates the cell cycle by inducing transition through G1/S and G2/M through binding and interacting with cyclin-dependent kinases such as CDK1 and CDK2. CCNA2 expression was observed to be downregulated in trophoblast of Recurrent miscarriage (RM) first- trimester villi, and CCNA2 promotes migration of HTR8/SVneo cells via the RhoA-ROCK signaling, and increases HTR8/SVneo cells proliferation and inhibits their apoptosis via the p53 pathway (Li et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">2019a</xref>), whereas silencing of CCNA2 repressed cell migration and invasion (Li et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">2019b</xref>). A previous study reported that CCNA2 is essential for uterine function and fertility (Aljubran, et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2024</xref>), and in addition to its function in regulating the cell cycle, CCNA2 also directs E2 and P4 signaling in vitro. The CCNA2 expression was detected to be markedly decreased in endometrial tissues, particularly in the stromal cells from the women undergoing fertilization in vitro who failed to achieve a successful pregnancy (Aljubran, et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2024</xref>). Data from <italic>Ccna2</italic> uterine tissue-conditional knockout mouse revealed that, loss of <italic>Ccna2</italic> led to an inability to achieve pregnancy which appears to be due to alterations in the process of decidualization (Aljubran, et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2024</xref>). Our data of Mendelian randomization analysis showed that, CCNA2 is identified to be associated with FGR, with 3 SNPs and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c; 0.05 (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;= 0.042) using IVW method (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>A).<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Identification of ubiquitination-associated protein regulation in FGR by Mendelian randomization analysis</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10020_2025_1268_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p><p id="Par33">The proteasome 20S subunit &#x003b1;7 (PSMA7), functioning as an &#x003b1;-type subunit of the 20S proteasome core particle that is involved in the regulated degradation of proteins in cells via the ubiquitin&#x02013;proteasome system (Ren et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">2019</xref>), has been proved to be a target interacting with some important proteins involved in transcription factor regulation (Du et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2009</xref>). A recent study further demonstrated that PSMA7 participates in degrading proteins through ubiquitin (Ub)-proteasome pathway (UPP) that plays an important role in the regulation of cell proliferation or cell cycle control, transcriptional regulation, immune and stress response, cell differentiation, and apoptosis (Du et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2009</xref>). Our data of Mendelian randomization analysis showed that, PSMA7 is identified to be associated with FGR, with 7 SNPs and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c; 0.05 (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;= 0.027) using weighted median method, and 7 SNPs and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c; 0.05 (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;= 0.035) using IVW method (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>B).</p><p id="Par34">R-spondin 3 (RSPO3), a member of the R-spondin family, plays a key role in development and tissue homeostasis (Niu, et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">2018</xref>). A previous study reveals that the fracture reducing allele at the RSPO3 locus is associated with upregulated mRNA and protein expression levels of RSPO3, giving rise to the increased trabecular bone mineral density and the reduced risk of distal forearm fractures in humans (Nilsson et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">2021</xref>), indicating the important role of RSPO3 in bone development. Moreover, pretreatment with RSPO3 could ameliorate the oxygen and glucose deprivation (OGD)/re-oxygenation (OGD/R)-induced neuronal cell death and oxidative injury by activating the Akt-Erk-&#x003b2;-Catenin signaling cascade, which is observed in both neuronal cells (Neuro-2a) and primary murine cortical neurons (Liu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">2023</xref>), suggesting the protective role of RSPO3 against hypoxia and also indicating the possible funcion of RSPO3 in fetal growth. In addition to a previous study showing <italic>Cynoglossus semilaevis</italic> Rspo3 mediates embryo development through deactivating the Wnt/&#x003b2;-Catenin signaling (Niu, et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">2018</xref>), more recently, Shinozuka et al. showed that Rspo3 is dispensable for multiple developmental processes involving roof plate-derived Wnt ligands (Shinozuka et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">2024</xref>), suggesting the pivotal regulation of Rspo3 through Wnt in fetal development. Our data of Mendelian randomization analysis showed that, RSPO3 is identified to be associated with FGR, with 5 SNPs and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c; 0.05 (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;= 0.048) using IVW method (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>C).</p><p id="Par35">STAM-binding-protein-like 1 (STAMBPL1, also known as AMSH-LP) shares 68% sequence identity and nearly identical folding of the catalytic JAB1/MPN/Mov34 metalloproteases (JAMMs) domains, as well as 56% overall sequence identity with STAMBP. As discussed above, STAMBPL1 expression is also associated with GDM in addition to FGR, it can be thereby naturally hypothesized that STAMBPL1 exerts protective effects on pregnant women during gestation. Acting as a deubiquitinase, STAMBPL1 plays a pivotal role in endocytic trafficking and lysosomal degradation (Wang, et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR105">2022</xref>), and is also a positive regulator of Tax activation of NFB (Lee et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">2017</xref>). Our data of Mendelian randomization analysis showed that, STAMBPL1 is identified to be associated with FGR, with 4 SNPs and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c; 0.05 (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;= 0.048) using IVW method (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>D).</p><p id="Par36">Transforming growth factor beta1 (TGFB1) is involved in selective intrauterine growth restriction (sIUGR, also known as FGR), which specifically occurs in monochorionic (MC) twins, usually has a poor prognosis and the underlying mechanisms are not well understood. The ten-eleven translocation 2 (TET2)-mediated DNA hydroxymethylation of TGFB1 is demonstrated to be associated with sIUGR in monochorionic twin pregnancies (Jiang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2023</xref>). Our data of Mendelian randomization analysis showed that, TGFB1 is identified to be associated with FGR, with 4 SNPs and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c; 0.05 (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;= 0.011) using IVW method (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>E).</p><p id="Par37">The Tumor Necrosis Factor Alpha-Induced Protein 3 (TNFAIP3, also known as the intracellular ubiquitin-editing protein A20) is a cytoplasmic protein that plays a key role in the negative regulation of inflammation and immunity (Verstrepen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100">2010</xref>). The N-terminal half of TNFAIP3 protein encodes a deubiquitinating (DUB) domain, whereas the C-terminal half encodes a zinc finger-containing E3 ligase domain. These two enzymatic activities work together to control the ubiquitination and subsequent degradation of cellular substrates (Wertz et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106">2004</xref>). Previous studies showed that TNFAIP3 expression is obviously induced by multiple stimuli, including the proinflammatory cytokines TNF&#x003b1; and IL-1, and microbial products that trigger pathogen recognition receptors, such as Toll-like receptors, while TNFAIP3 suppresses TNF&#x003b1;-induced signaling pathways (Turner <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">2006</xref>). In addition, TNFAIP3 is found to potentiate the deubiquitination of K63-polyubiquitin chains either directly through its N-terminal deubiquitinase domain or by disrupting the interaction between E3 and E2 enzymes that catalyze K63-polyubiquitination (Kolodziej et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">2011</xref>). Our data of Mendelian randomization analysis showed that, TNFAIP3 is identified to be associated with FGR, with 4 SNPs and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c; 0.05 (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;= 0.008) using weighted median method, and 7 SNPs and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c; 0.05 (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;= 0.001) using IVW method (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>F).</p><p id="Par38">Ubiquitin-conjugating enzyme E2 C (UBE2C) regulates ubiquitylation chain formation via the K11 linkage in ubiquitin-proteosome system (Zhang, et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR120">2023</xref>). UBE2C is found to be highly expressed in a variety of cancer types, which is strongly associated with an unfavorable prognosis, and is implicated in the progression of various cancers (Li, et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">2024</xref>; Chiang, et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2020</xref>; Wang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103">2017</xref>). For example, in lung cancer, UBE2C expression is induced by KRAS-G12D and UBE2C promotes ubiquitylation and degradation of DEPTOR, causing mTORC activation (Zhang, et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR120">2023</xref>). In addition, UBE2C-triggered sodium-coupled neutral amino acid transporter 2 (SNAT2) monoubiquitination at lysine 59 inhibits K63-linked polyubiquitination at lysine 33 of SNAT2, resulting in the consequently lymphangiogenesis and lymph node (LN) metastasis in patients with bladder cancer (BCa). Despite its function in carcinogenesis, the potential role of UBE2C in placentation and pregnant maintenance needs further investigation. Our data of Mendelian randomization analysis showed that, UBE2C is identified to be associated with FGR, with 3 SNPs and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c; 0.05 (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;= 0.010) using IVW method, and 4 SNPs and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c; 0.05 (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;= 0.005) using weighted median method (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>G).</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Preterm birth (PTB)</title><p id="Par39">Originally cloned in 1996 from mouse and in 1997 from human, the Mouse double minute 4 (MDM4), also known as MDMX or HDMX (human MDMX), is a critical negative regulator of the tumor suppressor p53. As a member in MDM protein family, MDM4 was identified to act as a critical regulator of p53 in cancer (Markey <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">2011</xref>). Recently, studies have revealed that MDM4 is also associated with PB occurrence and development. Mei et al<italic>.</italic> reported that pharmacological inhibition of MDM4 with XI-011, a small molecular inhibitor of MDM4 that significantly reduced MDM4 expression and increased the expression of total and acetylated p53, could effectively alleviate pulmonary fibrosis through the MDM4-p53-dependent pathway (Mei et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">2023</xref>), suggesting the potential role of MDM4 in fetal lung development and growth. Another study showed that, the expression of let-7 microRNA (miRNA) was obviously up-regulated in PTB-associated placental tissues, and let-7 regulated EVT cells proliferation, migration and invasion via targeting MDM4 (Zhang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR117">2019</xref>), reinforcing the notion that MDM4 would be a promising target for PTB prediction and diagnosis. Our data of Mendelian randomization analysis showed that, MDM4 is identified to be associated with PTB, with 3 SNPs and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c; 0.05 (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;= 0.001) using IVW method, and 3 SNPs and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c; 0.05 (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;= 0.001) using weighted median method (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>A).<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Identification of ubiquitination-associated protein regulation in PTB by Mendelian randomization analysis</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10020_2025_1268_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p><p id="Par40">Transformation-related protein 53 (Trp53), which encodes the p53 protein, functions as a tumor suppressor gene whose mutation is strongly associated with cancer (Hirota et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2010</xref>). A previous study revealed that deficiency of uterine-specific <italic>p53</italic> confers premature uterine senescence and promotes PTB in mice. Recently, Jiang et al<italic>.</italic> reported the long non-coding RNA SNHG29 was overexpressed in the placentas of women who delivered preterm with labor, and the elevated expression of SNHG29 regulates HTR8/SVneo cell senescence via the p53/p21 signaling in spontaneous PTB (Jiang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2021</xref>), indicating the increased pro-inflammatory cytokine expression and the subsequent release by senescent cells would be pivotal to the pathophysiology of spontaneous PTB. Similarly, either the antidiabetic drug metformin or the antioxidant resveratrol that activating the AMPK signaling protected against spontaneous and inflammation-induced PTB in <italic>p53</italic>-deleted female mice (Deng et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2016</xref>), further suggesting that metformin and resveratrol have therapeutic potential to prevent PTB. Our data of Mendelian randomization analysis showed that, TP53 is identified to be associated with PTB, with 8 SNPs and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c; 0.05 (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;= 0.027) using IVW method, and 8 SNPs and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c; 0.05 (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;= 0.043) using weighted median method (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>B).</p><p id="Par41">Ubiquitin-protein ligase E3 A (UBE3 A) acts as an E3 ubiquitin ligase whose dysregulation has been implicated in autism and Angelman syndrome (AS, an incurable neurodevelopmental disease) (Dindot, et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2023</xref>; Maranga et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">2020</xref>). Mechanistically, it is reported that UBE3 A promotes synapse elimination through suppressing activity of the BMP signaling (Furusawa et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2023</xref>), proving the essential role of UBE3 A during fetal neurodevelopment. Our data of Mendelian randomization analysis showed that, UBE3 A is identified to be associated with PTB, with 3 SNPs and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c; 0.05 (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;= 0.045) using IVW method (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>C).</p><p id="Par42">As a proteasome-associated deubiquitinating enzyme that is responsible for intracellular protein degradation, the Ubiquitin-specific protease 21(USP21) plays an important role in during oocyte maturation (Rong et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">2022</xref>), and a recent study additionally reported that the expression of USP21 was reduced in centrosomal protein of 78 kDa (<italic>Cep78</italic>)-knockout mice, leading to male infertility (Zhang, et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR119">2022</xref>), while its function in pregnant maintenance remains to be investigated. Our data of Mendelian randomization analysis showed that, USP21 is identified to be associated with PTB, with 5 SNPs and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c; 0.05 (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;= 0.049) using IVW method (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>D).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Targeting ubiquitination as potential therapeutic strategy for diseases during pregnancy</title><p id="Par43">Ubiquitination targeting therapy for perinatal diseases refers to the use of ubiquitination targeting to regulate and treat perinatal related diseases. Currently, the research on ubiquitination targeting therapy for perinatal diseases mainly focuses on the following two aspects (Cruz Walma et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2022</xref>): 1) Target identification; and 2) Drug development.</p><sec id="Sec16"><title>Target identification</title><p id="Par44">By studying the pathogenesis and related signaling pathways of perinatal diseases, protein targets closely related to disease occurrence and development can be identified. These targets may be factors that promote disease progression or inhibit disease progression, which have been discussed above and summarized in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Drug development</title><p id="Par45">Based on identified targets, drug molecules can be designed and synthesized to intervene in the occurrence and development of certain diseases by regulating the modification levels of ubiquitination targets. These developed drugs can be molecules that promote ubiquitination or inhibit ubiquitination, depending on the characteristics of the target. For example, recent studies have shown that E3 ubiquitin ligase, playing a key role in the process of fetal development and placental formation, affects the biological behavior of placental trophoblast cells and thereby causes a series of pregnancy complications that threaten the health of both mother and fetus (Feng et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2023</xref>). Silencing of Cullin 1, a member of Cullin protein family E3 ubiquitin ligase, significantly inhibits outgrowth of extravillous explants in vitro, as well as invasion and migration of HTR8/SVneo cells (Zeng et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR116">2021</xref>), suggesting its role in PE occurrence. Thus, developing drugs targeting such molecules as Cullin 1 could be promising in intervention of related diseases. Up to now, the research on ubiquitination targeting therapy for perinatal diseases is still at the preliminary stage (Dai et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2024</xref>), but it has potential clinical application prospects. Through this treatment strategy, it is expected to provide new means for the prevention and treatment of perinatal diseases.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Conclusion and perspectives</title><p id="Par46">Ubiquitination refers to the process of adding small particles of ubiquitin to target proteins, and ubiquitin is known as a small protein that can bind to other proteins and label them for cellular processes such as degradation, repair, or transport. Due to the work in the past decades, ubiquitination has been identified to function as an important cellular regulatory mechanism involved in regulating many biological processes in human placenta, such as placental development, placental function, and placental activity (Cockram et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2021</xref>; Qin et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">2022</xref>).</p><p id="Par47">The development of human placenta is initiated by the implantation of the blastocyst, and the placenta is developed from the trophectoderm (TE). Placenta plays an essential role in maintaining and supporting the growth and development of the embryo during pregnancy, when placenta provides nutrients, oxygen, and immune protective substances to the fetus, and plays a filtering and excretory role, expelling waste from the fetus from the mother (Aplin et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2020</xref>). In addition, the placenta also secretes hormones that regulate the physiological status of the mother and fetus (Tang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">2023</xref>), resulting in a successful pregnancy. As we summarize herein, recent studies have shown that, as an important post-translational modification, the ubiquitination regulation plays an important role in placentation.</p><p id="Par48">Ubiquitination participates in embryo implantation, placental formation and placental function during human placentation (Feng et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2023</xref>; Yin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR115">2024</xref>). During the embryo implantation process, ubiquitination modification can regulate the timing and location of embryo implantation (Jiang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2017</xref>). Accordingly, the functional deficiency/inactivation or overexpression/hyperactivation of certain ubiquitinase that modulate ubiquitination modification can lead to embryo implantation disorders. During placental formation, ubiquitination modification can regulate the interaction between embryonic and endometrial cells, thereby ensuring normal embryonic development and promoting placental development. Some studies regarding to ubiquitination enzymes and substrates have shown that ubiquitination modification plays a pivotal role in directing placental formation (Chen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2015</xref>; Liu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">2021</xref>). As the border tissue between the embryo and the mother, the placenta plays multiple functions such as nutritional supply, metabolic regulation, and immune protection (Jin, et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2022</xref>). Ubiquitination modification can regulate the expression and degradation of multiple key proteins in placental cells (summarized in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>), thereby affecting the normal functioning of the placenta.</p><p id="Par49">Currently, series of researches have elucidated that dysregulation of ubiquitination is closely associated with the occurrence and development of obstetric diseases or gestational disorders in clinic. For example, in certain pregnancy related diseases such as PE, GDM, FGR, and PTB that discussed in this review article, aberrant activity of the ubiquitination pathway may lead to abnormal degradation of some important proteins, leading to the deviant expression of those proteins including PSMB6, TNFAIP3, ATXN3, BARD1, RSPO1, STAMBPL1, UBE2G2, CCNA2, PSMA7, RSPO3, TGFB1, UBE2C, MDM4, TP53, UBE3 A, USP21 and consequently possible occurrence of the diseases (Chen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2021b</xref>; Li et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">2022</xref>; Aye et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2022</xref>). In addition, ubiquitination can also regulate some important signaling pathways related to placental development and function, such as cell growth- and cell cycle-associated signalings including the mTOR, AMPK, Wnt, TGF-beta, Hippo, RhoA-ROCK, TNF-alpha, BMP, and NF-B signalings, thereby affecting embryonic development and pregnancy outcomes.</p><p id="Par50">Overall, in both cell biology and developmental biology research, ubiquitination and placenta play important roles in understanding cell regulation and embryonic growth and development processes. Particularly, ubiquitination regulation of placental development is a complex and critical process involving the interaction of multiple ubiquitination enzymes and substrates. Future research can further explore the deeply molecular mechanisms by which ubiquitination modification regulates placental development and identify potentially targeted treatment or intervention strategies.</p></sec><sec id="Sec19" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="10020_2025_1268_MOESM1_ESM.xlsx"><caption><p>Supplementary Material 1.&#x000a0;Table S1. Employed SNPs instruments in Mendelian randomization analysis.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn><fn><p>Xue Wang, Xiaoqing Li and Shanshan Yuan contributed equally to this work.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We acknowledge and appreciate our colleagues for their valuable suggestions for this paper.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>X. Wang, X. Li, S. Yuan, Y. Song and C. Tang wrote the original manuscript and prepared the figures and table. Z. Gu, Z. An, Q. Xu and B. Cao edited the manuscript. Y. Song designed the manuscript. C. Tang designed and revised the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was supported by Foundation for The Top-Notch Youth Talent Cultivation Project of Independent Design Project of National Clinical Research Center for Child Health (No. Q21 A0006), and by Starting Research Foundation of The Children&#x02019;s Hospital Zhejiang University School of Medicine (No. 481) to C. Tang.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>No datasets were generated or analysed during the current study.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par51">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par52">The author declares that all work described here has not been published before and that its publication has been approved by all co-authors.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par53">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Aljubran F, et al. Uterine cyclin A2-deficient mice as a model of female early pregnancy loss. J Clin Invest. 2024;134(22):e163796.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Andreescu M, et al. A Review of Immunological Evaluation of Patients with Recurrent Spontaneous Abortion (RSA). Int J Mol Sci. 2025;26(2):785.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aplin</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Tracking placental development in health and disease</article-title><source>Nat Rev Endocrinol</source><year>2020</year><volume>16</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>479</fpage><lpage>494</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41574-020-0372-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32601352</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Aplin JD, et al. Tracking placental development in health and disease. Nat Rev Endocrinol. 2020;16(9):479&#x02013;94.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32601352</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arora</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Papaioannou</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The murine allantois: a model system for the study of blood vessel formation</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>2012</year><volume>120</volume><issue>13</issue><fpage>2562</fpage><lpage>2572</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1182/blood-2012-03-390070</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22855605</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Arora R, Papaioannou VE. The murine allantois: a model system for the study of blood vessel formation. Blood. 2012;120(13):2562&#x02013;72.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22855605</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aye</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Insulin increases adipose adiponectin in pregnancy by inhibiting ubiquitination and degradation: impact of obesity</article-title><source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source><year>2022</year><volume>107</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>66</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/clinem/dgab680</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34519830</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Aye I, et al. Insulin increases adipose adiponectin in pregnancy by inhibiting ubiquitination and degradation: impact of obesity. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2022;107(1):53&#x02013;66.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34519830</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bari</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gestational diabetic transcriptomic profiling of microdissected human trophoblast</article-title><source>J Endocrinol</source><year>2016</year><volume>229</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1530/JOE-15-0424</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26869332</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Bari MF, et al. Gestational diabetic transcriptomic profiling of microdissected human trophoblast. J Endocrinol. 2016;229(1):47&#x02013;59.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26869332</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benanti</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coordination of cell growth and division by the ubiquitin-proteasome system</article-title><source>Semin Cell Dev Biol</source><year>2012</year><volume>23</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>492</fpage><lpage>498</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.semcdb.2012.04.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22542766</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Benanti JA. Coordination of cell growth and division by the ubiquitin-proteasome system. Semin Cell Dev Biol. 2012;23(5):492&#x02013;8.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22542766</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bennani-Baiti</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Inflammation modulates RLIP76/RALBP1 electrophile-glutathione conjugate transporter and housekeeping genes in human blood-brain barrier endothelial cells</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2015</year><volume>10</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>e0139101</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0139101</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26406496</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Bennani-Baiti B, et al. Inflammation modulates RLIP76/RALBP1 electrophile-glutathione conjugate transporter and housekeeping genes in human blood-brain barrier endothelial cells. PLoS ONE. 2015;10(9):e0139101.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26406496</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brett</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Maternal-fetal nutrient transport in pregnancy pathologies: the role of the placenta</article-title><source>Int J Mol Sci</source><year>2014</year><volume>15</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>16153</fpage><lpage>16185</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms150916153</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25222554</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Brett KE, et al. Maternal-fetal nutrient transport in pregnancy pathologies: the role of the placenta. Int J Mol Sci. 2014;15(9):16153&#x02013;85.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25222554</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Browne</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Maternal butalbital use and selected defects in the national birth defects prevention study</article-title><source>Headache</source><year>2014</year><volume>54</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>54</fpage><lpage>66</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/head.12203</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24001268</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Browne ML, et al. Maternal butalbital use and selected defects in the national birth defects prevention study. Headache. 2014;54(1):54&#x02013;66.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24001268</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>miR-210-3p Impairs pancreatic beta-cell function by targeting Dtx1 in gestational diabetes mellitus</article-title><source>J Environ Pathol Toxicol Oncol</source><year>2022</year><volume>41</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1615/JEnvironPatholToxicolOncol.2022041670</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36374959</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Cao X, et al. miR-210-3p Impairs pancreatic beta-cell function by targeting Dtx1 in gestational diabetes mellitus. J Environ Pathol Toxicol Oncol. 2022;41(4):11&#x02013;23.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36374959</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Stimulation of GCMa transcriptional activity by cyclic AMP/protein kinase A signaling is attributed to CBP-mediated acetylation of GCMa</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>2005</year><volume>25</volume><issue>19</issue><fpage>8401</fpage><lpage>8414</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/MCB.25.19.8401-8414.2005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16166624</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Chang CW, et al. Stimulation of GCMa transcriptional activity by cyclic AMP/protein kinase A signaling is attributed to CBP-mediated acetylation of GCMa. Mol Cell Biol. 2005;25(19):8401&#x02013;14.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16166624</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chau</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A multiubiquitin chain is confined to specific lysine in a targeted short-lived protein</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1989</year><volume>243</volume><issue>4898</issue><fpage>1576</fpage><lpage>1583</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.2538923</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2538923</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Chau V, et al. A multiubiquitin chain is confined to specific lysine in a targeted short-lived protein. Science. 1989;243(4898):1576&#x02013;83.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2538923</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Increased ubiquitination and reduced plasma membrane trafficking of placental amino acid transporter SNAT-2 in human IUGR</article-title><source>Clin Sci (Lond)</source><year>2015</year><volume>129</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1131</fpage><lpage>1141</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/CS20150511</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26374858</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Chen YY, et al. Increased ubiquitination and reduced plasma membrane trafficking of placental amino acid transporter SNAT-2 in human IUGR. Clin Sci (Lond). 2015;129(12):1131&#x02013;41.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26374858</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Djekidel</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Author Correction: Distinct dynamics and functions of H2AK119ub1 and H3K27me3 in mouse preimplantation embryos</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2021</year><volume>53</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>936</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41588-021-00871-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33888911</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Chen Z, Djekidel MN, Zhang Y. Author Correction: Distinct dynamics and functions of H2AK119ub1 and H3K27me3 in mouse preimplantation embryos. Nat Genet. 2021b;53(6):936.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33888911</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Chen S, Liu Y, Zhou H. Advances in the Development Ubiquitin-Specific Peptidase (USP) Inhibitors. Int J Mol Sci. 2021;22(9). 10.3390/ijms22094546.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Chenge S, et al. Infectious and environmental placental insults: from underlying biological pathways to diagnostics and treatments. Pathog Dis. 2023;81:ftad024.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Chiang AJ, et al. UBE2C drives human cervical cancer progression and is positively modulated by mTOR. Biomolecules. 2020;11(1):37.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cockram</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ubiquitination in the regulation of inflammatory cell death and cancer</article-title><source>Cell Death Differ</source><year>2021</year><volume>28</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>591</fpage><lpage>605</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41418-020-00708-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33432113</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Cockram PE, et al. Ubiquitination in the regulation of inflammatory cell death and cancer. Cell Death Differ. 2021;28(2):591&#x02013;605.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33432113</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cremer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Proinsulin degradation and presentation of a proinsulin B-chain autoantigen involves ER-associated protein degradation (ERAD)-enzyme UBE2G2</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2024</year><volume>19</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>e0287877</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0287877</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38787820</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">Cremer T, et al. Proinsulin degradation and presentation of a proinsulin B-chain autoantigen involves ER-associated protein degradation (ERAD)-enzyme UBE2G2. PLoS ONE. 2024;19(5):e0287877.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38787820</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cruz Walma</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ubiquitin ligases: guardians of mammalian development</article-title><source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source><year>2022</year><volume>23</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>350</fpage><lpage>367</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41580-021-00448-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35079164</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Cruz Walma DA, et al. Ubiquitin ligases: guardians of mammalian development. Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol. 2022;23(5):350&#x02013;67.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35079164</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of key ubiquitination-related genes in gestational diabetes mellitus: A bioinformatics-driven study</article-title><source>Health Sci Rep</source><year>2024</year><volume>7</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>e70115</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hsr2.70115</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39377024</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">Dai Y, Lu S, Hu W. Identification of key ubiquitination-related genes in gestational diabetes mellitus: A bioinformatics-driven study. Health Sci Rep. 2024;7(10):e70115.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39377024</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>p53 coordinates decidual sestrin 2/AMPK/mTORC1 signaling to govern parturition timing</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><year>2016</year><volume>126</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>2941</fpage><lpage>2954</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI87715</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27454290</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Deng W, et al. p53 coordinates decidual sestrin 2/AMPK/mTORC1 signaling to govern parturition timing. J Clin Invest. 2016;126(8):2941&#x02013;54.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27454290</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dindot</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>An ASO therapy for Angelman syndrome that targets an evolutionarily conserved region at the start of the UBE3A-AS transcript</article-title><source>Sci Transl Med</source><year>2023</year><volume>15</volume><issue>688</issue><fpage>eabf4077</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/scitranslmed.abf4077</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36947593</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">Dindot SV, et al. An ASO therapy for Angelman syndrome that targets an evolutionarily conserved region at the start of the UBE3A-AS transcript. Sci Transl Med. 2023;15(688):eabf4077.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36947593</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>PSMA7, a potential biomarker of diseases</article-title><source>Protein Pept Lett</source><year>2009</year><volume>16</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>486</fpage><lpage>489</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/092986609788167824</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19442227</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="journal">Du H, et al. PSMA7, a potential biomarker of diseases. Protein Pept Lett. 2009;16(5):486&#x02013;9.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19442227</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR26"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR26" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Activation of gamma-globin expression by hypoxia-inducible factor 1alpha</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2022</year><volume>610</volume><issue>7933</issue><fpage>783</fpage><lpage>790</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-022-05312-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36224385</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26" publication-type="journal">Feng R, et al. Activation of gamma-globin expression by hypoxia-inducible factor 1alpha. Nature. 2022;610(7933):783&#x02013;90.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36224385</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR27"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR27" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Research progress of E3 ubiquitin ligase regulating biological behavior of human placental trophoblast cells</article-title><source>Front Endocrinol (Lausanne)</source><year>2023</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1124041</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fendo.2023.1124041</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37168980</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27" publication-type="journal">Feng J, et al. Research progress of E3 ubiquitin ligase regulating biological behavior of human placental trophoblast cells. Front Endocrinol (Lausanne). 2023;14:1124041.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37168980</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR28"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR28" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Furusawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Presynaptic Ube3a E3 ligase promotes synapse elimination through down-regulation of BMP signaling</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2023</year><volume>381</volume><issue>6663</issue><fpage>1197</fpage><lpage>1205</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.ade8978</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37708280</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28" publication-type="journal">Furusawa K, et al. Presynaptic Ube3a E3 ligase promotes synapse elimination through down-regulation of BMP signaling. Science. 2023;381(6663):1197&#x02013;205.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37708280</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR29"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR29" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gascoin-Lachambre</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cullins in human intra-uterine growth restriction: expressional and epigenetic alterations</article-title><source>Placenta</source><year>2010</year><volume>31</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>151</fpage><lpage>157</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.placenta.2009.11.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20005570</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29" publication-type="journal">Gascoin-Lachambre G, et al. Cullins in human intra-uterine growth restriction: expressional and epigenetic alterations. Placenta. 2010;31(2):151&#x02013;7.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20005570</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR30"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR30" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gauster</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Early human trophoblast development: from morphology to function</article-title><source>Cell Mol Life Sci</source><year>2022</year><volume>79</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>345</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00018-022-04377-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35661923</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30" publication-type="journal">Gauster M, et al. Early human trophoblast development: from morphology to function. Cell Mol Life Sci. 2022;79(6):345.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35661923</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR31"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR31" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gellersen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Brosens</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cyclic decidualization of the human endometrium in reproductive health and failure</article-title><source>Endocr Rev</source><year>2014</year><volume>35</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>851</fpage><lpage>905</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/er.2014-1045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25141152</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR31" publication-type="journal">Gellersen B, Brosens JJ. Cyclic decidualization of the human endometrium in reproductive health and failure. Endocr Rev. 2014;35(6):851&#x02013;905.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25141152</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR32"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR32" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gordeev</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Embryonic Stem Cell Differentiation to Definitive Endoderm As a Model of Heterogeneity Onset During Germ Layer Specification</article-title><source>Acta Naturae</source><year>2024</year><volume>16</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>62</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.32607/actanaturae.27510</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39877013</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32" publication-type="journal">Gordeev MN, et al. Embryonic Stem Cell Differentiation to Definitive Endoderm As a Model of Heterogeneity Onset During Germ Layer Specification. Acta Naturae. 2024;16(4):62&#x02013;72.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39877013</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR33"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR33" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hawsawi</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>BARD1 mystery: tumor suppressors are cancer susceptibility genes</article-title><source>BMC Cancer</source><year>2022</year><volume>22</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>599</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12885-022-09567-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35650591</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR33" publication-type="journal">Hawsawi YM, et al. BARD1 mystery: tumor suppressors are cancer susceptibility genes. BMC Cancer. 2022;22(1):599.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35650591</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR34"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR34" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hirota</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Uterine-specific p53 deficiency confers premature uterine senescence and promotes preterm birth in mice</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><year>2010</year><volume>120</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>803</fpage><lpage>815</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI40051</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20124728</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR34" publication-type="journal">Hirota Y, et al. Uterine-specific p53 deficiency confers premature uterine senescence and promotes preterm birth in mice. J Clin Invest. 2010;120(3):803&#x02013;15.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20124728</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR35"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR35" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mechanisms of BRCA1-BARD1 nucleosome recognition and ubiquitylation</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2021</year><volume>596</volume><issue>7872</issue><fpage>438</fpage><lpage>443</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-021-03716-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34321665</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR35" publication-type="journal">Hu Q, et al. Mechanisms of BRCA1-BARD1 nucleosome recognition and ubiquitylation. Nature. 2021;596(7872):438&#x02013;43.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34321665</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR36"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Huang P, et al. SOX4 facilitates PGR protein stability and FOXO1 expression conducive for human endometrial decidualization. Elife. 2022;11:e72073.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR37" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hubal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Inhibition of Src signaling induces autophagic killing of Toxoplasma gondii via PTEN-mediated deactivation of Akt</article-title><source>PLoS Pathog</source><year>2025</year><volume>21</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>e1012907</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1012907</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39869638</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR37" publication-type="journal">Hubal A, et al. Inhibition of Src signaling induces autophagic killing of Toxoplasma gondii via PTEN-mediated deactivation of Akt. PLoS Pathog. 2025;21(1):e1012907.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39869638</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR38"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR38" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Enhanced HOXA10 sumoylation inhibits embryo implantation in women with recurrent implantation failure</article-title><source>Cell Death Discov</source><year>2017</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>17057</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/cddiscovery.2017.57</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29018572</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR38" publication-type="journal">Jiang R, et al. Enhanced HOXA10 sumoylation inhibits embryo implantation in women with recurrent implantation failure. Cell Death Discov. 2017;3:17057.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29018572</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR39"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR39" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Long non-coding RNA SNHG29 regulates cell senescence via p53/p21 signaling in spontaneous preterm birth</article-title><source>Placenta</source><year>2021</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>64</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.placenta.2020.10.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33080448</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR39" publication-type="journal">Jiang J, et al. Long non-coding RNA SNHG29 regulates cell senescence via p53/p21 signaling in spontaneous preterm birth. Placenta. 2021;103:64&#x02013;71.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33080448</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR40"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR40" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>TET2-mediated DNA hydroxymethylation of TGFB1 is related to selective intrauterine growth restriction in monochorionic twin pregnancies</article-title><source>Placenta</source><year>2023</year><volume>144</volume><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.placenta.2023.11.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37992596</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR40" publication-type="journal">Jiang J, et al. TET2-mediated DNA hydroxymethylation of TGFB1 is related to selective intrauterine growth restriction in monochorionic twin pregnancies. Placenta. 2023;144:45&#x02013;54.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37992596</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR41"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR41" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>MicroRNA-3935 promotes human trophoblast cell epithelial-mesenchymal transition through tumor necrosis factor receptor-associated factor 6/regulator of G protein signaling 2 axis</article-title><source>Reprod Biol Endocrinol</source><year>2021</year><volume>19</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>134</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12958-021-00817-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34493304</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR41" publication-type="journal">Jin M, et al. MicroRNA-3935 promotes human trophoblast cell epithelial-mesenchymal transition through tumor necrosis factor receptor-associated factor 6/regulator of G protein signaling 2 axis. Reprod Biol Endocrinol. 2021;19(1):134.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34493304</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR42"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Jin M, et al. Micro-RNAs in human placenta: tiny molecules, immense power. Molecules. 2022;27(18):5943.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR43" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Joyce</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Interferon stimulated gene 15 conjugates to endometrial cytosolic proteins and is expressed at the uterine-placental interface throughout pregnancy in sheep</article-title><source>Endocrinology</source><year>2005</year><volume>146</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>675</fpage><lpage>684</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/en.2004-1224</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15528302</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR43" publication-type="journal">Joyce MM, et al. Interferon stimulated gene 15 conjugates to endometrial cytosolic proteins and is expressed at the uterine-placental interface throughout pregnancy in sheep. Endocrinology. 2005;146(2):675&#x02013;84.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15528302</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR44"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR44" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ju</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Solution structure and dynamics of human ubiquitin conjugating enzyme Ube2g2</article-title><source>Proteins</source><year>2010</year><volume>78</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1291</fpage><lpage>1301</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/prot.22648</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20014027</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR44" publication-type="journal">Ju T, et al. Solution structure and dynamics of human ubiquitin conjugating enzyme Ube2g2. Proteins. 2010;78(5):1291&#x02013;301.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20014027</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR45"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR45" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>YE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Serum R-Spondin 1 is a new surrogate marker for obesity and insulin resistance</article-title><source>Diabetes Metab J</source><year>2019</year><volume>43</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>368</fpage><lpage>376</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4093/dmj.2018.0066</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30398036</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR45" publication-type="journal">Kang YE, et al. Serum R-Spondin 1 is a new surrogate marker for obesity and insulin resistance. Diabetes Metab J. 2019;43(3):368&#x02013;76.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30398036</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR46"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR46" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kavsak</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Smad7 binds to Smurf2 to form an E3 ubiquitin ligase that targets the TGF beta receptor for degradation</article-title><source>Mol Cell</source><year>2000</year><volume>6</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1365</fpage><lpage>1375</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1097-2765(00)00134-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11163210</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR46" publication-type="journal">Kavsak P, et al. Smad7 binds to Smurf2 to form an E3 ubiquitin ligase that targets the TGF beta receptor for degradation. Mol Cell. 2000;6(6):1365&#x02013;75.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11163210</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR47"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR47" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Putative association between UBE2E2 polymorphisms and the risk of gestational diabetes mellitus</article-title><source>Gynecol Endocrinol</source><year>2013</year><volume>29</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>904</fpage><lpage>908</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/09513590.2013.813465</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23862583</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR47" publication-type="journal">Kim JY, et al. Putative association between UBE2E2 polymorphisms and the risk of gestational diabetes mellitus. Gynecol Endocrinol. 2013;29(10):904&#x02013;8.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23862583</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR48"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR48" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kolodziej</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>TNFAIP3 maintains intestinal barrier function and supports epithelial cell tight junctions</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2011</year><volume>6</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>e26352</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0026352</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22031828</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR48" publication-type="journal">Kolodziej LE, et al. TNFAIP3 maintains intestinal barrier function and supports epithelial cell tight junctions. PLoS ONE. 2011;6(10):e26352.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22031828</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR49"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR49" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gene expression profiling of hematologic malignant cell lines resistant to oncolytic virus treatment</article-title><source>Oncotarget</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1213</fpage><lpage>1225</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.13598</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27901484</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR49" publication-type="journal">Lee NH, et al. Gene expression profiling of hematologic malignant cell lines resistant to oncolytic virus treatment. Oncotarget. 2017;8(1):1213&#x02013;25.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27901484</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR50"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR50" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Downregulation of CCNA2 disturbs trophoblast migration, proliferation, and apoptosis during the pathogenesis of recurrent miscarriage</article-title><source>Am J Reprod Immunol</source><year>2019</year><volume>82</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>e13144</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/aji.13144</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31087423</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR50" publication-type="journal">Li X, et al. Downregulation of CCNA2 disturbs trophoblast migration, proliferation, and apoptosis during the pathogenesis of recurrent miscarriage. Am J Reprod Immunol. 2019a;82(1):e13144.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31087423</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR51"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR51" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dual regulatory role of CCNA2 in modulating CDK6 and MET-mediated cell-cycle pathway and EMT progression is blocked by miR-381-3p in bladder cancer</article-title><source>FASEB J</source><year>2019</year><volume>33</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1374</fpage><lpage>1388</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1096/fj.201800667R</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30138038</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR51" publication-type="journal">Li J, et al. Dual regulatory role of CCNA2 in modulating CDK6 and MET-mediated cell-cycle pathway and EMT progression is blocked by miR-381-3p in bladder cancer. FASEB J. 2019b;33(1):1374&#x02013;88.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30138038</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR52"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR52" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Aldosterone from endometrial glands is benefit for human decidualization</article-title><source>Cell Death Dis</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>679</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41419-020-02844-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32826848</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR52" publication-type="journal">Li SY, et al. Aldosterone from endometrial glands is benefit for human decidualization. Cell Death Dis. 2020;11(8):679.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32826848</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR53"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR53" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Destabilization of TP53 by USP10 is essential for neonatal autophagy and survival</article-title><source>Cell Rep</source><year>2022</year><volume>41</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>111435</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2022.111435</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36198274</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR53" publication-type="journal">Li H, et al. Destabilization of TP53 by USP10 is essential for neonatal autophagy and survival. Cell Rep. 2022;41(1):111435.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36198274</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR54"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Li W, et al. UBE2C-induced crosstalk between mono- and polyubiquitination of SNAT2 promotes lymphatic metastasis in bladder cancer. J Clin Invest. 2024;134(13):e179122.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR55" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lichter</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sequence analysis of beta-subunit genes of the 20S proteasome in patients with relapsed multiple myeloma treated with bortezomib or dexamethasone</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>2012</year><volume>120</volume><issue>23</issue><fpage>4513</fpage><lpage>4516</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1182/blood-2012-05-426924</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23018640</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR55" publication-type="journal">Lichter DI, et al. Sequence analysis of beta-subunit genes of the 20S proteasome in patients with relapsed multiple myeloma treated with bortezomib or dexamethasone. Blood. 2012;120(23):4513&#x02013;6.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23018640</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR56"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR56" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Limesand</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effects of chronic hypoglycemia and euglycemic correction on lysine metabolism in fetal sheep</article-title><source>Am J Physiol Endocrinol Metab</source><year>2009</year><volume>296</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>E879</fpage><lpage>E887</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpendo.90832.2008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19190258</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR56" publication-type="journal">Limesand SW, et al. Effects of chronic hypoglycemia and euglycemic correction on lysine metabolism in fetal sheep. Am J Physiol Endocrinol Metab. 2009;296(4):E879&#x02013;87.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19190258</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR57"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR57" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>USP22 regulates the formation and function of placental vasculature during the development of fetal growth restriction</article-title><source>Placenta</source><year>2021</year><volume>111</volume><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.placenta.2021.05.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34130183</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR57" publication-type="journal">Liu Z, et al. USP22 regulates the formation and function of placental vasculature during the development of fetal growth restriction. Placenta. 2021;111:19&#x02013;25.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34130183</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR58"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR58" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>UHRF1 shapes both the trophoblast invasion and decidual macrophage differentiation in early pregnancy</article-title><source>FASEB J</source><year>2022</year><volume>36</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>e22247</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1096/fj.202101647RR</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35262949</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR58" publication-type="journal">Liu H, et al. UHRF1 shapes both the trophoblast invasion and decidual macrophage differentiation in early pregnancy. FASEB J. 2022a;36(4): e22247.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35262949</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR59"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR59" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>STAMBPL1 promotes breast cancer cell resistance to cisplatin partially by stabilizing MKP-1 expression</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>2022</year><volume>41</volume><issue>16</issue><fpage>2265</fpage><lpage>2274</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41388-022-02252-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35236965</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR59" publication-type="journal">Liu R, et al. STAMBPL1 promotes breast cancer cell resistance to cisplatin partially by stabilizing MKP-1 expression. Oncogene. 2022b;41(16):2265&#x02013;74.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35236965</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR60"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR60" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Endothelial cell-derived RSPO3 activates Galphai1/3-Erk signaling and protects neurons from ischemia/reperfusion injury</article-title><source>Cell Death Dis</source><year>2023</year><volume>14</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>654</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41419-023-06176-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37805583</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR60" publication-type="journal">Liu TT, et al. Endothelial cell-derived RSPO3 activates Galphai1/3-Erk signaling and protects neurons from ischemia/reperfusion injury. Cell Death Dis. 2023;14(10):654.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37805583</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR61"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR61" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ubiquitination and proteasome-mediated degradation of BRCA1 and BARD1 during steroidogenesis in human ovarian granulosa cells</article-title><source>Mol Endocrinol</source><year>2007</year><volume>21</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>651</fpage><lpage>663</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/me.2006-0188</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17185394</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR61" publication-type="journal">Lu Y, et al. Ubiquitination and proteasome-mediated degradation of BRCA1 and BARD1 during steroidogenesis in human ovarian granulosa cells. Mol Endocrinol. 2007;21(3):651&#x02013;63.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17185394</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR62"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR62" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Peli1 signaling blockade attenuates congenital zika syndrome</article-title><source>PLoS Pathog</source><year>2020</year><volume>16</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>e1008538</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1008538</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32544190</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR62" publication-type="journal">Luo H, et al. Peli1 signaling blockade attenuates congenital zika syndrome. PLoS Pathog. 2020;16(6):e1008538.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32544190</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR63"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR63" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Maternal hyperglycemia inhibits pulmonary vasculogenesis during mouse fetal lung development by promoting GbetaL Ubiquitination-dependent mammalian target of Rapamycin assembly</article-title><source>Diabetol Metab Syndr</source><year>2023</year><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>49</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13098-022-00974-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36927703</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR63" publication-type="journal">Luo Q, et al. Maternal hyperglycemia inhibits pulmonary vasculogenesis during mouse fetal lung development by promoting GbetaL Ubiquitination-dependent mammalian target of Rapamycin assembly. Diabetol Metab Syndr. 2023;15(1):49.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36927703</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR64"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR64" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Downregulation of decidual SKP2 is associated with human recurrent miscarriage</article-title><source>Reprod Biol Endocrinol</source><year>2021</year><volume>19</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>88</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12958-021-00775-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34116705</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR64" publication-type="journal">Lv S, et al. Downregulation of decidual SKP2 is associated with human recurrent miscarriage. Reprod Biol Endocrinol. 2021;19(1):88.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34116705</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR65"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR65" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lyu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effects of oxycodone on placental lineages: evidence from the transcriptome profile of mouse trophoblast giant cells</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2024</year><volume>121</volume><issue>45</issue><fpage>e2412349121</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.2412349121</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39475633</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR65" publication-type="journal">Lyu Z, et al. Effects of oxycodone on placental lineages: evidence from the transcriptome profile of mouse trophoblast giant cells. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2024;121(45):e2412349121.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39475633</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR66"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR66" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maranga</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Angelman syndrome: a journey through the brain</article-title><source>FEBS J</source><year>2020</year><volume>287</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>2154</fpage><lpage>2175</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/febs.15258</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32087041</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR66" publication-type="journal">Maranga C, et al. Angelman syndrome: a journey through the brain. FEBS J. 2020;287(11):2154&#x02013;75.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32087041</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR67"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR67" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Markey</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of MDM4</article-title><source>Front Biosci (Landmark Ed)</source><year>2011</year><volume>16</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>1144</fpage><lpage>1156</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2741/3780</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21196223</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR67" publication-type="journal">Markey MP. Regulation of MDM4. Front Biosci (Landmark Ed). 2011;16(3):1144&#x02013;56.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21196223</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR68"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR68" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martin-Rufo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>de la Vega-Barranco</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lecona</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ubiquitin and SUMO as timers during DNA replication</article-title><source>Semin Cell Dev Biol</source><year>2022</year><volume>132</volume><fpage>62</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.semcdb.2022.02.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35210137</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR68" publication-type="journal">Martin-Rufo R, de la Vega-Barranco G, Lecona E. Ubiquitin and SUMO as timers during DNA replication. Semin Cell Dev Biol. 2022;132:62&#x02013;73.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35210137</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR69"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR69" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCullough</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Clague</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Urbe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>AMSH is an endosome-associated ubiquitin isopeptidase</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>2004</year><volume>166</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>487</fpage><lpage>492</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.200401141</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15314065</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR69" publication-type="journal">McCullough J, Clague MJ, Urbe S. AMSH is an endosome-associated ubiquitin isopeptidase. J Cell Biol. 2004;166(4):487&#x02013;92.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15314065</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR70"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR70" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mei</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pharmacological inhibition of MDM4 alleviates pulmonary fibrosis</article-title><source>Theranostics</source><year>2023</year><volume>13</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>2787</fpage><lpage>2799</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7150/thno.81993</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37284444</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR70" publication-type="journal">Mei Q, et al. Pharmacological inhibition of MDM4 alleviates pulmonary fibrosis. Theranostics. 2023;13(9):2787&#x02013;99.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37284444</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR71"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR71" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Millar</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The scope, functions, and dynamics of posttranslational protein modifications</article-title><source>Annu Rev Plant Biol</source><year>2019</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>119</fpage><lpage>151</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-arplant-050718-100211</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30786234</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR71" publication-type="journal">Millar AH, et al. The scope, functions, and dynamics of posttranslational protein modifications. Annu Rev Plant Biol. 2019;70:119&#x02013;51.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30786234</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR72"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR72" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mobley</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>MAP3K4 Controls the Chromatin Modifier HDAC6 during Trophoblast Stem Cell Epithelial-to-Mesenchymal Transition</article-title><source>Cell Rep</source><year>2017</year><volume>18</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>2387</fpage><lpage>2400</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2017.02.030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28273454</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR72" publication-type="journal">Mobley RJ, et al. MAP3K4 Controls the Chromatin Modifier HDAC6 during Trophoblast Stem Cell Epithelial-to-Mesenchymal Transition. Cell Rep. 2017;18(10):2387&#x02013;400.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28273454</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR73"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR73" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mohanty</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Infant sex-specific placental cadmium and DNA methylation associations</article-title><source>Environ Res</source><year>2015</year><volume>138</volume><fpage>74</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2015.02.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25701811</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR73" publication-type="journal">Mohanty AF, et al. Infant sex-specific placental cadmium and DNA methylation associations. Environ Res. 2015;138:74&#x02013;81.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25701811</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR74"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR74" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nambiar</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Maternal hepatocytes heterogeneously and dynamically exhibit developmental phenotypes partially via yes-associated protein 1 during pregnancy</article-title><source>Am J Physiol Gastrointest Liver Physiol</source><year>2023</year><volume>324</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>G38</fpage><lpage>G50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpgi.00197.2022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36283963</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR74" publication-type="journal">Nambiar SM, et al. Maternal hepatocytes heterogeneously and dynamically exhibit developmental phenotypes partially via yes-associated protein 1 during pregnancy. Am J Physiol Gastrointest Liver Physiol. 2023;324(1):G38&#x02013;50.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36283963</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR75"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR75" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>RSPO3 is important for trabecular bone and fracture risk in mice and humans</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2021</year><volume>12</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>4923</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-021-25124-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34389713</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR75" publication-type="journal">Nilsson KH, et al. RSPO3 is important for trabecular bone and fracture risk in mice and humans. Nat Commun. 2021;12(1):4923.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34389713</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR76"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Niu J, et al. Cynoglossus semilaevis Rspo3 regulates embryo development by inhibiting the Wnt/beta-Catenin signaling pathway. Int J Mol Sci. 2018;19(7):1915.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR77"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ochoa-Bernal MA, Fazleabas AT. Physiologic events of embryo implantation and decidualization in human and non-human primates. Int J Mol Sci. 2020;21(6):1973.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR78"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR78" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Disturbance of fetal growth by azithromycin through induction of ER stress in the placenta</article-title><source>Antioxid Redox Signal</source><year>2025</year><volume>42</volume><issue>1&#x02013;3</issue><fpage>16</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/ars.2024.0592</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38877798</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR78" publication-type="journal">Pan F, et al. Disturbance of fetal growth by azithromycin through induction of ER stress in the placenta. Antioxid Redox Signal. 2025;42(1&#x02013;3):16&#x02013;35.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38877798</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR79"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Perez-Garcia V, et al. BAP1/ASXL complex modulation regulates epithelial-mesenchymal transition during trophoblast differentiation and invasion. Elife. 2021;10:e63254.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR80"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR80" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pickart</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fushman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Polyubiquitin chains: polymeric protein signals</article-title><source>Curr Opin Chem Biol</source><year>2004</year><volume>8</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>610</fpage><lpage>616</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cbpa.2004.09.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15556404</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR80" publication-type="journal">Pickart CM, Fushman D. Polyubiquitin chains: polymeric protein signals. Curr Opin Chem Biol. 2004;8(6):610&#x02013;6.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15556404</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR81"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR81" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Probing protein ubiquitination in live cells</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2022</year><volume>50</volume><issue>21</issue><fpage>e125</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkac805</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36189882</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR81" publication-type="journal">Qin W, et al. Probing protein ubiquitination in live cells. Nucleic Acids Res. 2022;50(21):e125.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36189882</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR82"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR82" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effects of shRNA-mediated silencing of PSMA7 on cell proliferation and vascular endothelial growth factor expression via the ubiquitin-proteasome pathway in cervical cancer</article-title><source>J Cell Physiol</source><year>2019</year><volume>234</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>5851</fpage><lpage>5862</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jcp.26408</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29247526</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR82" publication-type="journal">Ren CC, et al. Effects of shRNA-mediated silencing of PSMA7 on cell proliferation and vascular endothelial growth factor expression via the ubiquitin-proteasome pathway in cervical cancer. J Cell Physiol. 2019;234(5):5851&#x02013;62.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29247526</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR83"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR83" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>USP16-mediated histone H2A lysine-119 deubiquitination during oocyte maturation is a prerequisite for zygotic genome activation</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2022</year><volume>50</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>5599</fpage><lpage>5616</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkac468</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35640597</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR83" publication-type="journal">Rong Y, et al. USP16-mediated histone H2A lysine-119 deubiquitination during oocyte maturation is a prerequisite for zygotic genome activation. Nucleic Acids Res. 2022;50(10):5599&#x02013;616.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35640597</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR84"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR84" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schafer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Paraschiakos</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Windhorst</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oncogenic activity and cellular functionality of melanoma associated antigen A3</article-title><source>Biochem Pharmacol</source><year>2021</year><volume>192</volume><fpage>114700</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bcp.2021.114700</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34303709</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR84" publication-type="journal">Schafer P, Paraschiakos T, Windhorst S. Oncogenic activity and cellular functionality of melanoma associated antigen A3. Biochem Pharmacol. 2021;192:114700.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34303709</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR85"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR85" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmitt</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Inactivation of the mouse Atxn3 (ataxin-3) gene increases protein ubiquitination</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><year>2007</year><volume>362</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>734</fpage><lpage>739</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbrc.2007.08.062</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17764659</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR85" publication-type="journal">Schmitt I, et al. Inactivation of the mouse Atxn3 (ataxin-3) gene increases protein ubiquitination. Biochem Biophys Res Commun. 2007;362(3):734&#x02013;9.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17764659</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR86"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR86" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schreiber</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Rise of Molecular Glues</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2021</year><volume>184</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2020.12.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33417864</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR86" publication-type="journal">Schreiber SL. The Rise of Molecular Glues. Cell. 2021;184(1):3&#x02013;9.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33417864</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR87"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR87" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Godbole</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Modi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Decidual control of trophoblast invasion</article-title><source>Am J Reprod Immunol</source><year>2016</year><volume>75</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>341</fpage><lpage>350</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/aji.12466</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26755153</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR87" publication-type="journal">Sharma S, Godbole G, Modi D. Decidual control of trophoblast invasion. Am J Reprod Immunol. 2016;75(3):341&#x02013;50.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26755153</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR88"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR88" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shinozuka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Rspo1 and Rspo3 are required for sensory lineage neural crest formation in mouse embryos</article-title><source>Dev Dyn</source><year>2024</year><volume>253</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>435</fpage><lpage>446</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/dvdy.659</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37767857</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR88" publication-type="journal">Shinozuka T, et al. Rspo1 and Rspo3 are required for sensory lineage neural crest formation in mouse embryos. Dev Dyn. 2024;253(4):435&#x02013;46.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37767857</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR89"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR89" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simister</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Placental transport of immunoglobulin G</article-title><source>Vaccine</source><year>2003</year><volume>21</volume><issue>24</issue><fpage>3365</fpage><lpage>3369</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0264-410X(03)00334-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12850341</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR89" publication-type="journal">Simister NE. Placental transport of immunoglobulin G. Vaccine. 2003;21(24):3365&#x02013;9.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12850341</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR90"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR90" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stefanski</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Murine trophoblast-derived and pregnancy-associated exosome-enriched extracellular vesicle microRNAs: Implications for placenta driven effects on maternal physiology</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2019</year><volume>14</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>e0210675</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0210675</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30730971</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR90" publication-type="journal">Stefanski AL, et al. Murine trophoblast-derived and pregnancy-associated exosome-enriched extracellular vesicle microRNAs: Implications for placenta driven effects on maternal physiology. PLoS ONE. 2019;14(2):e0210675.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30730971</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR91"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR91" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Human rspo1 mutation represses beige adipocyte thermogenesis and contributes to diet-induced adiposity</article-title><source>Adv Sci (Weinh)</source><year>2023</year><volume>10</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>e2207152</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/advs.202207152</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36755192</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR91" publication-type="journal">Sun Y, et al. Human rspo1 mutation represses beige adipocyte thermogenesis and contributes to diet-induced adiposity. Adv Sci (Weinh). 2023;10(12):e2207152.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36755192</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR92"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR92" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>RGS2 promotes estradiol biosynthesis by trophoblasts during human pregnancy</article-title><source>Exp Mol Med</source><year>2023</year><volume>55</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>240</fpage><lpage>252</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s12276-023-00927-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36653442</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR92" publication-type="journal">Tang C, et al. RGS2 promotes estradiol biosynthesis by trophoblasts during human pregnancy. Exp Mol Med. 2023;55(1):240&#x02013;52.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36653442</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR93"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR93" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thiery</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Epithelial-mesenchymal transitions in development and disease</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2009</year><volume>139</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>871</fpage><lpage>890</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2009.11.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19945376</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR93" publication-type="journal">Thiery JP, et al. Epithelial-mesenchymal transitions in development and disease. Cell. 2009;139(5):871&#x02013;90.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19945376</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR94"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR94" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tomaselli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Human RSPO1/R-spondin1 is expressed during early ovary development and augments beta-catenin signaling</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2011</year><volume>6</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>e16366</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0016366</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21297984</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR94" publication-type="journal">Tomaselli S, et al. Human RSPO1/R-spondin1 is expressed during early ovary development and augments beta-catenin signaling. PLoS ONE. 2011;6(1):e16366.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21297984</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR95"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR95" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Townley-Tilson</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The ubiquitin ligase ASB4 promotes trophoblast differentiation through the degradation of ID2</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>e89451</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0089451</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24586788</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR95" publication-type="journal">Townley-Tilson WH, et al. The ubiquitin ligase ASB4 promotes trophoblast differentiation through the degradation of ID2. PLoS ONE. 2014;9(2):e89451.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24586788</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR96"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR96" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular basis of epithelial barrier regulation: from basic mechanisms to clinical application</article-title><source>Am J Pathol</source><year>2006</year><volume>169</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1901</fpage><lpage>1909</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2353/ajpath.2006.060681</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17148655</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR96" publication-type="journal">Turner JR. Molecular basis of epithelial barrier regulation: from basic mechanisms to clinical application. Am J Pathol. 2006;169(6):1901&#x02013;9.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17148655</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR97"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR97" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Goor</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Differential responses in placenta and fetal thymus at 12 days post infection elucidate mechanisms of viral level and fetal compromise following PRRSV2 infection</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2020</year><volume>21</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>763</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-020-07154-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33148169</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR97" publication-type="journal">Van Goor A, et al. Differential responses in placenta and fetal thymus at 12 days post infection elucidate mechanisms of viral level and fetal compromise following PRRSV2 infection. BMC Genomics. 2020;21(1):763.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33148169</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR98"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR98" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vento-Tormo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Single-cell reconstruction of the early maternal-fetal interface in humans</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2018</year><volume>563</volume><issue>7731</issue><fpage>347</fpage><lpage>353</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-018-0698-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30429548</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR98" publication-type="journal">Vento-Tormo R, et al. Single-cell reconstruction of the early maternal-fetal interface in humans. Nature. 2018;563(7731):347&#x02013;53.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30429548</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR99"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR99" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>BRCA1/BARD1-dependent ubiquitination of NF2 regulates Hippo-YAP1 signaling</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2019</year><volume>116</volume><issue>15</issue><fpage>7363</fpage><lpage>7370</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1822155116</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30918126</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR99" publication-type="journal">Verma S, et al. BRCA1/BARD1-dependent ubiquitination of NF2 regulates Hippo-YAP1 signaling. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2019;116(15):7363&#x02013;70.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30918126</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR100"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR100" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Verstrepen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Expression, biological activities and mechanisms of action of A20 (TNFAIP3)</article-title><source>Biochem Pharmacol</source><year>2010</year><volume>80</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>2009</fpage><lpage>2020</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bcp.2010.06.044</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20599425</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR100" publication-type="journal">Verstrepen L, et al. Expression, biological activities and mechanisms of action of A20 (TNFAIP3). Biochem Pharmacol. 2010;80(12):2009&#x02013;20.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20599425</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR101"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR101" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vishnyakova</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gestation age-associated dynamics of mitochondrial calcium uniporter subunits expression in feto-maternal complex at term and preterm delivery</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2019</year><volume>9</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>5501</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-41996-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30940880</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR101" publication-type="journal">Vishnyakova PA, et al. Gestation age-associated dynamics of mitochondrial calcium uniporter subunits expression in feto-maternal complex at term and preterm delivery. Sci Rep. 2019;9(1):5501.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30940880</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR102"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Vishnyakova P, et al. Expression of estrogen receptor alpha by decidual macrophages in preeclampsia. Biomedicines. 2021;9(2):191.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR103"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR103" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>UBE2C induces EMT through Wnt/beta-catenin and PI3K/Akt signaling pathways by regulating phosphorylation levels of Aurora-A</article-title><source>Int J Oncol</source><year>2017</year><volume>50</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1116</fpage><lpage>1126</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3892/ijo.2017.3880</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28260026</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR103" publication-type="journal">Wang R, et al. UBE2C induces EMT through Wnt/beta-catenin and PI3K/Akt signaling pathways by regulating phosphorylation levels of Aurora-A. Int J Oncol. 2017;50(4):1116&#x02013;26.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28260026</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR104"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR104" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>ATXN3 deubiquitinates YAP1 to promote tumor growth</article-title><source>Am J Cancer Res</source><year>2023</year><volume>13</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>4222</fpage><lpage>4234</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37818078</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR104" publication-type="journal">Wang S, et al. ATXN3 deubiquitinates YAP1 to promote tumor growth. Am J Cancer Res. 2023;13(9):4222&#x02013;34.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37818078</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR105"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR105" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>E3 ligase RNF167 and deubiquitinase STAMBPL1 modulate mTOR and cancer progression</article-title><source>Mol Cell</source><year>2022</year><volume>82</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>770</fpage><lpage>784 e9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2022.01.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35114100</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR105" publication-type="journal">Wang D, et al. E3 ligase RNF167 and deubiquitinase STAMBPL1 modulate mTOR and cancer progression. Mol Cell. 2022;82(4):770-784 e9.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35114100</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR106"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR106" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wertz</surname><given-names>IE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>De-ubiquitination and ubiquitin ligase domains of A20 downregulate NF-kappaB signalling</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2004</year><volume>430</volume><issue>7000</issue><fpage>694</fpage><lpage>699</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature02794</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15258597</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR106" publication-type="journal">Wertz IE, et al. De-ubiquitination and ubiquitin ligase domains of A20 downregulate NF-kappaB signalling. Nature. 2004;430(7000):694&#x02013;9.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15258597</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR107"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR107" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Witus</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Klevit</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The BRCA1/BARD1 ubiquitin ligase and its substrates</article-title><source>Biochem J</source><year>2021</year><volume>478</volume><issue>18</issue><fpage>3467</fpage><lpage>3483</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/BCJ20200864</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34591954</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR107" publication-type="journal">Witus SR, Stewart MD, Klevit RE. The BRCA1/BARD1 ubiquitin ligase and its substrates. Biochem J. 2021;478(18):3467&#x02013;83.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34591954</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR108"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR108" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>MiR-135a-5p promotes the migration and invasion of trophoblast cells in preeclampsia by targeting beta-TrCP</article-title><source>Placenta</source><year>2020</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>63</fpage><lpage>69</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.placenta.2020.07.028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32758717</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR108" publication-type="journal">Wu D, et al. MiR-135a-5p promotes the migration and invasion of trophoblast cells in preeclampsia by targeting beta-TrCP. Placenta. 2020;99:63&#x02013;9.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32758717</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR109"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR109" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>ATXN3 promotes prostate cancer progression by stabilizing YAP</article-title><source>Cell Commun Signal</source><year>2023</year><volume>21</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>152</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12964-023-01073-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37349820</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR109" publication-type="journal">Wu L, et al. ATXN3 promotes prostate cancer progression by stabilizing YAP. Cell Commun Signal. 2023;21(1):152.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37349820</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR110"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR110" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Decreased ubiquitin modifying enzyme A20 associated with hyper-responsiveness to ovalbumin challenge following intrauterine growth restriction</article-title><source>Respir Res</source><year>2023</year><volume>24</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>50</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12931-023-02360-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36788604</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR110" publication-type="journal">Xu X, et al. Decreased ubiquitin modifying enzyme A20 associated with hyper-responsiveness to ovalbumin challenge following intrauterine growth restriction. Respir Res. 2023;24(1):50.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36788604</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR111"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR111" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>DCAF13 is essential for the pathogenesis of preeclampsia through its involvement in endometrial decidualization</article-title><source>Mol Cell Endocrinol</source><year>2022</year><volume>556</volume><fpage>111741</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mce.2022.111741</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35932979</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR111" publication-type="journal">Yan X, et al. DCAF13 is essential for the pathogenesis of preeclampsia through its involvement in endometrial decidualization. Mol Cell Endocrinol. 2022;556:111741.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35932979</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR112"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR112" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Expression of Smad ubiquitin regulatory factor 2 (Smurf2) in rhesus monkey endometrium and placenta during early pregnancy</article-title><source>J Histochem Cytochem</source><year>2007</year><volume>55</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>453</fpage><lpage>460</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1369/jhc.6A7069.2006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17189523</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR112" publication-type="journal">Yang Q, et al. Expression of Smad ubiquitin regulatory factor 2 (Smurf2) in rhesus monkey endometrium and placenta during early pregnancy. J Histochem Cytochem. 2007;55(5):453&#x02013;60.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17189523</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR113"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR113" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Simple structural modifications converting a bona fide MDM2 PROTAC degrader into a molecular glue molecule: a cautionary tale in the design of PROTAC degraders</article-title><source>J Med Chem</source><year>2019</year><volume>62</volume><issue>21</issue><fpage>9471</fpage><lpage>9487</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jmedchem.9b00846</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31560543</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR113" publication-type="journal">Yang J, et al. Simple structural modifications converting a bona fide MDM2 PROTAC degrader into a molecular glue molecule: a cautionary tale in the design of PROTAC degraders. J Med Chem. 2019;62(21):9471&#x02013;87.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31560543</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR114"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR114" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Evaluating the role of DNA methyltransferases in trophoblast fusion and preeclampsia development: Insights from methylation-regulated genes</article-title><source>FASEB J</source><year>2024</year><volume>38</volume><issue>13</issue><fpage>e23706</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1096/fj.202302705R</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38877842</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR114" publication-type="journal">Yang YF, et al. Evaluating the role of DNA methyltransferases in trophoblast fusion and preeclampsia development: Insights from methylation-regulated genes. FASEB J. 2024;38(13):e23706.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38877842</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR115"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Yin Y, et al. Insight into the post-translational modifications in pregnancy and related complications. Biol Reprod. 2025;112(2):204&#x02013;24.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR116"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR116" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>New insights into the roles of CUL1 in mouse placenta development</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><year>2021</year><volume>559</volume><fpage>70</fpage><lpage>77</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbrc.2021.04.064</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33933992</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR116" publication-type="journal">Zeng L, et al. New insights into the roles of CUL1 in mouse placenta development. Biochem Biophys Res Commun. 2021;559:70&#x02013;7.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33933992</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR117"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR117" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Let-7 inhibits the migration and invasion of extravillous trophoblast cell via targeting MDM4</article-title><source>Mol Cell Probes</source><year>2019</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>48</fpage><lpage>56</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mcp.2019.05.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31078695</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR117" publication-type="journal">Zhang L, et al. Let-7 inhibits the migration and invasion of extravillous trophoblast cell via targeting MDM4. Mol Cell Probes. 2019;45:48&#x02013;56.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31078695</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR118"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR118" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Factors associated with gestational diabetes mellitus: a meta-analysis</article-title><source>J Diabetes Res</source><year>2021</year><volume>2021</volume><fpage>6692695</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2021/6692695</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34046504</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR118" publication-type="journal">Zhang Y, et al. Factors associated with gestational diabetes mellitus: a meta-analysis. J Diabetes Res. 2021;2021:6692695.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34046504</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR119"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR119" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Loss-of-function mutations in CEP78 cause male infertility in humans and mice</article-title><source>Sci Adv</source><year>2022</year><volume>8</volume><issue>40</issue><fpage>eabn0968</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/sciadv.abn0968</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36206347</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR119" publication-type="journal">Zhang X, et al. Loss-of-function mutations in CEP78 cause male infertility in humans and mice. Sci Adv. 2022;8(40):eabn0968.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36206347</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR120"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zhang S, et al. The UBE2C/CDH1/DEPTOR axis is an oncogene and tumor suppressor cascade in lung cancer cells. J Clin Invest. 2023;133(4):e162434.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR121"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR121" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhen</surname><given-names>XX</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>MNSFbeta regulates TNFalpha production by interacting with RC3H1 in human macrophages, and dysfunction of MNSFbeta in decidual macrophages is associated with recurrent pregnancy loss</article-title><source>Front Immunol</source><year>2021</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>691908</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2021.691908</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34589082</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR121" publication-type="journal">Zhen XX, et al. MNSFbeta regulates TNFalpha production by interacting with RC3H1 in human macrophages, and dysfunction of MNSFbeta in decidual macrophages is associated with recurrent pregnancy loss. Front Immunol. 2021;12:691908.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34589082</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR122"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR122" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ubiquitin-specific protease 7 prevents recurrent spontaneous abortion by targeting enhancer of zeste homolog 2 to regulate trophoblast proliferation, apoptosis, migration, and invasion through the Wnt/beta-catenin pathwaydagger</article-title><source>Biol Reprod</source><year>2023</year><volume>109</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>204</fpage><lpage>214</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/biolre/ioad053</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37249558</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR122" publication-type="journal">Zhou M, et al. Ubiquitin-specific protease 7 prevents recurrent spontaneous abortion by targeting enhancer of zeste homolog 2 to regulate trophoblast proliferation, apoptosis, migration, and invasion through the Wnt/beta-catenin pathwaydagger. Biol Reprod. 2023;109(2):204&#x02013;14.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37249558</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article>