<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Medicine (Baltimore)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Medicine (Baltimore)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MD</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0025-7974</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1536-5964</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Lippincott Williams &#x00026; Wilkins</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Hagerstown, MD</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40388765</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12091594</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">MD-D-24-13207</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="art-access-id">00046</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000042490</article-id><article-version vocab="JAV" vocab-identifier="http://www.niso.org/publications/rp/RP-8-2008.pdf" article-version-type="Version of Record">3</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>5700</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Research Article</subject><subject>Clinical Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Sintilimab-induced diabetes mellitus and thyroid dysfunction in patient with gastric adenocarcinoma: A case report and literature review</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8985-3234</contrib-id><name><surname>Zan</surname><given-names>Ying</given-names></name><degrees>MSc</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="c1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Yedong</given-names></name><degrees>MSc</degrees><email>809406211@qq.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Wenxue</given-names></name><degrees>BSc</degrees><email>381814528@qq.com</email><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Xiaolu</given-names></name><degrees>BSc</degrees><email>1625307632@qq.com</email><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Si</surname><given-names>Jigang</given-names></name><degrees>MSc</degrees><email>sjg1019@163.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Department of Pharmacy, Zibo Central Hospital, Zibo, China</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Department of Pharmacy, Zhangdian Traditional Chinese Medicine Hospital, Zibo, China</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Department of pharmacy, Jinshan Town Health Center, Zibo, China.</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1"><label>*</label>Correspondence: Ying Zan, Department of Pharmacy, Zibo Central Hospital, Zibo, China (e-mail: <email xlink:href="hpyyq1211@163.com">hpyyq1211@163.com</email>).</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>16</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>104</volume><issue>20</issue><elocation-id>e42490</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>31</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2025 the Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License 4.0 (CCBY)</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="medi-104-e42490.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Rationale:</title><p>Immune checkpoint inhibitors bring hope to cancer patients but may also lead to severe immune-related adverse events (irAEs). Although irAEs during treatment are well-characterized, delayed immune-related events (DIRE) remain underreported. Here, we report a case of sintilimab-induced delayed immune-related diabetes mellitus, accompanied by ICI-related thyroid disease (ICI-TD). Cases involving both ICI-TD and ICI-related diabetes mellitus (ICI-DM) are also relatively rare. This study systematically aggregates dual endocrine irAEs to provide valuable insights for clinical practice.</p></sec><sec><title>Patient concerns:</title><p>A 60-year-old Chinese male diagnosed with gastric adenocarcinoma received a multimodal treatment regimen consisting of sintilimab, chemotherapy, and apatinib. He completed 3 cycles of chemotherapy and 4 cycles of sintilimab. Due to disease progression, sintilimab was discontinued, but apatinib was continued for an additional 1 month. No further antitumor therapy was administered afterward. Four months later, he was admitted to the emergency department due to persistent nausea, vomiting, and abdominal pain.</p></sec><sec><title>Diagnoses:</title><p>Thyroid dysfunction induced by sintilimab was identified during treatment. His laboratory tests contributed to the diagnosis of diabetes ketoacidosis. Fulminant type 1 diabetes mellitus attributed to sintilimab met diagnostic criteria: plasma glucose 42.01 mmol/L, glycated hemoglobin 7.5%, C-peptide &#x0003c;0.02 &#x000b5;g/L, and negative islet autoantibodies.</p></sec><sec><title>Interventions:</title><p>Levothyroxine replacement therapy was initiated for hypothyroidism, whereas diabetes ketoacidosis during hospitalization required intensive insulin therapy combined with fluid resuscitation.</p></sec><sec><title>Outcomes:</title><p>The patient exhibited persistent blood glucose fluctuations during hospitalization, including 2 hypoglycemic episodes. Post-treatment stabilization required basal-bolus insulin at discharge, with continued levothyroxine for hypothyroidism.</p></sec><sec><title>Lessons:</title><p>We report a rare case of concurrent ICI-TD and ICI-DM following sintilimab therapy. This case underscores the potential for DIRE, with onset occurring months posttreatment. Combined with a systematic review of existing cases, this study provides critical insights into surveillance strategies and pathogenesis of irAEs.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>DIRE</kwd><kwd>ICI-induced diabetes mellitus</kwd><kwd>ICI-induced thyroid dysfunction</kwd><kwd>irAEs</kwd><kwd>sintilimab</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name><meta-value>TRUE</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>
1. Introduction</title><p>In recent years, immune checkpoint inhibitors (ICIs) have emerged as powerful new drugs for the treatment of cancer. Immune checkpoints play a crucial role in maintaining immune tolerance and preventing autoimmune diseases. However, their inhibition by ICIs paradoxically enhances antitumor immunity while predisposing to autoimmune toxicities, reflecting the dual-edged role of ICIs in cancer therapy.</p><p>Multiglandular immune-related adverse events (irAEs) are generally associated with combined ICIs, whereas those induced by single ICI are uncommon.<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]</sup> However, with the widespread use of ICIs, reports of multiglandular irAEs associated with individual drugs have become more frequent.</p><p>Although the prevalence of ICI-induced diabetes mellitus (ICI-DM) is only 0.9%,<sup>[<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</sup> it can progress rapidly and become life-threatening, unlike other endocrine disorders. Up to 44% of patients experience other endocrine issues before or concurrently with diabetes, with the thyroid being the most commonly affected.<sup>[<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]</sup> This often leads to permanent hypothyroidism, which requires lifelong thyroxine supplementation, and in severe cases, can result in a thyroid crisis. However, thyroid issues often have a considerable latency period, are nonspecific in the early stages, and are difficult to identify. This significantly impacts the quality of life for patients and can disrupt ongoing antitumor therapy and prognosis.</p><p>The prescribing information often mention that delayed immune-related events (DIRE) may occur after discontinuation of ICIs, but in practice, reports of such cases are rare. DIRE was defined as new irAE manifesting&#x02005;&#x02265;&#x02005;90 days after discontinuation of immunotherapy.<sup>[<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]</sup> For patients with prior ICIs exposure, heightened vigilance for DIRE is critical to prevent misattribution-related harms: delayed autoimmune disease management and inappropriate discontinuation of beneficial therapies. In this context, we report a case of fulminant type 1 diabetes (FT1DM) and thyroid dysfunction with gastric adenocarcinoma induced by sintilimab. To our knowledge, this is a rare case of sintilimab-induced ICI-DM and ICI-induced thyroid dysfunction (ICI-TD). Additionally, the uniqueness of the case lies in the fact that his diabetes developed 4 months after discontinuing sintilimab.</p><p>We also review previous reports of these concurrent irAEs, aiming to assist clinicians in the early detection, diagnosis, prevention, and management of these conditions to reduce their severity and improve patient outcomes.</p></sec><sec sec-type="cases"><title>
2. Case presentation</title><sec><title>2.1. Initial diagnosis of gastric cancer</title><p>We presented a 60-year-old Chinese male patient with no prior history of diabetes mellitus or thyroid dysfunction, and a medical history of hypertension managed with regular nifedipine and valsartan. In February 2023, gastroscopy revealed a gastric antral lesion confirmed as poorly differentiated adenocarcinoma. Intraoperative findings showed extensive peritoneal metastases (pT4NxM1), prompting palliative gastrojejunostomy due to unresectability.</p></sec><sec><title>2.2. Treatment course and thyroid function changes</title><p>One month postoperatively, the patient was initiated on the SOX chemotherapy regimen (oxaliplatin&#x02005;+&#x02005;S-1) combined with sintilimab and apatinib (Fig. <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Prior to initial treatment, the patient&#x02019;s blood glucose levels and thyroid function were within normal limits, except for elevated thyroid peroxidase antibodies (TPOAb) level. Color Doppler ultrasonography demonstrated multiple discrete nodules without diffuse parenchymal changes.</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Timeline of patient treatment process.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="medi-104-e42490-g001" position="float"/></fig><p>The patient tolerated the first treatment cycle well. However, laboratory evaluations prior to cycle 2 revealed a marginally elevated T4 level (Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). During pre-cycle 3 screening, the patient was found to have developed thyrotoxicosis. Nevertheless, no significant symptoms were observed, requiring no therapeutic intervention, and anticancer therapy proceeded as scheduled.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Thyroid function test results during hospitalization.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 d before the first cycle</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 d after the first cycle</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 d after the second cycle</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61 d after the third cycle</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 d after the fourth cycle</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">149 d after the fourth cycle</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TSH</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.38</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.883</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.017&#x02193;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.072&#x02191;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.984</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.592&#x02191;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FT3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FT4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.66</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.23</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.09&#x02191;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69&#x02193;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">186.98&#x02191;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">328.38&#x02191;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54&#x02193;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">278.95&#x02191;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.45&#x02193;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TPOAb</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.3&#x02191;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TgAb</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thyroid ultrasound</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">multiple nodules&#x0ff0c;TIRADS-3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Levothyrocine</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100 &#x003bc;g/d</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100 &#x003bc;g/d</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100 &#x003bc;g/d</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other"><p>Normal range: FT3 (pmol/L): 3.5 to 6.5; FT4 (pmol/L): 7.01 to 15.96; TPOAb (IU/mL): 0 to 9; TgAb (IU/mL): 0 to 0.4; TSH (mU/L): 0.56 to 5.91; T3 (nmol/L): 1.012 to 2.479; T4 (nmol/L): 69.97 to 152.51.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>Abbreviations: FT3 = free triiodothyronine, FT4 = free thyroxine, T3 = triiodothyronine, T4 = thyroxine, TgAb = thyroglobulin antibody, TPOAb = thyroid peroxidase antibody, TSH = thyroid stimulating hormone.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>In July 2023, during thyroid function reassessment, laboratory evaluation revealed a T4 level of 54 nmol/L, T3 of 0.69 nmol/L, and TSH of 34.072 mU/L, consistent with overt hypothyroidism. Based on these findings, levothyroxine replacement therapy was initiated at 100 &#x003bc;g daily. During this treatment phase, the patient opted to discontinue the SOX regimen and received sintilimab combined with apatinib as monotherapy.</p><p>The August 2023 follow-up evaluation demonstrated persistent elevation of T4 with other thyroid function parameters remaining within normal limits. However, disease progression was identified during the examination, leading to the discontinuation of sintilimab after completing 4 cycles. After that, the patient self-discontinued levothyroxine and continued monotherapy with apatinib for approximately 1 month. Subsequently, the patient underwent no further antitumor therapy.</p></sec><sec><title>2.3. FT1DM after the discontinuation of sintilimab</title><p>Four months after the discontinuation of sintilimab, the patient was readmitted for follow-up treatment due to persistent nausea, vomiting, and abdominal pain. On the second day of admission, the patient presented with altered consciousness and critical blood biochemical values: glucose level was 42.01 mmol/L, urgent blood gas analysis revealed a pH of 6.922, and blood ketone body level was 2+. Given the diagnosis of diabetic ketoacidosis (DKA), immediate symptomatic treatment, including continuous insulin infusion and fluid supplementation, was initiated.</p><p>Subsequent tests revealed a glycated hemoglobin level of 7.5%, an insulin level of 0.46 &#x003bc;IU/L at 0 hours, a C-peptide level of &#x0003c;0.02 &#x003bc;g/L at 0 hours. Additionally, the negative islet-related antibodies (Table <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref>) and the disparity between HbA1c and blood glucose levels indicated an acute disruption of islet function, which was fulfilled Japanese Diabetes Society 2012 criteria for FT1DM.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Diagnostic laboratory parameters for diabetes and diabetic ketoacidosis.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Laboratory data</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Result</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference range</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sodium</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">137</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">136 to 146 mmol/L</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Potassium</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.7&#x02191;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4 to 4.5 mmol/L</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PH</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.922&#x02193;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.35 to 7.45</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pCO<sub>2</sub></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.1&#x02193;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 to 45&#x02009;mm Hg</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>-</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4&#x02193;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 to 26 mmol/L</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anion gap</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.9&#x02191;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0 to 16.0 mmol/L</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lactate</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0&#x02191;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 to 1.6 mmol/L</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glucose</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.01&#x02191;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.90 to 6.10 mmol/L</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Serum C-peptide</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0ff1c;0.02&#x02193;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1 to 4.4 &#x000b5;g/mL</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GADA</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.02</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 to 10 IU/mL</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IAA</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 to 1 COI</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICA</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 to 1 COI</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HbA1c</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5&#x02191;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6% to 6.0%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blood ketone bodies</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2+&#x02191;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other"><p>Abbreviations: GADA&#x02005;=&#x02005;glutamic acid decarboxylase antibody, HbA1c = hemoglobin A1c, IAA = insulin autoantibody, ICA = islet cell antibody.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The patient&#x02019;s blood glucose levels were monitored for approximately 1 month during hospitalization. Despite continuous adjustment of the insulin dose based on the patient&#x02019;s blood glucose levels, the coefficient of variation of glucose remained high at 50%, and the patient experienced 2 severe hypoglycemic episodes (Fig. <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). This was speculated to be related to the nearly complete loss of C-peptide secretion within 1 month after disease onset, indicating the patient had entered a fragile stage of diabetes.</p><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Range of blood glucose fluctuations during hospitalization with 2 hypoglycemic episodes.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="medi-104-e42490-g002" position="float"/></fig><p>After stabilizing blood glucose levels, the insulin C-peptide release test indicated a complete lack of insulin secretion (Table <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). At discharge, given the patient&#x02019;s poor islet function, the treatment plan included administering 3 units of rapid-acting insulin before each meal and 6 units of long-acting insulin before bed.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Islet function before discharge.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Islet function</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Result</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference range</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">INS0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.45</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6 to 24.9 mIU/L</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">INS1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">INS2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">INS3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C-P</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1 to 4.4&#x000b5;g/L</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C1h</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C2h</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C3h</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other"><p>Abbreviations: C-P&#x02005;=&#x02005;C-peptide; INS&#x02005;=&#x02005;insulin.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Given that all of the patient&#x02019;s previous blood glucose records were within the normal range, we have reason to suspect that the patient&#x02019;s current diabetes mellitus is induced by sintilimab.</p><p>During this hospitalization, laboratory tests revealed hypothyroidism, prompting the continuation of levothyroxine therapy (100 &#x003bc;g/d) for thyroid hormone replacement. Following this, the patient received Traditional Chinese Medicine (specific therapeutic regimen not documented) and was subsequently lost to follow-up at our institution.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>
3. Methods</title><p>Limited data exists on concurrent endocrinopathies in patients receiving ICIs. Therefore, it is essential to consolidate these cases. We conducted a search of English-language case reports on ICI-DM combined with ICI-TD up to May 2024 using Medical Subject Headings (MeSH) terms and keywords from PubMed. Additionally, we performed a secondary search of the bibliographies of all included manuscripts.</p><p>A total of 27 reports<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]</sup> involving 30 patients were retrieved. Each case provided the following details: year of publication, patient&#x02019;s age, gender, tumor type, type of ICI, previous medical history, previous medication history, onset time of diabetes, HbA1c levels, C-peptide levels, presence of DKA, islet autoantibodies, human leukocyte antigen (HLA) genotypes, onset time of thyroid dysfunction, types of thyroid dysfunction, thyroid autoantibodies, other glands involved and medications used (Table <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">4</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Detailed case summary of ICI-induced thyroid dysfunction and diabetes (n&#x02005;=&#x02005;30).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No.</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1<sup>[<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]</sup></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2<sup>[<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]</sup></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]</sup></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4<sup>[<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]</sup></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5<sup>[<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]</sup></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6<sup>[<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]</sup></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7<sup>[<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]</sup></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8<sup>[<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]</sup></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9<sup>[<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]</sup></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10<sup>[<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Publication year</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2024</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2024</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2023</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2023</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2022</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2022</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2021</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2021</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2020</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2020</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (yr)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cancer type</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Malignant vaginal melanoma</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SCC (urethral)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GE junction adenocarcinoma</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SCC (oropharynx)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lung adenocarcinoma</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NSCLC</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Melanoma</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Melanoma</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cutaneous<break/>melanoma</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parotid adenocarcinoma</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICI type</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nivolumab<break/>+<break/>ipilimumab</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Camrelizumab</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pembrolizumab</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Teriprizumab</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pembrolizumab</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pembrolizumab</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nivolumab</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ipilimumab+ nivolumab</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pembrolizumab</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nivolumab</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Previous medical history</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypertension and cerebral infarction</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypertension and acute ischemic stroke</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elevated blood lipids</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chronic sinusitis and thyroiditis</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Previous medication history</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Combined anlotinib</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Capecitabine, oxaliplatin</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Docetaxel, cisplatin, and tigisay</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aspirin, simvastatin, perindopril, omeprazole&#x0ff0c;Erlotinib</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Statins&#x0ff0c;carboplatin combined with pemetrexed (5 cycles)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time to diabetes onset (wk)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diabetes antibodies</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GADA (&#x02212;)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GADA (&#x02212;) IA-2A (&#x02212;) ICA (&#x02212;) IAA (&#x02212;)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GADA (&#x02212;)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GADA (+) IAA (&#x02212;)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GADA (+)<break/>ICA (&#x02212;) IAA (&#x02212;) ZnT8 (&#x02212;)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GADA (&#x02212;) IAA (+) ICA (&#x02212;)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GADA (+)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GADA (&#x02212;)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GADA (+)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GADA (&#x02212;)<break/>IA-2A (&#x02212;)<break/>ZnT8 (&#x02212;)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DKA</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HbA1c (%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C-peptide</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13&#x02009;ng/mL</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.3&#x02009;ng/mL</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.1&#x02009;ng/mL</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.01 nmol/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0ff1c;0.2&#x02009;ng/mL</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.02&#x02009;ng/mL</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6&#x02009;ng/mL</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.1&#x02009;ng/mL</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.55&#x02009;ng/mL</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HLA</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DRB1*04:05- DQB1*04:01</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DRB1*08:02-DQB1*03:02</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DRB1*04:05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time to thyrotoxicosis onset (wk)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,<break/>Normal after 100 d of medication</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16, Graves&#x02019; disease&#x0ff0c; 100 d later subclinical</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time to hypothyroidism onset (wk)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UK</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TD antibodies</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRAb(+)<break/>TPOAb(+) TgAb(+)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TPOAb(+) TgAb(+)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TPOAb(&#x02212;) TRAb(&#x02212;)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRAB(&#x02212;)<break/>TPOAb(+) TgAb(+)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TPOAb(+)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TPOAb(+) TgAb(&#x02212;)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TPOAb(+) TgAb(+)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TPOAb(&#x02212;)<break/>TgAb(&#x02212;)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TPOAb(&#x02212;)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRAb(+)<break/>TPOAb(&#x02212;) TgAb(&#x02212;)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Therapeutic drug</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-T4 (50 &#x000b5;g/d)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-T4 (75 &#x000b5;g/d) Normal after 1 mo of medication</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Propranolol</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-T4 (112 &#x000b5;g/d)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-T4 (75 &#x000b5;g/d)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Methimazole (2.5&#x02009;mg/d)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other glands involved</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICI-induced hypophysitis</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primary adrenal insufficiency (Addison disease)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crohn disease</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Isolated adrenocorti-cotropin</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hepatitis, adrenal insufficien-cy, arthritis and vitiligo</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICI-induced pneumonitis&#x0ff0c; polymyalgia rheumatica</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other Drugs</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HC (15&#x02009;mg/d)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HC</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mesalazine</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HC</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HC</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No.</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11<sup>[<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]</sup></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12<sup>[<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]</sup></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13<sup>[<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]</sup></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14<sup>[<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]</sup></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15<sup>[<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]</sup></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16<sup>[<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]</sup></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17<sup>[<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]</sup></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18<sup>[<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]</sup></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19<sup>[<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]</sup></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20<sup>[<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Publication year</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2020</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2020</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2019</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2019</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2019</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2019</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2019</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2019</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2018</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2018</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (yr)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cancer type</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SCC (lung)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High-grade neuroendocrine rectal tumor</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lung adenocarcinoma</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carcinoma of bladder</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Melanoma</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NSCLC</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ulcerated acral melanoma</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Melanoma</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lung adenocarcinoma</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Renal cell carcinoma</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICI type</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Durvalumab</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nivolumab</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Durvalumab</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Durvalumab</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pembrolizumab</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pembrolizumab</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pembrolizumab</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nivolumab</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nivolumab</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nivolumab</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Previous medical history</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, hypertension, dyslipidemia, pulmonary embolism&#x0ff0c; benign prostatic hyperplasia</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prostate cancer, hypertension&#x0ff0c;gout</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arterial hypertension, psoriasis, subclinical hyperthyroidism</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x03000;&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x03000;&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asthma&#x0ff0c; paroxysmal atrial fibrillation, gastro-esophageal reflux disease and hypertension</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x03000;&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subclinical hypothyroidism</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Previous medication history</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x03000;&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x03000;&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Enalapril</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inhaled corticosteroids and salbutamol</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x03000;&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pemetrexed, cisplatin</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sunitinib&#x0ff0c; interferon &#x003b1; combined with axitinib for 25 mo</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time to diabetes onset (wk)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diabetes antibodies</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GADA (+)<break/>ICA (&#x02212;)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GADA (+)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GADA (+) ICA (&#x02212;) ZnT8 (&#x02212;)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GADA (+) IA-2A (+)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GADA (&#x02212;)<break/>ICA (&#x02212;)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GADA (+) ICA (&#x02212;) IA-2A (&#x02212;)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GADA (+) IA-2A (+)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GADA (&#x02212;) IA-2A (&#x02212;)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GADA (+)<break/>ICA (&#x02212;)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GADA (&#x02212;)<break/>IA-2A (&#x02212;) ZnT8 (&#x02212;) IAA (&#x02212;)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DKA</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HbA1c (%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C-peptide</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;10&#x02009;ng/mL</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86 pmol/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02ng/mL</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.01&#x02009;&#x000b5;g/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02 nmol/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22 nmol/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Undetectable</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24&#x02009;ng/mL</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HLA</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DRB1*04-DQA1*03:01-DQB1*03:02</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DRB1*04:16-DQB1*02:05-DQA1*01:03</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DQB1*02/ DQB1 *06:02- DQA1 *01:02</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DRB1*09:01-DQB1*03:03</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time to thyrotoxicosis onset (wk)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3&#x02009;wk subclinical</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8&#x02009;wk subclinical</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time to hypothyroidism onset (wk)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">next weeks</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 wk</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UK</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TD antibodies</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TPOAb(&#x02212;)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TPOAb(+)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TPOAb(&#x02212;)<break/>TgAb(&#x02212;)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TPOAb(+) TgAb(+)<break/>TRAb(+)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TPOAb(&#x02212;)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TPOAb(&#x02212;)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TPOAb(+) TgAb(&#x02212;)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TPOAb(&#x02212;)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRAB(&#x02212;)<break/>TPOAb(+) TgAb(+)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Therapeutic drug</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-T4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-T4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-T4 (50 &#x000b5;g/d)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-T4<break/>(200 &#x000b5;g/d)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-T4 (125 &#x000b5;g/d)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-T4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-T4 (75 &#x000b5;g/d)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-T4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-T4 (50 &#x000b5;g/d)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-T4 (100&#x000b5;g/d)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other glands involved</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x03000;&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vitiligo</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other drugs</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x03000;&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x03000;&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No.</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21<sup>[<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]</sup></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22<sup>[<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]</sup></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23<sup>[<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]</sup></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24<sup>[<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]</sup></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25<sup>[<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]</sup></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26<sup>[<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]</sup></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27<sup>[<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]</sup></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28<sup>[<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]</sup></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29<sup>[<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]</sup></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30<sup>[<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Publication year</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2018</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2018</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2018</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2018</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2018</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2017</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2016</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2016</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2016</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2015</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (yr)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cancer type</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Melanoma</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Melanoma</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SCC (oropharynx)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Melanoma</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Melanoma</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SCC (lung)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Lung adenocarcinoma</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Melanoma</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SCC (lung)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SCC (jaw)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICI type</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pembrolizumab</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pembrolizumab</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pembrolizumab</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pembrolizumab</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ipilimumab+Pembrolizumab</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nivolumab</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ipilimumab&#x02005;+&#x02005;Pembrolizumab</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Ipilimumab&#x02005;+&#x02005;Nivolumab</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pembrolizumab</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PD-1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Previous medical history</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypertension, right nephrectomy</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x03000;&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T2DM</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypertension</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Previous medication history</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x03000;&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Combined carboplatin/5-FU</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cisplatin</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metformin&#x0ff0c;glimepiride</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paclitaxel&#x0ff0c;carboplatingemcitabine</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x03000;&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time to diabetes onset (wk)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diabetes antibodies</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GADA (&#x02212;)<break/>IA-2A (&#x02212;) ZnT8(&#x02212;)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GADA (&#x02212;) IA-2A (&#x02212;)<break/>ZnT8(&#x02212;)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GADA (+) IA-2A (&#x02212;) IAA (&#x02212;) ZnT8 (&#x02212;)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GADA (+) IA-2A (&#x02212;)<break/>IAA (+)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GADA (+) IA-2A (&#x02212;)<break/>IAA (&#x02212;)<break/>ZnT8 (&#x02212;)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GADA (+)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GADA (+) ICA (&#x02212;)<break/>IAA (&#x02212;) ZnT8 (&#x02212;)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GADA (+)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IAA (&#x02212;) ICA (&#x02212;) GADA (&#x02212;)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GADA (+) IA-2A (&#x02212;) IAA (&#x02212;) ZnT8 (&#x02212;)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DKA</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HbA1c(%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C-peptide</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 1 nmol/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.1 nmol/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.3 nmol/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11 nmol/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12 nmol/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">undetectable</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.1&#x02009;ng/mL</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03 nmol/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.1ng/mL</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HLA</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DRB1*01:01-DQA1*01-DQB1*05:01/<break/>DRB1*16:01-DQA1*01-DQB1*05:02</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DRB1*04:01 DQA1*02 DQB1*02:02/ DRB1*07:01 DQA1*03 DQB1*03:01</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DRB1*04-DQB1*03:02</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DRB1*03/DRB1*04 DQB1*03:02</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DRB1*03/ DRB1*15-DQB1*06</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HLA-I A2 and HLA-II DQB1*06:02</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DRB1*09:01-DQB1*03:03/<break/>DRB1*14:05-DQB1*05:03</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DR3-DQ2/DR4-DQ8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time to thyrotoxicosis onset (wk)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HT</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HT</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8&#x02009;wk thyroiditis</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24&#x02009;wk thyroiditis</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x02009;wk subclinical</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x03000;&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time to hypothyroidism onset (wk)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UK</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UK</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TD antibodies</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TPOAb(+)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TPOAb(+)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x03000;&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TPOAb(+)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TPOAb(+)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRAb(+)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRAb(&#x02212;)<break/>TPOAb(&#x02212;)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TPOAb(+)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Therapeutic drug</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x03000;&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-T4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-T4 (1.7&#x02009;mg/kg/d)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-T4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x03000;&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other glands involved</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maculopapular rash</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rash, arthriti</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rash, inflammatory polymyopathy</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rash</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Rash, tachycardia,<break/>and reports of hot flashes&#x0ff0c;ICI-induced hypophysitis</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x03000;&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other drugs</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x03000;&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x03000;&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">prednisone and metoprolol</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x03000;&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other"><p>Abbreviations: &#x02013;&#x02005;=&#x02005;not report, HC = hydrocortisone, HT = Hashimoto thyroiditis, IA-2A = islet antigen-2 antibody, UK = it happened but the specific time is unknown, ZnT8 = Zinc transporter 8.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>
4. Discussion</title><sec sec-type="results"><title>
4.1. Summary of the results</title><p>The median age of the collected patients was 61 years (range 23&#x02013;85 years), with a male predominance of 63.3%. Melanoma and lung cancer constituted the most frequent malignancies, comprising 40% and 30% of confirmed cases, respectively, both historically prioritized for ICI therapies due to earlier regulatory approvals. Other tumor types included esophageal cancer, rectal cancer, oropharyngeal squamous cell carcinoma, and others.</p><p>Over half of the patients received programmed cell death protein 1 (PD-1) inhibitors, including nivolumab, toripalimab, camrelizumab, and pembrolizumab. Three patients received programmed death-ligand 1 (PD-L1) inhibitors. Five patients received PD-1 combined with cytotoxic T-lymphocyte antigen 4 (CTLA-4) inhibitors: 3 with ipilimumab-nivolumab and 2 with ipilimumab-pembrolizumab.</p><p>Due to inconsistent descriptions of the timing of adverse reactions in each case report, we organized the cases on a weekly basis. A summary of the results can be found in Table <xref rid="T5" ref-type="table">5</xref>. The 30 cases of ICI-DM occurred between 3 to 45 weeks after treatment initiation (median 8 weeks), with 23 out of 30 patients presenting with DKA at diabetes onset. The following requires clinical attention: although ICI-induced DKA mostly presents with gastrointestinal symptoms, some patients may exhibit only polyuria, thirst, fatigue, agitation, or blurred vision but still develop severe DKA.<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]</sup> Additionally, ICI-DM can sometimes be difficult to control, with patients experiencing recurrent DKA even under insulin management.<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]</sup></p><table-wrap position="float" id="T5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Characteristics of ICI-induced thyroid dysfunction and diabetes (n&#x02005;=&#x02005;30).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristic</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All cases (n&#x02005;=&#x02005;30)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Age, yr</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Median (range)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61 (23&#x02013;85)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Gender</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Female/male</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 vs 19</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Tumor types</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Melanoma</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12/30 (40%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Lung cancer</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9/30 (30%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Other cancers</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9/30 (30%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Immune checkpoint inhibitor</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;PD-1 inhibitor</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22/30 (73.3%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;PD-L1 inhibitor</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/30 (10%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;PD-1&#x02005;+&#x02005;CTLA-4 inhibitors</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/30 (16.7%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Time to diabetes onset, wk</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Median (range)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (3&#x02013;45)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;GADA pos./GADA neg. (median)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 vs 14</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diabetic ketoacidosis</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23/30 (76.7%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;GADA pos./GADA neg.</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.2% vs 61.5%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hemoglobin A1c, median (range)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.9% (5.6%&#x02013;9.4%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low or undetectable C-peptide</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26/30 (86.7%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elevated lipase</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/30 (3.3%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elevated amylase</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/30 (3.3%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Diabetes antibodies</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;GADA (+)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18/30 (60%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;IAA (+)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/30 (6.7%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;IA-2A (+)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/30 (6.7%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;ICA (+)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;ZnT8 (+)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothyroidism following thyrotoxicosis</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11/30 (36.7%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;PD-1 inhibitor</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6/11 (54.5%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;PD-L1 inhibitor</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/11 (9.1%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;PD-1&#x02005;+&#x02005;CTLA-4 inhibitors</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/11 (36.4%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothyroidism alone</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11/30 (36.7%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thyrotoxicosis alone</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/30 (16.6%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not Report</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/30 (10%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">TD antibodies</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;TPOAb(+)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16/30 (53.3%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;TgAb(+)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6/30 (20 %)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;TRAb(+)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/30 (10 %)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">The sequence of occurrence</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;ICI-DM before ICI-TD</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7/30 (23.3%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;ICI-TD before ICI-DM</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7/30 (23.3%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;ICI-DM and ICI-TD concurrent</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13/30 (43.4%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Not Report</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/30 (10 %)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other"><p>Abbreviations: CTLA-4 = cytotoxic T-lymphocyte antigen 4, GADA = glutamic acid decarboxylase antibody, IA-2A = islet antigen-2 antibody, IAA = insulin autoantibody, ICA = islet cell antibody, ICI-DM = ICI-induced diabetes mellitus, ICI-TD = ICI-induced thyroid dysfunction, PD-1 = programmed cell death protein 1, PD-L1 = programmed death-ligand 1, TgAb&#x02005;=&#x02005;thyroglobulin antibody, TPOAb = thyroid peroxidase antibody, TRAb = thyroid stimulating hormone receptor antibody, ZnT8 = Zinc transporter 8.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Based on the rapid onset of the disease, ICI-DM is primarily characterized by FT1DM. At diagnosis, the median HbA1c level was 7.9% (range 5.6%&#x02013;9.4%), indicating only mild elevation, even within the normal range, which contrasts with the hyperglycemic symptoms observed. Nearly all ICI-DM patients exhibited reduced or undetectable C-peptide levels, distinguishing it from classic type 1 diabetes (T1DM), where C-peptide is detectable in approximately 93% of patients within the first 2 years of onset. Regarding autoantibodies, 40% of patients were autoantibody-negative, while 60% tested positive for glutamic acid decarboxylase antibodies (GADA), the predominant autoantibody, although the detection rate of this antibody was still lower than the 80% reported in classic T1DM.</p><p>Although organ-specific antibodies like GADA may be involved in irAEs, their exact role remains unclear. Rather than being a direct cause of diabetes, GADA may instead reflect an underlying autoimmune predisposition.<sup>[<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]</sup> Interestingly, previous studies<sup>[<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]</sup> support our findings, by showing that GADA positivity is associated with an earlier onset of ICI-DM (median 6 weeks vs 14 weeks) and a higher risk of DKA (88.2% vs 61.5%), suggesting that GADA may serve as a marker of more aggressive or advanced immune dysregulation.</p><p>Eleven patients developed hypothyroidism subsequent to thyrotoxicosis, 4 of which were associated with PD-1 and CTLA-4 inhibitors. Of course, we only collected 5 patients who were receiving dual ICI therapy. This supports the increased risk of transitioning from thyrotoxicosis to hypothyroidism with combination therapy.<sup>[<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]</sup> Additionally, 11 cases presented with hypothyroidism alone, while only 5 cases showed thyrotoxicosis (2 without long-term follow-up). Previous study has suggested that ICI-induced overt thyrotoxicosis (with or without hypothyroidism) and hypothyroidism (without thyrotoxicosis) may have distinct etiologies, rather than being different manifestations of the same disease process.<sup>[<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]</sup> Two patients<sup>[<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]</sup> who only developed hypothyroidism clearly tested positive for antibodies before treatment, which somewhat supports the view that hypothyroidism (without thyrotoxicosis) may be accelerated by ICI treatment for preexisting subclinical Hashimoto thyroiditis (HT), rather than ICI-induced new thyroiditis. Interestingly, the patient in our case was also TPOAb positive before treatment, but after treatment, we observed a change from thyrotoxicosis to hypothyroidism. In our summary of cases, we did find that the incidence of extrathyroid irAEs, such as primary adrenal insufficiency, secondary adrenal insufficiency, hypophysitis, and vitiligo, was significantly higher in patients with overt thyrotoxicosis (with or without transient hypothyroidism) compared to those with hypothyroidism. Thyroid dysfunction was detected in 7 cases before the onset of diabetes, 7 cases afterward, and concurrently with diabetes in 13 cases, with other 3 cases not reported. Thyrotoxicosis and hypothyroidism induced by ICIs often present asymptomatically or with fatigue similar to that caused by antitumor treatments, making them easily overlooked and detected concurrently with diabetes. This can result in cases where thyrotoxicosis is initially missed, potentially leading to an increase in cases presenting solely as hypothyroidism over time.</p><p>Early elevation of serum thyroglobulin (Tg)<sup>[<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]</sup> and preexisting Tg autoimmunity have been linked to PD-1 inhibitors&#x02013;induced destructive thyroiditis.<sup>[<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]</sup> Baseline thyroglobulin antibody (TgAb) or TPOAb positivity and irregular thyroid ultrasound findings are considered potential risk factors for ICI-TD,<sup>[<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]</sup> though the role of these antibodies remains debated. Some studies<sup>[<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]</sup> identify TgAb as an independent risk factor, while others<sup>[<xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]</sup> suggest TPOAb may predict hypothyroidism following thyrotoxicosis. However, some studies have indicated that there is no association between baseline TPOAb and TgAb levels and the risk of ICI-TD.<sup>[<xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]</sup> Currently, it remains inconclusive whether elevated thyroid autoantibodies are the causative factor of thyroid dysfunction or a humoral immune response triggered by the release of thyroid antigen during the development of destructive thyroiditis.<sup>[<xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]</sup> However, conflicting evidence exist,<sup>[<xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]</sup> and many ICI-TD patients lack detectable thyroid autoantibodies, implying alternative or antibody-independent mechanisms. Seventeen cases were positive for thyroid autoantibodies. However, due to the lack of detailed information on the actual progression of thyroid diseases, it is difficult to accurately determine the early onset of thyroid diseases in thyroid autoantibodies positive patients. Further prospective studies are required to draw conclusive results.</p></sec><sec><title>
4.2. The pathogenesis of ICI-DM and ICI-TD</title><p>The etiology of ICI-DM and ICI-TD remains incompletely understood, though T cell-mediated immunity is likely central. PD-1 possesses a protective effect within the human body,<sup>[<xref rid="R43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]</sup> and its expression in CD4+ T cells and Tregs is notably reduced in diabetic individuals. Similarly, diminished CTLA-4 expression has been observed in FT1DM,<sup>[<xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]</sup> suggesting that both checkpoints critically regulate disease progression. Preclinical studies reveal PD-1 inhibition accelerates diabetes onset across age groups, while CTLA-4 inhibition primarily affects young non-obese diabetic mice,<sup>[<xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]</sup> indicating distinct roles: CTLA-4 regulates na&#x000ef;ve T cells, whereas PD-1 controls both na&#x000ef;ve and autoimmune T cell activation. In a mouse model of diabetes, depleting CD8+ T cells temporarily cured the disease, while depleting CD4+ T cells failed to halt its progression.<sup>[<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]</sup> This suggests that activated autoimmune T cells are predominantly CD8+ T cells, consistent with the observation of specific IFN-&#x003b3; CD8+ T cells infiltrating the islets and almost completely destroying islet &#x003b2; cells in hyperglycemic mice treated with PD-L1 antibodies. &#x003b2; cells themselves protect against detrimental crosstalk with proinsulin-specific CD8+ T cells. Changes in the &#x003b2; cell environment, such as a selective deficiency of PD-L1 on target cells or the absence of PD-1 on T cells, may render pancreatic &#x003b2; cells more vulnerable to attacks by proinsulin-specific CD8+ T cells.<sup>[<xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]</sup> Additionally, PD-1 inhibitors can inhibit T cell migration, prolonging interaction time, promoting the coupling of T cells and major histocompatibility complex (MHC), enhancing T cell activation, and triggering cell-mediated autoimmune diabetes.<sup>[<xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]</sup> This can result in a sudden decrease in insulin storage, leading to DKA.</p><p>Cell-mediated cytotoxicity appears to have no significant impact on &#x003b1; cells and exocrine glands.<sup>[<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]</sup> Intriguingly, although glucagon levels remain stable, &#x003b1; cell responsiveness appears reduced.<sup>[<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]</sup> Elevated lipase and amylase in 2 ICI-DM patients<sup>[<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]</sup> suggest possible exocrine involvement, and some studies have reported antibodies against exocrine enzymes.<sup>[<xref rid="R48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]</sup> However, nonspecific enzyme elevation without diabetes has also been observed. Hence, further assessment of exocrine gland and &#x003b1; cell damage is requisite.</p><p>Consistent with ICI-DM findings, increased CD8+ T cell infiltration in affected organs plays a crucial role in the development of ICI-TD. Kobayashi<sup>[<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]</sup> identified that destructive thyroiditis is the main cause of PD-1 inhibitors induced thyroid dysfunction. Elevated levels of IL-2 (a Th1 cytokine) and reduced levels of MCP-1 (a Th2 chemokine) in the ICI-TD group indicate an increase in the Th1/Th2 balance,<sup>[<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]</sup> consistent with the Th1 imbalance observed in HT.<sup>[<xref rid="R49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]</sup> CD8+ T cells activated by IL-2 may destroy immune tolerance, targeting not only tumor cells but also attacking thyroid cells, leading to ICI-TD.</p><p>Interestingly, CD4+ T cells also play a crucial role in PD-1 inhibitors induced destructive thyroiditis. In a thyroglobulin-preimmunized mouse model of thyroid irAEs, Yasuda et al<sup>[<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]</sup> observed thyroidal infiltration of CD4+ T cells. Depletion of CD4+ T cells completely prevented disease progression, whereas CD8+ T cell depletion only partially did so, suggesting that Tg-specific cytotoxic CD4+ T cells may directly damage thyroid follicular cells via MHC Class II and regulate CD8+ T cell cytotoxicity.</p><p>There is no consensus on whether B-cell-mediated humoral immunity is involved in the development of ICI-DM and ICI-TD. Yasuda et al<sup>[<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]</sup> propose that humoral immunity is unlikely to play a predominant role in PD-1 inhibitors induced destructive thyroiditis, as depletion of CD20 B cells in mice did not prevent the progression. Moreover, DKA can occur without GADA, indicating that cell-mediated immune activation alone can occur without humoral immunity shortly before clinical presentation.<sup>[<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]</sup> However, opposing evidence exists: B cells and tertiary lymphoid structures have been observed in the tumors of ICI responders.<sup>[<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]</sup> What&#x02019;s more, although the number of Graves&#x02019; disease patients induced by ICI is relatively rare, our summary table includes 1 case that may have been caused by the activation of B cells and plasma cells by CD4+ T helper cells, leading to the production of thyroid stimulating hormone receptor antibodies.<sup>[<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]</sup></p></sec><sec><title>
4.3. Human leukocyte antigen associated with autoimmune diseases</title><p>Currently, it is widely believed that HLA is a genetic background element associated with autoimmune diseases, playing a crucial role in immune responses. The genetic polymorphism of HLA is closely linked to variations in the intensity of immune responses to foreign antigens.<sup>[<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]</sup> Immunotherapy may accelerate disease progression in individuals carrying diabetes-predisposing HLA alleles.<sup>[<xref rid="R50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]</sup></p><p>The presence of HLA-DR3 and/or DR4, especially with HLA-DQ3, indicates shared susceptibility to T1DM and thyroid autoimmunity.<sup>[<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]</sup> HLA haploid analysis was conducted on 15 patients with ICI-DM and ICI-TD, and susceptibility genes were identified in twelve patients. Specific haplotypes &#x02013; DRB1<bold>*</bold>08:02-DQA1<bold>*</bold>04:01&#x02013;DQB1<bold>*</bold>04:02 and DRB1<bold>*</bold>09:01&#x02013;DQA1<bold>*</bold>03:02&#x02013;DQB1<bold>*</bold>03:03 &#x02013; are more frequent in HT and T1DM patients than in controls, and were identified in 3 patients.<sup>[<xref rid="R51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]</sup> Interestingly, although DQB1*06 is considered protective in some autoimmune diseases.<sup>[<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]</sup> It was found in 3 patients, including 1 with both DR3 and DQ6, suggesting that protective haplotypes may not be superior to susceptible haplotypes in ICI-related irAEs.</p><p>A Japanese study<sup>[<xref rid="R52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]</sup> found DRB1<bold>*</bold>09:01&#x02013;DQB1<bold>*</bold>03:03 predominant in GADA-positive FT1DM, and DRB1<bold>*</bold>04:05&#x02013;DQB1<bold>*</bold>04:01 in GADA-negative FT1DM. However, Among the 3 patients with the aforementioned haplotypes that we know of, 2 do not support this view. Therefore, HLA typing alone is not a reliable method for predicting ICI-related irAEs in clinical practice.</p></sec><sec><title>
4.4. ICI-TD and ICI-DM caused by sintilimab</title><p>Sintilimab is a fully humanized IgG4 monoclonal antibody targeting PD-1, exhibiting a mechanism of action similar to nivolumab and pembrolizumab while demonstrating higher affinity for human PD-1.<sup>[<xref rid="R53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]</sup> Initially approved by China in 2018, sintilimab was later evaluated in the phase III ORIENT-16 trial involving patients with unresectable locally advanced or metastatic gastric and gastroesophageal junction adenocarcinoma. This study demonstrated that sintilimab plus chemotherapy significantly improved overall survival for all patients and for patients with a combined positive score of 5 or more compared with placebo plus chemotherapy.<sup>[<xref rid="R54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]</sup> At present, the combination of sintilimab with chemotherapy has been established as a first-line treatment option for gastric cancer across all patient subgroups.</p><p>Following sintilimab treatment, the patient sequentially developed ICI-TD and ICI-DM, both classified as irAEs in the ORIENT-16 study. According to the latest prescribing information summarizing clinical trial data, the incidence of hypothyroidism and hyperthyroidism was 17.4% and 8.9%, respectively, while the incidence of hyperglycemia and T1DM was 1.3%, with a median time to onset of 105 days (range: 9&#x02013;494 days). The prescribing information also notes that irAEs may occur during treatment or after discontinuation.</p><p>This case demonstrates several distinctive features. To begin with, this represents a rare case of sintilimab-induced ICI-DM and ICI-TD. In addition, ICI-DM does not occur during sintilimab. The delayed-onset of adverse events after treatment cessation is consistent with the findings of Couey et al,<sup>[<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]</sup> who reported that over half of DIRE cases occured following short courses of immunotherapy with &#x02264;4 treatment cycles, which matches the treatment course of our patient. Furthermore, although Seo et al<sup>[<xref rid="R55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]</sup> have reported delayed-onset diabetes occurring 4 to 6 months after therapy with nivolumab, atezolizumab, and ipilimumab, this is the first documented case associated with sintilimab, with onset more than 4 months after discontinuation. The mechanism may involve sustained PD-1 receptor occupancy on T cells following treatment discontinuation, as previous studies have demonstrated up to 40% receptor occupancy persisting 8 months after cessation of nivolumab therapy.<sup>[<xref rid="R56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]</sup></p><p>Although concurrent medications (tegafur, oxaliplatin, and apatinib) were administered, literature review excluded their causal roles. Tegafur and oxaliplatin lack reported endocrine toxicity, while apatinib&#x02019;s prescribing information describes hyperglycemia but not FT1DM. The hyperglycemia induced by it may be associated with insulin resistance.</p><p>As for thyroid dysfunction, the most recent hospital evaluation of the patient revealed that the hypothyroidism had persisted for over 5 months. It has been 3 months since apatinib was discontinued, which aligns more closely with the timeline of ICI-TD. Furthermore, thyroid dysfunction induced by ICIs are often challenging to reverse. The patient experienced a transition from thyrotoxicosis to hypothyroidism, with the pathological process more closely resembling the primary mechanism of ICI-TD, which is destructive thyroiditis. We found reports of sunitinib being associated with lymphocytic thyroiditis,<sup>[<xref rid="R57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]</sup> but current studies with the largest number of participants on apatinib-induced hypothyroidism have not clearly documented this process.<sup>[<xref rid="R58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]</sup> The temporal association and pathological evidence strongly implicate that sintilimab is the causative factor.</p><p>Routine monitoring during ICIs administration enables early detection of most adverse events. However, for patients with a history of ICI exposure, clinicians must remain vigilant about the potential emergence of DIRE, even months after discontinuing ICI therapy. In the event of disease occurrence, it is essential to consider not only recent treatments and interventions but also to carefully differentiate DIRE from other conditions to avoid misattribution. Misattribution may lead to delayed treatment or inappropriate discontinuation of beneficial therapies. It is also recommended that drug prescribing information for ICIs explicitly include a specified period of continued monitoring following drug discontinuation.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>
5. Limitations</title><p>This retrospective case study has inherent limitations due to incomplete data entries, which could potentially confound the causality assessment between ICIs and irAEs. Furthermore, the absence of postdischarge follow-up data precludes longitudinal observation of disease progression and prognostic evaluation. Existing literature suggests that previous treatment with TKIs appears to be a significant risk factor for developing hypothyroidism during PD-1 inhibitors therapy,<sup>[<xref rid="R59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]</sup> whereas no such association was found with previous chemotherapy.<sup>[<xref rid="R60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]</sup> Notably, our current hypothesis cautiously attributes the observed thyroid dysfunction primarily to sintilimab in this case, though future large-scale prospective studies are warranted to validate this causal relationship.</p></sec><sec><title>
6. Conclusion</title><p>We present a rare case of sintilimab-induced thyroid dysfunction and diabetes mellitus. Our case suggests that ICI-DM can occur not only during the period of medication but also within a certain period after discontinuation of the sintilimab.</p><p>We reviewed previous case reports to elaborate on the clinical manifestations, autoantibodies, potential pathogenesis, and reported factors influencing the prediction of these 2 endocrine irAEs, with the aim of enhancing clinicians&#x02019; awareness.</p></sec><sec><title>Author contributions</title><p><bold>Data curation:</bold> Wenxue Zhang, Xiaolu Gao.</p><p><bold>Investigation:</bold> Ying Zan, Wenxue Zhang.</p><p><bold>Methodology:</bold> Yedong Wei.</p><p><bold>Writing &#x02013; original draft:</bold> Ying Zan, Yedong Wei, Xiaolu Gao.</p><p><bold>Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing:</bold> Ying Zan, Jigang Si.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="abbr"><p>
<def-list><title>Abbreviations:</title><def-item><term>CD20 B cells</term><def><p>CD20 positive B cells</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CD4+T cell</term><def><p>CD4 positive T cells</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CD8+T cell</term><def><p>CD8 positive T cells</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>C-P</term><def><p>C-peptide</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CTLA-4</term><def><p>cytotoxic T-lymphocyte antigen 4</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DIRE</term><def><p>delayed immune-related events</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DKA</term><def><p>diabetic ketoacidosis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FT1DM</term><def><p>fulminant type 1 diabetes mellitus</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FT3</term><def><p>free triiodothyronine</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FT4</term><def><p>free thyroxine</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GAD</term><def><p>glutamic acid decarboxylase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GADA</term><def><p>glutamic acid decarboxylase antibody</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HbA1c</term><def><p>hemoglobin A1c</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HC</term><def><p>hydrocortisone</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HLA</term><def><p>human leukocyte antigen</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HT</term><def><p>Hashimoto thyroiditis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IA-2A</term><def><p>islet antigen-2 antibody</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IAA</term><def><p>insulin autoantibody</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ICA</term><def><p>islet cell antibody</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ICI-DM</term><def><p>ICI-induced diabetes mellitus</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ICIs</term><def><p>immune checkpoint inhibitors</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ICI-TD</term><def><p>ICI-induced thyroid dysfunction</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IFN-&#x003b3;</term><def><p>interferon &#x003b3;</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IL-2</term><def><p>interleukin-2</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>INS</term><def><p>insulin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>irAEs</term><def><p>immune-related adverse events</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MeSH</term><def><p>medical subject headings</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MHC</term><def><p>major histocompatibility complex</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NOD</term><def><p>non-obese diabetic</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PD-1</term><def><p>programmed cell death protein 1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PD-L1</term><def><p>programmed death-ligand 1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>pH</term><def><p>potential of hydrogen</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SOX</term><def><p>tegafur gimeracil oteracil and oxaliplatin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>T1DM</term><def><p>type 1 diabetes</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>T3</term><def><p>triiodothyronine</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>T4</term><def><p>thyroxine</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Tg</term><def><p>thyroglobulin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TgAb</term><def><p>thyroglobulin antibody</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Th1</term><def><p>T helper 1 cells</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Th2</term><def><p>T helper 2 cells</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TKI</term><def><p>tyrosine kinase inhibitor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TPOAb</term><def><p>thyroid peroxidase antibody</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TRAb</term><def><p>thyroid stimulating hormone receptor antibody</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Tregs</term><def><p>regulatory T cells</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TSH</term><def><p>thyroid stimulating hormone</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ZnT<sub>8</sub></term><def><p>zinc transporter 8</p></def></def-item></def-list>
</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group><fn fn-type="other"><p>Ethical approval was not required for the study involving human in accordance with the local legislation and institutional requirements. Written consent was obtained from the patient for publication.</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>The authors have no funding and conflicts of interest to disclose.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>The datasets generated during and/or analyzed during the current study are publicly available.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>How to cite this article: Zan Y, Wei Y, Zhang W, Gao X, Si J. Sintilimab-induced diabetes mellitus and thyroid dysfunction in patient with gastric adenocarcinoma: A case report and literature review. Medicine 2025;104:20(e42490).</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>[1]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salangsang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sapkota</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kharel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalla</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A case of pembrolizumab-induced diabetic ketoacidosis and hyperthyroidism in a patient with recurrent esophageal adenocarcinoma.</article-title>
<source>Cureus</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>e35276</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36825072</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>[2]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stamatouli</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Quandt</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Perdigoto</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Collateral damage: insulin-dependent diabetes induced with checkpoint inhibitors.</article-title>
<source>Diabetes</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>67</volume>:<fpage>1471</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>80</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29937434</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>[3]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsang</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Menzies</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Risk factors and characteristics of checkpoint inhibitor-associated autoimmune diabetes mellitus (CIADM): a systematic review and delineation from type 1 diabetes.</article-title>
<source>Diabetes Care</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>46</volume>:<fpage>1292</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37220262</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>[4]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Couey</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Delayed immune-related events (DIRE) after discontinuation of immunotherapy: diagnostic hazard of autoimmunity at a distance.</article-title>
<source>J ImmunoTher Cancer</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>165</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31269983</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>[5]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kidawara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kadoya</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kakutani-Hatayama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Koyama</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A case in which HLA-DR4 is involved in the development of complex immune-related endocrinological adverse events following combination therapy with nivolumab and ipilimumab.</article-title>
<source>Case Rep Endocrinol</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>2024</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>[6]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Challenges in autoimmune polyendocrine syndrome type 2 with the full triad induced by anti-programmed cell death 1: a case report and review of the literature.</article-title>
<source>Front Immunol</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>1366335</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38707904</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>[7]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Immune checkpoint inhibitor therapy-induced autoimmune polyendocrine syndrome type II and Crohn&#x02019;s disease: a case report.</article-title>
<source>World J Clin Cases</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>3267</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>74</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37274046</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>[8]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cunha</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Vieira</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Saraiva</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Duarte</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>New onset autoimmune diabetes mellitus and hypothyroidism secondary to pembrolizumab in a patient with metastatic lung cancer.</article-title>
<source>Endocrinol Diabet Metab Case Rep</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>2022</volume>:<fpage>21</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>0123</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>[9]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Anti&#x02011;PD&#x02011;1 immune checkpoint inhibitor inducing endocrine toxicity in a patient with advanced lung cancer: a case report and literature review.</article-title>
<source>Exp Ther Med</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>681</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36185768</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>[10]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ishiguro</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogata</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohashi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Type 1 diabetes associated with immune checkpoint inhibitors for malignant melanoma: a case report and review of 8 cases.</article-title>
<source>Medicine (Baltimore)</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>101</volume>:<fpage>e30398</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36107581</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>[11]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Afzal</surname><given-names>MZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Shirai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Ipilimumab and nivolumab induced immune-related adverse events in metastatic mucosal melanoma.</article-title>
<source>BMJ Case Rep</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>e243713</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>[12]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kethireddy</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bindal</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Shukla</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hegde</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Multiple autoimmune side effects of immune checkpoint inhibitors in a patient with metastatic melanoma receiving pembrolizumab.</article-title>
<source>J Oncol Pharm Pract</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>207</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32390537</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>[13]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kurihara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Oikawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakajima</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Simultaneous development of Graves&#x02019; disease and type 1 diabetes during anti&#x02010;programmed cell death&#x02010;1 therapy: a case report.</article-title>
<source>J Diabetes Invest</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1006</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>[14]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lopes</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Russo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Development of autoimmune diabetes with severe diabetic ketoacidosis and immune-related thyroiditis secondary to durvalumab: a case report.</article-title>
<source>Transl Lung Cancer Res</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>2149</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>56</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33209634</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>[15]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haque</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Zilbermint</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Nivolumab-induced autoimmune diabetes mellitus and hypothyroidism in a patient with rectal neuroendocrine tumor.</article-title>
<source>J Commun Hospital Internal Med Perspectives</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>338</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>[16]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chin</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenfield</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Durvalumab-induced diabetic ketoacidosis followed by hypothyroidism.</article-title>
<source>Endocrinol Diabet Metab Case Rep</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>2019</volume>:<fpage>19</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>0098</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>[17]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meng&#x000ed;bar</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Capel</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonfill</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Simultaneous onset of type 1 diabetes mellitus and silent thyroiditis under durvalumab treatment.</article-title>
<source>Endocrinol Diabet Metab Case Rep</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>2019</volume>:<fpage>19</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>0045</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>[18]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hakami</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ioana</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tun</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><name><surname>Sreenan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>McDermott</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A case of pembrolizumab-induced severe DKA and hypothyroidism in a patient with metastatic melanoma.</article-title>
<source>Endocrinol Diabet Metab Case Rep</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>2019</volume>:<fpage>18</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>0153</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>[19]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Filette</surname><given-names>JMK</given-names></name><name><surname>Pen</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Decoster</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Immune checkpoint inhibitors and type 1 diabetes mellitus: a case report and systematic review.</article-title>
<source>Eur J Endocrinol</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>181</volume>:<fpage>363</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>74</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31330498</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>[20]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gunjur</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Kee</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Cebon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Anti-programmed cell death protein 1 (anti-PD1) immunotherapy induced autoimmune polyendocrine syndrome type II (APS-2): a case report and review of the literature.</article-title>
<source>J ImmunoTher Cancer</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>241</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31488221</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>[21]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lupi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Brancatella</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cosottini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical heterogeneity of hypophysitis secondary to PD-1/PD-L1 blockade: insights from four cases.</article-title>
<source>Endocrinol Diabet Metab Case Rep</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>2019</volume>:<fpage>19</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>0102</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>[22]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tzoulis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Corbett</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Ponnampalam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Nivolumab-induced fulminant diabetic ketoacidosis followed by thyroiditis.</article-title>
<source>Endocrinol Diabet Metab Case Rep</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>2018</volume>:<fpage>18</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>0111</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>[23]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sakurai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Niitsuma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Arihara</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Painless thyroiditis and fulminant type 1 diabetes mellitus in a patient treated with an immune checkpoint inhibitor, nivolumab.</article-title>
<source>Tohoku J Exp Med</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>244</volume>:<fpage>33</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>40</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29343652</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>[24]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marchand</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Thivolet</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dalle</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Diabetes mellitus induced by PD-1 and PD-L1 inhibitors: description of pancreatic endocrine and exocrine phenotype.</article-title>
<source>Acta Diabetol</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>56</volume>:<fpage>441</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30284618</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>[25]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Galligan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Fourlanos</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Diabetes associated with immune checkpoint inhibition: presentation and management challenges.</article-title>
<source>Diabet Med</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>1283</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>90</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>[26]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Masood</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yavuz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Grosbach</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Autoimmune diabetes and thyroiditis complicating treatment with nivolumab.</article-title>
<source>Case Rep Oncol</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>230</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28611636</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>[27]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alhusseini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Samantray</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Autoimmune diabetes superimposed on type 2 diabetes in a patient initiated on immunotherapy for lung cancer.</article-title>
<source>Diabet Metab</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>43</volume>:<fpage>86</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>[28]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Salama</surname><given-names>AKS</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathews</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanks</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Genetic risk analysis of a patient with fulminant autoimmune type 1 diabetes mellitus secondary to combination ipilimumab and nivolumab immunotherapy.</article-title>
<source>J Immunother Cancer</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>89</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28031819</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>[29]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwak</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Anti-programmed cell death 1 therapy triggering diabetic ketoacidosis and fulminant type 1 diabetes.</article-title>
<source>Acta Diabetol</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>53</volume>:<fpage>853</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27300348</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>[30]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mellati</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Eaton</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Brooks-Worrell</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Anti&#x02013;PD-1 and Anti&#x02013;PDL-1 monoclonal antibodies causing type 1 Diabetes.</article-title>
<source>Diabetes Care</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>e137</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26116720</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>[31]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jaberi-Douraki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>SWS</given-names></name><name><surname>Pietropaolo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Autoimmune responses in T1DM: quantitative methods to understand onset, progression and prevention of disease.</article-title>
<source>Pediatr Diabetes</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>162</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>74</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24827702</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>[32]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muir</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Clifton-Bligh</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>GV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Thyroid immune-related adverse events following immune checkpoint inhibitor treatment.</article-title>
<source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>106</volume>:<fpage>e3704</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>13</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33878162</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>[33]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kurimoto</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Inaba</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ariyasu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Predictive and sensitive biomarkers for thyroid dysfunctions during treatment with immune-checkpoint inhibitors.</article-title>
<source>Cancer Sci</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>111</volume>:<fpage>1468</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>77</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32086984</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>[34]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yasuda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugiyama</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells are essential for the development of destructive thyroiditis induced by anti&#x02013;PD-1 antibody in thyroglobulin-immunized mice.</article-title>
<source>Sci Transl Med</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>eabb7495</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33980577</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>[35]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kimbara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujiwara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Association of antithyroglobulin antibodies with the development of thyroid dysfunction induced by nivolumab.</article-title>
<source>Cancer Sci</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>109</volume>:<fpage>3583</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>90</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30230649</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>[36]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Okada</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Okuji</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Anti-thyroid antibodies and thyroid echo pattern at baseline as risk factors for thyroid dysfunction induced by anti-programmed cell death-1 antibodies: a prospective study.</article-title>
<source>Br J Cancer</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>122</volume>:<fpage>771</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32009131</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>[37]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yasuda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Patients with antithyroid antibodies are prone to develop destructive thyroiditis by nivolumab: a prospective study.</article-title>
<source>J Endocr Soc</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>241</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>51</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29600292</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>[38]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ando</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Arima</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Risk of thyroid dysfunction in PD-1 blockade is stratified by the pattern of TgAb and TPOAb positivity at baseline.</article-title>
<source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>108</volume>:<fpage>e1056</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>62</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37084392</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>[39]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yano</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashida</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagata</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Nivolumab-induced thyroid dysfunction lacking antithyroid antibody is frequently evoked in Japanese patients with malignant melanoma.</article-title>
<source>BMC Endocr Disord</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>36</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29884162</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>[40]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>H-F</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H-Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Immune checkpoint inhibitors-related thyroid dysfunction: epidemiology, clinical presentation, possible pathogenesis, and management.</article-title>
<source>Front Endocrinol</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>649863</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>[41]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mazarico</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Capel</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Gim&#x000e9;nez-Palop</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Low frequency of positive antithyroid antibodies is observed in patients with thyroid dysfunction related to immune check point inhibitors.</article-title>
<source>J Endocrinol Invest</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>1443</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>50</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31093955</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>[42]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamauchi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakane</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukuda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical features of nivolumab-induced thyroiditis: a case series study.</article-title>
<source>Thyroid</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>894</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>901</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28537531</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>[43]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsutsumi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Jie</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Ihara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Phenotypic and genetic analyses of T-cell&#x02010;mediated immunoregulation in patients with Type 1 diabetes.</article-title>
<source>Diabet Med</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>1145</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>50</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16978382</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><label>[44]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fujisawa</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Haseda</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsutsumi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Low programmed cell death (PD-1) expression in peripheral CD4+ T cells in Japanese patients with autoimmune type 1 diabetes.</article-title>
<source>Clin Exp Immunol</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>180</volume>:<fpage>452</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25682896</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><label>[45]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ansari</surname><given-names>MJI</given-names></name><name><surname>Salama</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Chitnis</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The programmed death-1 (PD-1) pathway regulates autoimmune diabetes in nonobese diabetic (NOD) mice.</article-title>
<source>J Exp Med</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>198</volume>:<fpage>63</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12847137</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><label>[46]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rajasalu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Brosi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuster</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/>. <article-title>Deficiency in B7-H1 (PD-L1)/PD-1 coinhibition triggers pancreatic beta-cell destruction by insulin-specific, murine CD8 T-cells.</article-title>
<source>Diabetes</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>59</volume>:<fpage>1966</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>73</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20484136</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><label>[47]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fife</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><name><surname>Pauken</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Eagar</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Interactions between PD-1 and PD-L1 promote tolerance by blocking the TCR&#x02013;induced stop signal.</article-title>
<source>Nat Immunol</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>1185</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>92</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19783989</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><label>[48]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Panicot</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Mas</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Thivolet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lombardo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Circulating antibodies against an exocrine pancreatic enzyme in type 1 Diabetes.</article-title>
<source>Diabetes</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>48</volume>:<fpage>2316</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>23</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10580419</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><label>[49]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chaker</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bianco</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Jonklaas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Peeters</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Hypothyroidism.</article-title>
<source>Lancet</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>390</volume>:<fpage>1550</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>62</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28336049</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><label>[50]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kochupurakkal</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kruger</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Tripathi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Blockade of the programmed death-1 (PD1) pathway undermines potent genetic protection from type 1 diabetes. Ahmad R, ed.</article-title>
<source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e89561</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24586872</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><label>[51]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hashimoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Maruyama</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishiyama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Susceptibility alleles and haplotypes of human leukocyte antigen DRB1, DQA1, and DQB1 in autoimmune polyglandular syndrome type III in Japanese Population.</article-title>
<source>Horm Res</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>64</volume>:<fpage>253</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>60</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16254435</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R52"><label>[52]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsutsumi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Imagawa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikegami</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Makino</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanafusa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>; <collab>Japan Diabetes Society Committee on Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus Research</collab>. <article-title>Class II HLA genotype in fulminant type 1 diabetes: a nationwide survey with reference to glutamic acid decarboxylase antibodies.</article-title>
<source>J Diabetes Investig</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>62</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R53"><label>[53]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fei</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Jing</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/>. <article-title>Durable blockade of PD-1 signaling links preclinical efficacy of sintilimab to its clinical benefit.</article-title>
<source>mAbs</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1443</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>51</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31402780</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R54"><label>[54]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/>. <article-title>Sintilimab plus chemotherapy for unresectable gastric or gastroesophageal junction cancer: the ORIENT-16 randomized clinical trial.</article-title>
<source>JAMA</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>330</volume>:<fpage>2064</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38051328</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R55"><label>[55]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ham</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>New-onset type 1 diabetes mellitus as a delayed immune-related event after discontinuation of nivolumab.</article-title>
<source>Medicine (Baltimore)</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>101</volume>:<fpage>e30456</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36107574</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R56"><label>[56]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brahmer</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Drake</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Wollner</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Phase I study of single-agent anti&#x02013;programmed death-1 (MDX-1106) in refractory solid tumors: safety, clinical activity, pharmacodynamics, and immunologic correlates.</article-title>
<source>J Clin Oncol</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>3167</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>75</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20516446</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R57"><label>[57]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alexandrescu</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Popoveniuc</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Farzanmehr</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Dasanu</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dawson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Wartofsky</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Sunitinib-associated lymphocytic thyroiditis without circulating antithyroid antibodies.</article-title>
<source>Thyroid</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>809</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18631016</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R58"><label>[58]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical observation of apatinib-related hypothyroidism in patients with advanced malignancies.</article-title>
<source>Exp Ther Med</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>1961</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32782505</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R59"><label>[59]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rizza</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sbardella</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Gianfrilli</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Thyroid profile during the alternative Sunitinib dosing 2/1 schedule in metastatic renal cell carcinoma.</article-title>
<source>Endocrine</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>67</volume>:<fpage>597</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>604</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31679139</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R60"><label>[60]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sbardella</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Tenuta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sirgiovanni</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Thyroid disorders in programmed death 1 inhibitor&#x02010;treated patients: is previous therapy with tyrosine kinase inhibitors a predisposing factor?</article-title>
<source>Clin Endocrinol (Oxf)</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>92</volume>:<fpage>258</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>65</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31788837</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>