<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Breast Cancer Res Treat</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Breast Cancer Res Treat</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Breast Cancer Research and Treatment</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0167-6806</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1573-7217</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer US</publisher-name><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39327358</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11785703</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">7478</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10549-024-07478-5</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The efficacy of screening with FDG-PET/CT for distant metastases in breast cancer patients scheduled for neoadjuvant systemic therapy</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" equal-contrib="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-9287-8181</contrib-id><name><surname>Gunster</surname><given-names>Jetske L. B.</given-names></name><address><email>j.gunster@nki.nl</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-3694-4049</contrib-id><name><surname>van Duijnhoven</surname><given-names>Frederieke H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3242-4989</contrib-id><name><surname>Scholten</surname><given-names>Astrid N.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1046-2634</contrib-id><name><surname>Smorenburg</surname><given-names>Carolien H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-7650-8407</contrib-id><name><surname>Dezentje</surname><given-names>Vincent O.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6971-2688</contrib-id><name><surname>van Olmen</surname><given-names>Josefien P.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-0189-5953</contrib-id><name><surname>Marijnen</surname><given-names>Corrie A. M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-8131-5690</contrib-id><name><surname>Stokkel</surname><given-names>Marcel P. M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8155-7051</contrib-id><name><surname>Loo</surname><given-names>Claudette E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-2260-3983</contrib-id><name><surname>Schrijver</surname><given-names>A. Marjolein</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/03xqtf034</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.430814.a</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0674 1393</institution-id><institution>Department of Radiation Oncology, </institution><institution>Netherlands Cancer Institute-Antoni van Leeuwenhoek, </institution></institution-wrap>Amsterdam, Plesmanlaan 121, 1066 CX The Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/05xvt9f17</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.10419.3d</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 8945 2978</institution-id><institution>Department of Radiation Oncology, </institution><institution>Leiden University Medical Center, </institution></institution-wrap>Leiden, The Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/03xqtf034</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.430814.a</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0674 1393</institution-id><institution>Department of Surgical Oncology, </institution><institution>Netherlands Cancer Institute-Antoni Van Leeuwenhoek, </institution></institution-wrap>Amsterdam, The Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/03xqtf034</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.430814.a</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0674 1393</institution-id><institution>Department of Medical Oncology, </institution><institution>Netherlands Cancer Institute-Antoni Van Leeuwenhoek, </institution></institution-wrap>Amsterdam, The Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/03xqtf034</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.430814.a</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0674 1393</institution-id><institution>Department of Nuclear Medicine, </institution><institution>Netherlands Cancer Institute-Antoni Van Leeuwenhoek, </institution></institution-wrap>Amsterdam, The Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/03xqtf034</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.430814.a</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0674 1393</institution-id><institution>Department of Radiology, </institution><institution>Netherlands Cancer Institute-Antoni Van Leeuwenhoek, </institution></institution-wrap>Amsterdam, The Netherlands </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>26</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>26</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>209</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>117</fpage><lpage>124</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>3</day><month>4</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2024</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Purpose</title><p id="Par1">This study aims to identify which breast cancer patients benefit from the routine use of FDG-PET/CT in a large cohort of patients scheduled for neoadjuvant systemic therapy (NST).</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">A total of 1337 breast cancer patients eligible for NST were identified from a retrospective database between 2011 and 2020 at a single tertiary care hospital. All patients underwent staging with FDG-PET/CT prior to NST. The incidence and extent of asymptomatic distant metastases in different patient subgroups were determined, as well as the impact on treatment. Logistic regression analysis was used to identify prognostic patient and tumor characteristics.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">FDG-PET/CT detected distant metastases in 109 patients (8%). Initial clinical stage was a prognostic factor for the presence of distant metastases, with a significantly higher risk for stage 2b and 3 as opposed to lower stages (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001). The incidence of distant metastases was 3% (4/125) for stage 1, 2% (8/534) for stage 2a, 7% (24/354) for stage 2b and 23% (73/324) for stage 3. Other characteristics such as age, tumor subtype, histological type and grade were not correlated with the risk of distant metastases. Among the subset of patients with distant metastases, 46% received palliative treatment, while the remaining 54% were diagnosed with oligometastatic breast cancer and were treated with curative intent.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par4">The results of the current study support the routine use of FDG-PET/CT for the detection of distant metastases in breast cancer patients with initial clinical stage 2b and 3, regardless of tumor subtype.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Breast cancer</kwd><kwd>Neoadjuvant systemic therapy</kwd><kwd>FDG-PET/CT</kwd><kwd>Distant metastases</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Springer Science+Business Media, LLC, part of Springer Nature 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par5">Breast cancer is the most commonly diagnosed malignancy among women worldwide [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Accurate evaluation of the extent of disease is essential before initiating treatment, as it impacts prognosis and treatment strategy. Early detection of distant metastases may change curative into palliative therapy, reducing treatment burden for patients.</p><p id="Par6">In early stage breast cancer, initial staging is primarily focused on evaluating the extent of locoregional disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. While international clinical guidelines acknowledge the need for additional screening for distant metastases in patients with certain clinical features, there is considerable variation in recommendations between guidelines. For example, the ESMO Clinical Practice Guidelines recommend to consider screening for distant metastases in patients with suggestive symptoms, clinically positive axillary nodes, large tumors (&#x02265;&#x02009;5 cm) or aggressive biology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. On the other hand, the NCCN Clinical Practice Guidelines in Oncology advise screening for distant metastases in patients with either suggestive signs or symptoms or in case of unresectable, clinical stage 3 disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. This lack of consensus makes it challenging to establish a uniform approach for identifying distant metastases in breast cancer patients.</p><p id="Par7">In addition, there is ongoing debate regarding the choice of imaging modality. For the detection of distant metastases, 18F-fluorodeoxyglucose positron emission tomography coupled with computed tomography (FDG-PET/CT) has shown high accuracy compared to other imaging techniques [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. However, conducting routine FDG-PET/CT in early stage breast cancer patients may result in high rates of incidental findings and increased healthcare costs[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Consequently, the decision to utilize FDG-PET/CT in the initial staging of breast cancer patients requires careful consideration, as the potential benefits need to outweigh the downsides.</p><p id="Par8">Clarification on the tailored use of FDG-PET/CT is necessary, particularly for breast cancer patients scheduled for neoadjuvant systemic therapy (NST). The identification of metastatic disease can prompt a shift in treatment strategy towards palliative care, thereby avoiding unnecessary treatment. Additionally, advancements in the treatment of oligometastatic breast cancer emphasize the critical role of accurate staging at time of diagnosis.</p><p id="Par9">This study aims to identify which breast cancer patients benefit from the routine use of FDG-PET/CT, by analyzing a large cohort of patients scheduled for NST at our institute.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Study design and participants</title><p id="Par10">All patients with breast cancer scheduled for NST were identified from a retrospective database at the Netherlands Cancer Institute. The indication for NST was determined according to (inter)national guidelines incorporating information on age, clinical stage, tumor size and histological type. Data of patients scheduled for NST between January 2011 and December 2020 were collected.</p><p id="Par11">An FDG-PET/CT scan preceded by routine conventional imaging of the primary tumor and locoregional lymph nodes was required for inclusion. Conventional imaging for locoregional staging consisted of a mammography, ultrasound of the breast and regional lymph nodes and breast MRI. Exclusion criteria were recurrent breast cancer, axillary surgery performed prior to FDG-PET/CT and suspected metastatic disease based on clinical symptoms. In case of bilateral breast cancer, the tumor with the worst prognosis was included in the analysis.</p><p id="Par12">This study was approved by the Institutional Review Board of the Netherlands Cancer Institute-Antoni van Leeuwenhoek.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Imaging</title><p id="Par13">Before the FDG-PET/CT scan, blood glucose levels of patients were required to be lower than 10 mmol/L. A weight-adjusted dose of 180&#x02013;240 MBq 18F-FDG was administered intravenously. Approximately 1 h after administration, FDG-PET/CT scanning (Philips Gemini TF Big Bore, Cleveland, OH, USA) was performed with acquisitions from the base of the skull to the groin region for regional staging and detection of distant metastases. This involved a low-dose CT scan without contrast to correct for attenuation. Additional PET/CT images in prone position were acquired for the assessment of uptake in the primary tumor.</p><p id="Par14">Increased FDG uptake, exclusively seen on FDG-PET/CT and not corresponding to physiological uptake patterns or pre-existent activity, was classified as an additional lesion. Densities seen on low-dose CT scan were classified as additional lesions as well. All scans were interpreted by experienced nuclear medicine physicians with access to relevant clinical patient data. The standard clinical reads were used for analysis and each scan was read by a single nuclear medicine physician.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Distant metastases</title><p id="Par15">Additional distant lesions were further evaluated using targeted imaging procedures and, preferably, histopathological verification. Distant metastases detected within six months of follow-up after negative FDG-PET/CT were considered as occult metastases.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Outcomes</title><p id="Par16">The primary objective was to determine the incidence of asymptomatic distant metastases using FDG-PET/CT. Overall incidence was determined, as well as stage and tumor subtype specific incidence. Clinical stage was classified according to the eighth edition of the AJCC system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>] and a distinction was made between patients with stage 2a and 2b. Tumor subtype was classified as luminal (ER&#x02009;+&#x02009;and/or PR&#x02009;+&#x02009;, HER2-), HER2-positive (ER&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;and/or PR&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;, HER2&#x02009;+) or triple-negative (ER-, PR-, HER2-). Extent of metastatic disease was classified as 1&#x02013;3, 3&#x02013;5 or more than 5 lesions. Treatment modifications were recorded, including transitions to palliative care, or in case of limited disease, to curative-intent therapy targeting metastatic lesions.</p><p id="Par17">The secondary objective was to assess the association between clinical and pathological characteristics and the detection of distant metastases with FDG-PET/CT. High-risk characteristics such as young age, advanced clinical stage, HER2-positive or triple-negative subtype and high-grade tumors were considered relevant for analysis.</p><p id="Par18">Prior to analysis, we considered an incidence of asymptomatic distant metastases above 3% to be sufficiently high to justify the routine use of FDG-PET/CT.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par19">Descriptive and explorative analyses were performed with the use of statistical software R version 4.3.0. Data were expressed as means for continuous variables and proportions for categorical variables. The threshold for statistical significance was set at p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05. Frequencies and proportions of distant metastases detected with FDG-PET/CT were calculated and reported as percentages with 95% confidence intervals. Associations between patient and tumor characteristics and distant metastases were assessed with logistic regression analysis. In case of missing values for categorical variables, the missing values were tested for randomness and excluded from analysis if appropriate. Reference levels in the logistic regression analysis required a minimum number of five events.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec9"><title>Patient characteristics</title><p id="Par20">A total of 1471 patients scheduled for NST between 2011 and 2020 had FDG-PET/CT data available. Of these patients, 1337 met the inclusion criteria and were eligible for analysis (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). The mean age was 50 years. The majority of patients had clinical stage 2a (40%) disease. Tumors of the luminal subtype were most common (47%). Most patients had grade 2 (49%) or 3 (44%) disease. An overview of the baseline characteristics is shown in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Flowchart depicting the exclusion of patients from the current analysis</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10549_2024_7478_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Clinical and pathological baseline characteristics of all patients. Abbreviations:&#x000a0;<italic>NST</italic> non-specific type, <italic>ILC</italic> invasive lobular carcinoma</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left" colspan="2">All patients (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;1337)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><bold>Age, mean (SD), years</bold></td><td align="left">50</td><td align="left">12</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Female gender</bold></td><td align="left">1335</td><td align="left">100%</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Screen detected</bold></td><td align="left">251</td><td align="left">19%</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Unilateral breast cancer</bold></td><td align="left">1284</td><td align="left">96%</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Unifocal tumor</bold></td><td align="left">912</td><td align="left">68%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3"><bold>Clinical stage prior to FDG-PET/CT</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">125</td><td align="left">9%</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2a</td><td align="left">534</td><td align="left">40%</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2b</td><td align="left">354</td><td align="left">27%</td></tr><tr><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">324</td><td align="left">24%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3"><bold>Histology</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">NST</td><td align="left">1145</td><td align="left">86%</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ILC</td><td align="left">154</td><td align="left">11%</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Other</td><td align="left">36</td><td align="left">3%</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Missing</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">0%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3"><bold>Subtype</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Luminal</td><td align="left">634</td><td align="left">47%</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HER2&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td align="left">342</td><td align="left">26%</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Triple-negative</td><td align="left">361</td><td align="left">27%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3"><bold>Grade</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">55</td><td align="left">4%</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">659</td><td align="left">49%</td></tr><tr><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">583</td><td align="left">44%</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Missing</td><td align="left">40</td><td align="left">3%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3"><bold>Ki-67</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;10%</td><td align="left">297</td><td align="left">22%</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;10%</td><td align="left">990</td><td align="left">74%</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Missing</td><td align="left">50</td><td align="left">4%</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>FDG-avid tumor</bold></td><td align="left">1287</td><td align="left">96%</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Distant metastases</title><p id="Par21">A total of 109 patients were diagnosed with asymptomatic distant metastases following FDG-PET/CT. Thus, the overall incidence of distant metastases was 8% [95%CI 7&#x02013;10%].</p><p id="Par22">Histopathological confirmation of metastatic disease was obtained in 51 patients (47%). In the remaining 58 patients (53%), final diagnosis was based on imaging, primarily FDG-PET/CT, and often supplemented with an additional CT and/or MRI scan. This could be due to inconclusive histopathological samples, the inaccessibility of lesions for biopsy, or because imaging alone was highly suggestive for metastatic disease. All cases were thoroughly reviewed and discussed in multidisciplinary meetings, where imaging findings and clinical context were carefully considered before establishing a final diagnosis.</p><p id="Par23">In the 109 patients with distant metastases, the most common sites were bone (63%), distant lymph nodes (34%), liver (23%) and lung (21%). Less common sites included the endocrine system (2%), the gastrointestinal (1%) and urogenital (1%) tract or other remaining sites (1%).</p><p id="Par24">One patient developed distant metastases within 6 months after a negative FDG-PET/CT.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Stage and subtype specific incidence of distant metastases</title><p id="Par25">The rate of distant metastases was 3% [95%CI 1&#x02013;8%] for patients with clinical stage 1 and 2% [1&#x02013;3%] for stage 2a. In patients with stage 2b and 3, these rates increased to 7% [4&#x02013;10%] and 23% [18&#x02013;28%], respectively.</p><p id="Par26">Between tumor subtypes, rates for distant metastases were similar; 9% [95%CI&#x000a0;7&#x02013;12%] for luminal, 9% [6&#x02013;12%] for HER2-positive, and 6% [3&#x02013;8%] for triple-negative tumors.</p><p id="Par27">In luminal subtype patients, rates were 5% [95%CI&#x000a0;0&#x02013;2%] for stage 1, 3% [1&#x02013;6%] for stage 2a, 7% [4&#x02013;11%] for stage 2b and 31% [17&#x02013;31%] for stage 3. For patients with HER2-positive tumors, these numbers were 4% [1&#x02013;14%], 0% [0&#x02013;3%], 9% [4&#x02013;17%] and 25% [16&#x02013;36%], and for patients with triple-negative tumors, these rates were 2% [0&#x02013;10%], 1% [0&#x02013;4%], 6% [1&#x02013;15%] and 18% [10&#x02013;28%], respectively. Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> displays the number of patients with distant metastases per subtype, categorized by stage.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Distribution of distant metastases in patients, stratified by tumor subtype and clinical stage</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10549_2024_7478_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Treatment of distant metastases</title><p id="Par28">Among the 109 patients with distant metastases, therapy shifted from curative to palliative intent in 50 patients (46%). In 46 of these patients, metastatic disease was widespread (i.e., more than 5 lesions were detected). The remaining 4 patients initially presented with distant metastases confined to 3&#x02013;5 lesions, but clinicians made the decision not to pursue curative treatment. This decision was influenced by factors such as advanced age, significant comorbidity and unresponsiveness to systemic therapy.</p><p id="Par29">In 56 patients (51%), there was a limited number of metastatic lesions, classified as oligometastatic breast cancer. Specifically, 29 patients (52%) had a single lesion, 22 patients (39%) had 2 and 2 patients (4%) had 3 lesions. The remaining 3 patients (5%) had 3&#x02013;5 metastatic lesions. All these patients underwent curative-intent treatment tailored to their condition.</p><p id="Par30">There were 3 patients (3%) with distant metastases who chose not to proceed with treatment. These patients either sought alternative therapy or declined treatment.</p><p id="Par31">Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> provides a summary of patients with distant metastases who underwent treatment with either palliative or curative intent.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Summary of patients with distant metastases by clinical stage and tumor subtype, categorized by curative and palliative treatment intent.&#x000a0; Abbreviations:&#x000a0;<italic>DM</italic> distant metastases</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2"/><th align="left" colspan="2">Total of DM</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Curative treatment</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Palliative treatment</th></tr><tr><th align="left">n</th><th align="left">%</th><th align="left">n</th><th align="left">%</th><th align="left">n</th><th align="left">%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="7"><bold>Clinical stage</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">3%</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">100%</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0%</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2a</td><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">2%</td><td align="left">7</td><td align="left">88%</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">13%</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2b</td><td align="left">24</td><td align="left">7%</td><td align="left">11</td><td align="left">46%</td><td align="left">13</td><td align="left">54%</td></tr><tr><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">73</td><td align="left">23%</td><td align="left">34</td><td align="left">47%</td><td align="left">38</td><td align="left">53%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7"><bold>Subtype</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Luminal</td><td align="left">59</td><td align="left">9%</td><td align="left">28</td><td align="left">48%</td><td align="left">30</td><td align="left">52%</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HER2&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td align="left">30</td><td align="left">9%</td><td align="left">16</td><td align="left">52%</td><td align="left">15</td><td align="left">48%</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Triple-negative</td><td align="left">20</td><td align="left">6%</td><td align="left">12</td><td align="left">60%</td><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">40%</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Patient and tumor characteristics associated with distant metastases</title><p id="Par32">In univariable analysis (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>), clinical stage 1, 2a and 2b were associated with a significantly lower risk of detecting distant metastases as compared to patients with clinical stage 3 (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001). Comparison between subgroups 2a and 2b showed a significantly higher risk of distant metastases for patients with stage 2b (OR 4.78, [95%CI 2.12&#x02013;10.77], p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001). Furthermore, triple-negative subtype showed a significantly lower risk of distant metastases as compared to luminal subtype (p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.037). No significant associations between the risk of distant metastases and age, histological type and grade were found in univariable analysis.<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Univariable and multivariable logistic regression analysis. Statistically significant values are displayed in bold formatting (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). Abbreviations: <italic>NST</italic> non-specific type, <italic>ILC</italic> invasive lobular carcinoma</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2"/><th align="left" colspan="3">Univariable analysis</th><th align="left" colspan="3">&#x000a0;Multivariable analysis</th></tr><tr><th align="left">OR</th><th align="left">95% CI</th><th align="left">P value</th><th align="left">OR</th><th align="left">95% CI</th><th align="left">P value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><bold>Age</bold></td><td align="left">1.01</td><td align="left">0.99&#x02013;1.03</td><td align="left">0.258</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7"><bold>Clinical stage</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0.11</td><td align="left">0.04&#x02013;0.32</td><td align="left">&#x02009;<bold>&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</bold></td><td align="left">0.12</td><td align="left">0.04&#x02013;0.34</td><td align="left">&#x02009;<bold>&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">2a</td><td align="left">0.05</td><td align="left">0.03&#x02013;0.11</td><td align="left">&#x02009;<bold>&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</bold></td><td align="left">0.05</td><td align="left">0.03&#x02013;0.11</td><td align="left">&#x02009;<bold>&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">2b</td><td align="left">0.25</td><td align="left">0.15&#x02013;0.41</td><td align="left"><bold>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</bold></td><td align="left">0.24</td><td align="left">0.15&#x02013;0.40</td><td align="left"><bold>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">ref</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">ref</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7"><bold>Subtype</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Luminal</td><td align="left">ref</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">ref</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HER2&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td align="left">0.94</td><td align="left">0.59&#x02013;1.49</td><td align="left">0.782</td><td align="left">1.00</td><td align="left">0.61&#x02013;1.63</td><td align="left">0.999</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Triple-negative</td><td align="left">0.57</td><td align="left">0.34&#x02013;0.97</td><td align="left"><bold>0.037</bold></td><td align="left">0.68</td><td align="left">0.39&#x02013;1.18</td><td align="left">0.168</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7"><bold>Histology</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">NST</td><td align="left">ref</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ILC</td><td align="left">1.38</td><td align="left">0.79&#x02013;2.41</td><td align="left">0.265</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Other</td><td align="left">1.48</td><td align="left">0.51&#x02013;4.29</td><td align="left">0.467</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7"><bold>Grade</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0.49</td><td align="left">0.11&#x02013;2.01</td><td align="left">0.328</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">1.34</td><td align="left">0.89&#x02013;2.01</td><td align="left">0.163</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">ref</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par33">In multivariable analysis, the association between advanced stages of disease and distant metastases remained significant (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001). No other significant associations were demonstrated in multivariable analysis (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par34">This study investigated the value of screening for distant metastases with FDG-PET/CT in a large cohort of 1337 breast cancer patients. Our findings support the use of FDG-PET/CT for identifying asymptomatic distant metastases in patients with clinical stage 2b and 3, as the incidence in these groups exceeded our preset threshold value of 3%. Furthermore, as clinical stage advanced, there was a notable rise in patients shifting to palliative therapy, highlighting the significance of FDG-PET/CT in these groups.</p><p id="Par35">The value of FDG-PET/CT for detecting asymptomatic distant metastases has been addressed in previous smaller studies. Dayes et al. conducted a randomized trial involving 369 patients with stage 2b and 3 breast cancer, comparing FDG-PET/CT with conventional imaging [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. They found that FDG-PET/CT detected distant metastases in 23% of patients, whereas conventional imaging identified distant metastases in 11%. The authors therefore recommend the use of FDG-PET/CT in clinical stage 2b and 3 breast cancer, which aligns with our findings. Additionally, a comprehensive review by Groheux et al. reached similar conclusions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Although our study was observational rather than randomized, it includes the largest cohort to date on this topic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Moreover, our study included patients with early stage breast cancer as well. Given the current discrepancies in clinical guidelines for these patients, our study significantly contributes to the existing literature on this topic.</p><p id="Par36">We observed that the identification of distant metastases by FDG-PET/CT resulted in a shift in treatment strategy for all patients. Nearly half of the patients with distant metastases received palliative treatment and the other patients underwent more extensive, curative treatment, including local ablative therapy for their metastatic lesions. As a result, FDG-PET/CT led to a more tailored treatment strategy for patients in whom asymptomatic metastatic disease was detected. The treatment options for oligometastatic breast cancer (OMBC) are continuously evolving, with ESMO guidelines advocating a multimodal approach involving systemic therapy in combination with local ablative therapy for metastases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. These recommendations are primarily based on phase two trials and cohort studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. However, recent randomized trials, such as the NRG-BR002 study, show no significant difference in survival when adding local ablative therapy to standard systemic therapy for OMBC [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. Therefore, further results from ongoing randomized trials are needed before assessing the role of FDG-PET/CT in the detection of OMBC.</p><p id="Par37">Interestingly, we did not find a significant association between tumor subtype and distant metastases. Triple-negative tumors are known to act more aggressively with an increased likelihood of distant recurrence and death in the first five years after diagnosis compared to other breast cancer subtypes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Therefore, it might be expected that these patients more often present with metastatic disease at time of diagnosis. However, this was not confirmed in our study and these findings are supported by others. Ulaner et al. performed a retrospective analysis including 232 patients with stage 1 to 3 triple-negative breast cancer. FDG-PET/CT imaging at time of diagnosis demonstrated distant metastases in 0% of stage 1 patients, 5% of stage 2a, 15% of stage 2b and 33% of stage 3 patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. These percentages are similar to the findings in our cohort, consisting of breast cancer patients with luminal and HER2-positive breast cancer as well. Important to note is that our study excluded patients with clinical evidence of distant metastases prior to FDG-PET/CT. It might be that a relatively higher proportion of patients with triple-negative tumors presented with symptoms suggesting metastatic disease at time of diagnosis. Therefore, we compared our findings with national data from the Netherlands Cancer Registry (NCR) from the same time period [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. The NCR rates showed that symptomatic, synchronous distant metastases occurred in 6% of patients with triple-negative tumors, compared to 4% with luminal and 8% with HER2-positive tumors. We therefore consider the findings in our study to be representative and conclude that triple-negative tumors are not significantly associated with the risk of distant metastases at time of diagnosis.</p><p id="Par38">To the best of our knowledge, this is the largest study investigating the role of FDG-PET/CT in the workup for breast cancer patients. With an expanding indication for NST, optimization of the diagnostic workup is important and contributes to tailored treatment. Limitations of our study include the fact that it was performed at a single institute. The retrospective design makes it prone for selection and interpretation bias. Data were extracted from FDG-PET/CT reports cited by nuclear physicians. Therefore, findings may have been influenced by subjectivity of the involved physician.</p><p id="Par39">Our study highlights the importance of clinical breast cancer stage when deciding upon the value of FDG-PET/CT. The yield of FDG-PET/CT is higher with the clinical stage increasing, but there is no consensus on a threshold value for the risk of distant metastases to justify the routine use of FDG-PET/CT or other conventional methods for the detection of distant metastases. In daily practice at our institute, physicians generally apply a threshold value of 3%, but this is arbitrary. International guidelines do not include a threshold value and different aspects should be taken into consideration when deciding upon one.</p><p id="Par40">Besides the detection of distant metastases, there are other aspects that should be carefully considered for the implementation of FDG-PET/CT in routine practice. Firstly, FDG-PET/CT may lead to the detection of additional regional lymph node metastases, consequently resulting in upstaging and changes in treatment. Secondly, an important drawback of full-body scans such as FDG-PET/CT include high rates of incidental findings, exposing patients to invasive or non-invasive additional procedures. In addition to patient distress, this may lead to extra morbidity and higher healthcare costs. Given these concerns, future research should focus on evaluating the clinical impact of FDG-PET/CT on locoregional treatment strategies and examining the implications of incidental findings unrelated to breast cancer. Additionally, the overall cost-effectiveness of FDG-PET/CT in this context should be investigated.</p><p id="Par41">In conclusion, the use of FDG-PET/CT for the detection of asymptomatic distant metastases in breast cancer patients shows a substantial value in patients with clinical stage 2b or 3.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn><fn><p>Jetske L. B. Gunster and Frederieke H. van Duijnhoven contributed equally.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors thank medical student E. Fentener van Vlissingen for her contribution in the collection of patient data and statistician Mutamba T. Kayembe for reviewing the statistical analysis.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>Jetske L.B. Gunster: Conceptualization, Data curation, Methodology, Formal analysis, Visualization, Writing&#x02014;original draft, Writing&#x02014;review &#x00026; editing. Frederieke H. van Duijnhoven: Conceptualization, Investigation, Methodology, Supervision, Writing&#x02014;review &#x00026; editing. Astrid N. Scholten: Conceptualization, Methodology, Supervision, Writing&#x02014;review &#x00026; editing. Carolien H. Smorenburg: Conceptualization, Writing&#x02014;review &#x00026; editing. Vincent O. Dezentje: Conceptualization, Writing&#x02014;review &#x00026; editing. Josefien P. van Olmen: Conceptualization, Data curation, Writing&#x02014;review &#x00026; editing. Corrie A.M. Marijnen: Supervision, Writing&#x02014;review &#x00026; editing. Marcel P.M. Stokkel: Conceptualization, Writing&#x02014;review &#x00026; editing. Claudette E. Loo: Conceptualization, Writing&#x02014;review &#x00026; editing. A. Marjolein Schrijver: Conceptualization, Data curation, Methodology, Supervision, Writing&#x02014;review &#x00026; editing.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>We did not receive any grants from funding agencies in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>Datasets are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflicts of Interest</title><p id="Par42">All authors have no relevant financial or non-financial interests to declare.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">UICC: GLOBACAN 2022: New global cancer data. Accessed August 15, 2024. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://gco.iarc.fr/today/en">https://gco.iarc.fr/today/en</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cardoso</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kyriakides</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohno</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Penault-Llorca</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Poortmans</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubio</surname><given-names>IT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Early breast cancer: ESMO clinical practice guidelines for diagnosis, treatment and follow-up</article-title><source>Ann Oncol</source><year>2019</year><volume>30</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1674</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/annonc/mdz189</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31236598</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Cardoso F, Kyriakides S, Ohno S, Penault-Llorca F, Poortmans P, Rubio IT et al (2019) Early breast cancer: ESMO clinical practice guidelines for diagnosis, treatment and follow-up. Ann Oncol 30(10):1674. 10.1093/annonc/mdz189<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31236598</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gradishar</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name><name><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Aft</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Agnese</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Allison</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Breast cancer, version 3.2020, NCCN clinical practice guidelines in oncology</article-title><source>J Natl Compr Canc Netw.</source><year>2020</year><volume>18</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>452</fpage><lpage>78</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.6004/jnccn.2020.0016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32259783</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Gradishar WJ, Anderson BO, Abraham J, Aft R, Agnese D, Allison KH et al (2020) Breast cancer, version 3.2020, NCCN clinical practice guidelines in oncology. J Natl Compr Canc Netw. 18(4):452&#x02013;78. 10.6004/jnccn.2020.0016<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32259783</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koolen</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name><surname>Vrancken Peeters</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Aukema</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>WV</given-names></name><name><surname>Oldenburg</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Hage</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>18F-FDG PET/CT as a staging procedure in primary stage II and III breast cancer: comparison with conventional imaging techniques</article-title><source>Breast Cancer Res Treat</source><year>2012</year><volume>131</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>117</fpage><lpage>126</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10549-011-1767-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21935602</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Koolen BB, Vrancken Peeters MJ, Aukema TS, Vogel WV, Oldenburg HS, van der Hage JA et al (2012) 18F-FDG PET/CT as a staging procedure in primary stage II and III breast cancer: comparison with conventional imaging techniques. Breast Cancer Res Treat 131(1):117&#x02013;126. 10.1007/s10549-011-1767-9<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21935602</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Feeney</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Patil</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Integrated positron emission tomography/computed tomography may render bone scintigraphy unnecessary to investigate suspected metastatic breast cancer</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>2010</year><volume>28</volume><issue>19</issue><fpage>3154</fpage><lpage>3159</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/JCO.2009.27.5743</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20516453</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Morris PG, Lynch C, Feeney JN, Patil S, Howard J, Larson SM et al (2010) Integrated positron emission tomography/computed tomography may render bone scintigraphy unnecessary to investigate suspected metastatic breast cancer. J Clin Oncol 28(19):3154&#x02013;3159. 10.1200/JCO.2009.27.5743<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20516453</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Niikura</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Costelloe</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Madewell</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>FDG-PET/CT compared with conventional imaging in the detection of distant metastases of primary breast cancer</article-title><source>Oncologist</source><year>2011</year><volume>16</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1111</fpage><lpage>1119</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1634/theoncologist.2011-0089</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21765193</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Niikura N, Costelloe CM, Madewell JE, Hayashi N, Yu TK, Liu J et al (2011) FDG-PET/CT compared with conventional imaging in the detection of distant metastases of primary breast cancer. Oncologist 16(8):1111&#x02013;1119. 10.1634/theoncologist.2011-0089<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21765193</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dayes</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name><name><surname>Metser</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Hodgson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Parpia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Eisen</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>George</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Impact of (18)F-Labeled fluorodeoxyglucose positron emission tomography-computed tomography versus conventional staging in patients with locally advanced breast cancer</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>2023</year><volume>41</volume><issue>23</issue><fpage>3909</fpage><lpage>3916</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/JCO.23.00249</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37235845</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Dayes IS, Metser U, Hodgson N, Parpia S, Eisen AF, George R et al (2023) Impact of (18)F-Labeled fluorodeoxyglucose positron emission tomography-computed tomography versus conventional staging in patients with locally advanced breast cancer. J Clin Oncol 41(23):3909&#x02013;3916. 10.1200/JCO.23.00249<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37235845</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rakheja</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bryce</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Babyn</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Incidence and economic impact of incidental findings on (18)F-FDG PET/CT imaging</article-title><source>Can Assoc Radiol J</source><year>2018</year><volume>69</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>63</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.carj.2017.08.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29458956</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Adams SJ, Rakheja R, Bryce R, Babyn PS (2018) Incidence and economic impact of incidental findings on (18)F-FDG PET/CT imaging. Can Assoc Radiol J 69(1):63&#x02013;70. 10.1016/j.carj.2017.08.001<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29458956</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Srour</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolcott-Sapp</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Luu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Giuliano</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Amersi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Incidental radiologic findings in breast cancer patients who undergo staging prior to neo-adjuvant chemotherapy</article-title><source>Breast J</source><year>2021</year><volume>27</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>345</fpage><lpage>351</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tbj.14172</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33491830</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Srour MK, Lee M, Wolcott-Sapp S, Luu M, Chung A, Giuliano AE, Amersi F (2021) Incidental radiologic findings in breast cancer patients who undergo staging prior to neo-adjuvant chemotherapy. Breast J 27(4):345&#x02013;351. 10.1111/tbj.14172<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33491830</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giuliano</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Connolly</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Edge</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Mittendorf</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rugo</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Solin</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Breast cancer-major changes in the American joint committee on cancer eighth edition cancer staging manual</article-title><source>CA Cancer J Clin.</source><year>2017</year><volume>67</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>290</fpage><lpage>303</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3322/caac.21393</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28294295</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Giuliano AE, Connolly JL, Edge SB, Mittendorf EA, Rugo HS, Solin LJ et al (2017) Breast cancer-major changes in the American joint committee on cancer eighth edition cancer staging manual. CA Cancer J Clin. 67(4):290&#x02013;303<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28294295</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dayes</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name><name><surname>Metser</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Hodgson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Parpia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Eisen</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>George</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Impact of (18)F-Labeled Fluorodeoxyglucose positron emission tomography-computed tomography versus conventional staging in patients with locally advanced breast cancer</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol.</source><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/JCO.23.00249</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37235845</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Dayes IS, Metser U, Hodgson N, Parpia S, Eisen AF, George R et al (2023) Impact of (18)F-Labeled Fluorodeoxyglucose positron emission tomography-computed tomography versus conventional staging in patients with locally advanced breast cancer. J Clin Oncol. 10.1200/JCO.23.00249<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37235845</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Groheux</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hindie</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Breast cancer: initial workup and staging with FDG PET/CT</article-title><source>Clin Transl Imaging</source><year>2021</year><volume>9</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>221</fpage><lpage>231</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40336-021-00426-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33937141</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Groheux D, Hindie E (2021) Breast cancer: initial workup and staging with FDG PET/CT. Clin Transl Imaging 9(3):221&#x02013;231. 10.1007/s40336-021-00426-z<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33937141</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Baghdadi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Love</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sparano</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical utility of 18F-FDG PET/CT in staging localized breast cancer before initiating preoperative systemic therapy</article-title><source>J Natl Compr Canc Netw</source><year>2020</year><volume>18</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1240</fpage><lpage>1246</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.6004/jnccn.2020.7592</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32886897</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Ko H, Baghdadi Y, Love C, Sparano JA (2020) Clinical utility of 18F-FDG PET/CT in staging localized breast cancer before initiating preoperative systemic therapy. J Natl Compr Canc Netw 18(9):1240&#x02013;1246. 10.6004/jnccn.2020.7592<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32886897</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Groheux</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Giacchetti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Espie</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vercellino</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamy</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Delord</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The yield of 18F-FDG PET/CT in patients with clinical stage IIA, IIB, or IIIA breast cancer: a prospective study</article-title><source>J Nucl Med</source><year>2011</year><volume>52</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1526</fpage><lpage>1534</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2967/jnumed.111.093864</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21880576</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Groheux D, Giacchetti S, Espie M, Vercellino L, Hamy AS, Delord M et al (2011) The yield of 18F-FDG PET/CT in patients with clinical stage IIA, IIB, or IIIA breast cancer: a prospective study. J Nucl Med 52(10):1526&#x02013;1534. 10.2967/jnumed.111.093864<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21880576</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Groheux</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hindie</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Delord</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Giacchetti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamy</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>de Bazelaire</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prognostic impact of (18)FDG-PET-CT findings in clinical stage III and IIB breast cancer</article-title><source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source><year>2012</year><volume>104</volume><issue>24</issue><fpage>1879</fpage><lpage>1887</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jnci/djs451</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23243198</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Groheux D, Hindie E, Delord M, Giacchetti S, Hamy AS, de Bazelaire C et al (2012) Prognostic impact of (18)FDG-PET-CT findings in clinical stage III and IIB breast cancer. J Natl Cancer Inst 104(24):1879&#x02013;1887. 10.1093/jnci/djs451<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23243198</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Srour</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Walcott-Sapp</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Luu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Giuliano</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Amersi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Overuse of preoperative staging of patients undergoing neoadjuvant chemotherapy for breast cancer</article-title><source>Ann Surg Oncol</source><year>2019</year><volume>26</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>3289</fpage><lpage>3294</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1245/s10434-019-07543-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31342365</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Srour MK, Lee M, Walcott-Sapp S, Luu M, Chung A, Giuliano AE, Amersi F (2019) Overuse of preoperative staging of patients undergoing neoadjuvant chemotherapy for breast cancer. Ann Surg Oncol 26(10):3289&#x02013;3294. 10.1245/s10434-019-07543-0<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31342365</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Riedl</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Slobod</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Jochelson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Morrow</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldman</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Retrospective analysis of 18F-FDG PET/CT for staging asymptomatic breast cancer patients younger than 40 years</article-title><source>J Nucl Med</source><year>2014</year><volume>55</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1578</fpage><lpage>1583</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2967/jnumed.114.143297</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25214641</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Riedl CC, Slobod E, Jochelson M, Morrow M, Goldman DA, Gonen M et al (2014) Retrospective analysis of 18F-FDG PET/CT for staging asymptomatic breast cancer patients younger than 40 years. J Nucl Med 55(10):1578&#x02013;1583. 10.2967/jnumed.114.143297<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25214641</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gennari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Andre</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrios</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Cortes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>de Azambuja</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>DeMichele</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>ESMO clinical practice guideline for the diagnosis, staging and treatment of patients with metastatic breast cancer</article-title><source>Ann Oncol</source><year>2021</year><volume>32</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1475</fpage><lpage>1495</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.annonc.2021.09.019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34678411</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Gennari A, Andre F, Barrios CH, Cortes J, de Azambuja E, DeMichele A et al (2021) ESMO clinical practice guideline for the diagnosis, staging and treatment of patients with metastatic breast cancer. Ann Oncol 32(12):1475&#x02013;1495. 10.1016/j.annonc.2021.09.019<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34678411</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guckenberger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lievens</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouma</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Collette</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Dekker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>deSouza</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Characterisation and classification of oligometastatic disease: a european society for radiotherapy and oncology and european organisation for research and treatment of cancer consensus recommendation</article-title><source>Lancet Oncol</source><year>2020</year><volume>21</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>e18</fpage><lpage>e28</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1470-2045(19)30718-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31908301</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Guckenberger M, Lievens Y, Bouma AB, Collette L, Dekker A, deSouza NM et al (2020) Characterisation and classification of oligometastatic disease: a european society for radiotherapy and oncology and european organisation for research and treatment of cancer consensus recommendation. Lancet Oncol 21(1):e18&#x02013;e28. 10.1016/S1470-2045(19)30718-1<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31908301</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Ommen-Nijhof</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Steenbruggen</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name><surname>Capel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Vergouwen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vrancken Peeters</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiersma</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonke</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Survival and prognostic factors in oligometastatic breast cancer</article-title><source>Breast</source><year>2023</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>14</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.breast.2022.12.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36549169</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">van Ommen-Nijhof A, Steenbruggen TG, Capel L, Vergouwen M, Vrancken Peeters MT, Wiersma TG, Sonke GS (2023) Survival and prognostic factors in oligometastatic breast cancer. Breast 67:14&#x02013;20. 10.1016/j.breast.2022.12.007<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36549169</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Steenbruggen</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaapveld</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Horlings</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanders</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hogewoning</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lips</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Characterization of oligometastatic disease in a real-world nationwide cohort of 3447 patients with de novo metastatic breast cancer</article-title><source>JNCI Cancer Spectr.</source><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jncics/pkab010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33977227</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Steenbruggen TG, Schaapveld M, Horlings HM, Sanders J, Hogewoning SJ, Lips EH et al (2021) Characterization of oligometastatic disease in a real-world nationwide cohort of 3447 patients with de novo metastatic breast cancer. JNCI Cancer Spectr. 10.1093/jncics/pkab010<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33977227</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Chmura SJ WK, Woodward WA, et al (2022) NRG-BR002: a phase IIR/III trial of standard of care systemic therapy with or without stereotactic body radiotherapy (SBRT) and/or surgical resection (SR) for newly oligometastatic breast cancer (NCT02364557). Meeting Abstract | ASCO Annual Meeting I. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://ascopubs.org/doi/abs/10.1200/JCO.2022.40.16_suppl.1007">https://ascopubs.org/doi/abs/10.1200/JCO.2022.40.16_suppl.1007</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Tsai CJ YJ, Guttman DM, et al. (2022) Final analysis of consolidative use of radiotherapy to block (CURB) Oligoprogression trial - a randomized study of stereotactic body radiotherapy for oligoprogressive metastatic lung and breast cancers. ASTRO Annual meeting. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.redjournal.org/article/S0360-3016(22)03266-7/fulltext#articleInformation">https://www.redjournal.org/article/S0360-3016(22)03266-7/fulltext#articleInformation</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dent</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Trudeau</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pritchard</surname><given-names>KI</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanna</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kahn</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Sawka</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Triple-negative breast cancer: clinical features and patterns of recurrence</article-title><source>Clin Cancer Res</source><year>2007</year><volume>13</volume><issue>15 Pt 1</issue><fpage>4429</fpage><lpage>4434</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-06-3045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17671126</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">Dent R, Trudeau M, Pritchard KI, Hanna WM, Kahn HK, Sawka CA et al (2007) Triple-negative breast cancer: clinical features and patterns of recurrence. Clin Cancer Res 13(15 Pt 1):4429&#x02013;4434. 10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-06-3045<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17671126</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>NU</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanderplas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Theriault</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Edge</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>YN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clinicopathologic features, patterns of recurrence, and survival among women with triple-negative breast cancer in the national comprehensive cancer network</article-title><source>Cancer</source><year>2012</year><volume>118</volume><issue>22</issue><fpage>5463</fpage><lpage>5472</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cncr.27581</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22544643</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="journal">Lin NU, Vanderplas A, Hughes ME, Theriault RL, Edge SB, Wong YN et al (2012) Clinicopathologic features, patterns of recurrence, and survival among women with triple-negative breast cancer in the national comprehensive cancer network. Cancer 118(22):5463&#x02013;5472. 10.1002/cncr.27581<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22544643</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR26" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Foulkes</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>IE</given-names></name><name><surname>Reis-Filho</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Triple-negative breast cancer</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2010</year><volume>363</volume><issue>20</issue><fpage>1938</fpage><lpage>1948</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMra1001389</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21067385</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26" publication-type="journal">Foulkes WD, Smith IE, Reis-Filho JS (2010) Triple-negative breast cancer. N Engl J Med 363(20):1938&#x02013;1948. 10.1056/NEJMra1001389<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21067385</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR27" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ulaner</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Castillo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldman</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wills</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Riedl</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinker-Domenig</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>(18)F-FDG-PET/CT for systemic staging of newly diagnosed triple-negative breast cancer</article-title><source>Eur J Nucl Med Mol Imaging</source><year>2016</year><volume>43</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1937</fpage><lpage>1944</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00259-016-3402-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27129866</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27" publication-type="journal">Ulaner GA, Castillo R, Goldman DA, Wills J, Riedl CC, Pinker-Domenig K et al (2016) (18)F-FDG-PET/CT for systemic staging of newly diagnosed triple-negative breast cancer. Eur J Nucl Med Mol Imaging 43(11):1937&#x02013;1944. 10.1007/s00259-016-3402-9<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27129866</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Netherlands Cancer Registry (NCR) (2023) <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://iknl.nl/nkr-cijfers">https://iknl.nl/nkr-cijfers</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>