<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="review-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="issn">2168-8184</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cureus</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2168-8184</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cureus</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Palo Alto (CA)</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11681952</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7759/cureus.76472</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Pediatrics</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Infectious Disease</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Healthcare Technology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Vaccination Hesitancy and Its Impact on Immunization Coverage in Pediatrics: A Systematic Review</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Muacevic</surname><given-names>Alexander</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>John R</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mohamed Elawad</surname><given-names>Sahar Ali Osman</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yagoub Mohammed</surname><given-names>Azza Abdelbagi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Ali Karar</surname><given-names>Samia Ahmed</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hassan Farah</surname><given-names>Aala Abdelrahman</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mubarak Osman</surname><given-names>Ahmed Mohamed Elamin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-5" ref-type="aff">5</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff-1">
<label>1</label>
Pediatrics, Armed Forces Hospital, Jazan, SAU </aff><aff id="aff-2">
<label>2</label>
Neonatal Intensive Care, Maternity and Children Hospital, Hail, SAU </aff><aff id="aff-3">
<label>3</label>
Pediatrics, Royal Glamorgan Hospital, Cardiff, GBR </aff><aff id="aff-4">
<label>4</label>
Pediatric Medicine, Leeds Teaching Hospitals National Health Service (NHS) Trust, Leeds Children&#x02019;s Hospital, Leeds, GBR </aff><aff id="aff-5">
<label>5</label>
General Medicine, Jouf University Medical Services Center, Jouf, SAU </aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">
Samia Ahmed Ali Karar <email>dr.samiakarar@gmail.com</email>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>27</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic"><month>12</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><issue>12</issue><elocation-id>e76472</elocation-id><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2024, Mohamed Elawad et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Mohamed Elawad et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License CC-BY 4.0., which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="https://www.cureus.com/articles/330621-vaccination-hesitancy-and-its-impact-on-immunization-coverage-in-pediatrics-a-systematic-review">This article is available from https://www.cureus.com/articles/330621-vaccination-hesitancy-and-its-impact-on-immunization-coverage-in-pediatrics-a-systematic-review</self-uri><abstract><p>One significant global health issue that is present in more than 190 nations globally is routine vaccination reluctance. This study aimed to synthesize the current evidence on vaccination hesitancy and its impact on immunization coverage in pediatrics. We searched for relevant studies across four databases (Scopus, Web of Science, PubMed/EMBASE, and Cumulated Index in Nursing and Allied Health Literature). Prespecified inclusion and exclusion criteria were used to extract relevant studies while excluding irrelevant ones. We found 4,085 studies on four different databases in which&#x000a0;23 satisfied the inclusion and exclusion criteria. These 23&#x000a0;relevant studies involving 29,131 parents, guardians, and caregivers from over 30 countries met the inclusion criteria and quality assessment. Studies were assessed for risk bias using the Newcastle-Ottawa scale.&#x000a0;Vaccination hesitancy is caused by several factors, such as cultural customs, economic reforms, perceived rumors, myths, misconceptions, physicians and other healthcare professionals, and perceived risks and problems of vaccines. These results highlight the importance of addressing demand-side factors related to socioeconomic determinants and supply-side issues such as improving health literacy, combating misinformation, ensuring clarity in communication, and promoting a consistent, evidence-based message. More observations and research should be conducted regularly to develop strategies for encouraging youngsters to receive immunizations in large quantities.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>immunization</kwd><kwd>pediatric</kwd><kwd>systematic review</kwd><kwd>vaccination coverage</kwd><kwd>vaccination hesitancy</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction and background</title><p>Vaccination is regarded as one of the most significant advancements in public health [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Vaccination programs are credited with eradicating smallpox and poliomyelitis worldwide, as well as decreasing the morbidity and mortality of other infectious diseases. For instance, polio was eradicated in India in 2014 despite challenges such as high population density and remote, hard-to-reach areas. Similarly, the African region was certified polio-free in 2020, overcoming significant barriers in conflict-affected and resource-limited settings. High levels of vaccination program uptake are necessary for the incidence and prevalence of vaccine-preventable diseases (VPDs) to be successfully decreased [<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. High vaccination rates not only provide direct protection for those who receive vaccinations&#x000a0;but also lower the risk of infection for those who are still vulnerable in the community by reducing the spread of VPD, a phenomenon known as herd immunity [<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>].</p><p>The fact that the majority of affluent nations have high childhood immunization rates,&#x000a0;with markedly reduced incidence of VPDs compared to where immunization rates are low,&#x000a0;suggests that vaccination is still a commonly used public health intervention. These national figures, however, might conceal populations with low vaccination rates [<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Undervaccinated or unvaccinated populations have been primarily blamed for recent VPD epidemics, which have included measles, poliomyelitis, and pertussis in various affluent nations. Furthermore, numerous research findings have demonstrated that even those who have had vaccinations may harbor significant reservations and worries about them [<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>-<xref rid="REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>].</p><p>Parental vaccine hesitation regarding children's vaccinations is one specific issue. Children and the communities around them suffer greatly when parents are reluctant to vaccinate, as VPDs&#x000a0;remain a significant source of morbidity and mortality. For instance, the World Health Organization (WHO) reported that, in 2019, measles caused over 207,500 deaths globally, with outbreaks being disproportionately severe in undervaccinated regions. Conversely, highly vaccinated communities have seen dramatic reductions in disease incidence and related deaths, underscoring the importance of widespread immunization efforts. About one in four parents in the United States had grave reservations about vaccinating their children, according to a 2019 nationwide study. While overall childhood immunization rates stayed high between 2012 and 2017, the number of children who were not vaccinated at the age of 24 months continued to rise, according to a 2018 report from the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) [<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. More than one-third of American children aged 19-35 months were not adhering to the advised early childhood immunization schedule, according to a March 2020 analysis of the most recent CDC National Immunization Survey data [<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].</p><p>Understanding the impact of vaccination hesitancy on pediatric immunization coverage requires a comprehensive and systematic analysis of the available evidence. The reasons for hesitancy vary widely across different settings and populations, necessitating a nuanced approach to explore the underlying causes and their consequences. Furthermore, this issue is further compounded by the rapid dissemination of misinformation through social media platforms, which has been shown to amplify parental concerns and distrust toward vaccines. Identifying and addressing these challenges is essential to design effective interventions that can mitigate hesitancy and improve vaccine uptake [<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].</p><p>This systematic review aims to synthesize the current evidence on vaccination hesitancy and its impact on immunization coverage in pediatrics. By critically examining studies from diverse geographical and cultural contexts, this review seeks to provide a comprehensive understanding of the extent of the problem, its driving factors, and its implications for public health policies. Ultimately, the findings of this review will contribute to developing targeted strategies aimed at enhancing vaccination acceptance and ensuring the sustainability of immunization programs for children worldwide.</p></sec><sec sec-type="review"><title>Review</title><p>Methodology</p><p>Study Design</p><p>The systematic review adhered to the Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses [<xref rid="REF11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] technical checklists to enhance the transparency and usability of the approach.</p><p>Search Strategy</p><p>Without considering the publishing date, we looked through four (Scopus, Web of Science, PubMed/EMBASE, and Cumulated Index in Nursing and Allied Health Literature, CINAHL) databases to find studies that were published in English. Furthermore, we searched these databases for any recent or earlier systematic reviews on the topic. EndNote software (Clarivate, London, UK) was used to merge the results from four datasets and remove duplicates.&#x000a0;Gray literature was excluded to ensure the inclusion of only high-quality, peer-reviewed studies, minimizing the risk of bias and inaccuracies. A list of the databases and search methods used is provided in Table <xref rid="TAB1" ref-type="table">1</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Search strategies used for different databases</title><p>CINAHL:&#x000a0;Cumulated Index in Nursing and Allied Health Literature</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Sr. no.
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Database
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Search string
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
1
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Scopus
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
(TITLE-ABS-KEY("vaccination hesitancy" OR "vaccine hesitancy" OR "vaccine refusal" OR "vaccine acceptance" OR "immunization delay") AND ("immunization coverage" OR "vaccination coverage" OR "vaccine uptake" OR "immunization rates") AND ("pediatrics" OR "children" OR "infants" OR "adolescents"))
</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
2
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Web of Science
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
TS=("vaccination hesitancy" OR "vaccine hesitancy" OR "vaccine refusal" OR "vaccine acceptance" OR "immunization delay") AND ("immunization coverage" OR "vaccination coverage" OR "vaccine uptake" OR "immunization rates") AND ("pediatrics" OR "children" OR "infants" OR "adolescents")
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
3
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
PubMed/EMBASE
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
(("vaccination hesitancy"[Title/Abstract] OR "vaccine hesitancy"[Title/Abstract] OR "vaccine refusal"[Title/Abstract] OR "vaccine acceptance"[Title/Abstract] OR "immunization delay"[Title/Abstract]) AND ("immunization coverage"[Title/Abstract] OR "vaccination coverage"[Title/Abstract] OR "vaccine uptake"[Title/Abstract] OR "immunization rates"[Title/Abstract]) AND ("pediatrics"[MeSH Terms] OR "children"[MeSH Terms] OR "infants"[MeSH Terms] OR "adolescents"[MeSH Terms]))
</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
4
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
CINAHL
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
("vaccination hesitancy" OR "vaccine hesitancy" OR "vaccine refusal" OR "vaccine acceptance" OR "immunization delay") AND ("immunization coverage" OR "vaccination coverage" OR "vaccine uptake" OR "immunization rates") AND ("pediatrics" OR "children" OR "infants" OR "adolescents")
</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Eligibility Criteria</p><p>The inclusion and exclusion criteria for this systematic review are listed below (Table <xref rid="TAB2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). The purpose of this was to determine how common reluctance was among guardians, parents, and other caregivers.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Inclusion and exclusion criteria</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Question elements
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Inclusion criteria
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Exclusion criteria
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Population
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Studies focusing on pediatric populations, including children and adolescents (under 18 years of age)
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Studies focusing exclusively on adult populations without any relevance to pediatrics
</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Intervention
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Studies addressing vaccination hesitancy, vaccine acceptance, or refusal in relation to childhood immunization
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Studies not directly examining vaccination hesitancy or its impact on immunization coverage
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Outcomes
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Studies reporting immunization coverage, vaccination uptake rates, or the impact of hesitancy on vaccine-preventable disease rates
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Studies that do not report measurable outcomes related to immunization coverage, vaccine uptake, or determinants of hesitancy
</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Study design
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Quantitative studies, including observational (cohort, case-control, cross-sectional) and interventional (randomized controlled trials, quasi-experimental) designs
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Case reports, commentaries, editorials, or opinion pieces
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Study language
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Studies published in English
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Non-English language publications
</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Studies Selection</p><p>The retrieved articles were saved in EndNote for further use. First, all duplicated records were extracted from the list, and titles and abstracts were reviewed and summed by two chosen authors (SAME and AAYM). Those articles that could potentially meet these criteria were searched in full-text and then cross-checked based on their eligibility against the inclusion and exclusion criteria. Cases of dissimilar scores were discussed and compared to another reviewer (AESI), who served as a tiebreaker. Data from included studies were gathered using a Microsoft&#x000ae; Excel spreadsheet (Microsoft Corporation, Redmond, WA).</p><p>Data Extraction</p><p>Papers were independently screened&#x000a0;by two reviewers (SAME and AAYM), who then ranked them according to the study design, key&#x000a0;findings, first author name, and publication year. They extracted individual data on research features, methodology, and outcome measures using a standardized form. Discussions were held to settle the disagreements about the chosen papers by the third reviewer (AESI), who served as a tiebreaker.</p><p>Risk Bias Assessment</p><p>The risk bias of the included studies was assessed using the Newcastle-Ottawa scale (NOS). To categorize studies as low, moderate, or high, we considered selection process bias, intervention bias, departure from intervention bias, missing data bias, outcome bias, and results bias. Using the inclusion and exclusion criteria, a preference for selection was determined. Performance bias was assessed by considering allocation concealment and using a control arm. Different rankings were given to data management, full industrial sponsorship, biased reporting, and selective reporting. Reviewers looked at eligibility limitations and reported consistency across several sessions. The research was chosen by a second reviewer who considered any disparities in the ratings of the reviewers.</p><p>Results</p><p>Search Results</p><p>A total of 4,085 articles were found through searches in four databases (PubMed, Scopus, Web of Science, and CINAHL). Only 23 of them passed the quality assessment and satisfied the inclusion/exclusion criteria; 29,131 parents, guardians, and other caregivers of children ages 0-6 participated in these 23 reports&#x000a0;(Figure <xref rid="FIG1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>PRISMA flowchart</title><p>PRISMA:&#x000a0;Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses</p><p>Source: [<xref rid="REF12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0016-00000076472-i01" position="float"/></fig><p>Risk Bias Assessment</p><p>NOS&#x000a0;was used to assess the risk of bias in the present review. In the 23 retrieved studies, nine had a low bias risk, 13 had a moderate bias risk, and one had a high risk. One of the most significant methodological issues that concerned the authors of the present review related to the choice of controls in some of the investigations. Additionally, all the studies failed to mention blinding controls and patients for exposure, which might have contributed to measurement bias.</p><p>For the current systematic review, using the GRADEpro Guideline Development Tool (Evidence Prime Inc., Hamilton, ON), the quality of the evidence was considered moderate across the included studies. Most of these moderate qualities were achieved by sampling a heterogeneity of the included studies and heavily using observational, randomized controlled trials. These designs do not have the component of random exposure inherent to them, which, in turn, increases the exposure to bias (Table <xref rid="TAB3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Risk of bias assessment using the Newcastle-Ottawa scale</title><p>Rating scale: seven to nine stars = low risk of bias; four to six stars = moderate risk of bias; zero to three stars = high risk of bias</p><p>Selection: 1 = Is the definition sufficient? 2 = Is the case sufficiently representative? 3 = Select control (hospital or community). 4 = Definitions of controls</p><p>Comparability: 1 = comparability of cases and controls based on design or analysis</p><p>Exposure: 1 = determining exposure; 2 = calculation controls and cases are handled using the same methodology; 3 = the rate of nonreaction</p><p>For every numbered item in the exhibit and selection categories, a study may receive one star (&#x02605;). No more than two stars (&#x02605;&#x02605;) can be awarded for comparability. The hyphen (-) in empty cells signifies that the study has not received a star</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Study</td><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Selection</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Comparability</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Exposure</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brown et al. [<xref rid="REF13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Voo et al. [<xref rid="REF14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Giambi et al. [<xref rid="REF15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cherian et al. [<xref rid="REF16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Campbell et al. [<xref rid="REF17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Olbrich Neto and Olbrich [<xref rid="REF18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Migri&#x000f1;o et al. [<xref rid="REF19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bocquier et al. [<xref rid="REF20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wang et al. [<xref rid="REF21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Masters et al. [<xref rid="REF22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yakum et al. [<xref rid="REF23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ghosh et al. [<xref rid="REF24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Goruntla et al. [<xref rid="REF25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Khattak et al. [<xref rid="REF26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hadjipanayis et al. [<xref rid="REF27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Durmaz et al. [<xref rid="REF28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y&#x000f6;r&#x000fc;k and G&#x000fc;ler [<xref rid="REF29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thapar et al. [<xref rid="REF30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ustuner Top et al. [<xref rid="REF31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dub&#x000e9; et al. [<xref rid="REF32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Williams et al. [<xref rid="REF33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sahoo et al. [<xref rid="REF34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bianco et al. [<xref rid="REF35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02605;</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Characteristics of Included Studies</p><p>This systematic review included 23 studies that investigated vaccination hesitancy and its impact on immunization coverage in pediatrics. All studies employed a cross-sectional design, except one study by Hadjipanayis et al. [<xref rid="REF27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], which utilized a mixed-methods approach. The studies were conducted across various geographical locations, including Brazil [<xref rid="REF13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="REF18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], Malaysia [<xref rid="REF14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], Italy [<xref rid="REF15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="REF35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], India [<xref rid="REF16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="REF24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="REF25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="REF34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], England [<xref rid="REF17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], Philippines [<xref rid="REF19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], France [<xref rid="REF20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], China [<xref rid="REF21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], Ethiopia [<xref rid="REF22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], Cameroon [<xref rid="REF23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], Pakistan [<xref rid="REF26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], 18 European countries [<xref rid="REF27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], Turkey [<xref rid="REF28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="REF29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="REF31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], Canada [<xref rid="REF32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], and the United States [<xref rid="REF33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. This diverse geographical representation allows for a broader understanding of vaccination hesitancy in different cultural and socioeconomic contexts (Table <xref rid="TAB4" ref-type="table">4</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Characteristics and key findings of included studies</title><p>COVID-19: coronavirus disease 2019; PACV: Parents Attitudes about Childhood Vaccines; SAGE: Strategic Advisory Group of Experts on Immunization; VCI: vaccine confidence index; VH: vaccine hesitancy; WHO: World Health Organization</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Study
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Publishing year
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Country
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Study design
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Sample size
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Study period
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Data collection tool
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Key findings
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Brown et al. [<xref rid="REF13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
2018
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Brazil
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Cross-sectional study
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
952 parents
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
February and July 2016
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
VCI questionnaire
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Despite the high level of overall vaccination confidence, there was a discernible trend toward lower confidence levels being linked to higher levels of reluctance. Because vaccine hesitancy is dynamic and ever-changing, this calls for ongoing monitoring
</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Voo et al. [<xref rid="REF14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
2021
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Malaysia
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Cross-sectional study
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
405 parents
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
February-March 2018
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Self-administered questionnaire
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Higher educated parents were less vaccine-apprehensive, knew more about vaccinations, and were more inclined to make sure their kids finished the prescribed vaccination schedule, according to the study
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Giambi et al. [<xref rid="REF15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
2018
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Italy
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Cross-sectional study
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
3,130 parents
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
December 2015 to June 2016
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Self-structured questionnaire
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
All parents are concerned about vaccine safety, but reluctant and antivaccine parents are more so. Reluctant parents trust their own pediatricians and view vaccination as a preventative measure, much like provaccine parents do. This suggests that they might benefit from effective communication strategies
</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Cherian et al. [<xref rid="REF16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
2022
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
India
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Cross-sectional study
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
350 caregivers
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
November 2015 to April 2017
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Self-structured questionnaire
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
It was discovered that vaccine reluctance was quite common. The World Health Organization identified vaccination hesitancy as one of the main obstacles to improved global health in 2019
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Campbell et al. [<xref rid="REF17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
2017
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
England
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Cross-sectional study
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
1,792 parents
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
January and April 2015
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Self-administered questionnaire
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Parents continue to place a high value on health professionals in providing information on vaccinations, and this trust has grown in recent years
</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Olbrich Neto and Olbrich [<xref rid="REF18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
2023
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Brazil
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Cross-sectional study
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
1,261 parents
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
January 2018 to December 2019
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Self-administered questionnaire
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Parents believe that vaccines are safe and effective at preventing disease, and have more advantages than disadvantages. Doubts, worries, hesitation, and discrepancies were present alongside positive remarks. The degree of education has an impact on the availability of information, the pediatrician's care, and the sense of duty to get vaccinated
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Migri&#x000f1;o et al. [<xref rid="REF19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
2020
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Philippines
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Cross-sectional study
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
110 respondents
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Not reported
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
SAGE group questionnaire
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Vaccine hesitation determinants can vary greatly depending on context and environment, as seen by the absence of correlation between sociodemographic characteristics and vaccine hesitancy
</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Bocquier et al. [<xref rid="REF20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
2018
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
France
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Cross-sectional survey
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
3,927 parents
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
January and July 2016
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
SAGE group&#x02019;s questionnaire
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Vaccine delay and refusal are common among French parents, particularly those with higher levels of education. Research indicates that trust and commitment levels are important factors in determining VH
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Wang et al. [<xref rid="REF21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
2022
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
China
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Cross-sectional study
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
5,102 parents
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
September 2020 to June 2021
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
WHO SAGE Vaccine Hesitancy tool
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
The COVID-19 vaccine is becoming more and more popular in Wuxi City, China. To allay public fears over the safety of vaccines, effective interventions are required
</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Masters et al. [<xref rid="REF22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
2018
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Ethiopia
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Cross-sectional study
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
350 caregivers
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
June 1-21, 2017
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
WHO SAGE Vaccine Hesitancy tool
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Children's delayed immunization was highly correlated with high vaccine hesitation, suggesting that more efforts to inform clinicians and the community about vaccines may improve vaccine timeliness
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Yakum et al. [<xref rid="REF23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
2022
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Cameroon
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Cross-sectional study
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
529 parents
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
November 2021
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
WHO SAGE Vaccine Hesitancy tool
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Wealth has no bearing on vaccine reluctance, and in Yaounde, Cameroon, the main reason for vaccine hesitancy about routine vaccinations was a lack of trust
</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Ghosh et al. [<xref rid="REF24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
2022
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
India
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Cross-sectional study
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
1,678 caregivers
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
June 2018 to November 2019
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
WHO SAGE Vaccine Hesitancy tool
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
To help public health care providers prioritize resources and concentrate on preventable measures such as health awareness, maintaining institutional births, and expanding free health-service delivery to increase immunization coverage, the study highlights the severity of the incomplete immunization, or VH, issue and identifies its contributing factors
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Goruntla et al. [<xref rid="REF25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
2023
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
India
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Cross-sectional study
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
574 respondents
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
July to December 2021
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
WHO SAGE Vaccine Hesitancy tool
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
The main reasons for parents' reluctance or refusal are kid safety and health. Policymakers have to decrease vaccine hesitancy by creating policies based on WHO-SAGE working group predictions and demographic data in order to reach 100% vaccination coverage
</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Khattak et al. [<xref rid="REF26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
2021
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Pakistan
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Cross-sectional study
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
610 parents
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
March to July 2019
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
WHO SAGE Vaccine Hesitancy tool
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
The high prevalence of vaccination rejection among parents was linked to food security, unemployment, mobile phone ownership, lack of education, and the inability to comprehend words or write
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Hadjipanayis et al. [<xref rid="REF27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
2020
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
18 European countries
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Mixed study
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
5,736 parents
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Not reported
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
PACV and WHO SAGE Vaccine Hesitancy tool
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
The majority of parents in Europe believe in the importance of childhood&#x000a0;vaccination. However, significant lack of confidence was found in certain European countries, highlighting the need for continuous monitoring, awareness, and response plans
</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Durmaz et al. [<xref rid="REF28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
2022
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Turkey
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Cross-sectional study
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
1,087 parents
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
September and December 2021
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
PACV scale
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Public health policy can overcome obstacles and boost vaccination rates by comprehending the complex reasons behind vaccination hesitancy. Parents require information about vaccines, and the controversy related to COVID-19 vaccines can erode parents' trust in routine childhood immunizations
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Y&#x000f6;r&#x000fc;k and G&#x000fc;ler [<xref rid="REF29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
2021
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Turkey
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Cross-sectional study
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
370 parents
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
September to December 2020
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
PACV scale
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
In the upcoming years, it is important to keep a close eye on the prevalence of risk factors and vaccine reluctance
</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Thapar et al. [<xref rid="REF30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
2021
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
India
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Cross-sectional study
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
172 mothers
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
March and April 2017
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
PACV scale
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Mangalore's VH prevalence is extremely low when compared to comparable studies conducted in India and other countries. Due to worries about vaccine safety, a small percentage of participants had declined vaccination
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Ustuner Top et al. [<xref rid="REF31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
2023
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Turkey
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Cross-sectional study
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
582 parents
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
July 2021 and October 2021
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
PACV scale
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Regarding childhood vaccinations, 30% of the parents were hesitant. Digital literacy has a detrimental impact on vaccine hesitancy, but cyberchondria has a beneficial effect
</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Dub&#x000e9; et al. [<xref rid="REF32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
2019
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Canada
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Cross-sectional study
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
2,645 mothers of newborns
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
March 2014 to February 2015
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
PACV scale
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Despite the fact that most moms had favorable opinions about vaccinations, many were either moderately or extremely hesitant about them
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Williams et al. [<xref rid="REF33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
2021
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
United States
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Cross-sectional study
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
263 parents
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
August 2019 to February 2020
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
PACV scale
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
We were unable to attract new dyads that did not show up for care because of a social desirability bias that may have resulted from trust among staff and patients
</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Sahoo et al. [<xref rid="REF34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
2023
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
India
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Cross-sectional study
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
196 caregivers
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
March to May 2019
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
WHO SAGE and PACV scale
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Even among caregivers who attend a tertiary care facility, concerns about vaccine reluctance are common. Therefore, more research is needed to evaluate hesitancy in remote, inaccessible, urban, and rural regions
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Bianco et al. [<xref rid="REF35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
2019
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Italy
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Cross-sectional study
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
575 parents
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
April to June 2017
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
PACV scale
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
The findings of the study point to significant possible factors of VH, including attitudes toward prevention and the media and communication environments
</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>The sample sizes of the included studies varied considerably, ranging from 110 participants in the study by Migri&#x000f1;o et al. [<xref rid="REF19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] to 5,102 participants in the study by Wang et al. [<xref rid="REF21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. This variation in sample size should be considered when interpreting the results of individual studies and the overall findings of the review. The study periods also varied, with some studies collecting data over a few months, e.g., February and July 2016 in Brown et al. [<xref rid="REF13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], while others spanned over a year or more, e.g., November 2015 to April 2017 in Cherian et al. [<xref rid="REF16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. One study by Migri&#x000f1;o et al. [<xref rid="REF19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]&#x000a0;did not report the study period. This difference in study duration could potentially influence the findings due to temporal changes in public perception and attitudes towards vaccination.</p><p>Several data collection tools were used across the included studies. Some studies employed validated questionnaires, such as the vaccine confidence index used by Brown et al. [<xref rid="REF13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], the WHO Strategic Advisory Group of Experts on Immunization (SAGE) Vaccine Hesitancy tool [<xref rid="REF21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>-<xref rid="REF27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="REF34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], and the Parents Attitudes about Childhood Vaccines (PACV) scale [<xref rid="REF27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>-<xref rid="REF35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Other studies utilized self-administered or self-structured questionnaires [<xref rid="REF14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>-<xref rid="REF18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. The use of standardized tools like the WHO SAGE and PACV scales allows for comparisons across different studies and populations. However, the use of self-structured questionnaires may introduce heterogeneity in the data collected, as these tools may not have undergone rigorous validation processes.</p><p>The key findings of the studies highlighted various aspects of vaccination hesitancy. Several studies reported a correlation between lower vaccine confidence and higher hesitancy [<xref rid="REF13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="REF15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Some studies identified specific factors associated with hesitancy, such as lower parental education [<xref rid="REF14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], concerns about vaccine safety [<xref rid="REF15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="REF30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], lack of trust in healthcare providers [<xref rid="REF23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], and lower socioeconomic status [<xref rid="REF26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Other studies emphasized the role of effective communication strategies in addressing hesitancy [<xref rid="REF15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="REF21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] and highlighted the importance of healthcare professionals as trusted sources of information [<xref rid="REF17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. One study noted the influence of digital literacy and cyberchondria on vaccine hesitancy [<xref rid="REF31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Some studies also reported on the prevalence of vaccine delay and refusal [<xref rid="REF20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="REF22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] and the impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on vaccine confidence [<xref rid="REF21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="REF28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. The studies collectively underscore the complex and multifaceted nature of vaccination hesitancy and the need for tailored interventions to address this public health challenge.</p><p>Discussion</p><p>In this systematic review, 23 relevant studies concerning VH and its effects on immunization coverage within children were integrated. The cross-sectional research designs dominated the included studies and provided a wide geographical coverage, including European, Asian, African, and both American continents. The fact that the sample is diverse geographically is important, too, because cultural, socioeconomic, and healthcare practices affect perceptions of vaccines differently. One of the limitations we encountered included differences in the subject sample size from across the literature, the period of study in the various sources, and the variety of data collection tools applied. Nonetheless, such heterogeneity enhances the richness of the picture of VH as a phenomenon. This variability brings into the equations the notion that one is attempting to understand a phenomenon that is affected by multiple factors that may not work in a matrix called harmony.</p><p>One of the most common concepts that emerged from the discussed articles is the multifactorial approach to VH. The perception of safety was another category that came out clearly and was also affirmed in the literature review on vaccine hesitancy in other countries. These concerns are frequently based on information gathered through social media and community systems, highlighting the importance of efficient risk messaging and communication [<xref rid="REF36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. These issues must not only be answered but done so with proper, inclusive, and understandable information to establish credibility and promote empowered decision-making. As a fourth factor, confidence in the healthcare providers was identified as the other essential element in vaccine acceptance. Research showed that the level of parents' trust in healthcare professionals regarding information about vaccines was directly proportional to increased vaccination rates [<xref rid="REF37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. This shows that significant effort must be made toward&#x000a0;building good patient-doctor communications with an easy ability to discuss parental concerns, along with the presence of empathy and thoroughness. Doctors and nurses are in a better place to offer vaccination recommendations and boost people&#x02019;s confidence during the process [<xref rid="REF38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>].</p><p>Another crucial determinant of VH is inferred to be socioeconomic [<xref rid="REF39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Several higher hesitancy rates and hesitancy associations in lower income countries were observed, including the educational level of parents, unemployment of parents, and dietary insecurity. Thus, these results evidence the paramount importance of social factors concerning vaccination perception and practice. When people experience poverty and lack money for food and shelter, illness is not a priority, nor is the ability to receive concrete information about how to prevent it. There is a need to address these fundamental social and economic determinants of health to enhance vaccine coverage and equity. Moreover, the cultures and traditions across various population groups constitute one of the most important contributions to vaccine acceptance [<xref rid="REF40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Future interventions and programs in these regions must be created within a cultural context that is sensitive to social issues affecting each population. It can, therefore, be concluded that a one-size-fits-all type of intervention will not be efficient in intervening in the multiple factors that have been linked to VH.</p><p>The fact that many of the included studies employed different data collection instruments reduced the risk of heterogeneity but offered findings that were also informative. Due to the use of standardized tools, including the WHO SAGE Vaccine Hesitancy tool and the PACV scale, comparisons could be made across populations and other contexts of the research. These standardized tools are a more reliable way of measuring VH, and this makes it easy to notice patterns and trends all over the world. However, difficulties in some studies regarding the self-structuring of the questionnaires increase the requirements for other research, where the validated instruments should be used to improve the comparability of results of various researchers [<xref rid="REF20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="REF28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. This would enable more significant meta-analyses and a clearer picture of global VH as a benefit of the proposed research.</p><p>The review also gave strong tendentious proof concerning the influence of VH on precise immunization coverage rates. Several studies described statistically significant relationships between increased levels of VH and impaired or incomplete vaccination schedules in childhood. This has serious consequences concerning both personal and population health and leads to a much higher probability of the emergence of the given VPDs [<xref rid="REF41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Getting and sticking to high levels of immunization coverage is crucial for achieving herd immunity, which is essential for protecting other children who cannot be vaccinated on medical grounds, such as immunocompromised kids. Thus, VH elimination is not a luxury or an exercise in individual freedom, but a necessity on the part of population health.</p><p>The COVID-19 pandemic has made the issue of VH even more complicated. A few of the studies included in this review mentioned the decline in people&#x02019;s trust in vaccines, which was associated with COVID-19 perceived risk regarding vaccines developed in record time. This underlines the importance of timely tracking of attitudes toward&#x000a0;vaccines and explaining such risks in an attempt to restore people&#x02019;s confidence in immunization. It also brought out the applicability of the peripheral components as a result of digital literacy in their perception of vaccines. The high uptake and rapid dissemination of sometimes false and misleading information on social media means that the prevention of the spread of such information requires specific programs that will be directed toward&#x000a0;availing health literacy to the society and ensuring that the society comprehensively understands content constituents that are important in evaluating health information [<xref rid="REF42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>].</p><p>There are some limitations in our study. The frequent application of cross-sectional research also blunts the chances of proving cause-related relationships between VH and immunization coverage. Subsequent studies using more longitudinal approaches to study VH would be useful in descriptively charting the course of VH and its impact on future vaccination behaviors. Some of the weaknesses, which include the source of the study populations, the approach to data collection, and the study time frames used, also reduce the generalizability of results. In addition, the possibility of intervention effects by publication bias that elevated or statistically significant/positive findings are more likely to be published has to be considered.</p><p>However, despite these limitations, this systematic review provides much-needed information about the multifaceted and dynamic topic of VH and its effects on administrative efforts at increasing immunization coverage among children. The implications underlined in the present work are almost exclusively relevant to the necessity of using complex and comprehensive interventions involving the multiple factors that are deemed to cause VH. These interventions should prioritize several key areas: endorse and improve individual and collective communication between careers and parents; challenge misinformation constantly; educate on sustainable health; address structural factors that determine health; intervene to meet the needs of a particular community; and continue to supervise and evaluate this crucial field. By employing optimal analytic and preventive measures along with creating positive leadership and social accountability, VH will be effectively handled, and a larger initiative for the provision of high and equitable immunization among children will be achieved.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Some of the causes of VH include perceived risks and complications of vaccines, doctors and other healthcare workers, economic reforms, cultural practices, and perceived rumors, myths, and misconceptions. These findings highlight the importance of addressing supply-side factors relating to clarity, recognizable evidence-based voice, campaign against falsehoods, and health literacy as well as demand factors on socioeconomic determinants. More observations and studies should be done regularly to establish measures of promoting high uptake of the vaccines by children.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors of this review article represent a diverse international cohort, drawn from two different nations. This international perspective is complemented by their shared academic training and established history of collaborative research in related areas. Consequently, the review offers a comprehensive and insightful treatment of the subject matter.</p></ack><fn-group content-type="conflict"><title>Disclosures</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Conflicts of interest:</bold> In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following:</p><p><bold>Payment/services info:</bold> All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work.</p><p><bold>Financial relationships:</bold> All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work.</p><p><bold>Other relationships:</bold> All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="other"><title>Author Contributions</title><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Concept and design:</bold>&#x000a0; Samia Ahmed Ali Karar, Sahar Ali Osman Mohamed Elawad, Azza Abdelbagi Yagoub Mohammed, Aala Abdelrahman Hassan Farah, Ahmed Mohamed Elamin Mubarak Osman</p><p><bold>Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data:</bold>&#x000a0; Samia Ahmed Ali Karar, Sahar Ali Osman Mohamed Elawad, Azza Abdelbagi Yagoub Mohammed, Aala Abdelrahman Hassan Farah, Ahmed Mohamed Elamin Mubarak Osman</p><p><bold>Drafting of the manuscript:</bold>&#x000a0; Samia Ahmed Ali Karar, Sahar Ali Osman Mohamed Elawad, Azza Abdelbagi Yagoub Mohammed, Aala Abdelrahman Hassan Farah, Ahmed Mohamed Elamin Mubarak Osman</p><p><bold>Supervision:</bold>&#x000a0; Samia Ahmed Ali Karar</p><p><bold>Critical review of the manuscript for important intellectual content:</bold>&#x000a0; Sahar Ali Osman Mohamed Elawad, Azza Abdelbagi Yagoub Mohammed, Aala Abdelrahman Hassan Farah, Ahmed Mohamed Elamin Mubarak Osman</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="REF1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Impact of vaccines; health, economic and social perspectives</article-title><source>Front Microbiol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Plotkin</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>1526</fpage><volume>11</volume><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32760367</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Public health and economic consequences of vaccine hesitancy for measles in the United States</article-title><source>JAMA Pediatr</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hotez</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>887</fpage><lpage>892</lpage><volume>171</volume><year>2017</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28738137</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Parental vaccine hesitancy and childhood influenza vaccination</article-title><source>Pediatrics</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Santibanez</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Greby</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>0</fpage><volume>146</volume><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32601127</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Improving pediatric vaccination coverage in the United States</article-title><source>Acad Pediatr</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Stokley</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kempe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stockwell</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Szilagyi</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>0</fpage><lpage>2</lpage><volume>21</volume><year>2021</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Addressing parental vaccine hesitancy and other barriers to childhood/adolescent vaccination uptake during the coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic</article-title><source>Front Immunol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Olusanya</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bednarczyk</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shaban-Nejad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>663074</fpage><volume>12</volume><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33815424</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Parental perspectives on immunizations: impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on childhood vaccine hesitancy</article-title><source>J Community Health</source><person-group>
<name><surname>He</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mack</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Neely</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Anand</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>39</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><volume>47</volume><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34297272</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Parental vaccine hesitancy and association with childhood diphtheria, tetanus toxoid, and acellular pertussis; measles, mumps, and rubella; rotavirus; and combined 7-series vaccination</article-title><source>Am J Prev Med</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Srivastav</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lindley</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>367</fpage><lpage>376</lpage><volume>62</volume><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35190101</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Addressing parental vaccine hesitancy towards childhood vaccines in the United States: a systematic literature review of communication interventions and strategies</article-title><source>Vaccines (Basel)</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>590</fpage><volume>8</volume><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33049956</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Adherence to timely vaccinations in the United States</article-title><source>Pediatrics</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Hargreaves</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nowak</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Frew</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>0</fpage><volume>145</volume><year>2020</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Sociodemographic trends and correlation between parental hesitancy towards pediatric COVID-19 vaccines and routine childhood immunizations in the United States: 2021-2022 National Immunization Survey-Child COVID Module</article-title><source>Vaccines (Basel)</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Olusanya</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Masters</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sugerman</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Singleton</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>495</fpage><volume>12</volume><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38793746</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>PRISMA statement</article-title><source>Epidemiology</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Takkouche</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Norman</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>128</fpage><volume>22</volume><year>2011</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21150360</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>PRISMA 2020 and PRISMA-S: common questions on tracking records and the flow diagram</article-title><source>J Med Libr Assoc</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Rethlefsen</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Page</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>253</fpage><lpage>257</lpage><volume>110</volume><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35440907</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Vaccine confidence and hesitancy in Brazil</article-title><source>Cad Saude Publica</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sperandio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Turssi</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>0</fpage><volume>34</volume><year>2018</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Vaccine knowledge, awareness and hesitancy: a cross sectional survey among parents residing at Sandakan District, Sabah</article-title><source>Vaccines (Basel)</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Voo</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lean</surname><given-names>QY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ming</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Md Hanafiah</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Al-Worafi</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>1348</fpage><volume>9</volume><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34835279</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Parental vaccine hesitancy in Italy - results from a national survey</article-title><source>Vaccine</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Giambi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fabiani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>D'Ancona</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>779</fpage><lpage>787</lpage><volume>36</volume><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29325822</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Prevalence and predictors of vaccine hesitancy in an urbanized agglomeration of New Delhi, India</article-title><source>J Public Health (Oxf)</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Cherian</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Saini</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Philip</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>70</fpage><lpage>76</lpage><volume>44</volume><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33594438</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Changing attitudes to childhood immunisation in English parents</article-title><source>Vaccine</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Letley</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bedford</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ramsay</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yarwood</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>2979</fpage><lpage>2985</lpage><volume>35</volume><year>2017</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28442229</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Attitudes, hesitancy, concerns, and inconsistencies regarding vaccines reported by parents of preschool children</article-title><source>Rev Paul Pediatr</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Olbrich Neto</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Olbrich</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>0</fpage><volume>41</volume><year>2023</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Factors affecting vaccine hesitancy among families with children 2&#x000a0;years old and younger in two urban communities in Manila, Philippines</article-title><source>Western Pac Surveill Response J</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Migri&#x000f1;o J</surname><given-names>Jr</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gayados</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Birol</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><volume>11</volume><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33537161</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Social differentiation of vaccine hesitancy among French parents and the mediating role of trust and commitment to health: a nationwide cross-sectional study</article-title><source>Vaccine</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Bocquier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fressard</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cortaredona</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>7666</fpage><lpage>7673</lpage><volume>36</volume><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30391054</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Changes in parental attitudes toward COVID-19 vaccination and routine childhood vaccination during the COVID-19 pandemic: repeated cross-sectional survey study</article-title><source>JMIR Public Health Surveill</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xiu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>0</fpage><volume>8</volume><year>2022</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Vaccine hesitancy among caregivers and association with childhood vaccination timeliness in Addis Ababa, Ethiopia</article-title><source>Hum Vaccin Immunother</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Masters</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tefera</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Boulton</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>2340</fpage><lpage>2347</lpage><volume>14</volume><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29792555</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>The burden of vaccine hesitancy for routine immunization in Yaounde-Cameroon: a cross-sectional study</article-title><source>PLOS Glob Public Health</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Yakum</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Funwie</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ajong</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tsafack</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ze</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>0</fpage><volume>2</volume><year>2022</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Demography and determinants of incomplete immunization in children aged 1-5 years and vaccine-hesitancy among caregivers: an Eastern Indian perspective</article-title><source>Clin Epidemiol Glob Health</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Annigeri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hemram</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>101155</fpage><volume>17</volume><year>2022</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Prevalence and predictors of vaccine hesitancy among mothers of under-five children: a hospital-based cross-sectional study</article-title><source>J Educ Health Promot</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Goruntla</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Akanksha</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lalithaasudhaa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pinnu</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jinka</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bhupalam</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Doniparthi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>34</fpage><volume>12</volume><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37034856</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Prevalence of parental refusal rate and its associated factors in routine immunization by using WHO vaccine hesitancy tool: a cross sectional study at district Bannu, KP, Pakistan</article-title><source>Int J Infect Dis</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Khattak</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rehman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shahzad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>117</fpage><lpage>124</lpage><volume>104</volume><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33340667</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Vaccine confidence among parents: large scale study in eighteen European countries</article-title><source>Vaccine</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Hadjipanayis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>van Esso</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Del Torso</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>1505</fpage><lpage>1512</lpage><volume>38</volume><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31848051</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Parents' attitudes toward childhood vaccines and COVID-19 vaccines in a Turkish pediatric outpatient population</article-title><source>Vaccines (Basel)</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Durmaz</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Suman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ersoy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>&#x000d6;r&#x000fc;n</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>1958</fpage><volume>10</volume><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36423053</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Factors associated with pediatric vaccine hesitancy of parents: a cross-sectional study in Turkey</article-title><source>Hum Vaccin Immunother</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Y&#x000f6;r&#x000fc;k</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>G&#x000fc;ler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>4505</fpage><lpage>4511</lpage><volume>17</volume><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34665993</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Vaccine hesitancy among mothers of under-five children in Coastal South India: a facility-based cross-sectional study</article-title><source>F1000Res</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Thapar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Surendran</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>186</fpage><volume>10</volume><year>2021</year><uri xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/34631015/">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/34631015/</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34631015</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>The relation between digital literacy, cyberchondria, and parents' attitudes to childhood vaccines</article-title><source>J Pediatr Nurs</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Ustuner Top</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>&#x000c7;evik</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bora G&#x000fc;ne&#x0015f;</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>12</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><volume>70</volume><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36753874</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Overview of knowledge, attitudes, beliefs, vaccine hesitancy and vaccine acceptance among mothers of infants in Quebec, Canada</article-title><source>Hum Vaccin Immunother</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Dub&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>&#x000c8;</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Farrands</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lemaitre</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>120</lpage><volume>15</volume><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30095325</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Parental vaccine hesitancy and vaccination disparities in a safety-net system</article-title><source>Pediatrics</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bayliss</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Federico</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hambidge</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>O'Leary</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name>
</person-group><volume>147</volume><year>2021</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Decision-making in childhood vaccination: vaccine hesitancy among caregivers of under-5 children from a tertiary care institution in Eastern India</article-title><source>Ther Adv Vaccines Immunother</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Sahoo</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Parida</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Palepu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sahoo</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bhatia</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>25151355231152650</fpage><volume>11</volume><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36756042</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Parent perspectives on childhood vaccination: how to deal with vaccine hesitancy and refusal?</article-title><source>Vaccine</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Bianco</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mascaro</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zucco</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pavia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>984</fpage><lpage>990</lpage><volume>37</volume><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30655175</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Use of combination measles, mumps, rubella, and varicella vaccine: recommendations of the Advisory Committee on Immunization Practices (ACIP)</article-title><source>MMWR Recomm Rep</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Marin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Broder</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Temte</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>2</lpage><volume>7</volume><year>2010</year><uri xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/Mmwr/preview/mmwrhtml/rr5903a1.htm">https://www.cdc.gov/Mmwr/preview/mmwrhtml/rr5903a1.htm</uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Immunization programs for infants, children, adolescents, and adults: clinical practice guidelines by the Infectious Diseases Society of America</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Pickering</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Freed</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>817</fpage><lpage>840</lpage><volume>49</volume><year>2009</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19659433</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Vaccine hesitancy and healthcare providers</article-title><source>Vaccine</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Paterson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Meurice</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stanberry</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Glismann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rosenthal</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>6700</fpage><lpage>6706</lpage><volume>34</volume><year>2016</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27810314</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Addressing the vaccine confidence gap</article-title><source>Lancet</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>LZ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eskola</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>526</fpage><lpage>535</lpage><volume>378</volume><year>2011</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21664679</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><article-title>Vaccination and trust: how concerns arise and the role of communication in mitigating crises</article-title><source>World Health Organization</source><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">
<month>12</month>
<year>2024</year>
</date-in-citation><person-group>
<name><surname>World Health</surname><given-names>Organization</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>2017</fpage><publisher-name>Regional Office for Europe</publisher-name><year>2017</year><uri xlink:href="https://iris.who.int/bitstream/handle/10665/343299/WHO-EURO-2017-2908-42666-59448-eng.pdf?sequence=1">https://iris.who.int/bitstream/handle/10665/343299/WHO-EURO-2017-2908-42666-59448-eng.pdf?sequence=1</uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Communicating with parents about vaccination: a framework for health professionals</article-title><source>BMC Pediatr</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Leask</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kinnersley</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cheater</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bedford</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rowles</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>154</fpage><volume>12</volume><year>2012</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22998654</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Restoring confidence in vaccines in the COVID-19 era</article-title><source>Expert Rev Vaccines</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Verger</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dub&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>991</fpage><lpage>993</lpage><volume>19</volume><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32940574</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>