<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="issn">2168-8184</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cureus</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2168-8184</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cureus</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Palo Alto (CA)</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40400863</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12094683</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7759/cureus.82726</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>General Surgery</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Medical Education</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Haematometrocolpos Mimicking Appendicitis in an Adolescent Female: A Case Report</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Muacevic</surname><given-names>Alexander</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>John R</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>Wilhelm</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kimmie</surname><given-names>Mohammed Fayaz</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff-1">
<label>1</label>
General Surgery, University of Witwatersrand, Johannesburg, ZAF </aff><aff id="aff-2">
<label>2</label>
General Surgery, Robert Mangaliso Sobukwe Hospital, Kimberley, ZAF </aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">
Wilhelm Hansen <email>hansen504@gmail.com</email>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>21</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic"><month>4</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>17</volume><issue>4</issue><elocation-id>e82726</elocation-id><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2025, Hansen et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Hansen et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License CC-BY 4.0., which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="https://www.cureus.com/articles/350130-haematometrocolpos-mimicking-appendicitis-in-an-adolescent-female-a-case-report">This article is available from https://www.cureus.com/articles/350130-haematometrocolpos-mimicking-appendicitis-in-an-adolescent-female-a-case-report</self-uri><abstract><p>This report presents the case of a 15-year-old female patient who exhibited symptoms of abdominal distension, constipation, and cyclical lower abdominal pain. Subsequent evaluation led to a diagnosis of haematometrocolpos as a consequence of an imperforate hymen. Imaging studies confirmed substantial blood accumulation within the vaginal and uterine cavities, necessitating surgical intervention. The patient was subsequently referred to the gynaecological department for further management.&#x000a0;This case underscores the significance of recognising haematometrocolpos as a differential diagnosis in adolescent females presenting with primary amenorrhoea and abdominal pain. Given the overlap in presentations between surgical and gynaecological conditions, timely surgical consultation and imaging are imperative to prevent unnecessary interventions, while prompt diagnosis and appropriate surgical management are crucial to avert complications and preserve reproductive function. Furthermore, this case underscores the necessity for comprehensive clinical examination and imaging in patients with obstructive M&#x000fc;llerian anomalies, highlighting the vital role of the general surgeon in the initial assessment and the exclusion of acute surgical emergencies.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>appendicitis</kwd><kwd>diagnostic dilemma</kwd><kwd>general surgery</kwd><kwd>gynaecology</kwd><kwd>haematometrocolpos</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Acute abdominal pain in adolescent females frequently constitutes a common clinical presentation characterised by a wide differential diagnosis. This often necessitates urgent evaluation to rule out surgical emergencies, such as appendicitis [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>-<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Nevertheless, in post-pubertal patients, gynaecological conditions require consideration, particularly when there is a documented history of primary amenorrhoea or cyclical pelvic pain. Haematometrocolpos, which arises from obstructed menstrual outflow, is a rare yet significant aetiology of acute abdominal pain within this demographic. The condition is commonly attributed to an imperforate hymen, but may also stem from a transverse vaginal septum or other M&#x000fc;llerian anomalies [<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Patients may exhibit symptoms that mimic appendicitis; however, atypical presentations can arise due to the mass effect on adjacent structures, occasionally leading to urinary or gastrointestinal complaints. Early recognition of haematometrocolpus is essential to avoid misdiagnosis and ensure appropriate management, particularly when patients first present to general surgeons. Prompt identification is essential to avert complications such as retrograde menstruation, endometriosis, or secondary infection. This case underscores the importance of a broad differential in acute abdominal pain, its differentiation from more prevalent surgical conditions, and the pivotal role of the general surgeon in its initial assessment and management.</p></sec><sec sec-type="cases"><title>Case presentation</title><p>A 15-year-old female patient with no known comorbidities presented with a two-week history of right iliac fossa (RIF) pain. The pain was noted to be non-radiating and was accompanied by symptoms of nausea, vomiting and decreased appetite. There were no reported urinary symptoms, but the patient experienced constipation.&#x000a0;The patient's mother reported that she had not yet started menstruating. Initially, she sought assistance at a local clinic and was subsequently admitted to a community hospital, where she was administered analgesics and antibiotics (no blood results available). Despite these treatments, her clinical condition did not exhibit any sign&#x000a0;of improvement, and she was referred to general surgery at a regional hospital&#x000a0;for further management.</p><p>Upon admission, her vital signs were recorded as follows: blood pressure&#x000a0;132/83 mmHg, heart rate 125 beats per minute, respiratory rate (RR) 20 breaths per minute, oxygen saturation 98% on room air and temperature 36.7&#x000b0;C. Urinalysis indicated 1+ protein and 2+ ketones, alongside a negative urine beta-human chorionic gonadotropin (&#x003b2;-hCG) test.</p><p>During the general examination, findings were largely unremarkable. However, an abdominal examination revealed tenderness in the RIF with notable fullness, suggestive of a palpable mass upon palpation and rebound tenderness. Other systemic examinations were also unremarkable. Blood tests indicated mild leukocytosis, mild anaemia, thrombocytosis, mildly raised amylase, normal C-reactive protein, and no significant electrolyte abnormalities. Venous blood gas and co-oximetry results were within normal ranges. Detailed results are provided below (Tables <xref rid="TAB1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, <xref rid="TAB2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Blood results</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day of Hospital Stay&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Specimen Type</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Result</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference Range</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="12" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="12" colspan="1">Blood</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sodium: 134</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">135 - 145 mmol/L</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Potassium: 4.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5 - 5.0 mmol/L</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloride: 102</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">98 - 107 mmol/L</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bicarbonate: 19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 - 28 mmol/L</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urea: 5.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5 - 7.8 mmol/L</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Creatinine: 58</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 - 90 &#x000b5;mol/L</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amylase: 124</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 - 110 U/L</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lipase: 26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 - 60 U/L</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C-reactive protein: 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;10 mg/L</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">White cell count: 11.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0 - 11.0 &#x000d7; 10&#x02079;/L</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Haemoglobin: 11.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.0 - 16.0 g/dL</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Platelets: 601</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">150 - 400 &#x000d7; 10&#x02079;/L</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Venous blood gas</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day of Hospital Stay&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Specimen Type</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Result</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference Range</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="15" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="15" colspan="1">Blood</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pH: 7.36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.35 - 7.45</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pCO&#x02082;: 36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 - 45 mmHg</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pO&#x02082;: 42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 - 50 mmHg (venous)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sodium: 136</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">135 - 145 mmol/L</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Potassium: 4.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5 - 5.0 mmol/L</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloride: 104</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">98 - 107 mmol/L</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Calcium: 1.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.15 - 1.35 mmol/L</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hematocrit: 36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 - 46%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glucose: 6.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9 - 6.1 mmol/L</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lactate: 1.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 - 2.2 mmol/L</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total haemoglobin: 11.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.0 - 16.0 g/dL</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oxygen saturation: 56.8%&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60 - 80% (venous)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bicarbonate: 20.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 - 28 mmol/L</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Base excess: -5.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2 to +2 mmol/L</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anion gap: 16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 - 16 mmol/L</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>A formal ultrasound was booked for the patient. Ultrasound findings indicated extensive, mass-like thickening of the caecal wall, accompanied by a significant defect in the wall. A large, complex pelvic collection was observed, exerting compressive effects on the bladder. These findings strongly suggested an appendiceal perforation. Concern arose due to the insufficient detail in the gynaecological findings on ultrasound, prompting the treating team to order a computed tomography (CT) scan for a more thorough assessment.</p><p>Subsequent CT imaging of the abdomen revealed massive haematometrocolpos, wherein the uterus was distended by blood and was displaced into the RIF, measuring 7.2 cm &#x000d7; 3.8 cm &#x000d7; 7.1 cm. The vagina was markedly distended at dimensions of 8.4 cm &#x000d7; 8.8 cm &#x000d7; 18.1 cm, leading to compression of the rectum and partial anterior displacement of the bladder. Both ovaries appeared normal, but were displaced (with the right ovary located in the RIF and the left positioned anteriorly and superiorly). The appendix was normal with no indications of inflammation. The bowel, liver, gallbladder, spleen, pancreas, adrenal glands, kidneys, vasculature and bony structures presented unremarkable findings. There was an absence of intra-abdominal free fluid, abnormal collections or lymphadenopathy. These results suggested haematometrocolpos, potentially attributed to an imperforate hymen, thus warranting correlation with menstrual history and gynaecological evaluation (Figures <xref rid="FIG1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, <xref rid="FIG2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, <xref rid="FIG3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>CT axial view with normal appendix</title><p>CT:&#x000a0;computed tomography</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0017-00000082726-i01" position="float"/></fig><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>CT axial view with a fluid-filled uterine cavity</title><p>CT:&#x000a0;computed tomography</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0017-00000082726-i02" position="float"/></fig><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>CT axial view with a fluid-filled uterine cavity</title><p>CT:&#x000a0;computed tomography</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0017-00000082726-i03" position="float"/></fig><p>Following a comprehensive review of the CT report and imaging findings, the patient's case was discussed with the gynaecology department, and she was subsequently referred for further management.</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>This case highlights a 15-year-old female who presented with signs suggestive of acute appendicitis, including right iliac fossa tenderness, nausea, and normal inflammatory markers. However, instead of appendicitis, CT imaging revealed a distended uterus and a markedly blood-filled vagina, confirming the diagnosis of haematometrocolpos. Haematometrocolpos is an important differential for acute abdominal pain in young adolescent females, as, if diagnosed early, it can be treated with minimally invasive techniques and serious complications such as hydronephrosis or uterine rupture can be avoided [<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Because these patients often present first to general surgeons rather than obstetric or gynaecological specialists, a high index of suspicion is vital, especially when the clinical picture mimics common surgical conditions like appendicitis.</p><p>In a similar case reported by Al-Buloushi&#x000a0;et al., a young adolescent female presented to the emergency department with recurrent urinary tract infections and was initially treated and discharged. However, the persistence of these infections led the treating team to investigate further. As with our patient, her blood work was unremarkable except for mild leukocytosis. An ultrasound revealed an underlying abnormality, prompting an MRI&#x000a0;that ultimately confirmed haematometrocolpos [<xref rid="REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. This case further reinforces the importance of pursuing alternative diagnoses in adolescent females with persistent or atypical presentations.</p><p>One of the challenges with haematometrocolpos is that it is often overlooked initially, leading to delayed treatment and increased risk of complications [<xref rid="REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. It is defined as a condition in which blood or secretory fluid accumulates in the vagina due to obstruction, most commonly caused by congenital anomalies, infection, or trauma [<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. The most frequent cause is an imperforate hymen, accounting for approximately 90% of all cases [<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>-<xref rid="REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Patients typically present after puberty with symptoms such as cyclical abdominal pain, urinary retention, and amenorrhoea [<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>-<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Due to overlapping clinical features, it is frequently misdiagnosed as appendicitis, urinary tract infection, pelvic inflammatory disease, or adnexal pathology, as seen in our patient [<xref rid="REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>-<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. In this case, the likely underlying cause of haematometrocolpos was an imperforate hymen. Clinically, the diagnosis may be suggested by the presence of a tense, bulging, bluish hymenal membrane on vaginal examination [<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Although tumour markers like CA-125 and CA-19-9 may be elevated, they are not required for diagnosis [<xref rid="REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>].</p><p>In the emergency department, point-of-care ultrasound has become central to the evaluation of abdominal pain [<xref rid="REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. While not specific for haematometrocolpos, it serves as a valuable first-line tool capable of identifying M&#x000fc;llerian anomalies or clot accumulation within the vaginal canal [<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. MRI remains the most sensitive imaging modality, providing detailed anatomical information such as the site and integrity of obstructive anomalies. However, in this case, a CT scan was utilised, which is more readily available in acute settings where MRI access may be limited [<xref rid="REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].</p><p>The pathophysiology of haematometrocolpos mimicking acute appendicitis involves more than mass effect alone. Compression of adjacent structures-including the bladder and bowel-can produce gastrointestinal and urinary symptoms [<xref rid="REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="REF11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. A significant mechanism involves right-sided ureterohydronephrosis, which may explain the right iliac fossa pain observed in some cases. A distended uterus and vagina can compress the right ureter, resulting in obstruction, urinary stasis, and renal colic-like pain referred to the lower abdomen [<xref rid="REF12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Inflammation and peritoneal irritation, potentially worsened by retrograde menstruation, may further intensify symptoms and obscure the diagnosis. Recognising these mechanisms is essential in differentiating haematometrocolpos from true acute surgical conditions [<xref rid="REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="REF11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>].</p><p>Surgical management of haematometrocolpos depends on the underlying cause, with the primary goal of relieving the obstruction and preventing recurrence. In cases due to imperforate hymen, a hymenotomy or hymenectomy is typically performed to establish an outflow tract. These procedures are generally safe and can be completed under local or general anaesthesia [<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. More complex anomalies, such as a transverse vaginal septum, may require staged surgical correction to avoid complications like vaginal stenosis [<xref rid="REF13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. In our case, the patient was referred to the obstetrics and gynaecology department for definitive management.</p><p>From a general surgical perspective, recognising gynaecological causes of acute abdominal pain is critical to avoid misdiagnosis and unnecessary operative intervention. Given the overlapping clinical features between surgical and gynaecological conditions, early imaging and prompt referral are essential. Although surgical intervention is often required, medical management, such as hormonal therapy, may offer temporary symptom relief prior to surgery [<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Ultimately, the choice of treatment is determined by the underlying pathology and individual patient factors, including age and comorbidities [<xref rid="REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. General surgeons should be familiar with the basic management principles and referral pathways for such presentations.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Haematometrocolpos is an uncommon but important differential diagnosis in adolescent females presenting with acute abdominal pain, especially when the symptoms mimic more common conditions like appendicitis. This case underscores the necessity for a comprehensive clinical assessment, which should encompass a detailed menstrual history and a meticulous physical examination to identify any obstructive anomalies within the genital tract. Imaging, particularly ultrasound as a first-line tool, followed by CT if needed, plays a key role in confirming the diagnosis and guiding further management. Considering the overlap in clinical presentations between surgical and gynaecological pathologies, early consultation with surgical specialists and prompt imaging are imperative to avert unwarranted interventions. Although gynaecologists predominantly perform definitive treatment, the general surgeon plays a pivotal role in the early recognition, initial assessment, and exclusion of acute surgical emergencies. Early diagnosis is essential to avoid complications such as infection, retrograde menstruation, endometriosis, or delays in care. A multidisciplinary approach is essential to ensure optimal patient outcomes and reinforces the importance of considering gynaecological causes in the differential diagnosis of abdominal pain in young female patients.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group content-type="conflict"><title>Disclosures</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Human subjects:</bold> Consent for treatment and open access publication was obtained or waived by all participants in this study.</p><p><bold>Conflicts of interest:</bold> In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following:</p><p><bold>Payment/services info:</bold> All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work.</p><p><bold>Financial relationships:</bold> All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work.</p><p><bold>Other relationships:</bold> All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="other"><title>Author Contributions</title><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Concept and design:</bold>&#x000a0; Wilhelm Hansen</p><p><bold>Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data:</bold>&#x000a0; Wilhelm Hansen, Mohammed Fayaz Kimmie</p><p><bold>Drafting of the manuscript:</bold>&#x000a0; Wilhelm Hansen, Mohammed Fayaz Kimmie</p><p><bold>Critical review of the manuscript for important intellectual content:</bold>&#x000a0; Wilhelm Hansen, Mohammed Fayaz Kimmie</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="REF1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Acute abdominal pain in women of child-bearing age remains a diagnostic dilemma</article-title><source>J Family Community Med</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Abdelhadi</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><volume>8</volume><year>2001</year><uri xlink:href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC3437059/">https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC3437059/</uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Acute abdominal pain in children</article-title><source>Pediatr Gastroenterol Hepatol Nutr</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>219</fpage><lpage>224</lpage><volume>16</volume><year>2013</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24511517</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Common abdominal emergencies in children</article-title><source>Emerg Med Clin North Am</source><person-group>
<name><surname>D'Agostino</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>153</lpage><volume>20</volume><year>2002</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11826631</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><article-title>General Gynecology: The Requisites in Obstetrics and Gynecology</article-title><person-group>
<name><surname>Sokol</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sokol</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name>
</person-group><publisher-loc>Amsterdam, Netherlands</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Elsevier Health Sciences</publisher-name><year>2007</year><uri xlink:href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/book/9780323032476/general-gynecology">https://www.sciencedirect.com/book/9780323032476/general-gynecology</uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Hematometrocolpos disguised as abdominal pain</article-title><source>J Emerg Med</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Saleh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Katzenbach G</surname><given-names>3rd</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Espinosa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>0</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><volume>53</volume><year>2017</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>A case of image-guided hematometrocolpos drainage requiring tissue plasminogen activator in a pediatric patient</article-title><source>J Surg Case Rep</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sokkary</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>0</fpage><volume>2024</volume><year>2024</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Urinary retention complicated by hematocolpos in an adolescent girl: case report</article-title><source>Int J Surg Case Rep</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Al-Buloushi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>AlBusairi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alenezi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zahir</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>108934</fpage><volume>112</volume><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37925784</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Hematocolpometra diagnosed with point-of-care ultrasound in a pediatric patient with right lower quadrant abdominal pain</article-title><source>J Emerg Med</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Pearce</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Malik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>0</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><volume>66</volume><year>2024</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Congenital anomalies causing hemato/hydrocolpos: imaging findings, treatments, and outcomes</article-title><source>Jpn J Radiol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Tanitame</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tanitame</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Urayama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ohtsu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>733</fpage><lpage>740</lpage><volume>39</volume><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33840015</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Hematocolpos due to imperforate hymen: a case report and literature systematic review</article-title><source>Int Urogynecol J</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Marino</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alfieri</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tessitore</surname><given-names>IV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barba</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Manodoro</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Frigerio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>357</fpage><lpage>369</lpage><volume>34</volume><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35713674</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Hematometrocolpos in a pubescent girl with abdominal pain</article-title><source>Clin Pract Cases Emerg Med</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Kotter</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weingrow</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Canders</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>218</fpage><lpage>220</lpage><volume>1</volume><year>2017</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29849312</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Right hydronephrosis as a complication of acute appendicitis</article-title><source>Case Rep Emerg Med</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Okur</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Koca</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Y&#x00131;ld&#x00131;z</surname><given-names>&#x00130;</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barut</surname><given-names>&#x00130;</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>3231862</fpage><volume>2016</volume><year>2016</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27069699</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Congenital uterine anomaly with concurrent longitudinal and transverse vaginal septa: Presentation of two cases</article-title><source>J Pediatr Adolesc Gynecol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Giannakaki</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baroutis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kalampalikis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Michala</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>16</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><volume>6</volume><year>2025</year></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>