<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" id="deo270022" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">DEN Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">DEN Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.1002/(ISSN)2692-4609</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">DEO2</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>DEN Open</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2692-4609</issn><publisher><publisher-name>John Wiley and Sons Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Hoboken</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39346018</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11439380</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/deo2.70022</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">DEO270022</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Efficacy and safety of intravenous thiamylal in sedation for colonoscopy in children</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="left-running-head">OZAKA <sc>et&#x000a0;al.</sc>
</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="deo270022-cr-0001" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ozaka</surname><given-names>Sotaro</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6283-7012</contrib-id><xref rid="deo270022-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="deo270022-cr-0002" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>Haruhiko</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6352-1741</contrib-id><xref rid="deo270022-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="deo270022-cr-0003" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shimomori</surname><given-names>Yuta</given-names></name><xref rid="deo270022-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="deo270022-cr-0004" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kagoshima</surname><given-names>Yomei</given-names></name><xref rid="deo270022-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="deo270022-cr-0005" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Terashi</surname><given-names>Shohei</given-names></name><xref rid="deo270022-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="deo270022-cr-0006" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tsutsumi</surname><given-names>Koshiro</given-names></name><xref rid="deo270022-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="deo270022-cr-0007" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sagami</surname><given-names>Ryota</given-names></name><xref rid="deo270022-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="deo270022-cr-0008" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hirashita</surname><given-names>Yuka</given-names></name><xref rid="deo270022-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="deo270022-cr-0009" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fukuda</surname><given-names>Kensuke</given-names></name><xref rid="deo270022-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="deo270022-cr-0010" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ogawa</surname><given-names>Ryo</given-names></name><xref rid="deo270022-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="deo270022-cr-0011" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kodama</surname><given-names>Masaaki</given-names></name><xref rid="deo270022-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="deo270022-cr-0012" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Murakami</surname><given-names>Kazunari</given-names></name><xref rid="deo270022-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="deo270022-cr-0013" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Mizukami</surname><given-names>Kazuhiro</given-names></name><xref rid="deo270022-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><address><email>mizkaz0809@oita-u.ac.jp</email></address></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="deo270022-aff-0001">
<label>
<sup>1</sup>
</label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Department of Gastroenterology</named-content>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Faculty of Medicine</named-content>
<institution>Oita University</institution>
<city>Oita</city>
<country country="JP">Japan</country>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="correspondenceTo">
<label>*</label>
<bold>Correspondence</bold>
<break/>Kazuhiro Mizukami, Department of Gastroenterology, Faculty of Medicine, Oita University, 1&#x02010;1 Idaigaoka, Hasama, Yufu, Oita 879&#x02013;5593, Japan.<break/> Email: <email>mizkaz0809@oita-u.ac.jp</email>
<break/>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>4</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue seq="77">1</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/deo2.v5.1</issue-id><elocation-id>e70022</elocation-id><history>
<date date-type="rev-recd"><day>04</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></date>
<date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>7</month><year>2024</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></date>
</history><permissions><!--&#x000a9; 2025 John Wiley & Sons Ltd.--><copyright-statement content-type="article-copyright">&#x000a9; 2024 The Author(s). <italic toggle="yes">DEN Open</italic> published by John Wiley &#x00026; Sons Australia, Ltd on behalf of Japan Gastroenterological Endoscopy Society.</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link> License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="file:DEO2-5-e70022.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><sec id="deo270022-sec-0010"><title>Objectives</title><p>Since a standard sedation protocol for pediatric colonoscopy (CS) has not been established, evidence on optimal sedative agents is needed. This study aimed to evaluate the efficacy and safety of thiamylal in sedation for pediatric CS compared to midazolam.</p></sec><sec id="deo270022-sec-0020"><title>Methods</title><p>Children from 7 to 16 years of age who underwent CS under sedation with intravenous thiamylal or midazolam at our hospital between June 2010 and March 2024 were included in this retrospective observational study. The primary outcome was the efficacy (success rate of CS without mid&#x02010;awakening) of the drugs. Meanwhile, the secondary outcomes were the sedation level during CS, procedure time, recovery time, and adverse events related to sedation.</p></sec><sec id="deo270022-sec-0030"><title>Results</title><p>Sixty children were included in the study. The success rate of CS without mid&#x02010;awakening was significantly higher in the thiamylal group (90.6%) than in the midazolam group (64.3%; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.03). The two groups had no significant differences in median sedation depth, procedure time, or recovery time. Adverse events related to sedation in thiamylal group (22%) and midazolam group (25%) were similar. No severe adverse events were reported.</p></sec><sec id="deo270022-sec-0040"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Intravenous thiamylal provides effective and safe sedation in children requiring CS, with little or no mid&#x02010;awakening during the procedure.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-generated"><kwd id="deo270022-kwd-0001">children</kwd><kwd id="deo270022-kwd-0002">colonoscopy</kwd><kwd id="deo270022-kwd-0003">midazolam</kwd><kwd id="deo270022-kwd-0004">sedation</kwd><kwd id="deo270022-kwd-0005">thiamylal</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="funding-0001"><funding-source>None</funding-source></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="1"/><table-count count="4"/><page-count count="7"/><word-count count="4495"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>source-schema-version-number</meta-name><meta-value>2.0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>April 2025</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>details-of-publishers-convertor</meta-name><meta-value>Converter:WILEY_ML3GV2_TO_JATSPMC version:6.5.4 mode:remove_FC converted:27.02.2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="deo270022-sec-0050"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>With the increasing number of patients with inflammatory bowel disease and allergic gastrointestinal disorders, there has been an increase in cases requiring colonoscopy (CS) during childhood.<xref rid="deo270022-bib-0001" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="deo270022-bib-0002" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref> Appropriate sedation should be provided when performing gastrointestinal endoscopy to ensure the examination is performed safely and painlessly. However, children are often unable to follow an examiner's instructions or undergo CS with self&#x02010;control, and inadequate sedation causes physical and emotional distress to both patients and endoscopists. While adult patients undergo CS with conscious sedation, pediatric patients require deep sedation because of their relatively high level of anxiety, lack of cooperation, and pain sensitivity.<xref rid="deo270022-bib-0003" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="deo270022-bib-0004" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref> Some studies have shown that conscious sedation in a considerable percentage of children results in an unsafe, poor&#x02010;quality, prolonged, or aborted CS.<xref rid="deo270022-bib-0005" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref> It is also important to pay attention to the side effects of sedation, such as respiratory and cardiovascular complications. However, a standard sedation protocol for pediatric colonoscopies has not yet been established.</p><p>At our facility, endoscopists and pediatricians collaborate to provide CS to children. We used midazolam and thiamylal for endoscopic sedation because of their rapid effects and safety profile. Since 2010, we have used intravenous thiamylal effectively and safely for endoscopic sedation in pediatric patients. Thiamylal is a barbiturate sedative used in pediatric patients undergoing magnetic resonance imaging and other orthostatic procedures.<xref rid="deo270022-bib-0006" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="deo270022-bib-0007" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="deo270022-bib-0008" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>8</sup>
</xref> Few facilities use it for the sedation of pediatric CS, and there are no reports on its efficacy and safety. We hypothesized that thiamylal would have a better sedative effect than midazolam because of its shorter duration of sedation and reduced mid&#x02010;awakening. Therefore, this pilot study aimed to compare the efficacy and safety of intravenous thiamylal and midazolam for sedation during pediatric CS.</p></sec><sec id="deo270022-sec-0060"><title>METHODS</title><sec id="deo270022-sec-0070"><title>Participants</title><p>This retrospective observational study was based on a single&#x02010;facility database. Pediatric patients who underwent CS at the Oita University Hospital between June 2010 and March 2024 were included in the study. Children aged 7&#x02013;16 years who received CS sedation in the endoscopy room were enrolled in the study. The exclusion criteria were proctosigmoidoscopy, CS without sedation, CS with general anesthesia, and inadequate data. The group sedated with thiamylal alone or in combination with ketamine was defined as the thiamylal group, whereas the group sedated with a combination of midazolam and pethidine was defined as the midazolam group.</p></sec><sec id="deo270022-sec-0080"><title>Study design</title><p>Using electronic medical record data, we retrospectively analyzed patient characteristics, including age, sex, body weight, and American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA) physical status classification (ASA class I, a normal healthy patient; ASA class II, a patient with mild systemic disease; ASA class III, a patient with severe systemic disease). In all cases, written informed consent was obtained from at least one parent before endoscopy. The patients underwent CS alone or combined endoscopy (CS and esophagogastroduodenoscopy [EGD]). Patients who underwent combined endoscopy underwent EGD followed by CS. Bowel&#x02010;cleaning preparations for CS, such as magnesium citrate, polyethylene glycol, and polyethylene glycol plus ascorbic acid, licensed in Japan, were selected by pediatricians based on age, body weight, and clinical state. Sedation was usually performed by at least two pediatricians, and CS was performed by experienced endoscopists. The choice of sedative medication was made by the pediatrician responsible for sedation. Midazolam is the drug of choice for children with a history of bronchial asthma. The analgesics included ketamine in the thiamylal group and pethidine in the midazolam group. Anesthesia was induced with thiamylal (3&#x02013;4 mg/kg), ketamine (1 mg/kg), midazolam (0.05 mg/kg), and pethidine (35 mg). In the thiamylal group, atropine (10 mg) was administered at the start of anesthesia to prevent a ketamine&#x02010;induced increase in airway secretion. Drug doses were determined based on Japanese guidelines.<xref rid="deo270022-bib-0009" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>9</sup>
</xref> Sedation level was assessed using the Pediatric Sedation State Score (PSSS; Table <xref rid="deo270022-supinfo-0001" ref-type="">S1</xref>).<xref rid="deo270022-bib-0010" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>10</sup>
</xref>
</p><p>After administering anesthetics, achievement of PSSS &#x0003c;4 was confirmed, and the examination was started. Procedure time was defined as the time from insertion to endoscope removal. The pediatrician regularly monitored and recorded the heart rate, SpO2, and blood pressure during the procedure. Hypotension, bradycardia, and hypoxemia were also observed. Additional adverse events, including vomiting, agitation, and hyperventilation, were recorded. Hypoxemia was considered when SpO<sub>2</sub> is &#x0003c; 92%. No routine oxygen therapy was administered. The patients were evaluated for PSSS every 5 min from drug administration until the end of endoscopy. Because the patient was considered apt to tolerate CS without body movement requiring restraint, we defined adequate sedation if the PSSS score was &#x0003c; 4. If there was any movement or decrease in sedation depth during the endoscopy, an additional dose of thiamylal (1&#x02013;2 mg/kg) or midazolam (0.025&#x02013;0.05 mg/kg) was administered. Mid&#x02010;awakening was defined as the persistence of scores of 4 or higher on the PSSS, even after an additional dose. After the endoscopic procedure, the patient was transferred to an observation room and monitored by a nurse until fully awake. Adverse events during the recovery period were recorded. Full awakening from sedation was defined according to our institution's observation room exit criteria as follows: (1) patient can respond clearly to the call; (2) patient can move arms and legs freely and walk without wobbling; (3) patient can breathe deeply and cough freely; (4) systolic blood pressure &#x0003e;100 mmHg or recovered to the value immediately before sedation; (5) SpO2: 92% or higher without oxygen administration; and (6) no restless or erratic behavior. Recovery time was defined as the time from the end of the CS to full awakening.</p></sec><sec id="deo270022-sec-0090"><title>Outcomes</title><p>The primary outcome was the success rate of CS without mid&#x02010;awakening. Successful CS was defined as observing the total colon without interrupting the procedure. Secondary outcomes were the sedation level during endoscopy, procedure time, recovery time, and sedation&#x02010;related adverse events.</p></sec><sec id="deo270022-sec-0100"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Data were analyzed using EZR software version 1.54. We examined the difference between the thiamylal and midazolam groups using the Mann&#x02013;Whitney <italic toggle="yes">U</italic> test to compare the median values of non&#x02010;normally distributed variables and Pearson's chi&#x02010;square test or Fisher's exact test for nominal variables. The difference between the study groups was considered statistically significant when the <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02010;value was &#x0003c;0.05.</p></sec><sec id="deo270022-sec-0110"><title>Ethical consideration</title><p>This study was conducted in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki (revised in 2013). This study was approved by the Institutional Review Board at Oita University (IRB No. 2793). Patients and parents were fully informed about the sedation. Written informed consent was obtained from at least one parent.</p></sec></sec><sec id="deo270022-sec-0120"><title>RESULTS</title><sec id="deo270022-sec-0130"><title>Patient characteristics</title><p>Colonoscopies were performed in 88 patients during the study period. After excluding 28 patients (eight proctosigmoidoscopy, six without sedation, 10 with general anesthesia, and four with inadequate data), 60 patients were enrolled. A final analysis was performed as available case analysis on 32 patients in the thiamylal group and 28 in the midazolam group (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="deo270022-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Baseline patient characteristics are shown in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="deo270022-tbl-0001" ref-type="table">1</xref>. The median age of participants was 14 years. The median age was significantly lower in the thiamylal group than in the midazolam group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01).</p><fig position="float" fig-type="FIGURE" id="deo270022-fig-0001"><label>FIGURE 1</label><caption><p>A flow chart of the present study.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="DEO2-5-e70022-g001" position="anchor" id="jats-graphic-1"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="deo270022-tbl-0001" content-type="TABLE"><label>TABLE 1</label><caption><p>Patient characteristics.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><thead><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All cases (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 60)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thiamylal group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 32)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Midazolam group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 28)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02010;value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, years, median (interquartile range)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (12&#x02013;16)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (11&#x02013;13)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (14&#x02013;16)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (60)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (53)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (68)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weight, kg, median (interquartile range)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.0 (35.1&#x02013;51.8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.2 (30.3&#x02013;44.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.0 (45.5&#x02013;56.8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASA&#x02010;PS, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (35)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (25)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (46)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39 (65)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (75)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (54)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indication of endoscopy<xref rid="deo270022-tbl1-note-0001" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>&#x02020;</sup>
</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abdominal pain</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (32)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (34)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (29)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bloody stool</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (28)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (25)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (32)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diarrhea</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (33)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (31)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (36)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fever</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (12)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (13)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (11)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anal lesion</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (10)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (13)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Screening</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (13)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (13)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (14)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Endoscopic procedures, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Colonoscopy alone</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (58)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (59)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (57)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Colonoscopy + esophagogastroduodenoscopy</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (42)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (41)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (43)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sedatives, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thiamylal alone</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (13)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thiamylal + ketamine</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (47)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (87)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Midazolam + pethidine</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (47)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (100)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASA&#x02010;PS American Society of Anaesthesiologists' physical status classification</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="deo270022-tbl1-note-0001"><label>
<sup>&#x02020;</sup>
</label><p>There is a duplication.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd.</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap><p>Moreover, the median body weight was significantly lower in the thiamylal group than in the midazolam group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01). The indications for CS included abdominal pain, bloody stools, diarrhea, fever, anal lesions, and screening. The most common indication for CS was diarrhea (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 20, 33%). There were no significant differences in the indications between the two groups. Combined endoscopy was performed in 42% of patients.</p></sec><sec id="deo270022-sec-0140"><title>Efficacy of sedation</title><p>The success rates of CS were 100% in the intravenous thiamylal group and 96.4% in the intravenous midazolam group. One patient in the midazolam group required hyperventilation during the CS, and the examination was interrupted. Because mid&#x02010;awakening interferes with safe CS,<xref rid="deo270022-bib-0005" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref> the success rate of CS without mid&#x02010;awakening was analyzed. The success rate of CS without mid&#x02010;awakening was significantly higher in the thiamylal group (90.6%) than in the midazolam group (64.3%; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.03). The two groups had no statistically significant differences regarding median procedure time, median recovery time, and median PSSS during the procedure (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="deo270022-tbl-0002" ref-type="table">2</xref>). The median dose of thiamylal per body weight was 6.46 (4.31&#x02013;8.71) mg/kg, and midazolam per body weight was 0.11 (0.09&#x02013;0.15) mg/kg, respectively (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="deo270022-tbl-0002" ref-type="table">2</xref>). As body weight is an important factor affecting sedative effects, we performed a subgroup analysis excluding lightweight children. In a subgroup analysis of children aged 13&#x02013;16 years, the rate of mid&#x02010;awakening was significantly lower in the thiamylal group. However, the two groups had no significant difference in body weight (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="deo270022-tbl-0003" ref-type="table">3</xref>). The two groups had no significant differences in the median procedure or recovery times.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="deo270022-tbl-0002" content-type="TABLE"><label>TABLE 2</label><caption><p>Results of sedation.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><thead><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All cases (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 60)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thiamylal group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 32)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Midazolam group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 28)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02010;value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Successful CS, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59 (98.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 (100)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (96.4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Successful CS without mid&#x02010;wakening, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47 (78.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (90.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (64.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSSS, median (interquartile range)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (2&#x02013;3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (2&#x02013;3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5 (2&#x02013;3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Procedure time (min), median (interquartile range)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (21&#x02013;46)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (21&#x02013;49)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (25&#x02013;44)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recovery time (min), median (interquartile range)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (20&#x02013;78)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 (20&#x02013;80)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (21&#x02013;60)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sedative dose, median (interquartile range)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thiamylal (mg/kg)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.46 (4.31&#x02013;8.71)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.46 (4.31&#x02013;8.71)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Midazolam (mg/kg)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11 (0.09&#x02013;0.15)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11 (0.09&#x02013;0.15)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ketamine (mg/kg)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28 (0.99&#x02013;1.63)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28 (0.99&#x02013;1.63)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pethidine (mg/kg)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72 (0.62&#x02013;0.77)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72 (0.62&#x02013;0.77)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS colonoscopy, PSSS pediatrics sedation state score</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd.</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="deo270022-tbl-0003" content-type="TABLE"><label>TABLE 3</label><caption><p>Subgroup analysis of children aged 13&#x02013;16 years.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><thead><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thiamylal group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 18)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Midazolam group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 28)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02010;value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, years, median (interquartile range)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (13&#x02010;16)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (14&#x02010;16)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.018</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (44)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (68)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.205</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weight, kg, median (interquartile range)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.9 (35.1&#x02010;51.7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.0 (45.5&#x02010;56.8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.105</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mid&#x02010;awakening, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (36)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.032</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oxygen desaturation, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (14)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (17)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr></tbody></table><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd.</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap></sec><sec id="deo270022-sec-0150"><title>Adverse events of sedation</title><p>The adverse events during the procedure are shown in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="deo270022-tbl-0004" ref-type="table">4</xref>. Oxygen desaturation was most frequent, occurring in six patients in the thiamylal group (19%) and four in the midazolam group (14%). All cases were resolved with airway repositioning or temporary oxygen administration. There were no significant differences between the two groups. The two cases of hyperventilation observed in the midazolam group were due to fear. No serious adverse events, such as death, respiratory arrest, laryngospasm, or shock, led to discontinuation of the test. During recovery, vomiting (three children) was observed among the children only in the thiamylal group. Headaches were observed in one patient in each group. All adverse events during the recovery were self&#x02010;limited and did not require any medical intervention. No adverse events were observed in all patients at the follow&#x02010;up period up to 6 months after sedation.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="deo270022-tbl-0004" content-type="TABLE"><label>TABLE 4</label><caption><p>Adverse events during and after sedation.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><thead><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All cases (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 60)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thiamylal group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 32)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Midazolam group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 28)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02010;value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adverse events during sedation, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (24)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (22)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (25)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypoxemia</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (17)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (19)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (14)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vomiting</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (2)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Agitation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (2)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hyperventilation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Postsedation adverse events, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (13)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vomiting</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Headache</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd.</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec id="deo270022-sec-0160"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>This pilot study demonstrated the efficacy and safety of intravenous thiamylal sedation in pediatric CS compared to intravenous midazolam. Thiamylal demonstrated a 100% CS completion rate and a significantly lower mid&#x02010;awakening rate compared to midazolam.</p><p>Pediatric gastrointestinal endoscopy has evolved, with increasing diagnostic and therapeutic applications.<xref rid="deo270022-bib-0011" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>11</sup>
</xref> However, the painfulness and discomfort of CS make the process difficult for both patients and medical staff.<xref rid="deo270022-bib-0012" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>12</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="deo270022-bib-0013" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>13</sup>
</xref> Clinically, most patients report worry before undergoing endoscopy under sedation.<xref rid="deo270022-bib-0014" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>14</sup>
</xref> Worries reduce the willingness and compliance with the procedure, leading to delays in diagnosis and treatment. &#x000a0;Therefore, adequate sedation is crucial in pediatric CS because insufficient sedation can lead to severe psychological trauma and serious complications.<xref rid="deo270022-bib-0015" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>15</sup>
</xref> Although the guidelines for CS in children have been published by the American Society for Gastrointestinal Endoscopy, North American Society for Pediatric Gastroenterology, Hepatology, and Nutrition, and European Society for Pediatric Gastroenterology Hepatology and Nutrition (ESPGHAN), a consensus protocol for optimum sedation for CS has not been established.<xref rid="deo270022-bib-0016" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>16</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="deo270022-bib-0017" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>17</sup>
</xref> Many drugs are available for sedation during pediatric CS. Midazolam is more commonly used in Japan because of its effectiveness and fewer adverse effects.<xref rid="deo270022-bib-0018" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>18</sup>
</xref> In addition, because CS is a painful procedure, and sedatives alone provide inadequate sedation, a combination of sedatives and analgesics is recommended.<xref rid="deo270022-bib-0019" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>19</sup>
</xref>
</p><p>At our facility, thiamylal and midazolam are used for sedation during CS in children under close monitoring by a pediatrician. Thiamylal is an ultra&#x02010;short&#x02010;acting barbiturate, similar to thiopental, which exerts a sedative effect by acting as an agonist of GABA<sub>A</sub> receptors.<xref rid="deo270022-bib-0020" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>20</sup>
</xref> Thiamylal has been widely used clinically as an anesthetic agent since around 1950.<xref rid="deo270022-bib-0021" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>21</sup>
</xref> Although there have been several reports demonstrating the efficacy and safety of thiamylal in pediatric MRI or other procedural sedation,<xref rid="deo270022-bib-0006" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="deo270022-bib-0007" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="deo270022-bib-0008" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>8</sup>
</xref> there are few reports on the use of thiamylal for CS in children. &#x000a0;The success rate of CS by sedation with intravenous thiamylal in this study was 100% (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="deo270022-tbl-0002" ref-type="table">2</xref>), suggesting significant clinical efficacy. According to a previous report, the midazolam&#x02010;ketamine and propofol&#x02010;fentanyl combinations have demonstrated a 100% CS success rate in children.<xref rid="deo270022-bib-0022" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>22</sup>
</xref> In this study, the combination of thiamylal and ketamine showed a high CS completion rate comparable to that reported in this study. It should be emphasized that patients sedated with intravenous thiamylal had a lower rate of mid&#x02010;awakening during CS than those sedated with midazolam. As for midazolam, the combination of midazolam&#x02010;fentanyl, midazolam&#x02010;ketamine, and midazolam&#x02010;meperidine has been reported to have high endoscopy completion rates of 91.6% to 100% and few serious side effects.<xref rid="deo270022-bib-0023" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>23</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="deo270022-bib-0024" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>24</sup>
</xref> However, paradoxical reactions are likely to occur with the use of midazolam in young children,<xref rid="deo270022-bib-0025" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>25</sup>
</xref> and we often encounter cases of failed induction of sedation or awakening during examination. It is reported that the sedation success rate (PSSS: &#x0003c;3) for midazolam in pediatric MRI was 9.5%, which was significantly lower than the 88.1% rate for dexmedetomidine.<xref rid="deo270022-bib-0026" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>26</sup>
</xref>
</p><p>The ESPGHAN&#x000a0;suggests performing CS in children under general anesthesia or, if general anesthesia is not available, under deep sedation in a carefully monitored environment.<xref rid="deo270022-bib-0004" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref> If a pediatric patient awakens during an endoscopic procedure, they will not be able to control themselves and will have difficulty continuing the examination. This may also lead to psychological trauma in fearful patients. Two patients sedated with midazolam in this study became fearful and hyperventilated, and one had his CS interrupted. Thiamylal may be advantageous over midazolam in maintaining deep sedation with less mid&#x02010;awakening. In addition, subgroup analysis showed a significantly higher success rate of CS without mid&#x02010;awakening in the thiamylal group among low&#x02010;weight children and children with ASA2 comorbidity (Table <xref rid="deo270022-supinfo-0001" ref-type="">S2</xref>), suggesting that thiamylal may be useful for even low&#x02010;weight children who may be anxious about the CS.</p><p>In the present study, adverse events during examination occurred in 24% of the cases (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="deo270022-tbl-0003" ref-type="table">3</xref>). The most common adverse event was oxygen desaturation, occurring in 10 of 60 patients (17%). Although oxygen desaturation was observed in 6 of 32 patients (19%) in the thiamylal group, the incidence was similar to that in the midazolam group (14%). Irie et&#x000a0;al. reported that respiratory complications occurred in 10.2% of pediatric patients who underwent MRI under thiamylal sedation.<xref rid="deo270022-bib-0006" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref> Although the incidence of respiratory complications related to thiamylal was more frequent at 19% in this study, this may be due to the longer examination time and higher drug use for endoscopy than for MRI. Importantly, there were no severe adverse respiratory events requiring airway intervention or mask bag ventilation in the present study. In addition, vomiting was observed in 9% (3/32) of patients during recovery. Kinoshita et&#x000a0;al. reported vomiting in 22.6% of patients after ablation with thiamylal&#x02010;based sedation.<xref rid="deo270022-bib-0027" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>27</sup>
</xref>
</p><p>On the other hand, a previous study on midazolam reported that vomiting occurred in 5% of pediatric patients undergoing gastrointestinal endoscopy,<xref rid="deo270022-bib-0028" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>28</sup>
</xref> suggesting that vomiting is a relatively common but not unique side effect of thiamylal. Thus, we believe that our sedation protocol using thiamylal is acceptable regarding both the incidence and severity of adverse events. However, according to previous reports, barbiturates are associated with significantly more adverse events than etomidate or propofol.<xref rid="deo270022-bib-0029" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>29</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="deo270022-bib-0030" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>30</sup>
</xref> Therefore, sedation using thiamylal should be provided under the strict supervision of a pediatrician skilled in its use.</p><p>In this study, thiamylal was used more often in younger children with lighter weight (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="deo270022-tbl-0001" ref-type="table">1</xref>). As body weight is an important factor affecting sedative effects, a subgroup analysis was performed, excluding children with lighter body weight. Even in children with higher body weights, the rate of mid&#x02010;awakening was significantly lower in the thiamylal group (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="deo270022-tbl-0003" ref-type="table">3</xref>). In most cases of CS in adults, the patient can follow the examiner's instructions and can be examined under conscious sedation. Although older children may be able to undergo endoscopy with self&#x02010;restraint, some are unable to. Thus, thiamylal may be a good indication for older, larger children and even adults who are uncooperative with endoscopy, who had unsuccessful sedation in the past, or who were anxious and desired deep sedation.</p><p>The limitations of this study were as follows. First, it was a retrospective study. There was a tendency for thiamylal to be selected by younger children with low body weights, which could be considered a selection bias. The latest guideline for pediatric gastrointestinal endoscopy in Japan states that it is difficult to recommend a specific drug for sedation.<xref rid="deo270022-bib-0009" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>9</sup>
</xref> Therefore, even at our hospital, the criteria were not clearly defined and the choice of sedative was left to the judgment of the anesthesiologist. In our facility, thiamylal tended to be the customary choice for younger children, while midazolam, which is more commonly used in adults, was more likely to be selected for older children. Second, the small sample size precluded the evaluation of the most serious adverse events, such as cardiopulmonary arrest, laryngospasm, incidental aspiration, permanent neurological injury, or death.<xref rid="deo270022-bib-0031" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>31</sup>
</xref> Third, not only cases with CS alone but also those with combined EGD (CS + EGD) were included, and sedative doses were probably higher in CS + EGD cases, which are more invasive. Finally, the types of concomitant analgesics used in each group differed, which may be a confounding factor. However, the present findings have important implications for selecting sedatives for pediatric CS. Further prospective clinical studies with sufficient numbers of participants are required to address these limitations.</p><p>In conclusion, the results of this study demonstrate the adequate efficacy and safety of intravenous thiamylal for sedation during CS in children. Thiamylal had a higher rate of successful CS without mid&#x02010;awakening than midazolam. As there are no previous reports on using thiamylal for sedation in endoscopy, this study provides insights into a new option for sedation in pediatric endoscopy.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="deo270022-sec-0180"><title>CONFLICT OF INTEREST STATEMENT</title><p>None.</p></sec><sec id="deo270022-sec-0190"><title>PATIENT CONSENT STATEMENT</title><p>Written informed consent was obtained from at least one parent before endoscopy.</p></sec><sec id="deo270022-sec-0200"><title>CLINICAL TRIAL REGISTRATION</title><p>N/A</p></sec><sec id="deo270022-sec-0210"><title>ETHICS STATEMENT</title><p>This study was approved by the Institutional Review Board of Oita University Faculty of Medicine, and it was conducted in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supporting information</title><supplementary-material id="deo270022-supinfo-0001" position="float" content-type="local-data"/><supplementary-material id="deo270022-supitem-0001" position="float" content-type="local-data"><caption><p>
<bold>TABLE S1</bold> Pediatrics sedation state score (PSSS) is shown.</p></caption><media xlink:href="DEO2-5-e70022-s001.xlsx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="deo270022-supitem-0002" position="float" content-type="local-data"><caption><p>
<bold>TABLE S2</bold> Results of subgroup analysis of sedation effects are shown.</p></caption><media xlink:href="DEO2-5-e70022-s002.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="deo270022-sec-0170"><title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title><p>The authors thank Editage (<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.editage.jp/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.editage.jp/</ext-link>) for the English language editing.</p></ack><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="deo270022-sec-0230"><title>DATA AVAILABILITY STATEMENT</title><p>All pertinent data are included within the paper and its Supporting Information file. The data underlying this article will be shared on reasonable request to the corresponding author.</p></sec><ref-list id="deo270022-bibl-0001"><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="deo270022-bib-0001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270022-cit-0001">
<string-name>
<surname>Isoldi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Mallardo</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Quitadamo</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Leter</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Cucchiara</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Review on advances in pediatric endoscopy in the management of inflammatory bowel disease</article-title>. <source>Curr Pediatr Rev</source>
<year>2024</year>; DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/0115733963268547231128101929</pub-id> Online ahead of print.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270022-bib-0002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270022-cit-0002">
<string-name>
<surname>Tilma</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Tilma</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Tilma</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Retrospective study recommends endoscopy when diagnosing lymphocytic colitis or eosinophilic gastrointestinal disorder in children with abdominal pain</article-title>. <source>Acta Paediatr</source>
<year>2019</year>; <volume>108</volume>: <fpage>154</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>159</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30054943</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270022-bib-0003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270022-cit-0003">
<string-name>
<surname>Mahoney</surname>
<given-names>LB</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Lightdale</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Sedation of the pediatric and adolescent patient for GI procedures</article-title>. <source>Curr Treat Options Gastroenterol</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>412</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>421</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17897579</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270022-bib-0004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270022-cit-0004">
<string-name>
<surname>Tringali</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Thomson</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Dumonceau</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names>
</string-name>
<italic toggle="yes">et&#x000a0;al</italic>. <article-title>Pediatric gastrointestinal endoscopy: European Society of Gastrointestinal Endoscopy (ESGE) and European Society for Paediatric Gastroenterology Hepatology and Nutrition (ESPGHAN) Guideline Executive summary</article-title>. <source>Endoscopy</source>
<year>2017</year>; <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>83</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>91</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27617420</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270022-bib-0005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270022-cit-0005">
<string-name>
<surname>Sienkiewicz</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Albrecht</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Zi&#x000f3;&#x00142;kowski</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Dziechciarz</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Propofol&#x02010;alfentanyl versus midazolam&#x02010;alfentanyl in inducing procedural amnesia of upper gastrointestinal endoscopy in children&#x02013;Blind randomised trial</article-title>. <source>Eur J Pediatr</source>
<year>2015</year>; <volume>174</volume>: <fpage>1475</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1480</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25956274</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270022-bib-0006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270022-cit-0006">
<string-name>
<surname>Irie</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Hirai</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Kano</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Yanabe</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Migita</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Efficacy and safety of intravenous thiamylal in pediatric procedural sedation for magnetic resonance imaging</article-title>. <source>Brain Dev</source>
<year>2020</year>; <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>477</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>483</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32359890</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270022-bib-0007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270022-cit-0007">
<string-name>
<surname>Kuga</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Maeda</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ihara</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Pediatric procedural sedation in Japan: A single&#x02010;facility study of 1,436 cases</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Int</source>
<year>2020</year>; <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>1346</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1350</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32501599</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270022-bib-0008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270022-cit-0008">
<string-name>
<surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>CK</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Lau</surname>
<given-names>YW</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Chan</surname>
<given-names>HM</given-names>
</string-name>
<italic toggle="yes">et&#x000a0;al</italic>. <article-title>Intravenous thiamylal and local anesthetic infiltration for pediatric facial repair procedures performed in emergency departments</article-title>. <source>Kaohsiung J Med Sci</source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>192</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>199</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20434100</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270022-bib-0009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="miscellaneous" id="deo270022-cit-0009">
<collab collab-type="authors">Japanese Society for Pediatric Gastroenterology, Hepatology and Nutrition</collab>
. <article-title>Clinical guidelines for pediatrics gastrointestinal endoscopy</article-title>. <year>2017</year>. (in Japanese).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270022-bib-0010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270022-cit-0010">
<string-name>
<surname>Cravero</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Askins</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Sriswasdi</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Tsze</surname>
<given-names>DS</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Zurakowski</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Sinnott</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Validation of the pediatric sedation state scale</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>
<year>2017</year>; <volume>139</volume>: <elocation-id>e20162897</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28557732</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270022-bib-0011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270022-cit-0011">
<string-name>
<surname>Thomson</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Sharma</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Diagnostic yield of upper and lower gastrointestinal endoscopies in children in a tertiary centre</article-title>. <source>J Pediatr Gastroenterol Nutr</source>
<year>2017</year>; <volume>64</volume>: <fpage>903</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>936</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28333770</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270022-bib-0012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270022-cit-0012">
<string-name>
<surname>Friedt</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Welsch</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>An update on pediatric endoscopy</article-title>. <source>Eur J Med Res</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>24</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23885793</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270022-bib-0013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270022-cit-0013">
<string-name>
<surname>Sargin</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Uluer</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Aydogan</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</string-name>
<italic toggle="yes">et&#x000a0;al</italic>. <article-title>Anxiety levels in patients undergoing sedation for elective upper gastrointestinal endoscopy and colonoscopy</article-title>. <source>Med Arch</source>
<year>2016</year>; <volume>70</volume>: <fpage>112</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>115</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27147784</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270022-bib-0014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270022-cit-0014">
<string-name>
<surname>Sarg&#x00131;n</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Uluer</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>The effect of pre&#x02010;procedure anxiety on sedative requirements for sedation during upper gastrointestinal endoscopy</article-title>. <source>Turk J Surg</source>
<year>2020</year>; <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>368</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>373</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33778396</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270022-bib-0015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270022-cit-0015">
<string-name>
<surname>Miqdady</surname>
<given-names>MIS</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Hayajneh</surname>
<given-names>WA</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Abdelhadi</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Gilger</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Ketamine and midazolam sedation for pediatric gastrointestinal endoscopy in the Arab world</article-title>. <source>World J Gastroenterol</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>3630</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3635</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21987610</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270022-bib-0016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270022-cit-0016">
<collab collab-type="authors">ASGE Standards of Practice Committee</collab>
, <string-name>
<surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>KK</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Anderson</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names>
</string-name>
<italic toggle="yes">et&#x000a0;al</italic>. <article-title>Modifications in endoscopic practice for pediatric patients</article-title>. <source>Gastrointest Endosc</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>67</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18155419</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270022-bib-0017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270022-cit-0017">
<string-name>
<surname>Lightdale</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Mahoney</surname>
<given-names>LB</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Schwarz</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Liacouras</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Methods of sedation in pediatric endoscopy: A survey of NASPGHAN members</article-title>. <source>J Pediatr Gastroenterol Nutr</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>500</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>502</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18030225</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270022-bib-0018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270022-cit-0018">
<string-name>
<surname>Morita</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Takedatsu</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Yoshioka</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>
<italic toggle="yes">et&#x000a0;al</italic>. <article-title>Utility of diagnostic colonoscopy in pediatric intestinal disease</article-title>. <source>J Clin Med</source>
<year>2022</year>; <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>5747</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36233615</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270022-bib-0019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270022-cit-0019">
<string-name>
<surname>van Beek</surname>
<given-names>EJ</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Leroy</surname>
<given-names>PL</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Safe and effective procedural sedation for gastrointestinal endoscopy in children</article-title>. <source>J Pediatr Gastroenterol Nutr</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>171</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>185</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21975965</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270022-bib-0020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270022-cit-0020">
<string-name>
<surname>L&#x000f6;scher</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Rogawski</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>How theories evolved concerning the mechanism of action of barbiturates</article-title>. <source>Epilepsia</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>53</volume> (Suppl <issue>8</issue>): <fpage>12</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>25</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270022-bib-0021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270022-cit-0021">
<string-name>
<surname>Ishida</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Nishiyama</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Yamaguchi</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</string-name>
<italic toggle="yes">et&#x000a0;al</italic>. <article-title>Thiamylal anaesthetic therapy for febrile refractory status epilepticus in children</article-title>. <source>Seizure</source>
<year>2020</year>; <volume>80</volume>: <fpage>12</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>17</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32480278</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270022-bib-0022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270022-cit-0022">
<string-name>
<surname>Saylan</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Akbulut</surname>
<given-names>UE</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>A comparison of ketamine&#x02010;midazolam combination and propofol&#x02010;fentanyl combination on procedure comfort and recovery process in pediatric colonoscopy procedures</article-title>. <source>Pak J Med Sci</source>
<year>2021</year>; <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>483</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>488</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33679936</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270022-bib-0023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270022-cit-0023">
<string-name>
<surname>Gilger</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Spearman</surname>
<given-names>RS</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Dietrich</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Spearman</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Wilsey</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names>
<suffix>Jr</suffix>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Zayat</surname>
<given-names>MN</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Safety and effectiveness of ketamine as a sedative agent for pediatric GI endoscopy</article-title>. <source>Gastrointest Endosc</source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>659</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>663</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15114309</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270022-bib-0024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270022-cit-0024">
<string-name>
<surname>Motamed</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Aminpour</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Hashemian</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Soltani</surname>
<given-names>AE</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Najafi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Farahmand</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Midazolam&#x02010;ketamine combination for moderate sedation in upper GI endoscopy</article-title>. <source>J Pediatr Gastroenterol Nutr</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>422</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>426</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21857244</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270022-bib-0025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270022-cit-0025">
<string-name>
<surname>Moon</surname>
<given-names>YE</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Paradoxical reaction to midazolam in children</article-title>. <source>Korean J Anesthesiol</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>65</volume>: <fpage>2</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23904931</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270022-bib-0026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270022-cit-0026">
<string-name>
<surname>Chandrasekar</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Dwibedi</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Das</surname>
<given-names>RR</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Padhy</surname>
<given-names>BM</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Behera</surname>
<given-names>BK</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Comparison of oral triclofos and intranasal midazolam and dexmedetomidine for sedation in children undergoing magnetic resonance imaging (MRI): An open&#x02010;label, three&#x02010;arm, randomized trial</article-title>. <source>Eur J Pediatr</source>
<year>2023</year>; <volume>182</volume>: <fpage>1385</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1391</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36658444</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270022-bib-0027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270022-cit-0027">
<string-name>
<surname>Kinoshita</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Harada</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Takimoto</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Shibata</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Sakakibara</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Adachi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Fentanyl compared to buprenorphine for atrial fibrillation ablation analgesia and sedation: A retrospective cross&#x02010;sectional study</article-title>. <source>J Pharm Health Care Sci</source>
<year>2021</year>; <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>2</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33397507</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270022-bib-0028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270022-cit-0028">
<string-name>
<surname>Mamula</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Markowitz</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Neiswender</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</string-name>
<italic toggle="yes">et&#x000a0;al</italic>. <article-title>Safety of intravenous midazolam and fentanyl for pediatric GI endoscopy: Prospective study of 1578 endoscopies</article-title>. <source>Gastrointest Endosc</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>65</volume>: <fpage>203</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>210</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17258977</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270022-bib-0029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270022-cit-0029">
<string-name>
<surname>Baxter</surname>
<given-names>AL</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Mallory</surname>
<given-names>MD</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Spandorfer</surname>
<given-names>PR</given-names>
</string-name>
<italic toggle="yes">et&#x000a0;al</italic>. <article-title>Etomidate versus pentobarbital for computed tomography sedations: Report from the Pediatric Sedation Research Consortium</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Emerg Care</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>690</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>695</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18090099</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270022-bib-0030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270022-cit-0030">
<string-name>
<surname>Mallory</surname>
<given-names>MD</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Baxter</surname>
<given-names>AL</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Kost</surname>
<given-names>SI</given-names>
</string-name>; <collab collab-type="authors">Pediatric Sedation Research Consortium</collab>
<article-title>. Propofol vs pentobarbital for sedation of children undergoing magnetic resonance imaging: Results from the Pediatric Sedation Research Consortium</article-title>. <source>Paediatr Anaesth</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>601</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>611</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19645979</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270022-bib-0031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270022-cit-0031">
<string-name>
<surname>Bhatt</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Johnson</surname>
<given-names>DW</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Taljaard</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>
<italic toggle="yes">et&#x000a0;al</italic>. <article-title>Association of preprocedural fasting with outcomes of emergency department sedation in children</article-title>. <source>JAMA Pediatr</source>
<year>2018</year>; <volume>172</volume>: <fpage>678</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>685</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29800944</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>