<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Heliyon</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Heliyon</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Heliyon</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2405-8440</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11786664</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2405-8440(24)17094-6</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e41063</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e41063</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Effective adsorbent for the removal of methylene blue using natural serpentine/magnetite nanocomposites: Isotherm and kinetic study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name><surname>Basit</surname><given-names>Amtul</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name><surname>Yaqoob</surname><given-names>Zahida</given-names></name><email>zahidayaqoob20@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="cor2" ref-type="corresp">&#x0204e;&#x0204e;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name><surname>Zahid</surname><given-names>Aliya</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4"><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>Shaista</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5"><name><surname>Shoukat</surname><given-names>Beenish</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au6"><name><surname>Khaliq</surname><given-names>Abdul</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au7"><name><surname>Chughtai</surname><given-names>Muhammad Tajammal</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au8"><name><surname>Batul</surname><given-names>Rahila</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au9"><name><surname>Rehman</surname><given-names>Muhammad Atiq Ur</given-names></name><email>atique1.1@hotmail.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#x0204e;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au10"><name><surname>Husain</surname><given-names>Syed Wilayat</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Department of Materials Science and Engineering, Institute of Space Technology, Islamabad, 44000, Pakistan</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Department of Chemistry, Government College University, Lahore, 54000, Pakistan</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>College of Engineering, University of Hail, Saudi Arabia</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>College of Pharmacy, University of Hail, Saudi Arabia</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x0204e;</label>Corresponding author. <email>atique1.1@hotmail.com</email></corresp><corresp id="cor2"><label>&#x0204e;&#x0204e;</label>Corresponding author. <email>zahidayaqoob20@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>09</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>30</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>09</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue>2</issue><elocation-id>e41063</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>6</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2024 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="abs0010"><p>The natural serpentine from Skardu, Pakistan, has been incorporated with magnetite (Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>) to form a nanocomposite using a chemical co-precipitation method for the removal of methylene blue (MB) dye. Various techniques such as Field Emission Scanning Electron Microscopy (FESEM), Energy Dispersive X-ray spectroscopy (EDX), Fourier Transform Infrared spectroscopy (FTIR), Brunauer-Emmett-Teller (BET), and Vibrating Sample Magnetometer (VSM) have been employed for the characterization. It was found that the composite exhibits sheet-like morphologies, Mg- and Si-rich surfaces, a surface area of 20.8&#x000a0;m<sup>2</sup>/g, and magnetic properties. The adsorption study showed that the Freundlich isotherm and pseudo-second-order kinetics best described the process with the nanocomposite achieving a 98&#x000a0;% MB removal efficiency, outperforming the pure serpentine. These results highlight the potential of serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposite as an effective, cost-efficient adsorbent for wastewater treatment applications.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="graphical" id="abs0015"><title>Graphical abstract</title><p><fig id="undfig1" position="anchor"><alt-text id="alttext0010">Image 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="ga1"/></fig></p></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Serpentines</kwd><kwd>Magnetite</kwd><kwd>Nanocomposites</kwd><kwd>Removal</kwd><kwd>Co-precipitation</kwd><kwd>Dye adsorption</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0010">The growth of the dyeing industry is becoming more extensive because it can provide materials such as leather and beautiful fiber colors. This huge production of the dyeing and printing industry leads to a large amount of wastewater [<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Methylene blue (MB) is a common dye that is used for dyeing leather; this water-soluble dye is used for printing on cotton [<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. The major environmental concern is to remove MB from industrial effluents [<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. There are numerous methods to treat dye wastewater such as ion exchange, membrane method, flocculation sedimentation, chemical oxidation, and adsorption [<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Adsorption is the most common and cost-effective method among others, which removes wastes from water due to high surface area resulting in large adsorption capacity [<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Adsorption of different contaminants in water such as dyes, anions, heavy metals, and drug residue using cost-effective materials is often a promising approach for a sustainable future. Various materials have been studied to develop novel adsorbents for the treatment of wastewater. Zeolites, graphene nano-sheets, and clay minerals are among the synthetic and natural materials that have drawn interest due to their abundance, low cost, chemical inactivity, and superior adsorptive characteristics [<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>]. However, different possible conventional and non-traditional forms of these effective adsorbents and cost-effective nanoparticles have already been applied to wastewater treatment in order to remove particular organic and inorganic contaminants [<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Recently, magnetic adsorbents have become interesting for researchers because they can easily be recovered by using an external magnetic field [<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Farahat et al. reported the magnetic particle with serpentine as an adsorbent for Cr (VI) removal from tannery wastewater [<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Similarly, Nayl et al. prepared and characterized the magnetite talc nanocomposite as an effective adsorbent for Cr (VI) and organic dye [<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Kalantari et al. developed Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>/talc nanocomposite and used it to isolate heavy metals like Cu (II), Pb (II), and Ni (II) from water [<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>].</p><p id="p0015">Serpentine minerals are phyllosilicates that are typically generated during the hydration of basic to ultrabasic rocks with a vast metamorphic stability field. Serpentine, Mg<sub>3</sub>Si<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>(OH)<sub>4</sub> is widely abundant in Skardu that is mainly composed of one or more of the three magnesium silicate minerals [<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. The brucite octahedral magnesium hydroxide is held together by ionic and covalent bonds between tetrahedral silica sheets [<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Serpentine is distinguished by the presence of numerous hydroxyl (OH) functional groups, along with water molecules that are attached to its surface [<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Serpentine is frequently used as a decorative stone and as a raw material to produce asbestos and magnesium oxide with high purity [<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Magnetic nanoparticles are considered the best adsorbents to eliminate all kinds of contaminants from water and wastewater [<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Moreover, magnetite (Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>) is simple to prepare and functionalize in the lab, it has been thoroughly investigated as a core material. Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> may be able to satisfy the rising need for biological applications, such as drug delivery, thermal treatment, and diagnostic magnetic resonance imaging due to its superparamagnetism and low toxicity [<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanoparticles have shown to be highly effective in adsorbing heavy metal ions for removal. The adsorption process on magnetite occurs through a combination of electrostatic attraction and ligand exchange mechanisms [<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>].</p><p id="p0020">To our knowledge, no work has been reported regarding the use of naturally abundant serpentine from Skardu for dye removal from waste water. In the present work, naturally abundant serpentine from Skardu has been incorporated with Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanoparticles for the removal of methylene blue (MB) from contaminated aqueous solutions. Both serpentine and its nanocomposite were characterized using FE-SEM, FTIR, VSM, and BET. Kinetic and isotherm models were investigated to determine the adsorption capacity. Langmuir and Freundlich models were analyzed to fit the adsorption data of serpentine and the serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposite for the removal of MB.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><label>2</label><title>Materials and method</title><p id="p0025">The following materials were required to produce the serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposite; ferrous chloride tetrahydrate (FeCl<sub>2</sub>.4H<sub>2</sub>O) (Fe (II)), sodium hydroxide (NaOH), and ferric chloride hexahydrate (FeCl<sub>3</sub>.6H<sub>2</sub>O) (Fe (III)), methylene blue (C<sub>16</sub>H<sub>18</sub>CIN<sub>3</sub>S, 98.5 % purity), and Ethanol (99.9&#x000a0;%) which were all purchased from Sigma Aldrich. Serpentine was collected from Shiger, Skardu. All these aqueous solutions were used with de-ionized water.</p><sec id="sec2.1"><label>2.1</label><title>Synthesis of serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposite</title><p id="p0030">For the synthesis of serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposites, the procedure reported in the literature was followed [<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Firstly, 2.0&#x000a0;g of serpentine was mixed with 20&#x000a0;mL of deionized water and stirred for 1&#x000a0;h at 50&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. In another beaker, 6.5&#x000a0;g of FeCl<sub>3</sub>.6H<sub>2</sub>O and 2.5&#x000a0;g of FeCl<sub>2</sub>.4H<sub>2</sub>O were dissolved in 40&#x000a0;mL of deionized water at room temperature with continuous stirring. The molar ratio of FeCl<sub>3</sub> to FeCl<sub>2</sub> was adjusted to 2:1 by adding specific amounts of Fe<sup>3+</sup> and Fe<sup>2+</sup>. The contents of the two beakers were then mixed together, and the mixture was stirred for 1&#x000a0;h to allow the ions to adhere to the surface of the serpentine, resulting in a serpentine/Fe<sup>3+</sup>-Fe<sup>2+</sup>composites. Subsequently, 15&#x000a0;mL of freshly prepared NaOH (2.0&#x000a0;M) was added to the composite suspension with continued stirring. The resulting suspensions were centrifuged at 1000&#x000a0;rpm for 10&#x000a0;min, washed twice with ethanol and double-distilled water until a neutral pH was achieved, and then dried in an oven at 100&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. The procedures were conducted at room temperature in a nitrogen gas environment to maintain an oxygen-free atmosphere. The experimental protocols are illustrated in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>.<fig id="fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Experimental procedure for synthesis of serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposites.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0015">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><label>2.2</label><title>Adsorption experiment</title><p id="p0035">A stock solution of MB was prepared and diluted to the required concentration of 100&#x000a0;ppm (dye&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;50&#x000a0;mg, distilled water&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;500&#x000a0;mL), and a certain weight of adsorbent was employed in a 100&#x000a0;mL dye solution for both samples. The adsorbent was separated magnetically by using magnet and the analysis was done under the UV&#x02013;visible spectroscopy for MB removal.</p><p id="p0040">Equation <xref rid="fd1" ref-type="disp-formula">(1)</xref> determined the adsorbed amount (q<sub>t</sub>) of MB using the formula:<disp-formula id="fd1"><label>Eq.1</label><mml:math id="M1" altimg="si1.svg" alttext="Equation 1."><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where C<sub>i</sub> is the initial concentration (mg/L) of MB, W is the composite mass (g) C<sub>t</sub> is the concentration of (mg/L) of dye after time (t), and V is the dye solution volume (L).</p><p id="p0045">By adjusting the adsorbent dose (1&#x02013;5&#x000a0;mg), time interval (10&#x02013;60&#x000a0;min), and dye concentration (10&#x02013;50&#x000a0;ppm), the adsorption of MB on serpentine and serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposites, produced by co-precipitation technique, were investigated. The dye concentration was adjusted from 10 to 50&#x000a0;ppm and the dye-adsorbent interaction time was measured. The mixtures were shaken at 125&#x000a0;rpm for 60&#x000a0;min using an orbital shaker (Techno ISO-207). 3&#x000a0;mg of produced serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposites and 20&#x000a0;ppm of metal ion solution were combined, and then the trial was carried out at room temperature for the investigation of the time factor. The adsorption of the MB gradually increases over time up to 60&#x000a0;min which further increase in agitation time may leads towards the greater removal.The adsorbent dose effect was also studied by keeping all the other factors constant (20&#x000a0;ppm dye concentration, time&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;60&#x000a0;min). To ensure reproducibility, each kinetic experiment was repeated three times under identical conditions. The mean values are presented with standard deviations as error bars in the figures. The adsorption comparison between the serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposites and serpentine leads to conclude the better adsorption efficiency of serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposites.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><label>2.3</label><title>Characterization</title><p id="p0050">Field emission scanning electron microscopy (FESEM-EDS: Tescan-MIRA III) with an energy dispersive X-ray analyzer (EDX) was used to evaluate the morphology of the sample. To confirm the crystallinity of serpentine and serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposites, powdered samples were subjected to X-ray diffraction (XRD: Panalytical-PW3719) using Cu K&#x003b1; radiations in the 2&#x003b8; range from 20 to 80&#x000b0; (step size: 0.02). Fourier transform infrared spectroscopy (FTIR: Nicolet Summit LITE) in a transmittance mode was used to identify the functional groups in each sample. The scan speed was 4&#x000a0;m/s, and the range covered was 4000&#x02013;400&#x000a0;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. The magnetization behavior of the samples was evaluated using a vibrating sample magnetometer (LAKESHORE, 7407) to measure the magnetization at ambient temperature as a function of magnetic field strength (Oe). The surface area and pore size range for the serpentine and serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> were computed using the Brunauer-Emmett-Teller (BET) and Barrett-Joyner-Halenda (BJH) models (V-Sorb 2800, GOLD APP Instruments), respectively. Nitrogen (N<sub>2</sub>) adsorption-desorption isotherm was obtained at liquid N<sub>2</sub> temperature (77&#x000a0;K).</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><label>3</label><title>Results and discussion</title><sec id="sec3.1"><label>3.1</label><title>SEM analysis</title><p id="p0055">The surface morphologies of serpentine and serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> were evaluated via FE-SEM and their chemical compositions were analyzed through EDX as illustrated in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>. The layered surface with a few big flakes; is usually similar to the talc structure (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>(a)) [<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. However, no significant morphological differences between serpentine and serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposite were observed as shown in (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> b). Because serpentine has a high concentration of Mg, Si, and Al, the EDS analysis of the gray-colored patches reflects the chemical composition of serpentine (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>(c)). Similarly, EDS analysis of serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> shows Fe, Mg, Si, and Al (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>(d)).<fig id="fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>FESEM images (a) Serpentine (b) Serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> along with EDX analysis showing elemental composition for (c) Serpentine (d) Serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0020">Fig. 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><label>3.2</label><title>XRD analysis</title><p id="p0060">The XRD patterns of serpentine and serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposite are shown in <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>(a) and (b). The XRD pattern of serpentine and antigorite (JCPDS card No. 02-0095) exhibits a strong correlation with the minimal existence of talc mineral (JCPDS card no. 73-0147) at 2&#x003b8;&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;12.19&#x01d52;, 18.48&#x01d52;, 24.76&#x01d52;, 29.07&#x01d52;, 35.91&#x01d52;, 37.94&#x01d52;, 38.20&#x01d52;, 41.92&#x01d52;, 50.97&#x01d52;, 60.16&#x01d52;, 60.70&#x01d52;, 71.99&#x01d52;, and 72.19&#x01d52; which is shown in <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3 (a)</xref> [<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The distinctive peaks of magnetite (JCPDS card no. 89-0688) can be identified at 2&#x003b8;&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;22.12&#x01d52;, 30.69&#x01d52;, 36.03&#x01d52;, 44.90&#x01d52;, 58.14&#x01d52; and 62.04&#x01d52; (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> b) [<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. All mineral phases were found in serpentine, according to the mineralogical data for the produced serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposite. The analysis of serpentine composition revealed that MgO and SiO<sub>2</sub> are its primary constituents; these results also indicated from the EDX analysis.<fig id="fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>XRD pattern of (a) serpentine and (b) serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposite which matches the standard JCPDS cards.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0025">Fig. 3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr3"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec3.3"><label>3.3</label><title>FTIR analysis</title><p id="p0065"><xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> illustrates the comparison of FTIR spectra for the serpentine and serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposite. Serpentines are an assemblage of phyllosilicate minerals that possess hydroxyl groups (-OH) on their surface. These hydroxyl groupings can be employed to coordinate Fe metal ions. When Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanoparticles contact serpentine, the Fe ions present on the surface of nanoparticle can co-ordinate with the hydroxyl groups existing on the surface of serpentine [<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. For serpentine, serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposite, and serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>/MB adsorbent the attributed peak at 3689-3674&#x000a0;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> or 1640&#x000a0;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, 2126&#x000a0;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, 1482-1489&#x000a0;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, 934-939&#x000a0;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, and 601-609&#x000a0;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> due to the structural hydroxyl moiety of stretching vibration of Mg-OH and adsorbed water on the surface, C-H, Si-O-Si, Si-O<sub>4</sub>, Si-O-Mg bands of serpentine similar to bands mentioned for talc [<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>, <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>, <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>, <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>]. The absorption band at 592-540&#x000a0;cm&#x0207b;<sup>1</sup> corresponds to the Fe&#x02013;O bond in Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4.</sub> Hence, the FTIR analysis allows us to conclude that the Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanoparticles with a serpentine coating show distinctive absorption bands that match the Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> core and the serpentine covering.<fig id="fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>FTIR spectra of serpentine, Serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposite, and serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>/MB adsorbent.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0030">Fig. 4</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr4"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec3.4"><label>3.4</label><title>Surface area analysis</title><p id="p0070"><xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5 (a)</xref> shows the N<sub>2</sub> adsorption-desorption plot of serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposite and its pore size distribution. This allows the prediction that synthetic nanocomposite materials contain both macropores and mesopores. The pore size distribution obtained from the BJH analysis, the BJH curve shows narrow and intense peaks in the pore size distribution curve. The hole size distribution curve shows that they appear in a range of 1&#x02013;150&#x000a0;nm. The specific surface area of serpentine is found to be 16.6&#x000a0;m<sup>2</sup>/g which is much smaller than that of the nanocomposite materials, which reaches 20.8&#x000a0;m<sup>2</sup>/g to enhance the active sites for adsorption [<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>, <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>, <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>]. Similar kinds of results were reported in the previous work. The highest portion of pore size obtained in nanocomposite was 128&#x000a0;nm, which confirms the detection of mesoporosity in the NPs. A very small number of macrospores (&#x0003c;50&#x000a0;nm) were also detected. The 20.8&#x000a0;m<sup>2</sup>/g surface area of this nanocomposite is moderate compared to similar magnetic nanocomposites such as Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>/talc and Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>/reduced graphene which have surface areas ranging from 30 to 150&#x000a0;m<sup>2</sup>/g [<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. The serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> composite, while having surface area not as high as these advanced nanocomposites, still offers a good balance between surface area and cost-effectiveness. Moreover, it allows for better adsorption performance compared to pure serpentine. This improvement enables the nanocomposite to achieve a 98&#x000a0;% removal efficiency for methylene blue.<fig id="fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>(a) Type-IV isotherm with a wide hysteresis loop of the serpentine (b) the pore size distribution of the serpentine (c) Type-IV isotherm with a wide hysteresis loop of the serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> (d) the pore size distribution of the serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposite.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0035">Fig. 5</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr5"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec3.5"><label>3.5</label><title>Magnetic properties</title><p id="p0075">The magnetic properties of the nanocomposite were analyzed by the vibrating sample magnetometer (VSM) at room temperature. The results of magnetic saturation of serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposite were 0.534 emu/g as shown in <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>. Fei et al. reported the magnetic properties of polymer modified magnetic nanoparticles for the removal of cationic dyes using VSM [<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Similarly, Li et al. investigated the saturation magnetization (13.3 emu/g) of magnetic guar gum-grafted carbon nanotubes for separating methylene blue from an aqueous solution [<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. The magnetization was decreased with the addition of serpentine due to large amount of non-magnetic serpentine. The reduced saturation magnetization of serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposite observed that the talc layers act as magnetic insulation bounded to nanoparticles [<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. The incorporated magnetic nanoparticles enhance the overall surface area available for dye adsorption. The magnetic adsorbent can then be separated from wastewater using an external magnetic field [<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>].<fig id="fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>M&#x000a0;&#x02212;&#x000a0;H Curve for serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposite.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0040">Fig. 6</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr6"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec3.6"><label>3.6</label><title>Effect of concentration, contact time, and adsorbent dose on methylene blue</title><p id="p0080">The adsorbent dose resulted in 98&#x000a0;% removal of methylene blue in the case of the serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposite while it was 94&#x000a0;% in the case of serpentine. The increased adsorbent concentration leads to optimal adsorption efficiency at a 5&#x000a0;mg dose, as shown in <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>(a). This is due to the large surface area and more accessible adsorption sites of the serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposite [<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Increasing dye concentration leads to dye removal of 91&#x000a0;% for serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposites and 84&#x000a0;% for serpentine. This is due to the extended duration of interaction between the active site and the adsorbent/adsorbate, which leads to saturation and a decrease in adsorption capability, as illustrated in <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>(b). Initially the removal of the MB abruptly increases that shows that at the time of contact between MB and composites there is more active site available that leads to continue regular pattern of removal in case of serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4.</sub> MB removal is carried out with agitation time, resulting in approximately 91&#x000a0;% removal for serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> and 98&#x000a0;% for serpentine as shown in <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>(c). The percentage removal increases with the increase in agitation time due to the gradual mass transfer from the bulk region to the adsorbent surface. In case of serpentine the adsorption increases with time because it is layered structure which increases the adsorption capacity and then shows the smaller increases after equal interval of time while the serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> shows the regular pattern of dye removal. The better adsorption capability of serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposite is due to enhanced surface area as compared to serpentine as shown in <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>. The addition of Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4,</sub> increases the composites magnetic properties which make separation of adsorbent easier and Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> mixed-valence state (Fe<sup>2+</sup> and Fe<sup>3+</sup>) aid dye binding through redox interactions or electron transfer which facilitate dye molecule interaction (&#x003c0;-&#x003c0;&#x02217; interaction or exposure of aromatic ring at metal side) between the nanocomposites and MB dye. The porous nature of the serpentine and the interstitial spaces between the serpentine and the Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> also improve the diffusion of the dye particles. The fundamental principle for the greater adsorption of the serpentine is a synergic effect, strong chemical interaction, and availability of active site between the serpentine and Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>, as well as with MB dye.<fig id="fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Factor affecting the percentage removal of MB (a) Concentration of adsorbent (b) Dye concentration (c) Agitation time.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0045">Fig. 7</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr7"/></fig></p><p id="p0085">However, various factors such as the saturation of the nanocomposites, aggregation, competitive adsorption, and desorption cause a decrease in the removal percentage after some time because Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> causes the saturation of the active sites (unavailability of the active sites) and the aggregation of the nanocomposite (the magnetic property leads to a lower surface area of the nanocomposites). It also creates a desorption ability that causes the nanocomposite ions to return to the solution. In contrast, serpentine itself is more stable and consistent in solution with gradually attaining equilibrium [<xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>, <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>, <xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec3.7"><label>3.7</label><title>Adsorption isotherm modelling</title><p id="p0090">Langmuir, Freundlich, and Temkin isotherms were implemented to design a suitable adsorbent structure and optimize the adsorption process [<xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. To determine the adsorption efficiency of serpentine and serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposite for the removal of MB, mathematical models were developed [<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. We used the Langmuir model to compute the adsorption onto the outer surface of materials. The adsorption data were fitted to the Langmuir model and the resulting <xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref> indicates that the R<sup>2</sup> values for serpentine and serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposite were 0.792 and 0.8202, respectively. This formula was then applied to determine various adsorption characteristics in Equation <xref rid="fd2" ref-type="disp-formula">(2)</xref>.<disp-formula id="fd2"><label>Eq.2</label><mml:math id="M2" altimg="si2.svg" alttext="Equation 2."><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><fig id="fig8"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>Various isotherm models (a) Langmuir and (b) Freundlich (c) Temkin model.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0050">Fig. 8</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr8"/></fig></p><p id="p0095">C<sub>e</sub> represents the metal ion concentration at equilibrium on the nanocomposite surface, and q<sub>e</sub> represents the organic pollutant mass at equilibrium. The maximum adsorption capacity of the serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposite is given by q<sub>m</sub>, which is a key parameter in the Langmuir model. The linear form of the Langmuir model allows us to determine q<sub>m</sub> by analyzing the graph obtained by plotting C<sub>e</sub>/q<sub>e</sub> against C<sub>e</sub>. The q<sub>m</sub> value is obtained from the slope of the graph and then the intercept provides &#x02018;b&#x02019; value, and the additional parameter, R<sub>L</sub> (often known as separation factors), can be calculated using the following formula (equation <xref rid="fd3" ref-type="disp-formula">(3)</xref>).<disp-formula id="fd3"><label>Eq. 3</label><mml:math id="M3" altimg="si3.svg" alttext="Equation 3."><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>C<sub>o</sub> represents the initial concentration of metal ions in the solution, while b stands for the Langmuir constant. The R<sub>L</sub> factor ranges from 0 to 1 with higher R<sub>L</sub> values indicating a more advantageous separation factor for MB. The q<sub>m</sub> values for MB are about 854.70 and 1301 (mg/g), respectively, the R<sub>L</sub> value is 0.0901 for serpentine and 0.0805 for serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposite. Serpentine shows Langmuir constant (b) of about 0.025744 (L/mg), whereas 1.3715 (L/mg) for serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposite. The R<sup>2</sup> values demonstrate that the Langmuir model is suitable for describing the adsorption of organic pollutants on the surface of serpentine and serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposite as shown in <xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref>(a). Freundlich isotherms were used to determine the adsorption efficiency of nanocomposites by using their linear form, equation <xref rid="fd4" ref-type="disp-formula">(4)</xref>.<disp-formula id="fd4"><label>Eq. 4</label><mml:math id="M4" altimg="si4.svg" alttext="Equation 4."><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ln</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ln</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ln</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="p0100">The values of n and k<sub>f</sub> are the Freundlich constants determined by adsorption capacity and intensity by the graph constructed between ln q<sub>e</sub> and ln C<sub>e</sub> as shown in <xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8 (b)</xref>. The value of n is smaller than 1 which means the chemical adsorption occurs in both serpentine and serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposite as shown in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, along with R<sup>2</sup> values [<xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. The uptake of MB occurs at the heterogeneous active sites that build several layers (multilayers) onto the magnetic serpentine surface, according to the Freundlich equation. The development of monolayers is controlled by electrostatic interactions, and some dye molecules can be adsorbed by &#x003c0;-&#x003c0; interactions [<xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>].<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Adsorption isotherm<italic>s</italic> constant for the adsorption of MB onto serpentine and serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposite.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0060">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Model</th><th>Parameters</th><th>Serpentine</th><th>Serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="4" align="left">Langmuir model</td><td align="left">q<sub>m</sub> (mg/g)</td><td align="left">854.70</td><td align="left">1301</td></tr><tr><td align="left">k<sub>L</sub> (L/mg)</td><td align="left">0.02574</td><td align="left">1.3715</td></tr><tr><td align="left">R<sup>2</sup></td><td align="left">0.7901</td><td align="left">0.8202</td></tr><tr><td align="left">R<sub>L</sub></td><td align="left">0.0901</td><td align="left">0.0895</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" align="left">Freundlich model</td><td align="left">k<sub>f</sub> (mg/g)</td><td align="left">42.024</td><td align="left">45.356</td></tr><tr><td align="left">n</td><td align="left">0.6173</td><td align="left">0.5434</td></tr><tr><td align="left">R<sup>2</sup></td><td align="left">0.9716</td><td align="left">0.97971</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left">Temkin model</td><td align="left">B<sub>T</sub> (J/mol)</td><td align="left">2.5159</td><td align="left">2.241</td></tr><tr><td align="left">R<sup>2</sup></td><td align="left">0.72585</td><td align="left">0.7258501</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="p0105">In the case of serpentine, the Langmuir model is most suitable while in the case of serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposite, both Temkin and Freundlich models are suitably elaborated by R<sup>2</sup> value as shown in <xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref>(b) and (c). We prioritize the isotherm model by considering the R<sup>2</sup> factor to ensure that the sequence holds for each organic pollutant. Equilibrium description is carried out by using the Temkin isotherm model where the time adsorption molecules' energy decreases gradually due to adsorbent/adsorbate interaction. The linear form of the Temkin model is given by Equation <xref rid="fd5" ref-type="disp-formula">(5)</xref>.<disp-formula id="fd5"><label>Eq. 5</label><mml:math id="M5" altimg="si5.svg" alttext="Equation 5."><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">q</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">K</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">T</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:msub><mml:mtext>lnC</mml:mtext><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">B</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">T</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="p0110">The values of B<sub>T</sub> and K<sub>T</sub> which are Temkin constants, were determined using the intercept and slope of q<sub>e</sub> vs. ln (C<sub>e</sub>), as indicated in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. It was shown that the q<sub>e</sub> was a linear function of ln (C<sub>e</sub>), with R<sup>2</sup> values of 0.72585 for serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposite produced by the co-precipitation technique and 0.7258 for the value of serpentine, respectively as shown in <xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8 (c)</xref>. The Langmuir model's theoretical q<sub>m</sub> does not accurately reflect the real adsorption capacity due to the low R<sup>2</sup> value. The low value (0.8202) indicates a weak correlation between experimental data and the theoretical Langmuir model, making the calculated R<sub>m</sub> unreliable. The higher R<sup>2</sup> value for the Freundlich model (0.979) suggests that adsorption follows a multilayer mechanism with heterogeneous surface energies, which the Langmuir model cannot capture.</p><p id="p0115">The adsorption efficiency for removing MB dye from the aqueous phase using various previously reported adsorbents is summarized in <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Comparison of the maximum adsorption capacities of the serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposite for MB dye removal with various reported adsorbents.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0065">Table 2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Adsorbent</th><th>q<sub>max</sub> (mg/g)</th><th>Dye Concentration (mg/L)</th><th>Temperature (&#x000b0;C)</th><th>Contact Time (min)</th><th>References</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Polymer-modified using magnetic nanoparticles</td><td align="left">142.90</td><td align="left">50</td><td align="left">30</td><td align="left">120</td><td align="left">[<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Silver nanoparticles with grafted polymer of guar gum/acrylic acid</td><td align="left">833.33</td><td align="left">100</td><td align="left">25</td><td align="left">90</td><td align="left">[<xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Magnetic guar gum grafted with carbon nanotubes</td><td align="left">61.92</td><td align="left">20</td><td align="left">30</td><td align="left">60</td><td align="left">[<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Reduced graphene oxide with silver nanoparticles</td><td align="left">970</td><td align="left">50</td><td align="left">25</td><td align="left">150</td><td align="left">[<xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Xylan/poly (acrylic acid) with magnetic nanocomposite</td><td align="left">438.60</td><td align="left">25</td><td align="left">25</td><td align="left">120</td><td align="left">[<xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Natural serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposite</td><td align="left">392</td><td align="left">20</td><td align="left">25</td><td align="left">60</td><td align="left">Present study</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec3.8"><label>3.8</label><title>Adsorption kinetics</title><p id="p0120">Among the kinetic models used to clarify the mechanism of MB adsorption by serpentine and serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposites were the pseudo-1st-order, pseudo-2nd-order, intra-particles diffusion model, and Elovich model. Because there were multiple sites accessible for MB adsorption, the serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposites performed exceptionally well during the early adsorption stage. The adsorption rate constant and regulating mechanism were calculated using the pseudo-first-order and pseudo-second-order kinetics models. The pseudo-1st order (Eq. <xref rid="fd6" ref-type="disp-formula">(6)</xref>) and second-order kinetic (Eq. <xref rid="fd7" ref-type="disp-formula">(7)</xref>) models have the following linear forms.<disp-formula id="fd6"><label>Eq. 6</label><mml:math id="M6" altimg="si6.svg" alttext="Equation 6."><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ln</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ln</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="fd7"><label>Eq. 7</label><mml:math id="M7" altimg="si7.svg" alttext="Equation 7."><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where q<sub>e</sub> is the mass of the MB adsorbed per unit mass at equilibrium and q<sub>t</sub> is the mass of organic pollutants (MB) adsorbed at the surface of serpentine and serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposites at any given point. The slope of plot of ln (q<sub>e</sub>-q<sub>t</sub>) vs. time shown in <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref>(a) yields the pseudo-first-order rate constants for serpentine and serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>, which is &#x02212;3.6&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup>, and 0.00694, respectively. The R<sup>2</sup> values for serpentine (0.6915) and serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposites (0.8389) are displayed in <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>. Based on the slope and intercept values of the plot of t/q<sub>t</sub> vs. time as shown in <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref>(b), equation <xref rid="fd7" ref-type="disp-formula">(7)</xref> was utilized to get the pseudo-second-order rate constant (k<sub>2</sub>) for MB. The k<sub>2</sub> values for MB with two distinct sample types are - 2.21&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup> for serpentine and &#x02212;5.94&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup> for serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> are shown in <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>. Serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposites are adsorbing organic contaminants by pseudo-second-order kinetics, as indicated by the R<sup>2</sup> value which is almost equal to 1. The intra-particles diffusion model helps in the refined adsorption mechanism and this model rate constant, K<sub>d</sub>, is derived by plotting the graph of q<sub>t</sub> vs. t <sup>&#x000bd;</sup> (<xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9 (c)</xref>), and the boundary thickness [C] is defined by the linear form of equation <xref rid="fd8" ref-type="disp-formula">(8)</xref>.<disp-formula id="fd8"><label>Eq 8</label><mml:math id="M8" altimg="si8.svg" alttext="Equation 8."><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><fig id="fig9"><label>Fig. 9</label><caption><p>Adsorption kinetics (a) Pseudo 1st order, (b) Pseudo 2nd order, (c) IR model, (d) Elovich model.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0055">Fig. 9</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr9"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Adsorption kinetics models for serpentine and serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposites.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0070">Table 3</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Kinetics</th><th>Parameters</th><th>Serpentine</th><th>Serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left">Pseudo 1st order</td><td align="left">K<sub>1</sub> (min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</td><td align="left">&#x02212;3.6&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup></td><td align="left">0.00694</td></tr><tr><td align="left">R<sup>2</sup></td><td align="left">0.6915</td><td align="left">0.839</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left">Pseudo 2nd order</td><td align="left">K<sub>2</sub> (mg/g/min)</td><td align="left">2.21&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup></td><td align="left">5.94&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">R<sup>2</sup></td><td align="left">0.9993</td><td align="left">0.9997</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left">Intra-particle diffusion model</td><td align="left">k<sub>d</sub> (mg/g/min<sup>1/2</sup>)</td><td align="left">6.10591</td><td align="left">2.685</td></tr><tr><td align="left">R<sup>2</sup></td><td align="left">0.7768</td><td align="left">0.8003</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" align="left">Elovich model</td><td align="left">&#x003b1; (mg/g/min)</td><td align="left">111.25</td><td align="left">37242.28</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x003b2; (g/mg)</td><td align="left">574.4</td><td align="left">0.003</td></tr><tr><td align="left">R<sup>2</sup></td><td align="left">0.878</td><td align="left">0.999</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="p0125">Because MB ions were traveling instantly in the direction of the nanocomposite surface, the value of q<sub>t</sub> increased steadily with t<sup>1/2</sup>. Due to the energetically heterogeneous structure, the Elovich model supports second-order kinetics. Plotting the graph between lnt and time in the Elovich model (<xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9 (d)</xref>) allows us to calculate the values of &#x003b1; and &#x003b2; using Equation. <xref rid="fd9" ref-type="disp-formula">9</xref><disp-formula id="fd9"><label>Eq 9</label><mml:math id="M9" altimg="si9.svg" alttext="Equation 9."><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:mi>ln</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where the &#x003b2; value is 0.003&#x000a0;g/mg and &#x003b1; value is 37242.281 for serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposites, and 574.4&#x000a0;g/mg, and 111.25 for serpentine respectively. The value of R<sup>2</sup> given in <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> indicated the heterogeneous nature of the serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposites with better results as compared to serpentine [<xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. In the Elovich model the &#x003b2; value is related to the desorption capacity of the nanocomposites so that by comparing the value we can check the desorption capacity of these nanocomposites.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec4"><label>4</label><title>Advantages of serpentine, and serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposites</title><p id="p0130"><xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> shows adsorption capacity of other reported adsorbent in comparison to serpentine and serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposites ranging from 800 to 1300&#x000a0;mg/g. The adsorption capacity is influenced by surface area and pore size which is 16.6&#x000a0;m<sup>2</sup>/g and 112&#x000a0;nm for serpentine and 20.6&#x000a0;m<sup>2</sup>/g and 128&#x000a0;nm for serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>. FTIR analysis confirms the&#x000a0;presence of the oxygen-containing functional groups. The large surface area, pore size, and functional group lead to greater adsorption ability. Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> when combined with the serpentine increases the magnetic property results in easy separation of adsorption from the water for further reusability. The layered structure of the serpentine with Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> presence increases the adsorption sites for the removal of the MB dye as shown in the Freundlich adsorption isotherm (Linear in <xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref>(b), and non-linear in supplementary file). These nanocomposites also favor selective adsorption because the MB is a&#x000a0;positive charge dye and the Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> has a negative charge that leads to the removal of the dye. The main advantages of the nanocomposites are reusability capability, low cost, stability (shown in the PL spectra, and FTIR spectra), and surface interaction.</p><p id="p0135">Hence, the adsorption of MB by serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>. &#x0200b; is mainly governed by surface area, functional groups (hydroxyl groups), magnetic properties, and electrostatic interactions, with the synergistic effect between serpentine and serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>. playing a key role in enhancing adsorption efficiency.</p></sec><sec id="sec5"><label>5</label><title>Conclusions</title><p id="p0140">In summary, the study demonstrated the successful synthesis of serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposites using a straightforward co-precipitation method, with serpentine sourced naturally from Skardu, Pakistan. The nanocomposites exhibited enhanced adsorption capabilities for MB dye, achieving a removal efficiency of 98&#x000a0;% under optimal conditions. This high performance is attributed to the synergistic combination of serpentine's layered structure and hydroxyl groups with the magnetic and adsorption properties of Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanoparticles. Various characterization techniques, including FTIR, UV, SEM, EDS, VSM, XRD, and surface area analysis provided the physical and chemical properties of the nanocomposite. The adsorption process followed the Freundlich isotherm model (R<sup>2</sup>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.978) that indicates multilayer adsorption on a heterogeneous surface. The kinetics of the adsorption process fit well with the pseudo-second-order model (R<sup>2</sup>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.9993) which suggest the chemisorption is the primary mechanism of dye removal. The nanocomposite's high surface area (20.8&#x000a0;m<sup>2</sup>/g) and magnetic properties (saturation magnetization of 0.534 emu/g) enabled effective dye adsorption and easy separation using an external magnetic field. The present work is novel in utilizing naturally abundant serpentine to develop cost-effective and environmentally friendly adsorbents with high adsorption capacity for wastewater treatment. However, challenges such as Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>agglomeration, which reduces surface availability over prolonged use, were identified. Future work will explore advanced synthesis methods to overcome these limitations and evaluate the performance of the composite in removing a broader range of pollutants. The findings highlight the potential of serpentine/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposites as practical, scalable solutions for industrial wastewater treatment, contributing to sustainable water management practices.</p></sec><sec id="sec6"><title>CRediT authorship contribution statement</title><p id="p0150"><bold>Amtul Basit:</bold> Conceptualization, Investigation, Methodology, Resources, Validation, Writing &#x02013; original draft. <bold>Zahida Yaqoob:</bold> Conceptualization, Data curation, Investigation, Methodology, Writing &#x02013; original draft. <bold>Aliya Zahid:</bold> Conceptualization, Investigation, Methodology, Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing. <bold>Shaista Ali:</bold> Investigation, Methodology, Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing. <bold>Beenish Shoukat:</bold> Investigation, Methodology, Software, Writing &#x02013; original draft. <bold>Abdul Khaliq:</bold> Investigation, Methodology, Resources, Software, Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing. <bold>Muhammad Tajammal Chughtai:</bold> Investigation, Methodology, Writing &#x02013; original draft, Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing. <bold>Rahila Batul:</bold> Methodology, Software, Validation, Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing. <bold>Muhammad Atiq Ur Rehman:</bold> Conceptualization, Methodology, Project administration, Resources, Supervision, Visualization, Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing. <bold>Syed Wilayat Husain:</bold> Conceptualization, Investigation, Methodology, Project administration, Supervision, Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="sec7"><title>Data availability statement</title><p id="p0155">Data will be available upon request.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="coi0010"><title>Declaration of competing interest</title><p id="p0160">The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dou</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Selective adsorption of methyl orange and methylene blue by porous carbon material prepared from potassium citrate</article-title><source>ACS Omega</source><volume>8</volume><issue>38</issue><year>2023</year><fpage>35024</fpage><lpage>35033</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acsomega.3c04124</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37779983</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seliem</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barczak</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Anastopoulos</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giannakoudakis</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A novel nanocomposite of activated serpentine mineral decorated with magnetic nanoparticles for rapid and effective adsorption of hazardous cationic dyes: kinetics and equilibrium studies</article-title><source>Nanomaterials</source><volume>10</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/nano10040684</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adsorptive removal and kinetics of methylene blue from aqueous solution using NiO/MCM-41 composite</article-title><source>Phys. E Low-Dimens. Syst. Nanostruct.</source><volume>65</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>4</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.physe.2014.08.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Monte Blanco</surname><given-names>S.P.D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Kinetic, equilibrium and thermodynamic phenomenological modeling of reactive dye adsorption onto polymeric adsorbent</article-title><source>Chem. Eng. J.</source><volume>307</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>466</fpage><lpage>475</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cej.2016.08.104</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Korus</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Loska</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Removal of Cr(III) and Cr(VI) ions from aqueous solutions by means of polyelectrolyte-enhanced ultrafiltration</article-title><source>Desalination</source><volume>247</volume><issue>1&#x02013;3</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>390</fpage><lpage>395</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.desal.2008.12.036</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Removal of Cr(VI) from aqueous solution by flocculant with the capacity of reduction and chelation</article-title><source>J. Hazard Mater.</source><volume>248&#x02013;249</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>121</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhazmat.2013.01.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yue</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Simultaneous capture of methyl orange and chromium(VI) from complex wastewater using polyethylenimine cation decorated magnetic carbon nanotubes as a recyclable adsorbent</article-title><source>RSC Adv.</source><volume>9</volume><issue>9</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>4722</fpage><lpage>4734</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/c8ra08760a</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35514632</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alshammari</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Adsorption of Cr(VI) using &#x003b1;-Fe2O3 coated hydroxy magnesium silicate (HMS): isotherm, thermodynamic and kinetic study</article-title><source>Int. J. Environ. Anal. Chem.</source><volume>00</volume><issue>00</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/03067319.2021.1890061</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zayed</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fathy</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sillanp&#x000e4;&#x000e4;</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdel Wahed</surname><given-names>M.S.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Talc-graphite schist as a natural organo-mineral complex for methylene blue remediation: kinetic and isotherm study</article-title><source>SN Appl. Sci.</source><volume>2</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s42452-020-2501-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kishimoto</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Urabe</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adsorption characteristics of clay adsorbents - sepiolite, kaolin and synthetic talc - for removal of Reactive Yellow 138:1</article-title><source>Water Environ. J.</source><volume>29</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>375</fpage><lpage>382</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/wej.12131</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ai</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nanoscale zerovalent iron decorated on graphene nanosheets for Cr(VI) removal from aqueous solution: surface corrosion retard induced the enhanced performance</article-title><source>Chem. Eng. J.</source><volume>288</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>789</fpage><lpage>797</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cej.2015.12.022</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khamis</surname><given-names>M.I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>T.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jumean</surname><given-names>F.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sara</surname><given-names>Z.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Atallah</surname><given-names>B.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cyclic sequential removal of alizarin red S Dye and Cr(VI) ions using wool as a low-cost adsorbent</article-title><source>Processes</source><volume>8</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/PR8050556</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adsorption of malachite green in aqueous solution using sugarcane bagasse-barium carbonate composite</article-title><source>Colloids Interface Sci. Commun.</source><volume>44</volume><issue>August</issue><year>2021</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100485</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.colcom.2021.100485</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>&#x0201c; Highly efficient removal of Cr(vi) ions from wastewater by the pomegranate-like magnetic hybrid nano-adsorbent of polydopamine and Fe 3 O 4 nanoparticles ,&#x0201d;</article-title><source>New J. Chem.</source><volume>44</volume><issue>29</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>12785</fpage><lpage>12792</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/d0nj01293a</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Farahat</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanad</surname><given-names>M.M.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdel-khalek</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Decoration of serpentine with iron ore as an efficient low-cost magnetic adsorbent for Cr (VI) removal from tannery wastewater</article-title><source>Powder Technol.</source><volume>388</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>51</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.powtec.2021.04.061</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nayl</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abd-Elhamid</surname><given-names>A.I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>I.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Br&#x000e4;se</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preparation and characterization of magnetite talc (Fe3O4@Talc) nanocomposite as an effective adsorbent for Cr(VI) and alizarin red S dye</article-title><source>Materials</source><volume>15</volume><issue>9</issue><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ma15093401</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kalantari</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>M.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Masoumi</surname><given-names>H.R.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shameli</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Basri</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khandanlou</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rapid adsorption of heavy metals by Fe3O4/talc nanocomposite and optimization study using response surface methodology</article-title><source>Int. J. Mol. Sci.</source><volume>15</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>12913</fpage><lpage>12927</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms150712913</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25050784</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sengupta</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kadam</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajeswari</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dhobale</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Babu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Godbole</surname><given-names>S.V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of Indian serpentine by X-ray diffraction, photoacoustic spectroscopy and electron paramagnetic resonance spectroscopy</article-title><source>Appl. Clay Sci.</source><volume>50</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>305</fpage><lpage>310</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clay.2010.08.013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rashid</surname><given-names>M.I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yaqoob</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mujtaba</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalam</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fayaz</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Qazi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Carbon capture, utilization and storage opportunities to mitigate greenhouse gases</article-title><source>Heliyon</source><volume>10</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2024</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e25419</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e25419</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mom&#x0010d;ilovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>M.Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Randelovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Purenovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x00110;or&#x00111;evi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Onjia</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Matovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Morpho-structural, adsorption and electrochemical characteristics of serpentinite</article-title><source>Sep. Purif. Technol.</source><volume>163</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>72</fpage><lpage>78</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.seppur.2016.02.042</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yenes</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blanco</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peinado</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of serpentinites to define their appropriate use as dimension stone</article-title><source>Geol. Soc. Spec. Publ.</source><volume>271</volume><issue>May</issue><year>2007</year><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1144/GSL.SP.2007.271.01.06</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref24"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shukla</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Daverey</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synthesis and characterization of magnetic nanoparticles, and their applications in wastewater treatment: a review</article-title><source>Environ. Technol. Innov.</source><volume>24</volume><year>2021</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">101924</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eti.2021.101924</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lingamdinne</surname><given-names>L.P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Biogenic reductive preparation of magnetic inverse spinel iron oxide nanoparticles for the adsorption removal of heavy metals</article-title><source>Chem. Eng. J.</source><volume>307</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>74</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cej.2016.08.067</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref26"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Fe3O4@C core-shell carbon hybrid materials as magnetically separable adsorbents for the removal of dibenzothiophene in fuels</article-title><source>ACS Omega</source><volume>4</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>1652</fpage><lpage>1661</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acsomega.8b03157</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31459421</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref27"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Figuerola</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Corato</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Manna</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pellegrino</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>From iron oxide nanoparticles towards advanced iron-based inorganic materials designed for biomedical applications</article-title><source>Pharmacol. Res.</source><volume>62</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>126</fpage><lpage>143</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phrs.2009.12.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20044004</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref28"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Press</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Synthesis of Talc/Fe3O4 Magnetic Nanocomposites Using Chemical Co-precipitation Method Synthesis of Talc/Fe 3 O 4 Magnetic Nanocomposites Using Chemical Co-precipitation Method</part-title><year>2014</year><fpage>1817</fpage><lpage>1823</lpage><comment>May 2013</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref29"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shameli</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bin Ahmad</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yunus</surname><given-names>W.Z.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Darroudi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synthesis and characterization of silver/talc nanocomposites using the wet chemical reduction method</article-title><source>Int. J. Nanomed.</source><volume>5</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>743</fpage><lpage>751</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/IJN.S13227</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramirez</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Thermal and magnetic properties of nanostructured densified ferrimagnetic composites with graphene - graphite fillers</article-title><source>Mater. Des.</source><volume>118</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>75</fpage><lpage>80</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.matdes.2017.01.018</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref31"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alizadeh</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fakhari</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Safaei</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khodeai</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Repo</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Asadi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ionic liquid-decorated Fe3O4@SiO2 nanocomposite coated on talc sheets: an efficient adsorbent for methylene blue in aqueous solution</article-title><source>Inorg. Chem. Commun.</source><volume>121</volume><issue>August</issue><year>2020</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">108204</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.inoche.2020.108204</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref32"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Novel talc encapsulated lanthanum alginate hydrogel for efficient phosphate adsorption and fixation</article-title><source>Chemosphere</source><volume>256</volume><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2020.127124</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref33"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>An</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of a floating adsorbent to remove dyes from water: a novel efficient surface separation method</article-title><source>J. Hazard Mater.</source><volume>375</volume><issue>January</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>138</fpage><lpage>148</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhazmat.2019.04.060</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31054531</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref34"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>P.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of magnetic guar gum-grafted carbon nanotubes and the adsorption of the dyes</article-title><source>Carbohydr. Polym.</source><volume>87</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>1919</fpage><lpage>1924</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.carbpol.2011.09.086</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref35"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Awual</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasan</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shahat</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>&#x0201c;Functionalized novel mesoporous adsorbent for selective lead(II) ions monitoring and removal from wastewater&#x0201d; [Sensors and Actuators, B: erratum to</article-title><source>Chemical</source><volume>203</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>854</fpage><lpage>863</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.snb.2016.09.184</pub-id><comment>S0925400514009022)(10.1016/j.snb.2014.07.063),&#x0201d; Sensors Actuators, B Chem., vol. 242, p. 777, 2017</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref36"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shahat</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Awual</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khaleque</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alam</surname><given-names>M.Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Naushad</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chowdhury</surname><given-names>A.M.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Large-pore diameter nano-adsorbent and its application for rapid lead(II) detection and removal from aqueous media</article-title><source>Chem. Eng. J.</source><volume>273</volume><issue>Ii</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>286</fpage><lpage>295</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cej.2015.03.073</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref37"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Awual</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Schiff based ligand containing nano-composite adsorbent for optical copper(II) ions removal from aqueous solutions</article-title><source>Chem. Eng. J.</source><volume>279</volume><issue>Ii</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>639</fpage><lpage>647</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cej.2015.05.049</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref38"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thi Huong</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Son</surname><given-names>N.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Phuong</surname><given-names>V.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dung</surname><given-names>C.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huong</surname><given-names>P.T.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Son</surname><given-names>L.T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synthesis Fe3O4/Talc nanocomposite by coprecipition-ultrasonication method and advances in hexavalent chromium removal from aqueous solution</article-title><source>Adsorpt. Sci. Technol.</source><volume>38</volume><issue>9&#x02013;10</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>483</fpage><lpage>501</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0263617420969112</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref39"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Geng</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Highly efficient dye adsorption and removal: a functional hybrid of reduced graphene oxide-Fe 3O 4 nanoparticles as an easily regenerative adsorbent</article-title><source>J. Mater. Chem.</source><volume>22</volume><issue>8</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>3527</fpage><lpage>3535</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/c2jm15544c</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref40"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>B.X.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficient removal of cationic dyes from aqueous solution by polymer-modified magnetic nanoparticles</article-title><source>Chem. Eng. J.</source><volume>198&#x02013;199</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cej.2012.05.074</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref41"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liosis</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Papadopoulou</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Karvelas</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Karakasidis</surname><given-names>T.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarris</surname><given-names>I.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Heavy metal adsorption using magnetic nanoparticles for water purification: a critical review</article-title><source>Materials</source><volume>14</volume><issue>24</issue><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ma14247500</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref42"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biosorbents for heavy metals removal and their future</article-title><source>Biotechnol. Adv.</source><volume>27</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>226</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biotechadv.2008.11.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19103274</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref43"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Foo</surname><given-names>K.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hameed</surname><given-names>B.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Insights into the modeling of adsorption isotherm systems</article-title><source>Chem. Eng. J.</source><volume>156</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>2</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cej.2009.09.013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref44"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pirsaheb</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohammadi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharafi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Asadi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fluoride and nitrate adsorption from water by Fe(III)-doped scoria: optimizing using response surface modeling, kinetic and equilibrium study</article-title><source>Water Sci. Technol. Water Supply</source><volume>18</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>1117</fpage><lpage>1132</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2166/ws.2017.185</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref45"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ayawei</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ebelegi</surname><given-names>A.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wankasi</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modelling and interpretation of adsorption isotherms</article-title><source>J. Chem.</source><volume>2017</volume><year>2017</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2017/3039817</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref46"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shaban</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abukhadra</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>A.A.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jibali</surname><given-names>B.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Removal of Congo red, methylene blue and Cr(VI) ions from water using natural serpentine</article-title><source>J. Taiwan Inst. Chem. Eng.</source><volume>82</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>102</fpage><lpage>116</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jtice.2017.10.023</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref47"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seliem</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Komarneni</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Equilibrium and kinetic studies for adsorption of iron from aqueous solution by synthetic Na-A zeolites: statistical modeling and optimization</article-title><source>Microporous Mesoporous Mater.</source><volume>228</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>266</fpage><lpage>274</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.micromeso.2016.04.010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref48"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dhaliwal</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effective removal of methylene blue dye using silver nanoparticles containing grafted polymer of guar gum/acrylic acid as novel adsorbent</article-title><source>J. Polym. Environ.</source><volume>29</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>88</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10924-020-01859-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref49"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dhaliwal</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synthesis of rGO/AgNPs adsorbent for the effective removal of two basic dyes: kinetics, isotherms and thermodynamic studies</article-title><source>Int. J. Environ. Sci. Technol.</source><volume>20</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2023</year><fpage>11483</fpage><lpage>11500</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13762-022-04610-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref50"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>X.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jing</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preparation and adsorption property of xylan/poly(acrylic acid) magnetic nanocomposite hydrogel adsorbent</article-title><source>Carbohydr. Polym.</source><volume>118</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>16</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.carbpol.2014.11.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25542101</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref></ref-list><ack id="ack0010"><title>Acknowledgment</title><p id="p0165">This research has been funded by <funding-source id="gs1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100023674</institution-id><institution>Scientific Research Deanship</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> at University of Ha'il - Saudi Arabia through project number <award-id award-type="grant" rid="gs1">RG-23 221</award-id>.</p></ack></back></article>