<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="case-report" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mol Genet Metab Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Mol Genet Metab Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Molecular Genetics and Metabolism Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2214-4269</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12099698</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2214-4269(25)00041-2</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ymgmr.2025.101226</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">101226</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Empagliflozin as treatment in glycogen storage disease type IB patients</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0005"><name><surname>Arbelo Rodr&#x000ed;guez</surname><given-names>Mar&#x000ed;a</given-names></name><email>marbrodc@gmail.com</email><xref rid="af0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="cr0005" ref-type="corresp">&#x0204e;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0010"><name><surname>M&#x000e1;rquez Mesa</surname><given-names>Elena</given-names></name><xref rid="af0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0015"><name><surname>Lorenzo Gonz&#x000e1;lez</surname><given-names>Cristina</given-names></name><xref rid="af0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0020"><name><surname>Guti&#x000e9;rrez Vilar</surname><given-names>Marina</given-names></name><xref rid="af0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0025"><name><surname>Arhip</surname><given-names>Loredana</given-names></name><xref rid="af0015" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0030"><name><surname>Ruiz Pons</surname><given-names>M&#x000f3;nica</given-names></name><xref rid="af0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0035"><name><surname>Su&#x000e1;rez Llanos</surname><given-names>Jos&#x000e9; Pablo</given-names></name><xref rid="af0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><aff id="af0005"><label>a</label>Endocrinology and Nutrition Department, Hospital Universitario Nuestra Se&#x000f1;ora de Candelaria, Ctra. Del Rosario 145, Santa Cruz de Tenerife 38010, Spain</aff><aff id="af0010"><label>b</label>Pediatrics Department Hospital Universitario Nuestra Se&#x000f1;ora de Candelaria, Ctra. Del Rosario 145, Santa Cruz de Tenerife 38010, Spain</aff><aff id="af0015"><label>c</label>Nutricia-Danone, C/De Buenos Aires, 21, L'Eixample, Barcelona 08029, Spain</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cr0005"><label>&#x0204e;</label>Corresponding author. <email>marbrodc@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>03</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>6</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>03</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>43</volume><elocation-id>101226</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>31</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>26</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2025 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="ab0005"><sec><title>Background</title><p>Glycogen Storage Disease Ib (GSD Ib) is a disease that associates both neutropenia and neutrophil dysfunction, thereby causing recurrent infections and inflammatory bowel disease (IBD). As of now, the standard treatment of these complications has been the administration of granulocyte-stimulating factor (GCSF). However, recent studies have found that the use of empagliflozin, an antidiabetic drug, may have benefits by reducing the levels of 1,5 anhydroglucitol-6-phosphate (1,5-AG6P), a metabolite that accumulates in the cytosol of neutrophils and blocks the use of glucose.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>We therefore report our experience with three patients, one of them being a liver and kidney transplant recipient, with promising results. Morbidity has been greatly reduced in all cases consisting in weight gain, better neutrophil count and management of respiratory, osteoarticular and gastrointestinal comorbidities. Overall, an improvement in quality of life has been observed.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>SGLT2 inhibitors, and specifically empagliflozin offer promising results in improving morbidity and quality of life in patients with GSD Ib. In the cases presented, including a patient with double liver-kidney transplant, a good profile of tolerance, safety and effectiveness has been observed.</p></sec><sec><title>Synopsis</title><p>Empagliflozin offers promising results in improving morbidity and quality of life in patients with GSD Ib, including the first double organ transplant patient treated with this drug.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group id="ks0005"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Glycogen storage disease type Ib</kwd><kwd>Empagliflozin</kwd><kwd>Neutropenia</kwd><kwd>Neutrophil dysfunction</kwd><kwd>SGLT2 inhibitors</kwd><kwd><underline>1,5-andhydroglucitol</underline></kwd><kwd>Glucose-6-phosphate transporter</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta><def-list><title>Abbreviations</title><def-item><term id="kw0045">SGLT2</term><def><p>Sodium-glucose co-transporter 2 inhibitors</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="kw0055">GSD Ib</term><def><p>Glycogen storage disease type Ib</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="kw0065">G6PT</term><def><p>glucose-6-phosphate transporter</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="kw0075">1,5-AG6P:</term><def><p>1,5-Anhydroglucitol-6-phosphate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="kw0085">1,5-AG</term><def><p>1,5-Anhydroglucitol</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="kw0095">GCSF</term><def><p>Granulocyte colony-stimulating factor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="kw0105">IBD</term><def><p>Inflammatory bowel disease</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="kw0115">ANC</term><def><p>Absolute neutrophil count</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="kw0125">Hb</term><def><p>Hemoglobin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="kw0135">TG</term><def><p>Triglycerides</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="kw0145">HUNSC</term><def><p>Nuestra Se&#x000f1;ora de la Candelaria University Hospital.</p></def></def-item></def-list></front><body><sec id="s0005"><label>1</label><title>Background</title><p id="p0010">Glycogen storage disease type Ib (GSD Ib) (Orphacode 79,259) is a rare autosomal recessive disease, with an estimated prevalence of 1: 500,000, due to mutations in SLC37A4 encoding the glucose-6-phosphate transporter (G6PT) of the endoplasmic reticulum. A defect in this enzymatic complex affects glucose formation because both glycogenolysis and gluconeogenesis are inhibited, with negative effects on glycemic control [<xref rid="bb0005" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bb0010" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Liver failure and the development of hepatocellular carcinoma make these patients potential candidates for liver transplantation. Moreover, if there is not good metabolic control, kidney damage occurs (glomerular dysfunction) that can progress to kidney failure and require a transplant. Neutropenia is the hallmark feature of GSD Ib, however, the age at onset as well as the clinical course are variable. <underline>It may be present at birth or not appear until late in childhood as cyclic or permanent neutropenia. Polymorphonuclear neutrophils (PMNs) from patients with GSD Ib are not only reduced in number, but also dysfunctional and this makes individuals prone to recurring infections</underline> [<xref rid="bb0015" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]<underline>.</underline> Accumulation of 1,5- anhydroglucitol-6-phosphate (1,5-AG6P) within the granulocytes result in their energy deficiency and consequent apoptosis [<xref rid="bb0020" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Plasma 1,5-anhydroglucitol (1,5-AG) is an analog of glucose, and enters cells where it is phosphorylated to 1,5-AG6P.</p><p id="p0015">Sodium glucose co-transporter 2 inhibitors (SGLT2-I) such as empagliflozin are anti-diabetic drugs that inhibit renal glucose reabsorption resulting in an increased urinary excretion of glucose. <underline>This process results in the decrease of renal 1,5-AG reabsorption and, thereby, lowering its serum concentration</underline>. It has been proved that, in a G6PC3 (glucose-6-phosphatase catalytic subunit 3) deficient mouse model, that phenotypically and biochemically mimics the PMN impairment of patients with GSD Ib, treatment with an SGLT2- I was able to lower the blood level of 1,5-AG6P and consequently restore a normal neutrophil count [<xref rid="bb0020" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Recently, the same result was replicated in two G6PC3- deficient children [<xref rid="bb0025" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].</p><p id="p0020"><underline>For this reason, there is an increasing interest in investigating how the application of SGLT2-I in clinical practice is evolving</underline>. We report our experience in managing 3 GSD Ib patients with empagliflozin and discuss the possible benefits and difficulties that it brings in the treatment of this pathology.</p></sec><sec id="s0010"><label>2</label><title>Methods</title><p id="p0025">
<underline>A case series that include all patients with empagliflozin being initiated as treatment for GDS Ib and follow-up by the Endocrinology Service of the Nuestra Se&#x000f1;ora de la Candelaria University Hospital (HUSNC), Santa Cruz de Tenerife, Spain.</underline>
</p><p id="p0030">The information has been collected from the clinical records. The collected data was: epidemiological (age, sex, weight and height), clinical (cardiovascular risk factors, presence of GSD Ib and associated comorbidities), blood work (hemoglobin, neutrophil and calprotectin count), in-hospital (number of admissions and their main cause) and follow-up.</p><p id="p0035">Data collection was compliant with the Law on Protection of Personal Data and Guarantee of Digital Rights (Spanish Organic Law 3/2018). All patients received information about off-label use of the treatment. <underline>All three patients signed the informed consent.</underline></p></sec><sec id="s0015"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><sec id="s0020"><label>3.1</label><title>Case report 1</title><p id="p0040">A 19-year-old woman, diagnosed of GSD Ib (1211delCT) in 2004, when she was one month old, after suffering from severe hypoglycemia, hypotonia and hepatomegaly. Dietary treatment was started. After 3&#x000a0;months, she was discharged with a percutaneous endoscopic gastrostomy to ensure the provision of carbohydrates. <underline>During the following years, she was hospitalized several times because of nearby skin infection showing concurrent neutropenia in laboratory tests</underline>. This motivated the closure of the gastrostomy at 2-years-old, introducing a nasoduodenal tube as the preferred method of feeding. However, the neutrophil dysfunction persists even after ambulatory treatment initiation with granulocyte colony-stimulating factor (GCSF), causing once again the hospitalization of the patient every 2&#x02013;3&#x000a0;months because of new and varied infectious processes.</p><p id="p0045"><underline>When she was 9-years-old, after numerous hospital admissions with gastroenteritis as the main diagnosis, a colonoscopy was performed. The patient received the diagnosis of inflammatory bowel disease (IBD) after the medical procedure showed multiple ulcers from terminal ileum till left colon, starting treatment</underline>. The nasoduodenal tube was then also removed after careful total oral tolerance was observed. <underline>No further hospitalizations occurred until a septic shock with respiratory origin occurs 4&#x000a0;years later, requiring an intensive care unit admission with catecholamine treatment and mechanical ventilation to maintain hemodynamic stabilization</underline>. <underline>After the discharge, she continued with assisted ventilation at home in the form of nocturnal continuous positive airway pressure.</underline></p><p id="p0050"><underline>After 3&#x000a0;years with no improvement in neutrophil (absolute neutrophil count (ANC)</underline>&#x000a0;&#x02264;&#x000a0;<underline>0.2&#x02013;0.5&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10</underline><sup><underline>9</underline></sup><underline>/L), empagliflozin is initiated in October of 2020, the patient being 16&#x000a0;years old, weighting 45.5&#x000a0;kg with height being 146.2&#x000a0;cm, resulting in a body mass index (BMI) of 21.29&#x000a0;kg/m</underline><sup><underline>2</underline></sup>. <underline>She was also treated with long-acting starch 60&#x000a0;g thrice a day complimentary with scheduled dietary advice, enalapril, mesalazine, gabapentine and GCSF 300&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/day every three weeks</underline>. <underline>The starting dose of empagliflozin was 10&#x000a0;mg every 24&#x000a0;h for 3&#x000a0;days, and then, it was increased to 10&#x000a0;mg every 12&#x000a0;h indefinitely. The ANC at the start was 0.14&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10</underline><sup><underline>9</underline></sup><underline>/L, hemoglobin (Hb) 10.5&#x000a0;g/dL, uric acid 6.59&#x000a0;mg/dL and triglycerides (TG) 226&#x000a0;mg/dL.</underline></p><p id="p0055">One month after the start of the treatment, the digestive symptoms disappeared completely, concomitant with a weight gain of 2&#x000a0;kg in a single month and up to 7&#x000a0;kg in total. GCSF was discontinued after 2&#x000a0;years of treatment with the last ANC being of 1.24&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>9</sup>/L. Last follow-up with our team was in November 2023 when she presented a weight of 50.3&#x000a0;kg and ANC of 1.32&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>9</sup>/L, Hb 14.5&#x000a0;g/dL, uric acid 3.0&#x000a0;mg/dL and TG 256&#x000a0;mg/dL. <underline>No new hospital admissions occurred. The nocturnal CPAP was discontinued since February 2023. Lastly, while no endoscopic study has been performed, fecal calprotectin results have stayed positive (&#x0003e;60&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/g) and varying within a wide range with no apparent clinical repercussion</underline>. No side effects have been reported after 3&#x000a0;years of empagliflozin. <underline>The patient perceived an overall upgrade in her quality of life following no more hospitalization episodes and especially after being able to stop non-invasive ventilation support.</underline></p></sec><sec id="s0025"><label>3.2</label><title>Case report 2</title><p id="p0060"><underline>A 34-year-old woman had severe hypoglycemia, hyperuricemia and hypertriglyceridemia a week after her birth. Imaging tests showed hepatomegaly</underline>. She was diagnosed at one month old, with liver biopsy results compatible with GSD Ib (1211delCT).</p><p id="p0065"><underline>When she was 26-years-old, after an episode of hypoglycemia during a Rheumatology hospitalization at HUNSC, she began her follow-up in our Endocrinology department</underline>. <underline>With a history of large joint oligo arthritic crisis resistant to previous analgesic and anti-inflammatory treatment, results were compatible with Sj&#x000f6;gren disease and axonal polyneuropathy. She was also suspected of having either IBD or bacterial overgrowth following numerous episodes of diarrhea during the past year</underline>. <underline>With normal gastro- and colonoscopy, both antibiotic and 5-aminosalicylic acid (ASA-5) were initiated.</underline></p><p id="p0070"><underline>She has periodically been evaluated by with both the department of Hematology, who administered GCSF 300&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/d every 48&#x000a0;h; and the department of Gastroenterology, who closely followed a stable hepatic adenoma, maximum diameter of 2,5&#x000a0;cm</underline>. No clear diagnosis of IBD was shown.</p><p id="p0075"><underline>Treatment with empagliflozin was started in July 2021, when she was 31-years-old, with an initial dose of 10&#x000a0;mg every 24&#x000a0;h for 7&#x000a0;days and then 10&#x000a0;mg every 12&#x000a0;h</underline>. <underline>Her pre-treatment anthropometrics were: weight of 74&#x000a0;kg, height 152&#x000a0;cm and BMI of 32&#x000a0;kg/m</underline><sup><underline>2</underline></sup>. <underline>Laboratory studies demonstrated ANC of 0.2&#x000a0;<underline>&#x000d7;</underline>&#x000a0;10</underline><sup><underline>9</underline></sup><underline>/L, Hb 13.5&#x000a0;g/dL, uric acid 7.1&#x000a0;mg/dL and TG 108&#x000a0;mg/dL</underline>. <underline>She was given dietary advice and was educated about treatment with long-acting starch 60&#x000a0;g four times per day.</underline> In January 2024, the weight remained stable as well as the hemoglobin total count (14.2&#x000a0;g/dL now). Last ANC was of 7.16&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>9</sup>/L, with the administration of GCSF 300&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/d every 72&#x000a0;h. <underline>We proposed its suspension in the last consultative encounter</underline>. Uric acid decreased (3.5&#x000a0;mg/dL) and TG remained stable (165&#x000a0;mg/dL). In addition, she reported a decrease in axonal polyneuropathy symptoms, this being less walking instability.</p><p id="p0080">No new hospital admissions nor infectious processes have been observed since the start of the treatment. No side effects were reported. The improvement of peripheral neuropathy has been noted by the patient as the most favorable change after initiating the treatment.</p></sec><sec id="s0030"><label>3.3</label><title>Case report 3</title><p id="p0085"><underline>A 40-year-old male was diagnosed with GSD Ib shortly after his birth in 1983</underline>. He received a liver transplant when he was 7-years-old due to recurrent symptomatic hypoglycemia. He underwent several immunosuppression treatment modifications in the following years after showing various side effects (gingival hyperplasia with cyclosporine, severe neutropenia with hemolytic anemia with tacrolimus). <underline>However, the immunosuppressant therapy resulted in chronic kidney disease with kidney biopsy compatible with focal and segmental glomerulosclerosis, requiring a kidney transplant at the age of 28-years-old.</underline></p><p id="p0090">
<underline>The patient was admitted to the intensive care unit, when he was 30-years-old, with diagnosis of community acquired pneumonia (pneumococcus).</underline>
</p><p id="p0095"><underline>In 2016, with 32-years-old, a lymphoproliferative syndrome associated with post-liver transplant herpes virus-4 infection prompts a right hemicolectomy</underline>. Three small bowel obstructions occurred as a result of surgical adhesions, two of which required additional surgical procedures during the same year and 2&#x000a0;years later.</p><p id="p0100"><underline>The ANC did not improve over time, even after treatment with GCSF</underline>. <underline>Recurrent pneumonia was the leading cause of hospitalizations in the year 2016 and 2019</underline>. <underline>In 2018 the patient started having frequent stools, weight loss and consequent hypoalbuminemia.</underline> Colonoscopy results were compatible with IBD-like syndrome. It was also in this year that another intensive care unit admission was necessary after a septic shock of urinary tract origin.</p><p id="p0105">
<underline>At the end of 2021, another hospital admission occurred, with severe neutropenia being the cause of a resistant urinary tract infections.</underline>
</p><p id="p0110">Treatment with empagliflozin (10&#x000a0;mg every 24&#x000a0;h) was initiated in January 2022. <underline>The pretreatment ANC was 0.4&#x000a0;<underline>&#x000d7;</underline>&#x000a0;10</underline><sup><underline>9</underline></sup><underline>/L despite GCSF 300&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/day every 72&#x000a0;<underline>h</underline></underline>. <underline>His weight at the time was 45.6&#x000a0;kg, height 160&#x000a0;cm and BMI of 17.06&#x000a0;kg/m</underline><sup><underline>2</underline></sup>. <underline>Additionally, the concurrent immunosuppressive treatment consisted in low dose cyclosporine and prednisone</underline>. <underline>He presented with Hb 13&#x000a0;g/dL, uric acid 8,72&#x000a0;mg/dL and TG 54&#x000a0;mg/dL.</underline></p><p id="p0115"><underline>Three months after the start of empagliflozin, the digestive symptoms disappeared completely, which coincided with a weight gain of 3&#x000a0;kg</underline>. <underline>GCSF was discontinued in December of 2022, with ANC of 2.88&#x000a0;<underline>&#x000d7;</underline>&#x000a0;10</underline><sup><underline>9</underline></sup><underline>/L</underline>. <underline>It should be noted that the total empagliflozin dose was increased in the following month to 10&#x000a0;mg every 12&#x000a0;<underline>h</underline>, however, poor therapeutic adherence was noted. Constipation for the past 3&#x000a0;weeks after the start of empagliflozin was reported as the cause for poor compliance, with complete resolution after a reduction dose of 10&#x000a0;mg every 24&#x000a0;<underline>h</underline></underline>. <underline>In the March 2023 visit, laboratory values included ANC 4.33&#x000a0;<underline>&#x000d7;</underline>&#x000a0;10</underline><sup><underline>9</underline></sup><underline>/L, Hb 14.5&#x000a0;g/dL, uric acid 5.24&#x000a0;mg/dL and TG 56&#x000a0;mg/dL</underline>. <underline>Additionally, the patient has been evaluated twice in the emergency room, in August and September 2023. In August, he was diagnosed with an upper respiratory tract infection. After careful evaluation, he was discharged and started a short course of antibiotic monotherapy, which led to a complete resolution of the symptoms</underline>. <underline>In September, the patient reported dysuria for the past few days. He was discharged after normal results in both blood and urine samples</underline>. <underline>No other side effects were reported. As of 2024, up to 6&#x000a0;kg have been gained, and he has not required new admissions</underline>. <underline>Taking all of this into account, alongside the aforementioned cease of gastrointestinal symptoms, the patient experienced a significant improvement in his quality of life: a less hospital-dependent lifestyle appeared possible, the resumption of frequently social interactions and being able to start exercising.</underline></p></sec></sec><sec id="s0035"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0120">SGLT2-I are glucosuric drugs implemented as one of the fundamental pillars of treatment for Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus. Not only have they demonstrated benefit in this field, but their use has also been expanded in the treatment of symptomatic chronic heart failure and in chronic kidney disease [<xref rid="bb0030" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="bb0035" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>].</p><p id="p0125"><underline>The previously presented cases outlined empagliflozin as a promising treatment for neutropenia in patients with GSD Ib. In our cases, an initial dose of 10&#x000a0;mg of empagliflozin was chosen, with subsequent progression to a dose of 10&#x000a0;mg every 12&#x000a0;<underline>h</underline></underline>. If we compare it with the weight of each of them, we obtain weight-adjusted doses of approximately 0.4&#x000a0;mg/kg, 0.3&#x000a0;mg/kg and 0.4&#x000a0;mg/kg respectively. This is in line with previous studies conducted with empagliflozin that used height-weight-adjusted doses between 0.3 and 0.7&#x000a0;mg/kg/day [<xref rid="bb0040" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. <underline>Dose increase was carried out in three days in the case of our first patient, one week in the second patient and one month in the third patient (a slower dose increase was performed due to patient characteristics and comorbidities).</underline> No differences were observed in the tolerance of the treatment. <underline>Likewise, other authors have evaluated dose escalation at different speeds without reporting differences on its tolerance, from 2&#x000a0;days</underline> [<xref rid="bb0045" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]<underline>, 7&#x000a0;days</underline> [<xref rid="bb0050" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="bb0055" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]<underline>, 10&#x000a0;days</underline> [<xref rid="bb0060" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]<underline>, up to several weeks</underline> [<xref rid="bb0065" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="bb0070" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. On the other hand, the administration of this drug has been carried out twice daily, every 12&#x000a0;h, at half the total dose. This is due to the inconsistency in the intensity of glycosuria in a 24-h period, therefore, reducing the risk of hypoglycemia that we would obtain with high doses [<xref rid="bb0065" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. However, it should be noted that although this has been the method of choice we have elected, other authors have chosen to administer a single dose [<xref rid="bb0045" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Similar results have been described in both treatment regimens [<xref rid="bb0075" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. These findings, at first contradictory, may be due to the almost equal total dose used adjusted for weight.</p><p id="p0130">In terms of effectiveness, improvement in ANC has been achieved in all our patients. After the initiation of treatment, the clinical and analytical improvement is clear and consistent with current evidence [<xref rid="bb0040" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, <xref rid="bb0045" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, <xref rid="bb0050" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, <xref rid="bb0055" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, <xref rid="bb0060" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, <xref rid="bb0065" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, <xref rid="bb0070" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, <xref rid="bb0075" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>]. Furthermore, all three patients have shown an increase in ANC even after 12&#x000a0;months, as illustrated in <xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>. While not widely recognized, there have been some reports confirming the stabilization and enhancement of neutrophil function over extended periods of time [<xref rid="bb0045" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="bb0080" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. (See <xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.)<fig id="f0005"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Evolution of ANC after treatment with empagliflozin.</p><p><bold>*</bold> GCSF was discontinued.</p><p><bold>**</bold> GCSF was proposed for suspension.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0005">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1" id="lk0005"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="t0005"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Empagliflozin effects in GSD Ib patients.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0010">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Gender</th><th>Age</th><th>Empagliflozin final dosis</th><th>Treatment duration</th><th>Neutrophil count</th><th>IBD</th><th>Hypoglycemic events</th><th>Uric acid</th><th>TG</th><th>Other treatments</th><th>Notes</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>&#x02640;</td><td>19 y</td><td>0.4&#x000a0;mg/kg/d</td><td>3 y</td><td>&#x02191;<break/> Stop G-CSF</td><td>&#x02193;</td><td>None</td><td>&#x02193;</td><td>&#x02194;</td><td>enalapril<break/>mesalazine<break/>gabapentine</td><td>Mechanic ventilation (stop)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02640;</td><td>33 y</td><td>0.3&#x000a0;mg/kg/d</td><td>2.5 y</td><td>&#x02191;<break/> &#x02193; G-CSF</td><td>N/A</td><td>None</td><td>&#x02193;</td><td>&#x02194;</td><td>enalapril<break/>febuxostat rituximab</td><td>Sj&#x000f6;gren disease<break/>Axonal polyneuropathy &#x02193;<break/>Hepatic adenoma &#x02194;</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02642;</td><td>40 y</td><td>0.4/mg/kg/d</td><td>2 y</td><td>&#x02191;<break/> Stop G-CSF</td><td>&#x02193;</td><td>None</td><td>&#x02193;</td><td>&#x02194;</td><td>enalapril<break/>febuxostat<break/>cyclosporine<break/>prednisone</td><td>Liver transplant<break/>Kidney transplant</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>TG, triglycerides; IBD, inflammatory bowel disease; y, years; &#x02191;, increase; &#x02193;, decrease; &#x02194;, stable; N/A, not applicable.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="p0135">We do not have the necessary means in our center to evaluate white cell quality. Recent studies suggest that this clinical improvement in neutropenia does not have to correlate with a clear increase in the absolute neutrophil count, highlighting the relationship between symptomatic improvement and the decrease in 1,5AG6P in neutrophils [<xref rid="bb0040" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, <xref rid="bb0045" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, <xref rid="bb0050" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, <xref rid="bb0055" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, <xref rid="bb0060" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>]. An inverse correlation has been noted between 1,5AG concentration and the neutrophil count, chemotactic response, phagocytosis and NETosis [<xref rid="bb0085" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. The reduction in infections in these patients is not solely due to an increase in neutrophil count they also enhance their functional capacity, which is crucial for an effective immune response. This functional improvement is key to the reduction in infections, as evidenced by the results in our patients, who showed a lower frequency of infections following treatment. Moreover, <underline>a direct consequence of increased numbers and probably increased functionality of neutrophils is reflected in the decreased GCSF needs in our patients</underline>. In 2 out of 3 patients it has been completely removed, with good response. At the same time, withdrawal of treatment has been considered in the remaining patient. <underline>It is observed that there is a tendency towards complete discontinuation of GCSF in the literature</underline> [<xref rid="bb0050" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, <xref rid="bb0055" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, <xref rid="bb0060" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, <xref rid="bb0065" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, <xref rid="bb0070" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, <xref rid="bb0075" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>,<xref rid="bb0090" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Poor response to its withdrawal has been reported only once, in the end maintaining treatment with GCSF at doses significantly lower than those required prior to starting empagliflozin [<xref rid="bb0065" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Regarding Hb levels, we have observed a significant improvement in the first patient, slight improvement in the third patient and remaining stable in second one. In previous studies, a trend towards resolution of anemia has been observed [<xref rid="bb0065" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].</p><p id="p0140">There is a fair amount of data on IBD improvement in GSD Ib patients treated with empagliflozin. A cohort of 66 GSD Ib individuals with IBD prior to drug exposure was analyzed. Out of a total population of 110 individuals, 40&#x000a0;% did not present clinical findings of IBD before the drug treatment, while 78&#x000a0;% showed no IBD findings during the drug exposure [<xref rid="bb0075" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. In a small pediatric sample, clinical effectiveness rate of 83.3&#x000a0;% has been reported [<xref rid="bb0095" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>].</p><p id="p0145">In our sample, both patient number 1 and patient number 3 showed rapid improvement of gastrointestinal symptoms as well as weight gain after empagliflozin initiation. On the other hand, patient number 2 had good clinical control prior to the start of the treatment. However, all this information regarding the improvement of the disease is limited to the clinical aspect. No follow-up with imaging tests or scales have been performed in these patients. The current evidence, although limited, indicates how interesting it would be to evaluate the evolution of IBD with biopsy or colonoscopy [<xref rid="bb0055" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Despite this, the improvement in the quality of life of these patients is evident [<xref rid="bb0060" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="bb0065" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="bb0090" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].</p><p id="p0150">In the context of metabolic alterations of GSD Ib, patients can manifest hyperuricemia and hypertriglyceridemia. Although only a few authors reported pre-post SGLT2-I values of uric acid and some cases were concurrently on allopurinol to prevent renal damage [<xref rid="bb0065" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], empagliflozin seems to have ameliorative effects on hyperuricemia in some GSD Ib patients [<xref rid="bb0055" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, <xref rid="bb0060" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, <xref rid="bb0065" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>]. In our cases, all patients had a reduction in uric acid levels. <underline>This might be reflective of improved metabolic control but it is not clear if it could be directly related to the levels of 1,5-AG</underline> [<xref rid="bb0100" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. <underline>TG values were reported to have a variable trend during therapy</underline> [<xref rid="bb0065" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="bb0095" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]<underline>, in our patients the values remained stable.</underline></p><p id="p0155">An intriguing finding in our cohort was the reported improvement of axonal polyneuropathy symptoms in the second patient, which was described as greater stability when walking. Although the mechanisms remain speculative, this observation aligns with evidence demonstrating the neuroprotective effects of empagliflozin in diabetic rat models [2, [<xref rid="bb0105" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. These studies suggest that empagliflozin may improve nerve conduction and morphology through AMPK pathway activation, reduction of oxidative stress, modulation of inflammatory cytokines and enhancement of autophagy via mTOR inhibition. Furthermore, clinical data in humans have shown that, after three months of treatment, patients receiving empagliflozin exhibited significant improvements in electrophysiological studies and a reduction in biomarkers of oxidative stress and neuronal damage (NSE and MDA), despite no significant changes in glycemic control or cardiovascular risk scores [<xref rid="bb0110" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Given that the patient's neuropathy may have had an immune-mediated component, possibly related to Sj&#x000f6;gren's syndrome, it is conceivable that empagliflozin's anti-inflammatory and immunomodulatory effects contributed to the improvement observed.</p><p id="p0160">Liver transplantation in GSD Ib has been indicated for severe glucose intolerance, poor metabolic control and poor growth [<xref rid="bb0115" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], however, reports are scarce. We have not found any published evidence regarding GSD Ib and kidney transplant. In this context, it is important to consider evidence of treatment with empagliflozin in GSD Ib organ transplant recipients is limited. A recent international consensus recommends continuing empagliflozin after liver transplantation, even if the exact moment of restarting it needs to be individualized [<xref rid="bb0120" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. On the other hand, two GSD Ib patients who received liver transplantation and treatment with SGLT2-I have been reported [<xref rid="bb0125" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. One of them started empagliflozin after the first transplantation, while the other one started it before the procedure. No side effects were observed, while increase of PMN count and decrease of 1,5-AG levels were detected. At the same time, the administration of empagliflozin or any other SGLT2-I in kidney and liver transplant recipients is very limited.</p><p id="p0165">An increasing number of articles in recent years present promising results through the use of empagliflozin in kidney transplant recipients with diabetes mellitus, pre- and post-transplant [<xref rid="bb0130" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, <xref rid="bb0135" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, <xref rid="bb0140" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>, <xref rid="bb0145" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>]. The EMPA-Renal Tx 2019 found that SGLT2 inhibitors likely have no effect on kidney graft survival and does not increase hypoglycemia. However, eGFR transiently decreased at 8&#x000a0;weeks, and urinary tract infections were a concern [<xref rid="bb0135" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Nevertheless, other studies [<xref rid="bb0130" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="bb0145" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>, <xref rid="bb0150" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>] did not increase urinary tract infections and did not harm kidney function [<xref rid="bb0130" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="bb0150" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>].</p><p id="p0170">The main results seem similar to those of our patient. Kidney function remains stable, sometimes even improving after the initiation of treatment, or with slight initial deterioration. On the other hand, in regard of the safety of starting glucosuric treatment with a known relative frequent adverse effect of urinary tract infection on immunosuppressed patients (including pyelonephritis and urosepsis); in our case, this side effect has not been observed to date. Although the risk exists [<xref rid="bb0140" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>], the increased severity of the infection in this group of patients and its causal relationship with the drug is controversial. The long-term immunosuppression required after transplantation predisposes patients to opportunistic infections. Neutrophil function gain could avoid the increase of infectious processes in these patients. While there is no direct evidence to date, it is noteworthy to consider whether the potential role of empagliflozin in neutrophil function could potentially contribute to better post-transplant outcomes. Notably, no transplant rejection was observed in our case.</p><p id="p0175">In terms of metabolic control, no increase in hypoglycemic episodes was observed in any of the 3 patients. As has been established, the primary metabolic abnormality of GSD Ib is fasting hypoglycemia [<xref rid="bb0155" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. A recent retrospective cohort study of patients with GSD Ib, including both pediatric and adult population, reports fasting hypoglycemia in all 113 patients [<xref rid="bb0160" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. In this regard, in a cohort of 14 patients with GSD I (2 GSD Ib) CGM revealed periods of low blood glucose below 72&#x000a0;mg/dl in all patients [<xref rid="bb0165" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>].</p><p id="p0180">Large sample sizes effectively highlight an increase in hypoglycemia episodes after empagliflozin initiation. Level three hypoglycemia (&#x0003c; 54&#x000a0;mg/dl) was the most common adverse effect reported (18&#x000a0;% of all patients) [<xref rid="bb0075" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Along these lines, 50&#x000a0;% of Halligan et al. cohort of 8 GSD Ib patients showed hypoglycemic episodes [<xref rid="bb0065" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. However, they have not been able to determine whether they are a consequence of the drug, the underlying disease [<xref rid="bb0075" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] or a carbohydrate deficit in the diet [<xref rid="bb0065" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].</p><p id="p0185">The third patient presented has undergone both renal and hepatic transplants. Interactions may exist between commonly used immunosuppressants and SGLT2 inhibitors, however, the view is that potential interactions are overall modest and unlikely to result in hypoglycemia or compromise immunosuppression [<xref rid="bb0170" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. For example, treatment with canagliflozin has been documented as safe with no significant change in episodes of hypoglycemia [<xref rid="bb0175" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. One study emphasizes subjective improvement in severity of hypoglycemic events due to decrease in blood glucose lability [<xref rid="bb0180" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>].</p><p id="p0190">Other side effects have not been observed in direct relation to the initiation of empagliflozin. <underline>One of our patients reported constipation, consistent with findings reported in other studies</underline> [<xref rid="bb0065" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. <underline>However, poor therapeutic adherence at this moment prevents us from correlating the symptoms described with the drug</underline>. Other studies also do not report adverse effects with empagliflozin [<xref rid="bb0090" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], or minor side effects with resolution after dose reduction [<xref rid="bb0060" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].</p><p id="p0195">Furthermore, it has recently been published that treatment with empagliflozin in patients with GSD Ib is associated with a significant reduction in costs for the healthcare system [<xref rid="bb0185" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>].</p><p id="p0200">This case series has several limitations. Firstly, our results were obtained with a treatment used with an off-label indication and from a single hospital, with a very limited sample of a very rare disease. Secondly, the follow-up of our patients is limited. Patients are referred to our consultation as adults and, at the same time, as a particularity of our health area one of our patients has a medical history in different hospitals. Currently we do not have a quick and direct platform that allows sharing medical reports between the area. Thirdly, the approach to the disease is multidisciplinary. It would be interesting to evaluate in future studies the findings jointly with other departments involved in the management of the disease, with the relevant tests required. <underline>Fourthly, currently we are not able to determine 1,5-AG concentration in blood due to technological limitations</underline>. Finally, even though the three cases during consultation described satisfaction with the SGLT2-I treatment, referred as both the reduction of limiting symptomatology and either reduce or removal of other, more invasive, treatments; no quality of life specific questionnaires or scales were implemented.</p><p id="p0205">Expanded studies with larger samples, more years of follow-up and in multiple hospital settings are required to confirm the results observed in our case series.</p><p id="p0210">
<underline>The strength of our work was that we included a kidney and liver transplant patient who demonstrated a good clinical response with improvement in ANC, resolution of digestive symptoms and infectious complications without adverse side effects.</underline>
</p></sec><sec id="s0040"><label>5</label><title>Conclusion</title><p id="p0215"><underline>Empagliflozin offers promising results in improving morbidity and quality of life in patients with GSD Ib</underline>. In the 3 cases presented, a good profile of tolerance, safety and effectiveness of empagliflozin has been observed. However, expanded studies with larger samples, more years of follow-up and in multiple hospital settings are required to confirm the results observed in our case series. Additionally, it is essential to recognize the need for more standardized reporting. as current evidence is largely limited to individual case reports. An international registry for patients receiving SGLT2 inhibitors could help generate more cohesive data and support multicenter trials with defined efficacy endpoints. This would be especially valuable given the off-label use of these agents, providing robust data to inform potential future approvals.&#x0201d;</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s0050"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p id="p0225">Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="s0065"><title>CRediT authorship contribution statement</title><p id="p0240"><bold>Mar&#x000ed;a Arbelo Rodr&#x000ed;guez:</bold> Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing, Writing &#x02013; original draft, Visualization, Validation, Resources, Methodology, Investigation, Conceptualization. <bold>Elena M&#x000e1;rquez Mesa:</bold> Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing, Writing &#x02013; original draft, Validation, Resources, Project administration, Methodology, Investigation, Conceptualization. <bold>Cristina Lorenzo Gonz&#x000e1;lez:</bold> Writing &#x02013; original draft, Visualization. <bold>Marina Guti&#x000e9;rrez Vilar:</bold> Writing &#x02013; original draft. <bold>Loredana Arhip:</bold> Writing &#x02013; original draft, Visualization. <bold>M&#x000f3;nica Ruiz Pons:</bold> Validation, Supervision, Resources, Project administration, Methodology, Investigation, Conceptualization. <bold>Jos&#x000e9; Pablo Su&#x000e1;rez Llanos:</bold> Supervision, Project administration.</p></sec><sec id="s0060"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="p0235">All patients provided written consent for publication.</p></sec><sec id="s0055"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="p0230">Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="s0045"><title>Funding</title><p id="p0220">This research received no external funding.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="coi0005"><title>Declaration of competing interest</title><p id="p0245">The authors declare they have no competing interests.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="bi0005"><title>References</title><ref id="bb0005"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0005"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thyagu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maze</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schreiber</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sirrs</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stockler-Ipsiroglu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prolonged granulocyte colony stimulating factor use in glycogen storage disease type 1b associated with acute myeloid leukemia and with shortened telomere length</article-title><source>Pediatr. Hematol. Oncol.</source><volume>35</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/08880018.2018.1440675</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29652549</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0010"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0010"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maiorana</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tagliaferri</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dionisi-Vici</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Current understanding on pathogenesis and effective treatment of glycogen storage disease type Ib with empagliflozin: new insights coming from diabetes for its potential implications in other metabolic disorders</article-title><source>Front. Endocrinol. (Lausanne)</source><year>2023</year><fpage>14</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/FENDO.2023.1145111</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0015"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0015"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Visser</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rake</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Labrune</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leonard</surname><given-names>J.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moses</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Neutropenia, neutrophil dysfunction, and inflammatory bowel disease in glycogen storage disease type Ib: results of the European study on glycogen storage disease type I</article-title><source>J. Pediatr.</source><volume>137</volume><year>2000</year><fpage>187</fpage><lpage>191</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1067/MPD.2000.105232</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10931410</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0020"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0020"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Veiga-da-Cunha</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chevalier</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stephenne</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Defour</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paczia</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferster</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Failure to eliminate a phosphorylated glucose analog leads to neutropenia in patients with G6PT and G6PC3 deficiency</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><volume>116</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>1241</fpage><lpage>1250</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/PNAS.1816143116</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30626647</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0025"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0025"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boulanger</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stephenne</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Diederich</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mounkoro</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chevalier</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferster</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Successful use of empagliflozin to treat neutropenia in two G6PC3-deficient children: impact of a mutation in SGLT5</article-title><source>J. Inherit. Metab. Dis.</source><volume>45</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>759</fpage><lpage>768</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/JIMD.12509</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35506446</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0030"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0030"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyoshi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Akagi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ejiri</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pathophysiology and treatment of diabetic cardiomyopathy and heart failure in patients with diabetes mellitus</article-title><source>Int. J. Mol. Sci.</source><year>2022</year><fpage>23</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/IJMS23073587</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36613467</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0035"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0035"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Packer</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Anker</surname><given-names>S.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Filippatos</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pocock</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carson</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cardiovascular and renal outcomes with Empagliflozin in heart failure</article-title><source>N. Engl. J. Med.</source><volume>383</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>1413</fpage><lpage>1424</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMOA2022190</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32865377</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0040"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0040"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wortmann</surname><given-names>S.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Hove</surname><given-names>J.L.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Derks</surname><given-names>T.G.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chevalier</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Koller</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Treating neutropenia and neutrophil dysfunction in glycogen storage disease type Ib with an SGLT2 inhibitor</article-title><source>Blood</source><volume>136</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>1033</fpage><lpage>1043</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1182/BLOOD.2019004465</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32294159</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0045"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0045"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hexner-Erlichman</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Veiga-da-Cunha</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zehavi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vadasz</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sabag</surname><given-names>A.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tatour</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Favorable outcome of empagliflozin treatment in two pediatric glycogen storage disease type 1b patients</article-title><source>Front. Pediatr.</source><year>2022</year><fpage>10</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/FPED.2022.1071464</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0050"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0050"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bidiuk</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaciong</surname><given-names>Z.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sobieraj</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The overall benefits of empagliflozin treatment in adult siblings with glycogen storage disease type Ib: one year experience</article-title><source>Arch. Med. Sci.</source><volume>18</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>1095</fpage><lpage>1099</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5114/AOMS/150029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35982912</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0055"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0055"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miele</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fecarotta</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Veiga-da-Cunha</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinelli</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mollica</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Crohn disease-like enterocolitis remission after empagliflozin treatment in a child with glycogen storage disease type Ib: a case report</article-title><source>Ital. J. Pediatr.</source><year>2021</year><fpage>47</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/S13052-021-01100-W</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33658068</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0060"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0060"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tallis</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Karsenty</surname><given-names>C.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grimes</surname><given-names>A.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Karam</surname><given-names>L.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Elsea</surname><given-names>S.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sutton</surname><given-names>V.R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Untargeted metabolomic profiling in a patient with glycogen storage disease Ib receiving empagliflozin treatment</article-title><source>JIMD Rep.</source><volume>63</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>309</fpage><lpage>315</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/JMD2.12304</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35822097</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0065"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0065"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Halligan</surname><given-names>R.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dalton</surname><given-names>R.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mundy</surname><given-names>H.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Understanding the role of SGLT2 inhibitors in glycogen storage disease type Ib: the experience of one UK centre</article-title><source>Orphanet J. Rare Dis.</source><year>2022</year><fpage>17</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/S13023-022-02345-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35031060</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0070"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0070"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Makrilakis</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barmpagianni</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Veiga-da-Cunha</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Repurposing of Empagliflozin as a possible treatment for neutropenia and inflammatory bowel disease in glycogen storage disease type Ib: a case report</article-title><source>Cureus</source><year>2022</year><fpage>14</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7759/CUREUS.27264</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0075"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0075"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gr&#x000fc;nert</surname><given-names>S.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Derks</surname><given-names>T.G.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adrian</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Thihli</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ballhausen</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bidiuk</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Efficacy and safety of empagliflozin in glycogen storage disease type Ib: data from an international questionnaire</article-title><source>Genet. Med.</source><volume>24</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>1781</fpage><lpage>1788</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/J.GIM.2022.04.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35503103</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0080"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0080"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klinc</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Groselj</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mlinaric</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Homan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Markelj</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mezek Novak</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Case report: the success of empagliflozin therapy for glycogen storage disease type 1b</article-title><source>Front. Endocrinol. (Lausanne)</source><volume>15</volume><year>2024</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1365700</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/FENDO.2024.1365700</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0085"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0085"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaczor</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Malicki</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Folkert</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dobosz</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bryzek</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chruscicka-Smaga</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Neutrophil functions in patients with neutropenia due to glycogen storage disease type 1b treated with empagliflozin</article-title><source>Blood Adv.</source><volume>8</volume><year>2024</year><fpage>2790</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1182/BLOODADVANCES.2023012403</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38531056</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0090"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0090"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gr&#x000fc;nert</surname><given-names>S.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Elling</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maag</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wortmann</surname><given-names>S.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Derks</surname><given-names>T.G.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hannibal</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Improved inflammatory bowel disease, wound healing and normal oxidative burst under treatment with empagliflozin in glycogen storage disease type Ib</article-title><source>Orphanet J. Rare Dis.</source><year>2020</year><fpage>15</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/S13023-020-01503-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31941534</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0095"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0095"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Empagliflozin in children with glycogen storage disease-associated inflammatory bowel disease: a prospective, single-arm, open-label clinical trial</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2024</year><fpage>14</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/S41598-024-59320-Z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38168124</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0100"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0100"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ouchi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oba</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aoyama</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishii</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yano</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Serum uric acid in relation to serum 1,5-anhydroglucitol levels in patients with and without type 2 diabetes mellitus</article-title><source>Clin. Biochem.</source><volume>46</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>1436</fpage><lpage>1441</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/J.CLINBIOCHEM.2013.06.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23778057</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0105"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0105"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abdelkader</surname><given-names>N.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Elbaset</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moustafa</surname><given-names>P.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Empagliflozin mitigates type 2 diabetes-associated peripheral neuropathy: a glucose-independent effect through AMPK signaling</article-title><source>Arch. Pharm. Res.</source><volume>45</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>475</fpage><lpage>493</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/S12272-022-01391-5/FIGURES/6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35767208</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0110"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0110"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>El-Haggar</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hafez</surname><given-names>Y.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>El Sharkawy</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khalifa</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of empagliflozin in peripheral diabetic neuropathy of patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus</article-title><source>Med. Clin. (Barc.)</source><volume>163</volume><year>2024</year><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.medcli.2024.01.027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38653618</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0115"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0115"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakamoto</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Horikawa</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukuda</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Uchida</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeda</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Longterm outcomes of living donor liver transplantation for glycogen storage disease type 1b</article-title><source>Liver Transpl.</source><volume>26</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>57</fpage><lpage>67</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/LT.25649</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31587472</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0120"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0120"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gr&#x000fc;nert</surname><given-names>S.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Derks</surname><given-names>T.G.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mundy</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dalton</surname><given-names>R.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Donadieu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hofbauer</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Treatment recommendations for glycogen storage disease type IB- associated neutropenia and neutrophil dysfunction with empagliflozin: consensus from an international workshop</article-title><source>Mol. Genet. Metab.</source><year>2024</year><fpage>141</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/J.YMGME.2024.108144</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0125"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0125"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murko</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peschka</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsiakas</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulz-J&#x000fc;rgensen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Herden</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Santer</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Liver transplantation in glycogen storage disease type Ib: the role of SGLT2 inhibitors</article-title><source>Mol. Genet. Metab. Rep.</source><volume>35</volume><year>2023</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100977</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/J.YMGMR.2023.100977</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0130"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0130"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mahling</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schork</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nadalin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fritsche</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heyne</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guthoff</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sodium-glucose cotransporter 2 (SGLT2) inhibition in kidney transplant recipients with diabetes mellitus</article-title><source>Kidney Blood Press. Res.</source><volume>44</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>984</fpage><lpage>992</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000501854</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31437852</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0135"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0135"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Str&#x000f8;m Halden</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kvitne</surname><given-names>K.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Midtvedt</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajakumar</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertsen</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brox</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Efficacy and safety of empagliflozin in renal transplant recipients with Posttransplant diabetes mellitus</article-title><source>Diabetes Care</source><volume>42</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>1067</fpage><lpage>1074</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/DC19-0093</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30862658</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0140"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0140"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Attallah</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yassine</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of Empagliflozin in recipients of kidney transplant: a report of 8 cases</article-title><source>Transplant. Proc.</source><volume>51</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>3275</fpage><lpage>3280</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/J.TRANSPROCEED.2019.05.023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31732204</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0145"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0145"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwaiger</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Burghart</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Signorini</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ristl</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kopecky</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tura</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Empagliflozin in posttransplantation diabetes mellitus: a prospective, interventional pilot study on glucose metabolism, fluid volume, and patient safety</article-title><source>Am. J. Transplant.</source><volume>19</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>907</fpage><lpage>919</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/AJT.15223</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30585690</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0150"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0150"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>AlKindi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Omary</surname><given-names>H.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Al Hakim</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaaban</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boobes</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Outcomes of SGLT2 inhibitors use in diabetic renal transplant patients</article-title><source>Transplant. Proc.</source><volume>52</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>175</fpage><lpage>178</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/J.TRANSPROCEED.2019.11.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31924404</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0155"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0155"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D.Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fiske</surname><given-names>L.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carreras</surname><given-names>C.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinstein</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Natural history of hepatocellular adenoma formation in glycogen storage disease type I</article-title><source>J. Pediatr.</source><volume>159</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>442</fpage><lpage>446</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/J.JPEDS.2011.02.031</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21481415</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0160"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0160"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genetic variants and clinical features of patients with glycogen storage disease type Ib</article-title><source>JAMA Netw. Open</source><volume>8</volume><year>2025</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e2461888</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/JAMANETWORKOPEN.2024.61888</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0165"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0165"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaiser</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gautschi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bosanska</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meienberg</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baumgartner</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Spinas</surname><given-names>G.A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Glycemic control and complications in glycogen storage disease type I: results from the Swiss registry</article-title><source>Mol. Genet. Metab.</source><volume>126</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>355</fpage><lpage>361</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/J.YMGME.2019.02.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30846352</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0170"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0170"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vanhove</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Remijsen</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuypers</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gillard</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Drug-drug interactions between immunosuppressants and antidiabetic drugs in the treatment of post-transplant diabetes mellitus</article-title><source>Transplant. Rev. (Orlando)</source><volume>31</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>77</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/J.TRRE.2016.09.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27665059</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0175"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0175"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Virani</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajput</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficacy and safety of Canagliflozin in kidney transplant patients</article-title><source>Ind. J. Nephrol.</source><volume>29</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>278</fpage><lpage>281</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/IJN.IJN_2_18</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0180"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0180"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krams</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Adra</surname><given-names>D.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marchesini</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dageforde</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Atthota</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Joyal</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Modern glucose-lowering drugs in liver transplant recipients: improvement in weight, glycemic control, and potentially allograft steatosis</article-title><source>Front. Transpl.</source><volume>2</volume><year>2023</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1223169</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/FRTRA.2023.1223169</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0185"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0185"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Derks</surname><given-names>T.G.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Venema</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#x000f6;ller</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bos</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Overduin</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stolwijk</surname><given-names>N.N.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Repurposing empagliflozin in individuals with glycogen storage disease Ib: a value-based healthcare approach and systematic benefit-risk assessment</article-title><source>J. Inherit. Metab. Dis.</source><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/JIMD.12714</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="da0005"><title>Data availability</title><p id="p0005">No data was used for the research described in the article.</p></sec><ack id="ac0005"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p id="p0250">We would like to acknowledge our GSD Ib patients and their families.</p></ack></back></article>