<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int Arch Occup Environ Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int Arch Occup Environ Health</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>International Archives of Occupational and Environmental Health</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0340-0131</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1432-1246</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer Berlin Heidelberg</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40056194</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11972219</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2125</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00420-025-02125-y</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The association between occupational lead exposure and serum levels of vitamin D3 and a bone turnover biomarker in smelter workers</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mohammed</surname><given-names>Rateba Said</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-3698-9343</contrib-id><name><surname>Mourad</surname><given-names>Basma Hussein</given-names></name><address><email>basma.hussein@ymail.com</email><email>basma.hussein@kasralainy.edu.eg</email><email>basma.hussein@cu.edu.eg</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/03q21mh05</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.7776.1</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0639 9286</institution-id><institution>Department of Occupational and Environmental Medicine, Faculty of Medicine, </institution><institution>Cairo University, </institution></institution-wrap>Cairo, Egypt </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>8</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>8</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>98</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>297</fpage><lpage>307</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>1</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Objective</title><p id="Par1">Bone tissue is the chief target for lead (Pb) in chronic exposure. This study aimed to demonstrate the relation between the blood lead levels (BLL) and serum levels of 1,25 dihydroxy cholecalciferol (vitamin D3) and type I collagen cross-linked C-telopeptide (CTX-1) as a biomarker of bone turnover among some Egyptian workers occupationally exposed to Pb in the smelting process. The study also targeted to identify any clinical manifestations indicative of skeletal system affection and their association with the performed investigations.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">A total of 48 smelter workers and 48 administrative controls participated in the study. All subjects underwent comprehensive medical and occupational history taking and detailed clinical examinations, with a particular focus on symptoms indicative of skeletal system involvement. These symptoms included generalized bony aches, low back pain, joint pain, restricted joint movement, a history of fractures from minor trauma, and delayed fracture healing. BLL, as well as serum levels of vitamin D3 and CTX-1, were measured in all participants.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">Smelter workers exhibited significantly higher prevalence of bony aches, low back pain, joint pain, and past fractures from minor trauma compared to controls. The BLL and serum CTX-1 levels were significantly elevated in the exposed group, while serum vitamin D3 levels were notably lower. Logistic regression analysis revealed that BLL significantly predicted bony aches and low back pain. Additionally, serum vitamin D3 and CTX-1 levels were significant predictors of low back pain and joint pain, respectively, among exposed workers. The measured parameters were significantly correlated with one another and with the duration of employment in the exposed group.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par4">Significant associations between manifestations of skeletal system affection, BLL, and serum levels of vitamin D3 and CTX-1 were detected among smelter workers with chronic occupational exposure to Pb.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Chronic occupational pb exposure</kwd><kwd>Vitamin D3</kwd><kwd>Biomarker of bone turnover</kwd><kwd>CTX-1</kwd><kwd>Smelters workers</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Cairo University</institution></funding-source></award-group><open-access><p>Open access funding provided by The Science, Technology &#x00026; Innovation Funding Authority (STDF) in cooperation with The Egyptian Knowledge Bank (EKB).</p></open-access></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Springer-Verlag GmbH Germany, part of Springer Nature 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par5">When non-ferrous metals are smelted at high temperatures, some metals can gasify and become suspended in the air. Lead (Pb) is one of the most commonly encountered heavy metals during the smelting process. As a semi-volatile heavy metal, Pb tends to evaporate from ore particles at high temperatures during smelting, remaining in a gaseous state or condensing into fine particulate matter (PM) within cooling flue gas (Zhang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2022</xref>). This often results in elevated Pb levels in the industrial environment. Occupational exposure to Pb typically occurs through inhalation of Pb dust or fumes, with ingestion and dermal absorption playing lesser roles (CDC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2024a</xref>). Once absorbed, Pb binds to blood proteins and is distributed to various soft and hard tissues. The bone matrix is a primary target for Pb, as it can substitute for other divalent cations, including Ca&#x000b2;&#x0207a;, Mg&#x000b2;&#x0207a;, and Fe&#x000b2;&#x0207a; (Rodr&#x000ed;guez and Mandalunis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2018</xref>).</p><p id="Par6">Bone tissue consists of several cell types, including osteocytes, osteoblasts, osteoclasts, and bone lining cells, which are embedded within a calcified extracellular matrix. The bone matrix is composed of minerals (50&#x02013;70%), organic matter (20&#x02013;40%), and water (5&#x02013;10%). Type I collagen, synthesized by osteoblasts and deposited in layers within the mature (lamellar) bone, constitutes approximately 90% of the organic component of the extracellular matrix (Schlesinger et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2020</xref>). Osteoclastic activity has been linked to bone resorption, characterized by the release of type I collagen cross-linked C-telopeptide (CTX-1), a degradation product of collagen (Ying et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2023</xref>).</p><p id="Par7">Extensive laboratory and clinical studies have shown that long-term Pb exposure adversely affects bone tissue function through two primary mechanisms. First, Pb directly impacts bone tissue, reducing bone mass and density by inhibiting osteoblast and chondrocyte activity, inducing cytotoxicity, and triggering apoptosis in mesenchymal stem cells (Sharifi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2011</xref>; Akbal et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2014</xref>). Second, Pb exhibits a high affinity for thiol groups in the active sites of various enzymes, including kidney 1-&#x003b1;-hydroxylase, which is crucial for synthesizing 1,25-dihydroxycholecalciferol (vitamin D3). The inhibition of this enzyme by Pb, disrupts calcium and phosphorus metabolism, resulting in decreased intestinal absorption, hypocalcemia, and hypophosphatemia (Dongre et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2013</xref>).</p><p id="Par8">Decreased bone mineral density, along with Pb deposition in the cement lines of bone and increased collagen resorption, leads to delayed cartilage formation, a heightened risk of bone fractures, osteoporosis, and impaired fracture healing (Ravibabu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2020</xref>).</p><p id="Par9">Taking the aforementioned into consideration, the current study was designed to investigate the association between blood Pb levels and serum levels of vitamin D3 and CTX-1 as a biomarker of bone turnover in a subset of Egyptian workers occupationally exposed to Pb in a non-ferrous metal smelter. Additionally, the study aimed to identify clinical symptoms or complaints indicative of skeletal system involvement and their correlation with laboratory findings.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods and materials</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Study design, setting, and population</title><p id="Par10">This cross-sectional comparative study was conducted at a non-ferrous smelter in Helwan, Greater Cairo, Egypt, between May and June 2024. Workers in this facility are exposed to lead (Pb) during various high-risk activities involved in processing non-ferrous metals such as aluminum and copper. Their tasks include loading metal ores or concentrates into furnaces, which release Pb fumes and dust into the air during the smelting process.</p><p id="Par11">Additionally, workers are engaged in refining molten metals, where chemical treatments and high-temperature operations further vaporize Pb compounds, increasing the risk of inhalation exposure. Maintenance activities, such as cleaning furnaces, repairing equipment, and managing slag, often disturb accumulated Pb dust, leading to significant exposure through both inhalation and dermal contact. Furthermore, tasks such as sampling or quality testing of molten metal frequently expose workers to direct Pb fumes.</p><p id="Par12">Based on the sample size calculation, the study included 48 smelter workers with chronic occupational exposure to Pb and a control group of 48 administrative personnel who were not exposed to Pb. To qualify for the study, each exposed worker had to have been actively involved in the production process within the industrial setting for a minimum of two years. Notably, all exposed workers reported proper use of personal protective equipment (PPE). The PPE utilized included N95 air-purifying respirators, safety goggles, face shields, heat-resistant and flame-retardant suits, overalls, gloves, and boots. Additionally, the local exhaust ventilation system appeared to function effectively.</p><p id="Par13">Environmental monitoring of heavy metals, including lead (Pb), aluminum (Al), and copper (Cu), is conducted annually within the smelter to ensure compliance with national safety standards. Data from these monitoring efforts consistently show that the concentrations of these metals in the workplace air and surrounding environment remain within the permissible limits set by national regulatory bodies. The authors reviewed the results of this monitoring in collaboration with the smelter administration; however, the data were not made available for inclusion in this study. According to the Egyptian Environmental Affairs Agency (EEAA), the threshold limit value (TLV) for Pb in workplace air is set at 0.05&#x000a0;mg/m&#x000b3; (50&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/m&#x000b3;), averaged over an 8-hour workday. For Al and Cu, the EEAA has established TLVs of 5&#x000a0;mg/m&#x000b3; and 1&#x000a0;mg/m&#x000b3;, respectively, for respirable dust fractions (EEAA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">1995</xref>).</p><p id="Par14"><italic>Sample size calculation</italic>: The Power and Sample Size Calculator tool (version 3.0.43) was used to determine the sample size. The calculation was based on the following inputs: a significance level of 0.05, a mean difference between groups (g1 and g2) of 0.58, and a total sample size of 96 participants, with 48 individuals in each group (Yadav et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2018</xref>).</p><p id="Par15">Participants with endocrine or metabolic disorders affecting bone tissue, or those using medications known to influence calcium-phosphate metabolism and bone turnover, were excluded from the study.</p><p id="Par16">To form the control group, 48 matched individuals without a history of occupational Pb exposure were selected from the administrative department of the investigated smelter. After applying the exclusion criteria, control participants were chosen to match the exposed group in terms of sex, age, socioeconomic status, and specific medically significant behaviours, such as smoking.</p><p id="Par17">The Research Ethics Committee of the Faculty of Medicine, Cairo University, Egypt, approved the study (approval number: N-467-2023). The Chief Executive Officer (CEO) of the smelter also presented formal consent for the study.</p><p id="Par18">After receiving a detailed explanation of the study&#x02019;s purpose, each participant voluntarily provided written informed consent to participate. Strict confidentiality and adherence to good clinical practice principles were maintained throughout the processes of sample collection, testing, coding, and recording of results.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Data collection</title><p id="Par19">A team of experienced occupational doctors conducted interviews with the participants to gather personal and occupational information. The medical history and clinical examination focused on any complaints or signs indicating skeletal system involvement, including generalized bone aches, back pain, joint pain, limited joint movement, a history of fractures from minor impact or low-energy activities, and delayed healing of previous fractures.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Blood sample collection and laboratory investigations</title><p id="Par20">Five millilitres of whole blood were drawn from each participant at the end of the work shift: 2 mL in heparinized tubes and 3 mL in plain tubes. The 2-mL sample was used to estimate blood lead levels (BLL). The 3-mL sample was centrifuged at 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C and 3000 RPM for 10&#x000a0;min to extract serum for measuring serum vitamin D3 and CTX-1. Laboratory assays were conducted at the Clinical and Chemical Pathology Department Laboratory, Faculty of Medicine, Cairo University, Egypt.</p><sec id="Sec6"><title>Measurement of blood lead levels</title><p id="Par21">Until analysis, the 2-mL blood sample was kept at -20&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. The sample was digested with 2 mL of nitric acid and 0.2 mL of hydrogen peroxide using ETHOS-D (Milestone Microwave Laboratory Systems, Italy) while keeping power, temperature, and process duration constant. Using distilled water, the digested samples were diluted to a volume of 5 mL and then centrifuged. Using an atomic absorption spectrophotometer (GBC Avanta P, Australia), the concentration of Pb was determined. For the sample with the lowest concentration, a standard solution containing 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/dL of lead was generated using a stock solution. After three repetitions, the study revealed 100% recovery with % relative standard deviation (RSD) at &#x0003c;&#x02009;0.5 (Kalahasthi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2016</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Measurement of serum vitamin D3 and CTX-1</title><p id="Par22">The enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) was used to determine the amounts of serum vitamin D3 and CTX-1 (BT LAB Bioassay Technology Laboratory, Shanghai, China). Thermo Scientific Multiskan EX-reader (USA) was used to detect the absorbance of samples and standard specimens at 450&#x000a0;nm. The unknown sample&#x02019;s concentration was determined through the use of a standard curve and linear regression. For vitamin D3 and CTX-1, the range of the technique was 7&#x02013;500 pg/mL and 7&#x02013;1500 ng/mL, respectively. For vitamin D3 and CTX-1, the method&#x02019;s sensitivity was 3.14 pg/mL and 4.21 ng/mL, respectively (Ali et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2024</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par23">The statistical software for the social sciences (SPSS) version 28 (IBM Corp., Armonk, NY, USA) was used to code and input the data. For quantitative variables, the mean, standard deviation, median, minimum, and maximum were used to summarize the data; for categorical variables, the frequencies (number of cases) and relative frequencies (percentages) were used. For normally distributed quantitative variables, group comparisons were carried out using the unpaired t-test; for non-normally distributed quantitative variables, the non-parametric Mann-Whitney test was employed (Chan <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2003a</xref>). The normally distributed variables were the age, BMI, and levels of BLL, vitamin D3 and CTX-1 of the studied participants. The Chi-square (&#x003c7;2) test was used to compare categorical data. When the predicted frequency is less than five, the Exact test was utilized in its place. A 95% confidence interval for the odds ratio (OR) was computed (Chan <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2003b</xref>). The Spearman correlation coefficient was used to perform correlations between quantitative variables (Chan <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2003c</xref>). Logistic regression was done to detect independent predictors of the clinical manifestations of skeletal system affection (Chan <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2004a</xref>). For identifying independent predictors of vitamin D3 and CTX-1 levels, linear regression analysis was used (Chan <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2004b</xref>). The significance level of 0.05 for a P-value was deemed statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Results</title><p id="Par24">The general demographic details of the exposed and comparison groups are presented in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. There were no statistically significant differences between the exposed smelter workers and the administrative controls in terms of age, body mass index (BMI), smoking index, or duration of employment. The age of the smelter workers ranged from 25 to 58 years, and their employment duration ranged from 5 to 25 years.</p><p id="Par25">
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Comparison between the exposed and control groups as regards their general characteristics, BLL, and their serum levels of vitamin D3 and CTX-1</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2"/><th align="left" colspan="5">Exposed group (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;48)</th><th align="left" colspan="5">Control group (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;48)</th><th align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>P</italic> value</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Mean</th><th align="left">SD</th><th align="left">Median</th><th align="left">Minimum</th><th align="left">Maximum</th><th align="left">Mean</th><th align="left">SD</th><th align="left">Median</th><th align="left">Minimum</th><th align="left">Maximum</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Age (years)</td><td char="." align="char">37.29</td><td char="." align="char">10.07</td><td align="left">34</td><td align="left">25</td><td align="left">58</td><td char="." align="char">38.71</td><td char="." align="char">10.34</td><td align="left">36</td><td align="left">25</td><td align="left">57</td><td char="." align="char">0.498</td></tr><tr><td align="left">BMI</td><td char="." align="char">28.72</td><td char="." align="char">5.69</td><td align="left">28.45</td><td align="left">19.5</td><td align="left">40</td><td char="." align="char">29.4</td><td char="." align="char">4.32</td><td align="left">29.4</td><td align="left">20.7</td><td align="left">39.7</td><td char="." align="char">0.512</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Smoking index</td><td char="." align="char">97.92</td><td char="." align="char">162.41</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">700</td><td char="." align="char">91.67</td><td char="." align="char">155.17</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">500</td><td char="." align="char">0.479</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><p>Duration of employment</p><p>(years)</p></td><td char="." align="char">11.04</td><td char="." align="char">4.81</td><td align="left">9</td><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">25</td><td char="." align="char">12.19</td><td char="." align="char">6.66</td><td align="left">9</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">32</td><td char="." align="char">0.837</td></tr><tr><td align="left">BLL (&#x000b5;g/dl)</td><td char="." align="char">11.86</td><td char="." align="char">3.56</td><td align="left">11.9</td><td align="left">3.60</td><td align="left">20</td><td char="." align="char">4.30</td><td char="." align="char">1.40</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">7.2</td><td char="." align="char">
<bold>&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001*</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Vitamin D3 (pg/mL)</td><td char="." align="char">29.42</td><td char="." align="char">12.03</td><td align="left">31.6</td><td align="left">8.3</td><td align="left">72.64</td><td char="." align="char">48.23</td><td char="." align="char">21.22</td><td align="left">44.05</td><td align="left">8.1</td><td align="left">122</td><td char="." align="char">
<bold>&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001*</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CTX-1 (ng/mL)</td><td char="." align="char">725.73</td><td char="." align="char">233.79</td><td align="left">704.5</td><td align="left">139.1</td><td align="left">1177</td><td char="." align="char">393.15</td><td char="." align="char">188.63</td><td align="left">364.1</td><td align="left">65.3</td><td align="left">813.9</td><td char="." align="char">
<bold>&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001*</bold>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>SD&#x02009;=&#x02009;Standard deviation; BMI&#x02009;=&#x02009;Body Mass Index; Smoking index&#x02009;=&#x02009;The number of cigarettes smoked per day multiplied by the number of years of smoking; BLL&#x02009;=&#x02009;Blood Lead Level; CTX-1&#x02009;=&#x02009;Type I collagen cross-linked C-telopeptide</p><p>*p-value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 denotes statistical significance</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par26">In contrast, the mean blood lead level (BLL) in the exposed group (11.86&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.56&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/dL) was significantly higher than that in the comparison group (4.30&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.40&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/dL) (<italic>p</italic>-value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001). The mean serum level of vitamin D3 was significantly lower in the exposed smelter workers (29.42&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;12.03 pg/mL) compared with the administrative controls (48.23&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;21.22 pg/mL). Additionally, the mean serum level of the bone turnover biomarker CTX-1 was significantly elevated in the exposed group (725.73&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;233.79 ng/mL) compared with the control group (393.15&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;188.63 ng/mL) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p><p id="Par27">Medical history and clinical examination revealed that symptoms indicating skeletal system involvement were significantly more common (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) among exposed workers compared to the control group (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Recurrent bony aches were reported by 47.9% of exposed workers (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;23), with an odds ratio (OR) of 6.44 (95% CI: 2.309&#x02013;17.964). Additionally, 41.7% (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;20) reported prolonged low back pain (OR: 3.571, 95% CI: 1.379&#x02013;9.249), and 35.4% (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;17) experienced pain in multiple joints (OR: 4.716, 95% CI: 1.572&#x02013;14.152). Past fractures after minor trauma were reported by 27.1% (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;13) of workers, showing a statistically significant difference compared to the control group (OR: 5.571, 95% CI: 1.472&#x02013;21.083). In the administrative control group, the prevalence of bony aches, low back pain, joint pain, and past fractures was 12.5%, 16.7%, 10.4%, and 6.3%, respectively. Additionally, 10 exposed smelter workers reported limited joint movement, and 5 workers reported delayed healing of past fractures. However, the prevalence of these two symptoms did not differ significantly from the control group.</p><p id="Par28">
<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>The frequency distribution of the exposed and control participants with some clinical manifestations of skeletal system affection</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Manifestation</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Exposed group (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;48)</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Control group (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;48)</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">X<sup>2</sup></th><th align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>P</italic> value</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">OR</th><th align="left" colspan="2">95% CI</th></tr><tr><th align="left">No.</th><th align="left">%</th><th align="left">No.</th><th align="left">%</th><th align="left">Lower</th><th align="left">Upper</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Bony aches</td><td char="." align="char">23</td><td char="." align="char">47.9%</td><td char="." align="char">6</td><td char="." align="char">12.5%</td><td char="." align="char">14.279</td><td char="." align="char">
<bold>&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001*</bold>
</td><td char="." align="char">6.440</td><td char="." align="char">2.309</td><td char="." align="char">17.964</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Low back pain</td><td char="." align="char">20</td><td char="." align="char">41.7%</td><td char="." align="char">8</td><td char="." align="char">16.7%</td><td char="." align="char">7.261</td><td char="." align="char">
<bold>0.007*</bold>
</td><td char="." align="char">3.571</td><td char="." align="char">1.379</td><td char="." align="char">9.249</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Joint pain</td><td char="." align="char">17</td><td char="." align="char">35.4%</td><td char="." align="char">5</td><td char="." align="char">10.4%</td><td char="." align="char">8.491</td><td char="." align="char">
<bold>0.004*</bold>
</td><td char="." align="char">4.716</td><td char="." align="char">1.572</td><td char="." align="char">14.152</td></tr><tr><td align="left">History of past fracture after minor trauma</td><td char="." align="char">13</td><td char="." align="char">27.1%</td><td char="." align="char">3</td><td char="." align="char">6.3%</td><td char="." align="char">7.500</td><td char="." align="char">
<bold>0.006*</bold>
</td><td char="." align="char">5.571</td><td char="." align="char">1.472</td><td char="." align="char">21.083</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Limited joint movement</td><td char="." align="char">10</td><td char="." align="char">20.8%</td><td char="." align="char">5</td><td char="." align="char">10.4%</td><td char="." align="char">1.975</td><td char="." align="char">0.160</td><td char="." align="char">2.263</td><td char="." align="char">0.710</td><td char="." align="char">7.211</td></tr><tr><td align="left">History of delayed healing of fracture</td><td char="." align="char">5</td><td char="." align="char">10.4%</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td char="." align="char">2.1%</td><td char="." align="char">2.844</td><td char="." align="char">0.204</td><td char="." align="char">5.465</td><td char="." align="char">0.614</td><td char="." align="char">48.662</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*p-value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 denotes statistical significance</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par29">Logistic regression analysis was performed to predict the clinical manifestations of skeletal system involvement among exposed smelter workers using blood lead level (BLL), vitamin D3, and CTX-1 serum levels as independent variables (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). The results showed that BLL was a significant predictor of bony aches and low back pain, with an odds ratio (OR) greater than 1. Also, serum vitamin D3 levels significantly predicted low back pain, while serum CTX-1 levels were significant predictors of joint pain, both with ORs greater than 1.</p><p id="Par30">
<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Logistic regression analysis to predict the clinical manifestations of skeletal system affection using BLL, and serum levels of vitamin D3 and CTX-1 as independent variables among the exposed group</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="2"/><th align="left" rowspan="2">P value</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">OR</th><th align="left" colspan="2">95% C.I.</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Lower</th><th align="left">Upper</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">Bony aches</td><td align="left">BLL</td><td align="left">
<bold>0.041*</bold>
</td><td align="left">1.014</td><td align="left">1.000</td><td char="." align="char">1.029</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Vitamin D3</td><td align="left">0.495</td><td align="left">1.004</td><td align="left">0.992</td><td char="." align="char">1.017</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CTX-1</td><td align="left">0.332</td><td align="left">0.677</td><td align="left">0.308</td><td char="." align="char">1.488</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">Low back pain</td><td align="left">BLL</td><td align="left">
<bold>0.036*</bold>
</td><td align="left">1.066</td><td align="left">1.032</td><td char="." align="char">1.098</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Vitamin D3</td><td align="left">
<bold>0.028*</bold>
</td><td align="left">1.074</td><td align="left">1.055</td><td char="." align="char">1.089</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CTX-1</td><td align="left">0.312</td><td align="left">0.629</td><td align="left">0.256</td><td char="." align="char">1.545</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">Joint pain</td><td align="left">BLL</td><td align="left">0.816</td><td align="left">1.025</td><td align="left">0.834</td><td char="." align="char">1.260</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Vitamin D3</td><td align="left">0.386</td><td align="left">1.006</td><td align="left">0.993</td><td char="." align="char">1.020</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CTX-1</td><td align="left">
<bold>0.042*</bold>
</td><td align="left">1.034</td><td align="left">1.017</td><td char="." align="char">1.057</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">History of past fracture after minor trauma</td><td align="left">BLL</td><td align="left">0.920</td><td align="left">0.983</td><td align="left">0.697</td><td char="." align="char">1.385</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Vitamin D3</td><td align="left">0.158</td><td align="left">1.011</td><td align="left">0.996</td><td char="." align="char">1.027</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CTX-1</td><td align="left">0.298</td><td align="left">0.591</td><td align="left">0.219</td><td char="." align="char">1.592</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">Limited joint movement</td><td align="left">BLL</td><td align="left">0.816</td><td align="left">1.025</td><td align="left">0.834</td><td char="." align="char">1.260</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Vitamin D3</td><td align="left">0.386</td><td align="left">1.006</td><td align="left">0.993</td><td char="." align="char">1.020</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CTX-1</td><td align="left">0.482</td><td align="left">0.732</td><td align="left">0.307</td><td char="." align="char">1.747</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">History of delayed healing of fracture</td><td align="left">BLL</td><td align="left">0.920</td><td align="left">0.983</td><td align="left">0.697</td><td char="." align="char">1.385</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Vitamin D3</td><td align="left">0.158</td><td align="left">1.011</td><td align="left">0.996</td><td char="." align="char">1.027</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CTX-1</td><td align="left">0.298</td><td align="left">0.591</td><td align="left">0.219</td><td char="." align="char">1.592</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>BLL&#x02009;=&#x02009;Blood Lead Level; CTX-1&#x02009;=&#x02009;Type I collagen cross linked C-telopeptide</p><p>*p-value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 denotes statistical significance</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par31">To identify significant independent predictors for serum vitamin D3 and CTX-1 levels among the exposed workers, linear regression analyses were conducted. The findings (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>) revealed that BLL was a statistically significant independent predictor of serum vitamin D3 and CTX-1 levels in the exposed participants. Moreover, the duration of employment among the exposed workers was also identified as a statistically significant independent predictor of serum CTX-1 levels.</p><p id="Par32">
<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Linear regression analyses to identify significant independent predictors for the serum levels of vitamin D3 and CTX-1 among the exposed smelter workers</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="3">Model</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Unstandardized Coefficients</th><th align="left">Standardized Coefficients</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">t</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">P value</th><th align="left" colspan="2">95.0% Confidence Interval for B</th></tr><tr><th align="left">B</th><th align="left">Std. Error</th><th align="left">Beta</th><th align="left">Lower Bound</th><th align="left">Upper Bound</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Vitamin D3</td><td align="left" colspan="2">(Constant)</td><td align="left">66.920</td><td align="left">1.631</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">41.026</td><td align="left">
<bold>&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</bold>
</td><td align="left">63.635</td><td align="left">70.206</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">BLL</td><td align="left">-1.445</td><td align="left">0.556</td><td align="left">-0.428</td><td align="left">-2.601</td><td align="left">
<bold>0.013*</bold>
</td><td align="left">-2.564</td><td align="left">-0.326</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="2">CTX-1</td><td align="left">(Constant)</td><td align="left">444.821</td><td align="left">140.325</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">3.170</td><td align="left">
<bold>0.003</bold>
</td><td align="left">162.014</td><td align="left">727.628</td></tr><tr><td align="left">BLL</td><td align="left">38.893</td><td align="left">6.976</td><td align="left">0.592</td><td align="left">5.575</td><td align="left">
<bold>&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001*</bold>
</td><td align="left">24.833</td><td align="left">52.953</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Duration of employment</td><td align="left">3.186</td><td align="left">1.541</td><td align="left">0.065</td><td align="left">2.068</td><td align="left">
<bold>0.045*</bold>
</td><td align="left">0.080</td><td align="left">6.291</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>BLL&#x02009;=&#x02009;Blood Lead Level; CTX-1&#x02009;=&#x02009;Type I collagen cross linked C-telopeptide</p><p>*p-value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 denotes statistical significance</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par33">Spearman&#x02019;s correlation analyses were conducted to explore associations between age, BMI, smoking index, duration of employment, BLL, and serum levels of vitamin D3 and CTX-1 among exposed smelter workers. The results (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>, <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> and <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>) revealed significant positive correlations between the duration of employment and BLL (<italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.289, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.047), as well as between the duration of employment and serum CTX-1 levels (<italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.303, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.036).</p><p id="Par34">
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Correlation between the duration (years) of employment and the blood lead levels (BLL) among the exposed group (<italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.289, <italic>P</italic>-value&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.047)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="420_2025_2125_Fig1_HTML" id="d33e1266"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par35">
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Correlation between the duration (years) of employment and the serum levels of 1,25 dihydroxy-cholecalcifirol (vitamin D3) among the exposed group (<italic>r</italic> = -0.297, <italic>P</italic>-value&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.040)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="420_2025_2125_Fig2_HTML" id="d33e1283"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par36">
<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Correlation between the duration (years) of employment and the serum levels of type I collagen cross-linked C-telopeptide (CTX-1) among the exposed group (<italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.303, <italic>P</italic>-value&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.036)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="420_2025_2125_Fig3_HTML" id="d33e1300"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par37">
<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Correlation between the blood lead levels (BLL) and the serum levels of 1,25 dihydroxy-cholecalciferol (vitamin D3) among the exposed group (<italic>r</italic> = -0.754, <italic>P</italic>-value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="420_2025_2125_Fig4_HTML" id="d33e1317"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par38">
<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Correlation between the blood lead levels (BLL) and the serum levels of type I collagen cross-linked C-telopeptide (CTX-1) among the exposed group (<italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.812, <italic>P</italic>-value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="420_2025_2125_Fig5_HTML" id="d33e1334"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par39">
<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Correlation between the serum levels of type I collagen cross-linked C-telopeptide (CTX-1) and 1,25 dihydroxy-cholecalciferol (vitamin D3) among the exposed group (<italic>r</italic> = -0.789, <italic>P</italic>-value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="420_2025_2125_Fig6_HTML" id="d33e1351"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par40">A significant negative correlation was observed between the duration of employment and serum vitamin D3 levels (<italic>r</italic> = -0.297, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.040). In addition, the results revealed a significant negative correlation between BLL and serum vitamin D3 levels (<italic>r</italic> = -0.754, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001), and a significant positive correlation between BLL and serum CTX-1 levels (<italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.812, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001) among exposed participants. Furthermore, serum vitamin D3 levels showed a significant negative correlation with serum CTX-1 levels (<italic>r</italic> = -0.789, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001).</p><p id="Par41">No significant correlations were identified between the three laboratory investigations (BLL, serum vitamin D3, and CTX-1) and the age, BMI, or smoking index of the exposed workers.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par42">One of the most common heavy metals encountered during the smelting process is Pb, which is known to have harmful effects on human health. Previous research has shown that long-term exposure to Pb can disrupt bone tissue by either decreasing bone mineralization, through the inhibition of the kidney 1-&#x003b1;-hydroxylase enzyme (necessary for the synthesis of 1,25-dihydroxycholecalciferol, or vitamin D3), or by altering bone mass through the inhibition of chondrocytes and osteoblasts (Sharifi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2011</xref>; Dongre et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2013</xref>; Akbal et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2014</xref>; Zhang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2021</xref>). Pb may also accumulate in the bone cement, increasing the resorption of bone collagen. Collagen breakdown products, such as type I collagen cross-linked C-telopeptide (CTX-1), are used as biomarkers to indicate the presence of bone turnover (Ravibabu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2020</xref>; Schini et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2023</xref>).</p><p id="Par43">Focusing on the effect of occupational Pb exposure on workers&#x02019; bones in a non-ferrous smelter is justified because Pb has unique and well-documented pathways of deposition and toxicity in bone tissues. Unlike aluminium and copper, Pb has a high affinity for bone, accumulating over time and serving as a long-term marker of exposure. This storage affects bone remodeling, mineralization, and can lead to systemic effects when mobilized into the bloodstream. While exposure to other metals like aluminium may contribute to observed effects, their toxicokinetics and biological targets differ significantly from those of Pb. By isolating Pb&#x02019;s impact on bones, researchers can more accurately assess its specific health risks and guide targeted interventions for Pb exposure, which remains a major occupational hazard in smelters. This approach ensures clarity in understanding Pb&#x02019;s role despite the presence of other metals.</p><p id="Par44">In the current study, the mean value of the blood lead levels (BLL) among the exposed smelter workers (11.86&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.56&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/dL) showed a statistically significant elevation compared to the comparison group (4.30&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.40&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/dL). Similarly, a recent Egyptian study showed that the mean BLL among the exposed workers in a copper smelter (27.81&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.48&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/dL) was significantly higher than among the administrative controls (10.67&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.57&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/dL) (Mourad and El-Sherif <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2022</xref>). Also, in a previous Korean study, the BLL mean was significantly elevated among smelting workers (5.839&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/dL) compared to the general male population (2.44&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/dL) (An et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2017</xref>).</p><p id="Par45">Notably, the World Health Organization (WHO) recommends a blood lead level of 5&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/dL as the threshold for initiating a comprehensive examination of Pb exposure and taking action to minimize or eliminate it (WHO 2021). However, BLLs below 5&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/dL have been associated with adverse health effects on multiple organ systems. The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) has emphasized that no level of Pb exposure is entirely safe, particularly for vulnerable populations such as workers with prolonged exposure (CDC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2024b</xref>).</p><p id="Par46">The smelter workers exposed to Pb in the present study showed statistically significant lower serum levels of vitamin D3 compared to the administrative controls. This is consistent with the findings of Batra and colleagues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2020</xref>) in India, who reported significantly decreased serum levels of vitamin D (28.82&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;10.81 ng/ml) and significantly elevated blood lead levels (BLL) (38.02&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;19.92&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/dl) in Pb-exposed subjects compared to their controls. Similarly, Himani and colleagues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2020</xref>) observed high BLL and low serum vitamin D in workers in the battery industry in the Delhi NCR region, India. Additionally, similar results were found among workers exposed to Pb in the jewellery industry in Bangladesh (Mazumdar et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2017</xref>).</p><p id="Par47">Bone is considered to be essential for organ protection, movement, and bodily support. Osteoclast-mediated bone resorption and osteoblast-mediated bone growth are interdependent. Biomarkers of bone turnover provide a means of quantifying the dynamic processes of bone production and resorption. In clinical research, the International Osteoporosis Foundation suggests utilizing C-telopeptide (CTX) as a measure of bone resorption (Schini et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2023</xref>). In the current study, compared to the control group, the exposed workers&#x02019; serum levels of CTX-1 showed a statistically significant rise. Based on a prior study, Pb exposure affects bone resorption, which can lead to osteopenia. According to the study, Pb may have a part in the genesis of osteoporosis and that the disease could alter bone turnover causing variations in Pb content in bones (Brito et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2014</xref>). In contrast to the control group, which consisted of office workers, a more recent study revealed statistically significant elevated levels of the collagen degradation product (hydroxyproline in urine, or HyP-U) among workers who were occupationally exposed to lead (Pb) in a Pb-battery manufacturing plant located in Tamil Nadu, India (Kalahasthi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2021</xref>).</p><p id="Par48">According to Patrick (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2006</xref>), the review of literature revealed that the musculoskeletal system is susceptible to Pb poisoning, even at low levels of exposure. This can have an impact on bone growth and development, dentition, bone density, fracture healing, joint functioning, and motor abilities. In adults, more than 90% of the Pb body load is found in bone. In accordance to research on animals, Pb poisoning causes fibrous non-union and delayed fracture healing because of the acceleration of endochondral ossification (Carmouche et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2005</xref>). Medical history taking and clinical examination of the studied groups in the current study revealed a statistically significant elevated prevalence of several manifestations denoting skeletal system affection among exposed workers compared with their controls. The most commonly encountered complaints were recurrent generalized bony aches, prolonged low back pain, pain in multiple joints and a history of past fractures after minor traumas. Additionally, some exposed smelter workers reported limited joint movement while other workers gave a history of delayed healing of past fractures. Likewise, a recent study conducted in Tamil Nadu, India examined the musculoskeletal symptoms of long-term Pb exposure among employees of a Pb-battery manufacturing company. The findings revealed that among exposed individuals, lower back pain and discomfort were most common, followed by knee, shoulder, and neck pain. The study also found that even at low levels of Pb exposure, pain and discomfort in the neck, shoulders, and lower back were associated with signs of bone resorption (Kalahasthi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2021</xref>). Furthermore, Ravibabu et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2019</xref>) identified a correlation between inflammatory markers and musculoskeletal diseases in workers exposed to lead (Pb) from Pb-battery production plants. Another study conducted in Tahran, Iran, came to the conclusion that fatigue and persistent bone aches could be related to elevated blood Pb levels (Aliasgharpour and Hagani <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2005</xref>). In addition, those exposed to Pb experience severe fractures and heal more slowly than those who are not (Carmouche et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2005</xref>).</p><p id="Par49">The logistic regression analysis in the current study pointed to the significance of the BLL as an independent predictor of bony aches and low back pain with an odds ratio greater than 1, denoting an increased risk of these aches with elevated BLL among the exposed workers. Moreover, the serum levels of vitamin D3 and CTX-1 were revealed to be significant predictors of low back pain and joint pain, respectively. Studies have shown a significant association between low serum vitamin D levels and the prevalence of chronic low back pain, emphasizing the need for adequate vitamin D intake for musculoskeletal health (Zadro et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2017</xref>; Alonso-P&#x000e9;rez et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2024</xref>). Also, earlier research had demonstrated a significant association between serum levels of CTX-1 and the severity of joint pain and tenderness (Olama et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2015</xref>).</p><p id="Par50">The results of the correlation analysis in the present research revealed a significant positive correlation between BLL and the years of occupational exposure to Pb among the exposed participants. The same findings were observed in several previous studies (Rahimpoor et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2020</xref>; Al-Rudainy <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2010</xref>; Mortada et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2001</xref>). While blood Pb is commonly used for assessing recent or current exposure due to its short half-life (about 30 days), it can still reflect accumulated Pb exposure over time, especially in workers who have been employed for extended periods. Long-term, low-level exposure can lead to Pb accumulation in soft tissues and bone, causing fluctuations in blood Pb levels even years after initial exposure. Thus, BLL can still be a valuable indicator of chronic exposure in settings where workers have consistently been exposed to Pb over several years, highlighting the importance of regular monitoring even in long-term exposure scenarios (Dang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2024</xref>).</p><p id="Par51">On the other hand, the significant negative correlation between decreased serum levels of vitamin D and elevated blood lead levels (BLL) due to prolonged Pb exposure has been confirmed by multiple earlier studies (Batra et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2020</xref>; Himani et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2020</xref>; Mazumdar et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2017</xref>). The significant positive association between elevated serum CTX-1 levels and years of occupational Pb exposure, as well as the positive correlation between serum CTX-1 levels and blood Pb, supports the idea of increased bone resorption with prolonged Pb exposure. Similar findings were reported by Kalahasthi and colleagues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2021</xref>), although they used a different collagen degradation product, urinary hydroxyproline. The significant association between serum levels of vitamin D3 and CTX-1 may also be explained by an additional mechanism beyond their association with BLL. When there is a deficiency of vitamin D, the body absorbs less calcium and produces more parathyroid hormone (PTH), which increases bone resorption and CTX-1 levels (Sarkissian et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2019</xref>). The linear regression analysis highlighted the associations of BLL, serum vitamin D3 levels, and CTX-1 among the exposed smelter workers. However, the duration (years) of Pb exposure was found to be a statistically significant independent predictor for serum CTX-1 levels only.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Conclusions and recommendations</title><p id="Par52">The study&#x02019;s results suggest that high blood lead levels (BLLs) may have a significant impact on circulating vitamin D3 levels and bone resorption in workers occupationally exposed to Pb. The extrapolated data from this study could serve as a template to tailor guidelines for enhanced safety precautions and preventive actions aimed at improving working conditions and reducing worker exposure to Pb. The findings also emphasize the need for regular Pb exposure screening for employees. Those with BLLs exceeding the allowable limit should be informed about the harmful effects of Pb exposure and the importance of promptly implementing effective preventive measures. During routine physical examinations, serum levels of vitamin D3 and CTX-1 should be measured alongside BLL to detect any abnormalities. To maintain bone health and reduce musculoskeletal symptoms that may impair productivity, workers exposed to Pb should also consider taking supplements containing the active form of vitamin D.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors express their gratitude to all the studied groups who kindly consented to participate.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>This work was carried out in collaboration with both authors. Authors Mohammed RS and Mourad BH designed and performed the study. Author Mohammed RS designed the patient files. Authors Mohammed RS and Mourad BH managed the literature searches and wrote the first draft of the manuscript. Both authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>Open access funding provided by The Science, Technology &#x00026; Innovation Funding Authority (STDF) in cooperation with The Egyptian Knowledge Bank (EKB).</p><p>The authors obtained no financial support in relation to the research, writing, and publication of this work.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar2"><title>Disclaimer</title><p id="Par53">None.</p></notes><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p id="Par54">The authors have stated that they have no potential conflicts of interest with regard to the investigations, writing, or publication of this work.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akbal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tutkun</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Y&#x00131;lmaz</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lead exposure is a risk for worsening bone mineral density in middle-aged male workers</article-title><source>Aging Male</source><year>2014</year><volume>17</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>189</fpage><lpage>193</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24090225</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Akbal A, Tutkun E, Y&#x00131;lmaz H (2014) Lead exposure is a risk for worsening bone mineral density in middle-aged male workers. Aging Male 17(3):189&#x02013;193<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24090225</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Al-Rudainy</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Blood lead level among fuel station workers</article-title><source>Oman Med J</source><year>2010</year><volume>25</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>208</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22043339</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Al-Rudainy LA (2010) Blood lead level among fuel station workers. Oman Med J 25(3):208<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22043339</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Momeni</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name><surname>Obaid</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association between CTX-1 and Fibulin-1 serum levels with pathogenesis of multiple myeloma cancer</article-title><source>Asian Pac J Cancer Prev</source><year>2024</year><volume>25</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1599</fpage><lpage>1605</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38809631</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Ali AM, Momeni HR, Obaid HJ (2024) Association between CTX-1 and Fibulin-1 serum levels with pathogenesis of multiple myeloma cancer. Asian Pac J Cancer Prev 25(5):1599&#x02013;1605<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38809631</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aliasgharpour</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hagani</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of occupational lead exposure on industrial workers health condition in Tehran-Iran</article-title><source>East J Med</source><year>2005</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>23</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Aliasgharpour M, Hagani H (2005) Impact of occupational lead exposure on industrial workers health condition in Tehran-Iran. East J Med 10:20&#x02013;23</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alonso-P&#x000e9;rez</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez-P&#x000e9;rez</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Romero-Morales</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Abu&#x000ed;n-Porras</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x000f3;pez-Bueno</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossettini</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Relationship between serum vitamin D levels and Chronic Musculoskeletal Pain in adults: a systematic review</article-title><source>Nutrients</source><year>2024</year><volume>16</volume><issue>23</issue><fpage>4061</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39683456</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Alonso-P&#x000e9;rez JL, Mart&#x000ed;nez-P&#x000e9;rez I, Romero-Morales C, Abu&#x000ed;n-Porras V, L&#x000f3;pez-Bueno R, Rossettini G et al (2024) Relationship between serum vitamin D levels and Chronic Musculoskeletal Pain in adults: a systematic review. Nutrients 16(23):4061<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39683456</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>An</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sim</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The association between cadmium and lead exposure and blood pressure among workers of a smelting industry: a cross-sectional study</article-title><source>Ann Occup Environ Med</source><year>2017</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>47</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29034097</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">An HC, Sung JH, Lee J, Sim CS, Kim SH, Kim Y (2017) The association between cadmium and lead exposure and blood pressure among workers of a smelting industry: a cross-sectional study. Ann Occup Environ Med 29:47<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29034097</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Batra</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Thakur</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Meena</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Juyal</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Blood lead levels among the occupationally exposed workers and its effect on calcium and vitamin D metabolism: a case-control study</article-title><source>J Family Med Prim Care</source><year>2020</year><volume>9</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>2388</fpage><lpage>2393</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32754507</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Batra J, Thakur A, Meena SK, Singh L, Kumar J, Juyal D (2020) Blood lead levels among the occupationally exposed workers and its effect on calcium and vitamin D metabolism: a case-control study. J Family Med Prim Care 9(5):2388&#x02013;2393<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32754507</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brito</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name><surname>e Silva</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Marques</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zagalo</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cavaleiro</surname><given-names>II</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Changes in bone pb accumulation: cause and effect of altered bone turnover</article-title><source>Bone</source><year>2014</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>228</fpage><lpage>234</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24768754</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Brito JA, Costa IM, e Silva AM, Marques JM, Zagalo CM, Cavaleiro II et al (2014) Changes in bone pb accumulation: cause and effect of altered bone turnover. Bone 64:228&#x02013;234<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24768754</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carmouche</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Puzas</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Tiyapatanaputi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>CorySlechta</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gelein</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Lead exposure inhibits fracture healing and is associated with increased chondrogenesis, delay in cartilage mineralization, and a decrease in osteoprogenitor frequency</article-title><source>Environ Health Perspect</source><year>2005</year><volume>113</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>749</fpage><lpage>755</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15929899</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Carmouche JJ, Puzas JE, Zhang X, Tiyapatanaputi P, CorySlechta DA, Gelein R et al (2005) Lead exposure inhibits fracture healing and is associated with increased chondrogenesis, delay in cartilage mineralization, and a decrease in osteoprogenitor frequency. Environ Health Perspect 113(6):749&#x02013;755<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15929899</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) (2024b): CDC updates blood lead reference value. Atlanta: US Centers for Disease Control and Prevention; 2024. Available from:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/lead-prevention/php/news-features/updates-blood-lead-reference-value.html">https://www.cdc.gov/lead-prevention/php/news-features/updates-blood-lead-reference-value.html</ext-link> (Accessed January 25, 2024)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) (2024a): Preventing work-related lead exposure. CDC Workplace Safety and Health Topics. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/niosh/topics/lead/default.html&#x0200b;:contentReference%5Boaicite:0%5D">https://www.cdc.gov/niosh/topics/lead/default.html&#x0200b;:contentReference%5Boaicite:0%5D</ext-link>.(Accessed January 25, 2024).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biostatistics102: quantitative data&#x02013; Parametric &#x00026; non-parametric tests</article-title><source>Singap Med J</source><year>2003</year><volume>44</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>391</fpage><lpage>396</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Chan YH (2003a) Biostatistics102: quantitative data&#x02013; Parametric &#x00026; non-parametric tests. Singap Med J 44(8):391&#x02013;396</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biostatistics 103: qualitative data&#x02013;tests of independence</article-title><source>Singap Med J</source><year>2003</year><volume>44</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>498</fpage><lpage>503</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Chan YH (2003b) Biostatistics 103: qualitative data&#x02013;tests of independence. Singap Med J 44(10):498&#x02013;503</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biostatistics 104: Correlational Analysis</article-title><source>Singap Med J</source><year>2003</year><volume>44</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>614</fpage><lpage>619</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Chan YH (2003c) Biostatistics 104: Correlational Analysis. Singap Med J 44(12):614&#x02013;619</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biostatistics 201: Linear regression analysis</article-title><source>Singap Med J</source><year>2004</year><volume>45</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>61</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Chan YH (2004a) Biostatistics 201: Linear regression analysis. Singap Med J 45(2):55&#x02013;61</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biostatistics 202: logistic regression analysis</article-title><source>Singap Med J</source><year>2004</year><volume>45</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>153</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Chan YH (2004b) Biostatistics 202: logistic regression analysis. Singap Med J 45(4):149&#x02013;153</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chronic lead exposure and burden of cardiovascular disease during 1990&#x02013;2019: a systematic analysis of the global burden of disease study</article-title><source>Front Cardiovasc Med</source><year>2024</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1367681</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38655496</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Dang P, Tang M, Fan H, Hao J (2024) Chronic lead exposure and burden of cardiovascular disease during 1990&#x02013;2019: a systematic analysis of the global burden of disease study. Front Cardiovasc Med 11:1367681<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38655496</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dongre</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></name><name><surname>Suryakar</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Patil</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hundekari</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name><surname>Devarnavadagi</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biochemical effects of lead exposure on battery manufacture workers with reference to blood pressure, calcium metabolism and bone mineral density</article-title><source>Indian J Clin Biochem</source><year>2013</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24381424</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Dongre NN, Suryakar AN, Patil AJ, Hundekari IA, Devarnavadagi BB (2013) Biochemical effects of lead exposure on battery manufacture workers with reference to blood pressure, calcium metabolism and bone mineral density. Indian J Clin Biochem 28:65&#x02013;70<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24381424</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Egyptian Environmental Affairs Agency (EEAA) (1995) Prime Minister&#x02019;s Decree No. 338 of 1995. Promulgating the Executive Regulations of the Law for the Environment, Law No. 4 for 1994. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://faolex.fao.org/docs/pdf/egy4986E.pdf">https://faolex.fao.org/docs/pdf/egy4986E.pdf</ext-link> (Accessed January 25, 2024)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Himani, Kumar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ansari</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahdi</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Karunanand</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Blood lead levels in occupationally exposed workers involved in battery factories of Delhi-NCR Region: effect on vitamin D and calcium metabolism</article-title><source>Indian J Clin Biochem</source><year>2020</year><volume>35</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>80</fpage><lpage>87</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32071499</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">Himani, Kumar R, Ansari JA, Mahdi AA, Sharma D, Karunanand B et al (2020) Blood lead levels in occupationally exposed workers involved in battery factories of Delhi-NCR Region: effect on vitamin D and calcium metabolism. Indian J Clin Biochem 35(1):80&#x02013;87<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32071499</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kalahasthi R, Barman T, Rajmohan HR, Bagepally BS, Beerappa R (2016) Effectiveness of interventions on biological monitoring among workers exposed to pb from lead-acid storage battery plant. Int J Med Sci Public Health 5(9):(Online First).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kalahasthi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bagepally</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Barman</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association between Musculoskeletal Pain and bone turnover markers in long-term Pb-Exposed workers</article-title><source>J Res Health Sci</source><year>2021</year><volume>21</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>e00522</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34698656</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Kalahasthi R, Bagepally BS, Barman T (2021) Association between Musculoskeletal Pain and bone turnover markers in long-term Pb-Exposed workers. J Res Health Sci 21(3):e00522<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34698656</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mazumdar</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Goswami</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Status of serum calcium, vitamin D and parathyroid hormone and hematological indices among lead exposed jewelry workers in Dhaka, Bangladesh</article-title><source>Ind J Clin Biochem</source><year>2017</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>110</fpage><lpage>116</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Mazumdar I, Goswami K, Ali MS (2017) Status of serum calcium, vitamin D and parathyroid hormone and hematological indices among lead exposed jewelry workers in Dhaka, Bangladesh. Ind J Clin Biochem 32:110&#x02013;116</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mortada</surname><given-names>WI</given-names></name><name><surname>Sobh</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Defrawy</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Farahat</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Study of lead exposure from automobile exhaust as a risk for nephrotoxicity among traffic policemen</article-title><source>Am J Nephrol</source><year>2001</year><volume>21</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>274</fpage><lpage>279</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11509798</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">Mortada WI, Sobh MA, El-Defrawy MM, Farahat SE (2001) Study of lead exposure from automobile exhaust as a risk for nephrotoxicity among traffic policemen. Am J Nephrol 21(4):274&#x02013;279<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11509798</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mourad</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Sherif</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exploring the link between the serum/blood levels of heavy metals (pb, as, cd, and Cu) and 2 novel biomarkers of cardiovascular stress (growth differentiation factor 15 and Soluble Suppression of Tumorigenicity 2) in copper smelter workers</article-title><source>J Occup Environ Med</source><year>2022</year><volume>64</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>976</fpage><lpage>984</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35902369</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="journal">Mourad BH, El-Sherif GH (2022) Exploring the link between the serum/blood levels of heavy metals (pb, as, cd, and Cu) and 2 novel biomarkers of cardiovascular stress (growth differentiation factor 15 and Soluble Suppression of Tumorigenicity 2) in copper smelter workers. J Occup Environ Med 64(11):976&#x02013;984<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35902369</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR26"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR26" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olama</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>ElSaid</surname><given-names>TO</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Arman</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>C-telopeptide of type I collagen (CTX-1) in premenopausal Egyptian women with fibromyalgia syndrome</article-title><source>Egypt Rheumatol Rehabil</source><year>2015</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>80</fpage><lpage>86</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26" publication-type="journal">Olama SM, ElSaid TO, El-Arman MM (2015) C-telopeptide of type I collagen (CTX-1) in premenopausal Egyptian women with fibromyalgia syndrome. Egypt Rheumatol Rehabil 42:80&#x02013;86</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR27"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR27" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patrick</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lead toxicity, a review of the literature. Part 1: exposure, evaluation, and treatment</article-title><source>Altern Med Rev</source><year>2006</year><volume>11</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>2</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16597190</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27" publication-type="journal">Patrick L (2006) Lead toxicity, a review of the literature. Part 1: exposure, evaluation, and treatment. Altern Med Rev 11(1):2&#x02013;22<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16597190</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR28"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR28" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rahimpoor</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rostami</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Assari</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mirzaei</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zare</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of blood lead levels and their effects on hematological parameters and renal function in Iranian lead mine workers</article-title><source>Health Scope</source><year>2020</year><volume>9</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>e95917</fpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28" publication-type="journal">Rahimpoor R, Rostami M, Assari MJ, Mirzaei A, Zare MR (2020) Evaluation of blood lead levels and their effects on hematological parameters and renal function in Iranian lead mine workers. Health Scope 9(4):e95917</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR29"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR29" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ravibabu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bagepally</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Barman</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association of musculoskeletal disorders and inflammation markers in workers exposed to lead (pb) from Pb-battery manufacturing plant</article-title><source>Ind J Occup Environ Med</source><year>2019</year><volume>23</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>68</fpage><lpage>72</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29" publication-type="journal">Ravibabu K, Bagepally BS, Barman T (2019) Association of musculoskeletal disorders and inflammation markers in workers exposed to lead (pb) from Pb-battery manufacturing plant. Ind J Occup Environ Med 23(2):68&#x02013;72</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR30"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR30" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ravibabu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Barman</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Bagepally</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of bone turnover biomarkers in lead-battery workers with long-term exposure to lead</article-title><source>Int J Occup Med Environ Health</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>140</fpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30" publication-type="journal">Ravibabu K, Barman T, Bagepally BS (2020) Assessment of bone turnover biomarkers in lead-battery workers with long-term exposure to lead. Int J Occup Med Environ Health 11(3):140</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR31"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR31" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mandalunis</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A review of metal exposure and its effects on bone health</article-title><source>J Toxicol 2018 Article ID</source><year>2018</year><volume>4854152</volume><fpage>11</fpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR31" publication-type="journal">Rodr&#x000ed;guez J, Mandalunis PM (2018) A review of metal exposure and its effects on bone health. J Toxicol 2018 Article ID 4854152:11</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR32"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR32" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sarkissian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sivaraman</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Bout-Tabaku</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Bone turnover markers in relation to vitamin D status and disease activity in adults with systemic lupus erythematosus</article-title><source>Lupus</source><year>2019</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>156</fpage><lpage>162</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30509154</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32" publication-type="journal">Sarkissian A, Sivaraman V, Bout-Tabaku S et al (2019) Bone turnover markers in relation to vitamin D status and disease activity in adults with systemic lupus erythematosus. Lupus 28:156&#x02013;162<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30509154</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR33"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR33" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vilaca</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Gossiel</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Salam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Eastell</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bone turnover markers: basic biology to clinical applications</article-title><source>Endocr Rev</source><year>2023</year><volume>44</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>417</fpage><lpage>473</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36510335</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR33" publication-type="journal">Schini M, Vilaca T, Gossiel F, Salam S, Eastell R (2023) Bone turnover markers: basic biology to clinical applications. Endocr Rev 44(3):417&#x02013;473<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36510335</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR34"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR34" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schlesinger</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Blair</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Beer Stolz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Riazanski</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Tourkova</surname><given-names>IL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cellular and extracellular matrix of bone, with principles of synthesis and dependency of mineral deposition on cell membrane transport</article-title><source>Am J Physiol Cell Physiol</source><year>2020</year><volume>318</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>C111</fpage><lpage>C124</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31532718</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR34" publication-type="journal">Schlesinger PH, Blair HC, Beer Stolz D, Riazanski V, Ray EC, Tourkova IL et al (2020) Cellular and extracellular matrix of bone, with principles of synthesis and dependency of mineral deposition on cell membrane transport. Am J Physiol Cell Physiol 318(1):C111&#x02013;C124<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31532718</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR35"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR35" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharifi</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghazanfari</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Tekiyehmaroof</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharifi</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Investigating the effect of lead acetate on rat bone marrow-derived mesenchymal stem cells toxicity: role of apoptosis</article-title><source>Toxicol Mech Methods</source><year>2011</year><volume>21</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>230</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21244221</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR35" publication-type="journal">Sharifi AM, Ghazanfari R, Tekiyehmaroof N, Sharifi MA (2011) Investigating the effect of lead acetate on rat bone marrow-derived mesenchymal stem cells toxicity: role of apoptosis. Toxicol Mech Methods 21(3):225&#x02013;230<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21244221</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR36"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">World Health Organization (2021): WHO guidance to reduce illness due to lead exposure. Geneva, Switzerland. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/news/item/27-10-2021-who-guidance-to-reduce-illness-due-to-lead-exposure">https://www.who.int/news/item/27-10-2021-who-guidance-to-reduce-illness-due-to-lead-exposure</ext-link>. (Accessed January 25, 2024)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR37" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yadav</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Jha</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of vitamin D supplementation on bone metabolic markers in chronic kidney disease</article-title><source>J Bone Min Res</source><year>2018</year><volume>33</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>404</fpage><lpage>409</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR37" publication-type="journal">Yadav AK, Kumar V, Kumar V, Banerjee D, Gupta KL, Jha V (2018) The effect of vitamin D supplementation on bone metabolic markers in chronic kidney disease. J Bone Min Res 33(3):404&#x02013;409</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR38"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR38" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ying</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Biomarkers for prostate cancer bone metastasis detection and prediction</article-title><source>J Pers Med</source><year>2023</year><volume>13</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>705</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37240875</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR38" publication-type="journal">Ying M, Mao J, Sheng L, Wu H, Bai G, Zhong Z et al (2023) Biomarkers for prostate cancer bone metastasis detection and prediction. J Pers Med 13(5):705<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37240875</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR39"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR39" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zadro</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Shirley</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Carvalho-Silva</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamb</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mapping the association between vitamin D and low back pain: a systematic review and meta-analysis of observational studies</article-title><source>Pain Physician</source><year>2017</year><volume>20</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>611</fpage><lpage>640</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29149142</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR39" publication-type="journal">Zadro J, Shirley D, Ferreira M, Carvalho-Silva AP, Lamb SE, Cooper C et al (2017) Mapping the association between vitamin D and low back pain: a systematic review and meta-analysis of observational studies. Pain Physician 20(7):611&#x02013;640<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29149142</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR40"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR40" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Vitamin D is associated with blood lead exposure through bone turnover in type 2 diabetes patients</article-title><source>Endocr Connect</source><year>2021</year><volume>10</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>378</fpage><lpage>386</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33666568</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR40" publication-type="journal">Zhang H, Cui Y, Dong R, Zhang W, Chen S, Wan H et al (2021) Vitamin D is associated with blood lead exposure through bone turnover in type 2 diabetes patients. Endocr Connect 10(4):378&#x02013;386<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33666568</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR41"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR41" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Emission characteristics of heavy metals from a typical copper smelting plant</article-title><source>J Hazard Mater</source><year>2022</year><volume>424</volume><fpage>127311</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34600390</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR41" publication-type="journal">Zhang J, Sun X, Deng J, Li G, Li Z, Jiang J et al (2022) Emission characteristics of heavy metals from a typical copper smelting plant. J Hazard Mater 424:127311<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34600390</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article>