<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PeerJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PeerJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PeerJ</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PeerJ</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2167-8359</issn><publisher><publisher-name>PeerJ Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Diego, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12101439</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">19372</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19372</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Microbiology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Mycology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Drugs and Devices</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Epidemiology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Pathology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Antifungal activity and mechanism of novel peptide <italic toggle="yes">Glycine max</italic> antimicrobial peptide (GmAMP) against fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Candida tropicalis</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="author-1" contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Ruxia</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-2" contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Na</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Chaoqin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Mingjiao</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff-3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-5" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jiao</surname><given-names>Zhenlong</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff-3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-6" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>Jian</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-7" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Jin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-8" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Guo</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><email>guoguojsc@163.com</email></contrib><aff id="aff-1">
<label>1</label><institution>School of Basic Medical Sciences, Guizhou Key Laboratory of Microbial and Infectious Disease Prevention &#x00026; Control, Guizhou Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Guiyang, Guizhou</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff-2">
<label>2</label><institution>Key Laboratory of Environmental Pollution Monitoring and Disease Control (Guizhou Medical University), Ministry of Education</institution>, <addr-line>Guiyang, Guizhou</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff-3">
<label>3</label><institution>Translational Medicine Research Center, Guizhou Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Guiyang, Guizhou</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff-4">
<label>4</label><institution>School of Public Health, Guizhou Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Guiyang, Guizhou</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>Nancy</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>5</month><year iso-8601-date="2025">2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>13</volume><elocation-id>e19372</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="2024-11-18"><day>18</day><month>11</month><year iso-8601-date="2024">2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="2025-04-04"><day>4</day><month>4</month><year iso-8601-date="2025">2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2025 Cai et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Cai et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, reproduction and adaptation in any medium and for any purpose provided that it is properly attributed. For attribution, the original author(s), title, publication source (PeerJ) and either DOI or URL of the article must be cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/19372"/><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>There is a pressing need to create innovative alternative treatment approaches considering the overuse of antifungal drugs causes the number of clinically isolated fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Candida</italic> species to increase. <italic toggle="yes">Glycine max</italic> antimicrobial peptide (GmAMP) is a novel peptide screened by us using artificial intelligence modeling techniques, and pre-tests showed its strong antimicrobial activity against clinically fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Candida tropicalis</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>The study aimed to comprehensively investigate the antimicrobial activity and mechanisms of GmAMP against fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic>. The antifungal activity of GmAMP against fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> was assessed by using broth microdilution method, growth and fungicidal kinetics, hypha transformation, and antibiofilm assay. To further uncover the potential mechanisms of action of GmAMP, we performed scanning electron microscopy, flow cytometry, cell membrane potential probe 3, 3&#x02032;-Dipropylthiadicarbocyanine Iodide (DiSC<sub>3</sub>(5)), and reactive oxygen species (ROS) probe 2&#x02032;, 7&#x02032;-Dichlorodihydrofluorescein diacetate (DCFH-DA) detection to assess the cellular morphology and structure, membrane permeability, membrane depolarization, and ROS accumulation, respectively. At the same time, we used cytotoxicity and degree of erythrocyte hemolysis assays to assess GmAMP&#x02019;s toxicity <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>. Cytotoxicity and treatment efficacy were evaluated <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> by utilizing the <italic toggle="yes">Galleria mellonella</italic> larvae infection model.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>GmAMP exhibited significant antifungal activity against fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> with a minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) of 25 &#x000b5;M and demonstrated fungicidal effects at 100 &#x000b5;M within 2 h. GmAMP prevented the transition from yeast to hypha morphology, inhibited the biofilm formation rate of 88.32%, and eradicated the mature biofilm rate of 58.28%. Additionally, GmAMP treatment at 100 &#x000b5;M caused cell structure damage in fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic>, whereas GmAMP treatment at concentrations ranging from 25 to 100 &#x000b5;M caused membrane permeability, depolarization of cell membrane potential, and intracellular ROS accumulation. Moreover, GmAMP enhanced the survival rate of 75% for <italic toggle="yes">G. mellonella</italic> with fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> infection as well as reduced fungal burden <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> by approximately 1.0 &#x000d7; 10<sup>2</sup> colony forming units per larva (CFU per larva).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>GmAMP can disrupt the cell membrane of fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> and also shows favorable safety and therapeutic efficacy <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>. Accordingly, GmAMP has the potential to be an agent against drug-resistant fungi.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>Antimicrobial peptide</kwd><kwd>GmAMP</kwd><kwd>Drug-resistance</kwd><kwd>Antifungal activity</kwd><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Candida tropicalis</italic></kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="fund-1"><funding-source>National Natural Science Foundation of China</funding-source><award-id>81760647 and 82360700</award-id></award-group><award-group id="fund-2"><funding-source>Science and Technology Planning Project of Guizhou Province</funding-source><award-id>ZK[2022]345</award-id></award-group><award-group id="fund-3"><funding-source>Excellent Young Talents Plan of Guizhou Medical University</funding-source><award-id>[2021]104</award-id></award-group><award-group id="fund-4"><funding-source>Guizhou Key Laboratory</funding-source><award-id>ZDSYS[2023]004</award-id></award-group><funding-statement>This research received funding from the National Natural Science Foundation of China (No. 81760647, 82360700), Science and Technology Planning Project of Guizhou Province (ZK[2022] general project 345), Excellent Young Talents Plan of Guizhou Medical University (No. [2021]104) and Guizhou Key Laboratory (ZDSYS[2023]004). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Opportunistic fungal pathogens can cause cutaneous infections and invasive infections, posing a significantly higher risk of morbidity and mortality in immunocompromised patients (<xref rid="ref-35" ref-type="bibr">Pathakumari, Liang &#x00026; Liu, 2020</xref>). Among these pathogens, invasive candidiasis emerges as a prominent concern, characterized by mortality rates of approximately 25% (<xref rid="ref-38" ref-type="bibr">Pfaller &#x00026; Diekema, 2007</xref>; <xref rid="ref-40" ref-type="bibr">Sasani et al., 2021</xref>). Despite being a component of human microbiomes, <italic toggle="yes">Candida tropicalis</italic> is considered to be the second to fourth most virulent genus of <italic toggle="yes">Candida</italic> species and may result in invasive infections (<xref rid="ref-54" ref-type="bibr">Zuza-Alves, Silva-Rocha &#x00026; Chaves, 2017</xref>). Azole antifungal agents, including fluconazole, itraconazole, voriconazole, posaconazole, and others, constitute the primary therapeutic resources against <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> infection. However, the indiscriminate and excessive use of azoles has engendered the emergence of azole-resistant strains of <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> from clinical isolates. In addition, compared to other <italic toggle="yes">Candida</italic> species, <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> showed a greater rate of fluconazole resistance, according to epidemiologic research (<xref rid="ref-44" ref-type="bibr">Tseng et al., 2022</xref>). Consequently, the significant prevalence of azole resistance in clinical isolates of <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> has drawn more attention to invasive infection (<xref rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr">Fan et al., 2023</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> was included as a high-priority pathogen in the World Health Organization&#x02019;s (WHO) first list of fungal priority pathogens in 2022, which was intended to create a strategic framework for research, development, and public health interventions (<xref rid="ref-17" ref-type="bibr">Fisher &#x00026; Denning, 2023</xref>; <xref rid="ref-47" ref-type="bibr">World Health Organization (WHO) ARDA, Control of Neglected Tropical Diseases (NTD) &#x00026; Global Coordination and Partnership (GCP), 2022</xref>).</p><p>It is widely recognized that azoles, fluconazole in particular, are crucial are essential preventive and therapeutic medicines for the management of <italic toggle="yes">Candida</italic> infections. Despite the widespread and regular use of fluconazole, resistance is increasing, which has caused the emergence of cross-resistance to other antifungal medications (<xref rid="ref-18" ref-type="bibr">Forastiero et al., 2013</xref>). Studies have shown that resistance rates of <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> to azoles such as fluconazole, itraconazole, voriconazole, and posaconazole have recorded resistance rates as high as 40% to 80% (<xref rid="ref-47" ref-type="bibr">World Health Organization (WHO) ARDA, Control of Neglected Tropical Diseases (NTD) &#x00026; Global Coordination and Partnership (GCP), 2022</xref>). Furthermore, more than 21% of <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> isolates in China are resistant to fluconazole and even 21.7% of <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> isolates were resistant to 2&#x02013;4 azoles in Iran (<xref rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr">Badiee et al., 2022</xref>; <xref rid="ref-31" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2022</xref>). A number of mechanisms, such as changes in drug targets, elevation of drug target expression, and increased expression of efflux pumps, may be responsible for the resistance phenomena (<xref rid="ref-29" ref-type="bibr">Lee et al., 2021</xref>). As a result, antifungal drug therapies may be inefficient in treating drug-resistant candidiasis, which poses significant challenges in clinical management (<xref rid="ref-33" ref-type="bibr">McCarthy &#x00026; Walsh, 2017</xref>; <xref rid="ref-50" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2017</xref>). In order to address the current issue of fungal drug resistance, it is imperative to utilize both novel and promising antifungal medicines as well as alternative treatment techniques.</p><p>Antimicrobial peptides (AMPs) represent critical components of the immune defense system in organisms, with broad-spectrum antimicrobial activity, low drug resistance, and diverse bactericidal mechanisms (<xref rid="ref-30" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2020</xref>). Antimicrobial peptides can destroy multiple targets of pathogens through membrane and non-membrane interactions, which differs from the single target bactericidal principle of conventional antibiotics. The membrane destructive effect is primarily exerted through three mechanisms: barrel-stave, toroidal or carpet, these unique mechanism makes it not easily susceptible to the development of resistance (<xref rid="ref-19" ref-type="bibr">Gan et al., 2021</xref>). We have previously reported that we employed multitasking adaptive modeling and model adaptation to establish a prediction model and screening protocol for antifungal peptides based on antimicrobial peptide databases such as APD, DRAMP, CAMP, antifp, <italic toggle="yes">etc</italic>. (<xref rid="ref-49" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2022</xref>). Then we predicted more than three million unknown functional sequences in the UniProt database from the established model and screened out several hundreds of peptides that might be antifungally active then synthesized them by solid-phase organic synthesis method, and the antimicrobial activity was verified by wet lab experiments. The novel antimicrobial peptide SPGKKKKKKKKKKKTKKKKKK showed strong antimicrobial activity against fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> in the pre-test, with a minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) of 25 &#x000b5;M (MIC of fluconazole against this isolate &#x0003e;3,343 &#x000b5;M).</p><p>According to the sequence homology nomenclature in the antimicrobial peptide APD3 database (<uri xlink:href="http://aps.unmc.edu/AP/">http://aps.unmc.edu/AP/</uri>), the <italic toggle="yes">Glycine max</italic> antimicrobial novel peptide was named GmAMP. In this report, to more fully assess GmAMP, we first determined the MIC of GmAMP against four strains of clinically fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> and the standard strain of <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> ATCC 20962, for which GmAMP showed excellent antimicrobial activity. Besides, to assess the antifungal activity and mechanism of GmAMP, we performed experimental validation on fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic>. As a result, the antifungal mechanism of GmAMP against fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> was investigated in terms of physicochemistry and morphology, and its <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> efficacy was evaluated by the <italic toggle="yes">G. mellonella</italic> larvae infection model. Thus, the findings of this study provide a certain experimental foundation for the exploration and utilization of novel peptide antimicrobial drugs.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec sec-type="materials"><title>Materials</title><p>The peptide GmAMP (SPGKKKKKKKKKKKTKKKKKK) was synthesized by solid phase chemical synthesis method by Gil Biochemical Co., Ltd (Shanghai, China), purified by reversed-phase high-performance liquid chromatography (RP-HPLC) (<xref rid="supp-1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig. S1A</xref>), and the purity was &#x0003e;95%. They were dissolved in deionized water at a stock concentration of 5 mg/mL before use. The molecular weight of GmAMP was determined using electrospray ionization (ESI) mass spectrometer (ESI MS) (<xref rid="supp-1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig. S1B</xref>). We used the online website Heliquest software (<uri xlink:href="https://heliquest.ipmc.cnrs.fr/index.html">https://heliquest.ipmc.cnrs.fr/index.html</uri>) to predict the helix diagram and hydrophilicity, and AlphFold2 to predict the 3D structure of peptides. The molecular weight of the peptide was predicted by Expasy ProtParam (<uri xlink:href="https://web.expasy.org/protparam/">https://web.expasy.org/protparam/</uri>).</p></sec><sec><title>Strains and cell culture conditions</title><p>The fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> 4171, 4252, 6984, and 8402 were collected from infected patient&#x02019;s blood in the affiliated hospital of Guizhou Medical University. <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> ATCC 20962 was purchased from the Shanghai Conservation Biotechnology Center. All strains were grown in yeast extract peptone dextrose medium (YPD, Solarbio, Beijing, China) at 35 &#x000b0;C with shaking at 200 rpm until the cultures reached the logarithmic phase. RPMI-1640 (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA) supplemented with 15% fetal bovine serum (FBS) (Sigma-Aldrich) was used as the culture medium for hypha growth of <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic>. The mouse monocyte-macrophage cell line RAW 264.7 was donated by Jiahong Wu from the Key and Characteristic Laboratory of Modern Pathogen Biology, Guizhou Medical University, and cells were cultured in DMEM medium (Gibco, Waltham, MA, USA) containing 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS, Gibco), 100 U/mL penicillin (Gibco, Waltham, MA, USA), and 100 &#x000b5;g/mL streptomycin (Gibco, Waltham, MA, USA) and maintained at 37 &#x000b0;C in a humidified 5% CO<sub>2</sub> incubator.</p></sec><sec><title>Antifungal activity</title><p>The minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) of GmAMP for four fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> from clinical isolates, and a standard strain of <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> ATCC 20962 was determined by using broth microdilution method according to the Standards of Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute (CLSI) (<xref rid="ref-8" ref-type="bibr">Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute (CLSI), 2023</xref>). In brief, these yeasts of fungal strains were cultured in YPD broth medium at 35 &#x000b0;C to the logarithmic growth stage, and the cultures were washed by phosphate-buffered saline (PBS, 10 mM, pH 7.4) three times and resuspended to 0.5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>3</sup>~2.5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>3</sup> CFU/mL, then 100 &#x000b5;L above fungal suspension was added to a 96-well plate with a series concentration of GmAMP (100, 50, 25, 12, 6, 3 &#x000b5;M) or fluconazole (3,343 &#x000b5;M to 3 &#x000b5;M) (Yuan Ye, Shanghai, China) and 10 mM PBS and medium were used as the negative and blank controls, respectively. After co-incubation at 35 &#x000b0;C for 24 h, The drug concentration corresponding to the well without visible fungal growth was regarded as MIC, corresponding to 90% inhibition of fungal growth. The experiment was performed in triplicate and repeated three times.</p></sec><sec><title>Growth and fungicidal kinetics</title><p>To analyze the antifungal or fungicidal process of GmAMP against fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic>, the growth kinetics and time-kill kinetics of GmAMP on fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> were further investigated at different times after GmAMP treatment as to previously described (<xref rid="ref-39" ref-type="bibr">Ramesh et al., 2023</xref>). The concentration of the prepared fungal cells was 1.0 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup> CFU/mL according to the previously mentioned method and incubated with 25, 50, and 100 &#x000b5;M of GmAMP at 35 &#x000b0;C for 48 h. A microplate reader (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA) was used to record the OD<sub>630nm</sub> every 2 h during co-cultivation. In the meantime, the cultivated yeasts were harvested at certain intervals (0, 2, 4, 6, 8, 10, and 12 h), and the agar solid plate experiment was conducted following gradient dilution. The negative and blank controls in the experiment were 10 mM PBS and medium. Fungal colonies were counted after incubation at 35 &#x000b0;C for 24 h. The results were presented as the average of triplicate measurements from three independent assays.</p></sec><sec><title>Effect of GmAMP on hypha formation</title><p>To analyze the effect of GmAMP on the transition of yeast-to-hyphal phase in fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> as described previously (<xref rid="ref-23" ref-type="bibr">Jiang et al., 2016</xref>). The concentration of the prepared fungal cells was 1.0 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup> CFU/mL in RPMI 1640 medium (Gibco, Waltham, MA, USA) which contained 15% fetal bovine serum (Gibco, Waltham, MA, USA) according to the previously mentioned method. A total of 500 &#x000b5;L of fungal suspension was incubated with GmAMP at concentrations (25, 50, and 100 &#x000b5;M) in 24 well plates and 10 mM PBS as the negative control. Cells were co-incubated with peptides for 3, 6, 9, 12, and 24 h at 37 &#x000b0;C, then the hypha formation was observed and photographed under an inverted microscope.</p></sec><sec><title>Antibiofilm assay</title><p>Fungal cells grown to the logarithmic phase were adjusted to 1.0 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup> CFU/mL with RPMI-1640 liquid medium and added to 96-well polypropylene plates, which were then incubated at 37 &#x000b0;C for 90 min (biofilm formation assay) or 48 h (biofilm eradication assay) according to previous method (<xref rid="ref-53" ref-type="bibr">Zou et al., 2024</xref>). And 100 &#x000b5;L newly prepared 2, 3-bis(2-methoxy-4-nitro-5-sulfophenyl) 2H-tetrazolium5-carboxamide sodium salt (XTT) solution (Yuan Ye, Shanghai, China) was added to each well for 2 h at 37 &#x000b0;C after different concentrations of GmAMP were added and continued to co-incubate for 24 h. A microplate reader set to OD<sub>490nm</sub> was used to measure absorbance.</p><p>Sterile polylysine cell crawls were then placed on the bottom of a 24-well plate and 500 &#x000b5;L of the fungal suspension at the above concentration was added. The biofilm formation and mature biofilm were prepared according to the above method, and 500 &#x000b5;L of SYTO 9 (Invitrogen, Waltham, MA, USA) and propidium iodide (PI; Sigma) solution with the final concentration of 10 &#x000b5;M were added and incubated for 20 min while 10 mM PBS was used as the negative control. Seal the cover glass with nail polish, laser confocal microscopy (Olympus SpinSR10; Olympus, Tokyo, Japan) was used to observe and obtain images.</p></sec><sec><title>Scanning electron microscope</title><p>The concentration of the prepared fungal cells was 1.0 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup> CFU/mL based on the previous description with minor modifications (<xref rid="ref-2" ref-type="bibr">Alfaro-Vargas et al., 2022</xref>), incubated in GmAMP with culture medium at 35 &#x000b0;C for 2 h, and 10 mM PBS was used as a negative control, then the suspension was centrifuged at 5,000 rpm for 10 min, fixed with 2.5% glutaraldehyde overnight at 4 &#x000b0;C, and dehydrated with 50%, 75%, 95% and 100% series of ethanol solutions for 10 min. It was then dried in a vacuum evaporator and coated with a thin layer of gold-palladium. The samples were observed by scanning electron microscopy and the image acquisition was performed using a Hitachi Regulus SU8100 (Tokyo, Japan).</p></sec><sec><title>Flow cytometry analysis</title><p>The concentration of the prepared fungal cells was 1.0 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup> CFU/mL according to the previous description with minor modifications (<xref rid="ref-43" ref-type="bibr">Torres et al., 2023</xref>), the GmAMP with different concentrations was incubated at 35 &#x000b0;C for 1 h, and 10 mM PBS was used as the negative control. After that, the fungal suspension was incubated with SYTO 9 and PI staining with a final concentration of 10 &#x000b5;M at 35 &#x000b0;C for 15 min, and the stained cells were analyzed by flow cytometry.</p></sec><sec><title>Membrane potential</title><p>The concentration of the prepared fungal cells was 1.0 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup> CFU/mL as described in the previous study (<xref rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr">Decker et al., 2024</xref>), then added to 96-well plates while the membrane potential DiSC<sub>3</sub>(5) probe was added into the fungal suspension. The fungal suspension was then treated with different concentrations of GmAMP, and 10 mM PBS was used as the negative control for measured fluorescence intensity. The change of fluorescence intensity in 1 h was continuously and dynamically monitored with by RF-5301PC sectrofluoro-photometer (Bio-Tek Synergy HTX, Winooski, Vermont, USA).</p></sec><sec><title>Reactive oxygen species level</title><p>The levels of ROS were determined by using 2&#x02032;, 7&#x02032;-dichlorodihydrofluorescein diacetate (DCFH-DA; Yuan Ye, Shanghai, China) according to previously described methods (<xref rid="ref-41" ref-type="bibr">Shaban, Patel &#x00026; Ahmad, 2024</xref>). The 1.0 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup> CFU/mL of fungal suspension was added to 96-well plates while the Reactive Oxygen DCFH-DA probe (10 &#x000b5;M) was added into the fungal suspension. The fungal suspension was then treated with different concentrations of GmAMP. 10 mM PBS and 10 &#x000b5;M NAC (N-Acetylcysteine) were used as the negative and positive control. The change of fluorescence intensity in 1 h was continuously and dynamically monitored by RF-5301PC sectrofluoro-photometer (Bio-Tek Synergy HTX, Winooski, VT, USA).</p></sec><sec><title>Cytotoxicity Assays</title><p>Mouse RAW 264.7 cells were used to evaluate the cytotoxicity of GmAMP on mammalian cells as previously described (<xref rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr">de Oliveira et al., 2023</xref>). Cells were cultured in Dulbecco&#x02019;s Modified Eagle Medium (DMEM, Gibco, Grand Island, NY, USA) containing 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS; Gibco, Waltham, MA, USA), 1% penicillin-streptomycin (Gibco, Waltham, MA, USA), and maintained at 37 &#x000b0;C in a humidified 5% CO<sub>2</sub> incubator. Firstly, 100 &#x000b5;L of RAW 264.7 cells suspension (2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>4</sup> cells/mL) was added to 96-well plates for cultivating overnight. A total of 100 &#x000b5;L with different concentrations of GmAMP solution was added and then incubated at 37 &#x000b0;C for 24 h. 10 mM PBS and complete medium were used as the negative and blank controls, respectively. When the incubation period was over, 10 &#x000b5;L of CCK8 solution was added to each assay well following the manufacturer&#x02019;s protocols (MedChemExpress, Monmouth Junction, NJ, USA) and incubated for 1 h. Absorbance values were detected at OD<sub>450nm,</sub> and the percentage of cell survival was counted.</p><p>
<disp-formula id="ueqn-1">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-13-19372-e001.jpg" position="float"/><tex-math id="tex-ueqn-1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
${\mathrm{Cell}}\;{\mathrm{viability}}(\% ){\mathrm{ =  }}\left( {{{{\mathrm{Ab}}{{\mathrm{s}}_{{\mathrm{450nm}}}}{\mathrm{of}}\;{\mathrm{GmAMP}}\;{\mathrm{solution - Ab}}{{\mathrm{s}}_{{\mathrm{450nm}}}}{\mathrm{of}}\;{\mathrm{blank}}\;{\mathrm{control}}} \over {{\mathrm{Ab}}{{\mathrm{s}}_{{\mathrm{450nm}}}}{\mathrm{of}}\;{\mathrm{PBS}}\;{\mathrm{control - Ab}}{{\mathrm{s}}_{{\mathrm{450nm}}}}{\mathrm{of}}\;{\mathrm{blank}}\;{\mathrm{control}}}}} \right) \times {\mathrm{100}}\% .$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="mml-ueqn-1" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0"><mml:mspace width="0.278em"/></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">v</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">%</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">A</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>450</mml:mn><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0"><mml:mspace width="0.278em"/></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">G</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">A</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">M</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0"><mml:mspace width="0.278em"/></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">u</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">A</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>450</mml:mn><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0"><mml:mspace width="0.278em"/></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0"><mml:mspace width="0.278em"/></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">A</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>450</mml:mn><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0"><mml:mspace width="0.278em"/></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">B</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">S</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0"><mml:mspace width="0.278em"/></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">A</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>450</mml:mn><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0"><mml:mspace width="0.278em"/></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0"><mml:mspace width="0.278em"/></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">%</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math></alternatives></disp-formula>
</p></sec><sec><title>Hemolysis of human red blood cells</title><p>The human red blood cells (hRBCs) were used to evaluate the hemolytic activity of GmAMP based on previous descriptions with minor modifications (<xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr">Larr&#x000e1;n et al., 2022</xref>). The GmAMP with different concentrations and 2% hRBCs were added to the 96-well plate and incubated for 1 h in 37 &#x000b0;C. 1% Triton X-100 (Solarbio, Beijing, China) was the positive control, and 10 mM PBS was used as the negative control. When the incubation period was over, as the samples were gathered and centrifuged for 10 min at 1,000 rpm, the supernatant was moved to a fresh 96-well plate, and the OD<sub>540nm</sub> absorbance value was used to determine the extent of hemolysis. The hemolysis test of the new peptide has been approved by Ethics Committee of GuiZhou Medical University, approval number: 2022 Ethical Approval (302).</p><p>
<disp-formula id="ueqn-2">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-13-19372-e002.jpg" position="float"/><tex-math id="tex-ueqn-2">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
${\rm Hemolysis(\% ) =} \left(\displaystyle{{{\rm Ab}{{\rm s}_{540{\rm nm}}}{\rm \; of\; GmAMP\; solution} - {\rm Ab}{{\rm s}_{540{\rm nm}}}{\rm \; of\; PBS\; control}} \over {{\rm Ab}{{\rm s}_{540{\rm nm\; }}}{\rm of\; }\left( {{\rm TritonX} - 100} \right) - {\rm Ab}{{\rm s}_{540{\rm nm}}}{\rm \; of\; PBS\; control}}}\right) \times 100{\rm \% }.$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="mml-ueqn-2" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">H</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">y</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">%</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">A</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>540</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="thickmathspace"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="thickmathspace"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">G</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">A</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">M</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="thickmathspace"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">u</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">A</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>540</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="thickmathspace"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="thickmathspace"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">B</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">S</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="thickmathspace"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">A</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>540</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="thickmathspace"/></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="thickmathspace"/></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">T</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">A</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>540</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="thickmathspace"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="thickmathspace"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">B</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">S</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="thickmathspace"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">%</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math></alternatives></disp-formula>
</p></sec><sec><title><italic toggle="yes">Galleria mellonella</italic> infection model</title><p>The larvae used in the experiment were purchased from Huiyude Biotechnology Co., Ltd., (Tianjin, China), each weighing 250~300 mg and about 2~3 cm in length. As previously described with slight modifications (<xref rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr">Fernandes, Weeks &#x00026; Carter, 2020</xref>). All larvae were placed in a dark incubator at 35 &#x000b0;C overnight before the experiment. Ten larvae were randomly divided into each group to inject 10 &#x000b5;L of GmAMP solution with a concentration of 8~32 mg/kg into the last left proleg of larvae to evaluate the toxicity of GmAMP. The negative control was given an equal volume of sterile PBS. In order to assess the effectiveness of GmAMP, 12 larvae were randomly assigned to each group, and 10 &#x000b5;L of a fungal suspension containing roughly 5.0 &#x000d7; 10<sup>8</sup> CFU/mL was injected into the final left proleg of the larvae. After 1 h in the incubator, the same volume of GmAMP was injected into the last right proleg using the same method. Live and dead counts were taken every 24 h during the five days of incubation at 35 &#x000b0;C. Larvae were deemed dead when they went dark or mushy and had no discernible tactile reaction. Three larvae per group were chosen at random and placed into 1.5 mL of sterile PBS solution for high-speed homogenization and grinding after 24 h following GmAMP injection. The 10 &#x000b5;L gradient dilution was dropped onto a sterile solid YPD plate and incubated for 24 h. The number of fungal single colony was recorded, and the <italic toggle="yes">C. tropical</italic> burden of each larva was counted.</p></sec><sec><title>Data processing</title><p>Statistical mapping and data analysis were performed using GraphPad Prism 8.0 software (GraphPad Software). Data were expressed as mean &#x000b1; SD and analyzed by one-way ANOVA. Long-rank test was used for the analysis of Mantel-Cox survival curves for the <italic toggle="yes">G. mellonella</italic> survival experiment. <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>GmAMP chemical characteristics</title><p>The antibacterial activity of antimicrobial peptides is significantly influenced by their secondary structure. The antimicrobial peptide&#x02019;s interaction with the cell membrane is facilitated by the alpha-helical structure, which increases the antibacterial activity. (<xref rid="ref-37" ref-type="bibr">Personne et al., 2023</xref>). The antimicrobial peptide GmAMP, composed of 21 amino acids, is predicted to have an &#x003b1;-helical structure (<xref rid="fig-1" ref-type="fig">Figs. 1A</xref> and <xref rid="fig-1" ref-type="fig">1B</xref>). The molecular weight (MW) of GmAMP was confirmed to be 2,539.35 Da by mass spectrometry. Furthermore, GmAMP has a net charge of +17 and a hydrophobicity value of &#x02212;0.757 (<xref rid="fig-1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1C</xref>), these characteristics imply that GmAMP is a cationic hydrophilic peptide.</p><fig position="float" id="fig-1"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19372/fig-1</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Physicochemical properties of GmAMP.</title><p>(A) Helical wheel analysis of GmAMP. Positively charged amino acids are indicated in blue, the red &#x02018;N&#x02019; represents the starting position and the arrow represents the hydrophobic moment. (B) Predicted three-dimensonal spatial structures of GmAMP. (C) The physical and chemical properties of GmAMP.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-13-19372-g001" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Antifungal activity</title><p>The results of the antifungal activity assay showed that GmAMP had strong antimicrobial effects against clinical fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic>, with MICs ranging from 25 to 50 &#x000b5;M (<xref rid="table-1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). In comparison to this, the MIC values of fluconazole against <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> ATCC 20962 was 13.06 &#x000b5;M (4 &#x000b5;g/mL), which was consistent with the Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute standard (CLSI). The MIC values of fluconazole against clinical isolates exceeded 3,343 &#x000b5;M. Consequently, to gain a more comprehensive understanding of the impact of GmAMP on fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Candida tropicalis</italic> clinical isolate, the 4252 isolate (MIC = 25 &#x000b5;M) was selected for further investigation.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="table-1"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19372/table-1</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Antifungal activity of GmAMP.</title><p>Determination of antifungal activity of GmAMP against five strains of <italic toggle="yes">Candida tropicalis</italic>.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-13-19372-g007" position="float"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" content-type="text"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Strains</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">MIC (&#x000b5;M)</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GmAMP</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fluconazole</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> 4252</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;3,343</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> 4171</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;3,343</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> 6984</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;3,343</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> 8402</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;3,343</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> ATCC 20962</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Growth kinetics and fungicidal kinetics</title><p>To elucidate the effect of GmAMP on the growth process of fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic>, the growth curve of fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> under GmAMP treatment was further plotted, as shown in <xref rid="fig-2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2A</xref>, the fungal cells in the control group entered the logarithmic phase within 6 h and reached the stationary phase within 18 h. In comparison, GmAMP treatments at concentrations of 25 and 50 &#x000b5;M were found to slow down the proliferation rate of fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> and prolong the time to reach the logarithmic phase. When treated with GmAMP at a concentration of 100 &#x000b5;M, GmAMP showed an inhibitory effect on fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> and prevented the natural growth and reproduction of fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic>. The time-fungicidal kinetic curve was further plotted to clarify the fungicidal effect of GmAMP (<xref rid="fig-2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2B</xref>). Compared with the control group, GmAMP exhibited a powerful inhibitory effect on fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> when the concentrations of GmAMP were 25 and 50 &#x000b5;M. Notably, dealing with the concentration at 100 &#x000b5;M of GmAMP, the fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> was killed within 2 h. These results indicate that GmAMP manifests effective antimicrobial activity and fungicidal effect against fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic>. Low-concentration GmAMP exerts an inhibitory effect on the growth of drug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Candida tropicalis</italic>, whereas high-concentration high GmAMP directly kills Candida cells.</p><fig position="float" id="fig-2"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19372/fig-2</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Effect of GmAMP on the growth of fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic>.</title><p>(A) Growth kinetics of fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic>. (B) Time-killing kinetics of fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic>. (C) The transformation from yeast phase to mycelial phase of fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic>. Scale bar, 25 &#x000b5;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-13-19372-g002" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec><title>The transformation of yeast to the mycelial phase</title><p>The transformation of <italic toggle="yes">Candida</italic> mycelial morphology is closely related to its pathogenicity. Morphological changes during the transformation of the fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> yeast phase to the mycelial phase were observed by using an inverted microscope which is shown in <xref rid="fig-2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2C</xref>. The length of the mycelium of the fungus in the control group increased with incubation time, after 9 h of incubation, the yeast cells were observed to grow and form bundles of hyphae while forming branches of various sizes and lengths and intertwining with each other to form a net structure, and a more tightly netted biofilm is formed over time. Interestingly, the development of fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Candida tropicalis</italic> into its hyphal form was inhibited to varying degrees following treatment with GmAMP. Specifically, the morphological transformation from yeast to hyphae was partially inhibited at concentrations of 25 and 50 &#x003bc;M of GmAMP, whereas it was completely suppressed at a concentration of 100 &#x003bc;M. These results suggest that GmAMP inhibited the morphological transformation process of fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> from the yeast phase to the mycelial phase.</p></sec><sec><title>Inhibition of biofilm formation and eradication of mature biofilm</title><p>In order to investigate whether GmAMP has an anti-<italic toggle="yes">Candida tropicalis</italic> biofilm effect, we visualized the results by using confocal laser scanning microscopy. In the control group of the biofilm formation assay, a compact and intact biofilm was observed to emit predominantly green fluorescence colored by SYTO9, a dye that penetrates cells. Nevertheless, after GmAMP treatment, intact biofilm could no longer be formed and only dispersed incomplete membranes of different sizes were observed, while only single yeast cells could be seen in the high-concentration group (<xref rid="fig-3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3A</xref>). In the control group of the biofilm eradication assay, it was observed that the tightly structured and complete biofilm mainly emitted green fluorescence colored by SYTO9. After GmAMP treatment, we found that the tightly structured biofilm became loose and the network structure was reduced and thinned, while a reduction in the number of yeasts and an increase in the number of fungal damages was observed, with a predominantly red fluorescence colored by PI, a dye that penetrates injured cells (<xref rid="fig-3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3B</xref>). In addition, the biofilm activity of <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> was determined by XTT quantitative method. Compared with the control group, GmAMP at concentrations of 50, 100, and 200 &#x000b5;M inhibited biofilm formation by 49.75%, 71.28%, and 88.32%, respectively (<xref rid="fig-3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3C</xref>), and eradicated mature biofilm by 17.53%, 42.07%, and 58.28%, respectively (<xref rid="fig-3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3D</xref>). These results indicated that GmAMP inhibited biofilm formation and eradicated a certain amount of mature biofilm in fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic>.</p><fig position="float" id="fig-3"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19372/fig-3</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Effect of GmAMP on the biofilm of fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic>.</title><p>Inhibition (A) and eradication (B) effects of fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> biofilms treated with GmAMP at different concentrations observed by confocal laser scanning microscopy. Images obtained by live/dead staining (SYTO 9, green; PI, red). Scale bar, 20 &#x000b5;m. The activity level of biofilm under different concentrations of GmAMP was determined by the XTT reduction method (C and D), and the colorimetric absorbance was measured at OD<sub>490nm</sub>. The error bar represents the standard deviation of the three independent experiments. ***<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001 compared with the control group.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-13-19372-g003" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Antifungal mechanism</title><p>To investigate the impact of GmAMP on the cell morphology of fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic>, the morphological changes induced by GmAMP treatment of fungal cells for 2 h were directly observed by scanning electron microscopy. Untreated fungal cells were morphologically intact, with cell surfaces remaining round and smooth (<xref rid="fig-4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4A</xref>). When cells were exposed to 100 &#x000b5;M of GmAMP for 2 h, the cells were destroyed and the surface appeared rough and irregular (<xref rid="fig-4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4B</xref>). Thus, these outcomes suggested that the cellular structural integrity of fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> has been impaired. To further investigate the interaction of GmAMP on the cell membrane of fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic>, PI and SYTO9 fluorescence staining were used to determine the effect of GmAMP on the integrity of the cell membrane. PI and STOY9 are DNA-binding dyes emitting red and green fluorescence, respectively, and the former only penetrated the membrane-damaged cells, while the latter stained both live and dead cells (<xref rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr">Jin et al., 2005</xref>). As a result, when cells were exposed to 25, 50, and 100 &#x000b5;M of GmAMP, 45.02%, 76.88%, and 85.02% of the cells stained positively for PI, respectively. Moreover, PI staining positivity showed a dose-dependent correlation with GmAMP (<xref rid="fig-4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4D</xref>), which indicated that GmAMP disrupted the cell membrane integrity of fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic>. The membrane depolarization was detected using the membrane potential probe DiSC<sub>3</sub>(5). As shown in <xref rid="fig-4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4E</xref>, compared with the control group, we found that GmAMP treatment caused depolarization of the cell membrane potential of fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> and the level of membrane potential rose significantly with increasing concentration of GmAMP. Reactive oxygen species (ROS) generally maintain low levels within normal cells, but the accumulation of higher levels of ROS can damage cellular structures (<xref rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr">Huang et al., 2020</xref>). Here, different concentrations of GmAMP induced ROS accumulation in fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic>, and ROS levels showed a time-dose dependence (<xref rid="fig-4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4F</xref>). These results suggest that the presence of GmAMP induced ROS production, which contributed to the crucial factor in the antimicrobial effect of GmAMP.</p><fig position="float" id="fig-4"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19372/fig-4</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Effects of GmAMP cell morphology and cell membranes of fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic>.</title><p>The control group (A) and GmAMP group treated with 100 &#x000b5;M (B) of fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> morphological images by scanning electron microscopy. (C) Cell membrane permeability of GmAMP on the fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> was determined by flow cytometry, and with SYTO 9 and PI as pore formation mechanism marker. (D) The bar chart showed the percentage of PI positive cells. (E) DiSC<sub>3</sub>(5) was used to detect the cell membrane depolarization of fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic>. (F) The ROS-induced accumulation of DCFH-DA is a pore formation mechanism marker. The error bar represents the standard deviation of the three independent experiments. *** <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001 compared with the control group.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-13-19372-g004" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Hemolytic and cytotoxicity</title><p>To evaluate mammalian cytotoxicity, we assessed the safety of GmAMP on human red blood cells and RAW 264.7 cells. The hemolysis experiment was performed using 2% human red blood cells. At a concentration of 200 &#x000b5;M, GmAMP exhibited slight hemolysis with a hemolysis rate of 35.64% (<xref rid="fig-5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5A</xref>). Moreover, GmAMP showed no obvious cytotoxicity to RAW 264.7 cells, and the cell viability of mouse macrophage RAW 264.7 remained above 80% at 200 &#x000b5;M concentration of GmAMP (<xref rid="fig-5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5B</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig-5"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19372/fig-5</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>The hemolytsis and cytotoxicity effects of GmAMP.</title><p>(A) The cytotoxicity of GmAMP against RAW 264.7 cells. (B) The hemolysis rate of 2% human red blood cells.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-13-19372-g005" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Therapeutic effect on fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropical</italic> infection <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic></title><p>The <italic toggle="yes">G. mellonella</italic> larvae infection model was used to investigate the treatment efficacy of GmAMP <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>. In the peptide toxicity test (<xref rid="fig-6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6B</xref>), all larvae survived, suggesting that GmAMP did not exhibit significant toxicity within the 32 mg/kg dosage range. Survival of larvae infected with fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> was increased by injecting various concentrations of GmAMP, with 75% survival in the 32 mg/kg group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05), whereas the control group had 40% survival rate at 5 days post infection (<xref rid="fig-6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6C</xref>). These results were also reflected by the fungal burden of <italic toggle="yes">G. mellonella</italic> larvae. The number of colonies per larva was significantly reduced in all treatment groups after 24 h of treatment with GmAMP, whereas 32 mg/kg GmAMP reduced the fungal burden from 5.27 &#x000d7; 10<sup>8</sup> to 6.37 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup> CFU per larva (<xref rid="fig-6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6D</xref>). Consequently, GmAMP has the potential for clinical application as it effectively treats fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> infection and reduces the fungal burden <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>.</p><fig position="float" id="fig-6"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19372/fig-6</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title><italic toggle="yes">In vivo</italic> toxicity and therapeutic activity of GmAMP in the <italic toggle="yes">G. mellonella</italic> model.</title><p>(A) Schematic diagram of the GmAMP treatment. (B) The toxicity of GmAMP in <italic toggle="yes">G. mellonella</italic> larvae model. (C) Survival of larvae after treatment with GmAMP. (D) Fungal burden of larvae after treatment with GmAMP. *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05; ***<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001 compared with the group of fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> + PBS.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-13-19372-g006" position="float"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Antifungal drug resistance is currently rapidly developing due to the abuse of antibiotics, which is increasing the morbidity and fatality rate from invasive fungal infections (<xref rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr">Fan et al., 2024</xref>). The isolation rate of <italic toggle="yes">Candida</italic> species, such as <italic toggle="yes">Candida albicans</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Candida glabrata</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Candida tropicalis</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Candida krusei</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Candida parapsilosis</italic> is steadily increasing in hospitals (<xref rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr">Falagas, Roussos &#x00026; Vardakas, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="ref-28" ref-type="bibr">Lee et al., 2022</xref>). According to recent reports, China&#x02019;s proportion of isolates of <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> that are resistant to fluconazole is still increasing (<xref rid="ref-46" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2021</xref>). The development of new antifungal drugs to address this problem is imminent. Widely distributed in animals, plants, and other organisms, AMPs are a fast and effective barrier against pathogens in humans. AMPs exert their antimicrobial activity through a unique membrane-targeting mechanism that avoids the development of drug resistance and is regarded as a novel alternative to synthetic antibiotics (<xref rid="ref-34" ref-type="bibr">Mulukutla et al., 2024</xref>).</p><p>In this study, we determined <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> the antimicrobial activity of GmAMP against four clinical isolates of fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> and the standard strain of <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> ATCC 20962, and GmAMP showed good antimicrobial effect against clinical isolate of fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> 4252, with a MIC value of 25 &#x000b5;M. GmAMP not only delayed the proliferation rate and inhibited the growth and reproduction of fungi, but also effectively killed <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> within 2 h. These results suggest that GmAMP is an effective antimicrobial agent and further studies on the antifungal efficacy of GmAMP are necessary.</p><p>The process of transformation from the yeast phase to the mycelial phase, termed &#x0201c;biphasic&#x0201d;, is considered the most important pathogenic characteristic of <italic toggle="yes">Candida</italic>, and is also recognized as a key stage in biofilm formation and maturation (<xref rid="ref-52" ref-type="bibr">Zhu et al., 2024</xref>). Furthermore, the hyphae formed during the morphological transformation can penetrate cells and invade the bloodstream, expressing a wide range of virulence factors, and they are regarded as a more virulent phenotype than yeast (<xref rid="ref-25" ref-type="bibr">Khamzeh et al., 2023</xref>). Herein, GmAMP inhibited the transition of yeast phase cells to mycelial phase morphology, preventing the process of mycelial development, which demonstrates that GmAMP plays a key role in inhibiting the formation and maturation of fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> biofilm by preventing mycelial development. The yeast cells of <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> are characterized by a high capacity to form biofilms compared to other <italic toggle="yes">Candida</italic> species (<xref rid="ref-54" ref-type="bibr">Zuza-Alves, Silva-Rocha &#x00026; Chaves, 2017</xref>), which may be related to an increased amount of biomass in the membranes and extracellular matrix, leading to a denser structure (<xref rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr">Chandra &#x00026; Mukherjee, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="ref-11" ref-type="bibr">Desai &#x00026; Mitchell, 2015</xref>). Here, the 50 &#x000b5;M (2 &#x000d7; MIC) of GmAMP inhibits biofilm formation and has an eradicative effect on mature biofilms. Moreover, GmAMP inhibited and eliminated biofilms of fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic> in a concentration-dependent manner. Therefore, GmAMP showed good bioactivity in inhibiting morphological transformation and anti-biofilm processes.</p><p>It has been reported that most antimicrobial peptides exert their antimicrobial effects mainly by targeting cell membranes (<xref rid="ref-1" ref-type="bibr">Aguiar et al., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="ref-6" ref-type="bibr">Buda De Cesare et al., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="ref-20" ref-type="bibr">Hu et al., 2022</xref>). In the present study, the results of the scanning electron microscopy assay demonstrated that GmAMP disrupts the morphology and structure of the fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropicalis</italic>. A similar phenomenon was also found by <xref rid="ref-32" ref-type="bibr">Ma et al. (2020)</xref>, <xref rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al. (2023)</xref>. Moreover, we speculated the exact reason for the morphological damage and subsequent cell death is correlated with increased membrane permeability resulting from electrostatic interactions between the positively charged peptide GmAMP and the negatively charged components of the fungal cytoplasmic membrane (<xref rid="ref-5" ref-type="bibr">Boparai &#x00026; Sharma, 2020</xref>; <xref rid="ref-22" ref-type="bibr">Jayasinghe, Whang &#x00026; De Zoysa, 2023</xref>; <xref rid="ref-26" ref-type="bibr">Kodedov&#x000e1; et al., 2019</xref>). The experimental result verified membrane permeability by a significant increase in the number of PI-stained positive cells of the fungi treated with GmAMP. Changes in cell membrane permeability usually trigger variation in cell membrane potential, which is closely related to cellular function (<xref rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr">D&#x02019;Auria et al., 2022</xref>). When membrane-modifying compounds (<italic toggle="yes">e.g</italic>., peptides) depolarize the membrane then the potential is lost. DiSC<sub>3</sub>(5) is released into the solution, causing fluorescence enhancement, which indicates that the cytoplasmic membrane is altered because of the cell membrane depolarization by the action of GmAMP in a concentration-dependent manner, which suggests that the dissipation of membrane potential might be involved in the formation of channels or pores, then allowed the passage of ions or macromolecules, to lead cytoplasmic membrane dysfunction (<xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr">Bezerra et al., 2022</xref>; <xref rid="ref-45" ref-type="bibr">Venkatesh et al., 2017</xref>). It has been found that aerobic metabolism-generated ROS are usually present in cells that are in equilibrium with antioxidant enzymes, and excess ROS have certain deleterious effects on the basic structure of fungi, such as damage to nucleic acids, DNA, amino acid residues, and cell membranes (<xref rid="ref-36" ref-type="bibr">Perrone, Tan &#x00026; Dawes, 2008</xref>). We found that GmAMP induced the accumulation of reactive oxygen species in a dose-dependent manner (<xref rid="ref-42" ref-type="bibr">Taveira et al., 2022</xref>). In brief, we hypothesized that the cationic peptide GmAMP can interact with certain negatively charged substance molecules on the cell membrane through electrostatic interactions, it leads to a series of consequences such as increased membrane permeability, altered depolarization of the membrane potential, structural loss of membrane integrity, accumulation of ROS, and further leakage of intracellular contents, which finally leads to cytoplasmic membrane dysfunction and cell death.</p><p>The excellent antimicrobial activity of antimicrobial peptides is usually associated with strong hemolytic activity and cytotoxicity, and assessment of the <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> safety of AMP is paramount for further consideration as a potential clinical candidate (<xref rid="ref-51" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2024</xref>). In this study, our results showed that GmAMP showed little cytotoxicity and low hemolytic effect. Although some cytotoxicity and hemolytic activity were observed at higher concentrations, considering the MIC value of GmAMP was 25 &#x000b5;M (<xref rid="table-1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>), which was much lower than its cytotoxicity concentration, GmAMP safety is also guaranteed under the premise of ensuring its activity. However, the potential toxicity of GmAMP to other mammalian cells remains to be studied.</p><p>The safe and effective dose range of GmAMP is confirmed by cytotoxicity and hemolytic tests, laying the foundation for its application in animal studies. In this study, the therapeutic efficacy of GmAMP was tested <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> using the <italic toggle="yes">G. mellonella</italic> larvae infection model, which showed a significant improvement in survival. The fungal burden of <italic toggle="yes">G. mellonella</italic> larvae was considerably decreased <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> with GmAMP therapy. These findings suggest that GmAMP may exhibit a strong safety and certain therapeutic potential.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>This work describes the antifungal activity and mechanism of antimicrobial peptide GmAMP and therapeutic efficacy <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>. GmAMP possesses potent antimicrobial activity, anti-biofilm formation, and eradication ability, and may play an antimicrobial role by disrupting the structure of fungal cytomembrane. Here, GmAMP displays low cytotoxicity and low hemolytic activity <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> experiments. Furthermore, GmAMP exhibits a therapeutic effect against fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropical</italic> infection and reduces the number of fungi <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>. These properties make GmAMP a potential treatment for fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. tropical</italic> infection, which is worthy of further optimization and development. Furthermore, GmAMP provides further opportunities for the safe and effective clinical application of antimicrobial peptides in the development of drug resistance.</p></sec><sec id="supplemental-information" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplemental Information</title><supplementary-material id="supp-1" position="float" content-type="local-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19372/supp-1</object-id><label>Supplemental Information 1</label><caption><title>Determination of MIC value.</title></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-13-19372-s001.xlsx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="supp-2" position="float" content-type="local-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19372/supp-2</object-id><label>Supplemental Information 2</label><caption><title>The raw data for Figure 2.</title></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-13-19372-s002.xlsx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="supp-3" position="float" content-type="local-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19372/supp-3</object-id><label>Supplemental Information 3</label><caption><title>The raw data for Figure 3.</title></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-13-19372-s003.xlsx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="supp-4" position="float" content-type="local-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19372/supp-4</object-id><label>Supplemental Information 4</label><caption><title>The raw data for Figure 4.</title></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-13-19372-s004.xlsx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="supp-5" position="float" content-type="local-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19372/supp-5</object-id><label>Supplemental Information 5</label><caption><title>The raw data for Figure 5.</title></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-13-19372-s005.xlsx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="supp-6" position="float" content-type="local-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19372/supp-6</object-id><label>Supplemental Information 6</label><caption><title>The raw data for Figure 6.</title></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-13-19372-s006.xlsx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="supp-7" position="float" content-type="local-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19372/supp-7</object-id><label>Supplemental Information 7</label><caption><title>Characterization of GmAMP.</title><p>(A) purification of GmAMP. (B) electrospray ionization (ESI) mass spectrometer of GmAMP.</p></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-13-19372-s007.docx"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="additional-information"><title>Additional Information and Declarations</title><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing Interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec sec-type="author-contributions"><title>Author Contributions</title><p><xref rid="author-1" ref-type="contrib">Ruxia Cai</xref> conceived and designed the experiments, performed the experiments, analyzed the data, prepared figures and/or tables, authored or reviewed drafts of the article, and approved the final draft.</p><p><xref rid="author-2" ref-type="contrib">Na Zhao</xref> conceived and designed the experiments, performed the experiments, prepared figures and/or tables, authored or reviewed drafts of the article, and approved the final draft.</p><p><xref rid="author-3" ref-type="contrib">Chaoqin Sun</xref> performed the experiments, analyzed the data, prepared figures and/or tables, and approved the final draft.</p><p><xref rid="author-4" ref-type="contrib">Mingjiao Huang</xref> performed the experiments, prepared figures and/or tables, and approved the final draft.</p><p><xref rid="author-5" ref-type="contrib">Zhenlong Jiao</xref> analyzed the data, prepared figures and/or tables, and approved the final draft.</p><p><xref rid="author-6" ref-type="contrib">Jian Peng</xref> performed the experiments, prepared figures and/or tables, and approved the final draft.</p><p><xref rid="author-7" ref-type="contrib">Jin Zhang</xref> analyzed the data, authored or reviewed drafts of the article, and approved the final draft.</p><p><xref rid="author-8" ref-type="contrib">Guo Guo</xref> conceived and designed the experiments, authored or reviewed drafts of the article, and approved the final draft.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data Availability</title><p>The following information was supplied regarding data availability:</p><p>The raw measurements are available in the <xref rid="supplemental-information" ref-type="sec">Supplemental Files</xref>.</p></sec></sec><ref-list content-type="authoryear"><title>References</title><ref id="ref-1"><label>Aguiar et al. (2020)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Aguiar</surname><given-names>FLL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>de Paula</surname><given-names>CCS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Andreu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baptista</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gon&#x000e7;alves</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Antibiofilm activity on <italic toggle="yes">Candida albicans</italic> and mechanism of action on biomembrane models of the antimicrobial peptide Ctn[15&#x02013;34]</article-title><source>International Journal of Molecular Sciences</source><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><volume>21</volume><issue>21</issue><fpage>8339</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms21218339</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33172206</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-2"><label>Alfaro-Vargas et al. (2022)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Alfaro-Vargas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bastos-Salas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mu&#x000f1;oz-Arrieta</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pereira-Reyes</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Redondo-Solano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mora-Villalobos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>L&#x000f3;pez-G&#x000f3;mez</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Peptaibol production and characterization from <italic toggle="yes">Trichoderma asperellum</italic> and their action as biofungicide</article-title><source>Journal of Fungi</source><year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year><volume>8</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1037</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jof8101037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36294602</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-3"><label>Badiee et al. (2022)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Badiee</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Boekhout</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Haddadi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mohammadi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ghadimi-Moghadam</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Soltani</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zarei Mahmoudabadi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ayatollahi Mousavi</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Najafzadeh</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Diba</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Salimi-Khorashad</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Amin Shahidi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ghasemi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jafarian</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Epidemiology and antifungal susceptibility of candida species isolated from 10 tertiary care hospitals in Iran</article-title><source>Microbiology Spectrum</source><year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year><volume>10</volume><issue>6</issue><elocation-id>e0245322</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/spectrum.02453-22</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36445122</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-4"><label>Bezerra et al. (2022)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bezerra</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Freitas</surname><given-names>CDT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>AFB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Amaral</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Neto</surname><given-names>NAS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>RGG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Parra</surname><given-names>ALC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goldman</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>JTA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mesquita</surname><given-names>FP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>PFN</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Synergistic antifungal activity of synthetic peptides and antifungal drugs against <italic toggle="yes">Candida albicans</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">C. parapsilosis</italic> biofilms</article-title><source>Antibiotics</source><year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year><volume>11</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>553</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/antibiotics11050553</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35625197</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-5"><label>Boparai &#x00026; Sharma (2020)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Boparai</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Mini review on antimicrobial peptides, sources, mechanism and recent applications</article-title><source>Protein &#x00026; Peptide Letters</source><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><volume>27</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>4</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/0929866526666190822165812</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31438824</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-6"><label>Buda De Cesare et al. (2020)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Buda De Cesare</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cristy</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Garsin</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lorenz</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial peptides: a new frontier in antifungal therapy</article-title><source>mBio</source><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><volume>11</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>847</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mBio.02123-20</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-7"><label>Chandra &#x00026; Mukherjee (2015)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chandra</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Candida biofilms: development, architecture, and resistance</article-title><source>Microbiology Spectrum</source><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><volume>5</volume><issue>3</issue><elocation-id>MB-0020-2015</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/microbiolspec.mb-0020-2015</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-8"><label>Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute (CLSI) (2023)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute (CLSI)</collab>
</person-group><source>Performance standards for antimicrobial susceptibility testing</source><year iso-8601-date="2023">2023</year><publisher-loc>Wayne, PA</publisher-loc><publisher-name>CLSI, M100-Ed33</publisher-name><uri xlink:href="https://clsi.org/standards/products/microbiology/documents/m100/">https://clsi.org/standards/products/microbiology/documents/m100/</uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-9"><label>de Oliveira et al. (2023)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>de Oliveira</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>de Oliveira</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>FBA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nobre</surname><given-names>FD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>ADC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Albuquerque</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sidrim</surname><given-names>JJC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rocha</surname><given-names>MFG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Srivastava</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Romeiro</surname><given-names>LAS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brilhante</surname><given-names>RSN</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Antifungal activity of sustainable histone deacetylase inhibitors against planktonic cells and biofilms of <italic toggle="yes">Candida</italic> spp. and <italic toggle="yes">Cryptococcusneoformans</italic></article-title><source>Medical Mycology</source><year iso-8601-date="2023">2023</year><volume>61</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>877</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/mmy/myad073</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-10"><label>Decker et al. (2024)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Decker</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rautenbach</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Antibacterial efficacy and membrane mechanism of action of the <italic toggle="yes">Serratia</italic>-derived non-ionic lipopeptide, serrawettin W2-FL10</article-title><source>Microbiology Spectrum</source><year iso-8601-date="2024">2024</year><volume>12</volume><issue>7</issue><elocation-id>e0295223</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/spectrum.02952-23</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38842361</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-11"><label>Desai &#x00026; Mitchell (2015)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Desai</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Candida albicans biofilm development and its genetic control</article-title><source>Microbiology Spectrum</source><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><volume>7</volume><issue>3</issue><elocation-id>MB-0005-2014</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/microbiolspec.mb-0005-2014</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-12"><label>D&#x02019;Auria et al. (2022)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>D&#x02019;Auria</surname><given-names>FD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Casciaro</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>De Angelis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marcocci</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Palamara</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nencioni</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mangoni</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Antifungal activity of the frog skin peptide temporin G and its effect on <italic toggle="yes">Candida albicans</italic> virulence factors</article-title><source>International Journal of Molecular Sciences</source><year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year><volume>23</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>6345</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms23116345</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35683025</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-13"><label>Falagas, Roussos &#x00026; Vardakas (2010)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Falagas</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roussos</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vardakas</surname><given-names>KZ</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Relative frequency of albicans and the various non-albicans Candida spp among candidemia isolates from inpatients in various parts of the world: a systematic review</article-title><source>International Journal of Infectious Diseases</source><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><volume>14</volume><issue>11</issue><elocation-id>e954&#x02013;966</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijid.2010.04.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20797887</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-14"><label>Fan et al. (2024)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Geng</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mei</surname><given-names>YN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Author correction: tandem gene duplications contributed to high-level azole resistance in a rapidly expanding Candida tropicalis population</article-title><source>Nature Communications</source><year iso-8601-date="2024">2024</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>587</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-024-44825-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-15"><label>Fan et al. (2023)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tsui</surname><given-names>CKM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>CX</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>High prevalence of fluconazole resistant <italic toggle="yes">Candida tropicalis</italic> among candiduria samples in China: an ignored matter of concern</article-title><source>Frontiers in Microbiology</source><year iso-8601-date="2023">2023</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1125241</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2023.1125241</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36937265</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-16"><label>Fernandes, Weeks &#x00026; Carter (2020)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weeks</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Lactoferrin is broadly active against yeasts and highly synergistic with Amphotericin B</article-title><source>Antimicrobial Agents and Chemotherapy</source><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><volume>64</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>292</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.02284-19</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-17"><label>Fisher &#x00026; Denning (2023)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Denning</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The WHO fungal priority pathogens list as a game-changer</article-title><source>Nature Reviews Microbiology</source><year iso-8601-date="2023">2023</year><volume>21</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41579-023-00861-x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-18"><label>Forastiero et al. (2013)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Forastiero</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mesa-Arango</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alastruey-Izquierdo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alcazar-Fuoli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bernal-Martinez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pelaez</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Grimalt</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gomez-Lopez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cuesta</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zaragoza</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mellado</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Candida tropicalis</italic> antifungal cross-resistance is related to different azole target (Erg11p) modifications</article-title><source>Antimicrobial Agents and Chemotherapy</source><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><volume>57</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>4769</fpage><lpage>4781</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.00477-13</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23877676</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-19"><label>Gan et al. (2021)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gaynord</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rowe</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Deingruber</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Spring</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The multifaceted nature of antimicrobial peptides: current synthetic chemistry approaches and future directions</article-title><source>Chemical Society Reviews</source><year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year><volume>50</volume><issue>13</issue><fpage>7820</fpage><lpage>7880</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/D0CS00729C</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34042120</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-20"><label>Hu et al. (2022)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mo</surname><given-names>XM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>HN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>A novel antimicrobial peptide derived from human BPIFA1 protein protects against <italic toggle="yes">Candida albicans</italic> infection</article-title><source>Innate Immunity</source><year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year><volume>28</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>78</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/17534259221080543</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35201913</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-21"><label>Huang et al. (2020)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fujii</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Iwatani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chibana</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kojima</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kajiwara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Fungal NOX is an essential factor for induction of TG2 in human hepatocytes</article-title><source>Medical Mycology</source><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><volume>58</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>679</fpage><lpage>689</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/mmy/myz105</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31642483</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-22"><label>Jayasinghe, Whang &#x00026; De Zoysa (2023)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jayasinghe</surname><given-names>JNC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Whang</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>De Zoysa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Antifungal efficacy of antimicrobial peptide octominin II against <italic toggle="yes">Candida albicans</italic></article-title><source>International Journal of Molecular Sciences</source><year iso-8601-date="2023">2023</year><volume>24</volume><issue>18</issue><fpage>14053</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms241814053</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37762357</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-23"><label>Jiang et al. (2016)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Significance of hyphae formation in virulence of <italic toggle="yes">Candida tropicalis</italic> and transcriptomic analysis of hyphal cells</article-title><source>Microbiological Research</source><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><volume>192</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.micres.2016.06.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27664724</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-24"><label>Jin et al. (2005)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Samaranayake</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yip</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Samaranayake</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The use of new probes and stains for improved assessment of cell viability and extracellular polymeric substances in <italic toggle="yes">Candida albicans</italic> biofilms</article-title><source>Mycopathologia</source><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><volume>159</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>353</fpage><lpage>360</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11046-004-6987-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15883718</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-25"><label>Khamzeh et al. (2023)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Khamzeh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dahlstrand Rudin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Venkatakrishnan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stylianou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sanchez Klose</surname><given-names>FP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Urban</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bj&#x000f6;rnsdottir</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bylund</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Christenson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>High levels of short chain fatty acids secreted by <italic toggle="yes">Candida albicans</italic> hyphae induce neutrophil chemotaxis via free fatty acid receptor 2</article-title><source>Journal of Leukocyte Biology</source><year iso-8601-date="2023">2023</year><volume>115</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>536</fpage><lpage>546</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jleuko/qiad146</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-26"><label>Kodedov&#x000e1; et al. (2019)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kodedov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Valachovi&#x0010d;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cs&#x000e1;ky</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sychrov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Variations in yeast plasma-membrane lipid composition affect killing activity of three families of insect antifungal peptides</article-title><source>Cellular Microbiology</source><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><volume>21</volume><issue>12</issue><elocation-id>e13093</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/cmi.13093</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31376220</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-27"><label>Larr&#x000e1;n et al. (2022)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Larr&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>L&#x000f3;pez-Alonso</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Miranda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rigueira</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Su&#x000e1;rez</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Herrero-Latorre</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Measuring haemolysis in cattle serum by direct UV-VIS and RGB digital image-based methods</article-title><source>Scientific Reports</source><year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>13523</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-022-17842-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35941370</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-28"><label>Lee et al. (2022)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guk</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Antifungal and anti-inflammatory activities of PS1-2 peptide against fluconazole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Candida albicans</italic></article-title><source>Antibiotics</source><year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year><volume>11</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1779</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/antibiotics11121779</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36551434</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-29"><label>Lee et al. (2021)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Puumala</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Robbins</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cowen</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Antifungal drug resistance: molecular mechanisms in <italic toggle="yes">Candida albicans</italic> and beyond</article-title><source>Chemical Reviews</source><year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year><volume>121</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>3390</fpage><lpage>3411</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.chemrev.0c00199</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32441527</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-30"><label>Li et al. (2020)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial peptide CGA-N12 decreases the <italic toggle="yes">Candida tropicalis</italic> mitochondrial membrane potential via mitochondrial permeability transition pore</article-title><source>Bioscience Reports</source><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><volume>40</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>14</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/BSR20201007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-31"><label>Liu et al. (2022)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Extensive diversity and prevalent fluconazole resistance among environmental yeasts from tropical China</article-title><source>Genes</source><year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year><volume>13</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>444</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/genes13030444</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35327998</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-32"><label>Ma et al. (2020)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial peptide AMP-17 affects <italic toggle="yes">Candida albicans</italic> by disrupting its cell wall and cell membrane integrity</article-title><source>Infection and Drug Resistance</source><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>2509</fpage><lpage>2520</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/idr.S250278</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32801789</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-33"><label>McCarthy &#x00026; Walsh (2017)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Drug development challenges and strategies to address emerging and resistant fungal pathogens</article-title><source>Expert Review of Anti-Infective Therapy</source><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><volume>15</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>577</fpage><lpage>584</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14787210.2017.1328279</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28480775</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-34"><label>Mulukutla et al. (2024)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mulukutla</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shreshtha</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kumar Deb</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chatterjee</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chauhan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Recent advances in antimicrobial peptide-based therapy</article-title><source>Bioorganic Chemistry</source><year iso-8601-date="2024">2024</year><volume>145</volume><issue>1963</issue><fpage>107151</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bioorg.2024.107151</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38359706</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-35"><label>Pathakumari, Liang &#x00026; Liu (2020)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pathakumari</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Immune defence to invasive fungal infections: a comprehensive review</article-title><source>Biomedicine &#x00026; Pharmacotherapy</source><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><volume>130</volume><issue>165</issue><fpage>110550</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopha.2020.110550</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32739740</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-36"><label>Perrone, Tan &#x00026; Dawes (2008)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Perrone</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>SX</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dawes</surname><given-names>IW</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Reactive oxygen species and yeast apoptosis</article-title><source>Biochimica et Biophysica Acta (BBA)&#x02014;Molecular Cell Research</source><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><volume>1783</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1354</fpage><lpage>1368</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbamcr.2008.01.023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18298957</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-37"><label>Personne et al. (2023)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Personne</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Paschoud</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fulgencio</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baeriswyl</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>K&#x000f6;hler</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>van Delden</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stocker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Javor</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reymond</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>To fold or not to fold: diastereomeric optimization of an &#x003b1;-helical antimicrobial peptide</article-title><source>Journal of Medicinal Chemistry</source><year iso-8601-date="2023">2023</year><volume>66</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>7570</fpage><lpage>7583</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jmedchem.3c00460</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37227046</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-38"><label>Pfaller &#x00026; Diekema (2007)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pfaller</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Diekema</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Epidemiology of invasive candidiasis: a persistent public health problem</article-title><source>Clinical Microbiology Reviews</source><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><volume>20</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>163</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/CMR.00029-06</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17223626</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-39"><label>Ramesh et al. (2023)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ramesh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Madduri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rudramurthy</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Functional characterization of a bacillus-derived novel broad-spectrum antifungal lipopeptide variant against <italic toggle="yes">Candida tropicalis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Candida auris</italic> and unravelling its mode of action</article-title><source>Microbiology Spectrum</source><year iso-8601-date="2023">2023</year><volume>11</volume><issue>2</issue><elocation-id>e0158322</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/spectrum.01583-22</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36744953</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-40"><label>Sasani et al. (2021)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sasani</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Khodavaisy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rezaie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Salehi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yadegari</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The relationship between biofilm formation and mortality in patients with <italic toggle="yes">Candida tropicalis</italic> candidemia</article-title><source>Microbial Pathogenesis</source><year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year><volume>155</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>104889</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.micpath.2021.104889</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33878395</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-41"><label>Shaban, Patel &#x00026; Ahmad (2024)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shaban</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Antifungal activity of human antimicrobial peptides targeting apoptosis in Candida auris</article-title><source>Journal of Medical Microbiology</source><year iso-8601-date="2024">2024</year><volume>73</volume><issue>5</issue><elocation-id>e001835</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/jmm.0.001835</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-42"><label>Taveira et al. (2022)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Taveira</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>de Oliveira Mello</surname><given-names>&#x000c9;</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sim&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cherene</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>de Oliveira Carvalho</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Muzitano</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lassounskaia</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pireda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>de Castro Miguel</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Basso</surname><given-names>LGM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Da Cunha</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>da Motta</surname><given-names>OV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gomes</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>A new bioinspired peptide on defensin from <italic toggle="yes">C. annuum</italic> fruits: Antimicrobial activity, mechanisms of action and therapeutical potential</article-title><source>Biochimica et Biophysica Acta (BBA)&#x02014;General Subjects</source><year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year><volume>1866</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>130218</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbagen.2022.130218</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35905923</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-43"><label>Torres et al. (2023)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Torres</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barreto-Santamar&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ar&#x000e9;valo-Pinz&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Firacative</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>G&#x000f3;mez</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Escand&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Patarroyo</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mu&#x000f1;oz</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>In vitro antifungal activity of three synthetic peptides against <italic toggle="yes">Candida auris</italic> and other <italic toggle="yes">Candida</italic> species of medical importance</article-title><source>Antibiotics</source><year iso-8601-date="2023">2023</year><volume>12</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1234</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/antibiotics12081234</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37627654</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-44"><label>Tseng et al. (2022)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tseng</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>A predominant genotype of azole-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Candida tropicalis</italic> clinical strains</article-title><source>The Lancet Microbe</source><year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year><volume>3</volume><issue>9</issue><elocation-id>e646</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2666-5247(22)00179-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35752199</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-45"><label>Venkatesh et al. (2017)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Venkatesh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barathi</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goh</surname><given-names>ETL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Anggara</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fazil</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>AJY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Harini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aung</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barkham</surname><given-names>TMS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Loh</surname><given-names>XJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Beuerman</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lakshminarayanan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial activity and cell selectivity of synthetic and biosynthetic cationic polymers</article-title><source>Antimicrobial Agents and Chemotherapy</source><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><volume>61</volume><issue>10</issue><elocation-id>e00469</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/aac.00469-17</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28784676</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-46"><label>Wang et al. (2021)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kudinha</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mei</surname><given-names>YN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xi</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>YP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Continual decline in azole susceptibility rates in <italic toggle="yes">Candida tropicalis</italic> over a 9-year period in China</article-title><source>Frontiers in Microbiology</source><year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>702839</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2021.702839</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34305872</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-47"><label>World Health Organization (WHO) ARDA, Control of Neglected Tropical Diseases (NTD) &#x00026; Global Coordination and Partnership (GCP) (2022)</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>World Health Organization (WHO) ARDA</collab>
<collab>Control of Neglected Tropical Diseases (NTD)</collab>
<collab>Global Coordination and Partnership (GCP)</collab>
</person-group><article-title>WHO fungal priority pathogens list to guide research, development and public health action</article-title><year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year><uri xlink:href="https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789240060241">https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789240060241</uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-48"><label>Zhang et al. (2023)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cong</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Qiao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Switching from membrane disrupting to membrane crossing, an effective strategy in designing antibacterial polypeptide</article-title><source>Science Advances</source><year iso-8601-date="2023">2023</year><volume>9</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>eabn0771</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/sciadv.abn0771</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36696494</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-49"><label>Zhang et al. (2022)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Large-scale screening of antifungal peptides based on quantitative structure-activity relationship</article-title><source>ACS Medicinal Chemistry Letters</source><year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year><volume>13</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>104</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acsmedchemlett.1c00556</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35059128</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-50"><label>Zhang et al. (2017)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Forecasting of particulate matter time series using wavelet analysis and wavelet-ARMA/ARIMA model in Taiyuan</article-title><source>Journal of the Air &#x00026; Waste Management Association</source><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><volume>67</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>776</fpage><lpage>788</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10962247.2017.1292968</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28278031</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-51"><label>Zhang et al. (2024)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>XS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mwangi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>YQ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>QM</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Blap-6, a novel antifungal Peptide from the Chinese medicinal beetle <italic toggle="yes">Blaps rhynchopetera</italic> against <italic toggle="yes">Cryptococcus</italic> neoformans</article-title><source>International Journal of Molecular Sciences</source><year iso-8601-date="2024">2024</year><volume>25</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>5336</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms25105336</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38791374</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-52"><label>Zhu et al. (2024)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Mitochondrial protease oct1p regulates mitochondrial homeostasis and influences pathogenicity through affecting hyphal growth and biofilm formation activities in <italic toggle="yes">Candida albicans</italic></article-title><source>Journal of Fungi</source><year iso-8601-date="2024">2024</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>391</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jof10060391</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38921377</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-53"><label>Zou et al. (2024)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Activity and mechanism of action of antimicrobial peptide ACPs against <italic toggle="yes">Candida albicans</italic></article-title><source>Life Sciences</source><year iso-8601-date="2024">2024</year><volume>350</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>122767</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.lfs.2024.122767</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38843993</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-54"><label>Zuza-Alves, Silva-Rocha &#x00026; Chaves (2017)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zuza-Alves</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Silva-Rocha</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chaves</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>An update on <italic toggle="yes">Candida tropicalis</italic> based on basic and clinical approaches</article-title><source>Frontiers in Microbiology</source><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1927</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2017.01927</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29081766</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>