<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="case-report" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Dermatol Ther (Heidelb)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Dermatol Ther (Heidelb)</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Dermatology and Therapy</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2193-8210</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2190-9172</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer Healthcare</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Cheshire</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39589679</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11785849</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1304</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13555-024-01304-y</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Brief Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Brodalumab: Six-Year US Pharmacovigilance Report</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-4705-5303</contrib-id><name><surname>Lebwohl</surname><given-names>Mark G.</given-names></name><address><email>lebwohl@aol.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0009-0004-1005-5221</contrib-id><name><surname>Koo</surname><given-names>John Y.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-6892-6286</contrib-id><name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>April W.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-8394-2057</contrib-id><name><surname>Strober</surname><given-names>Bruce E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-3685-668X</contrib-id><name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>Soo Han</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0009-0005-7856-6615</contrib-id><name><surname>Rawnsley</surname><given-names>Nicole N.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff7">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3935-8355</contrib-id><name><surname>Goehring</surname><given-names>Earl L.</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff7">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mangin</surname><given-names>Gina D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff8">8</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-7810-2280</contrib-id><name><surname>Jacobson</surname><given-names>Abby A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff7">7</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/04a9tmd77</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.59734.3c</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0670 2351</institution-id><institution>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai, </institution></institution-wrap>5 East 98th Street, 5th Floor, New York, NY 10029 USA </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/043mz5j54</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.266102.1</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2297 6811</institution-id><institution>Psoriasis and Skin Treatment Center, </institution><institution>University of California, San Francisco, </institution></institution-wrap>San Francisco, CA USA </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/05t99sp05</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.468726.9</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0486 2046</institution-id><institution>University of California, Los Angeles, </institution></institution-wrap>Los Angeles, CA USA </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>Central Connecticut Dermatology Research, Cromwell, CT USA </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/03v76x132</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.47100.32</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 8710</institution-id><institution>Yale University, </institution></institution-wrap>New Haven, CT USA </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/00zdkew04</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.433688.2</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0380 1655</institution-id><institution>Salix Pharmaceuticals, </institution></institution-wrap>Bridgewater, NJ USA </aff><aff id="Aff7"><label>7</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/00zdkew04</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.433688.2</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0380 1655</institution-id><institution>Bausch Health Companies Inc, </institution></institution-wrap>Bridgewater, NJ USA </aff><aff id="Aff8"><label>8</label>Sand Lake Dermatology Center, Orlando, FL USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>26</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>26</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>213</fpage><lpage>222</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2024</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par1">Brodalumab is a human interleukin-17 receptor&#x000a0;A antagonist indicated for the treatment of moderate-to-severe plaque psoriasis in adult patients who are candidates for systemic therapy or phototherapy and have failed to respond or have lost response to other systemic therapies. In the USA, brodalumab has a boxed warning regarding suicidal ideation and behavior and is only available under a Risk Evaluation and Mitigation Strategy, but no causal association has been established. To assess long-term safety of brodalumab, we summarize pharmacovigilance data from 6&#x000a0;years of real-world clinical practice.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">Crude adverse event (AE) reporting rates per 100 patients were calculated for common AEs and AEs of special interest reported to Ortho Dermatologics by US patients and healthcare providers from August 15, 2017 through August 14, 2023. Brodalumab exposure was estimated as time from the first to last prescription-dispensing authorization dates. Adverse events were defined by Medical Dictionary for Regulatory Activities v26.0 Preferred Terms and standardized MedDRA queries.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">Data were collected from 5138 US patients (estimated exposure of 6900 patient-years). Over 6&#x000a0;years, 13 cases of adjudicated major adverse cardiovascular events were reported (0.25 events/100 patients). The rate of serious infections was 2.20 events/100 patients. Since the 5-year report, there was one new case of <italic>Candida</italic> infection and a serious fungal infection of the elbow. Among 57 reported malignancies affecting 49 patients, 4 were deemed possibly related to brodalumab. One new case of indeterminate inflammatory bowel disease unrelated to brodalumab was reported. No new suicide attempts were reported in year&#x000a0;6, and there were no completed suicides throughout 6&#x000a0;years.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par4">Pharmacovigilance data throughout 6&#x000a0;years are consistent with the safety profile of brodalumab established in clinical trials and previous US pharmacovigilance reports, with no completed suicides and a low fungal infection rate.</p></sec><sec><title>Graphical Abstract</title><p id="Par5">
<graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="13555_2024_1304_Figa_HTML" id="MO1"/></p></sec></abstract><abstract id="Abs2" abstract-type="plain-language-summary"><title>Plain Language Summary</title><p id="Par6">Brodalumab is an injectable treatment approved for moderate-to-severe plaque psoriasis in adults who lacked response to previous treatments. In the USA, brodalumab is only available under a Risk Evaluation and Mitigation Strategy for increased suicidality risks; however, findings from 6&#x000a0;years of real-world safety data have demonstrated a lack of association. In this report, we discuss safety findings reported by US patients and healthcare providers for 5138 patients treated with brodalumab over 6&#x000a0;years. Joint pain (known as arthralgia) was the most common safety finding, with 135 cases reported over 6&#x000a0;years. Other safety findings of interest across 6&#x000a0;years included 113 cases of serious infection (defined as prolonged infection or infection requiring intervention), 58 cases of depression, 57 cases of cancer (in 49 patients), 56 confirmed cases of COVID-19, and 13 cases of major cardiovascular events (such as heart attack or stroke). No completed suicides occurred throughout 6&#x000a0;years, and no new suicide attempts were reported in year&#x000a0;6. In indirect comparisons with safety data from patients with psoriasis receiving or eligible to receive similar treatments, brodalumab was not associated with an increased risk of serious infection, cancer, major cardiovascular events, or inflammatory bowel disease. Taken together, these data are consistent with safety findings from long-term clinical trials and previous safety reports of brodalumab.</p></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Adverse events</kwd><kwd>Drug reaction</kwd><kwd>Psoriasis</kwd><kwd>Real-world</kwd><kwd>Safety</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100019507</institution-id><institution>Ortho Dermatologics</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Springer Healthcare Ltd., part of Springer Nature 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="d33e328"><title>Key Summary Points</title><p id="Par7">
<table-wrap id="Taba"><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td align="left">
<bold><italic>Why carry out the study?</italic></bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Brodalumab, a human interleukin-17 receptor&#x000a0;A antagonist indicated for treatment of moderate-to-severe plaque psoriasis in adults, carries a boxed warning in the US prescribing information regarding suicidal ideation and behavior.</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Because patients with psoriasis often require long-term treatment, ongoing monitoring of adverse events (AEs) is necessary to establish the safety profile of brodalumab in a real-world setting.</td></tr><tr><td align="left">This report summarizes 6&#x000a0;years (August 15, 2017 through August 14, 2023) of brodalumab pharmacovigilance data reported to Ortho Dermatologics by US patients and healthcare providers with a focus on the most common AEs listed in the brodalumab package insert and AEs of special interest, including suicide and depression.</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<bold><italic>What was learned from the study?</italic></bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">The most commonly reported AE was arthralgia (135 total events); no new suicide attempts were reported in year&#x000a0;6, and no completed suicides were reported throughout the 6&#x000a0;years.</td></tr><tr><td align="left">This 6-year pharmacovigilance report supports the consistent safety profile of brodalumab established in pivotal trials and previous pharmacovigilance reports, with no new occurrences of completed or attempted suicide and a consistently low fungal infection rate.</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Digital Features</title><p id="Par8">This article is published with digital features, including a graphical abstract to facilitate understanding of the article. To view digital features for this article, go to 10.6084/m9.figshare.27247380.</p></sec><sec id="Sec3" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par9">Brodalumab is a human anti-interleukin (IL)&#x02212;17 receptor&#x000a0;A monoclonal antibody indicated for the treatment of moderate-to-severe plaque psoriasis in adults [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. The unique mechanism of action of brodalumab allows for blockade of multiple IL-17 isoforms that contribute to psoriatic disease, including IL-17A, IL-17C, and IL-17F; treatment with brodalumab also reduces the expression of IL-23 and IL-12 subunit genes, indicating that brodalumab may reduce inflammatory markers of psoriasis upstream&#x000a0;of IL-17 receptor&#x000a0;A [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>].</p><p id="Par10">Pharmacovigilance reports for the past 5&#x000a0;years have provided real-world evidence to fully characterize the safety profile of brodalumab, which was initially assessed in one phase&#x000a0;2 and two phase&#x000a0;3 studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. In the USA, brodalumab carries a boxed warning in the prescribing information regarding suicidal ideation and behavior and is only available under a Risk Evaluation and Mitigation Strategy (REMS); however, no established causal relationship between brodalumab and suicidality has been established during pivotal trials or subsequent pharmacovigilance reports [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Moreover, there were no specific exclusion criteria in brodalumab clinical trials regarding history of psychiatric disorders, suicidality, known suicidality risk factors, or substance abuse diagnoses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>].</p><p id="Par11">Along with clinical trials, real-world data allow for a more robust assessment of long-term safety concerns and can help fully characterize the safety profile of brodalumab. In the 5-year US pharmacovigilance report of brodalumab, we highlighted its consistency with the established safety profile reported in long-term clinical trials and previous pharmacovigilance reports [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. In the current report, we detail 6-year pharmacovigilance data in the USA as an update to the 5-year report.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Methods</title><p id="Par12">Methods have been previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Briefly, in this analysis, we summarize pharmacovigilance data reported by US patients and healthcare providers (HCPs) to Ortho Dermatologics (a division of Bausch Health Companies Inc), which markets brodalumab in the USA. Data are from August 15, 2017 through August 14, 2023. Adverse events (AEs) were defined by Medical Dictionary for Regulatory Activities (MedDRA) v26.0 Preferred Terms (PTs) and standardized MedDRA queries. The prevalence of the most common AEs listed in the brodalumab package insert (i.e., AEs with an incidence&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;1%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>] and other AEs of special interest are summarized with descriptive statistics.</p><p id="Par13">Overall drug exposure was estimated as the time between the initial and last prescription-dispensing authorization dates. Detailed medical histories, previous psoriatic therapies, time intervals between previous therapy and brodalumab initiation, and AE dates were either missing or not included in pharmacovigilance reports [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Thus, crude AE reporting rates per 100 patients are reported here.</p><p id="Par14">Ethics approval and informed consent were not required, as the postmarketing data summarized in this report were noninterventional and were not collected as part of a clinical study. The collected data were nonidentifiable.
</p></sec><sec id="Sec5" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec6"><title>Exposure and Unique Cases</title><p id="Par15">Within the 6-year period, data were collected from 5138 US patients who were administered brodalumab, with an estimated exposure of 6900 patient-years. Of the 5138 US patients, 2553 (50%) had &#x02265;&#x02009;1 AE reported; 24% were reported by HCPs, and 76% were reported by patients.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Common AEs</title><p id="Par16">In the brodalumab package insert, common AEs listed include arthralgia, headache, fatigue, diarrhea, oropharyngeal pain, nausea, myalgia, injection-site reactions, influenza, neutropenia, and <italic>Tinea</italic> infections [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. During the 6-year pharmacovigilance period, arthralgia was the most commonly reported AE, as previously reported in the 5-year report [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. There were 13 new cases of arthralgia (135 total events) since the 5-year report, resulting in similar crude AE reporting rates of 2.57 events/100 patients in year&#x000a0;5 and 2.63 events/100 patients in year&#x000a0;6. Since the 5-year report, there were seven new cases of headache (1.03 events/100 patients), five new cases of myalgia (0.74 events/100 patients), five new cases of fatigue (0.97 events/100 patients), three new cases of injection-site reactions (0.80 events/100 patients), and two new cases of diarrhea (0.68 events/100 patients). There was one new case each of oropharyngeal pain (0.45 events/100 patients), nausea (0.58 events/100 patients), and influenza (0.47 events/100 patients) in year&#x000a0;6. There were no new cases of neutropenia (0.02 events/100 patients). In the USA, no <italic>Tinea</italic> infections were reported throughout 6&#x000a0;years.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Other AEs of Special Interest</title><p id="Par17">Other AEs that have been deemed of special interest by the reporter or company include adjudicated major adverse cardiovascular events (MACE), serious infections, fungal infections, inflammatory bowel disease (IBD), malignancy, depression, and completed suicide (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Crude AE reporting rates of clinical events of special interest, as deemed by the reporter or company, per 100 patients. Crude AE reporting rate per 100 patients is the number of clinical events of special interest divided by 5138 brodalumab patients multiplied by 100 patients. Completed suicide events (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0) are reported. Clinical events of special interest were defined using MedDRA v26.0 terms. Serious infection (i.e., prolonged infection or infection requiring intervention) included any MedDRA PT identified under the SOC name <italic>Infections and infestations</italic>, for which the SOC was indicated as &#x0201c;primary&#x0201d; and event seriousness as &#x0201c;serious.&#x0201d; Depression included MedDRA PTs from <italic>Depression</italic> (excluding <italic>Suicide</italic> and <italic>Self-injury</italic>) SMQ (narrow). Malignancy included MedDRA PTs from <italic>Malignancies</italic> SMQ and <italic>Malignant lymphomas</italic> SMQ. Adjudicated MACE included MedDRA PTs from <italic>Ischemic CNS vascular conditions</italic> SMQ, <italic>Ischemic heart disease</italic> SMQ (<italic>Myocardial infarction</italic>), and <italic>Ischemic heart disease</italic> SMQ (<italic>Other</italic>), and where &#x0201c;medically confirmed&#x0201d; was blank. Fungal infection included MedDRA HLTs from <italic>Fungal infections</italic> NEC. Inflammatory bowel disease included MedDRA PTs <italic>Inflammatory bowel disease</italic>, <italic>Crohn&#x02019;s disease</italic>, and <italic>Colitis ulcerative</italic>. <italic>AE</italic> adverse event, <italic>CNS</italic> central nervous system, <italic>HLT</italic> high-level term, <italic>IBD</italic> inflammatory bowel disease, <italic>MACE</italic> major adverse cardiovascular events, <italic>MedDRA v26.0</italic> Medical Dictionary for Regulatory Activities, version 26.0, <italic>NEC</italic> not elsewhere classified, <italic>PT</italic> preferred term, <italic>SMQ</italic> standardized MedDRA query, <italic>SOC</italic> system organ class. <sup>a</sup>Excluding one invalid case of Crohn&#x02019;s disease</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13555_2024_1304_Fig1_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p><sec id="Sec9"><title>Adjudicated MACE</title><p id="Par18">Adjudicated MACE were medically confirmed by the reporting HCP. The crude AE reporting rate of adjudicated MACE for the 6-year period (0.25 events/100 patients) was lower than that of the Psoriasis Longitudinal Assessment and Registry (PSOLAR; 1.55 events/100 patients), an international registry that enrolled 12,095 patients with psoriasis who were receiving or eligible to receive systemic or biologic therapy, with an estimated follow-up of 31,818 patient-years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Throughout the 6&#x000a0;years, a total of 13 cases of adjudicated MACE were reported: 5 cases of myocardial infarction and 1 case each of stroke, ischemic stroke, acute coronary syndrome, left carotid stenosis, unstable angina, coronary artery bypass procedure, coronary artery disease requiring a stent, and transient ischemic attack. For 12 (92%) of these cases, patients had a known history of cardiovascular-associated risk factors (e.g., smoking, obesity), diagnoses/complications (e.g., hypertension, diabetes), or concomitant medications (e.g., aspirin, warfarin, metoprolol). Seven (54%) patients were reported to have continued brodalumab after the event.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Infections</title><p id="Par19">Serious infections (i.e., prolonged infections or infections requiring intervention) were defined as any MedDRA v26.0 PT identified under the System Organ Class (SOC) name &#x0201c;Infections and infestations,&#x0201d; for which the SOC was indicated as &#x0201c;primary&#x0201d; and event seriousness as &#x0201c;serious.&#x0201d; Throughout the 6&#x000a0;years, there were 113 cases of serious infections, 4 (4%) of which were determined to be related to brodalumab. The rate of serious infections (2.20 events/100 patients) slightly decreased compared with the 5-year report (2.23 events/100 patients) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. There was one new case of <italic>Candida</italic> infection since the 5-year report; this patient continued brodalumab. Additionally, there was one new serious fungal infection of the elbow after surgery, and this patient discontinued brodalumab; for this case, the reporter did not report causality, and the company reported possible causality. There were no new cases of hepatitis or tuberculosis (including latent infection or reactivation) compared with the 5-year reporting period [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>].</p><p id="Par20">Since the beginning of the pandemic, there were 56 confirmed and 2 suspected cases of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19). Among these cases, 41 (73%) and 13 (23%) had underlying comorbid conditions or no information regarding comorbidities, respectively. There were no new deaths due to COVID-19 in years&#x000a0;5 and 6 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Inflammatory Bowel Disease</title><p id="Par21">Throughout 6&#x000a0;years, three cases of inflammatory bowel disease were reported (0.06 events/100 patients), including one new case of indeterminate inflammatory bowel disease reported in a patient with a history of diarrhea. The patient discontinued treatment, although the investigator did not attribute the event to brodalumab. The patient rated general well-being as &#x0201c;very well&#x0201d; and abdominal pain as mild.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Malignancy</title><p id="Par22">The crude AE reporting rate for malignancy in year&#x000a0;6 (0.95 events/100 patients; 57 malignancies in 49 cases) was similar to that in year&#x000a0;5 (0.89 events/100 patients; 49 malignancies in 42 cases) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>] and less than that in PSOLAR (1.78 events/100 patients [excluding nonmelanoma skin cancer]) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Types of reported malignancies in new cases included dermatologic malignancies, such as nonmelanoma skin cancer (both basal cell carcinoma and squamous cell carcinoma) and malignant melanoma; invasive ductal breast carcinoma (patient underwent right breast lumpectomy); and lung and breast cancers. In one case, both basal cell carcinoma (recurrence of malignancy) and malignant melanoma were reported. Of the seven new cases, three patients continued, and four patients discontinued brodalumab. Four (8%) of the reported malignancies throughout the 6&#x000a0;years of data were deemed possibly related to brodalumab (keratoacanthoma-type squamous cell carcinoma, basal cell carcinoma, unspecified neoplasm [carcinoma removed from left hip], and breast cancer).</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Depression and Previous Case of Suicide Attempt</title><p id="Par23">Throughout 6&#x000a0;years, there were 58 documented cases of depression, with a crude AE reporting rate slightly lower than that of the 5-year report (1.13 vs 1.14 events/100 patients) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. The 4 (7%) cases deemed as related to brodalumab all occurred before the 4-year pharmacovigilance report [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Of the four new cases in year&#x000a0;6, reporters did not provide causality assessments. No new suicide attempts were reported in year&#x000a0;6, one suicide attempt was previously reported in year&#x000a0;3 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>], and no completed suicides were reported throughout the 6&#x000a0;years.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="Sec14" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par24">This US pharmacovigilance report summarizes 6&#x000a0;years of the most common AEs from the brodalumab package insert and additional AEs of special interest reported from August 15, 2017 through August 14, 2023. Consistent with clinical trials and previous pharmacovigilance reports, brodalumab exhibited a tolerable safety profile with no new safety signals reported. There were no new reports of neutropenia, and, in the USA, no <italic>Tinea</italic> infections have been reported throughout the 6&#x000a0;years. Among 13 cases of adjudicated MACE, most patients (92%) had a history of cardiovascular-associated risk factors, diagnoses/complications, or concomitant medications. Across 6&#x000a0;years, there were 56 cases of confirmed COVID-19 and 2 cases of suspected COVID-19; there were no COVID-19-related deaths during year&#x000a0;6. Most patients with COVID-19 (73%) had underlying comorbid conditions. Among 58 documented cases of depression, 4 (7%) were reported to be related to brodalumab (as described in the 3- and 4-year pharmacovigilance reports) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. No new cases of suicide attempts were reported during year&#x000a0;6, and no completed suicides were reported throughout the 6&#x000a0;years.</p><p id="Par25">To contextualize crude rates of AEs of special interest reported here, we conducted indirect comparisons with those of other recent observational studies. PSOLAR was an intercontinental registry including 12,095 patients with psoriasis receiving or eligible to receive biologic or systemic therapy (median follow-up, 2.5&#x000a0;years) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Crude rates reported in this 6-year report compared with those calculated from PSOLAR were lower for adjudicated MACE (0.25 vs 1.55 events/100 patients), serious infections (2.20 vs 3.95 events/100 patients), and malignancy (0.95 vs 1.78 events/100 patients [excluding nonmelanoma skin cancer in PSOLAR]). The crude rate of IBD observed here was the same as that from the 5-year report (0.06 events/100 patients for both) and lower than the rate previously calculated from a 20-year Danish study, which included a cohort of 235,038 patients with psoriasis receiving topical, systemic, or biologic therapy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. The crude rates of definite Crohn&#x02019;s disease and/or ulcerative colitis were 0.32 events/100 patients among those receiving any therapy (mean follow-up, approximately 6.8&#x000a0;years) and 0.14 events/100 patients among those receiving biologic therapy (mean follow-up, approximately 3.7&#x000a0;years). Because the prescribing information for brodalumab lists Crohn&#x02019;s disease as a contraindication [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>], the crude rate of IBD reported here may therefore be lower than that observed in other broader populations with psoriasis; however, this possibility is unlikely, as the Danish study excluded patients with a history of confirmed or suspected IBD to ensure that only new-onset cases were captured [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Thus, brodalumab is not associated with a heightened risk of adjudicated MACE, serious infection, malignancy, or IBD compared with other systemic or biologic therapies. However, results from both indirect comparisons have limited interpretability due to various factors, including a lack of objective controls and potentially different diagnostic criteria for AEs of special interest.</p><p id="Par26">There are several limitations related to the nature of pharmacovigilance reporting. For instance, only AEs reported to Ortho Dermatologics were documented, and the lack of controlled comparison groups hinders the interpretation of findings. Furthermore, because exact brodalumab administration dates are not available, patient-exposure estimates are based on prescription-dispensing authorization dates. Additionally, a lack of contextual information (typical in data reported via pharmacovigilance channels) restricts our interpretation of the association between brodalumab and reported AEs. Lastly, because brodalumab is only available through a restricted REMS program in the USA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>], treatment is not likely to be prescribed to patients with a known history of depression or suicidal ideation and behavior. Thus, it could be argued that the patient population in this report may not be representative of a real-world distribution of depression. However, a real-world analysis of patients with psoriasis initiating biologic therapy at or after enrollment in the CorEvitas (formerly Corrona) Psoriasis Patient Registry showed that prevalence rates of history of depression were similar among those initiating brodalumab, IL-12/23 or IL-23 inhibitors, or non-brodalumab IL-17A inhibitors (23%, 26%, and 27%, respectively) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. These findings suggest that despite the REMS-based program restrictions, rates of depression observed in this pharmacovigilance report may indeed reflect those of a real-world population. Regardless of potential selection biases, if a treatment were associated with a particular AE, it may be expected to occur within both screened and age-matched nonscreened populations. Further, global postmarketing data on brodalumab suggest the risk of suicide is comparable to that of other common biologics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. In the opinion of the physician authors of this paper, currently available real-world data do not support that brodalumab poses a unique or increased risk of suicide compared with similar biologics.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15" sec-type="conclusion"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par27">When selecting an optimal therapy for psoriasis, HCPs and patients must balance patient-specific factors, efficacy, and risk of AEs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. This 6-year US pharmacovigilance report supports the consistent safety profile of brodalumab established in pivotal trials and previous pharmacovigilance reports. Notably, no new cases of suicide attempts were reported in year&#x000a0;6, and no completed suicides were reported throughout the 6&#x000a0;years in the USA. Overall, brodalumab was well tolerated, with no new safety signals emerging after 6&#x000a0;years of pharmacovigilance monitoring, and a consistently low fungal infection rate.
</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Prior Presentation:</bold> Data included in this publication were presented in part at Maui Derm NP&#x02009;+&#x02009;PA Summer; June 19&#x02013;22, 2024; Colorado Springs, CO. This publication is an annual report of pharmacovigilance data of brodalumab; reports for previous years have been published and are cited where applicable within the text.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><sec id="FPar2"><title>Medical Writing and Editorial Assistance</title><p id="Par28">Writing support and editorial assistance were provided under the direction of the authors by Victoria Maksimova, PhD, and Jenna Lewis, MA, ELS, MedThink SciCom, and funded by Ortho Dermatologics. Ortho Dermatologics is a division of Bausch Health Companies Inc.</p></sec></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>All authors meet International Committee of Medical Journal Editors criteria for authorship for this article. Mark G. Lebwohl contributed to the conception and design of the study. Soo Han Yoon, Nicole N. Rawnsley, and Earl L. Goehring Jr contributed to the acquisition of data. Mark G. Lebwohl, John Y. Koo, April W. Armstrong, Soo Han Yoon, Nicole N. Rawnsley, Earl L. Goehring Jr, Gina D. Mangin, and Abby A. Jacobson contributed to the analysis and interpretation of data. All authors contributed to drafting or critically revising the manuscript for important intellectual content, have given approval of the final version of the manuscript for publication, and agree to be accountable for all aspects of the work.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>Funding for this study and the journal&#x02019;s Rapid Service Fee was provided by Ortho Dermatologics (a division of Bausch Health Companies Inc).</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data Availability</title><p>The datasets generated or analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of Interest</title><p id="Par29">Mark G. Lebwohl is an employee of Mount Sinai; receives research funds from AbbVie, Arcutis Biotherapeutics, Avotres, Boehringer Ingelheim, Cara Therapeutics, Clexio, Dermavant Sciences, Eli Lilly, Incyte, Inozyme, Janssen, Pfizer, Sanofi-Regeneron, and UCB; and is a consultant for Almirall, AltruBio, Apogee, Arcutis Biotherapeutics, AstraZeneca, Atomwise, Avotres, Boehringer Ingelheim, Bristol-Myers Squibb, Castle Biosciences, Celltrion, CorEvitas, Dermavant Sciences, Dermsquared, Evommune, Facilitation of International Dermatology Education, Forte Biosciences, Galderma, Genentech, Incyte, LEO Pharma, Meiji Seika Pharma, Mindera, Pfizer, Sanofi-Regeneron, Seanergy Dermatology, Strata, Takeda, Trevi Therapeutics, and Verrica. John Y. Koo has been a consultant or speaker for AbbVie, Amgen, Eli Lilly, EPI, Janssen, LEO Pharma, Novartis, Ortho Dermatologics, Pfizer, Regeneron, Sanofi, and Sun Pharmaceutical. April W. Armstrong has served as a research investigator for and/or scientific advisor to AbbVie, Almirall, Arcutis Biotherapeutics, ASLAN, Beiersdorf, Boehringer Ingelheim, Bristol-Myers Squibb, Dermavant Sciences, Dermira, Eli Lilly, EPI, Incyte, Janssen, LEO Pharma, Mindera, Nimbus, Novartis, Ortho Dermatologics, Pfizer, Regeneron, Sanofi, Sun Pharmaceutical, and UCB. Bruce E. Strober has been an investigator, scientific director, consultant, or member of a speakers bureau or advisory board for AbbVie, Acelyrin, Alamar, Almirall, Alumis, Amgen, Arcutis, Arena, Aristea, Asana, Boehringer Ingelheim, Bristol-Myers-Squibb, Capital One, Celltrion, CorEvitas and the CorEvitas Psoriasis Patient Registry, Dermavant, Inmagenebio, Incyte, Janssen, Leo, Eli Lilly, Kangpu Pharmaceuticals, Maruho, Okura, Meiji Seika Pharma, Protagonist, Monte Carlo, Takeda, Novartis, Pfizer, UCB Pharma, Rapt, Regeneron, Sanofi-Genzyme, SG Cowen, Union Therapeutics; holds stock options in Connect Biopharma and Mindera Health; and serves as the editor-in-chief of the <italic>Journal of Psoriasis and Psoriatic Arthritis</italic>. Soo Han Yoon is an employee of Salix Pharmaceuticals. Gina D. Mangin has been a speaker for AbbVie, Dermavant, and Sanofi-Regeneron and a consultant for Amgen, Arcutis Biotherapeutics, Bristol-Myers Squibb, Eli Lilly, Incyte, Janssen, and LEO Pharma. Nicole N. Rawnsley, Earl L. Goehring Jr, and Abby A. Jacobson are employees of Bausch Health Companies Inc.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3"><title>Ethical Approval</title><p id="Par30">Ethics approval and informed consent were not required, as the post-marketing data summarized in this report were noninterventional and were not collected as part of a clinical study.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Siliq [package insert]. Bridgewater, NJ: Bausch Health US, LLC; 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vidal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Puig</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrascosa-Carrillo</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonzalez-Cantero</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruiz-Carrascosa</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Velasco-Pastor</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>From messengers to receptors in psoriasis: the role of IL-17RA in disease and treatment</article-title><source>Int J Mol Sci</source><year>2021</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>6740</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms22136740</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34201664</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Vidal S, Puig L, Carrascosa-Carrillo JM, Gonzalez-Cantero A, Ruiz-Carrascosa JC, Velasco-Pastor&#x000a0;AM. From messengers to receptors in psoriasis: the role of IL-17RA in disease and treatment. Int J Mol Sci. 2021;22:6740.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34201664</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tollenaere</surname><given-names>MAX</given-names></name><name><surname>Hebsgaard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ewald</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Signalling of multiple interleukin (IL)-17 family cytokines via IL-17 receptor&#x000a0;A drives psoriasis-related inflammatory pathways</article-title><source>Br J Dermatol</source><year>2021</year><volume>185</volume><fpage>585</fpage><lpage>594</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/bjd.20090</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33792895</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Tollenaere MAX, Hebsgaard J, Ewald DA, et al. Signalling of multiple interleukin (IL)-17 family cytokines via IL-17 receptor&#x000a0;A drives psoriasis-related inflammatory pathways. Br J Dermatol. 2021;185:585&#x02013;94.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33792895</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Rand</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Bigler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gene expression profiles normalized in psoriatic skin by treatment with brodalumab, a human anti-IL-17 receptor monoclonal antibody</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>2014</year><volume>192</volume><fpage>3828</fpage><lpage>3836</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.1301737</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24646743</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Russell CB, Rand H, Bigler J, et al. Gene expression profiles normalized in psoriatic skin by treatment with brodalumab, a human anti-IL-17 receptor monoclonal antibody. J Immunol. 2014;192:3828&#x02013;36.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24646743</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Papp</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Menter</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Leonardi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Long-term efficacy and safety of brodalumab in psoriasis through 120&#x000a0;weeks and after withdrawal and retreatment: subgroup analysis of a randomized phase&#x000a0;III trial (AMAGINE-1)</article-title><source>Br J Dermatol</source><year>2020</year><volume>183</volume><fpage>1037</fpage><lpage>1048</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/bjd.19132</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32286683</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Papp K, Menter A, Leonardi C, et al. Long-term efficacy and safety of brodalumab in psoriasis through 120&#x000a0;weeks and after withdrawal and retreatment: subgroup analysis of a randomized phase&#x000a0;III trial (AMAGINE-1). Br J Dermatol. 2020;183:1037&#x02013;48.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32286683</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Papp</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Reich</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A prospective phase&#x000a0;III, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study of brodalumab in patients with moderate-to-severe plaque psoriasis</article-title><source>Br J Dermatol</source><year>2016</year><volume>175</volume><fpage>273</fpage><lpage>286</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/bjd.14493</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26914406</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Papp KA, Reich K, Paul C, et al. A prospective phase&#x000a0;III, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study of brodalumab in patients with moderate-to-severe plaque psoriasis. Br J Dermatol. 2016;175:273&#x02013;86.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26914406</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lebwohl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Leonardi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Three-year U.S. pharmacovigilance report of brodalumab</article-title><source>Dermatol Ther</source><year>2021</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>e15105</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/dth.15105</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34418244</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Lebwohl M, Leonardi C, Armstrong A, et al. Three-year U.S. pharmacovigilance report of brodalumab. Dermatol Ther. 2021;34:e15105.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34418244</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lebwohl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Leonardi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Two-year US pharmacovigilance report on brodalumab</article-title><source>Dermatol Ther (Heidelb)</source><year>2021</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>173</fpage><lpage>180</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13555-020-00472-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33337520</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Lebwohl M, Leonardi C, Wu JJ, et al. Two-year US pharmacovigilance report on brodalumab. Dermatol Ther (Heidelb). 2021;11:173&#x02013;80.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33337520</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lebwohl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Leonardi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>One-year pharmacovigilance update of brodalumab</article-title><source>J Drugs Dermatol</source><year>2020</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>807</fpage><lpage>808</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.36849/JDD.2020.5138</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32845586</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Lebwohl M, Leonardi C, Wu JJ, et al. One-year pharmacovigilance update of brodalumab. J Drugs Dermatol. 2020;19:807&#x02013;8.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32845586</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Puig</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lebwohl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bachelez</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sobell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobson</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long-term efficacy and safety of brodalumab in the treatment of psoriasis: 120-week results from the randomized, double-blind, placebo- and active comparator-controlled phase&#x000a0;3 AMAGINE-2 trial</article-title><source>J Am Acad Dermatol</source><year>2020</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>352</fpage><lpage>359</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaad.2019.05.095</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31175909</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Puig L, Lebwohl M, Bachelez H, Sobell J, Jacobson AA. Long-term efficacy and safety of brodalumab in the treatment of psoriasis: 120-week results from the randomized, double-blind, placebo- and active comparator-controlled phase&#x000a0;3 AMAGINE-2 trial. J Am Acad Dermatol. 2020;82:352&#x02013;9.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31175909</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lebwohl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Strober</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Menter</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Phase&#x000a0;3 studies comparing brodalumab with ustekinumab in psoriasis</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2015</year><volume>373</volume><fpage>1318</fpage><lpage>1328</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa1503824</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26422722</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Lebwohl M, Strober B, Menter A, et al. Phase&#x000a0;3 studies comparing brodalumab with ustekinumab in psoriasis. N Engl J Med. 2015;373:1318&#x02013;28.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26422722</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lebwohl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Koo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Leonardi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Brodalumab: 4-year US pharmacovigilance report</article-title><source>J Drugs Dermatol</source><year>2023</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>419</fpage><lpage>422</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.36849/JDD.7344</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37026879</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Lebwohl M, Koo J, Leonardi C, et al. Brodalumab: 4-year US pharmacovigilance report. J Drugs Dermatol. 2023;22:419&#x02013;22.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37026879</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Papp</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Leonardi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Menter</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Brodalumab, an anti-interleukin-17-receptor antibody for psoriasis</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2012</year><volume>366</volume><fpage>1181</fpage><lpage>1189</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa1109017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22455412</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Papp KA, Leonardi C, Menter A, et al. Brodalumab, an anti-interleukin-17-receptor antibody for psoriasis. N Engl J Med. 2012;366:1181&#x02013;9.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22455412</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lebwohl</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Koo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Brodalumab: 5-year US pharmacovigilance report</article-title><source>Dermatol Ther (Heidelb)</source><year>2024</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1349</fpage><lpage>1357</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13555-024-01162-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38724839</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Lebwohl MG, Koo J, Armstrong AW, et al. Brodalumab: 5-year US pharmacovigilance report. Dermatol Ther (Heidelb). 2024;14:1349&#x02013;57.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38724839</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lebwohl</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Papp</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Marangell</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Psychiatric adverse events during treatment with brodalumab: analysis of psoriasis clinical trials</article-title><source>J Am Acad Dermatol</source><year>2018</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>9.e5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaad.2017.08.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28985956</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Lebwohl MG, Papp KA, Marangell LB, et al. Psychiatric adverse events during treatment with brodalumab: analysis of psoriasis clinical trials. J Am Acad Dermatol. 2018;78:81&#x02013;9.e5.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28985956</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gottlieb</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalb</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Langley</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Safety observations in 12095 patients with psoriasis enrolled in an international registry (PSOLAR): experience with infliximab and other systemic and biologic therapies</article-title><source>J Drugs Dermatol</source><year>2014</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>1441</fpage><lpage>1448</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25607786</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Gottlieb AB, Kalb RE, Langley RG, et al. Safety observations in 12095 patients with psoriasis enrolled in an international registry (PSOLAR): experience with infliximab and other systemic and biologic therapies. J Drugs Dermatol. 2014;13:1441&#x02013;8.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25607786</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Egeberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Thyssen</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Burisch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Colombel</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Incidence and risk of inflammatory bowel disease in patients with psoriasis&#x02014;a nationwide 20-year cohort study</article-title><source>J Invest Dermatol</source><year>2019</year><volume>139</volume><fpage>316</fpage><lpage>323</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jid.2018.07.029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30130618</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Egeberg A, Thyssen JP, Burisch J, Colombel JF. Incidence and risk of inflammatory bowel disease in patients with psoriasis&#x02014;a nationwide 20-year cohort study. J Invest Dermatol. 2019;139:316&#x02013;23.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30130618</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kimmel G, Lebwohl M, Gordon K, von Csiky-Sessoms S, Cronin A, Jacobson A. Real-world disease severity of patients with psoriasis initiating brodalumab: findings from the Corrona Psoriasis Registry. Slides presented at: 78th Annual Meeting of the American Academy of Dermatology; March 20&#x02013;24, 2020; Denver, CO.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yeroushalmi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartholomew</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Hakimi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Koo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Examining worldwide postmarketing suicides from biologics used for psoriasis with a focus on brodalumab: a cross-sectional analysis using the Food and Drug Administration Adverse Event Reporting System (FAERS)</article-title><source>JAAD Int</source><year>2022</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>119</fpage><lpage>121</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jdin.2022.08.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36248199</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Yeroushalmi S, Chung M, Bartholomew E, Hakimi M, Koo J. Examining worldwide postmarketing suicides from biologics used for psoriasis with a focus on brodalumab: a cross-sectional analysis using the Food and Drug Administration Adverse Event Reporting System (FAERS). JAAD Int. 2022;9:119&#x02013;21.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36248199</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Amin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>No</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Egeberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Choosing first-line biologic treatment for moderate-to-severe psoriasis: what does the evidence say?</article-title><source>Am J Clin Dermatol</source><year>2018</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40257-017-0328-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29080066</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">Amin M, No DJ, Egeberg A, Wu JJ. Choosing first-line biologic treatment for moderate-to-severe psoriasis: what does the evidence say? Am J Clin Dermatol. 2018;19:1&#x02013;13.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29080066</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaushik</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Lebwohl</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Psoriasis: which therapy for which patient: focus on special populations and chronic infections</article-title><source>J Am Acad Dermatol</source><year>2019</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaad.2018.06.056</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30017706</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Kaushik SB, Lebwohl MG. Psoriasis: which therapy for which patient: focus on special populations and chronic infections. J Am Acad Dermatol. 2019;80:43&#x02013;53.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30017706</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaushik</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Lebwohl</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Psoriasis: which therapy for which patient: psoriasis comorbidities and preferred systemic agents</article-title><source>J Am Acad Dermatol</source><year>2019</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaad.2018.06.057</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30017705</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">Kaushik SB, Lebwohl MG. Psoriasis: which therapy for which patient: psoriasis comorbidities and preferred systemic agents. J Am Acad Dermatol. 2019;80:27&#x02013;40.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30017705</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article>