<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="issn">2168-8184</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cureus</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2168-8184</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cureus</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Palo Alto (CA)</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12098765</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7759/cureus.82790</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Trauma</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Orthopedics</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Sports Medicine</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Prevention of Postoperative Graft Rupture by Additional Lateral Extra-articular Tenodesis in Anterior Cruciate Ligament Reconstruction: A Case Series of Four Patients</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Muacevic</surname><given-names>Alexander</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>John R</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Fukuda</surname><given-names>Hideaki</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Asai</surname><given-names>Shigehiro</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>Rei</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ueno</surname><given-names>Keishin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ichiro</surname><given-names>Yamaura</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-5" ref-type="aff">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Iwai</surname><given-names>Hiroki</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-6" ref-type="aff">6</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff-1">
<label>1</label>
Sports Medicine and Joint Center, Inanami Spine and Joint Hospital, Shinagawa, JPN </aff><aff id="aff-2">
<label>2</label>
Orthopedics, Hokusetsu Hospital, Takatsuki, JPN </aff><aff id="aff-3">
<label>3</label>
Orthopedics, Inanami Spine and Joint Hospital, Shinagawa, JPN </aff><aff id="aff-4">
<label>4</label>
Orthopedics, Funabashi Orthopedic Hospital, Funabashi, JPN </aff><aff id="aff-5">
<label>5</label>
Sports Medicine and Joint Center, Funabashi Orthopedic Hospital, Funabashi, JPN </aff><aff id="aff-6">
<label>6</label>
Spine Surgery, Iwai Orthopedic Medical Hospital, Edogawa, JPN </aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">
Hideaki Fukuda <email>hidebee_hidely@yahoo.co.jp</email>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>22</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic"><month>4</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>17</volume><issue>4</issue><elocation-id>e82790</elocation-id><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2025, Fukuda et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Fukuda et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License CC-BY 4.0., which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="https://www.cureus.com/articles/359506-prevention-of-postoperative-graft-rupture-by-additional-lateral-extra-articular-tenodesis-in-anterior-cruciate-ligament-reconstruction-a-case-series-of-four-patients">This article is available from https://www.cureus.com/articles/359506-prevention-of-postoperative-graft-rupture-by-additional-lateral-extra-articular-tenodesis-in-anterior-cruciate-ligament-reconstruction-a-case-series-of-four-patients</self-uri><abstract><p>Anterior cruciate ligament (ACL) reconstruction is commonly performed; however, re-injury and graft failure remain significant concerns, particularly in high-demand individuals. Lateral extra-articular tenodesis (LET) has recently attracted attention as an adjunct to ACL reconstruction to reduce rotational instability and improve surgical outcomes. In this report, we describe four patients who underwent primary ACL reconstruction with additional LET. Despite experiencing significant traumatic knee events postoperatively, all four patients avoided ACL graft re-rupture. These cases suggest LET has a robust protective effect against ACL graft rupture, especially in patients at high risk for postoperative injury.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction</kwd><kwd>case reports</kwd><kwd>iliotibial band</kwd><kwd>lateral extra-articular tenodesis</kwd><kwd>prevention</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Anterior cruciate ligament (ACL) injuries frequently affect athletes and highly active individuals, with reconstruction surgeries widely performed to restore knee stability and function. Despite advancements, re-injury and graft ruptures remain prevalent concerns, particularly among younger, high-demand populations. Recent studies have indicated that lateral extra-articular tenodesis (LET), performed concurrently with ACL reconstruction, significantly enhances rotational knee stability and reduces ACL graft failure rates, especially in patients demonstrating risk factors such as high-grade pivot shift, generalized laxity, or involvement in pivoting sports.</p><p>Surgical indications for LET</p><p>Primary indications for performing LET include chronic ACL injuries, revision cases, cases exhibiting a high-grade pivot shift (Grade 2 or 3), or an increased posterior tibial slope greater than 12 degrees. Additional indications include participation in pivoting sports, generalized ligamentous laxity, knee hyperextension, and high-demand athletic activity.</p><p>Post-injury conservative management</p><p>After sustaining postoperative knee injuries, each patient underwent structured conservative management. Initially, management consisted of external immobilization for two weeks, partial weight-bearing, nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), and icing to reduce inflammation. Subsequently, patients utilized hinged braces, previously used postoperatively, for four to six weeks. Range-of-motion exercises and muscle-strengthening training commenced immediately upon brace application. Patients without significant pain, swelling, or range-of-motion limitations began stationary cycling exercises at three weeks post-injury, followed by jogging between three to four weeks, contingent upon favorable clinical progress. Activities were gradually escalated, culminating in sport-specific activities. Muscle strength and functional recovery were assessed systematically after eight weeks to determine readiness for full return to sports.</p></sec><sec sec-type="cases"><title>Case presentation</title><p>Case 1</p><p>A 16-year-old female national U16-level soccer player underwent primary ACL reconstruction using a bone-tendon-bone (BTB) autograft combined with LET augmentation. Thirteen months postoperatively, she sustained a noncontact knee injury. Postoperative computed tomography (CT) demonstrated an anatomically appropriate femoral tunnel location for LET. Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) revealed injury localized at the LET site, while sagittal MRI confirmed intact ACL graft integrity. Following conservative therapy, she returned to competitive soccer within 2.2 months without ACL graft rupture (Figure <xref rid="FIG1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Case 1 (CT&#x030fb;MRI)</title><p>(A) Postoperative CT scan. The arrow indicates the location of the bone tunnel for the lateral extra-articular tenodesis (LET). (B) MRI at the time of reinjury (fat-suppressed image): injury is observed at the site of the LET. (C) MRI at the time of reinjury (T2 sagittal image): the anterior cruciate ligament (ACL) is intact</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0017-00000082790-i01" position="float"/></fig><p>Case 2</p><p>A 28-year-old male professional mixed martial arts (MMA) athlete underwent primary ACL reconstruction using a quadriceps tendon-bone (QTB) autograft with additional LET. Ten months post-surgery, he experienced a traumatic contact injury to his knee. Postoperative CT scans showed the correct anatomical placement of the femoral tunnel for LET. MRI evaluation revealed LET disruption, while sagittal T2-weighted images indicated that the ACL graft remained intact. After conservative management, he returned successfully to competitive activities within 2.4 months without graft failure (Figure <xref rid="FIG2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Case 2 (CT&#x030fb;MRI)</title><p>(A) Postoperative CT image. The arrow marks the location of the bone tunnel created for the lateral extra-articular tenodesis (LET). (B) MRI at the time of reinjury (fat-suppressed sequence): evidence of damage is seen at the LET site. (C) MRI at the time of reinjury (T2-weighted sagittal view): the anterior cruciate ligament (ACL) remains intact</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0017-00000082790-i02" position="float"/></fig><p>Case 3</p><p>An 18-year-old male basketball player (Tegner Activity Score 7) underwent ACL reconstruction using a BTB autograft augmented by LET. At 15 months post-surgery, he experienced a contact-related traumatic knee injury. CT imaging confirmed proper femoral tunnel placement for LET, whereas MRI (fat-suppressed coronal sequence) identified signal alteration and disruption indicative of LET structural compromise. Sagittal MRI demonstrated intact ACL continuity without rupture. Conservative management facilitated a successful return to sports within 2.0 months post-injury (Figure <xref rid="FIG3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Case 3 (CT&#x030fb;MRI)</title><p>(A) Postoperative computed tomography (CT) image illustrating the anatomical placement of the femoral tunnel for the lateral extra-articular tenodesis (LET), indicated by the arrow. (B) Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) at the time of reinjury (fat-suppressed coronal sequence) reveals signal alteration and disruption at the LET construct site, suggestive of graft failure or structural compromise. (C) Sagittal T2-weighted MRI obtained at reinjury demonstrates preservation of anterior cruciate ligament (ACL) continuity, indicating no evidence of ACL rupture</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0017-00000082790-i03" position="float"/></fig><p>Case 4</p><p>A 17-year-old female basketball player (Tegner Activity Score 7) underwent primary ACL reconstruction utilizing a double-bundle hamstring autograft and LET augmentation. Eight months postoperatively, she sustained a contact injury during basketball play. Postoperative CT scans showed appropriate femoral tunnel placement for LET fixation. MRI examinations revealed extensive soft tissue injury involving the iliotibial band (ITB) and damage around the LET fixation site. Notably, the ACL midsubstance showed partial structural damage with preserved continuity. A follow-up MRI obtained three months post-injury demonstrated improved healing and continuity of the ACL graft. She returned to competitive basketball 3.6 months after conservative management (Figure <xref rid="FIG4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>).</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Case 4 (CT&#x030fb;MRI)</title><p>(A) Postoperative computed tomography (CT) image showing the location of the femoral tunnel for the lateral extra-articular tenodesis (LET), indicated by the yellow arrow. (B) Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) reveals extensive soft tissue damage extending from the region surrounding the tenodesis screw used for LET fixation to the entire iliotibial band (ITB). (C) The midsubstance of the reconstructed anterior cruciate ligament (ACL) demonstrates evident structural injury; however, partial fiber continuity is still preserved. (D) Follow-up MRI obtained three months after reinjury shows improved continuity of the ACL midsubstance, indicating spontaneous healing</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0017-00000082790-i04" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>ACL&#x000a0;reconstruction remains a commonly performed surgical intervention, particularly among athletes and individuals who engage in high-demand pivoting sports. However, postoperative ACL graft ruptures and recurrent injuries remain significant clinical concerns, especially in young athletes returning to competitive sports. Several anatomical, biomechanical, and patient-related risk factors such as generalized ligamentous laxity, high-grade pivot shifts, increased tibial posterior slope, and participation in high-risk sports have been identified, potentially contributing to these re-injuries [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>-<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. To address these challenges, LET&#x000a0;has emerged as a valuable adjunctive procedure combined with ACL reconstruction [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>-<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>-<xref rid="REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. The biomechanical rationale for LET is to augment rotational stability, thereby reducing excessive rotational forces acting on the ACL graft during high-demand activities [<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>-<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].</p><p>Recent studies strongly support the notion that LET, performed in combination with ACL reconstruction, can significantly decrease the rate of postoperative ACL graft failure. Indeed, our presented case series of four patients who underwent primary ACL reconstruction with LET augmentation strongly supports the clinical benefit of this approach. Despite sustaining traumatic reinjuries postoperatively, all four patients successfully avoided ACL graft rupture, suggesting the protective effect of LET against potential graft failures during high-risk events. Current literature strongly supports our clinical experience, demonstrating improved outcomes when LET augmentation is incorporated into ACL reconstruction. For instance, Guy et al. demonstrated elite alpine skiers exhibited markedly lower rates of graft re-rupture (6.5%) when LET was performed in conjunction with ACL reconstruction, compared to isolated ACL reconstruction (34%) [<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Similarly, Monaco et al. highlighted a significant difference in ACL graft rupture rates among adolescent athletes undergoing ACL reconstruction, with zero percent re-rupture rates in patients receiving LET versus a 15% rate in isolated ACL reconstruction [<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Furthermore, Getgood et al. demonstrated significantly reduced re-rupture rates with combined LET and ACL reconstruction procedures (4%) compared to ACL reconstruction alone (11%) [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>].</p><p>Additionally, systematic reviews and meta-analyses have shown that LET significantly improves postoperative rotational knee stability. Song et al. performed a meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials, concluding that the addition of LET to ACL reconstruction not only significantly reduces the graft rupture rate but also effectively improves anterior and rotational knee stability [<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Recent publications by Boksh et al. [<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] and Eggeling et al. [<xref rid="REF11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] further emphasized LET's efficacy in reducing residual anterolateral instability and graft failure rates.</p><p>Despite these convincing data, some controversies remain concerning patient selection and universal indication for LET. Akoto et al. emphasized that routine augmentation might not be necessary for every ACL reconstruction patient, particularly those without evident rotational instability or high-grade pivot shifts [<xref rid="REF12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Therefore, careful preoperative evaluation, individualized surgical indication, and patient-specific considerations remain critical factors when deciding whether LET augmentation should accompany ACL reconstruction.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>The presented four cases underscore the effectiveness of LET in primary ACL reconstructions, particularly for athletes and individuals at elevated risk for ACL re-injury. Adding LET may represent a valuable surgical strategy to significantly reduce the likelihood of ACL graft rupture following postoperative traumatic events.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group content-type="conflict"><title>Disclosures</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Human subjects:</bold> Consent for treatment and open access publication was obtained or waived by all participants in this study. Inanami Spine and Joint Hospital IRB Number 20241103 issued approval 20241103. This study was reviewed and approved by the Institutional Review Board of Inanami Spine and Joint Hospital, approval number [20241103]. Written informed consent was obtained from all participants in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki.
This retrospective study was approved by the Ethics Committee of (Institution Name), and the requirement for informed consent was waived due to the retrospective nature of the study.</p><p><bold>Conflicts of interest:</bold> In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following:</p><p><bold>Payment/services info:</bold> All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work.</p><p><bold>Financial relationships:</bold> All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work.</p><p><bold>Other relationships:</bold> All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="other"><title>Author Contributions</title><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Concept and design:</bold>&#x000a0; Hideaki Fukuda, Shigehiro Asai, Rei Yamaguchi, Keishin Ueno, Yamaura Ichiro, Hiroki Iwai</p><p><bold>Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data:</bold>&#x000a0; Hideaki Fukuda, Shigehiro Asai, Rei Yamaguchi, Keishin Ueno, Yamaura Ichiro, Hiroki Iwai</p><p><bold>Drafting of the manuscript:</bold>&#x000a0; Hideaki Fukuda, Shigehiro Asai, Rei Yamaguchi, Keishin Ueno, Yamaura Ichiro, Hiroki Iwai</p><p><bold>Critical review of the manuscript for important intellectual content:</bold>&#x000a0; Hideaki Fukuda, Shigehiro Asai, Rei Yamaguchi, Keishin Ueno, Yamaura Ichiro, Hiroki Iwai</p><p><bold>Supervision:</bold>&#x000a0; Hideaki Fukuda, Shigehiro Asai, Rei Yamaguchi, Keishin Ueno, Yamaura Ichiro, Hiroki Iwai</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="REF1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Lateral extra-articular tenodesis reduces failure of hamstring tendon autograft anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction: two-year outcomes from the STABILITY study randomized clinical trial</article-title><source>Am J Sports Med</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Getgood</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bryant</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Litchfield</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>285</fpage><lpage>297</lpage><volume>48</volume><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31940222</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Anterolateral procedure in adolescents undergoing ACL reconstruction with hamstrings: a comparative study</article-title><source>Am J Sports Med</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Monaco</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mazza</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Redler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>3358</fpage><lpage>3366</lpage><volume>50</volume><year>2022</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Risk of graft rupture after adding a lateral extra-articular procedure at the time of ACL reconstruction: a retrospective comparative study of elite alpine skiers from the French national team</article-title><source>Am J Sports Med</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Guy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fayard</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Saithna</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>1609</fpage><lpage>1617</lpage><volume>50</volume><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35416071</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Lateral extra-articular tenodesis reduces rotational laxity when combined with ACL reconstruction: a systematic review of the literature</article-title><source>Arthroscopy</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Hewison</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kaniki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Remtulla</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bryant</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Getgood</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>2022</fpage><lpage>2034</lpage><volume>31</volume><year>2015</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26116497</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Clinical outcomes of combined lateral extra-articular tenodesis and intra-articular ACL reconstruction in addressing ACL injury with anterolateral complex deficiency: a meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials</article-title><source>Arthroscopy</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>1802</fpage><lpage>1813</lpage><volume>32</volume><year>2016</year><uri xlink:href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/284077827_Clinical_Outcomes_of_Combined_Lateral_Extra-articular_Tenodesis_and_Intra-articular_Anterior_Cruciate_Ligament_Reconstruction_in_Addressing_High-Grade_Pivot-Shift_Phenomenon">https://www.researchgate.net/publication/284077827_Clinical_Outcomes_of_Combined_Lateral_Extra-articular_Tenodesis_and_Intra-articular_Anterior_Cruciate_Ligament_Reconstruction_in_Addressing_High-Grade_Pivot-Shift_Phenomenon</uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Lateral extra-articular tenodesis reduces graft failure and persistent instability in ACL reconstruction: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Am J Sports Med</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Boksh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Haque</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>190</fpage><lpage>202</lpage><volume>52</volume><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38164667</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Anterolateral ligament expert group consensus paper on the management of internal rotation and instability of the anterior cruciate ligament-deficient knee</article-title><source>J Orthop Traumatol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Sonnery-Cottet</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Daggett</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fayard</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>106</lpage><volume>18</volume><year>2017</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28220268</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Extra-articular lateral tenodesis in ACL reconstruction-indication, surgical technique, results</article-title><source>Arthroskopie</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>K&#x000e4;rcher</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Herbst</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>100</fpage><lpage>108</lpage><volume>27</volume><year>2014</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Anterolateral tenodesis or anterolateral ligament complex reconstruction: effect of flexion angle at graft fixation when combined with ACL reconstruction</article-title><source>Am J Sports Med</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Inderhaug</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stephen</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Amis</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>3089</fpage><lpage>3097</lpage><volume>45</volume><year>2017</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28898106</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Does combined intra- and extraarticular ACL reconstruction improve function and stability? A meta-analysis</article-title><source>Clin Orthop Relat Res</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Rezende</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>de Moraes</surname><given-names>VY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Martimbianco</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Luzo</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>da Silveira Franciozi</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Belloti</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>2609</fpage><lpage>2618</lpage><volume>473</volume><year>2015</year><uri xlink:href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC4488196/#:~:text=Combined%20intra%2D%20and%20extraarticular%20ACL%20reconstruction%20provided%20marginally%20improved%20knee,patient%2Dreported%20functional%20outcomes%20scores.">https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC4488196/#:~:text=Combined%20intra%2D%20and%20extraarticular%20ACL%20reconstruction%20provided%20marginally%20improved%20knee,patient%2Dreported%20functional%20outcomes%20scores.</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25845949</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Additional lateral extra-articular tenodesis in revision ACL reconstruction does not influence the outcome of patients with low-grade anterior knee laxity</article-title><source>Arch Orthop Trauma Surg</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Eggeling</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Drenck</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Frings</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>291</fpage><lpage>299</lpage><volume>142</volume><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34455475</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Slope-correction osteotomy with lateral extra-articular tenodesis and revision ACL reconstruction is highly effective in treating high-grade anterior knee laxity</article-title><source>Am J Sports Med</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Akoto</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alm</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Drenck</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Frings</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Krause</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Frosch</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>3478</fpage><lpage>3485</lpage><volume>48</volume><year>2020</year><uri xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/33135908/">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/33135908/</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33135908</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>