<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Emerg Microbes Infect</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Emerg Microbes Infect</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Emerging Microbes &#x00026; Infections</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2222-1751</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Taylor &#x00026; Francis</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40353576</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12093800</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2505645</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/22221751.2025.2505645</article-id><article-version vocab="JAV" vocab-identifier="http://www.niso.org/publications/rp/RP-8-2008.pdf" vocab-term="Version of Record" article-version-type="VoR">Version of Record</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Gene-modified genotype II live attenuated African swine fever virus induces cross-protection against genotype I but not against genotype IX</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="right-running-head">EMERGING MICROBES &#x00026; INFECTIONS</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="left-running-head">A. RATHAKRISHNAN ET AL.</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rathakrishnan</surname><given-names>Anusyah</given-names></name><xref rid="AF1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hemmink</surname><given-names>Johanneke D.</given-names></name><xref rid="AF2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Petrovan</surname><given-names>Vlad</given-names></name><xref rid="AF1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Reis</surname><given-names>Ana Luisa</given-names></name><xref rid="AF1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3845-3016</contrib-id><name><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>Linda K.</given-names></name><xref rid="AF1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><aff id="AF1"><label>a</label><institution>The Pirbright Institute</institution>, <city>Woking</city>, <country>United Kingdom</country></aff><aff id="AF2"><label>b</label><institution>International Livestock Research Institute</institution>, <city>Nairobi</city>, <country>Kenya</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>CONTACT</label> Linda K. Dixon <email xlink:href="linda.dixon@pirbright.ac.uk">linda.dixon@pirbright.ac.uk</email>
<institution>The Pirbright Institute</institution>, <city>Woking</city>, <state>Surrey</state>, <country>United Kingdom</country></corresp></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>12</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic"><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>12</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id seq="134">2505645</elocation-id><pub-history><event event-type="received"><date><day>27</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="revised"><date><day>11</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="accepted"><date><day>8</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="tagger"><event-desc>Nova techset</event-desc><date><day>12</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="build-issue-online"><event-desc>Converted to JATS 1.2 by Nova Techset</event-desc><date><day>12</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2025 The Author(s). Published by Informa UK Limited, trading as Taylor &#x00026; Francis Group, on behalf of Shanghai Shangyixun Cultural Communication Co., Ltd</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Author(s)</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. The terms on which this article has been published allow the posting of the Accepted Manuscript in a repository by the author(s) or with their consent.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="TEMI_14_2505645.pdf"/><abstract><title>ABSTRACT</title><p>African swine fever virus originated in a wildlife cycle in East Africa and spread to domestic pigs. At least twenty-three genotypes are present in Africa whereas only genotypes I and II have spread to other continents. Vaccine development has been directed mainly to genotype II. The ability of genotype II vaccines to induce cross-protection against other genotypes is unknown. Here, we compared cross-protection induced in pigs by an attenuated multiple gene-deleted genotype II modified live vaccine candidate against challenge with different genotypes. Protection against homologous virulent genotype II virus was 100%. Cross-protection against virulent genotype I virus varied between 57 and 71%. However, no protection was achieved against genotype IX challenge. The results indicate potential for use of vaccines in regions where genotypes I and II are circulating.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>KEYWORDS</title><kwd>African swine fever virus</kwd><kwd>vaccine</kwd><kwd>cross-protection</kwd><kwd>genotype</kwd><kwd>immune response</kwd><kwd>immune evasion</kwd></kwd-group><support-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>UK Government</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="open-funder-registry">10.13039/100013986</institution-id></institution-wrap>
</funding-source><award-id>300504</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>FCDO</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="open-funder-registry">10.13039/501100020171</institution-id></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by UKRI Biotechnology and Biological Sciences Research Council [BBS/E/I/ 00007039, BBS/E/I/00007037, BBS/E/I/00007031, BBS/E/PI/230001B, BBSE/PI/230002A, BBS/E/PI/23NB0004]. Some parts of the quoted research were funded in part by UK Aid from the UK Government through Global Alliance for Livestock Veterinary Medicines (GALVmed) (Project 300504) and FCDO.</funding-statement></funding-group></support-group><counts><fig-count count="6"/><table-count count="0"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="26"/><page-count count="12"/><word-count count="5820"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" disp-level="1" id="S001"><title>Introduction</title><p>African swine fever virus (ASFV) is maintained in wild suids and <italic toggle="yes">Ornithodoros</italic> species of soft ticks in East and Southern Africa causing few clinical signs. In domestic pigs and wild boar, ASFV causes a haemorrhagic disease with fatality approaching 100%.</p><p>ASFV is a large cytoplasmic DNA virus coding for approximately 170 to 190 proteins. Partial sequencing of the B646L gene, which codes for the major capsid protein p72, identified at least 23 genotypes in Africa [<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. These originate from the sylvatic cycle in East Africa. However, only five genotypes, I, II, VIII, IX and X, have been reported to have an extended field presence in domestic pigs. Genotype I is the prevalent strain in West and Central Africa and genotypes IX, X and VIII in East African countries [<xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Genotype II was first described in Madagascar and Mozambique but has now been detected in a further 8 African countries including two West African countries [<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Phylogenetic analysis of complete ASFV genome sequences from 9 genotypes available in the NCBI database identified 6 distinct clusters. Genotypes IX and X clusters are most closely related to each other but most widely separated from the other genome clusters [<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Genotype II ASFV spread to Georgia in the Caucasus region and from there to Russia and Eastern Europe, entering the European Union in 2014. In 2018, genotype II ASFV spread to China, causing huge economic losses and a large reduction of the pig population. Subsequently, ASFV has spread to most Asian countries, several in Oceania and the Caribbean (FAO Empres, WOAH WAHIS). In 2021, low virulent genotype I viruses [<xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] and in 2023, a highly virulent hybrid genotype I, genotype II virus was detected in China [<xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. This hybrid virus was later detected in Vietnam and Russia [<xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>].</p><p>Two modified live vaccines (MLV) for genotype II ASFV were licensed for use in Vietnam in 2023 [<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">8-10</xref>]. However, the potential for induction of cross-protection by genotype II MLVs against different genotypes has been little studied and this remains a crucial knowledge gap for the effective use of ASFV vaccines globally. The ability of sera from infected pigs to inhibit red blood cell binding to infected cells (HAD), correlated with cross-protection and identified 8 ASFV serotypes. Sequences of the <italic toggle="yes">EP402R</italic> gene coding for the protein required for HAD, pCD2v, and the adjacent <italic toggle="yes">EP153R</italic> gene, were used to assign additional strains in serotype groups [<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] which may predict cross-protection. However, few of these predictions have been tested experimentally with currently circulating strains. Previously an attenuated genotype I virus (BA71&#x00394;CD2v) was shown to induce cross-protection against genotype II. Cross-protection against virulent genotype IX was achieved after boosting with virulent genotype I but not after boost with the same attenuated genotype I [<xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Similarly, immunization of pigs with natural attenuated genotype I strain OURT88/3 and boost with virulent genotype I OURT88/1 induced cross-protection against genotype X challenge [<xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>].</p><p>Here we investigated cross-protection induced by an attenuated multiple gene-deleted genotype II strain [<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] against prevalent genotypes I and IX, that circulate in domestic pigs in Africa. High levels of protection against homologous virulent genotype II challenge were induced and partial cross-protection against challenge with virulent genotype I but no protection was obtained following challenge with virulent genotype IX virus. These results suggest that MLV ASFV vaccines based on genotype II may be useful in regions where genotype I is circulating.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" disp-level="1" id="S002"><title>Materials and methods</title><p>Full experimental details are provided in Supplementary information.</p><sec disp-level="2" id="S002-S2001"><title>Cells and viruses</title><p>Porcine bone marrow cells (PBMs) were cultured in EBSS supplemented with 10% pig serum, 1% pen-strep and 1% HEPES. Recombinant ASFV modified live vaccine (MLV) candidate, Georgia&#x00394;DP148R&#x00394;K145R&#x00394;EP153R-CD2v_mutantQ96R/K108D (G&#x00394;DKE-Cmut) [<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], virulent genotype II ASFV Georgia 2007/1, genotype I Benin 97/1 [<xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] and Kenya 1033 genotype IX isolate were described previously [<xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].</p></sec><sec disp-level="2" id="S002-S2002"><title>In vivo immunization and challenge of pigs</title><p>All three experiments were carried out in ILRI, Kenya as shown in <xref rid="F0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>. Groups of 7 pigs were immunized and boosted with G&#x00394;DKE-Cmut. Immunized pigs were challenged with virulent virus of genotypes I, II or IX in parallel with groups of 3 or 4 na&#x000ef;ve pigs as controls for the inoculum. Daily clinical scores were obtained [<xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] and blood samples were collected at different days post-immunization (dpi) and days post-challenge (dpc) as well as at termination. Animals were euthanized at a moderate severity humane endpoint or at the end of the study. At necropsy, macroscopic lesions typical of ASFV infection were scored [<xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>].
<fig position="float" id="F0001"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Experimental timelines. In every experiment, the pig group numbers, days, doses and viruses used for immunization, boost and challenge are shown.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="TEMI_A_2505645_F0001_OC" content-type="color" specific-use="web-only" position="float"/><graphic xlink:href="TEMI_A_2505645_F0001_PC" content-type="color" specific-use="print-only" position="float"/></alternatives></fig></p></sec><sec disp-level="2" id="S002-S2003"><title>ASFV genome in blood</title><p>DNA was extracted from whole blood collected in EDTA vacutainers and ASFV genome copies were measured by real time PCR. Standard curves from an ASFV p72 mimic plasmid were included to allow for genome quantification [<xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Results are presented as log<sub>10</sub> genome copies/mL. The cut-off for accurate detection was 10<sup>3</sup> ASFV genome copies/mL. The virus genome levels were defined as low if &#x02264;10<sup>4</sup> genome copies/mL, moderate if between 10<sup>4</sup> and 10<sup>6</sup> genome copies/mL and high if &#x02265;10<sup>6</sup> genome copies per mL.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2" id="S002-S2004"><title>ASFV P72 antibodies in serum</title><p>Antibody responses against the ASFV p72 protein were measured in serum using a commercial blocking ELISA (INgezim PPA Compac, Ingenasa). Samples showing &#x0003e;50% blocking rate were considered as positive, while anything &#x0003c;40% was considered as negative. Samples with blocking between 40 and 50% were considered as doubtful.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2" id="S002-S2005"><title>IFN-&#x003b3; cellular responses in pigs</title><p>Levels of the IFN-&#x003b3; cellular responses in the isolated PBMCs of vaccinated pigs were measured after stimulation with different virus strains using an ELISpot assay [<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The results are presented as spot forming cells (SFC) per million PBMC.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2" id="S002-S2006"><title>Statistical analyses</title><p>Statistical analyses were used to evaluate the differences between immunized and na&#x000ef;ve control pigs from day 0 post-challenge (42&#x02005;dpi) up to 6- or 7&#x02005;dpc. The parameters compared include rectal temperatures, clinical scores, post-mortem scores and genome copies/mL. Two-way ANOVA either using the mixed effect model (when missing values are present) or repeated measure model, both with Geisser-Greenhouse correction, was carried out alongside Tukey&#x02019;s multiple comparisons test (GraphPad Prism 10) for all parameters except post-mortem scores. For the post-mortem scores, unpaired, non-parametric, Mann&#x02013;Whitney test was employed to evaluate differences in the total cumulative scores between groups.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" disp-level="1" id="S003"><title>Results</title><p>Pigs were immunized and boosted with an attenuated genotype II virus with deletions of <italic toggle="yes">DP148R</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">K145R</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">EP153R,</italic> expressing a non-HAD pCD2v protein with mutations of residues Q96R and K108D. The challenge was with virulent genotype I Benin 97/1, virulent genotype II Georgia 2007/1 [<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] or virulent genotype IX Kenya 1033 [<xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. <xref rid="F0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref> shows the timeline of each of the experiments.</p><sec disp-level="2" id="S003-S2001"><title>Immunization and boost with G&#x00394;DKE-Cmut partially protects pigs against challenge with virulent genotype I strain Benin 97/1</title><sec disp-level="3" id="S003-S2001-S3001"><title>Clinical scores and temperatures</title><p>In the first experiment, one group of 7 pigs (Group A) was immunized intramuscularly with 5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>4</sup> TCID<sub>50</sub> of G&#x00394;DKE-Cmut MLV and boosted by the same route and dose at 21&#x02005;dpi. At 42&#x02005;dpi, the pigs were challenged intramuscularly with 10<sup>3</sup> HAD<sub>50</sub> genotype I Benin 97/1 in parallel with 4 na&#x000ef;ve pigs (Group B). After immunization and boost, none of the animals in Group A developed a body temperature above 40.5&#x000b0;C. Mild transient clinical signs including lethargy or joint swelling were observed in some animals. These are likely to have been non-procedure related and were also observed in some pigs before immunization (<xref rid="F0002" ref-type="fig">Figures 2</xref> and <xref rid="F0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>(A)).
<fig position="float" id="F0002"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Daily temperatures of pigs. Daily rectal temperatures for pigs in each of the three experiments are shown. Panels A and B show results from experiment 1, panels C and D from experiment 2, panels E, F, G, and H from experiment 3.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="TEMI_A_2505645_F0002_OC" content-type="color" specific-use="web-only" position="float"/><graphic xlink:href="TEMI_A_2505645_F0002_PC" content-type="color" specific-use="print-only" position="float"/></alternatives></fig>
<fig position="float" id="F0003"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Clinical scores of pigs. Panels A and B show results from experiment 1, panels C and D from experiment 2, panels E, F, G and H from experiment 3.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="TEMI_A_2505645_F0003_OC" content-type="color" specific-use="web-only" position="float"/><graphic xlink:href="TEMI_A_2505645_F0003_PC" content-type="color" specific-use="print-only" position="float"/></alternatives></fig></p><p>After challenge, all pigs in Group A showed an increase in temperature above 40.5&#x000b0;C. Two pigs reached the moderate severity humane endpoint (A095 and A097) on 47 or 48&#x02005;dpi (5- or 6&#x02005;dpc). The remaining five pigs survived until the end of the experiment and had temperatures above 40.5&#x000b0;C for one to three days. Maximum daily clinical scores after challenge in Group A, were between 13 and 16 on 46 or 47&#x02005;dpi for five pigs, including those that reached the humane endpoint on 47 or 48&#x02005;dpi. The other two pigs (A096 and A101) had a maximum daily clinical score of 4 or 10 on 47 and 48&#x02005;dpi, respectively. Daily clinical scores reduced after 48&#x02005;dpi in the pigs that survived until the end of the experiment.</p><p>All the control pigs (Group B), challenged with genotype I, reached the humane endpoint by 6&#x02005;dpc. Temperatures increased to above 40.5&#x000b0;C from 3&#x02005;dpc (<xref rid="F0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>(B)). Other clinical signs included loss of appetite and reluctance to get up (<xref rid="F0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>(B)).</p><p>The mean temperatures for pigs in Groups A and B after challenge were similar with no statistical difference except on the day of challenge when pigs in Group A had statistically higher mean temperatures than those in Group B (Figure S1A). Comparisons of the mean clinical scores between pigs in Groups A and B showed similarly increasing scores between 3 to 6&#x02005;dpc. At 6&#x02005;dpc, mean scores for pigs in Group A were statistically lower than for those in Group B (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0197) (Figure S2A).</p></sec><sec disp-level="3" id="S003-S2001-S3002"><title>ASFV genome in blood</title><p>No virus genome was detected post-immunization or boost in any of the pigs in Group A (<xref rid="F0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>(A)). After challenge with genotype I Benin97/1 at 42&#x02005;dpi, the two Group A pigs which reached the humane endpoint on 47 or 48&#x02005;dpi, had 10<sup>7.6</sup> or 10<sup>8.7</sup> genome copies/mL blood. In the pigs that survived challenge, virus genome was detected between 49 to 63&#x02005;dpi, decreasing from the highest values of 10<sup>5.7-7.8</sup> on 49&#x02005;dpi to 10<sup>4.4-7.0</sup> at termination (63&#x02005;dpi). One pig, A096, had no virus genome detected in blood after challenge (<xref rid="F0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>(A)).
<fig position="float" id="F0004"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Virus genome copies in blood. Virus genome copies per mL EDTA blood were measured by qPCR in samples collected at the indicated time points in each experiment. Values are shown on the y-axis on a log 10 scale. Panels A and B show results from experiment 1, panels C and D from experiment 2, panels E, F, G and H from experiment 3.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="TEMI_A_2505645_F0004_OC" content-type="color" specific-use="web-only" position="float"/><graphic xlink:href="TEMI_A_2505645_F0004_PC" content-type="color" specific-use="print-only" position="float"/></alternatives></fig></p><p>In the challenge control Group B, virus genome in blood was detected at 3&#x02005;dpc in three of the four pigs. On the day of cull, these pigs had genome copies per mL of 10<sup>8.9-9.1</sup> (<xref rid="F0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>(B)).</p><p>Mean values for virus genome copies per/mL were lower in pigs in Group A compared to Group B at 3&#x02005;dpc reaching statistical significance (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0399) at the peak of viremia measured on 5-, 6- or 7&#x02005;dpc (Figure S3A).</p></sec><sec disp-level="3" id="S003-S2001-S3003"><title>Macroscopic lesions observed at necropsy</title><p>One pig from Group A (A095), which reached the humane endpoint after challenge, had higher lesion scores compared to the second pig which reached the endpoint (A097) (<xref rid="F0005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>(A)). Lesions observed included enlargement and signs of haemorrhage in the spleen and several lymph nodes. Other signs included petechias on the medulla of the kidney, mild lung oedema, pericarditis and ascites. Three pigs (A096, A100, A101) had severe pericarditis and one pig (A095) had mild pericarditis. The mucosa of stomach and duodenum were slightly haemorrhagic in 4 pigs and one pig had skin haemorrhages in the ears. In control Group B, lesion scores associated with acute ASF ranged between 9 and 12.5 (<xref rid="F0005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>(A)). When compared, no significant differences in lesion scores were observed between individual pigs nor between groups A and B (Figure S4A).
<fig position="float" id="F0005"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Macroscopic lesion scores at termination. Macroscopic lesions were scored at termination either at a moderate severity humane endpoint or at the end of the experiment for surviving pigs. Panels show results from experiments 1 to 3. The x-axis shows the pig number and y axis the cumulative lesion score. Colours indicate lesions observed in the thoracic, abdominal, and skin/oral cavities as well as in the lymphoid system. Lesions in the thoracic cavity include the presence of thoracic exudates as well as lesions affecting cardio-respiratory system (black bar). Lesions in the abdominal cavity include the presence of ascites along with the presence of lesions affecting the gastrointestinal system including the stomach, intestines, liver and gallbladder (pink bar). Lesions in lymphoid tissues include tonsils, thymus, spleen and several lymph nodes (teal bar). The grey bar shows lesions in skin and oral cavity.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="TEMI_A_2505645_F0005_OC" content-type="color" specific-use="web-only" position="float"/><graphic xlink:href="TEMI_A_2505645_F0005_PC" content-type="color" specific-use="print-only" position="float"/></alternatives></fig></p></sec><sec disp-level="3" id="S003-S2001-S3004"><title>Immune responses</title><p>Serum levels of ASFV-specific antibodies (<xref rid="F0006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>(A)) were above the cut-off in 4 pigs in Group A at 14&#x02005;dpi and in all animals by 21&#x02005;dpi.
<fig position="float" id="F0006"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Antibody and cellular immune responses. Antibodies against ASFV p72 were measured using a commercial blocking ELISA. The results from different pig groups as labelled are shown in panels A, B, C and D. The x-axis shows days post-immunization that samples were collected. The y-axis shows % blocking. PBMCs collected before immunization, boost and challenge of pigs from Groups A, C, E and F were either mock-stimulated or stimulated with genotype II Georgia 2007/1, genotype I Benin97/1 or genotype IX Kenya 1033. Panels E, F, G and H show numbers of IFN-&#x003b3; producing cells per 10<sup>6</sup> cells measured by ELISpot assay (y-axis) and days post-immunization that cells were collected are shown on the x-axis.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="TEMI_A_2505645_F0006_OC" content-type="color" specific-use="web-only" position="float"/><graphic xlink:href="TEMI_A_2505645_F0006_PC" content-type="color" specific-use="print-only" position="float"/></alternatives></fig></p><p>The numbers of IFN-&#x003b3; producing cells in pigs from Group A showed a trend to be higher after genotype II stimulation, followed by genotype I and lowest for genotype IX stimulation (<xref rid="F0006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>(E), S5A-D). However, these differences were not significant and did not correlate with survival of individual pigs.</p></sec></sec><sec disp-level="2" id="S003-S2002"><title>Immunization and boost with a lower dose of attenuated genotype II G&#x00394;DKE-Cmut partially protects pigs from challenge with virulent genotype I Benin 97/1</title><sec disp-level="3" id="S003-S2002-S3001"><title>Temperatures and clinical scores</title><p>In experiment 2, we used the same prime dose as in experiment 1 but reduced the boost dose by 5-fold to determine if this may affect the levels of protection. Seven pigs (Group C) were immunized with G&#x00394;DKE-Cmut at 5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>4</sup> TCID<sub>50</sub> and boosted with 1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10 <sup>4</sup> after 21 days. After a further 21 days, the pigs were challenged with Benin 97/1 10<sup>3</sup> HAD<sub>50</sub> in parallel with a control group of 4 na&#x000ef;ve pigs (Group D) (<xref rid="F0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). After immunization, pig C024 had a temperature of 41&#x000b0;C at 7&#x02005;dpi and pig C014 had a temperature of 40.7&#x000b0;C at 8&#x02005;dpi. No further temperatures above 40.5&#x000b0;C were detected post-immunization or boost (<xref rid="F0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>(C)). Mild transient clinical signs including lethargy or joint swelling were observed in some animals (<xref rid="F0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>(C)). These are likely to have been non-procedure related and were also observed in some pigs before immunization.</p><p>After challenge at 42&#x02005;dpi, three pigs (C003, C011 and C017) reached the moderate severity endpoint at 47-, 48-, and 56&#x02005;dpi, respectively (5-, 6- or 14 dpc, respectively). Of the four pigs which survived, one had a temperature &#x0003e;40.5&#x000b0;C on 47&#x02005;dpi (5 dpc) but no further temperatures &#x0003e;40.5&#x000b0;C or other clinical signs. The other three Group C pigs had no increase in temperatures (<xref rid="F0002" ref-type="fig">Figures 2</xref> and <xref rid="F0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>(C)).</p><p>The 4 pigs in the non-immune control Group D were all terminated on 5 or 6dpc as expected, showing signs typical of acute ASF including high temperatures, loss of appetite and increasing lethargy (<xref rid="F0002" ref-type="fig">Figures 2</xref> and <xref rid="F0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>(D)).</p><p>No significant mean differences in temperature were detected between pigs in Groups C and D after challenge (Figure S1B). However, when the overall clinical scores were compared between Groups C and D, the scores of the immunized pigs were clearly lower than the na&#x000ef;ve-challenged pigs, with significant difference on 4 dpc (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.022) and on 6 dpc (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0008) (Figure S2B).</p><p>When we compared Group A (from Experiment 1) which received the same immunization dose as Group C, but a 5-fold higher booster dose, no significant differences were found after challenge in clinical scores (Figure S2C). The only significant difference was noted for temperatures on 4 dpc (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0287) (Figure S1C).</p></sec><sec disp-level="3" id="S003-S2002-S3002"><title>Virus genome in blood</title><p>One pig in Group C (C014) had a moderate level, 10<sup>4.5</sup>, of genome copies per mL blood on 7&#x02005;dpi. No virus genome was detected in any of the other Group C pigs after immunization or boost (<xref rid="F0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>(C)).</p><p>After challenge, high genome copy numbers per mL (10<sup>7.75-7.85</sup>) were detected in blood from two of the pigs (C003 and C011), which were euthanized at the humane end point on 5 or 6&#x02005;dpc, respectively. Surprisingly, no virus genome was detected in blood from the other pig which was culled on 14&#x02005;dpc at the humane endpoint (<xref rid="F0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>(C)). At 7&#x02005;dpc, ASFV genome copies of 10<sup>4.3</sup> per mL were detected in blood from pig C023, and at 14&#x02005;dpc 10<sup>6.9</sup> genome copies per mL blood in pig C016. In the other surviving pigs, no virus genome was detected after challenge. As expected, high levels of genome copies per mL (10<sup>8.8-9.3</sup>) were detected in blood from pigs in control Group D at termination (<xref rid="F0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>(D)). When compared, Group C showed lower levels of virus genome copies per mL blood than Group D, and at 5, 6 or 7&#x02005;dpc, these differences were statistically significant (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0045) (Figure S3B).</p><p>The mean genome copies per mL blood for pigs in Group C tended to be lower in comparison with mean values for pigs in Group A although they were not statistically significant (Figure S3C).</p></sec><sec disp-level="3" id="S003-S2002-S3003"><title>Macroscopic lesion scores at necropsy</title><p>At necropsy, the three pigs from Group C (C003, C011 and C017), which reached the humane endpoint, showed enlargement and signs of haemorrhage in the spleen and several lymph nodes. Mild or moderate lung oedema and pericarditis were observed in these three pigs and one pig had dark kidneys with petechias and mild haemorrhagic mucosa in the stomach and duodenum (<xref rid="F0005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>(B)). Of the pigs that survived until termination of the experiment, one pig (C014) had lesions typical of ASF. The other surviving pigs had, as expected, fewer lesions and low lesion scores of 5 or 6.</p><p>The control pigs in Group D had more severe signs typical of acute ASF (<xref rid="F0005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>(B)). Comparisons of the total scores showed no statistical significance between the pigs in Group C and D (Figure S4B). We also found no significant differences between immunized and genotype I challenged pigs of Group A and C (Figure S4C).</p></sec><sec disp-level="3" id="S003-S2002-S3004"><title>Immune responses</title><p>Antibody levels above the cut-off were detected in five pigs in Group C by 14&#x02005;dpi and in all animals by 35&#x02005;dpi (<xref rid="F0006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>(B)).</p><p>The highest numbers of IFN-&#x003b3; producing cells were seen in response to genotype II virus stimulation, which increased after boost in most pigs. On average, responses to genotype I and IX were lower but some outliers showed a higher response (<xref rid="F0006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>(F), S5E-H). Interestingly, pig C011, which reached the humane end point at 6 dpc, had the highest number of IFN-&#x003b3; producing cells following stimulation with both Georgia 2007/1 and Benin 97/1 (Figure S5E-H).</p></sec></sec><sec disp-level="2" id="S003-S2003"><title>Immunization and boost with G&#x00394;DKE-Cmut induces protection against virulent genotype II challenge but no cross-protection against virulent genotype IX challenge</title><p>The ability of the attenuated genotype II virus G&#x00394;DKE-Cmut to induce cross-protection against virulent genotype IX Kenya 1033 was compared with protection induced against genotype II virus challenge. Two groups of seven pigs (Groups E and F) were immunized intramuscularly with 5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>4</sup> TCID<sub>50</sub> of G&#x00394;DKE-Cmut on day 0 and pigs were boosted at 21&#x02005;dpi with the same dose and route. At 42&#x02005;dpi, pigs in Group E were challenged with 10<sup>3</sup> HAD<sub>50</sub> Georgia2007/1 genotype II in parallel with three na&#x000ef;ve pigs as controls for the challenge (Group G). Immunized pigs in Group F were challenged with 10<sup>2</sup> HAD<sub>50</sub> Kenya 1033 genotype IX in parallel with four challenge control pigs (Group H) (<xref rid="F0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>).</p><sec disp-level="3" id="S003-S2003-S3001"><title>Clinical scores and temperatures</title><p>After immunization, one pig in Group E, E079, had temperatures above 40.5&#x000b0;C for 3 separate days between 5- to 10&#x02005;dpi and another pig (E077) for one day, at 18&#x02005;dpi (<xref rid="F0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>(E)). After challenge, at 42&#x02005;dpi, with genotype II Georgia 2007/1, one pig (E071) had a temperature &#x0003e;40.5&#x000b0;C on three separate days, 48-, 51- and 53&#x02005;dpi (6, 9 and 11&#x02005;dpc). No other pigs had temperatures above 40.5&#x000b0;C and all pigs survived until the end of the experiment (<xref rid="F0002" ref-type="fig">Figures 2</xref> and <xref rid="F0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>(E)).</p><p>In the other immunized group (Group F), one pig (F095) had a temperature above 41&#x000b0;C for three days post-immunization (5&#x02013;7&#x02005;dpi) accompanied by other signs including lethargy and two days not eating and was terminated at the humane endpoint at 7&#x02005;dpi (<xref rid="F0002" ref-type="fig">Figures 2</xref> and <xref rid="F0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>(G)). None of the other pigs had temperatures above 40.5&#x000b0;C after immunization or boost. After challenge with Genotype IX Kenya 1033, all the pigs in Group F had 3 days of temperature above 41&#x000b0;C, lethargy and were not eating for two days. They were terminated at the humane end point on 5 to 7&#x02005;dpc (<xref rid="F0002" ref-type="fig">Figures 2</xref> and <xref rid="F0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>(G)). Mild transient clinical signs post immunization, including lethargy or joint swelling, were observed in some animals in Groups E and F. These are likely to have been non-procedure related and were also observed in some pigs before immunization.</p><p>The control groups challenged with genotype II Georgia 2007/1 (Group G) or Kenya 1033 (Group H) developed clinical signs of acute ASF including temperatures of 40.5&#x000b0;C to &#x0003e;41.0&#x000b0;C for 3 days and other clinical signs including lethargy and two days of not eating, and were terminated on 6 or 7&#x02005;dpc (Group G) or 6&#x02005;dpc (Group H) at the humane endpoint (<xref rid="F0002" ref-type="fig">Figures 2</xref>, <xref rid="F0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>(F,H)).</p><p>Significant differences were found in the both the temperatures and clinical scores between Group E (immunized) and G (na&#x000ef;ve), after challenge with the homologous virulent Georgia 2007/1 strain. Temperatures for the immunized Group E pigs were significantly lower than Group G on 6 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.022) and 7&#x02005;dpc (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0008) (Figure S1D), while for the overall observed clinical signs, they were significantly lower at 2 dpc (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.03) and 6&#x02005;dpc (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x0003c;0.0001) (Figure S2D). In contrast, temperatures and clinical scores for pigs in Group F (immunized) and control Group H showed no statistical differences (Figures S1E and S2E).</p></sec><sec disp-level="3" id="S003-S2003-S3002"><title>Virus genome in blood</title><p>After immunization, only one pig in Group E had detectable genome in blood, 10<sup>4.2</sup> genome copies per mL at 7&#x02005;dpi (<xref rid="F0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>(E)). In Group F, pig F095, which reached its humane endpoint on 7&#x02005;dpi had genome copies of 10<sup>5.5</sup> per mL blood. This moderate level of virus genome in blood suggests other factors may have contributed to this pig reaching the humane endpoint. One other pig in Group F, F080, had 10<sup>4.4</sup> genome copies per mL on 7&#x02005;dpi (<xref rid="F0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>(G)).</p><p>After challenge with virulent genotype II, two pigs in Group E had virus genome detected in blood. The levels ranged in one pig (E071), from 10<sup>7.5</sup> on 49&#x02005;dpi to 10<sup>6.9</sup> genome copies per mL at termination. The other pig, E079, had 10<sup>5.9</sup> genome copies per mL at termination. No other pigs in Group E had detectable virus genome in blood (<xref rid="F0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>(E)).</p><p>The 6 pigs in Group F, challenged with genotype IX, were terminated between 5 and 7 dpc (47&#x02013;49&#x02005;dpi). Genome copies per mL of blood detected at termination were 10<sup>8.5</sup> or higher in most pigs (<xref rid="F0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>(G)). Pigs F075 and F097 had genome copies per mL blood of 10<sup>7.5</sup> and 10<sup>7.1</sup> at termination, respectively.</p><p>In control Group G, challenged with virulent genotype II Georgia 2007/1, pigs had genome copies per mL of 10<sup>7.2-9.1</sup> at the humane endpoint (<xref rid="F0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>(F)). In control Group H, challenged with virulent genotype IX, all four pigs had genome copies per mL between 10<sup>8.9-9.1</sup> at termination at the humane endpoint on 5 or 6 dpc (<xref rid="F0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>(H)).</p><p>Comparison of mean values for genome copies/mL in blood between immunized pigs in Group E and control pigs in Group G showed significantly lower virus genomes in Group E at both 3&#x02005;dpc (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0075) and 5 to 7&#x02005;dpc (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0003) (Figure S3D). Despite reaching their humane endpoints, immunized pigs in Group F, that were challenged with genotype IX virulent isolate, had statistically significant lower virus genome copies per mL blood compared to the control Group H (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0249) (Figure S1E). This indicates that the immunization and boost with G&#x00394;DKE-Cmut virus had induced an immune response which reduced replication of the challenge virus, but not enough to afford protection.</p></sec><sec disp-level="3" id="S003-S2003-S3003"><title>Macroscopic lesion scores at necropsy</title><p>Pigs in Group E, immunized and challenged with genotype II, all had mild signs of haemorrhage detected in lymph nodes (<xref rid="F0005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>(C)). Four pigs had signs of haemorrhage in the duodenum, one had small petechias on both kidneys, five pigs had mild lung oedema, and five pigs showed signs of pericarditis. The three pigs in control Group G, challenged with virulent genotype II, had more severe lesions mostly in the lymphoid system. One pig had petechias through the cortex of both kidneys, and all three had haemorrhagic mucosa in the duodenum. All had lung oedema ranging from mild to severe. When the total lesion scores were compared between Group E and Group G, the immunized, protected pigs had significantly lower scores than the non-immune pigs (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0167) (Figure S4D).</p><p>In Group F, all immunized pigs challenged with genotype IX ASFV, had haemorrhagic lymph nodes and enlarged haemorrhagic spleens. In addition, three pigs had small petechias in the kidneys. Five pigs had signs of haemorrhage in mucosa of the stomach and duodenum and five had mild lung oedema (<xref rid="F0005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>(C)). The four na&#x000ef;ve pigs in Group H, all had haemorrhagic lymph nodes and spleens. Small petechias were detected in kidneys in two pigs. All four pigs had signs of haemorrhage in mucosa of the duodenum and mild lung oedema. As expected, no significant differences were observed between the immunized pigs and na&#x000ef;ve control pigs after challenge (Figure S4E).</p><p>In conclusion, there was no evidence that the attenuated genotype II G&#x00394;DKE-Cmut protected pigs against challenge with virulent genotype IX. All pigs immunized with the same vaccine and challenged with virulent genotype II survived.</p></sec><sec disp-level="3" id="S003-S2003-S3004"><title>Immune responses</title><p>Antibody responses in 10 pigs were above the cut-off at 14&#x02005;dpi, and good levels were observed in all animals by 35&#x02005;dpi (<xref rid="F0006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>(C,D)).</p><p>IFN-&#x003b3; cellular responses to genotype II stimulation were highest in both Groups E and F and increased after boost in most pigs. Responses to genotype IX stimulation were much lower (<xref rid="F0006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>(G,H) and S5I-N).</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" disp-level="1" id="S004"><title>Discussion</title><p>Control of ASFV is hindered by several factors including limited availability of vaccines [<xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Modified live vaccines provide the most promising approach, but their use is limited by a lack of knowledge on the extent of cross-protection that can be achieved between circulating isolates. MLVs based on the genotype II current pandemic strains have been licensed for use in Vietnam. However, these do not induce cross-protection against virulent genotype II and genotype I hybrids which were first detected in China, and subsequently in Vietnam and Russia [<xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Cross-protection induced by genotype II MLVs against other genotypes, including prevalent genotypes circulating in domestic pigs in Africa, genotypes I and IX, have not previously been reported.</p><p>Cross-protection cannot currently be predicted accurately based on genome sequences or analysis of immune responses <italic toggle="yes">ex vivo</italic>. Antibodies alone are not effective in providing protection and therefore, assays such as <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> neutralization assays, cannot be used to predict cross-protection. Cellular immunity is required for protection induced by attenuated ASFV [<xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Assays based on measuring cellular responses therefore have potential to predict cross-protection. We compared numbers of IFN-&#x003b3; producing cells detected by ELISpot assay following stimulation of PBMCs, from genotype II vaccinated pigs, with genotype II, I and IX ASFV isolates. This showed a trend of higher values following stimulation with the homologous genotype II, followed by genotype I but without statistical significance. Possibly, screening for responses from specific cellular subsets might show greater correlation with induction of protection.</p><p>We show here that our previously described multiple gene-deleted genotype II MLV G&#x00394;DKE-Cmut induced partial cross-protection against virulent genotype I challenge but no protection against virulent genotype IX. In the experiments described here, groups of pigs were immunized and boosted with G&#x00394;DKE-Cmut and challenged with either virulent genotype I Benin 97/1, genotype II Georgia 2007/1 and genotype IX Kenya 1033.</p><p>Pigs were immunized by the intramuscular route with 5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>4</sup> TCID<sub>50</sub> G&#x00394;DKE-Cmut and boosted with either 5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>4</sup> or 1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>4</sup> TCID<sub>50</sub> G&#x00394;DKE-Cmut, leading to survival of 5 out of 7 pigs (Group A) and 4 pigs from 7 (Group C) after challenge with genotype I, respectively. Based on these results it is not possible to draw conclusions about the effect of the booster dose on protection levels. Although the numbers of pigs that survived the challenge beyond the humane endpoint were higher in Group A, this is not statistically significant. In addition, the clinical scores, temperatures and levels of virus genome in blood showed a trend to be higher after challenge in pigs in Group A compared to Group C. Macroscopic lesions observed at necropsy were not significantly different between pigs in the vaccinated Groups A and C and control Groups B and D. Others have noted that macroscopic lesion scores at necropsy do not necessarily correlate with the severity of clinical signs suggesting that other factors are important [<xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Possibly using a more severe humane endpoint may have resulted in a greater difference in lesion scores between the na&#x000ef;ve and the immunized pigs after challenge with virulent virus. These results show that partial cross-protection of pigs can be achieved by immunization with genotype II MLV followed by challenge with virulent genotype I. Further optimization of the vaccination regime and challenge route may achieve higher levels of protection. It would be interesting to test if cross-protection could be induced by the genotype II MLV G&#x00394;DKE-Cmut against challenge with the virulent genotype I/II hybrid circulating in Asia.</p><p>All pigs vaccinated with G&#x00394;DKE-Cmut and challenged with genotype IX (Group F) reached the humane endpoint criteria at similar times post-challenge as the challenge control pigs, whereas all the immunized pigs challenged with genotype II (Group E) survived until the end of the study with few clinical signs. In previous studies using this MLV<italic toggle="yes">,</italic> we obtained 83% protection against genotype II challenge using a lower immunization and boost dose of 1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>4</sup> TCID<sub>50</sub> and 100% protection using 5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>4</sup> dose with few clinical signs observed either post-immunization or post-challenge [<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Even though all animals challenged with genotype IX reached the humane endpoint criteria, a significant difference was observed in levels of virus genome in blood of pigs in Group F compared to control Group H after challenge. This indicates that an immune response had been induced which partially controlled virus replication.</p><p>Previous studies showed cross-protection against genotype IX or X ASFV can be achieved by immunization of pigs with attenuated genotype I viruses and boosting with a virulent genotype I virus [<xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. This suggests that cross-protection between genotypes may be extended by applying a stronger booster dose of a less attenuated strain or possibly a higher or more frequent dose of the same strain used for immunization. The close similarity between available whole genome sequences for genotype I, suggest that the genotype II MLV used in this study may partially protect pigs against a wide range of genotype I isolates.</p><p>Most ASFV vaccine research is directed at developing vaccines against genotype II, thus, developing strategies to use these in Africa would have advantages. However, the results of this study, suggest that cross-protection against strains which are genetically more distant from genotype II is unlikely, as there was no evidence of cross-protection against challenge with virulent genotype IX. Complete genome sequencing showed genotype IX isolates are more distantly related to genotype II than genotype I isolates [<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] so it is not unexpected that protection against genotype IX was not achieved.</p><p>Thus for the control of ASFV in Africa, the development of ASFV vaccines based on the genotypes present in the different regions, such as genotype IX and closely related genotype X circulating in domestic pigs in East Africa, remains important [<xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. A thorough assessment of the ASFV strains present in a particular area before deployment of MLVs, is therefore crucial to avoid vaccine failure.</p><p>The use of <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> experiments to test cross-protective capability is expensive, time consuming and requires the use of contained animal facilities. There is an urgent need to develop methods to avoid the need for <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> challenge experiments. Reagents generated in our experiments will be useful to help establish <italic toggle="yes">ex vivo</italic> assays that can predict cross-protection. Increased knowledge of protective antigens will provide information to help predict cross-protection from genome sequences.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="SM3508" position="float" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Figure S4.tif</title></caption><media xlink:href="TEMI_A_2505645_SM3508.tif"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SM3507" position="float" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Supplementary_Data_formatted_for_EMI_revised-clean.docx</title></caption><media xlink:href="TEMI_A_2505645_SM3507.docx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SM3506" position="float" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Figure S2.tif</title></caption><media xlink:href="TEMI_A_2505645_SM3506.tif"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SM3505" position="float" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Figure S3.tif</title></caption><media xlink:href="TEMI_A_2505645_SM3505.tif"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SM3504" position="float" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Figure S6.tif</title></caption><media xlink:href="TEMI_A_2505645_SM3504.tif"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SM3503" position="float" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Figure S1.tif</title></caption><media xlink:href="TEMI_A_2505645_SM3503.tif"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SM3502" position="float" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Figure S5.tif</title></caption><media xlink:href="TEMI_A_2505645_SM3502.tif"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We would like to thank the clinical research facilities team at ILRI for their contributions to the animal experiments. The findings and conclusions contained within are those of the authors and do not necessarily reflect positions or policies of GALVmed or the UK Government. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</p></ack><sec sec-type="COI-statement" disp-level="1" id="S005"><title>Disclosure statement</title><p>No potential conflict of interest was reported by the author(s).</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s006"><title>Supplemental Material</title><p>Supplemental data for this article can be accessed online at <ext-link xlink:href="10.1080/22221751.2025.2505645" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1080/22221751.2025.2505645</ext-link>.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="CIT0001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Bastos</surname>
<given-names>AD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Penrith</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cruci&#x000e8;re</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Genotyping field strains of African swine fever virus by partial p72 gene characterisation</article-title>. <source>Arch Virol</source>. <year>2003 Apr</year>;<volume>148</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>693</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>706</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12664294</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Mulumba-Mfumu</surname>
<given-names>LK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Saegerman</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dixon</surname>
<given-names>LK</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>African swine fever: update on Eastern, Central and Southern Africa</article-title>. <source>Transbound Emerg Dis</source>. <year>2019 Jul</year>;<volume>66</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1462</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1480</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30920725</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hakizimana</surname>
<given-names>JN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yona</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Makange</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Complete genome analysis of the African swine fever virus genotypes II and IX responsible for the 2021 and 2023 outbreaks in Rwanda</article-title>. <source>Front Vet Sci</source>. <year>2025</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>1532683</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40041669</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Sun</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Genotype I African swine fever viruses emerged in domestic pigs in China and caused chronic infection</article-title>. <source>Emerg Microbes Infect</source>. <year>2021 Dec</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>2183</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2193</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34709128</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sun</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Highly lethal genotype I and II recombinant African swine fever viruses detected in pigs</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source>. <year>2023 May 29</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>3096</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37248233</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Igolkin</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mazloum</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zinyakov</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Detection of the first recombinant African swine fever virus (genotypes I and II) in domestic pigs in Russia</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Rep</source>. <year>2024 Sep 25</year>;<volume>51</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1011</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39320407</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vu</surname>
<given-names>TTH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yeom</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Molecular characterization of emerging recombinant African swine fever virus of genotype I and II in Vietnam, 2023</article-title>. <source>Emerg Microbes Infect</source>. <year>2024 Dec</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>2404156</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39258419</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Auer</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cattoli</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Padungtod</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Challenges in the application of African swine fever vaccines in Asia</article-title>. <source>Animals (Basel)</source>. <year>2024 Aug 25</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>17</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>O'Donnell</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Holinka</surname>
<given-names>LG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gladue</surname>
<given-names>DP</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>African swine fever virus georgia isolate harboring deletions of MGF360 and MGF505 genes is attenuated in swine and confers protection against challenge with virulent parental virus</article-title>. <source>J Virol</source>. <year>2015 Jun</year>;<volume>89</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>6048</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6056</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25810553</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Borca</surname>
<given-names>MV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ramirez-Medina</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Silva</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Development of a highly effective African swine fever virus vaccine by deletion of the I177L gene results in sterile immunity against the current epidemic Eurasia strain</article-title>. <source>J Virol</source>. <year>2020 Mar 17</year>;<volume>94</volume>:<fpage>7</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Malogolovkin</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Burmakina</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Titov</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Comparative analysis of African swine fever virus genotypes and serogroups</article-title>. <source>Emerg Infect Dis</source>. <year>2015 Feb</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>312</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>315</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25625574</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Sereda</surname>
<given-names>AD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Balyshev</surname>
<given-names>VM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kazakova</surname>
<given-names>AS</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Protective properties of attenuated strains of African swine fever virus belonging to seroimmunotypes I-VIII</article-title>. <source>Pathogens</source>. <year>2020 Apr 9</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>4</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Monteagudo</surname>
<given-names>PL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lacasta</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>L&#x000f3;pez</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>BA71&#x00394;CD2: a new recombinant live attenuated African swine fever virus with cross-protective capabilities</article-title>. <source>J Virol</source>. <year>2017 Nov 1</year>;<volume>91</volume>:<fpage>21</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>King</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chapman</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Argilaguet</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Protection of European domestic pigs from virulent African isolates of African swine fever virus by experimental immunisation</article-title>. <source>Vaccine</source>. <year>2011 Jun 20</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>28</issue>):<fpage>4593</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4600</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21549789</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Rathakrishnan</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reis</surname>
<given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Petrovan</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>A protective multiple gene-deleted African swine fever virus genotype II, Georgia 2007/1, expressing a modified non-haemadsorbing CD2v protein</article-title>. <source>Emerg Microbes Infect</source>. <year>2023 Dec</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>2265661</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37781934</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Chapman</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Darby</surname>
<given-names>AC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Da Silva</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Genomic analysis of highly virulent Georgia 2007/1 isolate of African swine fever virus</article-title>. <source>Emerg Infect Dis</source>. <year>2011 Apr</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>599</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>605</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21470447</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Chapman</surname>
<given-names>DAG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tcherepanov</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Upton</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Comparison of the genome sequences of non-pathogenic and pathogenic African swine fever virus isolates</article-title>. <source>J Gen Virol</source>. <year>2008 Feb</year>;<volume>89</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>397</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>408</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18198370</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hemmink</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abkallo</surname>
<given-names>HM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Henson</surname>
<given-names>SP</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>The African swine fever isolate ASFV-Kenya-IX-1033 is highly virulent and stable after propagation in the wild boar cell line WSL</article-title>. <source>Viruses</source>. <year>2022 Aug 29</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>9</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Galindo-Cardiel</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ballester</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Solanes</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Standardization of pathological investigations in the framework of experimental ASFV infections</article-title>. <source>Virus Res</source>. <year>2013 Apr</year>;<volume>173</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>180</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>190</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23313935</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>King</surname>
<given-names>DP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reid</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hutchings</surname>
<given-names>GH</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Development of a TaqMan PCR assay with internal amplification control for the detection of African swine fever virus</article-title>. <source>J Virol Methods</source>. <year>2003 Jan</year>;<volume>107</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>53</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>61</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12445938</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Alonso</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Borca</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dixon</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>ICTV virus taxonomy profile: asfarviridae</article-title>. <source>J Gen Virol</source>. <year>2018 May</year>;<volume>99</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>613</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>614</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29565243</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Diep</surname>
<given-names>NV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duc</surname>
<given-names>NV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ngoc</surname>
<given-names>NT</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Genotype II live-attenuated ASFV vaccine strains unable to completely protect pigs against the emerging recombinant ASFV genotype I/II strain in Vietnam</article-title>. <source>Vaccines (Basel)</source>. <year>2024 Sep 28</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>10</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Oura</surname>
<given-names>CAL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Denyer</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Takamatsu</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>In vivo depletion of CD8+ T lymphocytes abrogates protective immunity to African swine fever virus</article-title>. <source>J Gen Virol</source>. <year>2005 Sep</year>;<volume>86</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>2445</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2450</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16099902</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>S&#x000e1;nchez-Cord&#x000f3;n</surname>
<given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lean</surname>
<given-names>FZX</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Batten</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Comparative evaluation of disease dynamics in wild boar and domestic pigs experimentally inoculated intranasally with the European highly virulent African swine fever virus genotype II strain &#x0201c;Armenia 2007&#x0201d;</article-title>. <source>Vet Res</source>. <year>2024 Jul 15</year>;<volume>55</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>89</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39010163</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Abkallo</surname>
<given-names>HM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hemmink</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Oduor</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Co-Deletion of A238L and EP402R genes from a genotype IX African swine fever virus results in partial attenuation and protection in swine</article-title>. <source>Viruses</source>. <year>2022 Sep 13</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>9</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hemmink</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Khazalwa</surname>
<given-names>EM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abkallo</surname>
<given-names>HM</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Deletion of the CD2v gene from the genome of ASFV-Kenya-IX-1033 partially reduces virulence and induces protection in pigs</article-title>. <source>Viruses</source>. <year>2022 Aug 30</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>9</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>