<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="article-commentary"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Immunol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Immunol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Immunol.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Immunology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-3224</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40013155</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11860524</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2025.1555559</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Immunology</subject><subj-group><subject>General Commentary</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Commentary: Sodium levels and immunotherapy efficacy in mRCC patients with bone metastases: sub analysis of the Meet-Uro 15 study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Catalano</surname><given-names>Martina</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1840565"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rebuzzi</surname><given-names>Sara Elena</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1210553"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fornarini</surname><given-names>Giuseppe</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2029324"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Roviello</surname><given-names>Giandomenico</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn001" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/532855"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
<institution>Department of Health Sciences, Section of Clinical Pharmacology and Oncology, University of Firenze</institution>, <addr-line>Firenze</addr-line>, <country>Italy</country>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
<institution>Medical Oncology Unit, Ospedale San Paolo</institution>, <addr-line>Savona</addr-line>, <country>Italy</country>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
<institution>Medical Oncology Unit 1, Istituti di Ricovero e Cura a Carattere Scientifico (IRCCS) Ospedale Policlinico San Martino of Genova</institution>, <addr-line>Genova</addr-line>, <country>Italy</country>
</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Marco Bregni, San Raffaele Hospital (IRCCS), Italy</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Giuseppe Schepisi, Scientific Institute of Romagna for the Study and Treatment of Tumors (IRCCS), Italy</p></fn><corresp id="fn001">*Correspondence: Giandomenico Roviello, <email xlink:href="mailto:giandomenico.roviello@unifi.it">giandomenico.roviello@unifi.it</email>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><elocation-id>1555559</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>04</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>31</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2025 Catalano, Rebuzzi, Fornarini and Roviello</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Catalano, Rebuzzi, Fornarini and Roviello</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><related-article related-article-type="commentary-article" ext-link-type="doi" id="RA1" xlink:href="10.3389/fimmu.2024.1361010" journal-id="Front Immunol" journal-id-type="nlm-ta">A Commentary on <article-title>Sodium levels and immunotherapy efficacy in mRCC patients with bone metastases: sub analysis of Meet-Uro 15 study</article-title> By Catalano M, Rebuzzi SE, Maruzzo M, De Giorgi U, Buti S, Galli L, Fornarini G, Zucali PA, Claps M, Chiellino S, Zampiva I, Pipitone S, Ricotta R, Sorar&#x000f9; M, Mollica V, Tudini M, Fratino L, Prati V, Caffo O, Atzori F, Morelli F, Prati G, Nol&#x000e8; F, Vignani F, Cavo A, Di Napoli M, Malgeri A, Naglieri E, Signori A, Banna GL, Rescigno P, Cerbone L, Antonuzzo L and Roviello G (2024) <italic>Front. Immunol.</italic> 15:1361010. doi:&#x000a0;<object-id>10.3389/fimmu.2024.1361010</object-id>
</related-article><kwd-group><kwd>bone metastases</kwd><kwd>efficacy outcomes</kwd><kwd>sodium levels</kwd><kwd>renal cell carcinoma</kwd><kwd>immunotherapy</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><funding-statement>The author(s) declare that no financial support was received for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="0"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="3"/><page-count count="2"/><word-count count="548"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>section-in-acceptance</meta-name><meta-value>Cancer Immunity and Immunotherapy</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p>We are grateful to the correspondent for their thoughtful comments on our recently published study, &#x0201c;Sodium levels and immunotherapy efficacy in mRCC patients with bone metastases: sub analysis of the Meet-Uro 15 study.&#x0201d; We appreciate the opportunity to further discuss several key aspects of our work and the insightful suggestions for improving the robustness of our findings. Below, we address the concerns raised and offer clarification on the points mentioned.</p><p>We agree that metastatic renal cell carcinoma (mRCC) with bone metastases represents a unique subset of patients with particularly poor prognosis, and we acknowledge the importance of identifying prognostic factors to optimize treatment strategies. For this the focus of our study was on the prognostic role of natremia specifically in this patient population. In fact, in the MeetURO 15 study, we evaluated the prognostic role of natremia, including normonatremic patients with a cut-off of 140 mEq/L, in all patients with mRCC treated with nivolumab (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). The findings confirmed the negative prognostic role of sodium levels below 140 mEq/L. In this subanalysis, we aimed to determine whether sodium levels below 140 mEq/L retained their negative prognostic value specifically in RCC patients with bone metastases, obtaining confirmation (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>).</p><p>Regarding the proposal to integrate inflammatory markers and to develop a multivariable prognostic scoring system similar to the Lung Immune Prognostic Index (LIPI) used in non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC), we acknowledge the growing importance of incorporating systemic inflammatory markers such as the neutrophil-to-lymphocyte ratio (NLR) and lactate dehydrogenase (LDH) into prognostic models (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). Incorporating these variables may help to improve risk stratification and guide personalized therapeutic decisions for RCC patients, particularly those undergoing immunotherapy.</p><p>We also concur with the assertion that renal function, particularly serum creatinine levels, could play a role in influencing sodium levels and prognosis. The decision not to include creatinine in our initial analysis was based on the desire to isolate sodium as an independent variable, but we recognize that this exclusion may have introduced confounding factors. We agree that future analyses should adjust for renal function to better understand the relationship between hyponatremia and survival outcomes, especially considering the high prevalence of impaired renal function in RCC patients due to nephrectomy or nephrotoxic medications. This adjustment could lead to more precise conclusions about the prognostic significance of natremia in the context of renal impairment.</p><p>Finally, regarding the IMDC score, while it remains a widely utilized prognostic tool in mRCC, we agree with the suggestion that its applicability in the context of immunotherapy warrants further investigation. As immune checkpoint inhibitors become an integral part of mRCC treatment, the limitations of the IMDC score in capturing the dynamic nature of the tumor immune microenvironment are increasingly apparent. Developing new scoring systems that account for variables such as sodium and creatinine levels, as well as markers of immune activity and tumor-infiltrating lymphocytes, could significantly enhance the precision of prognostication in the immunotherapy era.</p><p>We appreciate the recognition of the novel contributions made by our study, particularly the targeted focus on RCC patients with bone metastases. Moving forward, we plan to pursue additional research that incorporates the suggestions provided, including broader cohort analyses and the integration of renal function parameters, to refine our understanding of the role of sodium in RCC prognosis.</p></body><back><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="s1"><title>Author contributions</title><p>MC: Data curation, Writing &#x02013; original draft. SR: Data curation, Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing. GF: Conceptualization, Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing. GR: Conceptualization, Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s3"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="ai-statement" id="s4"><title>Generative AI statement</title><p>The author(s) declare that no Generative AI was used in the creation of this manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s5"><title>Publisher&#x02019;s note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Catalano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rebuzzi</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Maruzzo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>De Giorgi</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Buti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Galli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Sodium levels and outcomes in patients with metastatic renal cell carcinoma receiving nivolumab</article-title>. <source>JAMA Netw Open</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>6</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<elocation-id>e2345185</elocation-id>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.45185</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38010650</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Catalano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rebuzzi</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Maruzzo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>De Giorgi</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Buti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Galli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Sodium levels and immunotherapy efficacy in MRCC patients with bone metastases: sub analysis of meet-uro 15 study</article-title>. <source>Front Immunol</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<elocation-id>1361010</elocation-id>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/FIMMU.2024.1361010</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39034992</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mezquita</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Auclin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferrara</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Charrier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Remon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Planchard</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Association of the lung immune prognostic index with immune checkpoint inhibitor outcomes in patients with advanced non-small cell lung cancer</article-title>. <source>JAMA Oncol</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>4</volume>:<page-range>351&#x02013;7</page-range>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/JAMAONCOL.2017.4771</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>