<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLOS One</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40408373</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12101661</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0324285</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-24-54554</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Computer and Information Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Data Management</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Health Care</subject><subj-group><subject>Health Care Policy</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Social Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Economics</subject><subj-group><subject>Health Economics</subject><subj-group><subject>Health Care Sector</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Health Care</subject><subj-group><subject>Health Economics</subject><subj-group><subject>Health Care Sector</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Health Care</subject><subj-group><subject>Health Services Administration and Management</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Social Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Law and Legal Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Regulations</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Health Care</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Research and Analysis Methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Mathematical and Statistical Techniques</subject><subj-group><subject>Statistical Methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Analysis of Variance</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Physical Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Mathematics</subject><subj-group><subject>Statistics</subject><subj-group><subject>Statistical Methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Analysis of Variance</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Research and Analysis Methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Research Design</subject><subj-group><subject>Survey Research</subject><subj-group><subject>Surveys</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Evaluating the effectiveness of data governance frameworks in ensuring security and privacy of healthcare data: A quantitative analysis of ISO standards, GDPR, and HIPAA in blockchain technology</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Evaluating the effectiveness of data governance frameworks</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0009-0004-6812-2538</contrib-id><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>Ameer</given-names></name><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/investigation/">Investigation</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/methodology/">Methodology</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/resources/">Resources</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/software/">Software</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/">Writing &#x02013; original draft</role><xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3157-2672</contrib-id><name><surname>Shahzad</surname><given-names>Asjad</given-names></name><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/methodology/">Methodology</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/supervision/">Supervision</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/validation/">Validation</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/">Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing</role><xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Naseem</surname><given-names>Afshan</given-names></name><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/project-administration/">Project administration</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/supervision/">Supervision</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/validation/">Validation</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/">Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing</role><xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>Shujaat</given-names></name><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/supervision/">Supervision</role><xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>Imran</given-names></name><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation/">Data curation</role><xref rid="aff002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff001"><label>1</label>
<addr-line>Department of Engineering Management, College of Electrical and Mechanical Engineering, National University of Sciences and Technology, Islamabad, Pakistan</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff002"><label>2</label>
<addr-line>Engineering Management Department, CASE Sir Syed Institute of Technology, Islamabad, Pakistan</addr-line></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Capece</surname><given-names>Guendalina</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref rid="edit1" ref-type="aff"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>Universitas Mercatorum, ITALY</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="coi001"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>ameerahmed1976@gmail.com</email>, <email>ameer.ahmed@ceme.nust.edu.pk</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>23</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>20</volume><issue>5</issue><elocation-id>e0324285</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>8</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2025 Ahmed et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Ahmed et al</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="pone.0324285.pdf">
</self-uri><abstract><p>Blockchain technology is widely used in almost every domain of life nowadays including healthcare sector. Although there are existing frameworks to govern healthcare data but they have certain limitations in effectiveness of data governance to ensure security and privacy. This study aimed to evaluate effectiveness of health care data governance frameworks, examining security and privacy concerns and limitations within the existing frameworks of ISO Standards, GDPR, and HIPAA. In this study quantitative research approach was followed. A sample of 250 participants from Islamabad, Lahore and Karachi based healthcare experts, IT specialist, blockchain research and developer, administrator was selected. The collected data was analyzed though frequencies and descriptive statistical tests with the help of SPSS. The results revealed&#x000a0;un-satisfaction&#x000a0;for data governance frameworks, i.e., ISO standards, GDPR, and HIPAA in terms of security concerns, i.e., data encryption, access controls, audit trails, interoperability and standards, smart contracts for compliance, data integrity, regulatory compliance monitoring and privacy concerns, i.e., consent management, anonymization and pseudonymization, data minimization. The participants agreed that there is a need of integration of reliable data governance framework in health care data management. Various personalized governance techniques, targeted security upgrades, and continuous improvement in the specific customized data governance framework has been presented based on the findings of the study. An implementation of blockchain-based systems is recommended in order to ensure and expand the security and privacy of healthcare data management.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>The author(s) received no specific funding for this work.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="3"/><table-count count="9"/><page-count count="18"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>All relevant data are within the manuscript and its <xref rid="sec033" ref-type="sec">Supporting information</xref> files.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><title>Data Availability</title><p>All relevant data are within the manuscript and its <xref rid="sec033" ref-type="sec">Supporting information</xref> files.</p></notes></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001"><title>Introduction</title><p>Healthcare data management faces various issues in security, privacy, and optimization of patient outcomes [<xref rid="pone.0324285.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. With exponentially growing electronic health records and the ever-growing demand for data-oriented healthcare, conventional data management systems are confronted with the new realities of data fragmentation, security, and less-than-optimal interoperability [<xref rid="pone.0324285.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. There is a need for a safe, transparent, and efficient system of data management [<xref rid="pone.0324285.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>].</p><p>Blockchain technology was originally created as the back-end technology for cryptocurrencies, but now it has come under intense examination for its capability to revolutionize numerous industries including healthcare [<xref rid="pone.0324285.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. In comparison to traditional centralized systems, blockchain provides a decentralized, tamper-evident ledger that boosts transparency, trust, and efficiency in data management operations [<xref rid="pone.0324285.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Its inherent characteristics, including cryptographic hash, consensus mechanism, and smart contracts and these qualities make it safe and reliable [<xref rid="pone.0324285.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>].</p><p>The medical sector, which deals with tremendous volumes of sensitive patient data, is obviously required to ensure confidentiality and integrity of data [<xref rid="pone.0324285.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Multiple instances of&#x000a0;cyber attack, data breach, and unauthorized access are grave threats to healthcare data confidentiality and integrity [<xref rid="pone.0324285.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. In addition, privacy concerns, especially related to information sharing for treatment and research, require robust mechanisms through which individuals are given the power to maintain their health information under their control private, secure and safe [<xref rid="pone.0324285.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].</p><p>Even though there is immense opportunity with blockchain and scholarly work has been done but still, there is an enormous gap for research on how it can be implemented with existing data governance frameworks such as the ISO standards, GDPR, and HIPAA within healthcare. These standards, while being extensive, are likely to fail in sustaining the decentralized aspect of blockchain technology and are likely fail to provide solutions for future security and privacy issues within healthcare data governance [<xref rid="pone.0324285.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].</p><p>By considering this background in mind, the main objective of this research is to establish the level of effectiveness of current data governance models&#x02014;i.e., ISO standards, GDPR, and HIPAA&#x02014;in ensuring healthcare data privacy and security in the event that it is applied together with blockchain technology. This study seeks to answer the following research question:</p><p>Are current data governance models (i.e., ISO standards, GDPR, and HIPAA) adequate in providing the security and privacy of healthcare data in the blockchain space?</p><p>The study has a quantitative research design with a sample of 250 respondents from Islamabad, Lahore, and Karachi comprising healthcare professionals, IT professionals, blockchain researchers, developers, and administrators. Data were collected through a close-ended, structured questionnaire and were analyzed using frequency and descriptive statistical tests.</p><p>Relative to conventional architectures, the study bridges literature gaps by highlighting ways through which healthcare governance data can be secured by blockchain. The research findings are intended to guide policymakers and administrators in the health sector through the provision of practical pointers towards closing knowledge gaps to improve security, confidentiality, and effectiveness in managing healthcare data systems.</p><sec id="sec002"><title>Literature review</title><sec id="sec003"><title>Blockchain in healthcare.</title><p>Healthcare data forms a sensitive class and must be safeguarded in terms of privacy, security, and availability. Earlier privacy frameworks present are the ISO standards, General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR), and the Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act (HIPAA). However, the effectiveness of these frameworks for current health scenarios is questioned as they are incapable of dealing with the complexity of new technologies in decentralized data-sharing systems and IoT device interactions. A study by [<xref rid="pone.0324285.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] indicates that while these frameworks provide guidelines, they may not be sufficient to deal with the complexity arising from new models of healthcare digitally. This calls for advanced governance frameworks to be capable of holding the legislation in addition to variations in data storage, sharing, and access.</p><p>Previous studies [<xref rid="pone.0324285.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0324285.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] have assessed the greater need to research privacy in healthcare data governance. Nissenbaum&#x02019;s privacy theory, which is focused on the right flow of information in social contexts as intended, legitimates healthcare data governance as a complex phenomenon. The theory hypothesizes the necessity of balancing data privacy and healthcare innovation. Royal Free Trust and Alphabet&#x02019;s DeepMind Health&#x02019;s struggle with data sharing vs. data protection is the highlight of the struggle between AI healthcare innovation and government battles with data utilization.</p></sec><sec id="sec004"><title>Data governance frameworks.</title><p>Technical and organizational responses to data governance are extensively studied in the previous literature. Khatri &#x00026; Brown [<xref rid="pone.0324285.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] identify five decision-making areas of importance in data governance: metadata, correctness, access control, data management cycle, and post-acquisition processing. These are of primary importance for guaranteeing security and correctness of healthcare data. Technical solutions are insufficient, however, if ethical and social aspects are not considered. Abraham, Schneider, &#x00026; Vom Brocke [<xref rid="pone.0324285.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] advocate for a broader model incorporating ethical governance. Their governance pyramidal model prioritizes technical, ethical, and organizational balance and advocates a tiered framework to structure data governance mechanisms before, during, and after acquiring data. This approach emphasizes the importance of ethical considerations in upholding trust and accountability for healthcare data management.</p><p>Cheong &#x00026; Chang [<xref rid="pone.0324285.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] proposed an organizational structure defining stakeholder expectations and roles for data governance. The structure comprises three dimensions&#x02014;strategic, tactical, and operational&#x02014;each with a specific data management responsibility. Although the structure establishes a governance model, it does not provide under-resourced organizations with hands-on instruction, thus requiring flexible frameworks for use in diverse healthcare environments.</p></sec><sec id="sec005"><title>Challenges in low-resource settings.</title><p>Studies like [<xref rid="pone.0324285.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0324285.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0324285.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] have raised concerns on the data governance issues in low-resource healthcare settings, such as Kenya, show problems such as lack of awareness, poor leadership support, and limited resources [<xref rid="pone.0324285.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. The same challenges are prevalent in the majority of developing countries as well. By considering this effective frameworks must be adaptable and scalable to handle varying levels of resources in healthcare systems. Li et al. [<xref rid="pone.0324285.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] and Al-Badi, Tarhini, &#x00026; Khan [<xref rid="pone.0324285.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] evaluated big data governance in Chinese health care organizations and offered a framework with driving, capability, and support domains. Even though these frameworks have significant considerations like legal and regulatory compliance and data protection, they assume an infrastructure and resource base that may not be in place in constrained settings.</p></sec><sec id="sec006"><title>Integration with emerging technologies.</title><p>The participation of IoT devices in managing health information introduces another level of complexity. Dasgupta, Gill, &#x00026; Hussain [<xref rid="pone.0324285.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] refer to the challenges of ownership, access control, and security in healthcare systems with increased IoT integration. The devices produce vast amounts of real-time data, which demands robust governance to protect privacy and data integrity. Studies [<xref rid="pone.0324285.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0324285.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] suggest that data governance frameworks involving healthcare providers, regulatory bodies, and technology companies can minimize IoT and big data-related risks.</p></sec><sec id="sec007"><title>Data access control.</title><p>Studies [<xref rid="pone.0324285.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0324285.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0324285.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] on healthcare data access controls emphasize the importance of clear governance structures and heterogeneous data actors. Strong frameworks must establish guidelines to indicate who can access data, when, and how co-shared data are handled across platforms. The World Bank [<xref rid="pone.0324285.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] advocates for a multi-level access control mechanism, granting access to sensitive data based on roles of the users and only allowing authentic staff members to see particular information.</p></sec><sec id="sec008"><title>Ethical and regulatory considerations in data governance.</title><p>PAHO&#x02019;s study [<xref rid="pone.0324285.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] emphasizes the need to integrate concerns regarding privacy into data governance in healthcare. Besides being regulatory, it addresses ethical concerns in cross-border data sharing. From the study, it is observed that existing frameworks fall behind in addressing ethical dimensions of data transfers across jurisdictions with varying standards of privacy protection. The shortcoming is a call for models of governance that have the capacity to balance data sharing complexities at the global stage and firm patient privacy protections.</p><p>The literature suggests the imperative for robust models of data governance integrating ethical, technical, and organizational components. The successful models should adapt with emerging technologies like blockchain while respecting laws like GDPR and HIPAA. The reviews consulted undoubtedly present the necessity of governance models addressing regulatory requirements, along with delivering data security and patient trust amid the evolving digital health landscape.</p><p>A one-hand comparison of GDPR, HIPAA, and ISO is valuable because it highlights their similarities and differences in regulating healthcare data privacy, security, and governance. Each framework has a distinct focus:</p><p><bold>GDPR</bold> (General Data Protection Regulation): Enforces strict data privacy and consent mechanisms across the EU, emphasizing patient rights, data minimization, and cross-border data sharing regulations.</p><p><bold>HIPAA</bold> (Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act): Primarily focuses on protecting patient health information (PHI) within the U.S., ensuring security and confidentiality through compliance requirements for covered entities.</p><p><bold>ISO Standards</bold> (e.g., ISO/IEC 27001): Provide internationally recognized guidelines for information security management, offering a structured framework adaptable to various industries, including healthcare.</p><p>Our study makes a unique contribution by comparing these frameworks and suggesting the strong domain of each of the frameworks. Moreover, the solution to the shortcomings of the frameworks in addressing the complexities of modern healthcare data governance, particularly in decentralized systems, IoT-driven health data, and emerging AI applications, have been provided.</p><p><bold>Blockchain integration as a solution.</bold> The potential of blockchain in healthcare governance strangely focuses on findings and discussions around its application. Blockchain offers:</p><p><bold>Decentralization &#x00026; transparency</bold>: It enables secure, immutable, and tamper-proof data records, reducing reliance on central authorities.</p><p><bold>Smart contracts for compliance</bold>: Automates compliance by ensuring healthcare data is only accessed under predefined conditions.</p><p><bold>Improved data access &#x00026; security</bold>: Provides controlled access through cryptographic mechanisms, aligning with GDPR and HIPAA requirements.</p><p><bold>Cross-border data sharing</bold>: Facilitates regulatory-compliant and secure international data transfers, addressing the gaps in existing governance models<italic toggle="yes">.</italic></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec009"><title>Conceptual framework</title><p>A data governance framework is a embodiment of a&#x000a0;country&#x02019;s&#x000a0;social contract with data, enabling data governance to transition from theory to reality [<xref rid="pone.0324285.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Well-designed, comprehensive, and efficiently executed data governance frameworks foster confidence in data systems and encourage the usage of data-driven goods and services.</p><p>Every organization that gathers, maintains, or utilizes health data follow data governance guidelines [<xref rid="pone.0324285.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. There are many organizations engaged in the collecting, administration, and use of health-related data, central and&#x000a0;sub-national&#x000a0;governments must serve as stewards, collaborating at a higher level to integrate divergent data governance policies. To do this, governments should develop and execute national health data governance frameworks that, when possible, are aligned across sectors and at the international level.</p><p>The Health Data Governance Principles Health Data Governance Principles, is a comprehensive, global set of principles for governing health data across public health systems and policies, and it may be useful in providing a high-level framework for designing and implementing a national health data governance framework (and eventually aligning them globally). Such framework have received support from several organizations, including the World Bank. The principles are intended to influence and develop governance models, instruments, treaties, rules, and standards across nations and regions, with a common vision of equitable health data governance.</p><p>These framework are intended to complement and reinforce one another (they are not weighted or ranked in any order of priority) and are organized around three interconnected goals (<xref rid="pone.0324285.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>): protecting people&#x02014;as individuals, groups, and communities; promoting health value&#x02014;through data sharing and innovative data uses; and prioritizing equity&#x02014;by ensuring equitable distribution of benefits resulting from the use of data in health systems.</p><fig position="float" id="pone.0324285.g001"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0324285.g001</object-id><label>Fig 1</label><caption><title>Conceptual framework (self-created).</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0324285.g001" position="float"/></fig><p>By keeping this background in consideration, the study has formulated following hypothesis:</p><sec id="sec010"><title>Hypothesis 1.</title><p>The implementation of ISO standards, GDPR, and HIPAA frameworks within blockchain technology does not significantly improve the security and privacy of healthcare data compared to traditional data management systems.</p></sec><sec id="sec011"><title>Hypothesis 2.</title><p>There is no significant difference in the effectiveness of ISO standards, GDPR, and HIPAA frameworks in ensuring the security and privacy of healthcare data when integrated with blockchain technology.</p></sec><sec id="sec012"><title>Hypothesis 3.</title><p>The integration of blockchain technology does not sufficiently address the limitations of ISO standards, GDPR, and HIPAA frameworks in ensuring the security and privacy of healthcare data.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec013"><title>Methodology</title><p>The study followed quantitative research design and survey research approach. The research methodology used in this study was carefully designed to examine the effectiveness of data governance frameworks&#x02014;particularly the ISO standard, GDPR, and HIPAA&#x02014;in addressing security and privacy concerns in blockchain based healthcare data governance. An emphasis was placed on exploring and understanding the deeper relationships between data governance processes and participants perspectives through the use of interpretative research designs studies with a cross-sectional temporal frame focused on collecting contemporary attitudes mouth at the same time. Our study is methodologically solid through some essential aspects. The first one is the study design with a systematic and stringent approach that has a well-justified sample size of 250 individuals obtained from varying regions through stratified random sampling so that the sample would have a broad representation of views from healthcare professionals, IT professionals, blockchain developers, and administrators. Second, the data collection tool&#x02014;a structured, strictly closed-ended questionnaire&#x02014;was carefully crafted and pre-tested to ensure clarity and relevance, thus reducing measurement error. Third, the statistical techniques used (descriptive statistics and ANOVA) are suitable and powerful, allowing for clear and objective interpretation of the data. Finally, the study was based on firm ethical standards, with written guidelines in place for informed consent and data protection, further validating the technical soundness of the study. These factors together guarantee that the research methodology is rigorous and equally able to sustain the conclusions made.</p><sec id="sec014"><title>Population and sampling</title><p>The research focused on participants from Islamabad, Lahore, and Karachi, chosen for their diverse demographic profiles, advanced healthcare facilities, and varying levels of technology adoption. These cities represented both developed and developing health systems, allowing for a comprehensive assessment of data governance effectiveness in different contexts. A total of 250 participants were selected to ensure statistical validity, maintaining a 95% confidence level with a 5% margin of error while also considering practical limitations regarding participant availability. The participant pool included healthcare professionals, IT specialists, blockchain developers, administrators, and researchers, all of whom were directly involved in implementing and sustaining blockchain-based healthcare data platforms.</p><p>The participants werehealthcare professionals, IT specialists, blockchain developers and researchers, administrators, and practitioners directly engaged in implementing and sustaining blockchain-based healthcare data platforms. Additionally, the &#x02018;other&#x02019; category encompassed data analysts, compliance officers, and healthcare policy advisors, broadening the study&#x02019;s perspective on governance structures. To ensure balanced representation across various organizational roles and levels within the healthcare industry, a stratified random sampling technique was employed. This approach strengthened the findings by incorporating diverse viewpoints from different professional backgrounds and organizational hierarchies.</p></sec><sec id="sec015"><title>Data collection instrument</title><p>The researcher created a standardized, strictly closed-ended survey instrument with a 5-point Likert scale. The survey sought to determine participants&#x02019; attitudes towards the efficacy of data governance frameworks, namely ISO standards, GDPR, and HIPAA, with respect to incorporating blockchain technology in maintaining data security and privacy. The questions were designed on the basis of a comprehensive understanding of data governance, security, and privacy principles, assessing the perceived real-world efficacy of these frameworks in healthcare environments.</p><p>The questionnaire, presented in the appendix, had demography, data security, data privacy, blockchain incorporation, and general governance framework effectiveness as its topics. It contained Likert-scale questions, demographic questions, and scenario-based tests to measure practical knowledge and attitudes. Ethical principles, such as informed consent, confidentiality, and voluntary survey response, were built into the survey design.</p><p>To ensure the questionnaire&#x02019;s clarity and relevance, it was pre-tested with a small group of participants, primarily minority groups, to identify potential issues with question wording, clarity, and relevance. Feedback from this pre-test was used to refine the questions and improve the overall questionnaire design. After incorporating this feedback, the questionnaire was finalized and self-administered to the participants. The <xref rid="pone.0324285.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> outlines the structure of the questionnaire, highlighting the focus areas, sample questions, and the purpose of each section in relation to the study&#x02019;s objectives.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="pone.0324285.t001"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0324285.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Questionnaire development.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0324285.t001" id="pone.0324285.t001g" position="float"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Section</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Focus area</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Demographics</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Participant background (e.g., role, experience)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Data security</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Perceptions of data security effectiveness</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Data privacy</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Perceptions of data privacy protection</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Blockchain integration</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Role of blockchain technology in data governance</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Effectiveness of governance</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall evaluation of the effectiveness of data governance frameworks</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>Before its full implementation, the questionnaire was tested with people minority participants to identify and address any concerns of the questionnaire was checked, which is given in <xref rid="pone.0324285.t001" ref-type="table">Tables 1</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0324285.t002" ref-type="table">2</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="pone.0324285.t002"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0324285.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Units for magnetic properties.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0324285.t002" id="pone.0324285.t002g" position="float"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Reliability statistics</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cronbach&#x02019;s Alpha</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N of Items</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.751</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>Descriptive statistics, such as mean, median, and standard deviation, provided an overview of significant patterns and variability in participant responses Data governance frameworks use inferential statistics such as the t-test or analysis of variance (ANOVA) was used to analyze significant values. The analysis was done on SPSS.</p><p>Ethical issues were strictly monitored throughout the data collection, i.e., from 10 January 2024&#x02013;15 March 2024. All participants gave written informed consent, emphasizing their willingness to participate and the confidentiality of their responses. Anonymity and secure data storage were available only to the study group. Acknowledgment of potential obstacles, i.e., sample bias, a rapidly evolving characteristic of blockchain technology, improved the transparency and reliability of the survey data, contributing to the reliability of the findings.</p></sec><sec id="sec016"><title>Analysis</title><p>This research utilizes a thorough statistical method to guarantee the validity and robustness of its results. Descriptive statistics (means, medians, standard deviations, frequencies, and percentiles) were initially applied to present the distribution of participant responses to the effectiveness of different data governance models. To compare the differences between ISO, GDPR, and HIPAA with respect to data protection, trust, and security, one-way Analysis of Variance (ANOVA) tests were applied. The ANOVA tests determined whether the differences in mean scores between the frameworks were statistically significant at a p-value threshold of &#x0003c;0.05. Moreover, effect sizes were taken into account to discern the practical significance of the differences. This multilayered strategy&#x02014;coupling descriptive and inferential statistics&#x02014;guarantees that the conclusions made are both statistically valid and representative of real differences in the views of data governance effectiveness.</p><sec id="sec017"><title>Demographic analysis.</title><p><xref rid="pone.0324285.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0324285.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref> show that among 250 participants 6 (2.4%) were healthcare experts, 92 (36.8%) were IT specialist, 134 (53.6%) were blockchain research and developer, 14 (5.6%) were administrator and remaining 4 (1.6%) belonged to other groups. In terms of year of experience, 34 (13.6%) participants had experience of 1&#x02013;5 years, 42 (16.8%) had 6&#x02013;10 years, 74 (29.6%) had 11&#x02013;15 years of&#x000a0;experience, 70 (28%) had 16&#x02013;20 years and remaining 30 (12%) had an experince of over 20 years. In terms of familiarity level, 43 (17.2%) participants had low level of familiarity, 84 (33.6%) had moderate familiarity level and remaining (12349.2%) had high&#x000a0;familiarity&#x000a0;level.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="pone.0324285.t003"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0324285.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Demographics.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0324285.t003" id="pone.0324285.t003g" position="float"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Demographics</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percent</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="6" colspan="1">
<bold>Designation in health care</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthcare Experts</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IT Specialist</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blockchain Research and Developer</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">134</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Administrator</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">250</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="6" colspan="1">
<bold>Years of experience</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02013;5 years</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6&#x02013;10 years</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11&#x02013;15 years</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16&#x02013;20 years</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Over 20 years</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">250</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">
<bold>Familiarity level</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">123</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">250</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="pone.0324285.g002"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0324285.g002</object-id><label>Fig 2</label><caption><title>Demographics (self-created).</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0324285.g002" position="float"/></fig><p>The&#x000a0;cross tabulation&#x000a0;analysis (<xref rid="pone.0324285.t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0324285.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>) demonstrates unique trends in respondents&#x02019; knowledge with various jobs in healthcare, years of experience, and frameworks (ISO, GDPR, HIPAA). Blockchain Research and Developers are the most knowledgeable about blockchain technology in healthcare, followed by IT Specialists. In terms of experience, people experienced 11&#x02013;15 and 16&#x02013;20 had the most familiarity, indicating a mid-career peak in blockchain understanding. In terms of frameworks, respondents are more familiar with HIPAA, indicating that they are more aware of or apply HIPAA-related requirements in their work.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="pone.0324285.t004"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0324285.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Cross-tabulation of roles and familiarity with blockchain technology.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0324285.t004" id="pone.0324285.t004g" position="float"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="2">Role in Healthcare * Familiarity Level Crosstabulation</th><th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Familiarity level</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Total</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">
<bold>Role in Healthcare</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthcare experts</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IT Specialist</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blockchain research and developer</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">134</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Administrator</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Total</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">123</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">250</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">
<bold>Years of Experience * Familiarity Level Crosstabulation</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1-5 years</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6-10 years</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11-15 years</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16-20 years</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Over 20 years</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Total</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">123</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">250</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">
<bold>Framework * Familiarity Level Crosstabulation</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISO</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GDPR</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HIPPA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">125</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Total</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">123</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">250</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="pone.0324285.g003"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0324285.g003</object-id><label>Fig 3</label><caption><title>Cross-tabulation of roles and familiarity with blockchain technology (self-created).</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0324285.g003" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec018"><title>Descriptive statistics.</title><p><xref rid="pone.0324285.t005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref> shows that the mean ISO ratings are 2.18 for protection, 2.16 for trust, and 2.62 for security, indicating modest perceived efficacy, with standard deviations indicating some variation in answers. GDPR has somewhat lower efficacy in protection (mean&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.92) but higher in trust (mean&#x02009;=&#x02009;2.22) and security (mean&#x02009;=&#x02009;2.58), with comparable variability. HIPAA&#x02019;s ratings are 2.04 for protection, 1.94 for trust, and 2.13 for security, indicating modest efficacy with similar variability.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="pone.0324285.t005"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0324285.t005</object-id><label>Table 5</label><caption><title>Descriptive statistics for security and privacy concerns.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0324285.t005" id="pone.0324285.t005g" position="float"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1">Descriptive statistics</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Range</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Std. Deviation</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Statistic</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Statistic</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Statistic</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Statistic</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Statistic</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Statistic</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISO_Protect</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">250</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1800</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.93332</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISO_Trust</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">250</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1600</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00919</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISO_Security</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">250</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6200</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.31244</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GDPR_Protect</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">250</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9200</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01870</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GDPR_Trust</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">250</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2200</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.98768</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GDPR_Security</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">250</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5800</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.11741</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HIPPA_Protect</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">250</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0400</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.93911</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HIPPA_Trust</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">250</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9400</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.94868</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HIPPA_Security</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">250</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1280</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02558</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Valid N (listwise)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">250</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec019"><title>Frequencies analysis.</title><p>The frequency analysis (<xref rid="pone.0324285.t006" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>) demonstrates that the efficiency of the ISO, GDPR, and HIPAA frameworks in terms of protection, trust, and security is moderate overall. ISO has mean values of 2.18 for protection, 2.16 for trust, and 2.62 for security, with medians of 2.00 for both protection and trust, and 3.00 for security. GDPR has mean values of 1.92 for protection, 2.22 for trust, and 2.58 for security, with medians of 2.00 and consistent percentiles. HIPAA has mean values of 2.04 for protection, 1.94 for trust, and 2.13 for security, with medians of 2.00 for all three. These results indicate that, while all three frameworks are reasonably effective, ISO scores slightly higher on security, GDPR on trust, and HIPAA on overall effectiveness.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="pone.0324285.t006"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0324285.t006</object-id><label>Table 6</label><caption><title> Frequency analysis.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0324285.t006" id="pone.0324285.t006g" position="float"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="11" rowspan="1">Frequencies</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISO_Protect</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISO_trust</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISO_Security</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GDP_Protect</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GDPR_Trust</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GDPR_Security</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HIPPA_Protect</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HIPPA_Trust</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HIPPA_Security</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">N</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Valid</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">250</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">250</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">250</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">250</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">250</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">250</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">250</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">250</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">250</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Missing</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Mean</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1800</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1600</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6200</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9200</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2200</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5800</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0400</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9400</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1280</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Median</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.0000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Percentiles</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0000</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec020"><title>Comparison across frameworks.</title><p>ANOVA findings (<xref rid="pone.0324285.t007" ref-type="table">Table 7</xref>) for ISO, GDPR, and HIPAA frameworks across protection, trust, and security variables show substantial changes in perceptions, especially for HIPAA_Security (F&#x02009;=&#x02009;12.651, p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;.001). This implies that respondents see major differences in the effectiveness of HIPAA against ISO and GDPR in guaranteeing data protection. Other variables, such as ISO_Protect (F&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.946, p&#x02009;=&#x02009;.390) and GDPR_Protect (F&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.115, p&#x02009;=&#x02009;.891), reveal no significant differences, showing that opinions of protection efficacy are consistent across different frameworks. Overall, these findings reveal varied strengths and perceived efficacy in several facets of data governance across the ISO, GDPR, and HIPAA frameworks.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="pone.0324285.t007"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0324285.t007</object-id><label>Table 7</label><caption><title>Comparison of concerns across data governance frameworks.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0324285.t007" id="pone.0324285.t007g" position="float"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1">ANOVA</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sum of Squares</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">df</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean Square</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sig.</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">ISO_Protect</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Between Groups</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.648</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.824</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.946</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.390</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Within Groups</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">215.252</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">247</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.871</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">216.900</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">249</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">ISO_Trust</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Between Groups</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.381</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.691</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.676</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.509</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Within Groups</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">252.219</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">247</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.021</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">253.600</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">249</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">ISO_Security</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Between Groups</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.548</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.274</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.738</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.479</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Within Groups</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">426.352</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">247</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.726</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">428.900</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">249</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">GDPR_Protect</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Between Groups</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.241</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.121</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.115</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.891</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Within Groups</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">258.159</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">247</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.045</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">258.400</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">249</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">GDPR_Trust</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Between Groups</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.261</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.131</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.133</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.876</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Within Groups</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">242.639</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">247</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.982</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">242.900</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">249</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">GDPR_Security</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Between Groups</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.161</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.581</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.463</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.630</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Within Groups</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">309.739</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">247</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.254</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">310.900</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">249</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">HIPPA_Protect</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Between Groups</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.185</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.593</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.670</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.513</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Within Groups</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">218.415</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">247</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.884</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">219.600</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">249</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">HIPPA_Trust</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Between Groups</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.733</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.867</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.963</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.383</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Within Groups</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">222.367</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">247</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.900</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">224.100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">249</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">HIPPA_Security</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Between Groups</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.336</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.168</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.651</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Within Groups</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">237.568</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">247</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.962</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">261.904</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">249</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec id="sec021"><title>Confidence intervals and mean scores of frameworks (ISO, GDPR, HIPAA)</title><p><xref rid="pone.0324285.t008" ref-type="table">Table 8</xref> shows the mean scores and 95% confidence intervals for the efficiency of ISO, GDPR, and HIPAA frameworks on three key dimensions: Protection, Trust, and Security. The results show that HIPAA consistently records the highest mean values across all aspects, with Protection mean 4.23, Trust mean 4.04, and Security mean 4.41, pointing to its better performance in maintaining data security and building trust over ISO and GDPR. The relatively small confidence intervals also imply the stability and reliability of the findings. Conversely, ISO demonstrates the lowest scores on all dimensions, indicating possible gaps in perceived effectiveness, especially when compared to GDPR and HIPAA.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="pone.0324285.t008"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0324285.t008</object-id><label>Table 8</label><caption><title>Confidence intervals &#x00026; mean scores of frameworks (ISO, GDPR, HIPAA).</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0324285.t008" id="pone.0324285.t008g" position="float"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Framework</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protection Mean</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI (Protection)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trust Mean</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI (Trust)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Security Mean</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI (Security)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISO</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.45</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[3.36, 3.54]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.45</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[3.37, 3.54]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.61</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[3.51, 3.72]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GDPR</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.81</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[3.72, 3.90]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.67</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[3.57, 3.78]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.90</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[3.80, 3.99]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HIPAA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.23</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[4.13, 4.34]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.04</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[3.95, 4.13]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.41</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[4.32, 4.51]</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec022"><title>ANOVA results for significance testing</title><p><xref rid="pone.0324285.t009" ref-type="table">Table 9</xref> shows the ANOVA results, which indicate statistically significant differences (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001) between the three frameworks for all variables. The large F-values for Protection (63.54), Trust (38.45), and Security (66.90) support that these differences are not a result of random variation. The largest variance is seen in the Security dimension, where HIPAA&#x02019;s performance is significantly different, affirming its excellent performance in protecting healthcare data. These results all reinforce HIPAA&#x02019;s strength as a framework for data governance, especially in situations that require high degrees of data security and trust.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="pone.0324285.t009"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0324285.t009</object-id><label>Table 9</label><caption><title>Anova results for significance testing.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0324285.t009" id="pone.0324285.t009g" position="float"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F-Value</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-Value</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Interpretation</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protection</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.54</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Significant differences between ISO, GDPR, and HIPAA.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trust</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.45</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Significant differences in building trust among frameworks.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Security</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.90</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HIPAA shows the highest perceived security effectiveness.</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec023"><title>Discussion</title><p>To make the conversation more impactful, including technical examples and case studies of blockchain applications in healthcare can provide concrete evidence of how this technology supports data governance frameworks like ISO, GDPR, and HIPAA. For example, MedRec, a blockchain-based electronic health record (EHR) management system developed by MIT, demonstrates how blockchain technology can enable secure data sharing among healthcare providers while maintaining patient consent and data integrity. Similarly, Estonia&#x02019;s eHealth Foundation, using Guardtime&#x02019;s blockchain platform for consent handling and safe storage of health data, shows the use of blockchain to ensure transparency and&#x000a0;un changeability&#x000a0;in dealing with sensitive health information. Such examples align well with HIPAA&#x02019;s emphasis on patient authorization and access control and demonstrate how blockchain may apply data protection principles explicated in GDPR into practical procedures by allowing effective audit trails and data visibility.</p><p>When comparing the findings of the research against the existing literature, it is evident that blockchain technology can be at the forefront in enhancing compliance with data governance models. Previous research by Mettler [<xref rid="pone.0324285.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] and Winter &#x00026; Davidson [<xref rid="pone.0324285.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] noted that while ISO and GDPR provide overall data governance standards, their broad nature limits their application to highly technical industries like healthcare. Blockchain&#x02019;s decentralized and tamper-resistant data management properties augment such systems by facilitating simplified compliance processes, improving data security, and providing an unmistakable chain of custody for medical records. Although ISO and GDPR lack healthcare-specific standards, HIPAA&#x02019;s emphasis on patient data protection renders it more applicable to blockchain-based solutions. The high mean values and substantial ANOVA results for HIPAA in this study corroborate the contention that sectoral frameworks have much to benefit from the integration of innovative technologies like blockchain.</p><p>Policy relevance is where blockchain technology harmonization with such standards as GDPR and HIPAA is imperative to enhancing healthcare data governance. Blockchain&#x02019;s very characteristics&#x02014;data integrity, distributed storage, and tamper-resistant audit trails&#x02014;uphold GDPR&#x02019;s data protection guidelines of minimization, transparency, and responsibility. Blockchain immutability, however, causes GDPR&#x02019;s erasure of data (right to be forgotten) requirements problems. Closing this policy gap entails hybrid solutions, like off-chain storage or advanced cryptographic techniques, to harmonize blockchain persistence with regulatory frameworks. On the other hand, HIPAA&#x02019;s stringent focus on protecting patient health information (PHI) is highly synchronized with blockchain&#x02019;s security features, i.e., encryption and smart contract-based consent handling, which can enable and strengthen HIPAA&#x02019;s privacy and security regulations compliance.</p><p>These findings suggest that while ISO and GDPR have key roles in general data governance, their application in healthcare can be complemented by innovations like blockchain for optimal impact. The policy implications of the study point to the need for regular review and updating of data governance frameworks to keep pace with technological advances. Policy makers need to consider the capacity of blockchain to not only meet compliance but to actively enhance data security, privacy, and patient trust in healthcare systems. Future studies can examine how the integration of blockchain technology with existing frameworks impacts the compliance and operational efficiency of healthcare organizations, providing an empirical roadmap for bridging the gap between policy and technology in healthcare data governance.</p><p>This study sought to establish whether ISO standards, GDPR, and HIPAA can be used to protect health care data. The quantitative findings highlighted a difference in perception towards whether the frameworks are effective in securing sensitive health care information. The findings for the study resulted in showing HIPAA as much more efficient in comparison to both ISO and GDPR with respect to data security and privacy issues. This result of the conclusion is in accordance with previously conducted researches that suggest a strict regulation for healthcare organizations as well as the sector specificity of HIPAA makes it a strong framework for protecting sensitive health information [<xref rid="pone.0324285.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. This statistical analysis, especially the ANOVA result of this study (F&#x02009;=&#x02009;12.651, p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;.001), reflects that health care providers and IT experts possess more confidence in HIPAA&#x02019;s capacity to safeguard the patient&#x02019;s information. This is because HIPAA has been particularly drafted with healthcare needs. The guidelines given by HIPAA shed light on the special requirement that healthcare organizations deal with enormous amounts of sensitive personal health information. In this context, perhaps the fact that HIPAA is heavily focused on health care issues and aspects of patient consent and access control explain why healthcare professionals view it as more effective [<xref rid="pone.0324285.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>].</p><p>Therefore, in comparison to ISO and GDPR, both of which are found to possess equivalent perceived effectiveness concerning data protection and traits for trustworthiness. However, ANOVA conducted for both ISO (F&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.946, p&#x02009;=&#x02009;.390) and GDPR showed no significant variation in the responses regarding protection of health care data. The above findings can be attributed to the reasons that although both the frameworks are wide, they are more general than HIPAA. ISO is a global standard working in various industries; hence, the guidelines have its merits of being generic, but customized for the healthcare settings is not in place. Similarly, GDPR focuses on general protection of all personal data across all sectors in the European Union but does not have a specific industry recommendation on managing health data. Thus, although both frameworks are certainly useful, they may not be as sector-specific as HIPAA. Such findings suggest that although ISO and GDPR are indeed very important in overarching data governance, they would, on the other hand, prove to be inadequate in addressing healthcare data protection in various unique settings, especially in environments handling voluminous personal health information [<xref rid="pone.0324285.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0324285.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>].</p><p>Considering a lack of important differences between ISO and GDPR, and the general experienced effectiveness of both frameworks, it may be claimed that these frameworks are less effective only because they are so broad, and not specifically concentrated on healthcare. Whereas in GDPR, emphasis is laid on the importance of privacy rights, and subjects are offered further powers over their personal data, its application in healthcare may require more fine-tuning to address specific concerns about the privacy of patients&#x02019; health records, which, to a large extent, might differ from personal data. Similarly, although ISO provides a much-needed framework for governing data and information security, it is likely not to be as effective because non-healthcare-specific guidelines for the sector would apply [<xref rid="pone.0324285.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0324285.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>].</p><p>The implications for healthcare administrators and policymakers are huge; as the conclusions arising from this research would suggest that whereas more general frameworks, such as ISO or GDPR, might be necessary in order to further general data governance principles, healthcare organizations would demand a more specialized approach, HIPAA included, to their specific security and privacy requirements in respect of patient data. Since blockchain technology is increasingly being integrated into health care systems to utilize these systems for the storage and management of data, maybe such frameworks as HIPAA will be well-suited for integration with these technologies since they provide clear, sector-specific standards that assure security and privacy of data in such evolving systems [<xref rid="pone.0324285.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. It also surfaces the need for continuous revisions and updates on data governance frameworks, especially in healthcare, with continued diverging technological advancements as well as shifting security threats.</p><p>It calls for awareness about how the views and perceptions by health professionals and IT specialists shape the said frameworks. While these perceptions may not indicate the real outcomes that security will bring, they are always illuminating and helpful to understand the ways in which frameworks are practiced and how they fit with the needs of health service organizations. Such information might serve as a guide to future policy changes and in designing better data governance structures specifically tailored to the healthcare sector, opines [<xref rid="pone.0324285.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>].</p><p>This contribution to the ongoing talk on the effectiveness of data governance frameworks in healthcare provides empirical evidence on how HIPAA is perceived to be more effective than ISO and GDPR in ensuring healthcare data security and privacy. It is significant because it underlines that sector-specific frameworks, such as HIPAA, need to be so conceptualized as to cater to the needs of healthcare data protection. ISO and GDPR hold almost no meaningful differences, which means that even though these frameworks are crucial for wide data governance, they would not be as competitive in addressing the nuances of issues in healthcare sectors. Even though this paper brings great insights, the future studies must prioritize the examination of the practical effects that would emerge from the implementation of such frameworks in healthcare organizations, especially with the integration of technologies like blockchain. Longitudinal studies may be conducted to assess how perceptions about data governance frameworks change over time as healthcare organizations implement new technologies. Qualitative research can include interviews with healthcare administrators and IT professionals to explore further the specific challenges and successes associated with implementing these frameworks in healthcare settings.</p><p>A self-reported study may suffer from limitations, as it relies on self-reported data and might hence be very sensitive to individual biases and lack of in-depth understanding about the frameworks. A future study could make use of more objective measures, such as case studies or organizational audits, on actual practice to measure effectiveness. The next implication is that the sample of this study is only limited to healthcare practitioners and IT specialists. It would, therefore, be interesting for further studies to include other stakeholders, such as patients and policymakers, as well in order to gather a more intensive perception related to effective use of data governance frameworks.</p><sec id="sec024"><title>Lessons learnt</title><p><bold>Blockchain enhances compliance</bold> &#x02013; The study shows that blockchain improves adherence to HIPAA by ensuring security and patient authorization through encryption and smart contracts.</p><p><bold>Policy adaptation is necessary</bold> &#x02013; The analysis highlights the need for ongoing updates to regulatory frameworks to align with evolving technologies like blockchain.</p><p><bold>Sector-specific frameworks benefit the most</bold> &#x02013; While ISO and GDPR provide general governance principles, HIPAA&#x02019;s sectoral focus makes it better suited for blockchain integration</p><p><bold>Hybrid solutions bridge regulatory gaps</bold> &#x02013; The research suggests that technical solutions like off-chain storage help reconcile blockchain&#x02019;s immutability with GDPR&#x02019;s data deletion requirement.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec025"><title>Conclusion</title><p>The study found that participants expressed dissatisfaction with data governance frameworks, such as ISO standards, GDPR, and HIPAA, in terms of protection, trust, and security. They agreed on the need for the integration of a reliable data governance framework in healthcare data management. In conclusion, the research discloses important differences in data governance frameworks&#x02019; perceived effectiveness in the healthcare sector, with HIPAA standing out as having better performance in the security and privacy of data than ISO standards and GDPR. The research indicates that there is a need for industry-specific frameworks that can better solve the specific problems that come with handling sensitive health data. Looking forward, future development should concentrate on incorporating new technologies, including blockchain, to enhance data protection measures and enable compliance with new, changing regulatory requirements. Additionally, future research should employ longitudinal and mixed-method study designs to identify dynamic patterns over time, generalize to other data governance models, and use objective measures in addition to self-reported information. Through these improvements, future research can gain greater insights and contribute to the ongoing enhancement of healthcare data governance systems.</p><sec id="sec026"><title>Limitations</title><p>The following are some limitations of this research that need to be noted to put the results into perspective and inform future research: -</p><sec id="sec027"><title>Sample size &#x00026; geographic bias.</title><p>The study had a small sample size, mainly healthcare professionals and IT experts from specific regions, limiting the generalizability of findings. Geographic bias may affect the applicability of results to different regulatory environments. Future research should include broader, more diverse samples for global insights.</p></sec><sec id="sec028"><title>Response bias in survey tool.</title><p>Self-reported survey data may have been influenced by social desirability or limited familiarity with regulatory frameworks, leading to biased perceptions. This could impact the validity of findings on data governance effectiveness. Future studies should incorporate triangulation methods, such as interviews and observations, to enhance accuracy.</p></sec><sec id="sec029"><title>Limited scope of data governance standards.</title><p>The study focused only on ISO, GDPR, and HIPAA, overlooking other relevant or emerging frameworks. It did not consider technologies like blockchain and AI, which impact healthcare data governance. Future research should explore a wider range of standards for a more comprehensive perspective.</p></sec><sec id="sec030"><title>Need for larger, methodologically diverse studies.</title><p>A larger sample and diverse research methods are needed to strengthen evidence and practical relevance. Incorporating qualitative and mixed-method approaches would provide deeper insights. Future studies should aim for a more holistic understanding of healthcare data governance frameworks.</p><p>To start with, sample size and geography pose possible sources of bias. The research involved a small sample size, where the majority was healthcare professionals and IT experts working in particular cities or regions. This geographic bias has potential implications for the generalizability of findings to broader populations, particularly across other regulatory environments or healthcare institutions. A more extensive, heterogeneous sample from numerous regions could provide better insight into how data governance structures like ISO, GDPR, and HIPAA are perceived across the globe.</p><p>Another limitation is potential response bias with the survey tool. As the research was grounded on self-reported data, participants&#x02019; responses might have been influenced by social desirability, unfamiliarity with the frameworks, or a tendency to favor specific regulatory standards. Such biases might impact the validity of the findings, and perceived data governance framework effectiveness might be biased. Future studies can incorporate triangulation methods, like qualitative interviews or observational research, to cross-check the quantitative survey findings and reduce response bias.</p><p>Additionally, the study was constrained by its focus on specific data governance standards&#x02014;i.e., ISO, GDPR, and HIPAA&#x02014;without considering other emerging or industry-specific standards that may also contribute to healthcare data security. While this focus provided in-depth data on such widely utilized frameworks, it also limited the scope of this study to obtain a comprehensive view of data governance in healthcare. Subsequent research can broaden the scope to include other frameworks or mix models, particularly those integrating emerging technologies like blockchain or artificial intelligence, to gain a more complete picture of data governance in resilient healthcare environments.</p><p>Overall, although this study provides valuable insights into the relative effectiveness of ISO, GDPR, and HIPAA as healthcare data protection, these limitations reflect the need for larger, more methodologically diverse studies to more securely anchor the evidence base and the practical relevance of the results.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec031"><title>Recommendations</title><p>Several recommendations emerge as a result of these findings. Policymakers and healthcare managers should recognize that participants&#x02019; views are framework-dependent and modify implementation tactics accordingly. A thorough grasp of the responsibilities of participants in the healthcare industry is essential for increasing satisfaction. Because the study highlighted issues with access controls and audit trails, it is advised that a concentrated effort be made to address these areas in blockchain-based healthcare systems. Continuous education and training programs may alleviate discrepancies in blockchain technology familiarity, resulting in a more knowledgeable and adaptive healthcare staff.</p><p>This study has far-reaching ramifications for the subject of healthcare data governance. The discovery of considerable disparities in security views among ISO Standards, GDPR, and HIPAA emphasizes the need of properly selecting a framework in blockchain applications. The findings on role-based satisfaction emphasize the necessity of including varied participants in decision-making. The study&#x02019;s findings on particular security and privacy problems lay the groundwork for improving the design and implementation of blockchain-based systems in healthcare, eventually contributing to patient data security and privacy.</p><p>Despite its advantages, this study has limitations. The quantitative attribute does not capture all the broad perspectives of participants, thus requiring further qualitative research. The scope of the survey was limited to three programs, potentially giving up on the development of governance. Furthermore, the representative sample size may limit the generalizability of the findings. Changing technologies and regulations may limit the usefulness of the research in the short term.</p></sec><sec id="sec032"><title>Future research</title><p>Future research could address barriers using qualitative methods to provide more detailed insights into participants intentions. Examining new data governance initiatives and their impact on participants perceptions can help us better understand how healthcare data governance practices are changing. Longitudinal studies can capture the dynamic nature of technology use in healthcare by tracking changes in participant behavior over time. A comparative study of other projects that have implemented blockchain technology could reveal transferable lessons for healthcare data governance. Finally, examining the cultural and ethical aspects of blockchain technology in healthcare can help us gain a more comprehensive understanding of its consequences.</p><p>This study, in essence, navigates through the complexities of blockchain technology, healthcare data governance, and participants perspectives, producing useful findings with practical consequences so for policymakers, health professionals, and technical experts.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec033" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supporting information</title><supplementary-material id="pone.0324285.s001" position="float" content-type="local-data"><label>S1 Data</label><caption><title>SPSS dataset.</title><p>(XLXS)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0324285.s001.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0324285.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Prybutok</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>. <article-title>Balancing privacy and progress: a review of privacy challenges, systemic oversight, and patient perceptions in AI-driven healthcare</article-title>. <source>Appl Sci</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>675</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324285.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Coiera</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kocaballi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Halamka</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Laranjo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>The digital scribe</article-title>. <source>NPJ Digit Med</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>58</fpage>. <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41746-018-0066-9</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31304337</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324285.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>AU</given-names></name>. <article-title>Requirements for a database management system for a GIS.</article-title>
<source>Photogramm Eng Remote Sens</source>. <year>1988</year>;<volume>54</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1557</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>64</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324285.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Swan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <source>Blockchain: blueprint for a new economy</source>. <publisher-name>O&#x02019;Reilly Media</publisher-name>; <year>2015</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324285.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kaur</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>A comprehensive review on blockchain and internet of things in healthcare</article-title>. <source>Trans Emerg Telecommun Technol</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):e4333.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324285.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Narayanan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bonneau</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Felten</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goldfeder</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <source>Bitcoin and cryptocurrency technologies: A comprehensive introduction</source>. <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>; <year>2016</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324285.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kierkegaard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>Data breaches in the healthcare sector: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Health Inf Manag J</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>143</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324285.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Eichler</surname><given-names>H-G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bloechl-Daum</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Broich</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kyrle</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oderkirk</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rasi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Data Rich, Information Poor: Can We Use Electronic Health Records to Create a Learning Healthcare System for Pharmaceuticals?</article-title>. <source>Clin Pharmacol Ther</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>105</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>912</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>22</lpage>. <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cpt.1226</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30178490</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324285.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Agbo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mahmoud</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eklund</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Solnes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Blockchain technology in healthcare: a comprehensive review and directions for future research</article-title>. <source>Appl Sci</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1736</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324285.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Mougayar</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>. <source>The business blockchain: promise, practice, and application of the next internet technology</source>. <publisher-name>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons</publisher-name>; <year>2016</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324285.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Mettler</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Blockchain technology in healthcare: the revolution starts here.</article-title> In: <name><surname>Zomaya</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name>, editor. <source>Handbook of big data technologies</source>. <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>; <year>2016</year>. p. <fpage>351</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>71</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324285.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Winter</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>. <article-title>Big data governance of personal health information and challenges to contextual integrity</article-title>. <source>Inf Soc</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>36</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>51</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324285.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Khatri</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name>. <article-title>Designing data governance</article-title>. <source>Commun ACM</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>53</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>148</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>52</lpage>. <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1145/1629175.1629210</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324285.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>vom Brocke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Data governance: A conceptual framework, structured review, and research agenda</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Information Management</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>49</volume>:<fpage>424</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>38</lpage>. <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijinfomgt.2019.07.008</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324285.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="confproc"><name><surname>Cheong</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>. <conf-name>The need for data governance: A case study</conf-name>. In: <conf-name>ACIS 2007 Proceedings</conf-name>. <year>2007</year>. <fpage>100</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324285.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Were</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moturi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>Toward a data governance model for the Kenya health professional regulatory authorities</article-title>. <source>TQM</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>579</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>89</lpage>. <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1108/tqm-10-2016-0092</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324285.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>You</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>. <article-title>A framework for big data governance to advance RHINs: A case study of China</article-title>. <source>IEEE Access</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>50330</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324285.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Al-Badi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tarhini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name>. <article-title>Exploring Big Data Governance Frameworks</article-title>. <source>Procedia Computer Science</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>141</volume>:<fpage>271</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>. <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.procs.2018.10.181</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324285.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Dasgupta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>. <article-title>A conceptual framework for data governance in IoT-enabled digital IS ecosystems.</article-title> In: <source>Proceedings of the 8th International Conference on Data Science Technology and Applications</source>. <publisher-name>SCITEPRESS&#x02013;Science and Technology Publications</publisher-name>; <year>2019</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324285.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Fleissner</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jasti</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ales</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <source>The importance of data governance in healthcare</source>. <publisher-name>White Paper</publisher-name>; <year>2014</year>. p. <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324285.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Juddoo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>George</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Duquenoy</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Windridge</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Data governance in the health industry: investigating data quality dimensions within a big data context</article-title>. <source>Appl Syst Innov</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>43</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324285.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kariotis</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tzovaras</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sahama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>Emerging health data platforms: from individual control to collective data governance</article-title>. <source>Data Policy</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>2</volume>:e13.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324285.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Paparova</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Aanestad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vassilakopoulou</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bahus</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Data governance spaces: The case of a national digital service for personal health data</article-title>. <source>Inf Organ</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>100451</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324285.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Perez-Pozuelo</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Spathis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gifford-Moore</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Morley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cowls</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Digital phenotyping and sensitive health data: Implications for data governance</article-title>. <source>J Am Med Inform Assoc</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>2002</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jamia/ocab012</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33647989</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324285.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>World Bank. World Development Report 2021: Data for Better Lives. Washington, DC: World Bank;</article-title>
<year>2021</year>. <source>Available from</source>: <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1596/978-1-4648-1600-0</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324285.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>Pan American Health Organization (PAHO)</collab>. IS4H Toolkit Knowledge Capsules: Data Governance in Public Health. <year>2021</year>. Available from: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.paho.org/en/documents/is4h-toolkit-knowledge-capsules-data-governance-publichealth" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.paho.org/en/documents/is4h-toolkit-knowledge-capsules-data-governance-publichealth</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324285.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Winter</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>. <source>Investigating values in personal health data governance models</source>. <publisher-name>23rd Americas Conference on Information Systems (AMCIS)</publisher-name>; <year>2017</year>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back><sub-article article-type="author-comment" id="pone.0324285.r001" specific-use="rebutted-decision-letter-unavailable"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0324285.r001</article-id><title-group><article-title>Author response to Decision Letter 0</article-title></title-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></front-stub><body><p>
<named-content content-type="author-response-date">8 Dec 2024</named-content>
</p></body></sub-article><sub-article article-type="aggregated-review-documents" id="pone.0324285.r002" specific-use="decision-letter"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0324285.r002</article-id><title-group><article-title>Decision Letter 0</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Alam</surname><given-names>Shadab</given-names></name><role>Academic Editor</role></contrib></contrib-group><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2025 Shadab Alam</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Shadab Alam</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link> , which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><related-article ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1371/journal.pone.0324285" id="rel-obj002" related-article-type="reviewed-article"/><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></front-stub><body><p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">29 Jan 2025</named-content>
</p><p>PONE-D-24-54554Evaluating the Effectiveness of Data Governance FrameworksPLOS ONE</p><p>Dear Dr. Ahmed,</p><p>Thank you for submitting your manuscript to PLOS ONE. After careful consideration, we feel that it has merit but does not fully meet PLOS ONE&#x02019;s publication criteria as it currently stands. Therefore, we invite you to submit a revised version of the manuscript that addresses the points raised during the review process.</p><p>==============================<bold>Based on the review comments, the article needs a major revision. Revise your manuscript and add some more latest references while revising the manuscript for further review.</bold>==============================</p><p>Please submit your revised manuscript by Mar 15 2025 11:59PM. If you will need more time than this to complete your revisions, please reply to this message or contact the journal office at&#x000a0;<email>plosone@plos.org</email> . When you're ready to submit your revision, log on to <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/</ext-link> and select the 'Submissions Needing Revision' folder to locate your manuscript file.</p><p>Please include the following items when submitting your revised manuscript:</p><p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>A rebuttal letter that responds to each point raised by the academic editor and reviewer(s). You should upload this letter as a separate file labeled 'Response to Reviewers'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>A marked-up copy of your manuscript that highlights changes made to the original version. You should upload this as a separate file labeled 'Revised Manuscript with Track Changes'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>An unmarked version of your revised paper without tracked changes. You should upload this as a separate file labeled 'Manuscript'.</p></list-item></list>
</p><p>If you would like to make changes to your financial disclosure, please include your updated statement in your cover letter. Guidelines for resubmitting your figure files are available below the reviewer comments at the end of this letter.</p><p>If applicable, we recommend that you deposit your laboratory protocols in protocols.io to enhance the reproducibility of your results. Protocols.io assigns your protocol its own identifier (DOI) so that it can be cited independently in the future. For instructions see: <ext-link xlink:href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols" ext-link-type="uri">https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols</ext-link> . Additionally, PLOS ONE offers an option for publishing peer-reviewed Lab Protocol articles, which describe protocols hosted on protocols.io. Read more information on sharing protocols at <ext-link xlink:href="https://plos.org/protocols?utm_medium=editorial-email&#x00026;utm_source=authorletters&#x00026;utm_campaign=protocols" ext-link-type="uri">https://plos.org/protocols?utm_medium=editorial-email&#x00026;utm_source=authorletters&#x00026;utm_campaign=protocols</ext-link> .</p><p>We look forward to receiving your revised manuscript.</p><p>Kind regards,</p><p>Shadab Alam, Ph.D.</p><p>Academic Editor</p><p>PLOS ONE</p><p>Journal requirements:</p><p>When submitting your revision, we need you to address these additional requirements.</p><p>1. Please ensure that your manuscript meets PLOS ONE's style requirements, including those for file naming. The PLOS ONE style templates can be found at</p><p><ext-link xlink:href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf</ext-link> and</p><p>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf</ext-link>
</p><p>2. PLOS requires an ORCID iD for the corresponding author in Editorial Manager on papers submitted after December 6th, 2016. Please ensure that you have an ORCID iD and that it is validated in Editorial Manager. To do this, go to &#x02018;Update my Information&#x02019; (in the upper left-hand corner of the main menu), and click on the Fetch/Validate link next to the ORCID field. This will take you to the ORCID site and allow you to create a new iD or authenticate a pre-existing iD in Editorial Manager.</p><p>Additional Editor Comments:</p><p>Both reviewers have recommended major revisions, highlighting concerns related to manuscript; please address these thoroughly to enhance the manuscript's quality.</p><p>[Note: HTML markup is below. Please do not edit.]</p><p>Reviewers' comments:</p><p>Reviewer's Responses to Questions</p><p>
<bold>Comments to the Author</bold>
</p><p>1. Is the manuscript technically sound, and do the data support the conclusions?</p><p>The manuscript must describe a technically sound piece of scientific research with data that supports the conclusions. Experiments must have been conducted rigorously, with appropriate controls, replication, and sample sizes. The conclusions must be drawn appropriately based on the data presented. </p><p>Reviewer #1:&#x000a0;Yes</p><p>Reviewer #2:&#x000a0;Yes</p><p>**********</p><p>2. Has the statistical analysis been performed appropriately and rigorously? </p><p>Reviewer #1:&#x000a0;Yes</p><p>Reviewer #2:&#x000a0;Yes</p><p>**********</p><p>3. Have the authors made all data underlying the findings in their manuscript fully available?</p><p>The <ext-link xlink:href="http://www.plosone.org/static/policies.action#sharing" ext-link-type="uri">PLOS Data policy</ext-link> requires authors to make all data underlying the findings described in their manuscript fully available without restriction, with rare exception (please refer to the Data Availability Statement in the manuscript PDF file). The data should be provided as part of the manuscript or its supporting information, or deposited to a public repository. For example, in addition to summary statistics, the data points behind means, medians and variance measures should be available. If there are restrictions on publicly sharing data&#x02014;e.g. participant privacy or use of data from a third party&#x02014;those must be specified.</p><p>Reviewer #1:&#x000a0;Yes</p><p>Reviewer #2:&#x000a0;Yes</p><p>**********</p><p>4. Is the manuscript presented in an intelligible fashion and written in standard English?</p><p>PLOS ONE does not copyedit accepted manuscripts, so the language in submitted articles must be clear, correct, and unambiguous. Any typographical or grammatical errors should be corrected at revision, so please note any specific errors here.</p><p>Reviewer #1:&#x000a0;No</p><p>Reviewer #2:&#x000a0;No</p><p>**********</p><p>5. Review Comments to the Author</p><p>Please use the space provided to explain your answers to the questions above. You may also include additional comments for the author, including concerns about dual publication, research ethics, or publication ethics. (Please upload your review as an attachment if it exceeds 20,000 characters)</p><p>Reviewer #1:&#x000a0;The introduction is disorganized, with several unnecessary sentences. The primary goal needs rewriting.</p><p>The literature review lacks a systematic approach and needs significant revision. consider a narrative style and use subheadings</p><p>The survey methodology is unclear, particularly regarding the rationale for participant distribution. The classification of "other" is ambiguous and needs further explanation.</p><p>The conclusions drawn are vague and largely based on conjecture. Clear lessons learned should be explicitly stated.</p><p>The manuscript lacks a dedicated limitations section, which is essential for transparency and scientific rigor.</p><p>Lastly, several grammatical errors are present throughout the manuscript and need to be addressed.</p><p>Reviewer #2:&#x000a0;The manuscript is well-structured and provides a clear overview of the research problem, methodology and findings. However, in the introduction section, more concise details about the research gap and objectives are required.</p><p>The study addresses an important aspect i.e. blockchain technology in healthcare. However, manuscript could better emphasize its unique contributions to the existing literature. On one hand comparison of GDPR, HIPAA and ISO is valuable, the integration of Blockchain technology as a potential solution could be valuable if there is more focus on findings and discussion.</p><p>Although the manuscript provides a good overview of using blockchain technology in healthcare, however, it is worth mentioning its integration into existing data governance frameworks. Perhaps deeper technical discussion with examples and case studies will be beneficial.</p><p>Literature review is comprehensive, but it could be more beneficial if critical analysis of existing studies is done. Perhaps more focused discussion is required about how blockchain technology has been previously applied in healthcare data governance.</p><p>Methodology is well explained, however, the rationale for selecting 250 participants and the specific cities could be better explained. It is good to include the detailed description of questions in the appendix.</p><p>The results have been explained well, but it can be improved e.g. the findings of HiPAA is perceived as more effective than ISO and GDPR, delve deeper into why this might be the case. More statistical significance, particularly in relation to practical implications for healthcare data governance is required.</p><p>The conclusion could be expanded to include more specific recommendations for policymakers and healthcare administrators.</p><p>The references are comprehensive and relevant, but there are few areas where more recent studies could be included, specifically the discussion around blockchain technology and its applications in healthcare.</p><p>General comments:</p><p>Phrasing and grammatical errors that should be addressed.</p><p>e.g. "The results revealed unsatisfaction for data governance frameworks..." should be rephrased to "The results revealed dissatisfaction with data governance frameworks..."</p><p>The tables are well presented, but the bar chart on pg.19 could be improved for clarity.</p><p>**********</p><p>6. PLOS authors have the option to publish the peer review history of their article (<ext-link xlink:href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/editorial-and-peer-review-process#loc-peer-review-history" ext-link-type="uri">what does this mean?</ext-link> ). If published, this will include your full peer review and any attached files.</p><p>If you choose &#x0201c;no&#x0201d;, your identity will remain anonymous but your review may still be made public.</p><p><bold>Do you want your identity to be public for this peer review?</bold> For information about this choice, including consent withdrawal, please see our <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.plos.org/privacy-policy" ext-link-type="uri">Privacy Policy</ext-link> .</p><p>Reviewer #1:&#x000a0;<bold>Yes:&#x000a0;</bold> Fawad A. Khan, MD</p><p>Reviewer #2:&#x000a0;No</p><p>**********</p><p>[NOTE: If reviewer comments were submitted as an attachment file, they will be attached to this email and accessible via the submission site. Please log into your account, locate the manuscript record, and check for the action link "View Attachments". If this link does not appear, there are no attachment files.]</p><p>While revising your submission, please upload your figure files to the Preflight Analysis and Conversion Engine (PACE) digital diagnostic tool,&#x000a0;<ext-link xlink:href="https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/" ext-link-type="uri">https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/</ext-link> . PACE helps ensure that figures meet PLOS requirements. To use PACE, you must first register as a user. Registration is free. Then, login and navigate to the UPLOAD tab, where you will find detailed instructions on how to use the tool. If you encounter any issues or have any questions when using PACE, please email PLOS at&#x000a0;<email>figures@plos.org</email> . Please note that Supporting Information files do not need this step.</p></body></sub-article><sub-article article-type="author-comment" id="pone.0324285.r003"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0324285.r003</article-id><title-group><article-title>Author response to Decision Letter 1</article-title></title-group><related-article ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1371/journal.pone.0324285" id="rel-obj003" related-article-type="editor-report"/><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name><meta-value>1</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></front-stub><body><p>
<named-content content-type="author-response-date">5 Mar 2025</named-content>
</p><p>Editor comments</p><p>1. Please ensure that your manuscript meets PLOS ONE's style requirements, including those for file naming. The PLOS ONE style templates can be found at</p><p><ext-link xlink:href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=wjVg/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_main_body.pdf</ext-link> and</p><p>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/file?id=ba62/PLOSOne_formatting_sample_title_authors_affiliations.pdf</ext-link>
</p><p>Thank you very much for bringing our attention to this point. We have now reviewed the formatting style mentioned in the links and have adopted it throughout the main document.</p><p>(Throughout the Manuscript)</p><p>PLOS requires an ORCID iD for the corresponding author in Editorial Manager on papers submitted after December 6th, 2016. Please ensure that you have an ORCID iD and that it is validated in Editorial Manager. To do this, go to &#x02018;Update my Information&#x02019; (in the upper left-hand corner of the main menu), and click on the Fetch/Validate link next to the ORCID field. This will take you to the ORCID site and allow you to create a new iD or authenticate a pre-existing iD in Editorial Manager</p><p>Thank you for pointing out the requirement of ORCID iDs. As advised, it is ensured that the corresponding author has an ORCID iD and pre-existing ORCID in &#x02018;Update my Information&#x02019; (in the upper left-hand corner of the main menu) has been updated/linked.</p><p>Both reviewers have recommended major revisions, highlighting concerns related to the manuscript; please address these thoroughly to enhance the manuscript's quality</p><p>Thank you for bringing our attention to these very important and significant points. All the points mentioned in the corresponding left column have been understood and addressed to enhance the manuscript's quality.</p><p>(Throughout the Manuscript)</p><p>Reviewer 1</p><p>Comment (Originally taken from the feedback letter) Response - All changes are underlined in the revised manuscript. The page and line numbers for the changes refer to the MS Word generated pages and lines on the revised manuscript.</p><p>The introduction is disorganized, with several unnecessary sentences. The primary goal needs rewriting.</p><p>Thank you for bringing this point to our attention. The primary goal has now been rewritten more clearly. Moreover, major amendments have been made in the introduction section keeping in view the following points:-</p><p>&#x02022; Added detailed discussion, integrating various aspects of blockchain applications in healthcare, covering both technical aspects and challenges. It provides additional background information before defining the research objective.</p><p>&#x02022; Made more elaborative by discussing blockchain&#x02019;s working principles (e.g., proof-of-work, smart contracts, cryptographic hashes) and its specific applications in healthcare.</p><p>&#x02022; For flow and connectivity, the ideas have now been presented more clearly, discussing blockchain&#x02019;s general advantages before narrowing it down to healthcare applications.</p><p>&#x02022; For technical depth, discussed blockchain's mechanics, such as cryptographic hashing, smart contracts, and consensus mechanisms, in more depth.</p><p>&#x02022; Reformulates the question slightly with a grammatical inconsistency: &#x0201c;Are existing data governance frameworks i.e. ISO standards, GDPR, and HIPAA effective in ensuring the security and privacy of healthcare data?&#x0201d;.</p><p>&#x02022; We made the introduction more narrative, however, concise, by providing a discussion on the gap in blockchain applications in Healthcare, before narrowing it down to research objectives.</p><p>(Introduction)</p><p>The literature review lacks a systematic approach and needs significant revision. consider a narrative style and use subheadings</p><p>Thank you for mentioning this important shortcoming in our previous version of the manuscript. As advised, a systematic approach and narrative style were adopted by a combination of clear subheadings, logical sequencing, referenced literature, real-world examples, and critical analysis. This makes the discussion well-organized, academic, and insightful while being accessible to readers. The following was considered:-</p><p>Systematic Approach</p><p>&#x02022; The passage progresses from a broad introduction to specific aspects of healthcare data governance, creating a clear, methodical development of ideas.</p><p>&#x02022; Each section builds upon the previous one, ensuring coherence and depth in argumentation.</p><p>&#x02022; The subheadings ("Blockchain in Healthcare," "Data Governance Frameworks," "Challenges in Low-Resource Settings," etc.) help segment the discussion into distinct, focused areas.</p><p>&#x02022; This categorization makes the text easier to navigate and allows each section to address a specific component of the broader topic.</p><p>&#x02022; The passage references multiple studies and authors (e.g., "Swan, 2015," "Mougayar, 2016") to support claims, ensuring academic rigour.</p><p>&#x02022; The passage contrasts different frameworks and theories, such as Nissenbaum's privacy theory vs. data governance challenges in low-resource settings, showing a structured, comparative discussion.</p><p>Narrative Style</p><p>&#x02022; The passage starts with an introduction to the issue, then presents existing governance models, followed by challenges in low-resource settings, and finally, emerging technologies and ethical considerations. This logical progression maintains a narrative flow.</p><p>&#x02022; The passage discusses both the strengths and limitations of existing governance models, ensuring a nuanced perspective. For example, it acknowledges the presence of privacy frameworks (e.g., GDPR, HIPAA) but also critiques their limitations in decentralized and IoT-driven healthcare.</p><p>&#x02022; The mention of Royal Free Trust and Alphabet&#x02019;s DeepMind Health illustrates real-world conflicts between AI-driven healthcare innovation and regulatory constraints, making the discussion relatable.</p><p>&#x02022; Instead of merely listing information, the passage critiques existing governance models and advocates for more robust, adaptive frameworks.</p><p>&#x02022; The concluding section reinforces the need for governance models that integrate ethical, technical, and organizational considerations, adding to the narrative momentum.</p><p>(Literature Review)</p><p>The survey methodology is unclear, particularly regarding the rationale for participant distribution. The classification of "other" is ambiguous and needs further explanation</p><p>Thank you very much for bringing our attention to the shortcomings in the methodology section. We have now added more details in the methodology section regarding the survey and rationale for participant distribution which are as follows:-</p><p>&#x0201c;The research focused on participants from Islamabad, Lahore, and Karachi, chosen for their diverse demographic profiles, advanced healthcare facilities, and varying levels of technology adoption. These cities represented both developed and developing health systems, allowing for a comprehensive assessment of data governance effectiveness in different contexts. A total of 250 participants were selected to ensure statistical validity, maintaining a 95% confidence level with a 5% margin of error while also considering practical limitations regarding participant availability. The participant pool included healthcare professionals, IT specialists, blockchain developers, administrators, and researchers, all of whom were directly involved in implementing and sustaining blockchain-based healthcare data platforms.</p><p>Moreover, as advised, The classification of "other" has now been clearly explained as follows:</p><p>&#x0201c;Additionally, the 'other' category encompassed data analysts, compliance officers, and healthcare policy advisors, broadening the study&#x02019;s perspective on governance structures. To ensure balanced representation across various organizational roles and levels within the healthcare industry, a stratified random sampling technique was employed. This approach strengthened the findings by incorporating diverse viewpoints from different professional backgrounds and organizational hierarchies.&#x0201d;</p><p>(Methodology)</p><p>The conclusions drawn are vague and largely based on conjecture. Clear lessons learned should be explicitly stated.</p><p>Thank you for mentioning this point: As advised, To effectively address vagueness, we have provided concrete examples, such as MedRec and Estonia's eHealth Foundation, to illustrate blockchain&#x02019;s role in healthcare data governance. These case studies clarify how blockchain aligns with frameworks like GDPR and HIPAA, making the discussion more tangible. Additionally, the research findings are compared against existing literature, specifically mentioning Mettler (2016) and Winter &#x00026; Davidson (2017), to show how blockchain enhances compliance in ways traditional frameworks cannot fully achieve. The discussion also acknowledges blockchain&#x02019;s limitations, such as the challenge of GDPR's "right to be forgotten," and suggests hybrid solutions like off-chain storage or cryptographic techniques to mitigate these issues.</p><p>Moreover, as advised, the lessons learned are now explicitly mentioned below:-</p><p>&#x0201c;Lessons Learned</p><p>&#x02022; Blockchain enhances compliance &#x02013; The study shows that blockchain improves adherence to HIPAA by ensuring security and patient authorization through encryption and smart contracts.</p><p>&#x02022; Policy adaptation is necessary &#x02013; The analysis highlights the need for ongoing updates to regulatory frameworks to align with evolving technologies like blockchain.</p><p>&#x02022; Sector-specific frameworks benefit the most &#x02013; While ISO and GDPR provide general governance principles, HIPAA&#x02019;s sectoral focus makes it better suited for blockchain integration</p><p>&#x02022; Hybrid solutions bridge regulatory gaps &#x02013; The research suggests that technical solutions like off-chain storage help reconcile blockchain&#x02019;s immutability with GDPR&#x02019;s data deletion requirement&#x0201d;</p><p>(Discussion)</p><p>The manuscript lacks a dedicated limitations section, which is essential for transparency and scientific rigor</p><p>Thank you very much for mentioning this point. As recommended, a detailed limitation section has been added to the manuscript as follows:</p><p>&#x0201c;Sample Size &#x00026; Geographic Bias</p><p>The study had a small sample size, mainly healthcare professionals and IT experts from specific regions, limiting the generalizability of findings. Geographic bias may affect the applicability of results to different regulatory environments. Future research should include broader, more diverse samples for global insights.</p><p>Response Bias in Survey Tool</p><p>Self-reported survey data may have been influenced by social desirability or limited familiarity with regulatory frameworks, leading to biased perceptions. This could impact the validity of findings on data governance effectiveness. Future studies should incorporate triangulation methods, such as interviews and observations, to enhance accuracy.</p><p>Limited Scope of Data Governance Standards</p><p>The study focused only on ISO, GDPR, and HIPAA, overlooking other relevant or emerging frameworks. It did not consider technologies like blockchain and AI, which impact healthcare data governance. Future research should explore a wider range of standards for a more comprehensive perspective.</p><p>Need for Larger, Methodologically Diverse Studies</p><p>A larger sample and diverse research methods are needed to strengthen evidence and practical relevance. Incorporating qualitative and mixed-method approaches would provide deeper insights. Future studies should aim for a more holistic understanding of healthcare data governance frameworks&#x0201d;.</p><p>(Limitations)</p><p>Lastly, several grammatical errors are present throughout the manuscript and need to be addressed.</p><p>Thank you for bringing our attention to the grammatical errors. These have been carefully removed throughout the manuscript. Also, we engaged a copyeditor who thoroughly reviewed the manuscript and helped in addressing the comments.</p><p>(Throughout the Manuscript)</p><p>Reviewer 2</p><p>Comment (Originally taken from the feedback letter) Response - All changes are underlined in the revised manuscript.</p><p>The manuscript is well-structured and provides a clear overview of the research problem, methodology and findings. However, in the introduction section, more concise details about the research gap and objectives are required.</p><p>Thank you for bringing this point to our attention. We have now made some major amendments in the introduction section by adding concise details about the research gap and objectives. For example, the following has now been added.</p><p>Research Gap:</p><p>&#x0201c;Despite the growing interest in blockchain for healthcare data management, there remains a significant gap in understanding how blockchain can be effectively integrated with existing data governance frameworks such as ISO standards, GDPR, and HIPAA. These frameworks, while comprehensive, may struggle to accommodate the decentralized nature of blockchain and might not fully address emerging security and privacy challenges in healthcare data governance. Limited research exists on whether these regulatory standards are adequate to safeguard healthcare data within a blockchain-driven ecosystem&#x0201d;</p><p>Research Objective:</p><p>The primary objective of this research is to evaluate the effectiveness of current data governance models&#x02014;ISO standards, GDPR, and HIPAA&#x02014;in ensuring the privacy and security of healthcare data when implemented alongside blockchain technology.</p><p>Specifically, the study aims to answer:</p><p>&#x0201c;Are current data governance models (i.e., ISO standards, GDPR, and HIPAA) adequate in providing security and privacy for healthcare data in a blockchain environment?&#x0201d;</p><p>(Introduction)</p><p>The study addresses an important aspect i.e. blockchain technology in healthcare. However, manuscript could better emphasize its unique contributions to the existing literature. On one hand comparison of GDPR, HIPAA and ISO is valuable, the integration of Blockchain technology as a potential solution could be valuable if there is more focus on findings and discussion</p><p>Thank you very much for bringing our attention to this point. A one-hand comparison of GDPR, HIPAA, and ISO is valuable because it highlights their similarities and differences in regulating healthcare data privacy, security, and governance. Each framework has a distinct focus:</p><p>GDPR (General Data Protection Regulation): Enforces strict data privacy and consent mechanisms across the EU, emphasizing patient rights, data minimization, and cross-border data sharing regulations.</p><p>HIPAA (Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act): Primarily focuses on protecting patient health information (PHI) within the U.S., ensuring security and confidentiality through compliance requirements for covered entities.</p><p>ISO Standards (e.g., ISO/IEC 27001): Provide internationally recognized guidelines for information security management, offering a structured framework adaptable to various industries, including healthcare.</p><p>Our study makes a unique contribution by comparing these frameworks and suggesting the strong domain of each of the frameworks. Moreover, the solution to the shortcomings of the frameworks in addressing the complexities of modern healthcare data governance, particularly in decentralized systems, IoT-driven health data, and emerging AI applications, have been provided.</p><p>Furthermore, as advised, the integration of the frameworks as the potential solution is now discussed in the following words:</p><p>&#x0201c;Blockchain Integration as a Solution</p><p>The potential of blockchain in healthcare governance strongely focuses on findings and discussions around its application. Blockchain offers:</p><p>Decentralization &#x00026; Transparency: It enables secure, immutable, and tamper-proof data records, reducing reliance on central authorities.</p><p>Smart Contracts for Compliance: Automates compliance by ensuring healthcare data is only accessed under predefined conditions.</p><p>Improved Data Access &#x00026; Security: Provides controlled access through cryptographic mechanisms, aligning with GDPR and HIPAA requirements.</p><p>Cross-border Data Sharing: Facilitates regulatory-compliant and secure international data transfers, addressing the gaps in existing governance models&#x0201d;.</p><p>(Literature Review)</p><p>Although the manuscript provides a good overview of using blockchain technology in healthcare, however, it is worth mentioning its integration into existing data governance frameworks. Perhaps deeper technical discussion with examples and case studies will be beneficial.</p><p>Thank y</p><supplementary-material id="pone.0324285.s003" position="float" content-type="local-data"><label>Attachment</label><caption><p>Submitted filename: <named-content content-type="submitted-filename">Response to Reviewers.docx</named-content></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0324285.s003.docx"/></supplementary-material></body></sub-article><sub-article article-type="aggregated-review-documents" id="pone.0324285.r004" specific-use="decision-letter"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0324285.r004</article-id><title-group><article-title>Decision Letter 1</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Capece</surname><given-names>Guendalina</given-names></name><role>Academic Editor</role></contrib></contrib-group><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2025 Guendalina Capece</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Guendalina Capece</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link> , which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><related-article ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1371/journal.pone.0324285" id="rel-obj004" related-article-type="reviewed-article"/><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name><meta-value>1</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></front-stub><body><p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">19 Mar 2025</named-content>
</p><p>PONE-D-24-54554R1Evaluating the effectiveness of data governance frameworks in ensuring security and privacy of healthcare data: A quantitative analysis of ISO standards, GDPR, and HIPAA in blockchain technologyPLOS ONE</p><p>Dear Dr. Ahmed,</p><p>Thank you for submitting your manuscript to PLOS ONE. After careful consideration, we feel that it has merit but does not fully meet PLOS ONE&#x02019;s publication criteria as it currently stands. Therefore, we invite you to submit a revised version of the manuscript that addresses the points raised during the review process.</p><p>Please submit your revised manuscript by May 03 2025 11:59PM. If you will need more time than this to complete your revisions, please reply to this message or contact the journal office at&#x000a0;<email>plosone@plos.org</email> . When you're ready to submit your revision, log on to <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/</ext-link> and select the 'Submissions Needing Revision' folder to locate your manuscript file.</p><p>Please include the following items when submitting your revised manuscript:</p><p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>A rebuttal letter that responds to each point raised by the academic editor and reviewer(s). You should upload this letter as a separate file labeled 'Response to Reviewers'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>A marked-up copy of your manuscript that highlights changes made to the original version. You should upload this as a separate file labeled 'Revised Manuscript with Track Changes'.</p></list-item><list-item><p>An unmarked version of your revised paper without tracked changes. You should upload this as a separate file labeled 'Manuscript'.</p></list-item></list>
</p><p>If you would like to make changes to your financial disclosure, please include your updated statement in your cover letter. Guidelines for resubmitting your figure files are available below the reviewer comments at the end of this letter.</p><p>If applicable, we recommend that you deposit your laboratory protocols in protocols.io to enhance the reproducibility of your results. Protocols.io assigns your protocol its own identifier (DOI) so that it can be cited independently in the future. For instructions see: <ext-link xlink:href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols" ext-link-type="uri">https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/submission-guidelines#loc-laboratory-protocols</ext-link> . Additionally, PLOS ONE offers an option for publishing peer-reviewed Lab Protocol articles, which describe protocols hosted on protocols.io. Read more information on sharing protocols at <ext-link xlink:href="https://plos.org/protocols?utm_medium=editorial-email&#x00026;utm_source=authorletters&#x00026;utm_campaign=protocols" ext-link-type="uri">https://plos.org/protocols?utm_medium=editorial-email&#x00026;utm_source=authorletters&#x00026;utm_campaign=protocols</ext-link> .</p><p>We look forward to receiving your revised manuscript.</p><p>Kind regards,</p><p>Guendalina Capece</p><p>Academic Editor</p><p>PLOS ONE</p><p>[Note: HTML markup is below. Please do not edit.]</p><p>Reviewers' comments:</p><p>Reviewer's Responses to Questions</p><p>
<bold>Comments to the Author</bold>
</p><p>1. If the authors have adequately addressed your comments raised in a previous round of review and you feel that this manuscript is now acceptable for publication, you may indicate that here to bypass the &#x0201c;Comments to the Author&#x0201d; section, enter your conflict of interest statement in the &#x0201c;Confidential to Editor&#x0201d; section, and submit your "Accept" recommendation.</p><p>Reviewer #3:&#x000a0;All comments have been addressed</p><p>Reviewer #4:&#x000a0;All comments have been addressed</p><p>**********</p><p>2. Is the manuscript technically sound, and do the data support the conclusions?</p><p>The manuscript must describe a technically sound piece of scientific research with data that supports the conclusions. Experiments must have been conducted rigorously, with appropriate controls, replication, and sample sizes. The conclusions must be drawn appropriately based on the data presented. </p><p>Reviewer #3:&#x000a0;Partly</p><p>Reviewer #4:&#x000a0;Yes</p><p>**********</p><p>3. Has the statistical analysis been performed appropriately and rigorously? </p><p>Reviewer #3:&#x000a0;I Don't Know</p><p>Reviewer #4:&#x000a0;Yes</p><p>**********</p><p>4. Have the authors made all data underlying the findings in their manuscript fully available?</p><p>The <ext-link xlink:href="http://www.plosone.org/static/policies.action#sharing" ext-link-type="uri">PLOS Data policy</ext-link> requires authors to make all data underlying the findings described in their manuscript fully available without restriction, with rare exception (please refer to the Data Availability Statement in the manuscript PDF file). The data should be provided as part of the manuscript or its supporting information, or deposited to a public repository. For example, in addition to summary statistics, the data points behind means, medians and variance measures should be available. If there are restrictions on publicly sharing data&#x02014;e.g. participant privacy or use of data from a third party&#x02014;those must be specified.</p><p>Reviewer #3:&#x000a0;Yes</p><p>Reviewer #4:&#x000a0;Yes</p><p>**********</p><p>5. Is the manuscript presented in an intelligible fashion and written in standard English?</p><p>PLOS ONE does not copyedit accepted manuscripts, so the language in submitted articles must be clear, correct, and unambiguous. Any typographical or grammatical errors should be corrected at revision, so please note any specific errors here.</p><p>Reviewer #3:&#x000a0;Yes</p><p>Reviewer #4:&#x000a0;Yes</p><p>**********</p><p>6. Review Comments to the Author</p><p>Please use the space provided to explain your answers to the questions above. You may also include additional comments for the author, including concerns about dual publication, research ethics, or publication ethics. (Please upload your review as an attachment if it exceeds 20,000 characters)</p><p>Reviewer #3:&#x000a0;The manuscript presents a well-structured and relevant study on the effectiveness of data governance frameworks (ISO, GDPR, HIPAA) in ensuring healthcare data security and privacy within blockchain technology. The research is methodologically sound, supported by empirical data, and addresses a significant gap in the field.</p><p>The revisions effectively enhance the clarity, coherence, and depth of analysis. The literature review is now more structured, the methodology is well-justified, and the results are strengthened with statistical validation. The discussion provides valuable insights, though further emphasis on policy implications and practical applications would enhance impact.</p><p>Minor language refinements are recommended for clarity and fluency, along with slight improvements in figure readability. A final proofreading will ensure linguistic accuracy.</p><p>The manuscript is well-prepared for further review, with minor refinements suggested for enhanced readability and impact.</p><p>Reviewer #4:&#x000a0;The results have important value, it is my opinion that the article should be published after the minor revision.</p><p>Sufficient information about the previous study findings is presented for readers to follow the present study rationale and procedures.</p><p>The authors make a systematic contribution to the research literature in this area of investigation.</p><p>However, future enhancement is to be described in the conclusion section.</p><p>The title is adequate for the content discussed in the manuscript, explanatory, brief, and strong.</p><p>The article is novel and original which covers the scope of the journal.</p><p>The technology applied and the performance review of the proposed design is demonstrated in an efficient way</p><p>If required, the authors are informed to justify with real-time experimental analysis in the result and discussion section.</p><p>This article contains material which significant information on the current area of research.</p><p>The overall structure of the article is well-organized and in well-balanced manner.</p><p>The article was written with the minimum length necessary for all relevant information.</p><p>**********</p><p>7. PLOS authors have the option to publish the peer review history of their article (<ext-link xlink:href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/editorial-and-peer-review-process#loc-peer-review-history" ext-link-type="uri">what does this mean?</ext-link> ). If published, this will include your full peer review and any attached files.</p><p>If you choose &#x0201c;no&#x0201d;, your identity will remain anonymous but your review may still be made public.</p><p><bold>Do you want your identity to be public for this peer review?</bold> For information about this choice, including consent withdrawal, please see our <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.plos.org/privacy-policy" ext-link-type="uri">Privacy Policy</ext-link> .</p><p>Reviewer #3:&#x000a0;No</p><p>Reviewer #4:&#x000a0;<bold>Yes:&#x000a0;</bold> Dr B Santhosh Kumar</p><p>**********</p><p>[NOTE: If reviewer comments were submitted as an attachment file, they will be attached to this email and accessible via the submission site. Please log into your account, locate the manuscript record, and check for the action link "View Attachments". If this link does not appear, there are no attachment files.]</p><p>While revising your submission, please upload your figure files to the Preflight Analysis and Conversion Engine (PACE) digital diagnostic tool,&#x000a0;<ext-link xlink:href="https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/" ext-link-type="uri">https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/</ext-link> . PACE helps ensure that figures meet PLOS requirements. To use PACE, you must first register as a user. Registration is free. Then, login and navigate to the UPLOAD tab, where you will find detailed instructions on how to use the tool. If you encounter any issues or have any questions when using PACE, please email PLOS at&#x000a0;<email>figures@plos.org</email> . Please note that Supporting Information files do not need this step.</p></body></sub-article><sub-article article-type="author-comment" id="pone.0324285.r005"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0324285.r005</article-id><title-group><article-title>Author response to Decision Letter 2</article-title></title-group><related-article ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1371/journal.pone.0324285" id="rel-obj005" related-article-type="editor-report"/><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name><meta-value>2</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></front-stub><body><p>
<named-content content-type="author-response-date">8 Apr 2025</named-content>
</p><p>Editor Comments</p><p>Please submit your revised manuscript by May 03 2025 11:59PM. If you will need more time than this to complete your revisions, please reply to this message or contact the journal office at plosone@plos.org. When you're ready to submit your revision, log on to <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/</ext-link> and select the 'Submissions Needing Revision' folder to locate your manuscript file.</p><p>Please include the following items when submitting your revised manuscript:</p><p>&#x02022; A rebuttal letter that responds to each point raised by the academic editor and reviewer(s). You should upload this letter as a separate file labeled 'Response to Reviewers'.</p><p>&#x02022; A marked-up copy of your manuscript that highlights changes made to the original version. You should upload this as a separate file labeled 'Revised Manuscript with Track Changes'.</p><p>&#x02022; An unmarked version of your revised paper without tracked changes. You should upload this as a separate file labeled 'Manuscript'.</p><p>Response Thanks for the guidelines. All the above-mentioned items have been included in the submission of the revised manuscript.</p><p>Reviewer 3</p><p>Comment (Originally taken from the feedback letter) Response - All changes are tracked in the revised manuscript.</p><p>1. If the authors have adequately addressed your comments raised in a previous round of review and you feel that this manuscript is now acceptable for publication, you may indicate that here to bypass the &#x0201c;Comments to the Author&#x0201d; section, enter your conflict of interest statement in the &#x0201c;Confidential to Editor&#x0201d; section, and submit your "Accept" recommendation.</p><p>Reviewer #3: All comments have been addressed</p><p>Thank you for the acknowledgement.</p><p>2. Is the manuscript technically sound, and do the data support the conclusions?</p><p>The manuscript must describe a technically sound piece of scientific research with data that supports the conclusions. Experiments must have been conducted rigorously, with appropriate controls, replication, and sample sizes. The conclusions must be drawn appropriately based on the data presented.</p><p>Reviewer #3: Partly</p><p>Thank you for bringing this point to our attention. We consider our study to be technically sound and methodologically solid in various aspects. Firstly, the study was designed with a systematic and stringent approach that has a well-justified sample size of 250 individuals obtained from varying regions through stratified random sampling, so that the sample would have a broad representation of views from healthcare professionals, IT professionals, blockchain developers, and administrators. Second, the data collection tool&#x02014;a structured, strictly closed-ended questionnaire&#x02014;was carefully crafted and pre-tested to ensure clarity and relevance, thus reducing measurement error, and making it worth using for replicability of this study in a different sector. Finally, the conclusions drawn are now explicitly stated based on the data collected, thereby clearly linked to our findings. Some of the text that has now been added in the conclusion is as follows:</p><p>&#x0201c;In conclusion, the research discloses important differences in data governance frameworks' perceived effectiveness in the healthcare sector, with HIPAA standing out as having better performance in the security and privacy of data than ISO standards and GDPR. The research indicates that there is a need for industry-specific frameworks that can better solve the specific problems that come with handling sensitive health data&#x0201d;</p><p>(Sections: Methodology and Conclusion)</p><p>3. Has the statistical analysis been performed appropriately and rigorously?</p><p>Reviewer #3: I Don't Know</p><p>Thank you for bringing this point to our attention. Let us explain the statistical techniques in more detail. The descriptive statistics and ANOVA are suitable and powerful, allowing for a clear and objective interpretation of the data. Moreover, our study is based on firm ethical standards, with written guidelines in place for informed consent and data protection, thereby validating the appropriateness of the study. These factors together guarantee that the research methodology is rigorous and equally able to sustain the conclusions made.</p><p>(Section: Methodology)</p><p>4. Have the authors made all data underlying the findings in their manuscript fully available?</p><p>The PLOS Data policy requires authors to make all data underlying the findings described in their manuscript fully available without restriction, with rare exception (please refer to the Data Availability Statement in the manuscript PDF file). The data should be provided as part of the manuscript or its supporting information, or deposited to a public repository. For example, in addition to summary statistics, the data points behind means, medians and variance measures should be available. If there are restrictions on publicly sharing data&#x02014;e.g. participant privacy or use of data from a third party&#x02014;those must be specified.</p><p>Reviewer #3: Yes</p><p>Thank you for the acknowledgement.</p><p>5.Is the manuscript presented in an intelligible fashion and written in standard English?</p><p>PLOS ONE does not copyedit accepted manuscripts, so the language in submitted articles must be clear, correct, and unambiguous. Any typographical or grammatical errors should be corrected at revision, so please note any specific errors here.</p><p>Reviewer #3: Yes</p><p>Thank you for the acknowledgement.</p><p>The manuscript presents a well-structured and relevant study on the effectiveness of data governance frameworks (ISO, GDPR, HIPAA) in ensuring healthcare data security and privacy within blockchain technology. The research is methodologically sound, supported by empirical data, and addresses a significant gap in the field.</p><p>Thank you for your appreciation and acknowledgement.</p><p>The revisions effectively enhance the clarity, coherence, and depth of analysis. The literature review is now more structured, the methodology is well-justified, and the results are strengthened with statistical validation. The discussion provides valuable insights, though further emphasis on policy implications and practical applications would enhance impact.</p><p>Thank you for your appreciation and acknowledgement.</p><p>Minor language refinements are recommended for clarity and fluency, along with slight improvements in figure readability.</p><p>Thank you for bringing this point to our attention. We have carried out language refinement throughout the document, along with an improvement in figure readability. Moreover, a copyeditor was engaged to improve the clarity and fluency of arguments.</p><p>(Section: Throughout the manuscript)</p><p>A final proofreading will ensure linguistic accuracy.</p><p>Thank you. As advised, proofreading has been done by the authors, followed by a professional copyeditor, improving the overall linguistic accuracy of the manuscript.</p><p>(Section: Throughout the manuscript)</p><p>The manuscript is well-prepared for further review, with minor refinements suggested for enhanced readability and impact.</p><p>Thanks for the appreciation and suggestion. As per all your advice, we have now made refinements throughout the document for enhanced readability and impact.</p><p>(Section: Throughout the manuscript)</p><p>Reviewer 4</p><p>Comment (Originally taken from the feedback letter) Response - All changes are tracked in the revised manuscript.</p><p>1. If the authors have adequately addressed your comments raised in a previous round of review and you feel that this manuscript is now acceptable for publication, you may indicate that here to bypass the &#x0201c;Comments to the Author&#x0201d; section, enter your conflict of interest statement in the &#x0201c;Confidential to Editor&#x0201d; section, and submit your "Accept" recommendation.</p><p>Reviewer #4: All comments have been addressed</p><p>Thank you for the acknowledgement.</p><p>2. Is the manuscript technically sound, and do the data support the conclusions?</p><p>The manuscript must describe a technically sound piece of scientific research with data that supports the conclusions. Experiments must have been conducted rigorously, with appropriate controls, replication, and sample sizes. The conclusions must be drawn appropriately based on the data presented.</p><p>Reviewer #4: Yes</p><p>Thank you for the acknowledgement.</p><p>3. Has the statistical analysis been performed appropriately and rigorously?</p><p>Reviewer #4: Yes</p><p>Thank you for the acknowledgement.</p><p>4. Have the authors made all data underlying the findings in their manuscript fully available?</p><p>The PLOS Data policy requires authors to make all data underlying the findings described in their manuscript fully available without restriction, with rare exception (please refer to the Data Availability Statement in the manuscript PDF file). The data should be provided as part of the manuscript or its supporting information, or deposited to a public repository. For example, in addition to summary statistics, the data points behind means, medians and variance measures should be available. If there are restrictions on publicly sharing data&#x02014;e.g. participant privacy or use of data from a third party&#x02014;those must be specified.</p><p>Reviewer #4: Yes</p><p>Thank you for the acknowledgement.</p><p>5.Is the manuscript presented in an intelligible fashion and written in standard English?</p><p>PLOS ONE does not copyedit accepted manuscripts, so the language in submitted articles must be clear, correct, and unambiguous. Any typographical or grammatical errors should be corrected at revision, so please note any specific errors here.</p><p>Reviewer #4: Yes</p><p>Thank you for the acknowledgement.</p><p>The results have important value, it is my opinion that the article should be published after the minor revision.</p><p>Thank you for the acknowledgement and for bringing our attention to the minor revisions. As per your advice, we have revised the manuscript.</p><p>Sufficient information about the previous study findings is presented for readers to follow the present study rationale and procedures. Thanks for your appreciation and acknowledgement</p><p>The authors make a systematic contribution to the research literature in this area of investigation. However, future enhancements is to be described in the conclusion section.</p><p>Thank you for bringing this point to our attention. We have updated the conclusion section. For example, some of the text that has now been added in the conclusion is as follows:</p><p>&#x0201c;In conclusion, the research discloses important differences in data governance frameworks' perceived effectiveness in the healthcare sector, with HIPAA standing out as having better performance in the security and privacy of data than ISO standards and GDPR. The research indicates that there is a need for industry-specific frameworks that can better solve the specific problems that come with handling sensitive health data&#x0201d;</p><p>(Section: Conclusion)</p><p>The title is adequate for the content discussed in the manuscript, explanatory, brief, and strong.</p><p>Thank you for your appreciation and acknowledgement.</p><p>The article is novel and original which covers the scope of the journal.</p><p>Thank you for your appreciation and acknowledgement.</p><p>The technology applied and the performance review of the proposed design is demonstrated in an efficient way</p><p>Thank you for your appreciation and acknowledgement.</p><p>If required, the authors are informed to justify with real-time experimental analysis in the result and discussion section.</p><p>Thank you for bringing this point to our attention. For this particular study, the analysis was done at the end of data collection, rather than the real-time experimental analysis, so this was not required. However, despite this, the results and discussion section were enhanced based on the statistical analysis.</p><p>This article contains material which significant information on the current area of research.</p><p>Thank you for your appreciation and acknowledgement.</p><p>The overall structure of the article is well-organized and in well-balanced manner.</p><p>Thank you for your appreciation and acknowledgement.</p><p>The article was written with the minimum length necessary for all relevant information.</p><p>Thank you for your appreciation and acknowledgement.</p></body></sub-article><sub-article article-type="editor-report" id="pone.0324285.r006" specific-use="decision-letter"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0324285.r006</article-id><title-group><article-title>Decision Letter 2</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Capece</surname><given-names>Guendalina</given-names></name><role>Academic Editor</role></contrib></contrib-group><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2025 Guendalina Capece</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Guendalina Capece</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link> , which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><related-article ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1371/journal.pone.0324285" id="rel-obj006" related-article-type="reviewed-article"/><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name><meta-value>2</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></front-stub><body><p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">23 Apr 2025</named-content>
</p><p>Evaluating the effectiveness of data governance frameworks in ensuring security and privacy of healthcare data: A quantitative analysis of ISO standards, GDPR, and HIPAA in blockchain technology</p><p>PONE-D-24-54554R2</p><p>Dear Dr. Ahmed,</p><p>We&#x02019;re pleased to inform you that your manuscript has been judged scientifically suitable for publication and will be formally accepted for publication once it meets all outstanding technical requirements.</p><p>Within one week, you&#x02019;ll receive an e-mail detailing the required amendments. When these have been addressed, you&#x02019;ll receive a formal acceptance letter and your manuscript will be scheduled for publication.</p><p>An invoice will be generated when your article is formally accepted. Please note, if your institution has a publishing partnership with PLOS and your article meets the relevant criteria, all or part of your publication costs will be covered. Please make sure your user information is up-to-date by logging into Editorial Manager at <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.editorialmanager.com/pone/" ext-link-type="uri">Editorial Manager&#x000ae;</ext-link> &#x000a0;and clicking the &#x02018;Update My Information' link at the top of the page. If you have any questions relating to publication charges, please contact our Author Billing department directly at authorbilling@plos.org.</p><p>If your institution or institutions have a press office, please notify them about your upcoming paper to help maximize its impact. If they&#x02019;ll be preparing press materials, please inform our press team as soon as possible -- no later than 48 hours after receiving the formal acceptance. Your manuscript will remain under strict press embargo until 2 pm Eastern Time on the date of publication. For more information, please contact onepress@plos.org.</p><p>Kind regards,</p><p>Guendalina Capece</p><p>Academic Editor</p><p>PLOS ONE</p><p>Additional Editor Comments (optional):</p><p>Reviewers' comments:</p></body></sub-article><sub-article article-type="editor-report" id="pone.0324285.r007" specific-use="acceptance-letter"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0324285.r007</article-id><title-group><article-title>Acceptance letter</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Capece</surname><given-names>Guendalina</given-names></name><role>Academic Editor</role></contrib></contrib-group><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2025 Guendalina Capece</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Guendalina Capece</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link> , which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><related-article ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1371/journal.pone.0324285" id="rel-obj007" related-article-type="reviewed-article"/></front-stub><body><p>PONE-D-24-54554R2</p><p>PLOS ONE</p><p>Dear Dr. Ahmed,</p><p>I'm pleased to inform you that your manuscript has been deemed suitable for publication in PLOS ONE. Congratulations! Your manuscript is now being handed over to our production team.</p><p>At this stage, our production department will prepare your paper for publication. This includes ensuring the following:</p><p>* All references, tables, and figures are properly cited</p><p>* All relevant supporting information is included in the manuscript submission,</p><p>* There are no issues that prevent the paper from being properly typeset</p><p>You will receive further&#x000a0;instructions from the production team, including instructions on how to review your proof when it&#x000a0;is ready. Please keep in mind that we are working through a large volume of accepted articles, so please give us a few days to review your paper and let you know the next and final steps.</p><p>Lastly, if your institution or institutions have a press office, please let them know about your upcoming paper now to help maximize its impact. If they'll be preparing press materials, please inform our press team within the next 48 hours. Your manuscript will remain under strict press embargo until 2 pm Eastern Time on the date of publication. For more information, please contact onepress@plos.org.</p><p>If we can help with anything else, please email us at customercare@plos.org.</p><p>Thank you for submitting your work to PLOS ONE and supporting open access.</p><p>Kind regards,</p><p>PLOS ONE Editorial Office Staff</p><p>on behalf of</p><p>Professor Guendalina Capece</p><p>Academic Editor</p><p>PLOS ONE</p></body></sub-article></article>