<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">JAMA Netw Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">JAMA Netw Open</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>JAMA Network Open</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2574-3805</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Medical Association</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40392553</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12093188</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2025.11488</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">zoi250390</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="category" specific-use="electronic"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Investigation</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="online-only"><subject>Online Only</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="subject-area"><subject>Psychiatry</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Exposure Therapy in Mixed Reality for Obsessive-Compulsive Disorder</article-title><subtitle>A Randomized Clinical Trial</subtitle><alt-title alt-title-type="headline">Exposure Therapy in Mixed Reality for Obsessive-Compulsive Disorder</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Exposure Therapy in Mixed Reality for Obsessive-Compulsive Disorder</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Miegel</surname><given-names>Franziska</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="zoi250390aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jelinek</surname><given-names>Lena</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="zoi250390aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lohse</surname><given-names>Luzie</given-names></name><degrees>MSc</degrees><xref rid="zoi250390aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Moritz</surname><given-names>Steffen</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="zoi250390aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bl&#x000f6;mer</surname><given-names>Jannik</given-names></name><degrees>MSc</degrees><xref rid="zoi250390aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Juckoff</surname><given-names>Kim</given-names></name><degrees>MSc</degrees><xref rid="zoi250390aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yassari</surname><given-names>Amir</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="zoi250390aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rolvien</surname><given-names>Lara</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="zoi250390aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="zoi250390aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Psychiatry and Psychotherapy, University Medical Center Hamburg-Eppendorf, Hamburg, Germany</aff><author-notes><title>Article Information</title><p><bold>Accepted for Publication:</bold> March 5, 2025.</p><p content-type="published-online"><bold>Published:</bold> May 20, 2025. doi:<uri content-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2025.11488</uri></p><p content-type="open-access-note"><bold>Open Access:</bold> This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link xlink:href="https://jamanetwork.com/pages/cc-by-license-permissions" ext-link-type="uri">CC-BY License</ext-link>. &#x000a9; 2025 Miegel F et al. <italic>JAMA Network Open</italic>.</p><corresp id="zoi250390cor1"><bold>Corresponding Author:</bold> Franziska Miegel, PD Dr, Department of Psychiatry and Psychotherapy, University Medical Center Hamburg-Eppendorf, Martinistrasse 52, 20246 Hamburg, Germany (<email xlink:href="f.miegel@uke.de">f.miegel@uke.de</email>).</corresp><p content-type="author-contributions"><bold>Author Contributions:</bold> Dr Miegel had full access to all of the data in the study and takes responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis.</p><p><italic>Concept and design:</italic> Miegel, Jelinek, Moritz, Bl&#x000f6;mer, Yassari, Rolvien.</p><p><italic>Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data:</italic> Miegel, Lohse, Juckoff, Yassari, Rolvien.</p><p><italic>Drafting of the manuscript:</italic> Miegel, Moritz, Bl&#x000f6;mer, Yassari.</p><p><italic>Critical review of the manuscript for important intellectual content:</italic> Miegel, Jelinek, Lohse, Bl&#x000f6;mer, Juckoff, Yassari, Rolvien.</p><p><italic>Statistical analysis:</italic> Miegel, Moritz.</p><p><italic>Obtained funding:</italic> Miegel, Bl&#x000f6;mer, Rolvien.</p><p><italic>Administrative, technical, or material support:</italic> Lohse, Bl&#x000f6;mer, Juckoff, Yassari.</p><p><italic>Supervision:</italic> Jelinek, Yassari, Rolvien.</p><p content-type="COI-statement"><bold>Conflict of Interest Disclosures:</bold> Dr Miegel reported receiving grant support from Christiane Herzog Stiftung and Werner Otto Stiftung outside the submitted work. Prof Jelinek reported receiving grant support from the Peter M&#x000f6;hrle foundation, the Werner Otto Foundation, the Hamburg Donors Parliament, grants from BMBF, German Research Foundation, and personal fees from publishers outside the submitted work. Dr Miegel and Dr Rolvien received funding from the Freie und Hansestadt Hamburg, Beh&#x000f6;rde f&#x000fc;r Arbeit, Gesundheit, Soziales, Familie und Integration. Dr Moritz has received research funding from the BMBF and has served on the advisory board of Boehringer Ingelheim. No other disclosures were reported.</p><p content-type="funding-statement"><bold>Funding/Support:</bold> This research was supported by the Freie und Hansestadt Hamburg and the Hamburgische Investitions und F&#x000f6;rderbank within the framework of the PROFI Tansfer Plus Program from EU funding (Europ&#x000e4;ischer Fond f&#x000fc;r Regionale Entwicklung) (Drs Miegel and Rolvien).</p><p><bold>Role of the Funder/Sponsor:</bold> The funders had no role in the design and conduct of the study; collection, management, analysis, and interpretation of the data; preparation, review, or approval of the manuscript; and decision to submit the manuscript for publication.</p><p content-type="data-sharing-statement"><bold>Data Sharing Statement:</bold> See <xref rid="note-ZOI250390-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 3</xref>.</p><p><bold>Additional Contributions:</bold> We thank Fabian J&#x000e4;ger, MSc, chief executive officer of PatientZero Games, for the excellent collaboration on this project and his outstanding technical development. PatientZero Games also received funding from the Freie und Hansestadt Hamburg and the Hamburgische Investitions und F&#x000f6;rderbank.</p><p><bold>Additional Information:</bold> ChatGPT (version GPT-4o; OpenAI) was used from July 15-19, 2024, to translate parts of the Introduction and parts of the Discussion from German to English. Dr Miegel takes responsibility for the integrity of the content generated.</p></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2025-05-20T10:00"><day>20</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>20</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><!--PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>.--><volume>8</volume><issue>5</issue><elocation-id>e2511488</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>8</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>5</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright 2025 Miegel F et al. <italic>JAMA Network Open</italic>.</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the CC-BY License.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf-version" xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2511488.pdf">jamanetwopen-e2511488.pdf</self-uri><self-uri content-type="silverchair" xlink:href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamanetworkopen/fullarticle/10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2025.11488"/><abstract abstract-type="key-points"><title>Key Points</title><sec id="ab-zoi250390-1"><title>Question</title><p>Can mixed reality exposure and response prevention therapy (MERP) effectively reduce symptoms in patients with contamination-related obsessive-compulsive disorder (OCD)?</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi250390-2"><title>Findings</title><p>In this single-center randomized clinical trial including 36 patients, MERP did not significantly reduce OCD symptom severity compared with an active control group, but qualitative feedback was valuable for revisions.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi250390-3"><title>Meaning</title><p>These findings provide insights into MERP&#x02019;s potential revisions and application in OCD.</p></sec></abstract><abstract><sec id="ab-zoi250390-4"><title>Importance</title><p>Exposure therapy in virtual reality (VR) is well established for anxiety disorders. While early studies show promise for VR-based exposure and response prevention (ERP) in obsessive-compulsive disorder (OCD), a key challenge of traditional VR is the weak sense of presence, deemed crucial for effectiveness.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi250390-5"><title>Objective</title><p>To evaluate the feasibility and efficacy of ERP in mixed reality (MERP).</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi250390-6"><title>Design, Setting, and Participants</title><p>This randomized clinical trial (RCT) included 2 outpatient treatment groups, MERP vs self-guided ERP (SERP) from March 15, 2022, to October 26, 2024. Participants were required to be 18 to 80 years of age and have contamination-related OCD (C-OCD). Exclusion criteria consisted of schizophrenia or bipolar disorder, severe substance use disorder, acute suicidality, and ongoing inpatient treatment. Patients&#x02019; symptom severity was assessed by the Yale-Brown Obsessive Compulsive Scale (Y-BOCS) before (baseline) and after the 6-week intervention period as well as 3 months after posttreatment (follow-up).</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi250390-7"><title>Intervention</title><p>Six sessions of MERP or SERP.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi250390-8"><title>Main Outcomes and Measures</title><p>Main outcome was the severity of OCD symptoms in the past 7 days on the Y-BOCS. Sense of presence and subjective appraisal were the secondary outcomes.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi250390-9"><title>Results</title><p>Thirty-six participants fulfilled inclusion criteria. Twenty-four participants (66.7%) were female; mean (SD) age was 35.42 (14.03) years. Both groups had severe OCD symptoms, with major depressive disorder as the most common comorbidity (23 [63.9%]). Twenty-nine participants (80.6%) completed the postintervention and follow-up assessments. At baseline, patients in the MERP group had a mean (SD) Y-BOCS score of 26.94 (5.83), while the SERP group had a mean (SD) score of 24.22 (4.12). The decline in patients&#x02019; OCD symptoms (Y-BOCS) was similar in the MERP (mean difference,&#x02009;3.15) and the SERP groups (mean difference,&#x02009;1.47) (&#x003b7;<sub>p</sub><sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.002; 95% CI, &#x02013;3.187 to 3.893). Significant improvements were observed within the MERP group from baseline to post treatment across several psychopathological variables, including OCD symptoms, with a medium to large effect (Cohen <italic>d</italic>, 0.584-0.931; 95% CI, 0.026-1.551). Sense of presence was moderate (mean [SD], &#x02264;3.24 [&#x02264;2.07]). Subjective appraisal was heterogeneous.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi250390-10"><title>Conclusions</title><p>This RCT on MERP in C-OCD provided important insights. While there were no significant between-group differences, changes in psychopathology within the MERP group suggest some level of effectiveness. However, the limited impact indicates that the full potential of MERP has not yet been realized, and future research should aim to improve immersion and overall effectiveness.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi250390-11"><title>Trial Registration</title><p>German Clinical Trial Registry: <ext-link xlink:href="https://drks.de/search/en/trial/DRKS00020969/entails" ext-link-type="uri">DRKS00020969</ext-link></p></sec></abstract><abstract abstract-type="teaser" specific-use="electronic"><p>This randomized clinical trial compares the efficacy of exposure and response prevention therapy in mixed reality with self-guided exposure and response prevention therapy among patients with contamination-related obsessive-compulsive disorder.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="H1-1-ZOI250390"><title>Introduction</title><p>Obsessive-compulsive disorder (OCD) is a disorder with a lifetime worldwide prevalence of 1% to 3%.<sup><xref rid="zoi250390r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> Treatment guidelines<sup><xref rid="zoi250390r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> recommend cognitive behavioral therapy (CBT) with exposure and response prevention (ERP) as the first-line treatment. In ERP, individuals face OCD-provoking stimuli but are prevented from enacting compulsions. This evidence-based therapeutic approach has exhibited high effectiveness (Hedges <italic>g</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.74)<sup><xref rid="zoi250390r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> in reducing symptom severity and improving overall functioning. Although CBT with ERP is the most effective treatment for OCD, it is not&#x02014;or not adequately&#x02014;used in clinical practice.<sup><xref rid="zoi250390r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> Only one-third of therapists apply exposure in vivo,<sup><xref rid="zoi250390r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> with just one-third of those adhering to protocols,<sup><xref rid="zoi250390r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> highlighting the disparity between recommendations and clinical practice. Senter et al<sup><xref rid="zoi250390r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> found that although CBT is recommended to 59% of patients with OCD, only 44% undergo treatment. Barriers to CBT with ERP can be patient related (eg, patient barriers [dropout rate 18.7%]<sup><xref rid="zoi250390r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup>), circumstance based (eg, during the COVID-19 pandemic ERP was used less often due to risk of infection<sup><xref rid="zoi250390r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup>), or therapist related (eg, time-consuming, fear of severe reactions<sup><xref rid="zoi250390r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup>). These challenges, compounded by the difficulty of simulating OCD-relevant situations in clinical settings, contribute to the treatment gap.<sup><xref rid="zoi250390r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup></p><p>Exposure therapy in virtual reality (VR) enables efficient exposure treatment within the therapist&#x02019;s workspace, eliminating travel time<sup><xref rid="zoi250390r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> and ensuring consistent experimental conditions, with extensive research showing comparable or slightly superior effects compared with traditional in vivo exposure for most anxiety disorders.<sup><xref rid="zoi250390r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="zoi250390r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="zoi250390r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> It also facilitates standardized therapist-led ERP within a controlled clinical setting, potentially increasing adherence to evidence-based treatment, and it enables the collection of objective data, such as eye-tracking measures, to enhance research, optimize ERP protocols, and improve treatment outcomes. Limited research has focused on applying ERP in VR (VERP) for OCD, and the heterogeneity of symptoms (eg, contamination, sexual obsessions) hinders the generalizability of outcomes. However, studies indicate that it is possible to induce emotional responses (heightened anxiety, increased compulsions) using VERP for patients with OCD.<sup><xref rid="zoi250390r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> VERP is feasible and shows potential treatment efficacy.<sup><xref rid="zoi250390r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> However, sense of presence is a major issue in studies on VERP. Also, creating new environments for unavailable OCD-provoking stimuli is technically complex.</p><p>While VR fully immerses patients into generated environments, augmented reality (AR) glasses superimpose virtual objects onto real surroundings, maintaining visibility and naturalistic movement and thus increasing how real the experience feels to the patient. Sense of presence is especially vital for inducing anxiety and disgust in ERP, and studies have confirmed that AR can induce these emotions in patients with contamination-related OCD (C-OCD).<sup><xref rid="zoi250390r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> Mixed reality (MR) goes beyond AR by allowing for real-time interaction and integration between the virtual and physical elements, creating a more immersive and interactive experience. This advancement may further enhance the sense of presence, which is crucial for exposure therapy. However, this must be explicitly examined in future studies using a comparative design among MR, AR, and VR.</p><p>While MR is already used in medicine, in psychological treatment it shows promise for ERP-based therapies by offering personalized sessions. Unlike VR, where whole virtual environments must be developed, MR only requires the development of new singular stimuli, which is of benefit for OCD due to its highly idiosyncratic nature. The increased sense of presence in MR fosters deeper engagement,<sup><xref rid="zoi250390r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> which especially aids patients with C-OCD, who often require touch to elicit disgust during exposure. A pilot study by some authors of the present study<sup><xref rid="zoi250390r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> was the first to date to explore the feasibility of MERP in a clinical sample. Patients with C-OCD were randomized to receive an add-on MERP intervention (6 sessions; intervention group) or continue their inpatient treatment (control group). Safety and acceptance were generally high, indicating the feasibility of MERP. However, participants criticized the realism of the objects and sounds. Based on this feedback, software modifications were made to improve the sense of presence and potentially the effectiveness of MERP.</p><p>The present randomized clinical trial (RCT) is the first, to our knowledge, that aims to investigate the efficacy of MERP by comparing it with an active control group (ie, self-guided ERP [SERP]) in outpatients with C-OCD. We hypothesized that the decline in OCD symptoms would be greater in the MERP group than the SERP group from baseline to posttreatment assessment and from baseline to follow-up assessment. We also assumed positive expectations regarding MERP, high acceptance rates, and high ratings of immersion.</p></sec><sec id="H1-2-ZOI250390"><title>Methods</title><sec id="H2-1-ZOI250390"><title>Design</title><p>This RCT was conducted from March 15, 2022, to October 26, 2024, and examined the efficacy of MERP vs an active control group using SERP. Assessments were conducted at baseline, 6 weeks post treatment, and 3-month follow-up by blinded raters. Participants were randomly assigned to MERP or SERP (1:1) using online software after the baseline assessment by the principal investigators (F.M. and L.R.). Instances of rater unblinding were recorded. All participants provided written informed consent and received &#x020ac;50 for completing all assessments. Standard care was allowed in both groups. The study received ethical approval by our local ethics committee of the Center for Psychosocial Medicine of the University Medical Center Hamburg-Eppendorf, Hamburg, Germany, was registered, and followed the tenets of the Declaration of Helsinki.<sup><xref rid="zoi250390r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> The study protocol has been published previously<sup><xref rid="zoi250390r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> and the version submitted to the local ethics committee is available in <xref rid="note-ZOI250390-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>. The study follows the Consolidated Standards of Reporting Trials (<ext-link xlink:href="http://www.equator-network.org/reporting-guidelines/consort/" ext-link-type="uri">CONSORT</ext-link>) reporting guideline.</p></sec><sec id="H2-2-ZOI250390"><title>Participants and Procedure</title><p>Participants were recruited from 2022 to 2023 from a patient database and through various advertisements (eg, newspapers, OCD support groups, social media). Eligibility was screened via telephone, with baseline and posttreatment assessments conducted in person and follow-up conducted via telephone; questionnaires were completed online. The Mini International Neuropsychiatric Interview (German version 7.0.2)<sup><xref rid="zoi250390r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> confirmed OCD diagnosis, identified comorbidities, and checked exclusion criteria. Exclusion criteria consisted of past or present diagnosis of schizophrenia or bipolar disorder, current severe substance use disorder, acute suicidality, severe neurological disorders related to OCD, and ongoing inpatient treatment. Participants aged 18 to 80 years with C-OCD, sufficient German language skills, and informed consent were eligible.</p></sec><sec id="H2-3-ZOI250390"><title>Intervention</title><sec id="H3-1-ZOI250390"><title>MERP</title><p>MERP sessions lasted 60 to 90 minutes and were conducted once a week for 6 weeks by a trained psychotherapist (among others by L.L.) with at least a master&#x02019;s degree in psychology. In the first session, participants&#x02019; medical history was assessed. The second session focused on psychoeducation and preparing for MERP, where participants rated the difficulty of virtual objects and selected those for increasing difficulty from sessions 3 to 6. MERP used MR glasses (Magic Leap One; Magic Leap Inc) with Unity software, version 2020.3.22f1 (Unity Technologies) to scan the real environment and accurately place virtual objects. The therapist used a controller to select and position objects in the room, and while in patient mode, the objects were locked in place for exposure, allowing the patient to interact with them using the controller (<xref rid="zoi250390f1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="zoi250390f1" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1. </label><caption><title>Snapshots of Various Virtual Objects That Were Integrated Into the Real Environment During Mixed Reality Exposure and Response Prevention</title><p>Unity software version 2020.3.22f1 (Unity Technologies) was used with permission to create the virtual objects within the mixed reality. The authors take responsibility for the content generated.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2511488-g001" position="float"/></fig><p>Using the tablet, the therapist could administer an artificial virus scan (green spots marking objects or places of high contamination) and activate coughing sounds in 3 levels of intensity. If the patient touched a previously contaminated object (the virus was represented by green spots), the virus particles spread onto the participant&#x02019;s hands (eFigure 1 in <xref rid="note-ZOI250390-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 2</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="H3-2-ZOI250390"><title>SERP</title><p>The active control group conducted SERP using a workbook that followed the same structure and content as the therapists&#x02019; MERP manual. This included psychoeducation on OCD and ERP, guidance on planning ERPs, and space for documenting experiences. Participants were instructed to complete 1 self-guided ERP exercise per week, for a total of 4 exercises, mirroring the frequency of ERP in the MERP condition. Unlike MERP, participants in SERP selected real objects for their ERPs and performed the exercises independently, without therapist involvement. They were encouraged to document their preparation and progress in the workbook.</p></sec></sec><sec id="H2-4-ZOI250390"><title>Measures</title><p>The Yale-Brown Obsessive Compulsive Scale (Y-BOCS)<sup><xref rid="zoi250390r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> was used to assess the severity of OCD symptoms in the past 7 days through a structured interview and served as the main outcome (scores range from 0-40, with higher scores indicating higher OCD symptom severity). The following questionnaires assessed secondary outcome variables: Obsessive Compulsive Inventory&#x02013;Revised,<sup><xref rid="zoi250390r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup> Beck Depression Inventory-II,<sup><xref rid="zoi250390r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> the 7-item Generalized Anxiety Disorder Scale (GAD-7),<sup><xref rid="zoi250390r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> the global item of the World Health Organization Quality of Life Instrument,<sup><xref rid="zoi250390r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> treatment expectations, Temple Presence Inventory (only 15 items and their factors were assessed based on ethical considerations and relevance to our research question),<sup><xref rid="zoi250390r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> and Subjective Appraisal Rating (based on the scale used by Miegel et al<sup><xref rid="zoi250390r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup>).</p></sec><sec id="H2-5-ZOI250390"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>All analyses were conducted with SPSS, version 29.0.1.0 (IBM Corporation). To evaluate the changes in symptoms between the MERP and SERP groups, we used analyses of covariance. Treatment type (MERP vs SERP) served as the between-participant factor, while the differences in outcome scores from baseline to post treatment and baseline to follow-up were the dependent variables. Baseline scores of the respective outcome variable were used as covariates. Paired <italic>t</italic> tests were planned<sup><xref rid="zoi250390r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> to assess within-group differences from baseline to posttreatment and follow-up assessments. Complete case (ie, participants who completed all assessments) and intention-to-treat (ITT using the multiple imputation method; participants who completed baseline assessment) analyses were conducted. A 2-sided significance threshold was applied. Sense of presence, expectations, and acceptability of MERP were analyzed descriptively. Exploratory moderation analyses using the Hayes PROCESS macro for SPSS and a process-based regression were conducted with all baseline variables as potential moderators for the change in OCD symptoms (difference score of the Y-BOCS total score from baseline to posttreatment assessment).</p><p>The power analysis was conducted with G*Power, version 3.1.9.6.<sup><xref rid="zoi250390r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> Based on the results of studies on VR and augmented reality exposure in anxiety disorders and the large effect sizes of 0.90 (Hedges <italic>g</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.90<sup><xref rid="zoi250390r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup>; Hedges <italic>g</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.33<sup><xref rid="zoi250390r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup>), we anticipated a larger effect size for MERP than for SERP due to an expected higher immersion resulting from the implementation in MR. Based on these assumptions, a sample size of 64 participants was needed to detect a large effect (<italic>f</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.4), with a power of .80 and an &#x003b1; level of .05.</p></sec></sec><sec id="H1-3-ZOI250390"><title>Results</title><sec id="H2-6-ZOI250390"><title>Sample</title><p>Thirty-six participants (18 in the MERP group and 18 in the SERP group) fulfilled inclusion criteria and were included in the final sample (<xref rid="zoi250390f2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>). Twenty-four participants (66.7%) were female, 11 (30.6%) were male, and 1 (2.8%) identified as gender diverse; mean (SD) age was 35.42 (14.03) years. As preregistered, we initially planned to recruit a larger sample of&#x02009;64 participants, but we had to stop after 1.5 years of recruitment due to limited resources. We were unable to reach the targeted sample size because of the restriction to the symptom domain of C-OCD, regional limitations (only patients living nearby could be included, as video-conference treatment was not possible), restrictions during the COVID-19 pandemic, and patients&#x02019; fears of coming to the hospital during the pandemic.</p><fig position="float" id="zoi250390f2" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2. </label><caption><title>Participant Flow Diagram</title><p>ITT indicates intention to treat; MERP, mixed reality exposure and response prevention; and SERP, self-guided exposure and response prevention.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2511488-g002" position="float"/></fig><p>The OCD symptoms of both groups could be classified as severe (<xref rid="zoi250390t1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). At baseline, patients in the MERP group had a mean (SD) Y-BOCS score of 26.94 (5.83), while the SERP group had a mean (SD) score of 24.22 (4.12). The most prevalent comorbid diagnosis was major depressive disorder (23 [63.9%]; present episode,&#x02009;3 [8.3%]; past episode,&#x02009;20 [55.6%]). On average, patients in the MERP group attended 5 sessions (mean [SD], 4.53&#x02009;[1.77]), with a range from 0 to 6 sessions. Only 1 of 17 participants attended 0 sessions (5.9%) and 6 attended all sessions (35.3%). Most participants were taking psychiatric medication for a mean (SD) duration of 156.50 (259.12) days.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="zoi250390t1"><label>Table 1. </label><caption><title>Sociodemographic and Psychopathological Characteristics at Baseline</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="38.66%" span="1"/><col width="25.07%" span="1"/><col width="18.62%" span="1"/><col width="17.65%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total sample (N&#x02009;=&#x02009;36)</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MERP (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;18)</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SERP (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;18)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sociodemographic</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Gender, No. (%) </td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Female</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (66.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (72.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (61.1)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Male</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (30.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (22.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (38.9)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Diverse</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (2.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (5.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Age, mean (SD), y</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.42 (14.03)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.28 (11.13)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.56 (16.14)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Formal education, mean (SD), y</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.83 (1.36)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.94 (1.29)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.72 (1.45)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medication used, No. (%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Antidepressant</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (52.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (55.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (50.0)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Antipsychotic</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 </td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 </td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Combination</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (13.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (16.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (11.1)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Other</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (2.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (5.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 </td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> None</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (30.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (22.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (38.9)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Psychopathology scores, mean (SD)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Y-BOCS total<xref rid="zoi250390t1n1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.58 (5.16)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.94 (5.83)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.22 (4.12)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Y-BOCS obsessions<xref rid="zoi250390t1n2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.36 (2.84)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.06 (3.30)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.67 (2.17)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Y-BOCS compulsions<xref rid="zoi250390t1n2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.22 (2.78)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.89 (2.93)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.56 (2.53)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> OCI-R<xref rid="zoi250390t1n3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.41 (12.81)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.67 (12.88)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.17 (12.22)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> BDI-II<xref rid="zoi250390t1n4" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.72 (12.21)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.67 (13.36)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.78 (10.49)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> GAD-7<xref rid="zoi250390t1n5" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>e</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.50 (5.84)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.28 (5.21)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.72 (6.47)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> WHOQOL-BREF global item<xref rid="zoi250390t1n6" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>f</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.86 (1.07)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.78 (0.94)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.94 (1.21)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Abbreviations: BDI-II, Beck Depression Inventory-II; GAD-7, Generalized Anxiety Disorder Scale-7; MERP, mixed reality exposure and response prevention; OCI-R, Obsessive Compulsive Inventory&#x02013;Revised; SERP, self-guided exposure and response prevention; WHOQOL-BREF, global item of the World Health Organization Quality of Life Instrument, Short Form; Y-BOCS, Yale-Brown Obsessive Compulsive Scale.</p><fn id="zoi250390t1n1"><label>
<sup>a</sup>
</label><p>Scores range from 0 to 40, with higher scores indicating greater symptom severity.</p></fn><fn id="zoi250390t1n2"><label>
<sup>b</sup>
</label><p>Scores range from 0 to 20, with higher scores indicating greater symptom severity.</p></fn><fn id="zoi250390t1n3"><label>
<sup>c</sup>
</label><p>Scores range from 0 to 72, with higher scores indicating greater symptom severity.</p></fn><fn id="zoi250390t1n4"><label>
<sup>d</sup>
</label><p>Scores range from 0 to 63, with higher scores indicating greater symptom severity.</p></fn><fn id="zoi250390t1n5"><label>
<sup>e</sup>
</label><p>Scores range from 0 to 21, with higher scores indicating greater symptom severity.</p></fn><fn id="zoi250390t1n6"><label>
<sup>f</sup>
</label><p>Scores range from 1 to 5, with higher scores indicating higher quality of life.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="H2-7-ZOI250390"><title>Completion Rate</title><p>Twenty-nine participants (80.6%) completed the postintervention and follow-up assessments. <xref rid="zoi250390f1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref> presents the flow diagram. The completion rate did not differ between groups (&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup><sub>1</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.177; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;.67). Those who did and did not complete the assessments did not differ on sociodemographic variables.</p></sec><sec id="H2-8-ZOI250390"><title>Complete Case and ITT Analyses</title><p>For all outcome variables, no significant differences between the MERP group and the SERP group from baseline to posttreatment assessment or from baseline to follow-up in the complete case analysis as well as the ITT analyses were found (<xref rid="zoi250390t2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Dependent <italic>t</italic> tests showed several significant changes in the MERP group (eg, Y-BOCS, <italic>t</italic><sub>14</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2.263; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;.02; Cohen <italic>d</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.584) (<xref rid="zoi250390t2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). One patient in the SERP and 1 in the MERP group responded (reduction in Y-BOCS total score of at least 35%) at posttreatment assessment and 1 patient in the MERP group responded at follow-up assessment. No patient achieved remission (Y-BOCS total score of &#x02264;12) at posttreatment assessment or follow-up.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="zoi250390t2"><label>Table 2. </label><caption><title>Between-Group Differences Across Time for the Primary and Secondary Outcomes</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="9.43%" span="1"/><col width="6.32%" span="1"/><col width="6.3%" span="1"/><col width="7.56%" span="1"/><col width="6.3%" span="1"/><col width="5.43%" span="1"/><col width="6.08%" span="1"/><col width="7.48%" span="1"/><col width="6.4%" span="1"/><col width="6.68%" span="1"/><col width="6.63%" span="1"/><col width="5.43%" span="1"/><col width="6.08%" span="1"/><col width="7.48%" span="1"/><col width="6.4%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1">Measure</th><th colspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Baseline score</th><th colspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Posttreatment score</th><th colspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Statistics for complete case sample</th><th rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> value for complete case sample</th><th rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> value for ITT sample</th><th colspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Follow-up score</th><th colspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Statistics for complete case sample</th><th rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> value for complete case sample</th><th rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> value for ITT sample</th></tr><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">MERP group (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;18)</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SERP group (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;18)</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MERP group (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;15)</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SERP group (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;16)</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>F</italic>
<sub>1,28</sub>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>&#x003b7;<sub>p</sub><sup>2</sup></italic>
</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">MERP group (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;14)</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SERP group (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;15)</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>F</italic>
<sub>1,28</sub>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>&#x003b7;<sub>p</sub><sup>2</sup></italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y-BOCS total<xref rid="zoi250390t2n1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.86 (6.04)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.40 (4.00)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.71 (5.62)<xref rid="zoi250390t2n2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="zoi250390t2n3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.93 (4.30)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.042</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02009;.84</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.96</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.00 (7.60)<xref rid="zoi250390t2n2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="zoi250390t2n4" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.60 (4.34)<xref rid="zoi250390t2n2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="zoi250390t2n5" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>e</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.034</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.85</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.92</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y-BOCS obsessions<xref rid="zoi250390t2n6" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>f</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.71 (3.38)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.40 (2.20)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.57 (3.18)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.47 (2.36)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.833</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.031</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.37</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.54</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.86 (3.86)<xref rid="zoi250390t2n7" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>g</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="zoi250390t2n8" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>h</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.53 (2.61)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.417</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.016</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.52</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.45</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y-BOCS compulsions<xref rid="zoi250390t2n6" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>f</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.14 (3.06)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.00 (2.27)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.14 (2.86)<xref rid="zoi250390t2n2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="zoi250390t2n9" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>i</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.47 (2.32)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.057</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.81</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.66</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.14 (3.84)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.07 (2.31)<xref rid="zoi250390t2n7" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>g</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="zoi250390t2n10" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>j</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.017</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.074</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.16</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.22</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OCI-R<xref rid="zoi250390t2n11" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>k</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.50 (14.10)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.00 (11.37)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.57 (13.70)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.47 (13.06)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.158</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.70</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.75</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.07 (14.68)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.40 (9.96)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.579</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.022</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.45</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.36</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BDI-II<xref rid="zoi250390t2n12" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>l</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.21 (13.90)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.93 (10.37)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.14 (16.44)<xref rid="zoi250390t2n2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="zoi250390t2n13" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>m</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.87 (11.50)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.010</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0004</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.92</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.67</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.21 (16.05)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.07 (10.98)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0004</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.98</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.96</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GAD-7<xref rid="zoi250390t2n14" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>n</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.21 (5.78)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.53 (6.69)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.64 (5.29)<xref rid="zoi250390t2n15" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>o</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="zoi250390t2n16" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>p</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.33 (5.83)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.748</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.028</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.40</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.42</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.00 (5.72)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.13 (5.17)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.513</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.119</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.07</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.08</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WHOQOL-BREF global item<xref rid="zoi250390t2n17" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>q</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.86 (0.86)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.07 (1.28)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.07 (1.07)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.87 (0.99)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.468</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.053</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.24</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.29</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.79 (1.05)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.07 (1.28)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.183</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.67</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.75</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Abbreviations: BDI-II, Beck Depression Inventory-II; GAD-7, Generalized Anxiety Disorder Scale-7; ITT, intention to treat; MERP, mixed reality exposure and response prevention; OCI-R, Obsessive Compulsive Inventory&#x02013;Revised; SERP, self-guided exposure and response prevention; WHOQOL-BREF, global item of the World Health Organization Quality of Life Instrument, Short Form; Y-BOCS, Yale-Brown Obsessive Compulsive Scale.</p><fn id="zoi250390t2n1"><label>
<sup>a</sup>
</label><p>Scores range from 0 to 40, with higher scores indicating greater symptom severity.</p></fn><fn id="zoi250390t2n2"><label>
<sup>b</sup>
</label><p>Significant effect at a medium effect size (Cohen <italic>d</italic>&#x0003e;0.05).</p></fn><fn id="zoi250390t2n3"><label>
<sup>c</sup>
</label><p>Cohen <italic>d</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.58.</p></fn><fn id="zoi250390t2n4"><label>
<sup>d</sup>
</label><p>Cohen <italic>d</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.66.</p></fn><fn id="zoi250390t2n5"><label>
<sup>e</sup>
</label><p>Cohen <italic>d</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.77.</p></fn><fn id="zoi250390t2n6"><label>
<sup>f</sup>
</label><p>Scores range from 0 to 20, with higher scores indicating greater symptom severity.</p></fn><fn id="zoi250390t2n7"><label>
<sup>g</sup>
</label><p>Significant effect at a large effect size (Cohen <italic>d</italic>&#x0003e;0.08).</p></fn><fn id="zoi250390t2n8"><label>
<sup>h</sup>
</label><p>Cohen <italic>d</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.93.</p></fn><fn id="zoi250390t2n9"><label>
<sup>i</sup>
</label><p>Cohen <italic>d</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.72.</p></fn><fn id="zoi250390t2n10"><label>
<sup>j</sup>
</label><p>Cohen <italic>d</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.94.</p></fn><fn id="zoi250390t2n11"><label>
<sup>k</sup>
</label><p>Scores range from 0 to 72, with higher scores indicating greater symptom severity.</p></fn><fn id="zoi250390t2n12"><label>
<sup>l</sup>
</label><p>Scores range from 0 to 63, with higher scores indicating greater symptom severity.</p></fn><fn id="zoi250390t2n13"><label>
<sup>m</sup>
</label><p>Cohen <italic>d</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.54.</p></fn><fn id="zoi250390t2n14"><label>
<sup>n</sup>
</label><p>Scores range from 0 to 21, with higher scores indicating greater symptom severity.</p></fn><fn id="zoi250390t2n15"><label>
<sup>o</sup>
</label><p>Significant effect at a small effect size (Cohen <italic>d</italic>&#x0003e;0.02).</p></fn><fn id="zoi250390t2n16"><label>
<sup>p</sup>
</label><p>Cohen <italic>d</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.49.</p></fn><fn id="zoi250390t2n17"><label>
<sup>q</sup>
</label><p>Scores range from 1 to 5, with higher scores indicating higher quality of life.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="H2-9-ZOI250390"><title>Sense of Presence</title><p>The sense of presence was measured by the 3 scales of the Temple Presence Inventory, for which means and SDs were computed. Engagement (mean [SD], 3.24&#x02009;[2.07]), perceptual realism (mean [SD], 1.97&#x02009;[1.33]), and spatial presence (mean [SD], 2.74&#x02009;[1.91]) were all below the midpoint of 4.</p></sec><sec id="H2-10-ZOI250390"><title>Patients&#x02019; Expectations of MERP</title><p>Patients&#x02019; expectations of MERP were mixed, with all 36 patients (100%) indicating that they thought they would attend all sessions. However, less than half of the participants (17 [47.2%]) expected that MERP would help them to implement what they learned in their everyday life. Half of participants (18 [50.0%]) agreed on the item &#x0201c;I am more likely to learn coping skills in ERP in vivo than in MERP.&#x0201d; Concerns such as dizziness were minimal (5 [13.9%]). In total, 30 participants (83.3%) expressed positive expectations for OCD symptom improvements and 34 (94.4%) found it easier to confront their OCD in the MR environment than in real life. eFigure 2 in <xref rid="note-ZOI250390-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 2</xref> shows all items and answers.</p></sec><sec id="H2-11-ZOI250390"><title>Subjective Appraisal of MERP and SERP</title><p>The subjective evaluation of MERP and SERP was moderate overall (<xref rid="zoi250390f3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>). The 2 groups differed significantly only on the item &#x0201c;I expect little long-term effects from the MERP/SERP,&#x0201d; with a more positive evaluation in the MERP group (&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup><sub>4</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;10.951 [<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;.03]). In response to the open question about MERP&#x02019;s advantages compared with in vivo exposure, most patients noted that MERP offers a valuable opportunity for those hesitant to engage in ERP or serves as a first step before in vivo therapy. The primary drawback identified was the constant awareness that the scenario in MERP was not real, leading to a perception of no genuine risk (eg, of contamination). When asked about objects needed for more effective OCD treatment, patients suggested automated teller machine (ATM) keypads, shopping carts, used cleaning cloths, mold, light switches, trash cans, shoes, and food.</p><fig position="float" id="zoi250390f3" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3. </label><caption><title>Subjective Appraisal</title><p>Participants included in the complete-case analysis provided subjective appraisals of self-guided exposure and response prevention (SERP) and mixed-reality exposure and response prevention (MERP). Some items were answered only by the SERP group or only by the MERP group.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2511488-g003" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="H2-12-ZOI250390"><title>Experiences With Treatment at Baseline and Posttreatment Assessment</title><p>Significantly more patients in the MERP group (15 [83.3%]) reported having undergone ERP in the past in comparison with the SERP group at baseline (8 [44.4%]) (&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup><sub>1</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;5.900 [<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;.02]), but there was no difference at posttreatment assessment for individual therapy or for therapist-guided ERP at posttreatment assessment (referring to the last 6 weeks). Therefore, we did not include it as a covariate in our main analyses. About two-thirds of participants in the SERP group (9 [61.1%]) conducted self-guided ERP at posttreatment assessment, compared with 5 (38.9%) in the MERP group, with no statistically significant difference between groups (&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup><sub>1</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.551 [<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;.21]). Patients in the SERP group completed approximately 4 (mean [SD], 4.29&#x02009;[2.06]) of 6 exercises.</p></sec><sec id="H2-13-ZOI250390"><title>Exploratory Analyses</title><p>Moderation analyses were conducted exploratorily by including all baseline variables as potential moderators for the change in OCD symptoms (Y-BOCS total score difference from baseline to posttreatment assessment) (eTable in <xref rid="note-ZOI250390-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 2</xref>). Positive &#x003b2; coefficients indicate that higher values on the moderator led to a greater improvement in OCD symptoms in the MERP vs the SERP group. Individuals in the MERP group, who had high levels of symptoms at baseline (&#x003b2; range, 3.482 [SE, 1.683] to 3.615 [SE, 1.273]; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;.05) and were older (&#x003b2;<italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;</italic>0.248 [SE, 0.119]; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;.05), showed greater reductions in OCD symptoms. Patients in the MERP group who did not indicate a panic disorder at baseline (&#x003b2;<italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;</italic>&#x02013;3.114 [SE, 1.416]; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;.04) showed greater reductions in OCD symptoms.</p></sec></sec><sec id="H1-4-ZOI250390"><title>Discussion</title><p>The present RCT aimed to investigate the efficacy of a highly innovative MERP compared with SERP in patients with C-OCD. Our findings are summarized as follows.</p><sec id="H2-14-ZOI250390"><title>Change in Symptoms</title><p>Contrary to our primary hypothesis, OCD symptoms (measured by Y-BOCS) did not decrease more in the MERP group than in the SERP group from baseline to post treatment or follow-up, contradicting studies supporting technical-assisted ERPs.<sup><xref rid="zoi250390r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="zoi250390r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="zoi250390r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> However, medium to large improvements were seen within the MERP group across various psychopathological variables, including OCD symptoms (Y-BOCS), anxiety (7-item Generalized Anxiety Disorder), and depression (Beck Depression Inventory-II), suggesting potential for improvement with intervention enhancements and more time. Still, only 2 patients in the MERP group (vs 1 in the SERP group) responded by post treatment or follow-up, highlighting limitations in the MERP intervention. Several factors may have influenced the nonsignificant between-group results.</p><p>First, the small sample size likely hindered the detection of significant between-group effects. The target was 64 participants, but recruitment challenges, such as limiting participation to patients with C-OCD in our region and COVID-19 restrictions, prevented this. Additionally, the SERP control condition may have been too strong, and the intervention duration too short, necessitating a larger sample to detect significant effects. Future studies should include multiple OCD domains and aim for a larger sample size. Second, the sense of presence in the MERP group was below the midpoint of the scale, reflecting limited engagement with the virtually supplemented environment. This suboptimal sense of presence may have affected efficacy. Previous research on VR-based treatments has shown that a stronger sense of presence is associated with greater emotional engagement,<sup><xref rid="zoi250390r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup> which in turn improves therapeutic outcomes. Thus, enhancements are needed in future studies to evoke appropriate negative emotions. Third, the ERP sessions may have been too brief and insufficiently intensive, with only 1 session per week for 6 weeks and just 4 exposure sessions. Guidelines recommend exposures on consecutive days and at least 2 lengthy sessions per week,<sup><xref rid="zoi250390r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> suggesting that nonsignificant effects may relate more to the delivery format than to technical augmentation. Future studies should explore whether this intensive ERP approach is feasible in MR. Forth, many participants needed 1 to 2 sessions to become familiar with the technology, which may have further reduced the available therapeutic time for effective ERP. This initial adjustment period could have limited MERP&#x02019;s impact, as less time remained to induce meaningful symptom changes. Last, the significant difference in prior ERP experience between the MERP (83.3%) and SERP groups (44.4%) may have contributed to the lack of significant effects. C-OCD among patients in the MERP group might have been more treatment resistant, which may have limited the patients&#x02019; responsiveness to the intervention. Although randomization usually aims to address this, the small sample size may have compromised its effectiveness in balancing these differences.</p></sec><sec id="H2-15-ZOI250390"><title>Treatment Expectations</title><p>Patients&#x02019; expectations of MERP were mixed. While all participants anticipated attending all sessions, only 47.2% expected that MERP would help them apply what they learned to everyday life. This skepticism regarding the feasibility of MERP may have been an additional inhibiting factor for recruitment. About half had similar expectations for MERP as for in vivo ERP, indicating aligned anticipated efficacy. Concerns such as dizziness were minimal (&#x0003c;15%), suggesting MR technology fears were not significant barriers. Expectations for OCD symptom improvements were high, with 83.3% expressing optimism. Notably, 94.4% found it easier to confront their OCD in the MR environment than in real life, suggesting MR could facilitate engagement in subsequent in vivo ERP.</p></sec><sec id="H2-16-ZOI250390"><title>Subjective Appraisal</title><p>In evaluating MERP and SERP, subjective ratings were mostly moderate, with a significant difference favoring MERP in long-term benefit expectations. However, few participants preferred MERP over traditional in vivo ERP. Participants were satisfied with the virtual objects used in MERP, finding them relevant and effective for their compulsions. Many viewed MERP as a safer initial step for those hesitant about in vivo ERP or as a precursor to it, which needs to be explored a priori in future studies with a design comparing MERP before ERP vs ERP alone. However, its artificial nature was a common drawback, limiting its impact. Participants also suggested incorporating other objects, such as ATM keypads and shopping carts, to enhance MERP&#x02019;s therapeutic value and better address individual OCD concerns. The list of stimuli points toward more everyday objects and scenarios that might feel more ecologically valid.</p></sec><sec id="H2-17-ZOI250390"><title>Exploratory Findings</title><p>The moderation analyses sought to identify factors influencing the effectiveness of MERP compared with SERP. Higher baseline symptom severity (Obsessive Compulsive Inventory scores) and older age were associated with more favorable outcomes in MERP, while the absence of panic disorder was also associated with better outcomes. Current research on these moderators is heterogeneous; some studies indicate that high symptom severity leads to poor outcomes,<sup><xref rid="zoi250390r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup> while others align with our findings.<sup><xref rid="zoi250390r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> There is limited research on age as a moderator in technology-assisted interventions, but one study found older adults reported a greater sense of presence in virtual environments, suggesting VR may benefit them more.<sup><xref rid="zoi250390r31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup> The nature of these moderators likely depends on the specific therapy used, indicating a need for more research. Our findings suggest that certain baseline characteristics may interact with treatment type (MERP vs SERP) to influence OCD outcomes, highlighting the importance of individualized treatment approaches and the need for clinicians to consider potential moderators when selecting therapeutic interventions.</p></sec><sec id="H2-18-ZOI250390"><title>Limitations</title><p>Several limitations of this study should be acknowledged. First, the relatively small sample size may limit between-group significance and generalizability due to recruitment challenges tied to a single symptom domain and regional constraints. Future MR devices could allow therapists to appear as avatars, enabling MERP implementation across different locations and increasing geographic flexibility. Technology-supported remote ERP is a promising approach, with options ranging from self-guided exposure exercises at home to more advanced setups where therapists provide virtual guidance via MR headsets. These technological advancements could help bridge treatment gaps and improve access to evidence-based interventions, particularly for patients without direct access to in-person ERP. Second, the focus on patients with C-OCD restricts the applicability of findings to this specific domain; this choice was made to assess MERP&#x02019;s feasibility and safety. Future studies should include patients with other symptom domains, such as aggressive obsessions, as some therapists may feel uneasy about placing a knife in front of a patient who experiences intrusive thoughts about harming others, to broaden the research scope. Additionally, MERP may not be suitable for all OCD domains, such as symmetry obsessions, where ERP in vivo is typically easy to implement. Third, as a high number of variables was included in the exploratory moderation analyses, the risk of type II error was high. Thus, these results need to be interpreted cautiously. Fourth, the progress of the SERP group was assessed retrospectively, meaning that the actual use may not have been fully captured. Future studies, particularly those offering compensation for participation, should aim to collect real-time data to better track treatment progress. Fifth, a significant proportion of participants in the MERP condition continued concurrent ERP treatment, making it difficult to determine the extent to which the observed effects can be attributed to MERP itself. However, concurrent ERP was also allowed in the control group, ensuring that this factor was at least consistent across conditions. Nevertheless, future studies could address this limitation by implementing the exclusion of concurrent treatments to more clearly isolate the specific effects of MERP. Sixth, the exact dosage of the medications could not be recorded, as patients often did not know or were unsure about it. Therefore, we cannot make any statement regarding the adequacy of the medication. This should be addressed in future studies through physician documentation.</p></sec></sec><sec id="H1-5-ZOI250390"><title>Conclusions</title><p>In this RCT, contrary to our primary hypothesis, OCD symptoms did not significantly decline more in the MERP group compared with the SERP group. However, the MERP group did show some improvements across several psychopathological variables. These findings indicate that while MERP may have potential in addressing OCD and related symptoms, further research is needed to address limitations such as sample size, symptom severity, sense of presence, and session intensity to better assess its efficacy and applicability. Additionally, subjective evaluations suggest that MERP could be considered as a preliminary approach before traditional ERP in vivo.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="REF-ZOI250390"><title>References</title><ref id="zoi250390r1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Fawcett</surname>
<given-names>EJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Power</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fawcett</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Women are at greater risk of OCD than men</article-title>. <source>J Clin Psychiatry</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>81</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<elocation-id>19r13085</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4088/JCP.19r13085</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi250390r2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group><collab>National Institute for Health and Care Excellence (NICE)</collab></person-group>. <source>2019 Surveillance of Obsessive-Compulsive Disorder and Body Dysmorphic Disorder: Treatment (NICE guideline CG31)</source>. <publisher-name>British Psychological Society</publisher-name>; February 7, <year>2019</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi250390r3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Reid</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Laws</surname>
<given-names>KR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Drummond</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Cognitive behavioural therapy with exposure and response prevention in the treatment of obsessive-compulsive disorder: a systematic review and meta-analysis of randomised controlled trials</article-title>. <source>Compr Psychiatry</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>106</volume>:<elocation-id>152223</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.comppsych.2021.152223</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33618297</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi250390r4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Moritz</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>K&#x000fc;lz</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Voderholzer</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hillebrand</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McKay</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jelinek</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>&#x0201c;Phobie &#x000e0; deux&#x0201d; and other reasons why clinicians do not apply exposure with response prevention in patients with obsessive-compulsive disorder</article-title>. <source>Cogn Behav Ther</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>162</fpage>-<lpage>176</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/16506073.2018.1494750</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30064295</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi250390r5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Senter</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Patel</surname>
<given-names>SR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dixon</surname>
<given-names>LB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Myers</surname>
<given-names>RW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Simpson</surname>
<given-names>HB</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Defining and addressing gaps in care for obsessive-compulsive disorder in the United States</article-title>. <source>Psychiatr Serv</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>72</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>784</fpage>-<lpage>793</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/appi.ps.202000296</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33957763</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi250390r6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Ong</surname>
<given-names>CW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Clyde</surname>
<given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bluett</surname>
<given-names>EJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Levin</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Twohig</surname>
<given-names>MP</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Dropout rates in exposure with response prevention for obsessive-compulsive disorder: What do the data really say?</article-title>
<source>J Anxiety Disord</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>40</volume>:<fpage>8</fpage>-<lpage>17</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.janxdis.2016.03.006</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27061971</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi250390r7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Fineberg</surname>
<given-names>NA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Ameringen</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Drummond</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>How to manage obsessive-compulsive disorder (OCD) under COVID-19: A clinician&#x02019;s guide from the International College of Obsessive Compulsive Spectrum Disorders (ICOCS) and the Obsessive-Compulsive and Related Disorders Research Network (OCRN) of the European College of Neuropsychopharmacology</article-title>. <source>Compr Psychiatry</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>100</volume>:<elocation-id>152174</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.comppsych.2020.152174</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32388123</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi250390r8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Boeldt</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McMahon</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McFaul</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Greenleaf</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Using virtual reality exposure therapy to enhance treatment of anxiety disorders: identifying areas of clinical adoption and potential obstacles</article-title>. <source>Front Psychiatry</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>773</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2019.00773</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31708821</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi250390r9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Carl</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stein</surname>
<given-names>AT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Levihn-Coon</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Virtual reality exposure therapy for anxiety and related disorders: a meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials</article-title>. <source>J Anxiety Disord</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>61</volume>:<fpage>27</fpage>-<lpage>36</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.janxdis.2018.08.003</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30287083</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi250390r10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Meyerbr&#x000f6;ker</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morina</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The use of virtual reality in assessment and treatment of anxiety and related disorders</article-title>. <source>Clin Psychol Psychother</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>466</fpage>-<lpage>476</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cpp.2623</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34097318</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi250390r11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Miegel</surname>
<given-names>FS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schr&#x000f6;der</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schultz</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>M&#x000fc;ller</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jelinek</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Expected increase in health competence improves over modules of an unguided internet-based cognitive-behavioural therapy for obsessive-compulsive disorder</article-title>. <source>Int J Psychol</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>58</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>443</fpage>-<lpage>448</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ijop.12919</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37287126</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi250390r12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Miegel</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>B&#x000fc;cker</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mostajeran</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Exposure and response prevention in virtual reality for obsessive-compulsive disorder: a case series</article-title>. <source>Psychiatr Q</source>. <year>2022</year>;93(3):861-882. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11126-022-09992-5</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35779165</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi250390r13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Inozu</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Celikcan</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Akin</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mustafao&#x0011f;lu Cicek</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The use of virtual reality (VR) exposure for reducing contamination fear and disgust: can VR be an effective alternative exposure technique to in vivo?</article-title>
<source>J Obsessive Compuls Relat Disord</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<elocation-id>100518</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jocrd.2020.100518</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi250390r14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a-Batista</surname>
<given-names>ZE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guerra-Pe&#x000f1;a</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alsina-Jurnet</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Design and validation of augmented reality stimuli for the treatment of cleaning obsessive-compulsive disorder</article-title>. <source>Front Psychol</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<elocation-id>618874</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2021.618874</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34135802</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi250390r15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Navas-Medrano</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Soler-Dominguez</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pons</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Mixed reality for a collective and adaptive mental health metaverse</article-title>. <source>Front Psychiatry</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<elocation-id>1272783</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2023.1272783</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38250268</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi250390r16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Miegel</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jelinek</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moritz</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lohse</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yassari</surname>
<given-names>AH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>B&#x000fc;cker</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Mixed results for exposure and response prevention therapy in mixed reality for patients with contamination-related obsessive-compulsive disorder: a randomized controlled pilot study</article-title>. <source>J Clin Psychol</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>79</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>2317</fpage>-<lpage>2336</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jclp.23550</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37317567</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi250390r17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><collab>World Medical Association</collab></person-group>. <article-title>World Medical Association Declaration of Helsinki: ethical principles for medical research involving human subjects</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>310</volume>(<issue>20</issue>):<fpage>2191</fpage>-<lpage>2194</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2013.281053</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24141714</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi250390r18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Lohse</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jelinek</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moritz</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bl&#x000f6;mer</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>B&#x000fc;cker</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Miegel</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Efficacy of exposure and response prevention therapy in mixed reality for patients with obsessive-compulsive disorder: study protocol for a randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>BMC Psychol</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>113</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40359-023-01116-3</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37055854</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi250390r19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Sheehan</surname>
<given-names>DV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lecrubier</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sheehan</surname>
<given-names>KH</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The Mini-International Neuropsychiatric Interview (M.I.N.I.): the development and validation of a structured diagnostic psychiatric interview for DSM-IV and ICD-10</article-title>. <source>J Clin Psychiatry</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>59</volume>(<issue>suppl 20</issue>):<fpage>22</fpage>-<lpage>33</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9881538</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi250390r20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Goodman</surname>
<given-names>WK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Price</surname>
<given-names>LH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rasmussen</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The Yale-Brown Obsessive Compulsive Scale, I: development, use, and reliability</article-title>. <source>Arch Gen Psychiatry</source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1006</fpage>-<lpage>1011</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archpsyc.1989.01810110048007</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2684084</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi250390r21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Foa</surname>
<given-names>EB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huppert</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Leiberg</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The Obsessive-Compulsive Inventory: development and validation of a short version</article-title>. <source>Psychol Assess</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>485</fpage>-<lpage>496</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/1040-3590.14.4.485</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12501574</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi250390r22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group><string-name><surname>Beck</surname>
<given-names>AT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Steer</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>GK</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <source>Beck Depression Inventory-II</source>. <edition>2nd ed</edition>. <publisher-name>Psychological Corporation</publisher-name>; <year>1996</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi250390r23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Spitzer</surname>
<given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kroenke</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Williams</surname>
<given-names>JBW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>L&#x000f6;we</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>A brief measure for assessing generalized anxiety disorder: the GAD-7</article-title>. <source>Arch Intern Med</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>166</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1092</fpage>-<lpage>1097</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archinte.166.10.1092</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16717171</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi250390r24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><collab>TheWHOQOL Group</collab></person-group>. <article-title>The World Health Organization Quality of Life Assessment (WHOQOL): development and general psychometric properties</article-title>. <source>Soc Sci Med</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1569</fpage>-<lpage>1585</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0277-9536(98)00009-4</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9672396</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi250390r25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group><string-name><surname>Lombard</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ditton</surname>
<given-names>TB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weinstein</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name></person-group>. Measuring presence: the Temple Presence Inventory. January 14, 2009. Accessed March 14, 2024. https://api.semanticscholar.org/CorpusID:11759204</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi250390r26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Faul</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Erdfelder</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Buchner</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lang</surname>
<given-names>AG</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Statistical power analyses using G*Power 3.1: tests for correlation and regression analyses</article-title>. <source>Behav Res Methods</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1149</fpage>-<lpage>1160</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3758/BRM.41.4.1149</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19897823</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi250390r27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Schr&#x000f6;der</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wrona</surname>
<given-names>KJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>M&#x000fc;ller</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Heinemann</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fischer</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dockweiler</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Impact of virtual reality applications in the treatment of anxiety disorders: A systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized-controlled trials</article-title>. <source>J Behav Ther Exp Psychiatry</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>81</volume>:<elocation-id>101893</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jbtep.2023.101893</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37453405</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi250390r28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Belloch</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cabedo</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carri&#x000f3;</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lozano-Quilis</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gil-G&#x000f3;mez</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gil-G&#x000f3;mez</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Virtual reality exposure for ocd: is it feasible?</article-title>
<source>Rev Psicopatol Psicol Clin</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>37</fpage>-<lpage>44</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi250390r29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Steketee</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Siev</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yovel</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lit</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wilhelm</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Predictors and moderators of cognitive and behavioral therapy outcomes for OCD: a patient-level mega-analysis of eight sites</article-title>. <source>Behav Ther</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>50</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>165</fpage>-<lpage>176</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.beth.2018.04.004</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30661557</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi250390r30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Boschen</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Drummond</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pillay</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morton</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Predicting outcome of treatment for severe, treatment resistant OCD in inpatient and community settings</article-title>. <source>J Behav Ther Exp Psychiatry</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>90</fpage>-<lpage>95</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jbtep.2009.10.006</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19926074</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi250390r31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Dilanchian</surname>
<given-names>AT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Andringa</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boot</surname>
<given-names>WR</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>a pilot study exploring age differences in presence, workload, and cybersickness in the experience of immersive virtual reality environments</article-title>. <source>Front Virtual Real</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<elocation-id>736793</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/frvir.2021.736793</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list><notes notes-type="supplementary-material" id="note-ZOI250390-1"><supplementary-material id="note-ZOI250390-1-s" position="float" content-type="local-data"><label>Supplement 1.</label><caption><p>
Trial Protocol
</p></caption><media xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2511488-s001.pdf"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material position="float" content-type="local-data"><label>Supplement 2.</label><caption><p><bold>eFigure 1.</bold> Visible Virus Particles on Hand After Touching the Contaminated Object</p><p><bold>eFigure 2.</bold> Patients&#x02019; Expectations of Mixed Reality Exposure and Response Prevention Therapy (MERP)</p><p><bold>eTable.</bold> Moderators for Obsessive-Compulsive Symptom Improvement</p></caption><media xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2511488-s002.pdf"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material position="float" content-type="local-data"><label>Supplement 3.</label><caption><p>
Data Sharing Statement
</p></caption><media xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2511488-s003.pdf"/></supplementary-material></notes></back></article><!--requester-ID tigray-->