<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Acta Neurochir (Wien)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Acta Neurochir (Wien)</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Acta Neurochirurgica</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0001-6268</issn><issn pub-type="epub">0942-0940</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer Vienna</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Vienna</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40407913</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12102136</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">6561</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00701-025-06561-0</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Incidence, predictors, and management of postoperative subdural empyema following chronic subdural hematoma evacuation: a population-based cohort study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jansson</surname><given-names>Sophia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Halvardsson Flores</surname><given-names>Nike</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Buwaider</surname><given-names>Ali</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>Helge</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shokri Stenstr&#x000f6;m</surname><given-names>Akhar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bartek</surname><given-names>Jiri</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Fletcher-Sandersj&#x000f6;&#x000f6;</surname><given-names>Alexander</given-names></name><address><email>alexander.fletcher-sandersjoo@ki.se</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/00m8d6786</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.24381.3c</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9241 5705</institution-id><institution>Department of Neurosurgery, </institution><institution>Karolinska University Hospital, </institution></institution-wrap>Stockholm, Sweden </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/01apvbh93</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412354.5</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2351 3333</institution-id><institution>Department of Neurosurgery, </institution><institution>Uppsala University Hospital, </institution></institution-wrap>Uppsala, Sweden </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/00m8d6786</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.24381.3c</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9241 5705</institution-id><institution>Infectious Diseases Unit, </institution><institution>Karolinska University Hospital, </institution></institution-wrap>Stockholm, Sweden </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/056d84691</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.4714.6</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1937 0626</institution-id><institution>Department of Clinical Neuroscience, </institution><institution>Karolinska Institutet, </institution></institution-wrap>Stockholm, Sweden </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>23</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>23</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>167</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>150</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>8</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Purpose</title><p id="Par1">Subdural empyema (SDE) is a rare but potentially serious complication following chronic subdural hematoma (CSDH) evacuation. This study aimed to establish the incidence of postoperative SDE, identify risk factors for its development, characterize the bacterial pathogens involved, and evaluate optimal surgical management strategies.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">Patients aged&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;15&#x000a0;years who underwent CSDH evacuation at the Karolinska University Hospital between 2006 and 2022 were retrospectively screened for postoperative SDE. Logistic regression analyses were used to identify predictors of SDE development and treatment failure.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">Among 2656 operations for CSDH, 37 (1.4%) resulted in postoperative SDE. Independent predictors of SDE were larger CSDH diameter (odds ratio [OR] 1.12, 95% confidence interval [CI] 1.06 &#x02013; 1.17, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001) and Cloxacillin prophylaxis during index CSDH-surgery (OR 4.63, 95% CI 2.19 &#x02013; 11.0, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001). Hemiparesis (54%) and wound infection (30%) were the most common SDE symptoms, and fever was frequently absent. Cutibacterium acnes was the most common bacterial isolate, identified in 76% of cases. Craniotomy was more effective than burr-hole evacuation for managing SDE, with the latter showing a higher risk of reoperation (OR 11.5, 95% CI 1.72 &#x02013; 230, <italic>p =&#x02009;</italic>0.032). The median antibiotic treatment duration was 48&#x000a0;days (interquartile range 35&#x02013;77). One-year mortality did not differ significantly between patients with and without SDE (8.1% vs. 12%, <italic>p =&#x02009;</italic>0.618).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par4">A larger CSDH diameter and Cloxacillin prophylaxis significantly increased the risk of postoperative SDE. Craniotomy was more effective than burr-hole evacuation for SDE management, and one-year mortality was not elevated in patients who developed an SDE.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Burr-hole</kwd><kwd>Chronic subdural hematoma</kwd><kwd>Craniotomy</kwd><kwd>Neurosurgery</kwd><kwd>Postoperative infection</kwd><kwd>Subdural empyema</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Karolinska Institute</institution></funding-source></award-group><open-access><p>Open access funding provided by Karolinska Institute.</p></open-access></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Springer-Verlag GmbH Austria, part of Springer Nature 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par14">Chronic subdural hematoma (CSDH) is among the most common neurosurgical conditions, with an annual incidence ranging from 1.72 to 20.6 per 100,000 individuals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. With an aging population, the incidence of CSDH is rising [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>], and burr-hole evacuation remains the gold-standard treatment for symptomatic CSDH with significant mass effect. However, several postoperative complications can occur, with subdural empyema (SDE), a purulent collection between the dura mater and the arachnoid, being one of the potentially more serious if left untreated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>].</p><p id="Par15">The risk of developing a postoperative SDE after CSDH evacuation has been reported to range from 0.8% to 2.1% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>] (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Due to this, fewer than 50 cases have been reported in the literature, leaving a significant gap in our understanding of several critical aspects of this complication. For example, predictors of SDE development have not been identified, and the optimal surgical strategy for managing SDE is also unclear. Additionally, the most common bacterial pathogens have not been identified, which hampers the selection of empirical antibiotic treatment. To address these knowledge gaps, we analyzed a large population-based cohort of patients who underwent CSDH surgery with the aim to:<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p id="Par16"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p id="Par17">Identify predictors of SDE development following CSDH evacuation</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par18">Identify the most common bacterial pathogens involved</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par19">Evaluate optimal surgical strategies for SDE evacuation</p></list-item></list></p></list-item></list><table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Summary of previous cohort studies reporting on SDE following chronic subdural hematoma evacuation</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Study</th><th align="left">Design</th><th align="left">CSDH (n)</th><th align="left">SDE (n, %)</th><th align="left">Conclusion regarding SDE</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Bartek et al. (2017) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]</td><td align="left">Retrospective cohort study</td><td align="left">759</td><td align="left">7 (0.9%)</td><td align="left">Only incidence rate reported</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Chan et al. (2017) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]</td><td align="left">Retrospective cohort study</td><td align="left">302</td><td align="left">3 (1.0%)</td><td align="left">Only incidence rate reported</td></tr><tr><td align="left">El Ouadih et al. (2020) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]</td><td align="left">Retrospective cohort study</td><td align="left">203</td><td align="left">2 (1.0%)</td><td align="left">Antibiotic prophylaxis did not affect SDE rates</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Nayil et al. (2012) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]</td><td align="left">Retrospective cohort study</td><td align="left">1181</td><td align="left">9 (0.8%)</td><td align="left">All SDE patients presented with hemiparesis within three weeks post-CSDH evacuation; all underwent craniotomy; two (22%) died</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Rauhala et al. (2020) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]</td><td align="left">Retrospective cohort study</td><td align="left">978</td><td align="left">20 (2.0%)</td><td align="left">SDE was more common in patients who underwent CSDH reoperation (4.3% vs. 0.9%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Rohde et al. (2002) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]</td><td align="left">Retrospective cohort study</td><td align="left">376</td><td align="left">8 (2.1%)</td><td align="left">Only incidence rate reported</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>CSDH</italic> chronic subdural hematoma, <italic>SDE</italic> subdural empyema</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par20">By exploring these areas, our study sought to enhance the understanding of this rare but potentially serious complication.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Study design and population</title><p id="Par21">We conducted a single-center retrospective study of all patients aged &#x02265;&#x02009;15 years who underwent surgical treatment for a CSDH from 2006 to 2022. Patients were identified using the procedure code"AAD10"(evacuation of CSDH) in the Orbit surgical management system (Evry Healthcare Systems, Solna, Sweden). From this cohort, we systematically screened for patients who developed a postoperative SDE by manually reviewing each patient's medical record in the TakeCare electronic records system (CompuGroup Medical Sweden AB, Farsta, Sweden). Imaging data were retrieved from the Sectra Picture Archiving and Communication System (PACS) IDS7 (Sectra AB, Link&#x000f6;ping, Sweden). The study was approved by the regional ethical review board (EPN 2017/247 and EPN 2013/591&#x02013;31/1), who waived the need for informed consent. We excluded patients with CSDHs in arachnoid cysts, external hydrocephalus, or prior neurosurgery within the prior six months, to align with the methodological standards of randomized controlled trials in the field [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. We also excluded those who&#x02019;s initial CSDH evacuation was performed at another hospital, to ensure complete access to perioperative data and standardized treatment protocols.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Variables</title><p id="Par22">Demographic and comorbidity data included age, sex, diabetes mellitus, moderate-to-severe renal disease (defined as chronic kidney disease stage &#x02265;&#x02009;3), and the Charlson Comorbidity Index, which was calculated based on recorded diagnoses at the time of surgery. Clinical and radiological variables included the preoperative Glasgow Coma Scale score, hematoma diameter, midline shift, and whether the CSDH was bilateral. Hematoma diameter was defined as the maximal thickness in the coronal orientation perpendicular to the skull curvature. In cases of bilateral CSDH, the maximal diameter was measured on each side, and the larger of the two was used for analysis. Midline shift was measured at the point of greatest displacement from the midline on the preoperative CT scan. Treatment-related variables included operative time (measured from skin incision to closure), type of anesthesia (local or general), surgical method (burr-hole or mini-craniotomy), type of perioperative antibiotic prophylaxis, and whether a CSDH reoperation was performed within six months of the index procedure.</p><p id="Par23">For patients who developed a postoperative SDE, we collected the time from index surgery to SDE evacuation, presenting symptoms, C-reactive protein (CRP) levels prior to reoperation, and the highest recorded body temperature within 24 h of SDE evacuation. Additional data included empyema diameter and consistency (liquid or semi-solid), the type of surgical procedure used for SDE evacuation (burr-hole or craniotomy), and the bacterial isolates identified from intraoperative cultures. We also recorded the total duration of antibiotic treatment (including intravenous and oral components), whether hyperbaric oxygen therapy was used, whether SDE reoperation was required, and one-year mortality.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>CSDH treatment protocol</title><p id="Par24">All patients were managed under a standardized protocol for their initial CSDH evacuation. CSDHs were radiologically confirmed using computed tomography (CT) or magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), supplemented by perioperative confirmation as needed. A single dose of intravenous antibiotics was administered preoperatively, though precise timing and any potential intraoperative redosing were not consistently documented. From the start of the study until April 2014, the standard prophylaxis consisted of 2&#x000a0;g intravenous Cloxacillin. Beginning in May 2014, this was replaced by 1.5 g intravenous Cefuroxime. For patients unable to tolerate these regimens, 600 mg intravenous Clindamycin was used in both time periods. The standard surgical approach during the entire study period involved a single burr-hole craniostomy under local anesthesia, followed by saline irrigation and a 24-h active subgaleal drainage, defined as a closed-suction drain connected to a compressible bulb reservoir. Irrigation was typically performed using saline at body temperature, except during periods when the center participated in a randomized trial comparing irrigation temperatures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Postoperative CT scans were obtained at the discretion of the treating physician, most commonly in cases of neurological deterioration or if the patient failed to improve clinically. Follow-up was conducted by telephone or in person, typically within 1&#x02013;2 months postoperatively.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Definition of postoperative SDE</title><p id="Par25">Diagnosing a postoperative SDE can be challenging because it often resembles recurrent CSDH on CT scans [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>], and no standardized definition currently exists [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. In this study, we defined an SDE as having occurred when the below two criteria were met:<list list-type="order"><list-item><p id="Par26">Perioperative findings suggestive of infection, including purulent or pus-like fluid, foul odor, thickened or inflamed dura and subdural membranes, or granulation/fibrous tissue in the subdural space.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par27">Positive bacterial growth from cultures obtained during SDE evacuation, initiated at the surgeon&#x02019;s suspicion of infection.</p></list-item></list></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Statistical analyses</title><p id="Par28">All continuous data deviated from a normal distribution pattern (Shapiro&#x02013;Wilk test p-value &#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05); therefore, we presented them as medians with interquartile ranges (IQRs). Categorical data were presented as counts and percentages. Patients were stratified based on the development of SDE, and mortality rates were compared using the Chi-square test. A Kaplan&#x02013;Meier curve was employed to illustrate the cumulative risk of SDE development over time from index CSDH surgery. We then conducted two separate sets of univariable and step-down multivariable logistic regression analyses. The first aimed to identify predictors of SDE development following index CSDH surgery, and the second focused on determining predictors of reoperation after initial SDE evacuation. Missing data were handled through listwise deletion. All statistical analyses were performed using R version 4.1.2, and a p-value &#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec9"><title>Baseline characteristics</title><p id="Par29">During the study period, 2745 patients underwent a CSDH evacuation. Of these, 89 were excluded due to prior neurosurgery within 6&#x000a0;months (<italic>n =</italic>&#x02009;67), CSDH in an arachnoid cyst (<italic>n =</italic>&#x02009;14) and external hydrocephalus (<italic>n =</italic>&#x02009;8). The remaining 2656 patients were included in this study (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Their median age was 76 years (IQR, 68&#x02013;83), and 72% were male. The median Charlson comorbidity index was 1.0 (IQR 0.0&#x02013;2.0). Most procedures (93%, <italic>n =</italic>&#x02009;2476) were performed under local anesthesia. Within 6&#x000a0;months of the initial surgery, 10% of patients had required reoperation due to a CSDH recurrence (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Flow chart of the patient selection process</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="701_2025_6561_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Overview of the study cohort</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Variable</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">All patients<break/>(<italic>n =</italic>&#x02009;2656)</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Postoperative SDE</th></tr><tr><th align="left"><bold>No (</bold><bold><italic>n =</italic></bold><bold>&#x02009;2619)</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Yes (</bold><bold><italic>n =</italic></bold><bold>&#x02009;37)</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Age (years)</td><td align="left">76 (68&#x02013;83)</td><td align="left">76 (68&#x02013;83)</td><td align="left">75 (66&#x02013;82)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Male sex</td><td align="left">1910 (72%)</td><td align="left">1878 (72%)</td><td align="left">32 (86%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Diabetes</td><td align="left">430 (16%)</td><td align="left">424 (16%)</td><td align="left">6 (16%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Moderate-to-severe renal disease</td><td align="left">102 (3.8%)</td><td align="left">100 (3.8%)</td><td align="left">2 (5.4%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Charlson comorbidity index</td><td align="left">1.0 (0.0&#x02013;2.0)</td><td align="left">1.0 (0.0&#x02013;2.0)</td><td align="left">1.0 (0.0&#x02013;2.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Pre-operative GCS</td><td align="left">15 (14&#x02013;15)</td><td align="left">15 (14&#x02013;15)</td><td align="left">15 (14&#x02013;15)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Hematoma diameter (mm)</td><td align="left">21 (17&#x02013;25)</td><td align="left">21 (17&#x02013;25)</td><td align="left">25 (23&#x02013;27)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Midline shift (mm)</td><td align="left">7.0 (4.0&#x02013;11)</td><td align="left">7.0 (4.0&#x02013;11)</td><td align="left">8.0 (5.0&#x02013;10)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Operative time (skin-to-skin) (min)</td><td align="left">29 (20&#x02013;41)</td><td align="left">29 (20&#x02013;41)</td><td align="left">27 (20&#x02013;37)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Bilateral CSDH evacuation</td><td align="left">445 (17%)</td><td align="left">440 (17%)</td><td align="left">5 (14%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Local anesthesia only</td><td align="left">2476 (93%)</td><td align="left">2440 (93%)</td><td align="left">36 (97%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Surgical method</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Burr-hole</td><td align="left">2408 (91%)</td><td align="left">2374 (91%)</td><td align="left">34 (92%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Mini-craniotomy</td><td align="left">248 (9.3%)</td><td align="left">245 (9.4%)</td><td align="left">3 (8.1%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CSDH reoperation</td><td align="left">266 (10%)</td><td align="left">259 (9.9%)</td><td align="left">7 (19%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Days from CSDH surgery to empyema evacuation</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">23 (17&#x02013;39)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">1-year mortality</td><td align="left">312 (12%)</td><td align="left">309 (12%)</td><td align="left">3 (8.1%)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Data are presented as median (IQR) or count (%). <italic>CSDH</italic> chronic subdural hematoma, <italic>GCS</italic> Glasgow Coma Scale, <italic>mm</italic> millimeters, <italic>SDE</italic> subdural empyema. Bold <italic>p-</italic>values indicate statistical significance (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c; 0.05)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Incidence and predictors of SDE</title><p id="Par30">Among 40 patients reoperated due to suspected infection, 37 (1.4%) had positive intraoperative cultures and were classified as SDE. The median time from initial CSDH surgery to SDE evacuation was 23 days (IQR 17&#x02013;39, Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Initial CSDH diameter (odds ratio [OR] 1.12, 95% confidence interval [CI] 1.06&#x02013;1.17, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c; 0.001) and Cloxacillin prophylaxis (OR 4.63, 95% CI 2.19&#x02013;11.0, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c; 0.001) were identified as independent predictors of SDE development (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Kaplan&#x02013;Meier plot illustrating the time from index chronic subdural hematoma evacuation to surgical intervention for postoperative subdural empyema</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="701_2025_6561_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Univariable and multivariable logistic regression predicting empyema development</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Variable</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Univariable model</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Final step-down multivariable model</th></tr><tr><th align="left"><bold>OR (95% CI)</bold></th><th align="left"><bold><italic>p</italic></bold><bold>-value</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>OR (95% CI)</bold></th><th align="left"><bold><italic>p-</italic></bold><bold>value</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><bold>Demographics</bold></td><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Age (years)</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">0.99 (0.97&#x02013;1.02)</td><td char="." align="char">0.646</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Male sex</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">2.53 (1.07&#x02013;7.41)</td><td char="." align="char">0.055</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Diabetes</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">1.00 (0.37&#x02013;2.25)</td><td char="." align="char">0.996</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Moderate-to-severe renal disease</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">1.44 (0.23&#x02013;4.81)</td><td char="." align="char">0.620</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Imaging findings</bold></td><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Hematoma diameter (mm)</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char"><bold>1.11 (1.05&#x02013;1.16)</bold></td><td char="." align="char"><bold>&#x02009;&#x0003c; 0.001</bold></td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char"><bold>1.12 (1.06&#x02013;1.17)</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>&#x02009;&#x0003c; 0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Midline shift (mm)</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">1.03 (0.96&#x02013;1.10)</td><td char="." align="char">0.462</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Treatment-related variables</bold></td><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left"><p>Cloxacillin prophylaxis</p><p>(<italic>ref: Cefuroxime</italic>)</p></td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char"><bold>4.09 (1.95&#x02013;9.63)</bold></td><td char="." align="char"><bold>&#x02009;&#x0003c; 0.001</bold></td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char"><bold>4.63 (2.19&#x02013;11.0)</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>&#x02009;&#x0003c; 0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Operative time (min)</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">1.00 (0.99&#x02013;1.02)</td><td char="." align="char">0.743</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Bilateral CSDH evacuation</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">0.77 (0.26&#x02013;1.83)</td><td char="." align="char">0.596</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CSDH evacuation using mini-craniotomy</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">0.85 (0.20&#x02013;2.40)</td><td char="." align="char">0.796</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CSDH reoperation</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">2.13 (0.85&#x02013;4.62)</td><td char="." align="char">0.076</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>CSDH</italic> chronic subdural hematoma, <italic>mm</italic> millimeters, <italic>min</italic> minutes, <italic>ref</italic> reference. Bold <italic>p-</italic>values indicate statistical significance (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c; 0.05). Dashes (&#x02013;) used for excluded variables in the final step-down model</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>SDE presentation and bacterial isolates</title><p id="Par31">Among the 37 patients with an SDE, the most common presenting symptom was hemiparesis (55%), followed by wound infection (30%), dysphasia (22%), confusion (14%), headache (14%), and gait instability (8.1%). The median CRP level prior to SDE evacuation was 66 mg/L (IQR 34&#x02013;131). The most frequently isolated pathogen was Cutibacterium acnes (76%), followed by Staphylococcus aureus (16%), Coagulase-negative staphylococci (5.4%), Klebsiella aerogenes (5.4%), Finegoldia magna (5.4%), and Enterobacter cloacae (2.7%) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). No patient underwent a preoperative diagnostic puncture; all cultures were collected intraoperatively.
<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Clinical presentation and microbiological findings</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Variable</th><th align="left">SDE patients (<italic>n =</italic>&#x02009;37)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Empyema diameter (mm)</td><td align="left">23 (19&#x02013;25)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Bilateral empyema</td><td align="left">5 (14%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Presenting symptom</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Hemiparesis</td><td align="left">20 (54%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Wound infection</td><td align="left">11 (30%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Dysphasia</td><td align="left">8 (22%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Confusion</td><td align="left">5 (14%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Headache</td><td align="left">5 (14%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Gait instability</td><td align="left">3 (8.1%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CRP prior to empyema evacuation (mg/L)</td><td align="left">66 (34&#x02013;131)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Highest body temperature within 24 h prior to empyema evacuation, &#x000b0;C</td><td align="left">37.2 (36.8&#x02013;37.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Microbiological culture</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Cutibacterium acnes</td><td align="left">28 (76%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Staphylococcus aureus</td><td align="left">6 (16%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Coagulase-Negative Staphylococci</td><td align="left">2 (5.4%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Klebsiella aerogenes</td><td align="left">2 (5.4%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Finegoldia magna</td><td align="left">2 (5.4%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Enterobacter cloacae</td><td align="left">1 (2.7%)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Data is shown as median (interquartile range) or count (proportion). <italic>C</italic> Celsius, <italic>CRP</italic> C-reactive protein, <italic>mm</italic> millimeters, <italic>SDE</italic> subdural empyema</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Treatment of SDE and predictors of SDE reoperation</title><p id="Par32">For the SDE surgery, 18 (49%) received a burr-hole evacuation and 19 (51%) underwent a craniotomy. SDE consistency was semi-solid in 25 patients (68%) and liquid in 12 (32%) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>). Empiric antibiotic therapy was initiated in all cases and adjusted based on microbiological findings and clinical response. Further changes were commonly made at the time of oral transition. The median antibiotic treatment duration was 48 days (IQR 35&#x02013;76), with a median of 11 days (IQR 7.0&#x02013;29) of intravenous antibiotics and 30 days (IQR 30&#x02013;56) of oral therapy. Five patients had an antibiotic treatment duration &#x0003c;&#x02009;4 weeks, due to death (<italic>n =</italic>&#x02009;3), non-compliance (<italic>n =</italic>&#x02009;1), and non-tolerable side effects (<italic>n =</italic>&#x02009;1). The latter two did not require an SDE reoperation. Hyperbaric oxygen therapy was utilized in 5 patients (14%) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>).
<table-wrap id="Tab5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Treatment approaches and outcomes</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Variable</th><th align="left">SDE patients (<italic>n =</italic>&#x02009;37)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Surgical method</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Burr-hole evacuation</td><td align="left">18 (49%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Craniotomy</td><td align="left">19 (51%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Empyema consistency</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> Liquid</td><td align="left">12 (32%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Semi-solid</td><td align="left">25 (68%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Antibiotic treatment</td><td align="left">37 (100%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Treatment duration (days)</td><td align="left">48 (35&#x02013;76)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Intravenous antibiotics (days)</td><td align="left">11 (7.0&#x02013;29)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Oral antibiotics (days)</td><td align="left">30 (9.0&#x02013;56)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Hyperbaric oxygen chamber</td><td align="left">5 (14%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Empyema reoperation</td><td align="left">8 (22%)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Data is shown as median (interquartile range) or count (proportion). <italic>SDE</italic> subdural empyema</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par33">Eight patients (22%) required a reoperation for their SDE (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>). In the regression analysis predicting SDE reoperation, burr-hole evacuation was independently associated with a higher risk compared to craniotomy (OR 11.5, 95% CI 1.72&#x02013;230, <italic>p =&#x02009;</italic>0.032). Other factors, such as age, preoperative CRP, time to surgery, specific bacterial pathogens, and SDE consistency, were not linked to reoperation risk (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref>).
<table-wrap id="Tab6"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Univariable and multivariable logistic regression predicting empyema reoperation</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Variable</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Univariable model</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Final step-down multivariable model</th></tr><tr><th align="left"><bold>OR (95% CI)</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>p-value</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>OR (95% CI)</bold></th><th align="left"><bold><italic>p</italic></bold><bold>-value</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Age (years)</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">1.04 (0.97&#x02013;1.07)</td><td char="." align="char">0.341</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">&#x02013;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Pre-operative CRP</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">0.99 (0.98&#x02013;1.01)</td><td char="." align="char">0.377</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">&#x02013;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Empyema diameter (mm)</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">1.01 (0.88&#x02013;1.16)</td><td char="." align="char">0.867</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">&#x02013;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Cutibacterium acnes</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">2.67 (0.38&#x02013;54.0)</td><td char="." align="char">0.392</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">&#x02013;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Staphylococcus aureus</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">2.08 (0.25&#x02013;13.7)</td><td char="." align="char">0.453</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">&#x02013;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Burr-hole evacuation</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">11.5 (1.72&#x02013;230)</td><td char="." align="char"><bold>0.032</bold></td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">11.5 (1.72&#x02013;230)</td><td char="." align="char"><bold>0.032</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Semi-solid state</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">0.38 (0.07&#x02013;1.95)</td><td char="." align="char">0.239</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">&#x02013;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02013;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>CRP</italic> C-reactive protein. Bold text in the p-value column indicates a statistically significant correlation (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c; 0.05). Dashes (&#x02013;) used for excluded variables in the final step-down model</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par34">We conducted the largest population-based study to date examining SDE after CSDH evacuation, aiming to determine its incidence, define predictive factors, identify the main bacterial pathogens, and evaluate optimal surgical strategies.</p><sec id="Sec14"><title>Incidence and predictors of SDE</title><p id="Par35">Our analysis revealed a 1.4% incidence of postoperative SDE, aligning with previously reported rates of 0.8&#x02013;2.1% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Initial CSDH diameter emerged as an independent predictor of SDE development. Possible explanations include a larger subdural space that fosters bacterial growth after CSDH evacuation, longer operative times, and incomplete evacuation of larger CSDH leaving residual blood to fuel infection. In addition, Cloxacillin prophylaxis was linked to a 4.6-fold higher risk of SDE compared to Cefuroxime. This is consistent with a prior study at our center showing that switching from Cloxacillin to Cefuroxime reduced the surgical site infection rate from 13.3% to 5.4% in tumor surgery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. The likely explanation is Cloxacillin&#x02019;s narrower spectrum, primarily targeting staphylococci and streptococci, with insufficient coverage against Cutibacterium acnes, the predominant SDE pathogen in our cohort. Cefuroxime, in contrast, offers broader-spectrum activity and better pharmacokinetics (including enhanced central nervous system penetration) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. These findings underscore the importance of tailoring prophylactic antibiotics to local resistance patterns and highlight the need for periodic reassessment of prophylaxis protocols.</p><p id="Par36">Other variables, including age, sex, comorbidities, surgical approach, and previous CSDH reoperation, did not show significant associations with SDE development in our cohort. This finding contrasts with Rauhala et al., who observed higher SDE rates among patients requiring CSDH reoperation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. However, the univariable p-value for reoperation in our study was 0.076, suggesting that an association, though not statistically confirmed, cannot be entirely ruled out. Further investigation with larger sample sizes should help clarify this relationship.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Presenting symptoms and diagnostic challenges</title><p id="Par37">Hemiparesis (55%) was the most common SDE symptom, followed by wound infection (30%) and dysphasia (22%), mirroring the results of Nayil et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. In all our cases of wound infection, the bacteria isolated matched those identified during SDE evacuation. It should also be noted that 65% of the SDE patients had normal body temperatures, illustrating how SDE can mimic recurrent CSDH both clinically and radiologically. Surgeons must therefore remain alert to the potential of an underlying SDE when encountering postoperative wound complications or unexplained neurological deterioration. MRI, as well as an increased CRP, may offer improved specificity in discriminating between recurrent CSDH and SDE.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Bacterial pathogens</title><p id="Par38">Cutibacterium acnes was the most frequently isolated organism, followed by Staphylococcus aureus, a pattern suggesting intraoperative contamination as a major mechanism in SDE pathogenesis. Previous reports have similarly identified Cutibacterium acnes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>], Staphylococcus aureus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>], Klebsiella oxytoca [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>], and E. coli [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>] as SDE pathogens. Notably, 24 of the 28 Cutibacterium acnes cases in our cohort occurred when Cloxacillin was the standard prophylaxis, underscoring its limited anaerobic coverage. Although culture contamination is a known concern with Cutibacterium acnes, we required both positive cultures and perioperative evidence of infection to distinguish pathogenic infection from potential contaminants. Given this, we believe our findings strongly support prophylactic antibiotic regimens with sufficient activity against anaerobes &#x02013; particularly Cutibacterium acnes &#x02013; to reduce the risk of postoperative SDE.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Optimal surgical management</title><p id="Par39">Craniotomy was more effective than burr-hole evacuation for treating SDE, as burr-hole patients had a markedly higher likelihood of SDE reoperation (OR 11.5, 95% CI 1.72&#x02013;230, <italic>p =&#x02009;</italic>0.032). This observation aligns with prior recommendations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>], presumably because craniotomy facilitates more comprehensive removal of infected tissue. Burr-hole evacuation is likely particularly inadequate for semi-solid SDE, which constituted 65% of our cases. Consequently, surgeons opting for burr-hole procedures should be prepared to transition to craniotomy if they encounter poor drainage or partitioned SDE. Anesthesia choice also comes into play here, since craniotomy typically necessitates general anesthesia.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Postoperative antibiotic strategies and outcome</title><p id="Par40">Every SDE patient in our cohort received antibiotic therapy, which was generally designed to cover the most common pathogens in postoperative&#x000a0;SDE, including coagulase-negative staphylococci, Cutibacterium acnes, anaerobes, and gram-negative bacilli. Empiric regimens typically included a third-generation cephalosporin or carbapenem in combination with a glycopeptide or oxazolidinone. Adjustments were often made within the first 24 h after infectious disease consultation, followed by further tailoring based on culture results and again during the transition from intravenous to oral therapy.</p><p id="Par41">The median treatment duration was 48 days (IQR 35&#x02013;76), generally conforming to guidelines for spontaneous SDE [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. As most cases were evacuated using burr-hole craniostomy without bone flap fixation devices, the risk of biofilm formation was minimal, explaining why more prolonged courses were not required. We excluded treatment duration from our regression models to avoid reverse causality: reoperations may have led to extended antibiotic courses rather than vice versa. Although the optimal duration remains poorly defined, our data suggest a practical range of 5&#x02013;10 weeks, guided by clinical response, microbial data, inflammatory marker trends, and imaging evidence of resolution.</p><p id="Par42">Lastly, one-year mortality was similar between those who developed SDE (7.5%) and those who did not (12%, <italic>p =&#x02009;</italic>0.618), suggesting that timely recognition and appropriate management can yield outcomes comparable to patients without this complication.</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Study limitations</title><p id="Par43">This study&#x02019;s retrospective, single-center design limits the generalizability of our findings, and reliance on medical records restricted the evaluation of long-term functional outcomes. Our definition of SDE &#x02013; requiring intraoperative findings plus positive cultures &#x02013; is not standardized, raising the possibility of both missed and overdiagnosed cases. Moreover, because only those who underwent reoperation could be definitively diagnosed, patients who deteriorated rapidly or never returned for surgery may have harbored undetected infections, further&#x000a0;leading to an underestimate of the true incidence. We also lacked detailed data on certain patient-specific risk factors (e.g., nutritional status and smoking), which may influence SDE susceptibility. Moreover, we did not include functional or neurological outcomes, as follow-up varies considerably between patients, and including this data would likely introduce selective bias. Looking ahead, prospective, multicenter studies that adopt standardized diagnostic criteria, gather more comprehensive clinical data, and evaluate functional outcomes will be important for addressing these limitations and refining SDE management strategies.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par44">In this population-based analysis of 2656 CSDH operations, 1.4% of patients developed a postoperative SDE &#x02013; most often caused by Cutibacterium acnes. A larger baseline CSDH diameter and the use of Cloxacillin rather than Cefuroxime for surgical prophylaxis significantly elevated the risk of SDE. Craniotomy was superior to burr-hole evacuation for managing postoperative SDE, as the latter carried a higher likelihood of reoperation. Despite the clinical burden posed by SDE, one-year mortality rates were similar in patients with and without this complication, underscoring the value of early diagnosis and appropriate treatment.</p></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>CI</term><def><p id="Par5">Confidence interval</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CRP</term><def><p id="Par6">C-reactive protein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CSDH</term><def><p id="Par7">Chronic subdural hematoma</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CT</term><def><p id="Par8">Computed tomography</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IQR</term><def><p id="Par9">Interquartile range</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MRI</term><def><p id="Par10">Magnetic resonance imaging</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>OR</term><def><p id="Par11">Odds ratio</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PACS</term><def><p id="Par12">Picture Archiving and Communication System</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SDE</term><def><p id="Par13">Subdural empyema</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p>Sophia Jansson and Nike Halvardsson Flores shared first authorship.</p></fn><fn><p>Jiri Bartek and Alexander Fletcher-Sandersj&#x000f6;&#x000f6; shared last authorship.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Publisher's Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>Not applicable.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors'contributions</title><p>SJ, NHF, and AFS designed the study. SJ, NHF, AB, and HJ collected the data. AFS performed the statistical analysis. All authors contributed to data interpretation. SJ, NHF, and AFS drafted the manuscript, and all authors reviewed and approved the final version. JB and AFS supervised the study.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>Open access funding provided by Karolinska Institute.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The datasets used and/or analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par45">The study was approved by the regional ethical review board (EPN 2017/247 and EPN 2013/591&#x02013;31/1), who waived the need for informed consent.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par46">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bartek</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sj&#x000e5;vik</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kristiansson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>St&#x000e5;hl</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Fornebo</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>F&#x000f6;rander</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Jakola</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Predictors of recurrence and complications after chronic subdural hematoma surgery: a population-Based Study</article-title><source>World Neurosurg</source><year>2017</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>609</fpage><lpage>614</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.wneu.2017.07.044</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28735129</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Bartek J, Sj&#x000e5;vik K, Kristiansson H, St&#x000e5;hl F, Fornebo I, F&#x000f6;rander P, Jakola AS (2017) Predictors of recurrence and complications after chronic subdural hematoma surgery: a population-Based Study. World Neurosurg 106:609&#x02013;614<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28735129</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bartley</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartek</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jakola</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Sundblom</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>F&#x000e4;lt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>F&#x000f6;rander</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Marklund</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Tisell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of Irrigation fluid temperature on recurrence in the evacuation of chronic subdural hematoma: a randomized clinical trial</article-title><source>JAMA Neurol</source><year>2023</year><volume>80</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>58</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamaneurol.2022.4133</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36409480</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Bartley A, Bartek J, Jakola AS, Sundblom J, F&#x000e4;lt M, F&#x000f6;rander P, Marklund N, Tisell M (2023) Effect of Irrigation fluid temperature on recurrence in the evacuation of chronic subdural hematoma: a randomized clinical trial. JAMA Neurol 80(1):58&#x02013;63<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36409480</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>DYC</given-names></name><name><surname>Woo</surname><given-names>PYM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mak</surname><given-names>CHK</given-names></name><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>ACH</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>CCH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>NMW</given-names></name><name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>SCP</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>TFD</given-names></name><name><surname>Poon</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of subdural drain for chronic subdural haematoma? A 4-year multi-centre observational study of 302 cases</article-title><source>J Clin Neurosci</source><year>2017</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jocn.2016.10.039</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27914805</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Chan DYC, Woo PYM, Mak CHK, Chu ACH, Li CCH, Ko NMW, Ng SCP, Sun TFD, Poon WS (2017) Use of subdural drain for chronic subdural haematoma? A 4-year multi-centre observational study of 302 cases. J Clin Neurosci 36:27&#x02013;30<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27914805</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Critchley</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Strachan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Postoperative subdural empyema caused by Propionibacterium acnes&#x02013;a report of two cases</article-title><source>Br J Neurosurg</source><year>1996</year><volume>10</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>321</fpage><lpage>323</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/02688699650040241</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8799549</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Critchley G, Strachan R (1996) Postoperative subdural empyema caused by Propionibacterium acnes&#x02013;a report of two cases. Br J Neurosurg 10(3):321&#x02013;323<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8799549</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dabdoub</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Adorno</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name><name><surname>Urbano</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Silveira</surname><given-names>EN</given-names></name><name><surname>Orlandi</surname><given-names>BMM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Review of the Management of Infected Subdural Hematoma</article-title><source>World Neurosurg</source><year>2016</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>663.e1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.wneu.2015.11.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26585725</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Dabdoub CB, Adorno JO, Urbano J, Silveira EN, Orlandi BMM (2016) Review of the Management of Infected Subdural Hematoma. World Neurosurg 87:663.e1&#x02013;8<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26585725</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Mountoure</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Shabani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gelsomino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Janich</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Kurpad S (2016) Intracranial subdural empyema mimicking a recurrent chronic subdural hematoma</article-title><source>J Surg Case Rep</source><year>2016</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>rjw158</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jscr/rjw158</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Doan N, Patel M, Nguyen HS, Mountoure A, Shabani S, Gelsomino M, Janich K (2016) Kurpad S (2016) Intracranial subdural empyema mimicking a recurrent chronic subdural hematoma. J Surg Case Rep 9:rjw158</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>El Ouadih</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Vernhes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mulliez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Berton</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Al Gahatany</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Traore</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Khalil</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemaire</surname><given-names>J-J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Postoperative empyema following chronic subdural hematoma surgery: clinically based medicine</article-title><source>Neurochirurgie</source><year>2020</year><volume>66</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>365</fpage><lpage>368</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuchi.2020.06.132</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32861684</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">El Ouadih Y, Vernhes J, Mulliez A, Berton Q, Al Gahatany M, Traore O, Khalil T, Lemaire J-J (2020) Postoperative empyema following chronic subdural hematoma surgery: clinically based medicine. Neurochirurgie 66(5):365&#x02013;368<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32861684</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hjortdal Gr&#x000f8;nh&#x000f8;j</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>TSR</given-names></name><name><surname>Miscov</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Optimal drainage time after evacuation of chronic subdural haematoma (DRAIN TIME 2): a multicentre, randomised, multiarm and multistage non-inferiority trial in Denmark</article-title><source>Lancet Neurol</source><year>2024</year><volume>23</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>787</fpage><lpage>796</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1474-4422(24)00175-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38878790</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Hjortdal Gr&#x000f8;nh&#x000f8;j M, Jensen TSR, Miscov R et al (2024) Optimal drainage time after evacuation of chronic subdural haematoma (DRAIN TIME 2): a multicentre, randomised, multiarm and multistage non-inferiority trial in Denmark. Lancet Neurol 23(8):787&#x02013;796<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38878790</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holloway</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilberger</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Jemsek</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Giguere</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibiotic prophylaxis during clean neurosurgery: a large, multicenter study using cefuroxime</article-title><source>Clin Ther</source><year>1996</year><volume>18</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>84</fpage><lpage>94</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0149-2918(96)80181-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8851455</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Holloway KL, Smith KW, Wilberger JE, Jemsek JG, Giguere GC, Collins JJ (1996) Antibiotic prophylaxis during clean neurosurgery: a large, multicenter study using cefuroxime. Clin Ther 18(1):84&#x02013;94<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8851455</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jolayemi</surname><given-names>EO</given-names></name><name><surname>Bankole</surname><given-names>OB</given-names></name><name><surname>Ojo</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Contemporary Management of Intracranial Subdural Empyema: An Institutional Experience</article-title><source>J West Afr College Surg</source><year>2022</year><volume>12</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>56</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/jwas.jwas_127_22</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Jolayemi EO, Bankole OB, Ojo OA et al (2022) Contemporary Management of Intracranial Subdural Empyema: An Institutional Experience. J West Afr College Surg 12(3):56</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kanazawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Karatsu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuramae</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishihara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Postoperative infected organised subdural haematoma that necessitated wide craniotomy</article-title><source>BMJ Case Rep</source><year>2021</year><volume>14</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>e245134</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bcr-2021-245134</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34344662</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Kanazawa T, Karatsu K, Kuramae T, Ishihara M (2021) Postoperative infected organised subdural haematoma that necessitated wide craniotomy. BMJ Case Rep 14(8):e245134<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34344662</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y-S</given-names></name><name><surname>Joo</surname><given-names>S-P</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>D-J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S-H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>T-S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Delayed intracranial subdural empyema following burr hole drainage: Case series and literature review</article-title><source>Medicine (Baltimore)</source><year>2018</year><volume>97</volume><issue>18</issue><fpage>e0664</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000010664</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29718890</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Kim Y-S, Joo S-P, Song D-J, Kim S-H, Kim T-S (2018) Delayed intracranial subdural empyema following burr hole drainage: Case series and literature review. Medicine (Baltimore) 97(18):e0664<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29718890</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nayil</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramzan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sajad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zahoor</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nizami</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Laharwal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirmani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhat</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Subdural hematomas: an analysis of 1181 Kashmiri patients</article-title><source>World Neurosurg</source><year>2012</year><volume>77</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>103</fpage><lpage>110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.wneu.2011.06.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22405391</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Nayil K, Ramzan A, Sajad A, Zahoor S, Wani A, Nizami F, Laharwal M, Kirmani A, Bhat R (2012) Subdural hematomas: an analysis of 1181 Kashmiri patients. World Neurosurg 77(1):103&#x02013;110<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22405391</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nouri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gondar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaller</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Meling</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chronic Subdural Hematoma (cSDH): A review of the current state of the art</article-title><source>Brain Spine</source><year>2021</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>100300</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bas.2021.100300</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36247395</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Nouri A, Gondar R, Schaller K, Meling T (2021) Chronic Subdural Hematoma (cSDH): A review of the current state of the art. Brain Spine 1:100300<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36247395</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raj</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Tommiska</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Koivisto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Burr-hole drainage with or without irrigation for chronic subdural haematoma (FINISH): a Finnish, nationwide, parallel-group, multicentre, randomised, controlled, non-inferiority trial</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2024</year><volume>403</volume><issue>10446</issue><fpage>2798</fpage><lpage>2806</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(24)00686-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38852600</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Raj R, Tommiska P, Koivisto T et al (2024) Burr-hole drainage with or without irrigation for chronic subdural haematoma (FINISH): a Finnish, nationwide, parallel-group, multicentre, randomised, controlled, non-inferiority trial. Lancet 403(10446):2798&#x02013;2806<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38852600</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rauhala</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hel&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Huhtala</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Heikkil&#x000e4;</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Iverson</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Niskakangas</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x000d6;hman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Luoto</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chronic subdural hematoma-incidence, complications, and financial impact</article-title><source>Acta Neurochir (Wien)</source><year>2020</year><volume>162</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>2033</fpage><lpage>2043</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00701-020-04398-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32524244</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Rauhala M, Hel&#x000e9;n P, Huhtala H, Heikkil&#x000e4; P, Iverson GL, Niskakangas T, &#x000d6;hman J, Luoto TM (2020) Chronic subdural hematoma-incidence, complications, and financial impact. Acta Neurochir (Wien) 162(9):2033&#x02013;2043<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32524244</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rohde</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Graf</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hassler</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Complications of burr-hole craniostomy and closed-system drainage for chronic subdural hematomas: a retrospective analysis of 376 patients</article-title><source>Neurosurg Rev</source><year>2002</year><volume>25</volume><issue>1&#x02013;2</issue><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>94</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s101430100182</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11954771</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Rohde V, Graf G, Hassler W (2002) Complications of burr-hole craniostomy and closed-system drainage for chronic subdural hematomas: a retrospective analysis of 376 patients. Neurosurg Rev 25(1&#x02013;2):89&#x02013;94<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11954771</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Skyrman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartek</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Haghighi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fornebo</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Skoglund</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Jakola</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>von Vogelsang</surname><given-names>A-C</given-names></name><name><surname>F&#x000f6;rander</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preoperative antibiotic prophylaxis regimen in brain tumour surgery in Sweden: a quasi-experimental study</article-title><source>Acta Neurochir (Wien)</source><year>2020</year><volume>162</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>2849</fpage><lpage>2856</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00701-020-04309-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32383013</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Skyrman S, Bartek J, Haghighi M, Fornebo I, Skoglund T, Jakola AS, von Vogelsang A-C, F&#x000f6;rander P (2020) Preoperative antibiotic prophylaxis regimen in brain tumour surgery in Sweden: a quasi-experimental study. Acta Neurochir (Wien) 162(11):2849&#x02013;2856<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32383013</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tamai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ichinose</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Murakami</surname><given-names>K-I</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueno</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Munemoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Morphological characteristics of infected subdural hematoma: comparison with images of chronic subdural hematoma</article-title><source>Clin Neurol Neurosurg</source><year>2020</year><volume>194</volume><fpage>105831</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clineuro.2020.105831</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32294578</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Tamai S, Watanabe T, Ichinose T, Murakami K-I, Ueno M, Munemoto S, Nakada M, Hayashi Y (2020) Morphological characteristics of infected subdural hematoma: comparison with images of chronic subdural hematoma. Clin Neurol Neurosurg 194:105831<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32294578</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Subdural empyema complicated after trepanation and drainage of chronic subdural hematoma: a case report</article-title><source>Medicine</source><year>2019</year><volume>98</volume><issue>52</issue><fpage>e18587</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000018587</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31876760</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">Xue H, Zhang W, Shi L, Zhang Y, Yu B, Yang H (2019) Subdural empyema complicated after trepanation and drainage of chronic subdural hematoma: a case report. Medicine 98(52):e18587<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31876760</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chronic Subdural Hematoma: Epidemiology and Natural History</article-title><source>Neurosurg Clin N Am</source><year>2017</year><volume>28</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>205</fpage><lpage>210</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nec.2016.11.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28325454</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Yang W, Huang J (2017) Chronic Subdural Hematoma: Epidemiology and Natural History. Neurosurg Clin N Am 28(2):205&#x02013;210<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28325454</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article>