<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Clin Invest</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Clin Invest</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">J Clin Invest</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Journal of Clinical Investigation</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0021-9738</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1558-8238</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Society for Clinical Investigation</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39589822</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11785923</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">182235</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI182235</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>AAV9/<italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic> gene therapy rescues abnormal EEG patterns and cognitive behavioral deficiencies in <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> mice</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Weirui</given-names></name><email>weirui.guo@utsouthwestern.edu</email><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rioux</surname><given-names>Matthew</given-names></name><email>Matthew.Rioux@UTSouthwestern.edu</email><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shaffo</surname><given-names>Frances</given-names></name><email>frances.shaffo@gmail.com</email><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Yuhui</given-names></name><email>Yuhui.Hu@UTSouthwestern.edu</email><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0583-1351</contrib-id><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Ze</given-names></name><email>ze.yu@utsouthwestern.edu</email><xref rid="A2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1838-0502</contrib-id><name><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>Chao</given-names></name><email>Chao.Xing@utsouthwestern.edu</email><xref rid="A2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="A3" ref-type="aff">3</xref><xref rid="A4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6240-8621</contrib-id><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>Steven J.</given-names></name><email>steven.gray@utsouthwestern.edu</email><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="A2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="A5" ref-type="aff">5</xref><xref rid="A6" ref-type="aff">6</xref><xref rid="A7" ref-type="aff">7</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Pediatrics,</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>McDermott Center for Human Growth and Development,</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Department of Bioinformatics,</aff><aff id="A4"><label>4</label>O&#x02019;Donnell School of Public Health,</aff><aff id="A5"><label>5</label>Department of Neurology,</aff><aff id="A6"><label>6</label>Department of Molecular Biology, and</aff><aff id="A7"><label>7</label>O&#x02019;Donnell Brain Institute, University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center, Dallas, Texas, USA.</aff><author-notes><corresp>Address correspondence to: Steven J. Gray, Department of Pediatrics, University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center, Room NA2.508, 6000 Harry Hines Blvd., Dallas, TX 75390. Phone: 214.648.0670; Email: <email>Steven.Gray@UTSouthwestern.edu</email>.</corresp><fn><p><bold>Authorship note:</bold> WG and MR contributed equally to this work and are co&#x02013;first authors.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2024-11-26T12:00:00-0500"><day>26</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2025-02-03T12:00:00-0500"><day>3</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>26</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><!--PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>.--><volume>135</volume><issue>3</issue><elocation-id>e182235</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>25</day><month>4</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2024, Guo et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Guo et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ext-link-type="uri">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="https://www.jci.org/articles/view/182235">This article is available online at https://www.jci.org/articles/view/182235</self-uri><abstract><p>The solute carrier family 6 member 1 (<italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic>) gene encodes the &#x003b3;-aminobutyric acid (GABA) transporter GAT-1, the deficiency of which is associated with infantile encephalopathy with intellectual disability. We designed 2 AAV9 vectors, with either the JeT or MeP promoter, and conducted preclinical gene therapy studies using heterozygous and homozygous <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic>-KO mice at different developmental ages and various routes of administration. Neonatal intracerebroventricular administration of either vector resulted in significantly normalized EEG patterns in <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1<sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup></italic> or <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1<sup>+/&#x02013;</sup></italic> mice as well as improvement in several behavioral phenotypes of <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1<sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup></italic> mice. However, some mortality and adverse effects were observed in neonatal-treated mice. Intrathecal administration of either vector at P5 normalized EEG patterns in <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1<sup>+/&#x02013;</sup></italic> mice, but in <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1<sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup></italic> mice, the treatment only rescued nest building without impact on EEG. Both vectors were well tolerated in all mice treated at P5 or later (including WT mice), up to 1 year after injection. Overall, our data demonstrate compelling efficacy when mice are treated at an early development age. We also identified that outside of the neonatal treatment window, the severe homozygous KO model is more refractory to treatment, whereas our treatments in the heterozygous mice, which genotypically match human patients, have resulted in stronger benefits.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="graphical"><p>
<graphic xlink:href="jci-135-182235-g043.jpg" position="float"/>
</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="toc"><p>AAV9/<italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic> gene therapy rescues abnormal EEG patterns and cognitive behavioral deficiencies in <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic>-/- mice</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="specialties"><kwd>Therapeutics</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="keywords"><kwd>Neurological disorders</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>Taysha Gene Therapies</funding-source><award-id>NA</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source>SLC6A1 Connect</funding-source><award-id>NA</award-id></award-group></funding-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>The solute carrier family 6 member 1 (<italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic>) related disorders constitute a group of rare neurodevelopmental syndromes with early childhood onset of phenotypes, featuring epilepsy, intellectual disability, movement disorders, and behavior resembling autism spectrum disorder (ASD) (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). Initially identified in 2015 within a group of patients with Doose syndrome, the range of phenotypes linked to <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic>-related disorders has since broadened. The estimated prevalence of these disorders is approximately 1 in 38,000 births (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>).</p><p><italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic>-related disorders typically result from a pathogenic genetic variant in 1 copy of the <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic> gene, which encodes the voltage-dependent &#x003b3;-aminobutyric acid (GABA) transporter type 1 (GAT-1). GAT-1 is responsible for GABA reuptake from presynaptic nerve terminals as well as glial cells (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). At present, there are more than 200 known pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic>, with the majority being de novo mutations (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). The mechanisms through which these pathogenic variants lead to clinical manifestations are not well understood. The anticipated molecular mechanism involves the loss of function resulting in haploinsufficiency (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>).</p><p>Similar to other neurodevelopmental disorders, <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic>-related disorders currently lack effective treatments. The available interventions primarily focus on symptom control, involving the administration of antiseizure medications, supportive developmental therapies, and medications aimed at mitigating the impact of symptoms (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). Notably, there is no observed correlation between seizure control and cognitive behavioral outcomes (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>).</p><p>Over the past 20 years, there has been substantial exploration of viral vector-based gene therapy as a potential treatment for genetic disorders. In numerous studies, the recombinant adeno-associated viral vector type 9 (AAV9) has consistently demonstrated both safety and efficacy as a vehicle for delivering transgenic cargo to the central nervous system (CNS) (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). AAV9 has become the preferred choice for CNS gene delivery due to its capacity to facilitate broad transgene expression across the CNS tissues of rodents and larger animal models following injection in the cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). Moreover, intrathecal AAV9 gene therapy is currently being employed in active clinical trials for conditions such as giant axonal neuropathy, CLN7 Batten disease, Rett syndrome, and spastic paraplegia 50 (SPG50) disease, among others (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>).</p><p>In this research, we assessed and selected the most suitable mouse model from <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic>-KO and patient variant knockin (KI) mice to recapitulate the disease symptoms of <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic>-related disorders observed in humans. We then designed and tested AAV9 vectors carrying the human <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic>) transgene in the KO mouse model to evaluate the efficacy and safety of AAV9/<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> gene transfer across different development ages.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>The constitutive Slc6a1-KO mouse model and 2 KI mouse models of human patient variants S295L and A288V similarly recapitulate many features of human SLC6A1-related disorders.</title><p>The <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic> point missense mutations S295L and A288V have been discovered in human <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic> patients with epilepsy, intellectual disability, and neurodevelopmental disorders (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). Both missense mutations were previously characterized in vitro at the molecular level. The S295L variant displayed a complete loss of GABA uptake function and endoplasmic reticulum&#x02013;associated degradation, while the A288V variant displayed a partial loss of GABA reuptake function in cultured cells (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). To consider the suitability of the S295L and A288V missense variants as animal models of <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic>-related disorders for gene-replacement therapy, we conducted detailed phenotyping of 2 transgenic mouse lines carrying each variant (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). We compared the body weight (BW), behavior, and EEG profile of each variant to the previously characterized B6.129S1 KO mouse (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>).</p><p>We measured the phenotypes of heterozygous and homozygous S295L and A288V KI mouse models, in parallel with the constitutive heterozygous <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>+/&#x02013;</sup> and homozygous <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> KO (null) mouse models that lacked 1 or 2 copies of the Slc6a1 gene. Since abnormal EEG readings, including epileptiform discharges and seizures, are a hallmark of <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic>-related disorders, we used 48-hour EEG telemetry recordings of the mouse brain to monitor epileptiform activities and compare the 3 allelic models. The heterozygous <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>S295L/+</sup>, <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>A288V/+</sup>, and <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>+/&#x02013;</sup> mice all showed a similar epileptic seizure phenotype with abundant 3&#x02013;7 Hz and low amplitude polyspike trains (as shown in <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1, A and B</xref>, and <xref rid="sd" ref-type="sec">Supplemental Figure 1</xref>; supplemental material available online with this article; <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1172/JCI182235DS1" ext-link-type="uri">https://doi.org/10.1172/JCI182235DS1</ext-link>). The homozygous <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>S295L/S295L</sup>, <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>A288V/A288V</sup>, and <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> mice all showed a similarly stronger epileptic seizure phenotype, with abundant 3&#x02013;7 Hz polyspike trains, higher spike amplitude, and much longer duration compared with the heterozygous mice (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1, A and B</xref>, and <xref rid="sd" ref-type="sec">Supplemental Figure 1</xref>). These polyspike trains are rarely observed in WT mice, though some exhibited low-amplitude spike trains with a very short duration (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1, A&#x02013;C</xref>, and <xref rid="sd" ref-type="sec">Supplemental Figure 1</xref>). In <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> mice, polyspike trains are often accompanied by a cessation of muscle activity, which is consistent with typical absence seizures (<xref rid="sd" ref-type="sec">Supplemental Video 1</xref>). We further investigated the motor and cognitive phenotypes across the 3 mouse models (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref> and <xref rid="sd" ref-type="sec">Supplemental Figure 2</xref>). Similar to the <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>+/&#x02013;</sup> mice, <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>S295L/+</sup> and <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>A288V/+</sup> mice did not show any statistically significant abnormal phenotypes compared with WT controls. However, in some tests, such as nest building and rotarod, the heterozygous mice had scores that trended lower than WT, suggesting possible mild phenotypes that could emerge with larger sample sizes. Mice homozygous for the S295L or A288V alleles phenocopied each other and the <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> KO mice in BW, nest building, fear conditioning, and open-field tests (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1, D&#x02013;F</xref>). There were some differences in the models with respect to the distance traveled in open-field testing, rotarod, and hindlimb clasping. Compared with the <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> KO mice, the <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>S295L/S295L</sup> KI mice had slightly better rotarod performance and lacked a significant reduction in distance traveled in the open-field test (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1H</xref> and <xref rid="sd" ref-type="sec">Supplemental Figure 2B</xref>). Interestingly, the partial loss of GABA uptake function (~25% of WT function, in vitro measured in cultured cells; ref. <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>) in <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>A288V/A288V</sup> mice did not cause significant impairment in rotarod testing or induce a hind limb clasping phenotype (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1, G&#x02013;I</xref>, and <xref rid="sd" ref-type="sec">Supplemental Figure 2C</xref>). Taken together, all 3 homozygous mouse models (<italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup>, <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>S295L/S295L</sup>, and <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>A288V/A288V</sup>) develop key behavior phenotypes that are consistent with the human <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic> disorders. Additionally, <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup>, <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>S295L/S295L</sup>, and <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>A288V/A288V</sup> displayed nearly identical EEG phenotypes. Due to the subtle difference of behavioral phenotypes in the homozygous mice, we have ranked the models, in order of severity (most to least) as <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic> KO, S295L KI, and A288V KI (<xref rid="sd" ref-type="sec">Supplemental Table 1</xref>). Overall, the heterozygous <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>+/&#x02013;</sup> KO and homozygous <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> KO mice showed the most consistent and robust phenotypes and were thus chosen as the primary models for our gene replacement studies.</p></sec><sec><title>AAV9/hSLC6A1 gene therapy via neonatal intracerebroventricular injection rescues brain epilepsy and key behavioral phenotypes in Slc6a1 heterozygous and homozygous KO mice.</title><p>To test our hypothesis that broad CNS delivery of the human <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic> gene (<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic>) using AAV9 can provide an effective treatment and long-term therapeutic benefit for SLC6A1-related disorders, we designed 2 AAV9 vectors carrying <italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> driven by 2 different promoters and conducted preclinical gene-therapy studies using heterozygous (<italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>+/&#x02013;</sup>) and homozygous (<italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup>) KO mice. One promoter is a weak universal promoter (JeT) (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>), whereas the other is a predominantly neuronal promoter (MeP229) (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>) (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A</xref>). The 2 AAV9/<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> vectors were tested separately via bilateral intracerebroventricular (ICV) injection into neonatal P1 <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>+/&#x02013;</sup> and <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> mice (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A</xref>). We first investigated whether AAV9/<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> gene therapy could rescue the epileptic seizure phenotype previously characterized in <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>+/&#x02013;</sup> and <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> KO mice, which is a common feature of human <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic>-related disorders. Neonatal ICV administration of both JeT and MeP vectors (3 &#x000d7; 10<sup>11</sup> vg per mouse) resulted in markedly reduced seizures, assessed by EEG in both <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>+/&#x02013;</sup> and <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> mice. In <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>+/&#x02013;</sup> mice, both AAV9/MeP-<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> and AAV9/JeT-<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> reduced the duration of EEG spike trains to the extent that they were not significantly different from normal WT levels (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2, B and C</xref>). In <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> mice, the AAV9/MeP-<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> vector showed partial reduction of the EEG spike train duration to approximately 17%. The AAV9/JeT-<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> vector showed a greater degree of rescue in 3 treated <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> KO mice (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2, B and D</xref>). The AAV9/MeP-hSLC6A1 vector treatment in neonatal mice also ameliorated the fear conditioning, nest building, rotarod performance, and hind limb clasping phenotypes in <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> KO mice. However, this treatment did not significantly improve the reduced BW or the center duration of open-field testing in <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> KO mice (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2, E&#x02013;J</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>+/&#x02013;</sup> mice consistently showed slightly decreased (but not significant) rotarod performance relative to WT littermates. Although none of the differences between WT mice, treated <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>+/&#x02013;</sup> mice, and untreated <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>+/&#x02013;</sup> mice were significant, we observed an apparent normalization of rotarod performance in AAV9/<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> ICV-treated <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>+/&#x02013;</sup> mice (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2J</xref>). Although the ICV treatment did not affect the aggregated behavioral phenotypes we assessed in the <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>+/&#x02013;</sup> mice, we did observe some adverse events (including death) across all of our neonatal ICV vector treatment groups. The JeT vector resulted in approximately 50% early mortality and some sporadic adverse effects while the MeP229 vector resulted in 17% early mortality also with some sporadic adverse effects (<xref rid="sd" ref-type="sec">Supplemental Table 2</xref>). Due to the high mortality rate of mice treated with the JeT vector design, enrollment of this arm of the study was ended prematurely, and no behavioral tests were conducted on these mice.</p><p>We investigated the pattern of <italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> transgene expression in <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>+/&#x02013;</sup> mouse brain slices using in situ RNAscope. The greatest expression was seen in the neocortex and hippocampus, with less expression in the midbrain and cerebellum. The vector with the JeT promoter showed the highest transduction rates, with about 57% of cells in the neocortex, approximately 28% of cells in the hippocampus, and approximately 21% of cells in the thalamus expressing the <italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> mRNA. The vector with the MeP229 promoter showed a transduction rate of about 35% of cells in the neocortex, approximately 22% of cells in the hippocampus, and approximately 3% of cells in the thalamus (<xref rid="sd" ref-type="sec">Supplemental Figure 3</xref>). To explore how the vector-mediated expression compared with the endogenous <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic> expression pattern, we use a duplexed RNAscope assay to measure the ratio of endogenous <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic>-positive cells among the viral transduced cells in each mouse brain area (<xref rid="sd" ref-type="sec">Supplemental Figure 3F</xref>). Overall, AAV9/<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> treatment of neonatal mice showed a strong attenuation of seizure deficits in heterozygous <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>+/&#x02013;</sup> mice and both seizure and behavioral deficits in homozygous <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> KO mice. These results provide early proof-of-concept evidence for possible benefits from AAV9/<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> treatment. However, concerning adverse effects (including mortality) were apparent with both vector designs and strongest in the JeT promoter construct.</p></sec><sec><title>Intrathecal administration of AAV9/hSLC6A1 to P5 mice rescues abnormal EEG patterns in heterozygous Slc6a1<sup>+/&#x02013;</sup> mice and nest-building behavior in homozygous Slc6a1<sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> KO mice, but fails to rescue brain EEG epilepsy in Slc6a1<sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> KO mice.</title><p>The neonatal mouse treatment age is earlier than would be practical to model a human treatment, so we do not view the neonatal ICV approach as having direct clinical relevance. To explore the translational relevance of the JeT or MeP vector designs with AAV9, we tested both vectors by intrathecal (i.t.) lumbar puncture in heterozygous and homozygous <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic>-KO mice at P5 (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3A</xref>). i.t. administration of either AAV9/MeP229-<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> or AAV9/JeT-<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> (5.6 &#x000d7; 10<sup>11</sup> vg or 1.12 &#x000d7; 10<sup>12</sup> vg for each) to P5 <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>+/&#x02013;</sup> mice significantly reduced seizures assessed via telemetry EEG recording (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3, B and C</xref>). The MeP vector at the low dose (5.6 &#x000d7; 10<sup>11</sup> vg) and JeT vector at the high dose (1.12 &#x000d7; 10<sup>12</sup> vg) showed the greatest normalization of the EEG patterns, equivalent to WT. However, the severe EEG seizure phenotype in <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> KO mice was not rescued by either vector construct regardless of dose (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3, B and D</xref>). However, both vectors normalized nest-building behavioral deficits in <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> KO mice compared with vehicle-treated <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>+/&#x02013;</sup> mice (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3E</xref>). Neither vector significantly improved the reduced BW, fear conditioning, center duration of open field, rotarod performance, or the hind limb clasping phenotype in <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> KO mice (<xref rid="sd" ref-type="sec">Supplemental Figure 4</xref>), However, in rotarod tests, the JeT vector at a low dose (5.6 &#x000d7; 10<sup>11</sup> vg) showed a trend toward increasing rotarod performance in treated <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> KO mice, but this was not observed in the high-dose JeT treatment group (<xref rid="sd" ref-type="sec">Supplemental Figure 4</xref>, F and G). We did not observe a dose response within the treatment groups in any of the behavioral tests, except for the nest-building tests of the MeP treatment groups (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3E</xref>). Neither the MeP nor the JeT vector caused early mortality or adverse effects after i.t. administration at P5 (<xref rid="sd" ref-type="sec">Supplemental Table 3</xref>). We investigated the expression pattern of <italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> in the <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>+/&#x02013;</sup> mouse brain cortex using in situ RNAscope. In general, the JeT vector showed higher transduction rates (~12% of cells at 5.6 &#x000d7; 10<sup>11</sup> vg dose, ~19% at 1.12 &#x000d7; 10<sup>12</sup> vg) than the MeP vector (~9% of cells at 5.6 &#x000d7; 10<sup>11</sup> vg dose, ~14% at 1.12 &#x000d7; 10<sup>12</sup> vg) in the brain cortex (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3, F and G</xref>). We measured the ratio of endogenous <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic>-positive cells among the viral transfected cells (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3H</xref>). Analyzing the MeP vector at the 5.6 &#x000d7; 10<sup>11</sup> vg dose, approximately 33% of cells expressing the <italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> transgene overlapped with endogenous murine <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">mSlc6a1</italic>) expression. The JeT vector at the 5.6 &#x000d7; 10<sup>11</sup> vg dose showed only approximately 15% of cells expressing the <italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> transgene overlapping with <italic toggle="yes">mSlc6a1</italic> expression. These results suggest that, of the 2 vector constructs, the selective expression pattern mediated by the MeP229 promoter more closely matched the endogenous <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic> expression pattern. However, the JeT promoter confers expression to a greater overall number of cells, which appears to mediate an overall more potent effect, in terms of both efficacy and adverse effects.</p></sec><sec><title>i.t. administration of AAV9/hSLC6A1 to P10 or P28 Slc6a1<sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> KO mice showed weak or no behavioral improvements.</title><p>To explore the translational relevance of the JeT or MeP vector designs with AAV9, we tested both vectors by i.t. administration in <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> KO mice at P10 and P28 (7.0 &#x000d7; 10<sup>11</sup> vg for AAV9/MeP-hSLC6A1; 7.5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>11</sup> vg for AAV9/JeT-<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic>) (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4A</xref>). Neither reduced <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> KO seizures as assessed via telemetry EEG recording (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4B</xref>). Mice treated at P10 via i.t. administration with the JeT vector showed improvement in nest building and modest but statistically nonsignificant improvement in rotarod performance. However, there was no apparent change for any other behavioral measures (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4, C&#x02013;F</xref>, and <xref rid="sd" ref-type="sec">Supplemental Figure 5</xref>). We did not observe any significant improvement in any behavioral tests in P10 i.t. treated mice with the MeP vector (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4, C&#x02013;F</xref>, and <xref rid="sd" ref-type="sec">Supplemental Figure 5</xref>). Neither the JeT nor the MeP vector P28 treated mice showed any improvement in EEG or behavior phenotypes (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4, C&#x02013;F</xref>, and <xref rid="sd" ref-type="sec">Supplemental Figure 5</xref>). To increase the number of cells transduced at P10 via i.t. administration, we performed repeated dosing of the MeP vector in a subset of <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> KO mice. Mice were given 2 subsequent i.t. injections of 1.1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>12</sup> vg 2 hours apart (2.2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>12</sup> vg total dose). A single i.t. injection (1.1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>12</sup> vg total dose) group was included as a control. The highest dose (2.2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>12</sup> vg) of the MeP vector via double i.t. administration at P10 still failed to provide any EEG pattern or behavioral benefit to <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> KO mice (<xref rid="sd" ref-type="sec">Supplemental Figure 6</xref>). Both AAV9/MeP-<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> and AAV9/JeT-<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> vectors delivered via i.t. administration at P10 and P28 were well tolerated even up to a dose of 2.2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>12</sup> vg of the MeP vector at P10, with no adverse effects observed across all treated animals (<xref rid="sd" ref-type="sec">Supplemental Table 3</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>AAV-PHP.eB/MeP-hSLC6A1 gene therapy initiated at P23 does not rescue abnormal EEG patterns or behavioral phenotypes in heterozygous or homozygous Slc6a1 KO mice.</title><p>It is not clear whether the efficacy seen in the neonatal ICV treated or P5 i.t. treated mice was due to the higher transduction efficiency in neocortex and hippocampus at this age and route of administration or whether the earlier intervention was the main driver of the treatment efficacy. To begin to discriminate between these possibilities, the MeP229-<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> construct was packaged into the PHP.eB viral capsid/vector to be dosed into approximately P23 mice by an i.v. injection route. While PHP.eB is not directly translatable to primates, it can achieve substantially higher transduction than AAV9 following i.v. administration at an older age in mice (<xref rid="sd" ref-type="sec">Supplemental Figure 7</xref>; ref. <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). We evaluated the dose-responsive safety and efficacy of PHP.eB/MeP229-<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> in <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>+/&#x02013;</sup> and <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> KO mice at P23 to determine if the disease is rescuable at that older age (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5A</xref>). All doses of the PHP.eB/<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> vector (2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>10</sup>, 2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>11</sup>, or 1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>12</sup> vg per mouse) failed to reduce abnormal EEG patterns in either <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>+/&#x02013;</sup> or <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> KO mice (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5, B&#x02013;D</xref>). Additionally, mice treated with the 2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>10</sup> or 2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>11</sup> vg doses only showed a moderate nest-building behavioral improvement (the 1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>12</sup> vg group was not assessed for behavioral rescue) (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5, E&#x02013;J</xref>). Similar to P28 i.t. treatment data, P23 i.v. administration of the PHP.eB/MeP-hSLC6A1 vector failed to provide any benefit to <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> KO mice. AAV-PHP.eB/MeP-<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> treatment at P23 was well tolerated, with no adverse effects observed in any of the i.v.-treated animals (<xref rid="sd" ref-type="sec">Supplemental Table 3</xref>). We used the in situ RNAscope assay to assess the expression pattern of human <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic> transgene via AAV-PHP.eB IV administration at different doses in P23 WT mice. Compared with AAV9/MeP-<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> vector i.v. administration, the AAV-PHP.eB/MeP-<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> vector showed much greater transgene expression, evenly distributed throughout the mouse brain. The 2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>11</sup> vg dose of PHP.eB/MeP-<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> vector showed an approximately 4%&#x02013;5% overall cell transduction rate in the neocortex, hippocampus, and thalamus brain regions. The highest dose (1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>12</sup> vg) showed an approximately 13% cellular transduction rate across the brain including the neocortex, hippocampus, and thalamus. Of note, compared with the neonatal ICV injections, the PHP.eB/MeP vector achieved higher transduction rates in regions outside of the neocortex and hippocampus, such as the cerebellum. We found that 20% of the PHP.eB/MeP-<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> transfected cells were positive for endogenous murine <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic> expression, which is similar to what we found after neonatal ICV administration with AAV9. Overall, i.v. administration of AAV-PHP.eB/MeP-<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> at P23 conferred more even transgene expression throughout the whole brain; however, no benefits were seen aside from a modest normalization of nest building.</p></sec><sec><title>i.t. administration of AAV9/JeT-hSLC6A1 or AAV9/MeP-hSLC6A1 is safe and well tolerated in WT mice.</title><p>Overexpression of GAT1 in transgenic mice has previously been shown to result in cognitive impairment, increased susceptibility to seizures, and impaired reproduction (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). In our studies, neonatal ICV administration of either AAV9/<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> vector design caused adverse effects in heterozygous and homozygous <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic>-KO mice, whereas administration at older ages by i.t. was well tolerated. To further evaluate the safety of the MeP and the JeT AAV9/<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> vectors, WT C57BL/6J mice were i.t. injected with vehicle, AAV9/JeT-<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> vector (1.75 &#x000d7; 10<sup>11</sup> vg [low] or 7.0 &#x000d7; 10<sup>11</sup> vg [high] doses), or AAV9/MeP-<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> vector (1.88 &#x000d7; 10<sup>11</sup> vg [low] or 7.5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>11</sup> vg [high] doses) at P28 in a pilot safety study (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6A</xref>). The mice were monitored after injection for up to 1 year for BW, survival, body condition, blood chemistry, and comprehensive postmortem histopathology. There were no significant differences in BW between groups in male or female mice at any point of assessment and any dose tested (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6, B and C</xref>). Serum from mice taken at 3 weeks after dosing was analyzed for blood biochemistry, including total bilirubin (TBIL), blood urea nitrogen (BUN), albumin (ALB), creatine kinase (CK), and aspartate aminotransferase (AST). None of the above showed significant changes induced by either vector, with the exception of a reduction in bilirubin levels observed in the MeP high-dose&#x02013;treated WT mice (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6, D&#x02013;H</xref>). Likewise, there were no treatment-related signs of body condition change across the duration of the study in any group. Given the findings from neonatal treatment that the JeT construct posed a greater safety concern (<xref rid="sd" ref-type="sec">Supplemental Table 2</xref>), tissues from all JeT-injected WT mice were evaluated for histopathology abnormalities. We have included all findings in <xref rid="sd" ref-type="sec">Supplemental Table 3</xref> and <xref rid="sd" ref-type="sec">Supplemental Data Set 1</xref>, which, in summary, only identified findings typical in aged mice, with no relation to treatment. In another pilot toxicity study, WT C57BL/6J mice were i.t. injected with vehicle, AAV9/JeT-<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> vector, or AAV9/<italic toggle="yes">MeP-hSLC6A1</italic> vector at an earlier age (P10). The mice were monitored after injection for up to 6 months for BW, survival, body condition, and histopathology abnormalities (JeT only) (<xref rid="sd" ref-type="sec">Supplemental Figure 8A</xref> and <xref rid="sd" ref-type="sec">Supplemental Data Set 1</xref>). The P10 i.t. administration also did not affect any of the parameters listed in WT mice (<xref rid="sd" ref-type="sec">Supplemental Figure 8</xref>, B and C). Single-cell RNA-Seq was used to assess the JeT vector-induced expression of the human <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic> transgene compared with the endogenous murine <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic> levels in WT mice from this P10 i.t. safety study. The uniform manifold approximation and projection (UMAP) plot displays the results of unbiased clustering of 27,375 single-cell nuclei from mouse brain cortex tissue following high-dose (7.5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>11</sup> vg) i.t. treatment of the AAV9/JeT-<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> vector at P10 (<xref rid="sd" ref-type="sec">Supplemental Figure 8D</xref>). The mouse endogenous <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic> mRNA expression is selectively enriched in the clusters of GABAergic inhibitory neurons, astrocytes, and oligodendrocyte precursor cells (<xref rid="sd" ref-type="sec">Supplemental Figure 8E</xref> and <xref rid="sd" ref-type="sec">Supplemental Data Set 2</xref>). The JeT promoter&#x02013;driven human <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic> transgene mRNA expression was more evenly distributed throughout all the clusters, consistent with the nonspecific nature of the JeT promoter (<xref rid="sd" ref-type="sec">Supplemental Figure 8F</xref> and <xref rid="sd" ref-type="sec">Supplemental Data Set 2</xref>). There were 57 cells analyzed that had overlapping expression of human and mouse <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic>, allowing for direct comparison of <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic> expression levels in those cells. Of the 57 overlapping cells, compared with the endogenous mouse <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic> expression level, 40 cells had the same level of mRNA expression, in 15 cells, the expression of JeT-<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> was slightly higher, and in 2 cells, the JeT-<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> expression was lower (<xref rid="sd" ref-type="sec">Supplemental Figure 8G</xref>). Whenever the human and murine <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic> levels differed, the fold change was relatively small. Overall, these results demonstrate that the JeT promoter drives mRNA expression in the neocortex, with approximately 20% of cells that normally express <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic>. This leads to about 80% of transduced cells gaining expression of <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic> where it is not normally expressed.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Recombinant AAV9-mediated gene therapy has been widely applied in preclinical and clinical research for the treatment of CNS disorders, often using an i.t. administration route (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). In this study, we have designed an AAV-based treatment strategy that delivers the codon-optimized human <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic> gene under different regulatory promoters (MeP or JeT) to a mouse model of <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic>-related disorders. We demonstrated AAV9/<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> gene therapy has potential as a treatment for <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic>-related disorders, when administered at early development ages.</p><p>At the beginning of our study, there was uncertainty regarding the suitability of available <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic> mouse models and how different <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic> variant alleles might contribute to distinct disease phenotypes. Upon assessing <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic> animal models, we found that the heterozygous <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>A288V/+</sup> KI mice and the heterozygous <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>S295L/+</sup> KI mice showed abnormal EEG phenotypes identical to those of the heterozygous <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>+/&#x02013;</sup> KO mice. Furthermore, as a partial loss-of-function variant, the homozygous <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>A288V/A288V</sup> KI mice showed somewhat milder behavioral phenotypes than the homozygous <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>S295L/S295L</sup> (complete loss of function) and the homozygous <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> null KO mice (<xref rid="sd" ref-type="sec">Supplemental Table 1</xref>). The majority of evidence supports that haploinsufficiency or loss of function of SLC6A1 primarily underlies the phenotypes of <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic> mouse models and human clinical symptoms, rather than gain-of-function or dominant-negative effects. Therefore, the heterozygous and homozygous <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic> KO models are suitable to test an AAV9 gene replacement approach. Additionally, the milder cognitive behavioral and motor phenotypes observed in <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic> A288V homozygous mice suggest that the functional dosage of <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic> critically underlies the pathogenic processes associated with <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic>. The <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic> haploinsufficiency concept is also supported by a recent study that identified more than 200 loss-of-function <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic> variants from patients with ASD without overt epileptic phenotypes (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). The human clinical phenotype includes 2 common domains of symptoms: epilepsy and neuropsychological features affecting cognition and behaviors. EEG abnormalities in human patients are most commonly generalized epileptiform discharges. When available, EEG recordings with seizure semiology data have identified (atypical) absence, atonic, and myoclonic seizures as the dominant types of seizures seen in patients (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). Although the technical limitations of the 2 electrode EEG sensors used in this study prevented us from defining the seizure semiology in <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic> mice, we were able to robustly identify polyspike-wave discharges paired with a cessation of muscle activity, typical of absence seizures. These findings suggest that the <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic> mouse models we tested not only have similar epileptic phenotypes to each other but are characteristically similar to the prevalent epilepsy phenotypes in humans. We concluded that the <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/+</sup> heterozygous mice phenotypically model the clinical epilepsy phenotype of human patients but do not strongly represent the cognitive-behavioral phenotypes observed in human patients (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). On the other hand, the homozygous <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> KO mice phenotypically model severe cognitive-behavioral features seen in human patients, including learning and memory deficits and anxious behaviors, as well as developmental and motor disorders. However, the epilepsy phenotype is much more severe in the homozygous KO mice than in the heterozygous mice (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1, A&#x02013;C</xref>). Our studies evaluated treatment in both models, in an attempt to comprehensively evaluate both behavioral and epilepsy symptoms across the 2 models.</p><p>GABA, acting as the predominant inhibitory neurotransmitter, also plays a crucial role in governing the migration and maturation processes of newly formed neurons throughout the development of the CNS (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). The regulation of GABA reuptake levels through the functioning of the <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic> gene may be implicated throughout critical periods from the embryonic period through adolescence. Therefore, AAV9/<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> gene transfer may variably impact different disease phenotypes if AAV9/<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> is delivered after critical periods of CNS development (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). In our studies, we selected multiple treatment ages (P1, P5, P10, P23, and P28) in an effort to explore the impact of treatment at different developmental ages. Regarding the abnormal EEG phenotypes in heterozygous <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>+/&#x02013;</sup> mice, both neonatal P1 ICV and P5 i.t. treated mice displayed therapeutic benefit (substantially normalized EEG epilepsy patterns) from AAV9/MeP-<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> or AAV9/JeT-<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> treatment (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>). This benefit was not seen in the older P23 treatment groups (P10 and P28 treatment was not tested in heterozygous <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>+/&#x02013;</sup> mice) (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>). For homozygous <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> KO mice (which have more severe EEG phenotypes), neonatal ICV administration effectively rescued the abnormal EEG patterns (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>). However, at P5 and older, the AAV9/<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> treatment failed to show any benefit on the EEG pattern. One might infer that in homozygous KO mice, the pathogenic epileptic circuits developed during the early development period are different from those in heterozygous mice. Our studies indicate that it is ineffective to rescue them by gene replacement outside of this period. For behavioral phenotypes in homozygous KO mice, multiple behaviors were ameliorated with gene-therapy treatment from P1 to P5. However, in older KO mice (P10 and P23 treatments), efficacy is much lower, with only nest-building deficiency being ameliorated (<xref rid="sd" ref-type="sec">Supplemental Table 4</xref>). Considering the different therapeutic response between <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>+/&#x02013;</sup> and <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> mice, our results suggest that for the epilepsy phenotype, the complete loss of SLC6A1 function creates more severe and potentially irreversible changes in brain circuitry beyond very early mouse postnatal periods. In contrast, the presence of approximately 50% functional SLC6A1 through early development made the <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>+/&#x02013;</sup> mice receptive to treatment and phenotypic reversal was possible up to at least P5. An important caveat is that gene-transfer efficiency was also higher in younger mice. Ultimately, a definitive answer to this question of timing and phenotypic &#x0201c;reversibility&#x0201d; may require the use of genetic reconstitution of SLC6A1 in mouse models, such as was done for Rett syndrome (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). Until then, our results warrant caution in evaluating other therapeutic candidates for <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic>-related disorders in homozygous KO mice outside of neonatal administration: their complete absence of functional <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic> does not match the human haploinsufficiency condition, and aspects of their disease may be too severe to rescue. In the absence of further orthogonal data on the topic, our current conclusion is that heterozygous mice are likely the best model to evaluate the effectiveness of any potential therapeutics for <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic>-related disorders.</p><p>The <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic> gene is primarily expressed in the CNS of mammals and predominantly expressed in GABAergic inhibitory neurons, although it can also be found in glia cells (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). In our 2 AAV9/<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> vector designs, both JeT and MeP229 promoters will express human <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic> outside of cells that typically express endogenous <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic> (<xref rid="sd" ref-type="sec">Supplemental Figure 9</xref>). This raises a theoretical question of whether the ectopic overexpression of <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic> outside of cells that normally express <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic> could be helpful or harmful. From an efficacy perspective, the ectopic expression of <italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> in excitatory neurons or other cell types may have global effects in restoring extracellular GABA levels through the GABA uptake function of SLC6A1 protein. However, it may also influence excitatory transmission and activity. Both excitatory and inhibitory activity contribute to the underlying mechanisms of the epileptic and behavioral phenotypes in the <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic> mouse models. These dual effects on both excitatory and inhibitory circuits should be considered in efficacy studies. The treatment window may also be affected or altered by the balance between the harmful and beneficial effects of ectopic expression. Future vector designs that restrict ectopic expression of <italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> may help address these questions, but this is beyond the scope of our current study. Based on in situ RNAscope analysis and single-cell RNA-Seq data, the JeT AAV9/<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> vector shows a much broader expression in the mouse brain compared with MeP-<italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic>. Almost approximately 80% of JeT-<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic>-expressed cells do not overlap with the <italic toggle="yes">mSlc6a1</italic>-positive cells. However, a positive aspect is that the transcription levels of human JeT-expressed <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic> are equal to or slightly higher than the expression levels of the endogenous mouse <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic> following i.t. injection (<xref rid="sd" ref-type="sec">Supplemental Figure 8</xref>). In terms of efficacy, the MeP vector demonstrated either better or equal efficacy compared with the JeT vector in most assessments. This was particularly evident in the early stages of development, as observed in neonatal and P5 treated mice. Our RNAscope data revealed that both the MeP and JeT vectors transfected a similar percentage of brain cortex cells that normally express <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic> (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>). From a safety perspective, the neonatal ICV treatment group exhibited a high degree of adverse effects, particularly with the JeT promoter but also to a lesser extent with the MeP promoter. While we can&#x02019;t rule out general toxicity of AAV9 at this age and route, we conclude that this toxicity is most likely due to expression of the <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic> transgene due to the following: (a) The effects seemed to be somewhat promoter dependent, even when the 2 SLC6A1 vectors were administered at the same dose. (b) While we were not able to determine the cause of death of mice that died prematurely, limited histological examination didn&#x02019;t show signs of neurodegeneration (data not shown), and the appearance of convulsive seizures in some mice is consistent with the notion of a GABA-related excitatory/inhibitory imbalance. (c) In other studies conducted by our group using similarly manufactured AAV, we have not observed this type of toxicity from AAV9 vectors carrying other transgenes (for example, an AAV9/FIG4 vector injected at a higher dose of 5.4E11 vg ICV at P1; ref. <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). We would hypothesize that a lower dose would be tolerated better, but this wasn&#x02019;t tested. In contrast, the ectopic overexpression of human <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic> by MeP vectors appeared to be well tolerated at P5 or older age treatment groups via i.t. injection. The JeT vector showed higher adverse events in response to earlier age treatment groups, including neonatal and P5, but at P10 and P28 ages, the JeT vector was well tolerated in both treated WT and KO mice. Based on these data, the JeT vector exhibited notably greater safety concerns, suggesting that either the overall higher expression or the expression in non&#x02013;<italic toggle="yes">mSlc6a1</italic>-expressing cells is detrimental. Since the JeT vector did not provide additional efficacy, it may be advisable to use a more restrictive promoter.</p><p>While neonatal ICV injection in mice may not be directly translationally relevant due to differences in developmental ages between mice and humans, the observed benefits to treated mice still provide proof of concept that AAV9 gene replacement therapy can normalize both epilepsy and cognitive behavioral phenotypes in <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic> heterozygous and homozygous mice. Considering the challenges imposed by the mouse model phenotypes in relation to the human condition, there are multiple implications and caveats stemming from our results. As the <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>+/&#x02013;</sup> model shows minimal to no behavioral abnormalities, our experiments in that model could not address whether our gene-therapy approach has an impact on the behavioral aspects of the disease. Our results following neonatal ICV treatment of <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> mice and the nest-building results from P5 treatment of <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> mice suggest that the vector can rescue at least some aspects of behavior, at least at this early age, but we may not have appropriate models to answer the specific question of behavioral rescue at later ages. In terms of the age dependence of the treatment in heterozygous mice, the gene-therapy treatment was effective at P5 and ineffective at P23 (with PHP.eB). However, it remains possible that a P23 rescue is possible with higher gene-transfer efficiency. Future studies will need to fine tune that intervention window. When considering the equivalent age in humans, an important caveat is that there is an expected time course of at least 2 weeks before the transgene expression reaches maximal levels. At this early age in a mouse, over the course of 2 weeks the brain undergoes very rapid growth through multiple phases of critical brain development. In a human, that same period of brain growth and development stretches over years, where (relatively speaking) the transgene expression will turn on very rapidly. Thus, we conclude that early intervention is important to maximize efficacy in this gene-therapy approach for <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic>, but extreme caution should be taken trying to extrapolate equivalent treatment windows in a human.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Sex as a biological variable.</title><p>Our study examined male and female animals, and similar findings are reported for both sexes.</p></sec><sec><title>Viral vector design, development, and vector preparation.</title><p>We designed and developed the MeP229-<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic>-SV40pA and JeT-<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic>-SV40pA plasmids (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A</xref>). The transgene plasmid consists of a human <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic> codon-optimized DNA coding sequence of 1800 bp (<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1opt</italic>) between a 229 bp MeP229 promoter or a 164 bp JeT promoter and a 123 bp SV40pA polyadenylation signal. The MeP229 and JeT plasmids were packaged into scAAV9 vectors. The scAAV9 vectors were produced at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill (UNC) Vector Core or University of Texas Southwestern (UTSW) Vector Core, and titered by qPCR.</p></sec><sec><title>SLC6A1 animals.</title><p><italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> KO mice (B6.129S1-<italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic>tm1Lst/Mmucd, RRID: MMRRC_000426-UCD) were from the Mutant Mouse Resource and Research Center (MMRRC) at University of California at Davis (originally donated by Henry Lester, California Institute of Technology, Pasadena, California, USA), <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>S295L/S295L</sup> mice were from Shanghai Model Organisms (C57BL/6-<italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic>em2(S295L) Smoc, catalog number NM-KI-190014. <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>A288V/A288V</sup> mice were obtained through a collaboration with Jing Qiong Kang at Vanderbilt University (Nashville, Tennessee, USA). All the mice used in this study were received by our lab on the C57BL6/J background. Each strain was then backcrossed to WT C57BL6/J mice (purchased from the Jackson Laboratory) by our lab for at least 4 generations prior to use in any experimental studies. Breeding strategies for these mice consisted of heterozygous male mice crossed with heterozygous female mice. The exception to the HET &#x000d7; HET breeding strategy was in generating <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> and <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>+/&#x02013;</sup> mice for the ICV studies. Here, a <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> male was crossed with <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>+/&#x02013;</sup> female mice. A harem breeding scheme was used throughout; 1 male mouse was housed permanently with 2 female mice.</p></sec><sec><title>Efficacy study design.</title><p>The goal of our study was to develop and characterize a potential AAV9 gene-replacement therapy for human <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic>-related disorders. We first characterized 3 animal preclinical models of <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic>-related disorders, recapitulating core features pathologically and phenotypically observed in human <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic>-related disorders. The heterozygous <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>+/&#x02013;</sup> KO and homozygous <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> KO mice were chosen as the primary models for our gene-replacement studies. Two AAV9 vectors were designed, carrying human <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic> driven by either the weak universal promoter (JeT) or the predominantly neuronal promoter (MeP229). An initial proof-of-concept study was carried out in neonatal <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>+/&#x02013;</sup> and homozygous <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> KO mice by ICV administration. A larger and more comprehensive age- and dose-response study was then carried out in P5, P10, P23, and P28 mice by i.t. lumbar puncture administration or i.v. administration (P23 only, with a PHP.eB/MeP vector). Animal numbers used in each experiment are provided in the corresponding figure legends. We included approximately equal numbers of male and female mice in our study. Mice of each genotype were randomly allocated to treatment or control groups within each study. All outcome tests were conducted and analyzed in a blinded manner. In our analysis, sex did not affect the significance of any of the data presented in this study. We combined the data from both sexes to present the figures more concisely.</p></sec><sec><title>AAV dosing for efficacy studies.</title><p>Mixed litters of WT, <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>+/&#x02013;</sup> KO, and <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> KO mice were randomized into treatment groups for each study described throughout the results section. For neonatal ICV injections, cryoanesthetized mouse pups received bilateral bolus injections of vehicle or AAV into the lateral ventricles, 1.5 &#x003bc;L per hemisphere. For i.t. injections, restrained but unanesthetized mice received a single bolus injection of vehicle or AAV, into the L4/L5 region of the lumbar spinal cord, in a volume of 5&#x02013;8 &#x003bc;L. For the experiments described in <xref rid="sd" ref-type="sec">Supplemental Figure 6</xref>, a single i.t. injection of 10 &#x003bc;L or 2 sequential i.t. injections of 10 &#x003bc;L each were administered to the mice 2 hours apart. For i.v. injections, restrained mice received a bolus injection of vehicle or AAV into the tail vein in a volume of 20 &#x003bc;L.</p></sec><sec><title>EEG and analysis.</title><p>DSI PhysioTel HD-X02 implantable telemetry sensors were used throughout this study and implanted subcutaneously in WT, <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>+/&#x02013;</sup>, and <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> KO mice using the Data Sciences International (DSI) manual guidelines for telemetry implantation surgery. Mice used for EEG telemetry recordings were 3&#x02013;4 months old, and we used both male and female mice. Following surgeries, mice recovered for about 2 weeks. Video monitoring with synchronized EEG and electromyography (EMG) recordings was conducted continuously for 48 hours using DSI PhysioTelwireless receives and Ponemah software at the Neuro Models Core of UTSW. A 10 Hz high pass filter was used to smooth the EEG signal for seizure detection. The seizure detection (Spike Train) analysis module of NeuroScore Software scans the EEG signal to detect seizure activity with the parameters (absolute threshold: 200 &#x003bc;V; max spike interval: 1.5 seconds; min no. spikes: 3). For the EEG data, since all the WT mice were from the same C57BL6/J background, and they all showed identical EEG patterns, we collapsed all of the WT littermates from all 3 mouse model lines into a single group.</p></sec><sec><title>Behavioral tests.</title><p>Behavioral testing of all <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic> KO mice (WT, <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>+/&#x02013;</sup>, and <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup>), S295L (WT, <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>S295L/+</sup>, and <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>S295L/S295L</sup>) and A288V (WT, <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>A288V/+</sup>, and <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>A288V/A288V</sup>) mice was carried out in mice at approximately 2 months old, in males and females. All mice were put through the same behavioral battery of tests at 3 months old. Testing was performed in the following order: nest building, open field, social interaction, marble burying, rotarod, and fear conditioning. The mice were not retested on any of the aforementioned tests; however, they were trained (as is standard) for rotarod and fear conditioning. Training was conducted before the testing date for each, but after all other evaluations. The mice were then allowed to rest for at least 2 weeks before surgery was performed to implant the EEG/EMG sensor at 4 months old. Behavioral tests were carried out by investigators blinded to the genotype and/or treatment of the mice. Fear conditioning, rotarod and open-field behavioral tests were performed at UTSW Rodent Behavior Core.</p></sec><sec><title>Fear conditioning.</title><p>Fear conditioning is measured in boxes equipped with a metal grid floor connected to a scrambled shock generator (Med Associates Inc.). For training, mice were individually placed in the chamber. After 2 minutes, the mice received 3 tone-shock pairings (30 second white noise, 80 dB tone coterminated with a 2 second, 0.5 mA foot shock, 1 minute intertrial interval). The following day, memory of the context was measured by placing the mice into the same chambers and freezing was measured automatically by the Med Associates software (Video Freeze Version 2.7.3.0) for 5 minutes. Forty-eight hours after training, memory for the white noise cue was measured by placing the mice in a box with altered floors and walls, different lighting, and a vanilla smell. Freezing was measured for 3 minutes, then the noise cue was turned on for an additional 3 minutes and freezing was measured.</p></sec><sec><title>Rotarod.</title><p>Mice were placed onto a stationary rod (Columbus Instruments) and then the rod was started at 4 rpm. The rod was 3 cm diameter and made from a textured hard plastic. Any mice that fell off the stationary rod or the slow-moving rod were replaced until they could stay on for 2&#x02013;3 seconds. The acceleration began from 4 to 40 rpm over 5 minutes (acceleration increases 0.5 rpm every 4 seconds). The time until the mouse fell from the rod was recorded. Any mouse that held on to the rotating rod for a full turn was scored as if it fell on the turn. Each mouse received 4 trials a day (with a minimum of 20 minutes intertrial interval) for 2 days.</p></sec><sec><title>Open field.</title><p>Mice were placed in the periphery (placed along a wall, but in the center of the wall) of a novel plastic open-field environment (44 cm &#x000d7; 44 cm, walls 30 cm high) in a dimly lit room (approximately 60 lux) and allowed to explore for 10 minutes. The animals were monitored from above by a video camera connected to a computer running video-tracking software (Ethovision, Noldus) to determine the time, distance moved, and number of entries into 2 areas: the periphery (5 cm from the walls) and the center (14 cm &#x000d7; 14cm). The open-field arenas were wiped with Coverage Plus NPD Cleaner Disinfectant (STERIS catalog 638708) and allowed to dry between mice.</p></sec><sec><title>Nest building.</title><p>The nest-building test has been described in detail previously (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Hindlimb clasping.</title><p>Mice were suspended just above the bedding of an empty cage by holding the mouse about 1/2 inch from the base of the tail. The front paws were allowed to touch the bedding in the cage but unable to bear weight. The mouse was suspended for a total of 30 seconds to evaluate hind limb clasping score with scores range from 0 to 5: 0 = no fist making/clasping of paws, no retraction of either hind limb toward body. Limps stay splayed/extended for the entire 30 seconds; 1 = fist making/clasping, and/or quick retraction with immediate reextension of one hind limb; 2 = fist making/clasping, and quick retraction with immediate reextension of both hind limbs (alternating retraction of limbs); 3 = fist making/clasping, alternating or simultaneous retraction of limbs, no extension of retracted limb (retraction hold) within 1&#x02013;5 seconds; 4 = fist making/clasping, alternating or simultaneous retraction of limbs, no extension of retracted limb (retraction hold) of 1 limb for longer than 5 continuous seconds; 5 = fist making/clasping, alternating or simultaneous retraction of limbs, no extension of retracted limb (retraction hold) of both limbs for longer than 5 continuous seconds. The final score is determined by averaging the results of multiple tests to enhance accuracy.</p></sec><sec><title>Pilot safety study in WT BL/6J mice.</title><p>The pilot safety studies were designed to identify any short-term or long-term safety issues associated with the AAV9/<italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic> treatment. They were not conducted in strict compliance with good laboratory practice (GLP). The non-GLP safety study was initiated in WT C57BL/6J mice at P28. Six males and 6 females per cohort were injected i.t. with 5 &#x003bc;L of vehicle, low and high doses of AAV9/MeP229, or JeT <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic> vector. Treated mice were monitored for BW, survival, and body condition, and assessed for signs of adverse effects weekly for the first 4 weeks and monthly thereafter, up to 1 year after injection. Blood samples were collected at 3 weeks and at 12 months after injection for serological assessment of hepatic and renal function (TBIL, ALT, AST, BUN, and CK). A comprehensive necropsy was conducted at 12 months after injection for histopathology. In another non-GLP toxicity study, WT C57BL/6J mice were i.t. injected with 5 &#x003bc;L of vehicle, low and high doses of AAV9/MeP229, or JeT <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic> vector at P10. Treated mice were monitored for BW, survival, and body condition and assessed for signs of adverse effects for up to 6 months after injection. Histological assessment of all major organs and tissues of all study mice was carried out by a veterinary pathologist who was blinded to treatment.</p></sec><sec><title>RNAscope staining and image analysis.</title><p>Animals were perfused for 5 minutes with 1&#x000d7; PBS at a rate of 3.5 mL/min. The tissues were then harvested and fixed in 10% neutral-buffered formalin (NBF) for 24 hours before being transferred to 70% ethanol. Subsequently, the tissues were processed, embedded in paraffin, and cut into 5 &#x003bc;m sections. Separate sections were utilized for RNAscope to detect human transgene <italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> mRNA or mouse endogenous <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic> mRNA using custom-made <italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic>-Codon-C1 probe and mouse Mm-Slc6a1-C3 probe, following the RNAscope Multiplex Fluorescent Reagent Kit, version 2, protocol, nuclear staining with DAPI dye. All stained brain slides, with 1 section for each animal, were captured using the Zeiss Axioscan 7 slide scanner. The cortex, hippocampus, thalamus, and cerebellum regions of the brain were selected for cell count analysis, with at least 1,000 nuclei counted in each brain area per sample.</p></sec><sec><title>Analyses of single-cell transcriptomes.</title><p>A single nuclei suspension from the mouse brain cortex was prepared as previously described (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). A concentration of 1,000 nuclei/&#x003bc;L was submitted for 10X Genomics sequencing at the UTSW Next Generation Sequencing Core. Cell Ranger 5.0.1 (10x Genomics, <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.10xgenomics.com/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.10xgenomics.com/</ext-link>) was used to process the raw sequencing data. BCL files were converted to FASTQ files and aligned to customized mouse (mm10) reference transcriptome generated with cellranger mkref. Transcript counts of each cell were quantified using unique molecular identifier and valid cell barcode. The gene expression matrix from Cell Ranger was used as input to the Seurat R package (version 4.0.5) for downstream analysis. Cells with fewer than 250 genes per cell and high mitochondrial gene content were filtered out. The global-scaling normalization method LogNormalize was used for normalization. A subset of genes exhibiting high variation across the single cells was determined. The highly variable genes were calculated using the FindVariableFeatures module. The shared nearest neighbor (SNN) graph was constructed with the FindNeighbors module by determination of the k-nearest neighbors of each cell. The clusters were then identified by optimization of SNN modularity using the FindClusters module. We obtained 25 clusters with a resolution of 0.6. Clusters were merged and labeled to 12 clusters on the basis of known gene markers specific to various cell types. Differential expression analysis, clusters visualization, and plotting were all performed with Seurat.</p></sec><sec><title>Study approval.</title><p>All animal experiments were reviewed and approved by the UTSW Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistics.</title><p>All quantitative data in the figures are presented as mean &#x000b1; SEM, analyzed using GraphPad Prism Software (version 9.4.1). Based on the ROUT test, only 3 outliers in <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4D</xref> were excluded from the calculation (see <xref rid="sd" ref-type="sec">Supporting Data Values</xref>). Differences between data sets were carried out using 1-way ANOVA with Dunnett&#x02019;s multiple-comparisons test or 2-way ANOVA with &#x00160;id&#x000e1;k&#x02019;s multiple-comparisons test as indicated in each figure legend. <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05 was considered significant for all statistical analyses.</p></sec><sec><title>Data availability.</title><p>All data associated with this study are available in the main text or the supplemental materials, and additional study details are available from the authors upon request. Any plasmids, vectors, or animal models used in this study are available upon request through a material transfer agreement. The single-cell RNA-Seq data are available in the NCBI&#x02019;s Gene Expression Omnibus database (GEO GSE278732). Values for all data points in graphs are reported in the <xref rid="sd" ref-type="sec">Supporting Data Values</xref> file.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Author contributions</title><p>WG, MR, FS, and SJG conceptualized the study, WG, MR, FS, and YH performed experiments and data analysis. ZY and CX helped with bioinformatics analysis for single-cell RNA-Seq. SJG supervised all activities of the study. WG, MR, and SJG wrote the original manuscript draft. WG, MR, FS, YH, ZY, CX, and SJG reviewed the manuscript. The order of co&#x02013;first authors was established based on equal overall contributions to the project, with WG listed first due to his lead role in creating the original manuscript draft.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sd"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="SD1" position="float" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Supplemental data</title></caption><media xlink:href="jci-135-182235-s037.pdf" id="d67e1678" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SD2" position="float" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Supplemental data set 1</title></caption><media xlink:href="jci-135-182235-s038.xlsx" id="d67e1682" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SD3" position="float" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Supplemental data set 2</title></caption><media xlink:href="jci-135-182235-s039.xlsx" id="d67e1686" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SD4" position="float" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Supplemental video 1</title></caption><media xlink:href="jci-135-182235-s040.mp4" id="d67e1690" position="anchor" mimetype="video" mime-subtype="mp4"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SD5" position="float" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Supporting data values</title></caption><media xlink:href="jci-135-182235-s041.xlsx" id="d67e1694" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Jing Qiong Kang at Vanderbilt University for providing the A288V KI mouse line. We thank SLC6A1 Connect for providing the S295L KI mouse line. We thank the Neuro Models Core of UTSW and UTSW Rodent Behavior Core for help with mouse EEG measurement and behavioral tests. The study was funded by SLC6A1 Connect and Taysha Gene Therapies.</p></ack><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Conflict of interest:</bold> SJG and FS are inventors on the SLC6A1 vector designs (US patent #12,077,772) and have received income related to that invention. SJG has received consulting income from Taysha Gene Therapies.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Copyright:</bold> &#x000a9; 2024, Guo et al. This is an open access article published under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Reference information:</bold><italic toggle="yes"> J Clin Invest</italic>. 2025;135(3):e182235. https://doi.org/10.1172/JCI182235.</p></fn><fn><p>See the related Commentary at <related-article related-article-type="commentary" ext-link-type="doi" id="R188703" xlink:href="10.1172/JCI188703">Gene-replacement therapy in neurodevelopmental disorders: progress and challenges</related-article>.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Goodspeed</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Current knowledge of SLC6A1-related neurodevelopmental disorders</article-title><source>Brain Commun</source><year>2020</year><volume>2</volume><issue>2</issue><elocation-id>fcaa170</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/braincomms/fcaa170</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7677605</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33241211</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Carvill</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Mutations in the GABA transporter SLC6A1 cause epilepsy with myoclonic-atonic seizures</article-title><source>Am J Hum Genet</source><year>2015</year><volume>96</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>808</fpage><lpage>815</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajhg.2015.02.016</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4570550</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25865495</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Goodspeed</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>A draft conceptual model of SLC6A1 neurodevelopmental disorder</article-title><source>Front Neurosci</source><year>2022</year><volume>16</volume><elocation-id>1026065</elocation-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">9893116</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnins.2022.1026065</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36741059</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lopez-Rivera</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>A catalogue of new incidence estimates of monogenic neurodevelopmental disorders caused by de novo variants</article-title><source>Brain</source><year>2020</year><volume>143</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1099</fpage><lpage>1105</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/brain/awaa051</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7174049</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32168371</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Broer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gether</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The solute carrier 6 family of transporters</article-title><source>Br J Pharmacol</source><year>2012</year><volume>167</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>256</fpage><lpage>278</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1476-5381.2012.01975.x</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3481037</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22519513</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Madsen</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>The subcellular localization of GABA transporters and its implication for seizure management</article-title><source>Neurochem Res</source><year>2015</year><volume>40</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>410</fpage><lpage>419</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11064-014-1494-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25519681</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>XT</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Localization and function of GABA transporters GAT-1 and GAT-3 in the basal ganglia</article-title><source>Front Syst Neurosci</source><year>2011</year><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>63</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnsys.2011.00063</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3148782</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21847373</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kahen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Neurodevelopmental phenotypes associated with pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic></article-title><source>J Med Genet</source><year>2022</year><volume>59</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>536</fpage><lpage>543</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/jmedgenet-2021-107694</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34006619</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Johannesen</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Defining the phenotypic spectrum of SLC6A1 mutations</article-title><source>Epilepsia</source><year>2018</year><volume>59</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>389</fpage><lpage>402</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/epi.13986</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5912688</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29315614</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mattison</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>SLC6A1 variants identified in epilepsy patients reduce &#x003b3;-aminobutyric acid transport</article-title><source>Epilepsia</source><year>2018</year><volume>59</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>e135</fpage><lpage>e141</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/epi.14531</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30132828</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mermer</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Common molecular mechanisms of SLC6A1 variant-mediated neurodevelopmental disorders in astrocytes and neurons</article-title><source>Brain</source><year>2021</year><volume>144</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>2499</fpage><lpage>2512</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/brain/awab207</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">8418336</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34028503</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage" publication-format="online"><comment>Godspeed K, et al. SLC6A1-Related neurodevelopmental disorder. In: Adam MP, et al., eds. <italic toggle="yes">Genereviews</italic> [Internet]. University of Washington; 2024. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK589173/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK589173/</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>AAV-based in vivo gene therapy for neurological disorders</article-title><source>Nat Rev Drug Discov</source><year>2023</year><volume>22</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>789</fpage><lpage>806</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41573-023-00766-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37658167</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Saraiva</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Gene therapy for the CNS using AAVs: The impact of systemic delivery by AAV9</article-title><source>J Control Release</source><year>2016</year><volume>241</volume><fpage>94</fpage><lpage>109</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jconrel.2016.09.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27637390</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Biodistribution of adeno-associated virus gene therapy following cerebrospinal fluid-directed administration</article-title><source>Hum Gene Ther</source><year>2023</year><volume>34</volume><issue>3-4</issue><fpage>94</fpage><lpage>111</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/hum.2022.163</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36606687</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Intrathecal AAV9/AP4M1 gene therapy for hereditary spastic paraplegia 50 shows safety and efficacy in preclinical studies</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><year>2023</year><volume>133</volume><issue>10</issue><elocation-id>e164575</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI164575</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">10178841</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36951961</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>AAV9/MFSD8 gene therapy is effective in preclinical models of neuronal ceroid lipofuscinosis type 7 disease</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><year>2022</year><volume>132</volume><issue>5</issue><elocation-id>e146286</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI146286</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">8884910</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35025759</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Adeno-associated viral vector serotype 9-based gene replacement therapy for <italic toggle="yes">SURF1</italic>-related Leigh syndrome</article-title><source>Mol Ther Methods Clin Dev</source><year>2021</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>158</fpage><lpage>168</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.omtm.2021.09.001</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">8517205</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34703839</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Development of intrathecal AAV9 gene therapy for giant axonal neuropathy</article-title><source>Mol Ther Methods Clin Dev</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>160</fpage><lpage>171</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.omtm.2018.02.005</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5948230</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29766026</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sinnett</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Engineered microRNA-based regulatory element permits safe high-dose miniMECP2 gene therapy in Rett mice</article-title><source>Brain</source><year>2021</year><volume>144</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>3005</fpage><lpage>3019</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/brain/awab182</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">8783608</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33950254</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kalvakuntla</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Patterns of developmental regression and associated clinical characteristics in SLC6A1-related disorder</article-title><source>Front Neurosci</source><year>2023</year><volume>17</volume><elocation-id>1024388</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnins.2023.1024388</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">9990465</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36895422</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nwosu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>4-Phenylbutyrate restored gamma-aminobutyric acid uptake and reduced seizures in SLC6A1 patient variant-bearing cell and mouse models</article-title><source>Brain Commun</source><year>2022</year><volume>4</volume><issue>3</issue><elocation-id>fcac144</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/braincomms/fcac144</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">9336585</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35911425</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mermer</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Astrocytic GABA transporter 1 deficit in novel SLC6A1 variants mediated epilepsy: connected from protein destabilization to seizures in mice and humans</article-title><source>Neurobiol Dis</source><year>2022</year><volume>172</volume><elocation-id>105810</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nbd.2022.105810</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">9472560</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35840120</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Number, density, and surface/cytoplasmic distribution of GABA transporters at presynaptic structures of knock-in mice carrying GABA transporter subtype 1-green fluorescent protein fusions</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2002</year><volume>22</volume><issue>23</issue><fpage>10251</fpage><lpage>10266</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.22-23-10251.2002</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6758747</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12451126</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>GABA transporter deficiency causes tremor, ataxia, nervousness, and increased GABA-induced tonic conductance in cerebellum</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2005</year><volume>25</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>3234</fpage><lpage>3245</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.3364-04.2005</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6725086</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15788781</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>GABA transporter-1 (GAT1)-deficient mice: differential tonic activation of GABAA versus GABAB receptors in the hippocampus</article-title><source>J Neurophysiol</source><year>2003</year><volume>90</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>2690</fpage><lpage>2701</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/jn.00240.2003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12815026</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tornoe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Generation of a synthetic mammalian promoter library by modification of sequences spacing transcription factor binding sites</article-title><source>Gene</source><year>2002</year><volume>297</volume><issue>1-2</issue><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0378-1119(02)00878-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12384282</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Optimizing promoters for recombinant adeno-associated virus-mediated gene expression in the peripheral and central nervous system using self-complementary vectors</article-title><source>Hum Gene Ther</source><year>2011</year><volume>22</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1143</fpage><lpage>1153</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/hum.2010.245</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3177952</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21476867</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mathiesen</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>CNS Transduction benefits of AAV-PHP.eB over AAV9 are dependent on administration route and mouse strain</article-title><source>Mol Ther Methods Clin Dev</source><year>2020</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>447</fpage><lpage>458</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.omtm.2020.10.011</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7683292</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33294493</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Overexpression of gamma-aminobutyric acid transporter subtype I leads to susceptibility to kainic acid-induced seizure in transgenic mice</article-title><source>Cell Res</source><year>2001</year><volume>11</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>61</fpage><lpage>67</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.cr.7290067</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11305326</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Transgenic mice overexpressing gamma-aminobutyric acid transporter subtype I develop obesity</article-title><source>Cell Res</source><year>2000</year><volume>10</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>303</fpage><lpage>310</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.cr.7290057</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11191352</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Haploinsufficiency underlies the neurodevelopmental consequences of SLC6A1 variants</article-title><source>Am J Hum Genet</source><year>2024</year><volume>111</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1222</fpage><lpage>1238</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajhg.2024.04.021</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">11179425</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38781976</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pontes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Novel functions of GABA signaling in adult neurogenesis</article-title><source>Front Biol (Beijing)</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>496</fpage><lpage>507</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11515-013-1270-2</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3839947</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24285940</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Functional correction of neurological and somatic disorders at later stages of disease in MPS IIIA mice by systemic scAAV9-hSGSH gene delivery</article-title><source>Mol Ther Methods Clin Dev</source><year>2016</year><volume>3</volume><elocation-id>16036</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/mtm.2016.36</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4898406</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27331076</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Guy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Reversal of neurological defects in a mouse model of Rett syndrome</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2007</year><volume>315</volume><issue>5815</issue><fpage>1143</fpage><lpage>1147</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1138389</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7610836</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17289941</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fattorini</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Microglial expression of GAT-1 in the cerebral cortex</article-title><source>Glia</source><year>2020</year><volume>68</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>646</fpage><lpage>655</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/glia.23745</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31692106</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Minelli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>GAT-1, a high-affinity GABA plasma membrane transporter, is localized to neurons and astroglia in the cerebral cortex</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>1995</year><volume>15</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>7734</fpage><lpage>7746</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.15-11-07734.1995</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6578038</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7472524</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Presa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>AAV9-mediated FIG4 delivery prolongs life span in Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease type 4J mouse model</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><year>2021</year><volume>131</volume><issue>11</issue><elocation-id>e137159</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI137159</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">8159684</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33878035</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Deacon</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Assessing nest building in mice</article-title><source>Nat Protoc</source><year>2006</year><volume>1</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>1117</fpage><lpage>1119</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2006.170</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17406392</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ayhan</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Nuclei isolation from surgically resected human hippocampus</article-title><source>STAR Protoc</source><year>2021</year><volume>2</volume><issue>4</issue><elocation-id>100844</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.xpro.2021.100844</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">8455478</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34585170</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref></ref-list><notes notes-type="version-changes"><sec sec-type="version-changes"><label>Version 1</label><title>11/26/2024</title><p>In-Press Preview</p></sec><sec sec-type="version-changes"><label>Version 2</label><title>02/03/2025</title><p>Electronic publication</p></sec></notes></back><floats-group><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>The constitutive <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic> KO mouse model and 2 KI mouse models of human patient variants S295L and A288V similarly phenocopy human SLC6A1-related disorders.</title><p>All assessments were conducted in WT, heterozygous (<italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>+/&#x02013;</sup>, <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>S295L/+</sup>, <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>A288V/+</sup>), and homozygous (<italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup>, <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>S295L/S295L</sup>, <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>A288V/A288V</sup>) <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic> KO and KI mice. (<bold>A</bold>) Representative EEG and EMG recording examples. A 10 Hz high pass filter was used to smooth the EEG signal. (<bold>B</bold>) Quantification of total spike train duration across a 48-hour EEG recording period (% recording time) in WT and heterozygous <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic> KO and KI mice (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 6, 3, 3, and 4, left to right on the panel). (<bold>C</bold>) Quantification of total spike train duration across a 48-hour EEG recording period (% recording time) in WT and homozygous <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic> KO and KI mice (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 6, 6, 6, and 3, left to right on the panel). (<bold>D</bold>) BW quantification at 8 weeks old. (<bold>E</bold>) Nest-building scores. (<bold>F</bold>) Time spent in the center (s) of an open field. (<bold>G</bold>) Freezing percentage time during the contextual fear conditioning tests. (<bold>H</bold>) Average latency to fall (s, average of 8 trials) of the rotarod test. (<bold>I</bold>) Hindlimb clasping scores. (Sample number in <bold>D</bold>, <bold>E</bold>, and <bold>G</bold>&#x02013;<bold>I</bold>: WT, <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>S295L/+</sup>, <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>S295L/S295L</sup>: <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 19&#x02013;20 per group; WT, <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>A288V/+</sup>, <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>A288V/A288V</sup>: <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 20 per group; WT, <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/+</sup>, <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup>: <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 10&#x02013;12 per group). Data are represented as means &#x000b1; SEM. One-way ANOVA with Dunnett&#x02019;s multiple-comparisons test was used for statistical analysis. *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05; **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01; ***<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; ****<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.0001.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jci-135-182235-g031" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>AAV9/<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> gene therapy rescues abnormal EEG patterns and key behavioral phenotypes in <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic> heterozygous and homozygous KO mice by neonatal ICV injection.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Experimental design of AAV9/<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> gene therapy via neonatal ICV injection (study plan, duration, and readouts). Three &#x000d7; 10<sup>11</sup> vg AAV9/<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> vector or vehicle was administered to each mouse. Study readouts at each time point after dose administration or at the specified age are listed. Schematic diagram of the AAV9/<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> gene transfer cassettes using a MeP229 promoter (mostly neuron-specific promoter) or JeT promoter (weak ubiquitous promoter), the full-length codon-optimized human <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic> cDNA, and the SV40 poly(A) tail. (<bold>B</bold>) Representative EEG and EMG recording examples for heterozygous (<italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>+/&#x02013;</sup>) and homozygous (<italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup>) mice injected with vehicle, AAV9/JeT-<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic>, or AAV9/MeP229-<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic>. A 10 Hz high pass filter was used to smooth the EEG signal. (<bold>C</bold>) Quantification of total spike train duration across a 48-hour EEG recording period (% recording time) of heterozygous mice injected with vehicle, AAV9/JeT-<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic>, or AAV9/MeP229-<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 8, 5, and 5, left to right on the panel). (<bold>D</bold>) Quantification of total spike train duration across a 48-hour EEG recording period (% recording time) of homozygous mice injected with vehicle, AAV9/JeT-<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic>, or AAV9/MeP229-<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 9, 9, and 3, left to right on the panel). Additional assessments in live <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>+/&#x02013;</sup> and <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> mice only compared vehicle and AAV9/MeP229-<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> treatment, after discontinuation of AAV9/JeT-<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> due to high mortality (panels <bold>E</bold>&#x02013;<bold>J</bold>). (<bold>E</bold>) BWs (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 22, 12, 22, 27; left to right on the panel), (<bold>F</bold>) nest-building scores (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 22, 12, 22, 27; left to right on the panel), (<bold>G</bold>) contextual and cued fear conditioning freezing levels (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 18, 8, 17, 21; left to right on the panel), (<bold>H</bold>) center time in an open field (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 18, 8, 17, 21; left to right on the panel), (<bold>I</bold>) hind limb clasping scores (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 22, 12, 22, 27; left to right on the panel), (<bold>J</bold>) rotarod latency to fall time (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 18, 8, 17, 21; left to right on the panel). Data are represented as means &#x000b1; SEM. One-way ANOVA with Dunnett&#x02019;s multiple comparisons test was used for statistical analysis in <bold>C</bold> and <bold>D</bold>. Two-way ANOVA with &#x00160;id&#x000e1;k&#x02019;s multiple-comparisons test was used for statistical analysis in <bold>E</bold>&#x02013;<bold>J</bold>. *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05; **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01; ***<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; ****<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.0001.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jci-135-182235-g032" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>i.t. administration of AAV9/<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> to P5 mice rescues abnormal EEG patterns in <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>+/&#x02013;</sup> mice and some cognitive behaviors in <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> mice, but fails to rescue the abnormal EEG patterns in <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> mice.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Experimental design of AAV9/<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> gene therapy via i.t. injection in P5 mice. Either vehicle, AAV9/MeP229-<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic>, or AAV9/<italic toggle="yes">JeT-hSLC6A1</italic> were administered at doses of 5.6 &#x000d7; 10<sup>11</sup> vg or 1.12 &#x000d7; 10<sup>12</sup> vg. Study readouts at specified ages are listed. (<bold>B</bold>) Representative EEG and EMG recording examples for treated <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>+/&#x02013;</sup> and <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup>. A 10 Hz high pass filter was used to smooth the EEG signal. (<bold>C</bold>) Quantification of total spike train duration across a 48-hour EEG recording period (% recording time) for treated <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>+/&#x02013;</sup> mice (left to right: <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 7, 9, 12, 9, and 9). (<bold>D</bold>) Quantification of total spike train duration across a 48-hour EEG recording period (% recording time) for treated <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> mice (left to right: <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 6, 8, 5, 7, and 6). (<bold>E</bold>) Nest-building scores in treated <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> mice compared with vehicle-treated <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>+/&#x02013;</sup> mice (left to right: <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 10, 10, 10, 8, 10, and 9). For <bold>C</bold>&#x02013;<bold>E</bold>, data are represented by the mean &#x000b1; SEM. One-way ANOVA with Dunnett&#x02019;s multiple-comparisons test was used for statistical analysis. (<bold>F</bold>) RNAscope multiplex fluorescent images showing mRNA expression of the <italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> transgene (green) and mouse endogenous <italic toggle="yes">mSlc6a1</italic> (red) from the cortex in treated <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>+/&#x02013;</sup> mouse brain sections, counterstained with DAPI (blue). Scale bar: 100 &#x003bc;m. (<bold>G</bold>) Quantification of the percentage of transduced human <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A1</italic>-positive cells in the cortex of treated <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>+/&#x02013;</sup> mice. The percentage of <italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> transduced cells are expressed as a ratio of green <italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic>-positive cells to the total number of blue nuclear DAPI positive cells (counting at least 1,000 nuclei of each sample/brain area); (<bold>H</bold>) Quantification of the percentage of endogenous <italic toggle="yes">mSlc6a1</italic>-positive cells in <italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic>-transduced cells in each brain region (expressed as a ratio of the double SLC6A1-positive cells [red and green] to transduced <italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic>-positive cells [green]). Data are represented as mean &#x000b1; SEM. <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 6 per group. One-way ANOVA with Dunnett&#x02019;s multiple-comparisons test was used for statistical analysis. *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05; **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01; ***<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; ****<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.0001.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jci-135-182235-g033" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>i.t. administration of AAV9/<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> to P10 or P28 <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> KO mice showed weak or no behavioral improvements.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Experimental design of preclinical AAV9/<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> gene therapy via i.t. injection to P10 or P28 <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> KO mice. Either vehicle, 7 &#x000d7; 10<sup>11</sup> vg AAV9/MeP229-<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic>, or 7.5x10<sup>11</sup> vg AAV9/JET-<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> were administered. Study readouts at specified ages are listed. (<bold>B</bold>) Quantification of total spike train duration across a 48-hour EEG recording period (% recording time) (left to right: <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 5, 5, 4, 4, 4, 3, 4, and 4). (<bold>C</bold>) Nest-building scores (left to right: <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 17, 9, 9, 8, 27, 18, 19, and 19) (<bold>D</bold>) Freezing percentage of time during the contextual fear conditioning tests (left to right: <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 17, 9, 9, 8, 22, 15, 15, and 14). (<bold>E</bold>) Latency to fall (s) across 8 trials of the rotarod tests and (<bold>F</bold>) average latency to fall (s, average of 8 trials) of the rotarod tests (left to right: <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 17, 9, 9, 8, 27, 18, 19, and 19). Data are represented as means &#x000b1; SEM. One-way ANOVA with Dunnett&#x02019;s multiple-comparisons test was used for statistical analysis. *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05; **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01; ****<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.0001.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jci-135-182235-g034" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>AAV-PHP.eB/MeP-<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> gene therapy initiated at P23 provides minimal behavior benefit and does not rescue abnormal EEG patterns in heterozygous and homozygous <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic> KO mice.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Experimental design of the i.v.-administered AAV-PHP.eB/MeP-<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> gene therapy approach. WT, <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>+/&#x02013;</sup>, or <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1</italic><sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> mice were treated at P23 with 0, 2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>10</sup>, 2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>11</sup>, or 1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>12</sup> vg. Weight and behavioral assessments were not conducted on heterozygous mice due to their lack of a phenotype or on mice receiving the 1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>12</sup> vg dose due to the small number of animals. Study readouts at each time point after vector administration or at specified ages are listed. (<bold>B</bold>) Representative EEG and EMG recording examples. A 10 Hz high pass filter was used to smooth the EEG signal. (<bold>C</bold>) <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1<sup>+/&#x02013;</sup></italic> quantification of the total spike train duration over a 48-hour EEG recording period (% recording time) (left to right: <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 8, 9, 10, 8, and 5). (<bold>D</bold>) <italic toggle="yes">Slc6a1<sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup></italic> quantification of total spike train duration over a 48-hour EEG recording period (% recording time) (left to right: <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 8, 11, 9, 9, and 3). (<bold>E</bold>) BWs, (<bold>F</bold>) nest-building scores, (<bold>G</bold>) contextual and cued fear conditioning freezing levels, (<bold>H</bold>) center time in an open field, (<bold>I</bold>) hind limb clasping scores, (<bold>J</bold>) rotarod latency to fall time. <bold>E</bold>&#x02013;<bold>I</bold>, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 20-25 per group. All data are represented as means &#x000b1; SEM. One-way ANOVA with Dunnett&#x02019;s multiple-comparisons test was used for statistical analysis. *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05; **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01; ***<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; ****<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.0001.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jci-135-182235-g035" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>i.t. administration of either AAV9/JeT-<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> or AAV9/MeP-<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> in WT mice at P28 did not lead to any adverse effects up to a year after injection.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Experimental design of the pilot toxicology study in male and female WT C57Bl6/J mice injected with vehicle, AAV9/MeP229-<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> (1.75 &#x000d7; 10<sup>11</sup> vg [low] or 7.0 &#x000d7; 10<sup>11</sup> vg [high]), and AAV9/JeT-<italic toggle="yes">hSLC6A1</italic> (1.88 &#x000d7; 10<sup>11</sup> vg [low] or 7.5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>11</sup> vg [high]) via i.t. injection at P28. Study readouts at each time point after dose administration or at specified age are listed. (<bold>B</bold>) Longitudinal BWs of treated male mice. <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 6 per group. (<bold>C</bold>) Longitudinal BWs of treated female mice. <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 6 per group. (<bold>D</bold>&#x02013;<bold>H</bold>) Blood chemistry tests (AST, TBIL, BUN, CK, or ALB) at 3 weeks after injection. <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 10&#x02013;12 per group. All data are represented as means &#x000b1; SEM. One-way ANOVA with Dunnett&#x02019;s multiple-comparisons test was used for statistical analysis. *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jci-135-182235-g036" position="float"/></fig></floats-group></article>