<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="letter"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Circ Arrhythm Electrophysiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Circ Arrhythm Electrophysiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">HAE</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Circulation. Arrhythmia and Electrophysiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1941-3149</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1941-3084</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Lippincott Williams &#x00026; Wilkins</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Hagerstown, MD</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40242861</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12094257</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">CIRCAE-2024-013621D</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="art-access-id">00009</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIRCEP.124.013621</article-id><article-version vocab="JAV" vocab-identifier="http://www.niso.org/publications/rp/RP-8-2008.pdf" article-version-type="Version of Record">3</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll"><subject>10004</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Letters</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Intermediate Monocytes and High Levels of Chemokine CCL3 Are Associated With Increased Risk of Atrial Fibrillation in the General Population</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1034-9965</contrib-id><name><surname>Sveen</surname><given-names>Kari Anne</given-names></name><degrees>MD, PhD</degrees><email>kasvee@ous-hf.no</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6285-9935</contrib-id><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>J. Gustav</given-names></name><degrees>MD, PhD</degrees><email>j.gustav.smith@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff"/><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff"/><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff"/><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2935-0181</contrib-id><name><surname>Goncalves</surname><given-names>Isabel</given-names></name><degrees>MD, PhD</degrees><email>isabel.goncalves@med.lu.se</email><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff"/><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff"/><xref rid="aff7" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2691-9192</contrib-id><name><surname>Edsfeldt</surname><given-names>Andreas</given-names></name><degrees>MD, PhD</degrees><email>andreas.edsfeldt@med.lu.se</email><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff"/><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff"/><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff"/><xref rid="aff7" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0289-5210</contrib-id><name><surname>Engelbertsen</surname><given-names>Daniel</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><email>daniel.engelbertsen@med.lu.se</email><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2249-8220</contrib-id><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>Linda S.</given-names></name><degrees>MD, PhD</degrees><email>linda.johnson@med.lu.se</email><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2581-484X</contrib-id><name><surname>Melander</surname><given-names>Olle</given-names></name><degrees>MD, PhD</degrees><email>olle.melander@med.lu.se</email><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff"/><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff"/><xref rid="aff8" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8618-9152</contrib-id><name><surname>Engstr&#x000f6;m</surname><given-names>Gunnar</given-names></name><degrees>MD, PhD</degrees><email>gunnar.engstrom@med.lu.se</email><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9752-7479</contrib-id><name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>Jan</given-names></name><degrees>MD, PhD</degrees><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff"/><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3918-0857</contrib-id><name><surname>Bj&#x000f6;rkbacka</surname><given-names>Harry</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><email>harry.bjorkbacka@med.lu.se</email><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff"/><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7075-1772</contrib-id><name><surname>Bengtsson</surname><given-names>Eva</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff"/><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff"/><xref rid="aff9" ref-type="aff"/><xref rid="aff10" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><aff id="aff1">Department of Endocrinology, Morbid Obesity and Preventive Medicine, Oslo University Hospital, Oslo, Norway (K.A.S.).</aff><aff id="aff2">Department of Cardiology, Clinical Sciences, Lund University and Sk&#x000e5;ne University Hospital, Lund, Sweden (J.G.S.).</aff><aff id="aff3">The Wallenberg Laboratory/Department of Molecular and Clinical Medicine, Institute of Medicine, Gothenburg University and the Department of Cardiology, Sahlgrenska University Hospital, Gothenburg, Sweden (J.G.S.).</aff><aff id="aff4">Wallenberg Center for Molecular Medicine, Lund University, Lund, Sweden (J.G.S., A.E.).</aff><aff id="aff5">Lund University Diabetes Center, Lund University, Lund, Sweden (J.G.S., I.G., A.E., O.M., J.N., H.B., E.B.).</aff><aff id="aff6">Department of Clinical Sciences, Malm&#x000f6;, Lund University, Sweden (I.G., A.E., D.E., L.S.J., O.M., G.E., J.N., H.B., E.B.).</aff><aff id="aff7">Department of Cardiology, Sk&#x000e5;ne University Hospital, Sweden (I.G., A.E.).</aff><aff id="aff8">Department of Internal Medicine, Sk&#x000e5;ne University Hospital, Sweden (O.M.).</aff><aff id="aff9">Department of Biomedical Science, Faculty of Health and Society, Malm&#x000f6; University, Malm&#x000f6;, Sweden (E.B.).</aff><aff id="aff10">Biofilms &#x02013; Research Center for Biointerfaces, Malm&#x000f6; University, Malm&#x000f6;, Sweden (E.B.).</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1">Correspondence to: Eva Bengtsson, PhD, Department of Biomedical Science, Malm&#x000f6; University, Jan Waldenstr&#x000f6;ms gata 25, 21428 Malm&#x000f6;, Sweden; or Department of Clinical Sciences, Lund University, CRC 91:12, Box 50332, 20213 Malm&#x000f6;, Sweden. E-mail <email xlink:href="eva.bengtsson@mau.se">eva.bengtsson@mau.se</email>; or <email xlink:href="eva.bengtsson@med.lu.se">eva.bengtsson@med.lu.se</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>18</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>e013621</fpage><lpage>e013621</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2025 The Authors.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><italic toggle="yes">Circulation: Arrhythmia and Electrophysiology</italic> is published on behalf of the American Heart Association, Inc., by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. This is an open access article under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution</ext-link> License, which permits use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided that the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="hae-18-e013621.pdf"/><kwd-group><kwd>atrial fibrillation</kwd><kwd>chemokines</kwd><kwd>monocytes</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name><meta-value>TRUE</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Atrial fibrillation (AF) is increasing in prevalence and linked to higher morbidity and mortality rates. Emerging evidence implicates inflammation as a key driver of AF pathogenesis.<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> Our study aimed to investigate associations between circulating monocyte subsets, monocyte-attracting chemokines and incidence of AF in a large community-based cohort.</p><p>The Malm&#x000f6; Diet and Cancer Cardiovascular Cohort is a prospective cohort study conducted between 1991 and 1994.<sup><xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> Incident AF cases were recorded until December 31, 2014, using national registers.<sup><xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> The study was approved by the Swedish ethical review authority, and all participants gave informed consent. Blood monocyte subsets, analyzed by flow cytometry in 666 randomly selected individuals from mononuclear leukocytes frozen at baseline,<sup><xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> were defined as classical (CD14<sup>++</sup>CD16<sup>&#x02212;</sup>), intermediate (CD14<sup>++</sup>CD16<sup>+</sup>), and nonclassical (CD14<sup>+</sup>CD16<sup>++</sup>). Percentage monocyte subsets were calculated as a percentage of total monocytes (classical, intermediate, and nonclassical). Chemokines (MCP1 [monocyte chemoattractant protein-1], CX3CL1 [CX3C motif chemokine ligand 1], CCL4 [CC motif chemokine ligand], CCL3) and IL-6 (interleukin-6) were measured in plasma using proximity extension analysis (Proseek Multiplex Cardiovascular Panel I; Olink Proteomics, Sweden; n=4704). Monocyte and chemokine analyses overlapped in 528 subjects (Figure [A]). Plasma TNF&#x003b1; (tumor necrosis factor-&#x003b1;) was analyzed in the overlapping subjects using multiplex immunoassay (Millipore). Metabolic syndrome subjects were classified according to the NCEP ATP III definition. Associations with incident AF over time were analyzed by log-rank test and Kaplan-Meier curves. Hazard ratios (95% CIs) were calculated using Cox proportional hazards regression adjusted according to model 1 (age and sex), model 2 (age, sex, clinical risk factors, and prevalent cardiovascular disease; Figure [C]), model 2+cytokines (TNF&#x003b1;, IL-6), or model 2+chemokines (MCP1, CCL3). Proportional hazards assumptions were assessed using Cox regression with time-dependent covariate. <italic toggle="yes">International Classification of Diseases</italic> codes were previously reported.<sup><xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> Correlations were assessed using Spearman rank correlations. The data are available upon reasonable request.</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure.</label><caption><p><bold>Intermediate CD14<sup>++</sup>CD16<sup>+</sup> monocytes and chemokine CCL3 (CC motif chemokine ligand 3) are associated with increased risk of atrial fibrillation (AF). A</bold>, Overview of MDC-cardiovascular cohort. <bold>B</bold>, Baseline characteristics of subjects with and without incident AF. Incident AF cases were recorded during median 18.6 years (subjects analyzed for monocyte subsets) and 21.4 years (subjects analyzed for chemokines) follow-up. <bold>C</bold>, Intermediate monocytes are associated with increased risk of developing AF depicted in Kaplan-Meier curves, tertile 1 to tertile 3 (T1&#x02013;T3), lowest to highest, log-rank test. HR of incident AF with 95% CI of highest vs lowest tertile of intermediate monocytes (numbers or percentages) adjusted according to model 2 (age, sex, systolic blood pressure, current smoking, body mass index [BMI], triglycerides, high-density lipoprotein [HDL]-cholesterol, glucose, glomerular filtration rate, prevalent coronary event, stroke, and heart failure, and presence of carotid plaque), model 2+cytokines (TNF&#x003b1; and IL-6), or model 2+chemokines (CCL3 and MCP1 [monocyte chemoattractant protein-1]). <bold>D</bold>, CCL3 is associated with increased risk of developing AF, depicted in Kaplan-Meier curves, quartile 1 to quartile 4 (Q1&#x02013;Q4), lowest to highest, log-rank test. HR of incident AF with 95% CI of highest vs lowest quartile adjusted according to model 1 (age and sex) or model 2 (as above). <bold>E</bold>, CCL3 is associated with increased risk of developing AF in subjects with metabolic syndrome (MetS) depicted in Kaplan-Meier curves, below (&#x0003c;) and above (&#x0003e;) median in subjects with (n=937) or without (n=3661) metabolic syndrome. Hazard ratio of incident AF with 95% CI of above vs below median levels of CCL3 adjusted according to model 1 (age and sex).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="hae-18-e013621-g001" position="float"/></fig><p>Incident AF cases demonstrated elevated levels of intermediate and classical monocytes compared with non-AF subjects (Figure [B]). However, only intermediate monocytes were associated with incident AF after adjusting for risk factors and prevalent cardiovascular disease (Figure [C], model 2). The association remained in a sensitivity analysis excluding subjects with prevalent coronary events, strokes, and heart failures (hazard ratio, 1.82 [1.12&#x02013;2.97]), number of monocytes, tertile 3 versus tertile 1, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02009;=0.017). To take vascular disease over time into account, incident coronary events and heart failures that occurred prior to incident AF were censored. Importantly, the association between incident AF and numbers of intermediate monocytes remained and was even stronger (hazard ratio 2.21 [1.30&#x02013;3.75], tertile 3 versus tertile 1, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02009;=0.003).</p><p>Next, we analyzed if monocyte-attracting chemokines were associated with incident AF. Classical monocytes express chemokine receptor CCR2 (CC motif chemokine receptor) and are recruited to sites of inflammation by MCP1. Nonclassical monocytes express high levels of CX3CR1 (CX3C motif chemokine receptor 1) and patrol the vasculature, attracted by CX3CL1. Intermediate monocytes release proinflammatory cytokines and express CCR2, CX3CR1 and high levels of CCR5, which binds to a variety of chemokines, including CCL3 and CCL4. In the present study, MCP1 and CCL3 were elevated in incident AF cases (Figure [B]). After age and sex adjustment, only CCL3 remained associated with incident AF; however, the association was lost after the addition of clinical risk factors (Figure D). Notably, CCL3 correlated with factors of the metabolic syndrome: waist (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>&#x02009;=0.27, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;0.001), glucose (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>&#x02009;=0.19, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;0.001), triglycerides (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>&#x02009;=0.25, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;0.001), systolic blood pressure (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>&#x02009;=0.17, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;0.001), and inversely with high-density lipoprotein (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02212;0.24, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;0.001). Subjects with metabolic syndrome had higher levels of CCL3 than nonmetabolic syndrome subjects (1.23 [0.99&#x02013;1.55] versus 1.01 [0.75&#x02013;1.31] arbitrary units; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;0.001). Interestingly, the association of CCL3 with AF was stronger in individuals with metabolic syndrome (Figure [E]).</p><p>Finally, we assessed correlations of intermediate monocytes with inflammatory cytokines and chemokines. In line with the role of intermediate monocytes in inflammatory cytokine secretion and migration into tissues via CCL3, intermediate monocytes correlated with TNF&#x003b1; (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>&#x02009;=0.12, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02009;=0.007) and CCL3 (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>&#x02009;=0.09, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02009;=0.04). Furthermore, IL-6 levels were higher in incident AF cases (Figure [B]). Importantly, the association of intermediate monocytes with incident AF remained after the addition of plasma cytokines or chemokines to the regression model (Figure [C]).</p><p>Our findings highlight the independent association between intermediate monocytes, characterized by their proinflammatory profile, and incident AF. The study supports prior murine studies of a role of monocytes/macrophages contributing to AF.<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> While classical monocytes were also elevated in incident AF cases, their lack of association in multivariable models suggests a less important role. It is possible that locally enhanced secretion of proinflammatory cytokines by intermediate monocytes may explain the specific association of this monocyte subtype with AF. Our results emphasize the role of chemokine CCL3 in AF, particularly in individuals with metabolic syndrome. Obesity increases the risk of AF and is associated with an increased amount of epicardial fat, producing proinflammatory mediators.<sup><xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> CCL3, expressed by adipocytes, may thus contribute to inflammatory cell recruitment into the myocardium.</p><p>This study supports a role of intermediate monocytes and CCL3 in the inflammatory pathway leading to AF. Future research should explore whether reducing inflammation through lifestyle or pharmacological interventions targeting monocytes and chemokines can mitigate AF risk.</p><sec><title>Article Information</title><sec><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>The authors are grateful to PhD Katarina Berg, Linda Andersson, and Irena Ljungcrantz for excellent work in measuring monocyte subsets.</p></sec><sec><title>Sources of Funding</title><p>This study was supported by Swedish Heart Lung Foundation, the Swedish Research Council, Swedish Governmental Funding of Clinical Research, the Crafoord foundation, Albert P&#x000e5;hlsson foundation, Knut and Alice Wallenberg foundation to the Wallenberg Center for Molecular Medicine in Lund, Sk&#x000e5;ne University Hospital Funds, Swedish Foundation for Strategic Research to Lund University Diabetes Center, and the Swedish Society for Medical Research.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Disclosures</title><p>Dr Johnson received consulting fees from MEDICALgortihmics and Pfizer. The other authors report no conflicts.</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="abbr"><p><def-list><title>Nonstandard Abbreviations and Acronyms</title><def-item><term>AF</term><def><p>atrial fibrillation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CCL</term><def><p>CC motif chemokine ligand</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CCR</term><def><p>CC motif chemokine receptor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CX3CL1</term><def><p>CX3C motif chemokine ligand 1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CX3CR1</term><def><p>CX3C motif chemokine receptor 1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IL-6</term><def><p>interleukin-6</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MCP1</term><def><p>monocyte chemoattractant protein-1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TNF&#x003b1;</term><def><p>tumor necrosis factor-&#x003b1;</p></def></def-item></def-list>
</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p>For Sources of Funding and Disclosures, see page 405.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hulsmans</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schloss</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name><name><surname>Bapat</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwamoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Vinegoni</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Paccalet</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamazoe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Grune</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pabel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Recruited macrophages elicit atrial fibrillation.</article-title>
<source>Science</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>381</volume>:<fpage>231</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>239</lpage>. <comment>doi: 10.1126/science.abq3061</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37440641</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ljungcrantz</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bryngelsson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hedblad</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Fredrikson</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bjorkbacka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Elevated CD14++CD16- monocytes predict cardiovascular events.</article-title>
<source>Circ Cardiovasc Genet</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>122</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>131</lpage>. <comment>doi: 10.1161/CIRCGENETICS.111.960385</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22238190</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Platonov</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Hedblad</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Engstrom</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Melander</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Atrial fibrillation in the Malmo Diet and Cancer study: a study of occurrence, risk factors and diagnostic validity.</article-title>
<source>Eur J Epidemiol</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>95</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>102</lpage>. <comment>doi: 10.1007/s10654-009-9404-1</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19936945</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sveen</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bjorkbacka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Orho-Melander</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Engstrom</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Goncalves</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Melander</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bengtsson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>High levels of autoantibodies against apoB100 p210 are associated with lower incidence of atrial fibrillation in women.</article-title>
<source>J Intern Med</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>291</volume>:<fpage>207</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>217</lpage>. <comment>doi: 10.1111/joim.13393</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34532909</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gawalko</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Saljic</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Abu-Taha</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Jespersen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Linz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Nattel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Heijman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fender</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dobrev</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Adiposity-associated atrial fibrillation: molecular determinants, mechanisms, and clinical significance.</article-title>
<source>Cardiovasc Res</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>119</volume>:<fpage>614</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>630</lpage>. <comment>doi: 10.1093/cvr/cvac093</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35689487</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>