<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" id="jeo270150" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Exp Orthop</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Exp Orthop</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.1002/(ISSN)2197-1153</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JEO2</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Experimental Orthopaedics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2197-1153</issn><publisher><publisher-name>John Wiley and Sons Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Hoboken</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39839855</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11746939</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jeo2.70150</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">JEO270150</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Original Paper</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Paper</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Assessment of four sterilization techniques for meniscal allograft transplantation in rabbits</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="jeo270150-cr-0001" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X. S.</given-names></name><xref rid="jeo270150-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="jeo270150-cr-0002" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>H. G.</given-names></name><xref rid="jeo270150-aff-0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="jeo270150-cr-0003" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>D. Q.</given-names></name><xref rid="jeo270150-aff-0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="jeo270150-cr-0004" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>D. Z.</given-names></name><xref rid="jeo270150-aff-0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="jeo270150-cr-0005" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y. T.</given-names></name><xref rid="jeo270150-aff-0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="jeo270150-cr-0006" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z. J.</given-names></name><xref rid="jeo270150-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><address><email>lzjsdd@163.com</email></address></contrib><contrib id="jeo270150-cr-0007" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y. D.</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0009-0006-9980-7702</contrib-id><xref rid="jeo270150-aff-0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><address><email>drzyd@126.com</email></address></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="jeo270150-aff-0001">
<label>
<sup>1</sup>
</label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Department of Orthopedics</named-content>
<institution>Children's Hospital Affiliated to Capital Institute of Pediatrics</institution>
<city>Beijing</city>
<country country="CN">China</country>
</aff><aff id="jeo270150-aff-0002">
<label>
<sup>2</sup>
</label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Senior Department of Orthopedics</named-content>
<institution>the Fourth Medical Center of PLA General Hospital</institution>
<city>Beijing</city>
<country country="CN">China</country>
</aff><aff id="jeo270150-aff-0003">
<label>
<sup>3</sup>
</label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Department of Orthopedics, Senior Department of Orthopedics</named-content>
<institution>the Fifth Medical Center of PLA General Hospital</institution>
<city>Beijing</city>
<country country="CN">China</country>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="correspondenceTo">
<label>*</label>
<bold>Correspondence</bold> Y. D. Zhang, Department of Orthopedics, Senior Department of Orthopedics, the Fifth Medical Center of PLA General Hospital, Beijing 100071, China.<break/>
Email: <email>drzyd@126.com</email>
<break/>
Z. J. Liu, Department of Orthopedics, Children's Hospital Affiliated to Capital Institute of Pediatrics, Beijing 100020, China.<break/>
Email: <email>lzjsdd@163.com</email>
<break/>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><issue seq="66">1</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jeo2.v12.1</issue-id><elocation-id>e70150</elocation-id><history>
<date date-type="rev-recd"><day>25</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date>
<date date-type="received"><day>27</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date>
</history><permissions><!--&#x000a9; 2025 The Author(s). Journal of Experimental Orthopaedics published by John Wiley & Sons Ltd on behalf of European Society of Sports Traumatology, Knee Surgery and Arthroscopy.--><copyright-statement content-type="article-copyright">&#x000a9; 2025 The Author(s). <italic toggle="yes">Journal of Experimental Orthopaedics</italic> published by John Wiley &#x00026; Sons Ltd on behalf of European Society of Sports Traumatology, Knee Surgery and Arthroscopy.</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link> License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="file:JEO2-12-e70150.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><sec id="jeo270150-sec-0010"><title>Purpose</title><p>This study aimed to compare the effects of four sterilization techniques on meniscal allograft transplantation (MAT) in rabbits.</p></sec><sec id="jeo270150-sec-0020"><title>Methods</title><p>In total, 85 medial or lateral meniscuses were obtained from 22 adult New Zealand white rabbits. These 85 meniscal allografts were seeded with <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic>) and randomly divided into five groups (<italic toggle="yes">n&#x02009;</italic>=&#x02009;17): iodine group, Cobalt&#x02010;60 group, glutaraldehyde group, ethylene oxide group and control group. Bacterial colonies of the allografts were determined before (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;7) and after (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;7) sterilization. Histological features were analyzed using haematoxylin and eosin (H&#x00026;E) staining (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3). An additional 50 medial or lateral meniscuses were taken from 13 adult New Zealand white rabbits, and they were kept fresh&#x02010;frozen (&#x02212;40&#x000b0;C) for 1 month. Subsequently, these 50 meniscuses were randomly divided into five groups, which were treated with iodine, Cobalt&#x02010;60, glutaraldehyde, ethylene oxide and normal saline, separately (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;10), and stored at &#x02212;20&#x000b0;C before MAT. MAT was given to the knee joints of the right hind legs of 50 adult Japanese white rabbits. After 6 weeks of MAT, the transplanted meniscal allografts were taken for biomechanical test (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;7) and H&#x00026;E staining (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3).</p></sec><sec id="jeo270150-sec-0030"><title>Results</title><p>The results of the bacterial count indicated that the number of <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> colonies was less than 1 colony&#x02010;forming unit (CFU)/allograft in all five groups after sterilization, except for the control group (415 CFU/allograft). H&#x00026;E staining revealed that allografts in the iodine group presented the complete structure; allografts in the Cobalt&#x02010;60 and glutaraldehyde groups were preserved relatively well; and allografts in the control and ethylene oxide groups were severely destructed, especially in the ethylene oxide group. Using the transplanted allografts, the biomechanical test showed that the maximum load of allografts in each group was significantly different, with ethylene oxide effective sterilization agents being used for disinfecting meniscal grafts (iodine group: 270.71&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;62.81&#x02009;N, Cobalt&#x02010;60 group: 182.14&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;71.29&#x02009;N, glutaraldehyde group: 254.29&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;31.55&#x02009;N, ethylene oxide group: 40.00&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;22.73&#x02009;N and control group: 183.14&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;76.40) (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.001). H&#x00026;E staining with transplanted allografts revealed that allografts in the iodine group had the most intact structure; allografts in the Cobalt&#x02010;60 and glutaraldehyde groups presented a relatively intact structure; and allografts in the control and ethylene oxide groups were seriously damaged, especially in the ethylene oxide group.</p></sec><sec id="jeo270150-sec-0040"><title>Conclusion</title><p>It was found that iodine, Cobalt&#x02010;60, glutaraldehyde and ethylene oxide are effective sterilization agents for disinfecting meniscal grafts. Iodine exhibited superior preservation of both the biomechanics and structural integrity of the meniscal allografts, whereas ethylene oxide caused the most severe destruction to the meniscal allografts.</p></sec><sec id="jeo270150-sec-0050"><title>Level of Evidence</title><p>Not applicable because this is an animal study.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd id="jeo270150-kwd-0001">biomechanics</kwd><kwd id="jeo270150-kwd-0002">meniscal allograft transplantation</kwd><kwd id="jeo270150-kwd-0003">morphological structure</kwd><kwd id="jeo270150-kwd-0004">sterilization</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="funding-0001"><funding-source>National Natural Science Foundation of China</funding-source><award-id>82072451</award-id></award-group><award-group id="funding-0002"><funding-source>Research and Translational Application of Clinical Characteristic Diagnosis and Treatment Techniques in the Capital</funding-source><award-id>Z221100007422014</award-id></award-group><award-group id="funding-0003"><funding-source>Natural Science Foundation of Beijing</funding-source><award-id>7202199</award-id></award-group><award-group id="funding-0004"><funding-source>Project of Children's Hospital affiliated to Capital Institute of Pediatrics</funding-source><award-id>QN2019&#x02010;17</award-id></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="4"/><table-count count="2"/><page-count count="9"/><word-count count="5558"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>source-schema-version-number</meta-name><meta-value>2.0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>January 2025</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>details-of-publishers-convertor</meta-name><meta-value>Converter:WILEY_ML3GV2_TO_JATSPMC version:6.5.4 mode:remove_FC converted:27.02.2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><p content-type="self-citation">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270150-cit-0035">
<string-name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>XS</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Jia</surname>
<given-names>HG</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Gu</surname>
<given-names>DQ</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Luo</surname>
<given-names>DZ</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>YT</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>ZJ</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Assessment of four sterilization techniques for meniscal allograft transplantation in rabbits</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Orthopaedics</source>. <year>2025</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<elocation-id>e70150</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jeo2.70150</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39839855</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
</p><fn-group><fn id="jeo270150-note-0001"><p>X. S. Wang and H. G Jia contributed equally to this study.</p></fn></fn-group></notes></front><body><def-list list-content="abbreviations"><title>Abbreviations</title><def-item><term>CFU</term><def><p>colony&#x02010;forming units</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>H&#x00026;E</term><def><p>haematoxylin and eosin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MAT</term><def><p>meniscal allograft transplantation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>
<italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic>
</term><def><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic>
</p></def></def-item></def-list><sec id="jeo270150-sec-0060"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>The meniscuses function as buffering absorbers that could decrease the contact area of the tibiofemoral joint surface, thereby stabilizing the knee joints [<xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Meniscal injuries would affect the kinematics of the knee, increase the peak contact pressure, and even facilitate the degenerative process of the knee joints [<xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. The management of meniscal injuries includes conservative physical therapy combined with anti&#x02010;inflammatory medications or surgical intervention [<xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. However, previous studies have demonstrated that meniscus resection could significantly increase the stress on the tibiofemoral joint surface and even lead to secondary osteoarthritis [<xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Therefore, allogeneic meniscal allograft transplantations (MATs) promote restoring the native state of the biomechanics in the injured knee and provide effective treatment options for patients with meniscus injuries [<xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>].</p><p>The first successful MAT was performed by Milachowski in 1984 [<xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. MAT was initially regarded as an experimental attempt or salvage procedure to delay arthroplasty in patients with meniscectomy&#x02010;related arthritis [<xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. After years of refinement in recipient indications, graft processing and preservation and operational skills, MAT has been proven effective in reducing pain and restoring knee joint function [<xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. MAT has become an advantageous alternative intervention strategy for patients with meniscal injuries. Although MAT is relatively rarely conducted, which is estimated to be 1/1,000,000 population, the advantage of MAT is still striking it may improve the stability of the knee over meniscectomy [<xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. The disparities in the application of MAT are summarized as follows: (1) the long&#x02010;term benefit in preventing future osteoarthritis remains elusive; (2) economic and ethical issues; (3) the development of meniscal allograft preparation techniques and (4) surgical challenges [<xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>].</p><p>Sterilization, defined as the procedure of eliminating all organisms, is critical in the preparation of allografts because it can prevent the transmission of bacteria or viruses from the donor to the recipient [<xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. The risk of transmitting diseases through connective tissue allografts, including menisci, has been extensively documented [<xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Although the incidence of allograft&#x02010;derived infection is as low as 0.00015%, the transmission of pathogens (e.g., human immunodeficiency virus or hepatitis C virus) is still a health&#x02010;related concern [<xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Irradiation and chemical sterilization are common sterilization techniques for musculoskeletal allografts [<xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. However, potential damages in the mechanical and biochemical properties of the allografts during the sterilization processes have remarkably attracted researchers' attention [<xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Numerous sterilization methods are inappropriate for meniscal allografts due to their adverse effects on grafts or recipients [<xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. It has been proven that Gamma irradiation is associated with adverse effects on the biomechanical properties of meniscal allografts, while ethylene oxide is linked to inflammatory responses [<xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Therefore, the exploration of effective and safe sterilization techniques for MAT is essential.</p><p>The present study aimed to compare the long&#x02010;term efficacy of four common sterilization techniques for MAT in rabbits, including iodine, Cobalt&#x02010;60, glutaraldehyde and ethylene oxide.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials-and-methods" id="jeo270150-sec-0070"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec id="jeo270150-sec-0080"><title>Study design</title><p>With the approval of the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee of the Beijing Keyu (KY20230618005), all experimental procedures were conducted according to the guidelines for the laboratory animals.</p><p>This study was divided into two parts. In the first part, the effectiveness of four sterilization techniques on meniscuses was examined. <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic>) was selected for this experiment due to its clinical relevance, as it is a common pathogen responsible for joint infections, particularly in orthopaedic surgeries and allograft procedures. This choice aimed to replicate a real&#x02010;world clinical scenario, in which <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> contamination is a significant concern. While spores of Bacillus or yeasts are typically used for industrial sterilization quality control, the concentration of this study was to test sterilization effectiveness against a pathogen more likely to be encountered in clinical settings. The <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> strain used in this study was a commercial strain obtained from the American Type Culture Collection, ensuring consistency and reliability across experiments.</p><p>Dissection was performed on 85 medial or lateral menisci from 22 adult New Zealand white rabbits, each with a body weight of 2.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.5&#x02009;kg. These 85 meniscuses were randomly divided into five groups (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;17): iodine group, Cobalt&#x02010;60 group, glutaraldehyde group, ethylene oxide group and control group. This indicated that each group contained 17 menisci. All the meniscuses were seeded with 10<sup>6</sup> colony&#x02010;forming units (CFU)/mL <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> and incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for 48&#x02009;h. From each group, seven meniscuses were randomly selected for microbial analysis (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;7), and the number of <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> colonies was counted. Subsequently, four experimental groups of meniscal allografts were sterilized with iodine, Cobalt&#x02010;60, glutaraldehyde, and ethylene oxide, while the control group was treated with normal saline. The remaining meniscuses in each group were used for histological evaluation (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3) or reserved for further experiments.</p><p>In the second part of the experiment, the long&#x02010;term effects of four sterilization technologies on meniscal allografts were evaluated. Another 50 medial or lateral meniscuses were taken from 13 adult New Zealand white rabbits and kept fresh&#x02010;frozen (&#x02212;40&#x000b0;C) for 1 month. Subsequently, all 50 meniscuses were randomly divided into five groups, treated with iodine, Cobalt&#x02010;60, glutaraldehyde, ethylene oxide or normal saline (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;10). MATs were randomly implanted into the right knee joints of 50 Japanese white rabbits using these meniscal allografts. After 6 weeks, the transplanted meniscal allografts were retrieved for biomechanical testing (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;7) and histological evaluation (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3).</p><p>Notably, the limit of detection for the bacterial colony counts was 1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10&#x000b2; CFU/allograft. CFU counts below this threshold were recorded as &#x02018;&#x0003c;1 CFU/allograft&#x02019; in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="jeo270150-tbl-0001" ref-type="table">1</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="jeo270150-tbl-0001" content-type="Table"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Bacterial colony count of <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> before and after sterilization (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;7).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="left" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="left" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="left" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><thead valign="bottom"><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" valign="bottom"><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Before sterilization (CFU/allograft)</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">After sterilization (CFU/allograft)</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sterilization rate (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iodine</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">629&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;225.00</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;1</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cobalt&#x02010;60</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">526&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;79.00</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;1</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glutaraldehyde</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">537&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;251.00</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;1</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethylene oxide</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">600&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;86.00</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;1</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">620&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;202.00</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">415.00&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;21.50</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.854</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> Value</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.755</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;0.001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="jeo270150-tbl1-note-0001"><p>Abbreviations: CFU, colony&#x02010;forming unit; <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd.</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap></sec><sec id="jeo270150-sec-0090"><title>Harvesting of the allogenic meniscuses</title><p>The New Zealand white rabbits, which were donors of meniscal allografts, were given euthanasia. Their medial or lateral meniscuses were then excised. The meniscuses were washed with normal saline to remove the residual blood and cut into sections with the appropriate shape.</p></sec><sec id="jeo270150-sec-0100"><title>Bacterial colony count</title><p>The meniscuses used as samples for the bacterial colony count were placed in Eppendorf tubes and quickly frozen using liquid nitrogen. The frozen meniscuses were then crushed into powder and suspended in 1000&#x02009;&#x003bc;L of normal saline. To ensure complete bacterial recovery, the samples were vortexed thoroughly in saline solution to detach the bacteria. The entire suspension was serially diluted before plating the dilutions on trypticase&#x02010;soy&#x02010;blood agar 3000<italic toggle="yes">g</italic> for 10&#x02009;min to separate bacterial cells, and the supernatant was collected and plated. The plates were incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for 24&#x02009;h to allow visible <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> colony formation. After the incubation period, the CFU was counted to determine the bacterial load.</p></sec><sec id="jeo270150-sec-0110"><title>Sterilization of the meniscal allografts</title><p>In this study, five groups of menisci underwent different sterilization treatments. The menisci in the iodine group were immersed in a 10% iodine solution for 6&#x02009;h to ensure adequate microbial inactivation. The Cobalt&#x02010;60 group was exposed to gamma radiation at a dose of 25&#x02009;kGy for 24&#x02009;h to achieve sterilization. The glutaraldehyde group was treated with a 2.5% glutaraldehyde solution for 6&#x02009;h, while the ethylene oxide group was exposed to ethylene oxide gas for 24&#x02009;h under controlled conditions. The control group was treated with normal saline for 6&#x02009;h without any sterilization. Following the sterilization procedures, all menisci were thoroughly rinsed by immersing them three times in sterile normal saline for 6&#x02009;h to remove any residual sterilizing agent.</p></sec><sec id="jeo270150-sec-0120"><title>Surgical procedure</title><p>Meniscal allografts were immersed in a solution containing 80&#x02009;mg of gentamicin (1.6&#x02009;mg/mL) in 50&#x02009;mL of normal saline and then trimmed to the appropriate size. The recipient Japanese white rabbits were anaesthetised with ketamine and sumantin. The skin of the transplant site was disinfected three times with iodine, and a medial parapatellar incision was made. A total meniscectomy was conducted by removing the medial meniscus of the right hind legs of the recipient rabbits. The size&#x02010;matched meniscal allograft was placed and sutured to the right hind knee cavity of the recipient. Subsequently, the medial collateral ligament, subcutaneous area and skin were sutured respectively.</p></sec><sec id="jeo270150-sec-0130"><title>Haematoxylin and eosin (H&#x00026;E) staining</title><p>The meniscus tissue was fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde for 24&#x02009;h, followed by dehydration in graded ethanol, clearing in xylene and embedding in paraffin. The embedded meniscus was sectioned into 5&#x02010;&#x000b5;m&#x02010;thick slices using a microtome. H&#x00026;E staining was performed to visualize the histological structure of the meniscus.</p></sec><sec id="jeo270150-sec-0140"><title>Biomechanical test</title><p>The biomechanical test was performed using a computer&#x02010;controlled test machine (Instron) as previously described [<xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. The meniscus was cut into 3&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;3&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;1&#x02009;mm<sup>3</sup> pieces. The working temperature was kept at 23&#x000b0;C, and the meniscus was hydrated with normal saline. The biomechanical test of the meniscus was performed according to the manufacturer's instructions.</p></sec><sec id="jeo270150-sec-0150"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>The quantitative data were analyzed using SPSS 16.0 software (IBM). The differences between the groups were examined via the Student&#x02013;Newman&#x02013;Keuls method and <italic toggle="yes">q</italic> test, and differences among the groups were analyzed by one&#x02010;way analysis of variance (ANOVA). <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="jeo270150-sec-0160"><title>RESULTS</title><sec id="jeo270150-sec-0170"><title>Effectiveness of the four sterilization technologies on meniscus</title><p>The effectiveness of the four sterilization technologies on the meniscus was compared with the bacterial colony count. As presented in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="jeo270150-tbl-0001" ref-type="table">1</xref>, the difference in <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> colony count of the meniscus before sterilization was not statistically significant among the five groups (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.755), indicating that the bacterial burden of the meniscus was comparable across the five groups.</p><p>Following the adjustments in the bacterial retrieval method, including vortexing the samples and serially diluting the suspensions, as well as extending the incubation time to 24&#x02009;h at 37&#x000b0;C, the CFU was counted. This allowed for a more accurate and reliable determination of the bacterial load across all groups. After sterilization, the bacterial colony count of <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> in the iodine, Cobalt&#x02010;60, glutaraldehyde and ethylene oxide groups was less than 1 CFU/allograft, while it was 415.00&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;21.50 CFU/allograft in the control group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001). The sterilization rate in the iodine, Cobalt&#x02010;60, glutaraldehyde and ethylene oxide groups was 100%, while the bacterial reduction rate in the control group was 81.85% (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001).</p><p>These results indicate that iodine, Cobalt&#x02010;60, glutaraldehyde and ethylene oxide were all potent disinfectants for meniscus sterilization, effectively reducing the bacterial load to near zero.</p></sec><sec id="jeo270150-sec-0180"><title>Effects of the four sterilization technologies on the histological features of the fresh meniscuses</title><p>After the sterilization process, the sampling meniscuses from five groups (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3) were stained with H&#x00026;E, and their histological features were analyzed under a light microscope. As illustrated in Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="jeo270150-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, the structures of the meniscuses in the iodine group were the most intact among the five groups, except for a very small number of uniformly distributed small pores within the meniscuses. The structures of the meniscuses in the Cobalt&#x02010;60 group structure were relatively well preserved, accompanied by widely distributed slender spindle&#x02010;shaped small pores, which were arranged in a regular and orderly manner. The structures of the meniscuses in the glutaraldehyde group were relatively well preserved, accompanied by widely distributed short spindle&#x02010;shaped small pores that were arranged irregularly. The structures of the meniscuses in the ethylene oxide group were the most severely damaged, which presented a disordered, tortuous and irregular arrangement, accompanied by widely distributed large cracks and regional tissue debris. The structural damage of the meniscuses in the control group was relatively severe, accompanied by regional tortuous and irregular arrangement and widely distributed tortuous cracks.</p><fig position="float" fig-type="Figure" id="jeo270150-fig-0001"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Histological features of the fresh meniscuses after sterilization.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JEO2-12-e70150-g001" position="anchor" id="jats-graphic-1"/></fig></sec><sec id="jeo270150-sec-0190"><title>Effects of the four sterilization technologies on the biomechanics of meniscal allografts after 6 weeks of transplantation</title><p>A biomechanical test was employed to evaluate the mechanical properties of the meniscal grafts after MAT. As presented in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="jeo270150-tbl-0002" ref-type="table">2</xref>, the iodine group could tolerate the highest average load (270.71&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;62.81&#x02009;N), while the ethylene oxide group only withstood the lowest average load of (40.00&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;22.73&#x02009;N). The average maximal load in the Cobalt&#x02010;60, glutaraldehyde and control groups was 182.14&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;71.29, 254.29&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;31.55 and 183.14&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;76.40&#x02009;N, respectively.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="jeo270150-tbl-0002" content-type="Table"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Biomechanics of the meniscal allografts after 6 weeks of transplantation (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;7).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="left" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><thead valign="bottom"><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" valign="bottom"><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Load (N)</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iodine</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">270.71&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;62.81</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cobalt&#x02010;60</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">182.14&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;71.29</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glutaraldehyde</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">254.29&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;31.55</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethylene oxide</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.00&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;22.73</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">183.14&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;76.40</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> Value</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.000</td></tr></tbody></table><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd.</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap><p>The statistical differences among the groups were evaluated using one&#x02010;way ANOVA (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="jeo270150-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). The results of pairwise comparison showed that the maximum load in the ethylene oxide group was significantly lower than in the Cobalt&#x02010;60, control, glutaraldehyde and iodine groups (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01). The maximum load in the iodine group was significantly higher than in the Cobalt&#x02010;60 and control groups (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05).</p><fig position="float" fig-type="Figure" id="jeo270150-fig-0002"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Biomechanics of the meniscal allograft after 6 weeks of transplantation. *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 and **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JEO2-12-e70150-g004" position="anchor" id="jats-graphic-3"/></fig><p>Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="jeo270150-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref> displays the representative gross morphology of the meniscal allografts before and after the biomechanical test. It was found that meniscal allografts in the ethylene oxide group were crushed into pieces after the biomechanical test. The morphology of meniscal allografts in the iodine, glutaraldehyde, control and Cobalt&#x02010;60 groups was less deformed. It was revealed that meniscuses in the glutaraldehyde group became dark after transplantation.</p><fig position="float" fig-type="Figure" id="jeo270150-fig-0003"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Representative graphs of the gross morphology of the meniscal allografts before and after the biomechanical test.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JEO2-12-e70150-g002" position="anchor" id="jats-graphic-5"/></fig></sec><sec id="jeo270150-sec-0200"><title>Effects of the four sterilization technologies on the histologic features of meniscal allografts after 6 weeks of transplantation</title><p>The histological features of the meniscal allografts after transplantation were assessed using H&#x00026;E staining and were visualized under a light microscope. As illustrated in Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="jeo270150-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, the meniscal allografts in the iodine group presented the complete structure, with a regular overall arrangement, while regionally distributed small and narrow shuttle&#x02010;shaped pores were also observed, which were arranged irregularly. Implanted tissues were found in a few regions in meniscal allografts in the iodine group. The meniscal allografts in the Cobalt&#x02010;60 group presented a relatively complete structure with almost regular arrangement and widely distributed spindle&#x02010;shaped small pores and small cracks. Implanted tissues were observed in some local regions in meniscal allografts in the Cobalt&#x02010;60 group. The structures of meniscal allografts in the glutaraldehyde group were relatively complete, accompanied by regular arrangement and widely distributed small tortuous pores. A great number of inflammatory cells were infiltrated in the implanted tissues in the meniscal allografts in the glutaraldehyde group. The structures of the meniscal allografts in the control group were severely damaged, accompanied by tortuous arrangement and widely distributed large spindle&#x02010;shaped cracks. Implanted tissues with a large number of inflammatory cells were observed. The structural damage of the meniscuses in the ethylene oxide group was the most severe among the five groups. A remarkable number of fragmented tissues and large cracks were widely distributed in the meniscal allografts in the ethylene oxide group.</p><fig position="float" fig-type="Figure" id="jeo270150-fig-0004"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Histological features of the meniscal allograft after 6 weeks of transplantation.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JEO2-12-e70150-g003" position="anchor" id="jats-graphic-7"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="jeo270150-sec-0210"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>In the present study, an evaluation was conducted to assess both the short&#x02010; and long&#x02010;term effects of four common sterilization technologies on disinfecting meniscal allografts. The investigation revealed that iodine, Cobalt&#x02010;60, glutaraldehyde and ethylene oxide proved to be effective sterilization techniques for MAT. Notably, iodine demonstrated superior preservation of meniscal allografts in terms of biomechanics and histological structure, while ethylene oxide exhibited the most pronounced detrimental effect on meniscal allograft integrity.</p><p>Despite advancements in meniscus&#x02010;preserving technologies over the past decades, a recent study highlighted that 65% of arthroscopically identified meniscal tears were irreparable [<xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Surgical interventions for meniscal injuries were considered necessary in the majority of cases, with approximately 1,000,000 meniscectomies performed annually [<xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. However, it is acknowledged that meniscus resection surgeries can impact knee joint biomechanics, potentially leading to the early onset of knee joint osteoarthritis. MAT can be a viable treatment option for patients with meniscal deficiencies, aiming to restore biomechanical properties. Sterilization is a crucial step in the preparation of meniscal allografts, as allograft&#x02010;associated infections pose significant challenges and are considered the most concerning complication of transplantation [<xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. In the present study, the efficacy and long&#x02010;term effects of four disinfectants on meniscal allografts in rabbits were compared.</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> is one of the most common pathogens for allograft&#x02010;associated infections [<xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], and it is also an opportunistic pathogen with a high level of antibiotic resistance [<xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>], motivating us to select <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> as bacterial load in the present study. In this study, the differences in <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> colony count on the meniscuses before sterilization among the five groups were not statistically significant. After sterilization with iodine, Cobalt&#x02010;60, glutaraldehyde and ethylene oxide separately, the <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> colony count in each group was less than 1 CFU/allograft (disinfection rate, 100%), while the <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> colony count was 415 CFU/allograft in the control group. These results indicated that iodine, Cobalt&#x02010;60, glutaraldehyde and ethylene oxide were sufficient to eliminate <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> that seeded onto the meniscuses. H&#x00026;E staining was utilized to evaluate the histological features of the meniscuses. It was found that iodine demonstrated optimal preservation in terms of both the biomechanics and structural integrity of the meniscuses, whereas ethylene oxide caused the most severe deterioration of the meniscal tissue.</p><p>Despite favourable mid&#x02010;term clinical outcomes reported for MAT, the long&#x02010;term clinical implications necessitate further investigation [<xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. McCormick et al. studied 172 MAT cases, noting a 2&#x02010;year survival rate of meniscal grafts at 95% [<xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Saltzman et al. reported survival rates of 98% at 1.7 years, 84% at 5 years and 45% at 10 years after MAT for meniscal grafts [<xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. The factors influencing the survival rate of meniscal grafts were complicated. Recipients' age and physical conditions have been found as the most relevant factors in the clinical outcome of MAT [<xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. The quality of the meniscal grafts also plays a crucial role in determining the prognosis of transplantation [<xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Previous studies have demonstrated that sterilization could affect the biomechanical and histological properties of meniscal grafts [<xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Therefore, the long&#x02010;term effects of four common sterilization agents on the meniscal allografts in rabbits were assessed in the present study.</p><p>The meniscus, crucial for weight&#x02010;bearing, has been extensively investigated in previous research [<xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Alterations in contact stress have attracted researchers' attention in the context of meniscectomy [<xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Prior research reported a substantial increase in contact pressure (up to 110%) and a reduction in the contact area of the knee joint (up to 75%) in patients with partial&#x02010;to&#x02010;total meniscectomy, particularly in cadaver studies [<xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Abnormal load conditions in the knee joint can lead to cartilage injury, resulting in vascular invasion, dehydration and ossification of the cartilage. Consequently, meniscectomy is commonly associated with an elevated risk of early&#x02010;onset osteoarthritis [<xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. MAT has been proposed as an operative option for total or subtotal meniscectomies to restore the native biomechanical properties of the knee joint [<xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Therefore, tests were conducted to assess the effects of four sterilization agents on the biomechanics of meniscal allografts. The results indicated that meniscal grafts in the iodine group endured the highest average load (270.71&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;62.81&#x02009;N), while those in the ethylene oxide group experienced only 40.00&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;22.73&#x02009;N. The average maximum load in the Cobalt&#x02010;60 and glutaraldehyde groups was 182.14&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;71.29 and 254.29&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;31.55&#x02009;N, respectively. Additionally, histological evaluations at six weeks after MAT revealed that the meniscal grafts in the iodine group were well&#x02010;preserved, whereas those in the ethylene oxide group exhibited the most severe destruction. These findings suggest that iodine is an efficient and safe disinfectant for meniscal graft preparation, while ethylene oxide is inappropriate for the sterilization of meniscuses.</p><p>Iodine has a long history of application in the sterilization of mucosa and skin [<xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Particularly effective for local disinfection therapy, iodine is widely utilized for surface decontamination and exhibits a broad antimicrobial spectrum, targeting bacteria, viruses, fungi and protozoans [<xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Notably, iodine ensures rapid disinfection within seconds, with negligible resistance and minimal allergic or toxic risks [<xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. In clinical settings, iodine finds extensive use for procedures, such as skin or mucosa disinfection before or after surgery [<xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Zhao et al. reported that a polyvinylpyrrolidone&#x02010;iodine solution could preserve the mechanical properties of the osteogenic allografts [<xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Consistent with the findings of a previous study [<xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], the present study revealed iodine as the most effective disinfectant for preserving the biomechanical and histological properties of meniscal grafts.</p><p>Gamma irradiation was noted to be associated with negative influences on the biomechanical features of the meniscal tissue [<xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. The present study, in line with prior research [<xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], indicated that Cobalt&#x02010;60 is inferior to iodine in preserving the biomechanical and histological properties of meniscal grafts. Widely employed as a biocide in clinical settings, glutaraldehyde is also utilized for allograft disinfection [<xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. It is also used in allograft disinfection [<xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. It has been reported that glutaraldehyde could desensitize the vascular allograft [<xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Powers et al. found that glutaraldehyde&#x02010;cross&#x02010;linked meniscuses presented an acceptable histocompatibility [<xref rid="jeo270150-bib-0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. The findings of the present study suggested that while glutaraldehyde relatively well preserved the biomechanical and histological properties of meniscal grafts, it was still inferior to iodine in terms of histological preservation. The use of <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> as a model for assessing sterilization effectiveness in this study could be justified for several reasons. First, <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> is a common pathogen associated with allograft infections, making it clinically relevant in the context of MAT. Its prevalence in such infections highlights the importance of evaluating sterilization techniques against a representative and opportunistic pathogen. Additionally, <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> exhibits a high level of antibiotic resistance, posing a significant risk for post&#x02010;transplant infections. By using this bacterium, the study could provide a reliable assessment of the sterilization methods' effectiveness, as they must demonstrate the ability to eliminate resistant strains. Furthermore, the significant reduction of <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> colonies observed after applying the sterilization techniques suggested their efficacy in achieving disinfection, reinforcing the choice of this model. Future studies will expand on this by exploring other pathogens of interest, while the current findings contribute valuable insights into the safety of meniscal allograft procedures.</p><p>The strength of this study lies in its novelty as the first investigation to compare the effects of four common sterilization agents on MAT in rabbits. One limitation of the study is that the limit of detection for CFU counts was 1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10&#x000b2; CFU/allograft. As a result, any bacterial presence below this threshold could not be quantified, and values below this limit were recorded as &#x02018;&#x0003c;1 CFU/allograft&#x02019;. This should be taken into account when interpreting the results. The findings highlighted iodine as a potent and safe disinfectant for meniscal grafts. However, it is important to note that this study was conducted at the animal level, and thus, the conclusions drawn from this study require further clinical evaluation.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="jeo270150-sec-0220"><title>CONCLUSIONS</title><p>In conclusion, the present research demonstrated that iodine, Cobalt&#x02010;60, glutaraldehyde and ethylene oxide could be effective sterilization agents for disinfecting meniscal grafts. Iodine emerged as an efficient and safe disinfectant for MAT, while ethylene oxide posed a significant risk of severe destruction to meniscal allografts.</p></sec><sec id="jeo270150-sec-0230"><title>AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS</title><p>
<bold>X. S. Wang</bold>: writing&#x02014;original draft, software, formal analysis. <bold>H. G. Jia</bold>: writing&#x02014;review and editing, validation, data curation. <bold>D. Q. Gu</bold>: investigation, project administration. <bold>D. Z. Luo</bold>: validation, resources. <bold>Y. T. Zhao</bold>: investigation, data curation. <bold>Z. J. Liu</bold>: resources, supervision. <bold>Y. D. Zhang</bold>: conceptualization, funding acquisition, supervision.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="jeo270150-sec-0260"><title>CONFLICT OF INTEREST STATEMENT</title><p>The authors declare no conflicts of interest.</p></sec><sec id="jeo270150-sec-0250"><title>ETHICS STATEMENT</title><p>All animal protocols were approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee of the Beijing Keyu (KY20230618005). All animal experiments were carried out in accordance with relevant guidelines and regulations. All methods were reported in accordance with ARRIVE guidelines.</p></sec></body><back><ack id="jeo270150-sec-0240"><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title><p>This work was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (82072451), the Research and Translational Application of Clinical Characteristic Diagnosis and Treatment Techniques in the Capital (Z221100007422014), the Natural Science Foundation of Beijing (7202199), and Project of Children's Hospital affiliated to Capital Institute of Pediatrics (QN2019&#x02010;17).</p></ack><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="jeo270150-sec-0280"><title>DATA AVAILABILITY STATEMENT</title><p>The data that support the findings of this study are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request.</p></sec><ref-list content-type="cited-references" id="jeo270150-bibl-0001"><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="jeo270150-bib-0001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270150-cit-0001">
<string-name>
<surname>Aavik</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Kibur</surname>
<given-names>RT</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Lieberg</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Lepner</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Aunapuu</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Arend</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Cold&#x02010;stored venous allografts in different preserving solutions: a study on changes in vein wall morphology</article-title>. <source>Scand J Surg</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>108</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>67</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>75</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30319041</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270150-bib-0002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270150-cit-0002">
<string-name>
<surname>Ahmad&#x02010;Mansour</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Loubet</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Pouget</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Dunyach&#x02010;Remy</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Sotto</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Lavigne</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>
<italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> toxins: an update on their pathogenic properties and potential treatments</article-title>. <source>Toxins</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<elocation-id>677</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34678970</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270150-bib-0003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270150-cit-0003">
<string-name>
<surname>Bansal</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Floyd</surname>
<given-names>ER</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>A Kowalski</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Aikman</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Elrod</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Burkey</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Meniscal repair: the current state and recent advances in augmentation</article-title>. <source>J Orthop Res</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1368</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1382</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33751642</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270150-bib-0004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270150-cit-0004">
<string-name>
<surname>Baratz</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Fu</surname>
<given-names>FH</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Mengato</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Meniscal tears: the effect of meniscectomy and of repair on intraarticular contact areas and stress in the human knee</article-title>. <source>Am J Sports Med</source>. <year>1986</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>270</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>275</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3755296</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270150-bib-0005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270150-cit-0005">
<string-name>
<surname>Bui</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Lovric</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Oliver</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Bertollo</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Broe</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Walsh</surname>
<given-names>WR</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Meniscal allograft sterilisation: effect on biomechanical and histological properties</article-title>. <source>Cell Tissue Bank</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>467</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>475</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25589449</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270150-bib-0006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270150-cit-0006">
<string-name>
<surname>Cavendish</surname>
<given-names>PA</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>DiBartola</surname>
<given-names>AC</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Everhart</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Kuzma</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>WJ</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Flanigan</surname>
<given-names>DC</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Meniscal allograft transplantation: a review of indications, techniques, and outcomes</article-title>. <source>Knee Surg Sports Traumatol Arthrosc</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>3539</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3550</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32415360</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270150-bib-0007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270150-cit-0007">
<string-name>
<surname>Dantas</surname>
<given-names>LR</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Wollmann</surname>
<given-names>LC</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Suss</surname>
<given-names>PH</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Kraft</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ribeiro</surname>
<given-names>VST</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Tuon</surname>
<given-names>FF</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Disinfection protocol for human musculoskeletal allografts in tissue banking using hydrogen peroxide 30</article-title>. <source>Cell Tissue Bank</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>643</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>649</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34091815</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270150-bib-0008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270150-cit-0008">
<string-name>
<surname>Ditkowski</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Leeten</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Jashari</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Jones</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Heying</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>
<italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> adheres avidly to decellularised cardiac homograft tissue in vitro in the fibrinogen&#x02010;dependent manner</article-title>. <source>Cardiol Young</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1783</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1787</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32951625</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270150-bib-0009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270150-cit-0009">
<string-name>
<surname>Eras</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Graffunder</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ahmed</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Brune</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Influence of peracetic acid&#x02010;ethanol sterilisation on the biomechanical properties of human meniscus transplants</article-title>. <source>J Exp Orthop</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>18</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33674898</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270150-bib-0010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270150-cit-0010">
<string-name>
<surname>Espejo&#x02010;Reina</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Aguilera</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Espejo&#x02010;Reina</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Espejo&#x02010;Reina</surname>
<given-names>MP</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Espejo&#x02010;Baena</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>One&#x02010;third of meniscal tears are repairable: an epidemiological study evaluating meniscal tear patterns in stable and unstable knees</article-title>. <source>Arthroscopy</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>857</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>863</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30704886</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270150-bib-0011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270150-cit-0011">
<string-name>
<surname>Gluck</surname>
<given-names>TM</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Lamberti</surname>
<given-names>JJ</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>El&#x02010;Said</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Devaney</surname>
<given-names>EJ</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Murthy</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Long&#x02010;term results using glutaraldehyde&#x02010;treated homograft pericardium in congenital heart surgery</article-title>. <source>Ann Thorac Surg</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>113</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>182</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>190</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33290739</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270150-bib-0012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270150-cit-0012">
<string-name>
<surname>He</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Wan</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Qiu</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Preparation and characterization of an optimized meniscal extracellular matrix scaffold for meniscus transplantation</article-title>. <source>Front Bioeng Biotechnol</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<elocation-id>779</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32775323</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270150-bib-0013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270150-cit-0013">
<string-name>
<surname>Jain</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Kumar</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Arora</surname>
<given-names>VK</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Saha</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Aggarwal</surname>
<given-names>AN</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Jain</surname>
<given-names>AK</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Study of cell viability and etiology of contamination in decalcified bone allograft: a pilot study</article-title>. <source>Indian J Orthop</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>56</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>16</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>23</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35070138</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270150-bib-0014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270150-cit-0014">
<string-name>
<surname>Kaarre</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Herman</surname>
<given-names>ZJ</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Zsidai</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Grassi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Zaffagnini</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Samuelsson</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Meniscus allograft transplantation for biologic knee preservation: gold standard or dilemma?</article-title>
<source>Knee Surg Sports Traumatol Arthrosc</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>3579</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3581</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36205759</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270150-bib-0015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270150-cit-0015">
<string-name>
<surname>Makker</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Lamba</surname>
<given-names>AK</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Faraz</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Tandon</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Sheikh Ab Hamid</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Aggarwal</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Comparative evaluation of bioburden and sterility of indigenously prepared bone allograft with and without gentamicin</article-title>. <source>Cell Tissue Bank</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>243</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>253</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30903410</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270150-bib-0016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270150-cit-0016">
<string-name>
<surname>Matei</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Puscas</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Patrascu</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Lehene</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ziebro</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Scurtu</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Stability of glutaraldehyde in biocide compositions</article-title>. <source>Int J Mol Sci</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<elocation-id>3372</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32397667</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270150-bib-0017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270150-cit-0017">
<string-name>
<surname>McCormick</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Harris</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Abrams</surname>
<given-names>GD</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Hussey</surname>
<given-names>KE</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Wilson</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Frank</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Survival and reoperation rates after meniscal allograft transplantation: analysis of failures for 172 consecutive transplants at a minimum 2&#x02010;year follow&#x02010;up</article-title>. <source>Am J Sports Med</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>892</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>897</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24532597</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270150-bib-0018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270150-cit-0018">
<string-name>
<surname>Nguyen</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Chikkalingaiah</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Walker</surname>
<given-names>PD</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Wall</surname>
<given-names>BM</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Resolution of IgA and C3 immune deposits in <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus</italic> infection&#x02010;associated glomerulonephritis in a kidney transplant recipient</article-title>. <source>Clin Nephrol</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>94</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>97</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>102</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32567542</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270150-bib-0019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270150-cit-0019">
<string-name>
<surname>Powers</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Davenport</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Wisnewski</surname>
<given-names>PJ</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Glutaraldehyde&#x02010;cross&#x02010;linked meniscal allografts: clinical, gross, and histological results</article-title>. <source>J Invest Surg</source>. <year>1988</year>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>249</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>257</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3155294</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270150-bib-0020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270150-cit-0020">
<string-name>
<surname>Ronnblad</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Barenius</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Engstrom</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Eriksson</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Predictive factors for failure of meniscal repair: a retrospective dual&#x02010;center analysis of 918 consecutive cases</article-title>. <source>Orthop J Sports Med</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<elocation-id>2325967120905529</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32284936</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270150-bib-0021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270150-cit-0021">
<string-name>
<surname>Saltzman</surname>
<given-names>BM</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Meyer</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Weber</surname>
<given-names>AE</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Poland</surname>
<given-names>SG</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Yanke</surname>
<given-names>AB</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Cole</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Prospective clinical and radiographic outcomes after concomitant anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction and meniscal allograft transplantation at a mean 5&#x02010;year follow&#x02010;up</article-title>. <source>Am J Sports Med</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>550</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>562</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28272928</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270150-bib-0022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270150-cit-0022">
<string-name>
<surname>Sherman</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>DiPaolo</surname>
<given-names>ZJ</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ray</surname>
<given-names>TE</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Sachs</surname>
<given-names>BM</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Oladeji</surname>
<given-names>LO</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Meniscus injuries</article-title>. <source>Clin Sports Med</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>165</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>183</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31767104</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270150-bib-0023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270150-cit-0023">
<string-name>
<surname>Southworth</surname>
<given-names>TM</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Naveen</surname>
<given-names>NB</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Tauro</surname>
<given-names>TM</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Chahla</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Cole</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Meniscal allograft transplants</article-title>. <source>Clin Sports Med</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>93</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>123</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31767113</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270150-bib-0024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270150-cit-0024">
<string-name>
<surname>Spierings</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Velthuijs</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Mansoor</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Bertrand</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Uquillas</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ito</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>A decellularized and sterilized human meniscus allograft for off&#x02010;the&#x02010;shelf meniscus replacement</article-title>. <source>J Exp Orthop</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>116</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36464727</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270150-bib-0025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270150-cit-0025">
<string-name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Jiang</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prognostic factors to determine survivorship of meniscal allograft transplant: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Orthop J Sports Med</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<elocation-id>23259671211007215</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34159210</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270150-bib-0026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270150-cit-0026">
<string-name>
<surname>Wells</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Scanaliato</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Dunn</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Garcia</surname>
<given-names>EJ</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Meniscal injuries: mechanism and classification</article-title>. <source>Sports Med Arthrosc</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>154</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>157</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34398118</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270150-bib-0027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270150-cit-0027">
<string-name>
<surname>Willinger</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Foehr</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Achtnich</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Forkel</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Voss</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Liska</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effect of lower limb alignment in medial meniscus&#x02010;deficient knees on tibiofemoral contact pressure</article-title>. <source>Orthop J Sports Med</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<elocation-id>2325967118824611</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30800688</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270150-bib-0028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270150-cit-0028">
<string-name>
<surname>Willinger</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Lang</surname>
<given-names>JJ</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Berthold</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Muench</surname>
<given-names>LN</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Achtnich</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Forkel</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Varus alignment aggravates tibiofemoral contact pressure rise after sequential medial meniscus resection</article-title>. <source>Knee Surg Sports Traumatol Arthrosc</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1055</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1063</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31377827</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270150-bib-0029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270150-cit-0029">
<string-name>
<surname>Witten</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Houghtaling</surname>
<given-names>PL</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Shrestha</surname>
<given-names>NK</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Gordon</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Jaber</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Blackstone</surname>
<given-names>EH</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Aortic allograft infection risk</article-title>. <source>J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>165</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1303</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1315.e9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34366128</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270150-bib-0030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270150-cit-0030">
<string-name>
<surname>Worhacz</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Carter</surname>
<given-names>TR</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Meniscal allograft transplantation: does surgical technique influence clinical outcomes?</article-title>
<source>Curr Rev Musculoskelet Med</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>163</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>172</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37014608</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270150-bib-0031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270150-cit-0031">
<string-name>
<surname>Yow</surname>
<given-names>BG</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Donohue</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Tennent</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Meniscal allograft transplantation</article-title>. <source>Sports Med Arthrosc</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>168</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>172</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34398122</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270150-bib-0032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270150-cit-0032">
<string-name>
<surname>Zaffagnini</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Di Paolo</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Stefanelli</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Dal Fabbro</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Macchiarola</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Lucidi</surname>
<given-names>GA</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>The biomechanical role of meniscal allograft transplantation and preliminary in&#x02010;vivo kinematic evaluation</article-title>. <source>J Exp Orthop</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>27</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31240420</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270150-bib-0033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270150-cit-0033">
<string-name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effects of chemical sterilization and gamma irradiation on the biochemical and biomechanical properties of human tendon allografts in vitro study</article-title>. <source>Orthop Surg</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>2657</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2668</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36054510</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270150-bib-0034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270150-cit-0034">
<string-name>
<surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Hu</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Xia</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Hou</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Use of polyvinylpyrrolidone&#x02010;iodine solution for sterilisation and preservation improves mechanical properties and osteogenesis of allografts</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<elocation-id>38669</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27934929</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>