<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="abstract"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Eur Psychiatry</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Eur Psychiatry</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">EPA</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>European Psychiatry</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0924-9338</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1778-3585</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11859965</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1192/j.eurpsy.2024.1322</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="other">EPV0671</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S0924933824013221</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Abstract</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="section"><subject>e-Poster Viewing</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Practice recommendations to manage Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease based on the targeted behavioral and psychological symptoms</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Ouazzani Housni Touhami</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2940" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2941" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2942" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor1174" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Layoussifi</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2940" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2941" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2942" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Benjelloun</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2940" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2941" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2942" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff2940"><sup>1</sup>Faculty of Medicine, <institution>Mohammed VI University of Health and Sciences</institution></aff><aff id="aff2941"><sup>2</sup>Psychiatry Department, <institution>Cheikh Khalifa International University Hospital</institution></aff><aff id="aff2942"><sup>3</sup>Psychiatry Department, <institution>Mohammed VI International University Hospital</institution>, <city>Casablanca</city>, <country>Morocco</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1174"><label>*</label>Corresponding author.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="collection" iso-8601-date="2024-04"><month>4</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>67</volume><issue seq="1297">Suppl 1</issue><issue-title content-type="special_issue">Abstracts of the 32nd European Congress of Psychiatry</issue-title><fpage>S638</fpage><lpage>S638</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2024</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Author(s)</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article, distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution licence (<uri xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</uri>), which permits unrestricted re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="S0924933824013221a.pdf"/><abstract><sec id="sec7057"><title>Introduction</title><p>Behavioral and psychological symptoms (BPS) of Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease, known as neuropsychiatric symptoms, involve a range of symptoms that include agitation, psychosis (hallucinations, delusions), affective symptoms (depression and anxiety), apathy, and sleep disturbances. These behavioral and psychological symptoms harm the patients&#x02019; daily lives and significantly burden their families. Managing BPS of Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease requires a targeted approach focused on each symptom to achieve a better therapeutic response.</p></sec><sec id="sec7058"><title>Objectives</title><p>Providing practice pharmacological recommendations targeted to each of the behavioral and psychological symptoms of Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease.</p></sec><sec id="sec7059"><title>Methods</title><p>A literature review was conducted using Medline via PubMed, Embase, PsycINFO, and Cochrane databases until September 2023.</p></sec><sec id="sec7060"><title>Results</title><p>There is a consensus in the literature that non-pharmacological approaches should be recommended as the first-line treatment for most behavioral and psychological symptoms of Alzheimer&#x02019;s.</p><p>Second-generation antipsychotics (risperidone and olanzapine, with improved efficacy; aripiprazole and quetiapine, with better tolerance) are recommended for severe agitation states with a risk of self or hetero-aggression, as well as for persistent psychotic symptoms in Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease. The benefit-risk balance of these agents must be assessed, with close monitoring of heart arrhythmias, metabolic risk, orthostatic hypotension, and extrapyramidal symptoms. The recommendations suggest tapering antipsychotics within the first three months of their prescription. Selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs) such as Escitalopram, Citalopram, and Sertraline can be considered a therapeutic option for persistent affective symptoms (depression and anxiety) with significant functional impairment or suicidal risk, severe apathy, or constant agitation. Minimum effective doses are recommended for Escitalopram and Citalopram due to the risk of QT interval prolongation. There is limited evidence regarding the effectiveness of benzodiazepines, mood stabilizers, cholinesterase inhibitors, and memantine for various behavioral and psychological symptoms; the benefit-risk ratio and therapeutic response do not support the prescription of these agents. Melatonin and Mirtazapine have limited benefits for sleep disturbances, while benzodiazepines, antihistamines, and antipsychotics should be avoided.</p></sec><sec id="sec7061"><title>Conclusions</title><p>The pharmacological approach should target a thorough clinical assessment of the psychopathological dimensions of behavioral and psychological symptoms of Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease. The prescription should be based on evaluating the benefit-risk balance and adherence to literature recommendations for patient safety.</p></sec><sec id="sec7062"><title>Disclosure of Interest</title><p>None Declared</p></sec></abstract><counts><page-count count="1"/></counts></article-meta></front></article>