<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Implant Dent</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int J Implant Dent</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>International Journal of Implant Dentistry</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2198-4034</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer Berlin Heidelberg</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39853624</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11759739</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">591</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40729-025-00591-0</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Treatment of peri-implant mucositis using an Er:YAG laser or an ultrasonic device: a randomized, controlled clinical trial</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-8092-665X</contrib-id><name><surname>Bengtsson</surname><given-names>Viveca Wallin</given-names></name><address><email>viveca.wallin_bengtsson@hkr.se</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5936-1116</contrib-id><name><surname>Aoki</surname><given-names>Akira</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1610-7430</contrib-id><name><surname>Mizutani</surname><given-names>Koji</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0009-0005-9402-3952</contrib-id><name><surname>Lindahl</surname><given-names>Christel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-0992-2362</contrib-id><name><surname>Renvert</surname><given-names>Stefan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/00tkrft03</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.16982.34</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0697 1236</institution-id><institution>Department of Oral Health, Faculty of Oral Health Science, </institution><institution>Kristianstad University, </institution></institution-wrap>291 88 Kristianstad, Sweden </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/05dqf9946</institution-id><institution>Department of Periodontology, Graduate School of Medical and Dental Sciences, </institution><institution>Institute of Science Tokyo, </institution></institution-wrap>Yushima, Bunkyo-Ku, Tokyo, Japan </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/0093a8w51</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.418400.9</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2284 8991</institution-id><institution>Blekinge Institute of Technology, </institution></institution-wrap>Karlskrona, Sweden </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/02tyrky19</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.8217.c</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 9705</institution-id><institution>Division of Restorative Dentistry and Periodontology, </institution><institution>Dublin Dental University Hospital, Trinity College Dublin, </institution></institution-wrap>Dublin, Ireland </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>24</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>24</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>12</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>6</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>5</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>9</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2025, corrected publication 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Purpose</title><p id="Par1">The study assessed the clinical outcomes following treatment of peri-implant mucositis using Er:YAG laser or an ultrasonic device over six months. Patients' experience of pain, aesthetics, and Quality of life were further assessed.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">One dental implant, per included patient, diagnosed with peri-implant mucositis underwent treatment with an Er:YAG laser (test) or an ultrasonic scaler (control) randomly. Treatments were performed at baseline and months three and six. At each session, oral hygiene was instructed after plaque registration, and the patient was guided in proper cleaning technique using a toothbrush and interproximal aids as needed. Full mouth bleeding on probing (FMBoP), full mouth plaque score (FMPS), implant bleeding on probing (BoP), implant mean graded bleeding (mBI), implant probing pocket depts (PPD), implant suppuration and bone levels were assessed. Oral health-related Quality of life (OHQoL) and visual analog scales (VAS), which reflect aesthetic satisfaction and pain of the treatment, were also evaluated.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">Forty-six patients were included. FMBoP was significantly reduced from 30.1 to 21.5% (test) (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001) respectively from 35.0% to 30% (control) (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01). FMPS showed significant reduction from 61.5 to 32.7% (test) (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001) and from 58.7 to 39.1% (control) (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001). At the implant BoP reduced from 89.0 to 55.7% (test) (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001) respectively from 94.9 to 63.7% (control) (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001). mBI was reduced from 1.3 to 0.6 (test) (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01) and from 1.9 to 0.8 (control) (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001). Distribution of &#x0201c;no bleeding&#x0201d; increased from 13 to 61% (test) (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) and from 0 to 35% (control) (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). At month three, statistically significant intergroup differences were shown for PPD&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;4&#x000a0;mm with 43.5% (test) respectively 73.9% (control) (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). At month six, statistically significant intergroup differences, were shown for FMBoP 21.5% (test) respectively 30% (control) (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) and for plaque score at the implant 4.0% (test) respectively 26% (control) (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). Less pain was reported in the laser group at three days 0.08 (test) respectively 0.2 (control) (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par4">Treatment of peri-implant mucositis was effective regardless of whether the treatment was performed with an Er:YAG laser or an ultrasonic scaler. Fewer diseased sites were diagnosed at six months following laser treatment.</p><p id="Par5"><italic>Trial registration</italic>: Registered at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.clinicaltrials.gov">www.clinicaltrials.gov</ext-link>: study no, NCT05772299.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Er:YAG laser</kwd><kwd>Patient-reported outcome measures</kwd><kwd>Peri-implant mucositis</kwd><kwd>Professional mechanical plaque removal</kwd><kwd>Ultrasonic scaler</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Morita Corporation Japan J. MORITA MFG. CORP., Japan</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Kristianstad University</institution></funding-source></award-group><open-access><p>Open access funding provided by Kristianstad University.</p></open-access></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Deutsche Gesellschaft f&#x000fc;r Implantologie im Zahn&#x02010;, Mund&#x02010; und Kieferbereich e.V., Japanese Society of Oral Implantology 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par6">Teeth that have been lost are often replaced with dental implants. The prognosis for dental implant treatment is good, and a survival rate of 93% has been reported after 20&#x000a0;years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. However, peri-implant mucositis or peri-implantitis is a common complication. On a patient level, the prevalence of peri-implant mucositis ranges from 1 to 47% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>], and meta-analyses estimated a weighted mean prevalence of peri-implant mucositis of 43% (CI: 32&#x02013;54%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>].</p><p id="Par7">The objective of peri-implant mucositis treatment is to eliminate or significantly reduce the levels of pathogens to a level resulting in a clinically healthy situation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>] and the therapy should be evaluated 2&#x02013;3&#x000a0;months after treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>].</p><p id="Par8">Dental implants generally have a screw-shaped design, and to facilitate healing and osseointegration, the surface structure is often rough. Treatment models effectively used to treat the tooth's root surfaces with periodontal diseases, like submarginal instrumentation, are challenging to use on the rough threaded implant surface [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>].</p><p id="Par9">The European Federation of Periodontology (EFP) clinical practical guideline 2023 recommends self-performed, effective oral hygiene and professional mechanical plaque removal (PMPR) when treating peri-implant mucositis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. PMPR aims to reduce soft tissue inflammation by removing hard and soft deposits from the surface of the dental implant and the supra-structure. PMPR can be performed using an ultrasonic device with plastic or carbon-coated tips, an air-polishing device, plastic, carbon or titanium curettes, and lasers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>].</p><p id="Par10">Randomized clinical trials evaluating laser treatment of peri-implant mucositis are lacking [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Patient-reported outcome measures (PROMs) have only infrequently been studied evaluating the prevention and management of peri-implant mucositis and peri-implantitis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>] and especially not postoperative pain, aesthetics related to the treatment and the effect on Quality of life (OHRQoL) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. The aim of the present study was to assess clinical outcomes following treatment of peri-implant mucositis using either an Er:YAG laser device or an ultrasonic device over six months. A second aim was to assess patients' experience of pain, aesthetics, and Quality of life in treating peri-implant mucositis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Study design</title><p id="Par11">This study was a single-blinded randomized six-month clinical trial (RCT) approved by the National Ethics Review Board in Uppsala, Sweden (2020-02586). The RCT was conducted according to the World Medical Association Declaration of Helsinki principles, revised in 2013. The CONSORT guidelines for clinical trials were followed. The study was registered under <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.clinicaltrials.gov">www.clinicaltrials.gov</ext-link> (study no. NCT05772299).</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Study population</title><p id="Par12">The patients were referred for a treatment of peri-implant mucositis. Sixty-four patients were screened and reviewed for medical history and available radiographs. Potential cases, according to the inclusion and exclusion criteria, further underwent a full mouth routine periodontal examination. Forty-six subjects who fulfilled the inclusion criteria and consented were consecutively included.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Inclusion criteria&#x02014;presence of peri-implant mucositis</title><p id="Par13">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p id="Par14">One dental implant with a minimum of one or more peri-implant sites with probing depth&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;4&#x000a0;mm combined with bleeding and/or pus on probing</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par15">A limited allowed bone loss&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;2&#x000a0;mm measured from the implant shoulder (changes resulting from initial bone remodelling)</p></list-item></list></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Exclusion criteria</title><p id="Par16">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p id="Par17">Subjects with uncontrolled diabetes mellitus (HbA1c&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;6.5)</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par18">Subjects requiring prophylactic antibiotics</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par19">Subjects taking prednisolone</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par20">Subjects taking medications with effects on gingival growth</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par21">Subjects taking systemic antibiotics in the preceding month</p></list-item></list></p><p id="Par22">For confidentiality, coding was used and saved according to the regulations of Kristianstad University, Sweden. The patients were referred for treatment between 2021 and 2023. Due to Covid 19, when no patient treatment was performed the start of the study was delayed. Before entering the study, a preparatory treatment phase was performed, including instruction in oral hygiene measures and debridement of teeth and implants not to be part of the study.&#x000a0;Good patient motivation and compliance were also identified. The patients were informed about the study and filled out written consent.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Randomization</title><p id="Par23">After entering the study, patients were randomly assigned to treatment with an Er:YAG laser (test) or an ultrasonic device (control) using pre-prepared randomization according to pre-defined computerized randomization.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Measurements</title><p id="Par24">The clinical study was conducted at the speciality clinic of periodontology at Kristianstad University. Unaware of the treatment, the same examiner (CLL) performed the measurements, and the patients were asked not to talk about their treatment. Measurements were recorded at baseline and in months one, three, and six using a manual plastic probe tip diameter of 0.5&#x000a0;mm (<italic>Colorvue</italic> Probe, <italic>Hu-Friedy</italic>, <italic>USA</italic>) and probing force of 0.2 N., The following measurements were recorded for the full mouth: bleeding on probing (FMBoP) (4 sites/tooth, 6 sites/implant) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>], plaque score (FMPS) (4 sites/tooth, 6 sites/implant) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Measurements at the implant were: bleeding on probing (BoP) (6 sites), severity of bleeding graded 0&#x02013;3 0&#x02009;=&#x02009;no bleeding, 1&#x02009;=&#x02009;a dot of bleeding, 2&#x02009;=&#x02009;a line of bleeding, and 3&#x02009;=&#x02009;a drop of bleeding (6 sites) (i.e. modified bleeding index or mBI) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>], suppuration (6 sites), plaque (6 sites), probing pocket depths (PPDs) (6 sites), hyperplasia, buccal recession of the mucosal margin.</p><p id="Par25">Patient evaluation of the treatment: Oral health&#x02013;related quality of life (OHQoL) was measured with the Oral Health Impact Profile&#x02013;14 version (OHIP-14) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>] at baseline and month six. The Quality of life was expressed as the sum of the fourteen questions, a maximum of 56 scores. The mean values were calculated. A lower score indicates high OHQoL, and a higher score indicates low OHQoL. The analysis did not include patients who had not answered all questions.</p><p id="Par26">Visual Analogue Scales consisted of a 10-point graded straight horizontal line, with the left end indicating 0 "no pain and the right end indicating 10 "worst pain". The VAS concerned pain during treatment, the same day, day two and day three after the treatment. Further, the other VAS reflected the patients' aesthetic satisfaction at baseline and month six. The left end on the VAS indicated "not at all satisfied", and the right was "very satisfied". Each patient's mean visual analogue score was calculated.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Radiographic examination</title><p id="Par27">Intraoral digital periapical standardized radiographs of the site of interest were taken with a bite-block to detect loss of bone at baseline and month six. Radiographs were analysed by an independent and blinded examiner (VWB) using the Synedra View software for personal computers. The known distance between implant thread pitch lengths was used to calibrate the images. The distance between the implant shoulder and the most superior alveolar bone level on the mesial and distal aspects of the implant was measured and merged. The intra-class coefficient (ICC) for the distance between the implant shoulder and the alveolar bone level was 0.94 (95% CI: 0.84&#x02013;0.98, p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.00).</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Treatment procedures</title><p id="Par28">The same treatments were performed at baseline, months three and six. Final evaluation data was provided in month six. All treatments were performed by a non-blinded periodontist (VWN). No implant-supported constructions were removed, and no local anaesthesia was used. At each session and after plaque registration, the patients were instructed to use proper home care using a toothbrush and interproximal aids as needed. Treatment in the test group (test) was done using an Er: YAG laser (Erbium-doped yttrium&#x02013;aluminium-garnet; Er: YAG, AdvErL EVO, Morita Corporation, Japan&#x02014;&#x0003e;&#x02009;J. MORITA MFG. CORP., Japan) with tip PS400TS and power 50&#x000a0;mJ, frequency 10 PPS and proportion air/water 7/7 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. The tip was placed in the peri-implant pocket, and a moving motion was from bottom to coronal at the implant surface, with a sweeping motion covering the soft tissue. The treatment in the control group (control) was performed with an ultrasonic device (Electro Medical Systems, EMS) with a plastic-coated tip (PI Instrument Nyon; EMS, Nyon, Switzerland). The tip was placed in the peri-implant pocket and used in a similar way as described above (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). All treatments were finalized by polishing with a rubber cup and polishing paste. Postoperative complications were asked for in the examination protocol as an open question at each examination, and treatment time was registered.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Peri-implant mucositis before, during and after treatment with Er: YAG laser or ultrasonic scaler. <bold>a</bold> Peri-implant mucositis 11 before treatment <bold>b</bold> Er: YAG laser treatment 11 <bold>c</bold> six months after Er: YAG laser treatment 11 <bold>d</bold> Peri-implant mucositis 12 before treatment <bold>e</bold> ultrasonic scaling 12 <bold>f</bold> six months after ultrasonic scaling 12</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40729_2025_591_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p id="Par29">At month one, measurements, oral hygiene instructions, and polishing with a rubber cup and polishing paste were performed (CLL).</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par30">The IBM SPSS version 27.0 statistical software package (SPSS Inc., Armonk, NY, USA) for personal computers was used in the analyses. The statistical unit was based on both the patient and the implant. Descriptive and comparative statistics were used when analysing the data. The primary outcome measure in this study was bleeding on probing (BoP). A power analysis was performed, and thirty-eight patients were minimum to reach a clinically significant difference at&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;30% reduction in bleeding of probing (BoP) between the groups with alpha 0.05 and power 80%. Forty-six individuals were included in the study, and all analyses were based on the "per protocol" principle. Mean values, standard deviation (SD) and frequency distributions are given. Independent t-test (equal variance not assumed) and paired t-test were used to compare inter- and intra-group differences. The chi-square test and non-parametric McNemar test were used for categorical variables. Statistical significance was set at p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Results</title><p id="Par31">This study was based on 46 patients (56.5% women) treated per protocol (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). The mean age was 64.4&#x000a0;years&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;13.8 range 29&#x02013;82. For baseline characteristics, see Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Consort flow chart</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40729_2025_591_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Baseline characteristics of the patients in percent and for packyears mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Variables</th><th align="left">Test group %</th><th align="left">Control group %</th><th align="left">Total patients %</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Cardiovascular diseases</td><td align="left">43.5%</td><td align="left">47.8%</td><td align="left">45.7%</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Diabetes mellitus</td><td align="left">8.7%</td><td align="left">8.7%</td><td align="left">8.7%</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Current smokers</td><td align="left">4.3%</td><td align="left">8.7%</td><td align="left">6.5%</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Packyears in current smokers (years)</td><td align="left">36&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;<sup>&#x02020;</sup></td><td align="left">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.4</td><td align="left">16&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;17.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Former smokers</td><td align="left">34.8%</td><td align="left">47.8%</td><td align="left">41.3%</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Using prescribed medicines</td><td align="left">47.8%</td><td align="left">65.2%</td><td align="left">56.5%</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Test group&#x02009;=&#x02009;Er:YAG laser, control group&#x02009;=&#x02009;Ultrasonic scaler</p><p><sup>&#x02020;</sup>NA&#x02009;=&#x02009;not applicable</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par32">After treatment at baseline, postoperative complications were reported by 4/46 (8.9%), including irritated mucosa (test), swollen mucosa (test), pain when touching (test), and a feeling of pressure (control). At month three, postoperative complications were reported by two individuals. One from the test group reporting bleeding, and one from the control group reported soreness in the corner of the mouth.</p><p id="Par33">Of the treated implants, 50.0% were Astra Tech, 37.0% were Nobel BioCare, 2.2% were Biomet 3i, and 4.3% were unidentified. Treatment time was for the test: 3.5&#x000a0;min at baseline, 2.8&#x000a0;min at month three and 2.9&#x000a0;min at month six. The corresponding figures for the control were 3.8&#x000a0;min at baseline, 3.1&#x000a0;min at month three and 2.7&#x000a0;min at month six. No significant intergroup differences existed.</p><sec id="Sec13"><title>Full mouth clinical indices</title><p id="Par34">At month three, FMBoP in the test was 20.8%&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;8.9, and in the control, 29.8%&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;17.2 (CI: &#x02212;&#x000a0;17.3 to &#x02212;&#x000a0;0.8; p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.03). Intergroup difference was also shown at month six, with FMBoP in the test 21.5%&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;9.0 and 30.0%&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;15.7 in the control (CI: &#x02212;&#x000a0;16.1 to &#x02212;&#x000a0;0.8; p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.03). FMBoP was significantly reduced in both groups (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Full-mouth bleeding on probing and plaque scores at different timepoints mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="40729_2025_591_Tab2_HTML" id="MO3"/><table-wrap-foot><p>Significant intergroup differences at months three and six in full mouth bleeding on probing</p><p>*p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 statistically significant difference in respective group at different timepoints compared to baseline. ** p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01 statistically significant difference in respective group at different timepoints compared to baseline. *** p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001 statistically significant difference in respective group at different timepoints compared to baseline</p><p>Arrows in the hook clamps show statistically significant difference * p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 between groups at month three and six</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par35">Full mouth plaque score was significantly reduced in both groups compared to baseline. No statistical intergroup differences existed (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Implant clinical indices</title><sec id="Sec15"><title>Bleeding on probing</title><p id="Par36">In the test, BoP was reduced from 89.0%&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;13.9 to 55.7%&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;22.8 (CI: 22.9&#x02013;43.7, p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.00), and in the control, from 94.9%&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;10.6 to 63.7%&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;21.6 (CI: 23.0&#x02013;39.4; p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.00) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). No statistical intergroup differences existed in BoP.<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Implant bleeding, scores (mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD) and prevalence of implant probing pocket depths&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;4&#x000a0;mm, pus, and mucosal changes (%) at different timepoints on six sites</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="40729_2025_591_Tab3_HTML" id="MO4"/><table-wrap-foot><p>Significant intergroup differences at baseline in graded bleeding, at month three in probing pocket depth (PPD)&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;4&#x000a0;mm and at month six in plaque</p><p>*p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 statistically significant difference in respective group at different timepoints compared to baseline. ** p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01 statistically significant difference in respective group at different timepoints compared to baseline. *** p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001 statistically significant difference in respective group at different timepoints compared to baseline</p><p>Arrows in the hook clamps show statistically significant difference * p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 between groups. &#x02020; NA&#x02009;=&#x02009;Not applicable</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Severity of bleeding</title><p id="Par37">The mBI was significantly reduced in both groups (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). No intergroup differences in mean graded bleeding (mBI) were shown. For the distribution of bleeding, see Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Distribution of graded bleeding on probing i.e. the severity at the implant surfaces (6 surfaces per implant) in both groups at baseline and six months. *p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 statistically significant difference from baseline to six months in respective group</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40729_2025_591_Fig3_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Presence of plaque</title><p id="Par38">Plaque was significantly reduced from baseline to 6&#x000a0;months from 43.0%&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.5 to 4.0%&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2 in the test (CI: 0.2&#x02013;0.6; p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.00) and from 52.0%&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.5 to 26.0%&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.4 in the control (CI: &#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0&#x02013;0.5; p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.03). At month six the presence of plaque was 4.0%&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2 in the test and 26.0%&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.5 in the control (CI: &#x02212;&#x000a0;0.4 to &#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0; p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.04) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Peri-implant probing pocket depth (PPD)</title><p id="Par39">At baseline, the mean PPD was in the test, 4.0&#x000a0;mm&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.3 and in the control, 4.8&#x000a0;mm&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.2 (CI: &#x02212;&#x000a0;1.6 to &#x02212;&#x000a0;0.8; p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.03). At month six, the mean PPD in the test was 3.6&#x000a0;mm&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.4, and in the control, the mean PPD was 4.3&#x000a0;mm&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.1 (CI: 0.1&#x02013;0.7; p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.05). In both groups, the reduction in mean PPD was statistically significant in the test (CI: 0.1&#x02013;0.7; p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.02), and in the control (CI: 0.2&#x02013;0.7; p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.00).</p><p id="Par40">As a result of therapy, the prevalence of PPD&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;4&#x000a0;mm decreased. At month three, the prevalence of PPD&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;4&#x000a0;mm was 43.5% in the test and 73.9% in the control (CI: 1.1&#x02013;12-8; p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.03). The reduction in prevalence of PPD&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;4&#x000a0;mm from baseline to months three and six was for the test 17.2%, and in the control, the reduction at month three was 4.4% and at month six 8.7%.</p><p id="Par41">At month six, 26% of the implants in the test demonstrated sites with a PPD&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;4&#x000a0;mm&#x02009;+&#x02009;BoP and or pus, respectively 52% in the control (CI: 0.9&#x02013;10.7; p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.07).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Radiographic images</title><p id="Par42">At baseline radiographs, the mean distance of the merged mesial and distal surfaces of the study implant was 0.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.83&#x000a0;mm in the test and 1.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.62&#x000a0;mm in the control (CI: &#x02212;&#x000a0;0.7 to 0.2; p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.32). At month six, the corresponding figures were 0.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.80&#x000a0;mm and 1.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.58&#x000a0;mm in the test, respectively, in the control (CI: &#x02212;&#x000a0;0.6 to 0.2; p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.40). Intragroup comparisons showed no statistical differences.</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Patient-reported outcome measures</title><sec id="Sec21"><title>Pain</title><p id="Par43">Pain during treatment reported on a VAS scale was at baseline 2.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.6 in the test and 3.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.0 in the control (CI: &#x02212;&#x000a0;3.0 to 0.5; p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.15) and three days posttreatment 0.08&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 in the test and in the control 0.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3 (CI: &#x02212;&#x000a0;0.3 to &#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0; p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.04) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Patient-reported outcomes on visual analogue scales of treating peri-implant mucositis with Er:YAG laser or ultrasonic scaler mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="40729_2025_591_Tab4_HTML" id="MO6"/><table-wrap-foot><p>Significant intergroup differences at month six in pain day three</p><p>Arrows in the hook clamp show a statistically significant difference *p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 between groups at month six. For the pain visual analogue scale, 0 indicates &#x0201c;no pain&#x0201d;, and 10 indicates &#x0201c;worst pain&#x0201d;. For aesthetics the visual analogue scale 0, indicating &#x0201c;not at all satisfied&#x0201d;, and 10, indicating &#x0201c;very satisfied&#x0201d;</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Aesthetics</title><p id="Par44">Satisfaction with the aesthetics was in the test 8.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.7 at baseline, and 8.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.3 in the control (CI: &#x02212;&#x000a0;1.0 to 1.4; p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.69). At month six it was 8.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.4 in the test and 8.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.6 in the control (CI: &#x02212;&#x000a0;0.9 to 0.9; p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.92) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title>Quality of life</title><p id="Par45">At baseline, the total OHIP-14 score in the test was 1.27&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.9, and 4.26&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.3 in the control (CI: &#x02212;&#x000a0;5.4 to &#x02212;&#x000a0;0.6; p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.00). The total OHIP-14 score at month six in the test was 1.48&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.5, in the control, 2.17&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.4 (CI: &#x02212;&#x000a0;2.5 to 1.1; p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.22). No statistical differences over time were observed in any of the groups.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="Sec24"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par46">The present study assessed, the treatment of peri-implant mucositis using either an Er:YAG laser or an ultrasonic device. FMBoP and FMPs were significantly reduced in both groups. At the implant level, significant reductions were shown in the extent and severity of bleeding for both groups.</p><p id="Par47">A few clinical randomized studies on peri-implant mucositis treatment evaluating a single mode of treatment are reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Er:YAG laser has been used in another randomized clinical trial to treat peri-implant mucositis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. In that study, the Er:YAG laser was used in combination with titanium curettes, and the effectiveness of the Er:YAG laser could, therefore, not be evaluated.</p><p id="Par48">The primary outcome measure in the present study was change in BoP. The reduction of BoP at the implant in the Er:YAG laser group was 33.3%, compared to 31.2% in the ultrasonic group. In another randomized clinical study, BoP at the implant was reduced by 27.2% at implants treated by a glycine powder air-polishing device compared to 30.5% at implants treated by the same ultrasonic scaler used in the present study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. The reduction of BoP in the two studies is similar. In the study by Riben-Grundstrom et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>], the BoP figures are, however, lower than those in the current study. The higher baseline implant bleeding values may have negatively affected the final treatment results in the present study. It has been demonstrated that BoP &#x002c3;50% of the implant sites predict disease progression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>].</p><p id="Par49">In this study, mBI was significantly reduced over time in both groups. In the Er:YAG laser group, mBI reduced from 1.3 at baseline to 0.6 at month six, and the figures for the ultrasonic group were from 1.9 to 0.8. These reductions in mBI are equivalent to two previous studies demonstrating reductions in mBI of 0.6&#x02013;0.8 at six months [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. One of them compared combined ultrasonic scaling and glycine powder air-polishing with ultrasonic scaling alone [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>], and the other study compared a chitosan rotating brush as a single mode with titanium curettes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. The importance of mBI in predicting progressive bone loss remains questionable [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Maybe the severity of bleeding, using the grading of bleeding [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>], is a better indicator of treatment needs than just measuring BoP. The EFP clinical practice guideline 2023 involving peri-implant mucositis highlights the importance of profuse bleeding at implants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Re-treatment is recommended if two or more surfaces at the implant demonstrate profuse bleeding [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Possibly bleeding grade 1, "a point of bleeding", and even bleeding grade 2 ", a line of bleeding", may constitute the consequence of traumatizing the mucosa while measuring the pocket and may not represent an inflammatory response. If so, this may risk falsely raising the extent of bleeding [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Using this way of reasoning and adding bleeding grade 1 to grade 0, at month six, in the Er:YAG laser group, 83.0% of the surfaces and 83.0% in the ultrasonic group did not demonstrate bleeding due to inflammation. Wohlfahrt et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>] also measured the severity of bleeding with the same grading system as in the present study. When grade 1 and grade 0 were combined, the authors reported that 86.0% of the surfaces in the chitosan group and 79.0% in the titan curette group were bleeding-free after treatment. These figures represent the severity of bleeding when considering bleeding grade 1 as traumatic and not inflammatory-driven bleeding and are equivalent to what is reported in the present study. If grade 1 to grade 0 were added concerning the severity of bleeding, ten implants would have been considered successfully treated (seven from the Er:YAG laser group and three from the ultrasonic group).</p><p id="Par50">An increase in PPD is often a sign of peri-implant mucositis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>], therefore, a reduction could be considered a sign of healing. Following treatment, there was a reduction in the prevalence of PPD&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;4&#x000a0;mm in both groups. At month three the prevalence of probing pocket depths&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;4&#x000a0;mm in the Er:YAG laser group was 43.5% and significantly lower compared with the ultrasonic group, 73.9% (p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.03). The reduction of pockets observed at month three remained in the test group until month six. In the control group, there was some further improvement.</p><p id="Par51">PROMs are seldom described in studies following the treatment of peri-implant mucositis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. In the present study, PROMS were included as outcome variables. Pain experienced during treatment decreased over time and was lower than reported by Wohlfhart et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. The studies used different modes of treatment and are, therefore, difficult to compare. It could, however, be noted that the pain sensation was low regardless of the therapy used in the present study. Three days after treatment at month six, Er:YAG laser group patients reported a statistically lower pain sensation than those in the ultrasonic group. In a meta-analysis by Mikami et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>] reporting pain following non-surgical periodontal treatment with either an Er:YAG laser or conventional root planning, significantly lower patient-reported pain was reported in the laser group.</p><p id="Par52">A limitation of the present study is the difference in mean PPD at baseline between groups. The shallower PPD in the test group may have limited the healing potential following therapy and, thus, the potential intergroup differences. Another limitation of the present study is that the level of the sub- or supra-mucosal restoration margin was not registered. The placement of the restoration margin may have influenced the treatment results [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. It has been demonstrated that the width of the keratinized mucosa may affect the treatment outcomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. A limitation of the present study is that the width of the keratinized mucosa was not measured.</p><p id="Par53">The EFP clinical practice guidelines 2023 recommend regular supportive care in patients with healthy peri-implant tissues to prevent the development of peri-implant diseases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. If peri-implant mucositis has developed, self-performed, effective oral hygiene, and professional mechanical plaque removal, are recommended [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Management of peri-implant mucositis is considered a preventive measure for the onset of peri-implantitis and must be treated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. This study demonstrated that treating peri-implant mucositis using an Er:YAG laser or an ultrasonic scaler is effective, and both therapies can therefore be recommended for treating peri-implant mucositis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec25"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par54">Er:YAG laser and ultrasonic scaler as single modes of therapy were effective in treating peri-implant mucositis and reduced bleeding and probing pocket depths. Fewer diseased sites were diagnosed at six months following laser treatment.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p>This article has been updated to correct an author name.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Publisher's Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Change history</bold></p><p>2/26/2025</p><p>A Correction to this paper has been published: 10.1186/s40729-025-00599-6</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>Not applicable.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>VWB contributed to conceptualization (equal), investigation (lead), analysis of data (lead), interpretation of data (equal), and writing the original draft (lead). AA contributed to the conceptualization (equal), critical reading, and manuscript revision (equal). KM contributed to the conceptualization (equal), critical reading and revising of the manuscript (equal). CL contributed to investigation (equal), data management (lead), critical reading and revising of the manuscript (equal). SR contributed to conceptualization (lead), funding acquisition (lead), project administration (lead), interpretation of data (equal), critical reading, and revising the manuscript (equal). All authors revised and approved the manuscript before submission.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>Open access funding provided by Kristianstad University. This study was co-founded by Morita Corporation, Japan&#x02014;&#x0003e;&#x02009;J. MORITA MFG. CORP., Japan.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>No datasets were generated or analysed during the current study.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par55">This longitudinal clinical study was approved by the Regional Ethics Board in Uppsala (Dnr 2020-02586). All the subjects signed an informed consent form to have their data used for scientific purposes. The study was conducted in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki in 1975 revised in 2013.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par56">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par57">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roccuzzo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Imber</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Marruganti</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Salvi</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramieri</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Roccuzzo</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical outcomes of dental implants in patients with and without a history of periodontitis: a 20-year prospective study</article-title><source>J Clin Periodontol</source><year>2022</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>1346</fpage><lpage>1356</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jcpe.13716</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36054302</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Roccuzzo A, Imber JC, Marruganti C, Salvi GE, Ramieri G, Roccuzzo MJ. Clinical outcomes of dental implants in patients with and without a history of periodontitis: a 20-year prospective study. J Clin Periodontol. 2022;49:1346&#x02013;56.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36054302</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heitz-Mayfield</surname><given-names>LJA</given-names></name><name><surname>Needleman</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Salvi</surname><given-names>GEB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Consensus statements and clinical recommendations for preventing and managing biologic and technical implant complications</article-title><source>Int J Oral Maxillofac Implants</source><year>2014</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>346</fpage><lpage>350</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.11607/jomi.2013.g5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24660208</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Heitz-Mayfield LJA, Needleman I, Salvi GEB. Consensus statements and clinical recommendations for preventing and managing biologic and technical implant complications. Int J Oral Maxillofac Implants. 2014;29:346&#x02013;50.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24660208</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Derks</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomasi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Peri-implant health and disease. A systematic review of current epidemiology</article-title><source>J Clin Periodontol</source><year>2015</year><volume>42</volume><issue>Suppl 16</issue><fpage>158</fpage><lpage>171</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Derks J, Tomasi C. Peri-implant health and disease. A systematic review of current epidemiology. J Clin Periodontol. 2015;42(Suppl 16):158&#x02013;71.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heitz-Mayfield</surname><given-names>LJA</given-names></name><name><surname>Salvi</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Peri-implant mucositis</article-title><source>J Clin Periodontol</source><year>2018</year><volume>45</volume><issue>Suppl 20</issue><fpage>237</fpage><lpage>245</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Heitz-Mayfield LJA, Salvi GE. Peri-implant mucositis. J Clin Periodontol. 2018;45(Suppl 20):237&#x02013;45.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Renvert</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Polyzois</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Treatment of pathologic peri-implant pockets</article-title><source>Periodontol</source><year>2000</year><volume>2018</volume><issue>76</issue><fpage>180</fpage><lpage>190</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Renvert S, Polyzois I. Treatment of pathologic peri-implant pockets. Periodontol. 2000;2018(76):180&#x02013;90.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herrera</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Berglundh</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prevention and treatment of peri-implant diseases&#x02014;the EFP S3 level clinical practice guideline</article-title><source>J Clin Periodontol</source><year>2023</year><volume>50</volume><issue>Suppl 26</issue><fpage>4</fpage><lpage>76</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jcpe.13823</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37271498</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Herrera H, Berglundh T, Schwarz F, et al. Prevention and treatment of peri-implant diseases&#x02014;the EFP S3 level clinical practice guideline. J Clin Periodontol. 2023;50(Suppl 26):4&#x02013;76.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37271498</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Teughels</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Assche</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sliepen</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Quirynen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of material characteristics and or surface topography on biofilm development</article-title><source>Clin Oral Implant Res</source><year>2006</year><volume>17</volume><issue>Suppl 2</issue><fpage>68</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-0501.2006.01353.x</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Teughels W, Van Assche N, Sliepen I, Quirynen M. Effect of material characteristics and or surface topography on biofilm development. Clin Oral Implant Res. 2006;17(Suppl 2):68&#x02013;81.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Motohiro</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Masahiro</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Masaya</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shigetada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshinobu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kazunori</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of decontamination methods of oral biofilms formed on screw-shaped, rough and machined surface implants: an ex vivo study</article-title><source>Int J Implant Dent</source><year>2020</year><volume>22</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>18</fpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Motohiro O, Masahiro W, Masaya Y, Shigetada K, Yoshinobu M, Kazunori I. Evaluation of decontamination methods of oral biofilms formed on screw-shaped, rough and machined surface implants: an ex vivo study. Int J Implant Dent. 2020;22(6):18.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wyrwich</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name><surname>Norquist</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenderking</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name><surname>Acaster</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Industry Advisory Committee of International Society for Quality-of-Life Research (ISOQOL). Methods for interpreting change over time in patient-reported outcome measures</article-title><source>Qual Life Res</source><year>2013</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>475</fpage><lpage>483</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11136-012-0175-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22528240</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Wyrwich KW, Norquist JM, Lenderking WR, Acaster S. Industry Advisory Committee of International Society for Quality-of-Life Research (ISOQOL). Methods for interpreting change over time in patient-reported outcome measures. Qual Life Res. 2013;22:475&#x02013;83.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22528240</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Verket</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Koldsland</surname><given-names>OC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bunaes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lie</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Romandini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Non-surgical therapy of peri-implant mucositis-mechanical/physical approaches: a systematic review</article-title><source>J Clin Periodontol</source><year>2023</year><volume>50</volume><issue>Suppl 26</issue><fpage>135</fpage><lpage>145</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jcpe.13789</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36802083</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Verket A, Koldsland OC, Bunaes D, Lie SA, Romandini M. Non-surgical therapy of peri-implant mucositis-mechanical/physical approaches: a systematic review. J Clin Periodontol. 2023;50(Suppl 26):135&#x02013;45.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36802083</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Claffey</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Nylund</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiger</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Garrett</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Egelberg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diagnostic predictability of scores of plaque, bleeding, suppuration and probing depth for probing attachment loss. 3 1/2 years of observation following initial periodontal therapy</article-title><source>J Clin Periodontol</source><year>1990</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>108</fpage><lpage>114</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-051X.1990.tb01071.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2406292</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Claffey N, Nylund K, Kiger R, Garrett S, Egelberg J. Diagnostic predictability of scores of plaque, bleeding, suppuration and probing depth for probing attachment loss. 3 1/2 years of observation following initial periodontal therapy. J Clin Periodontol. 1990;17:108&#x02013;14.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2406292</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O'Leary</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Drake</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Naylor</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The plaque control record</article-title><source>J Periodontol</source><year>1972</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>38</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1902/jop.1972.43.1.38</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4500182</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">O&#x02019;Leary TJ, Drake RB, Naylor JE. The plaque control record. J Periodontol. 1972;43:38.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4500182</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mombelli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>van Oosten</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sch&#x000fc;rch</surname><given-names>E</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The microbiota associated with successful or failing osseointegrated titanium implants</article-title><source>Oral Microbiol Immunol</source><year>1987</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>145</fpage><lpage>151</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1399-302X.1987.tb00298.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3507627</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Mombelli A, van Oosten MA, Sch&#x000fc;rch E Jr, Lang NP. The microbiota associated with successful or failing osseointegrated titanium implants. Oral Microbiol Immunol. 1987;2:145&#x02013;51.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3507627</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Slade</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Derivation and validation of a short-form oral health impact profile</article-title><source>Community Dent Oral Epidemiol</source><year>1997</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>284</fpage><lpage>290</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-0528.1997.tb00941.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9332805</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Slade GD. Derivation and validation of a short-form oral health impact profile. Community Dent Oral Epidemiol. 1997;25:284&#x02013;90.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9332805</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taniguchi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Aoki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizutani</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Optimal Er:YAG laser irradiation parameters for debridement of microstructured fixture surfaces of titanium dental implants</article-title><source>Lasers Med Sci</source><year>2013</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>1057</fpage><lpage>1068</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10103-012-1171-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22886137</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Taniguchi Y, Aoki A, Mizutani K, et al. Optimal Er:YAG laser irradiation parameters for debridement of microstructured fixture surfaces of titanium dental implants. Lasers Med Sci. 2013;28:1057&#x02013;68.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22886137</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wohlfahrt</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Aass</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Koldsland</surname><given-names>OC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Treatment of peri-implant mucositis with a chitosan brush-A pilot randomized clinical trial</article-title><source>Int J Dent Hyg</source><year>2019</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>170</fpage><lpage>176</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/idh.12381</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30582880</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Wohlfahrt JC, Aass AM, Koldsland OC. Treatment of peri-implant mucositis with a chitosan brush-A pilot randomized clinical trial. Int J Dent Hyg. 2019;17:170&#x02013;6.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30582880</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Riben-Grundstr&#x000f6;m</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Norderyd</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Andr&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Renvert</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Treatment of peri-implant mucositis using a glycine powder air-polishing or ultrasonic device: a randomized clinical trial</article-title><source>J Clin Periodontol</source><year>2015</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>462</fpage><lpage>469</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jcpe.12395</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25851433</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Riben-Grundstr&#x000f6;m C, Norderyd O, Andr&#x000e9; U, Renvert S. Treatment of peri-implant mucositis using a glycine powder air-polishing or ultrasonic device: a randomized clinical trial. J Clin Periodontol. 2015;42:462&#x02013;9.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25851433</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clementini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fabrizi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Discepoli</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Minoli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>De Sanctis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of the adjunctive use of Er:YAG laser or erythritol powder air-polishing in the treatment of peri-implant mucositis: a randomized clinical trial</article-title><source>Clin Oral Implant Res</source><year>2023</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>1267</fpage><lpage>1277</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/clr.14167</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Clementini M, Fabrizi S, Discepoli N, Minoli M, De Sanctis M. Evaluation of the adjunctive use of Er:YAG laser or erythritol powder air-polishing in the treatment of peri-implant mucositis: a randomized clinical trial. Clin Oral Implant Res. 2023;34:1267&#x02013;77.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berglundh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Romandini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Derks</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Berglundh</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical findings and history of bone loss at implant sites</article-title><source>Clin Oral Implant Res</source><year>2021</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>314</fpage><lpage>323</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/clr.13701</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Berglundh J, Romandini M, Derks J, Sanz M, Berglundh T. Clinical findings and history of bone loss at implant sites. Clin Oral Implant Res. 2021;32:314&#x02013;23.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karlsson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Derks</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#x000e5;kansson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wennstr&#x000f6;m</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Petzold</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Berglundh</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interventions for peri-implantitis and their effects on further bone loss: a retrospective analysis of a registry-based cohort</article-title><source>J Clin Periodontol</source><year>2019</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>872</fpage><lpage>879</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jcpe.13129</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31077421</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">Karlsson K, Derks J, H&#x000e5;kansson J, Wennstr&#x000f6;m JL, Petzold M, Berglundh T. Interventions for peri-implantitis and their effects on further bone loss: a retrospective analysis of a registry-based cohort. J Clin Periodontol. 2019;46:872&#x02013;9.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31077421</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>ZH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of glycine powder air-polishing as an adjunct in the treatment of peri-implant mucositis: a pilot clinical trial</article-title><source>Clin Oral Implant Res</source><year>2014</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>683</fpage><lpage>689</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/clr.12123</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Ji YJ, Tang ZH, Wang R, Cao J, Cao CF, Jin LJ. Effect of glycine powder air-polishing as an adjunct in the treatment of peri-implant mucositis: a pilot clinical trial. Clin Oral Implant Res. 2014;25:683&#x02013;9.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Renvert</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindahl</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Roos-Jans&#x000e5;ker</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Persson</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Treatment of peri-implantitis using an Er:YAG laser or an air-abrasive device: a randomized clinical trial</article-title><source>J Clin Periodontol</source><year>2011</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-051X.2010.01646.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21091527</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">Renvert S, Lindahl C, Roos-Jans&#x000e5;ker AM, Persson GR. Treatment of peri-implantitis using an Er:YAG laser or an air-abrasive device: a randomized clinical trial. J Clin Periodontol. 2011;38:65&#x02013;73.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21091527</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berglundh</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Armitage</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Araujo</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Peri-implant diseases and conditions: consensus report of workgroup 4 of the 2017 World Workshop on the classification of periodontal and peri-implant diseases and conditions</article-title><source>J Clin Periodontol</source><year>2018</year><volume>45</volume><issue>20</issue><fpage>286</fpage><lpage>291</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Berglundh T, Armitage G, Araujo MG, et al. Peri-implant diseases and conditions: consensus report of workgroup 4 of the 2017 World Workshop on the classification of periodontal and peri-implant diseases and conditions. J Clin Periodontol. 2018;45(20):286&#x02013;91.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mikami</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizutani</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwata</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Aoki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Patient-reported outcomes of laser-assisted pain control following non-surgical and surgical periodontal therapy: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2020</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>e0238659</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0238659</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32941479</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">Mikami R, Mizutani K, Sasaki Y, Iwata T, Aoki A. Patient-reported outcomes of laser-assisted pain control following non-surgical and surgical periodontal therapy: a systematic review and meta-analysis. PLoS ONE. 2020;15: e0238659.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32941479</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heitz-Mayfield</surname><given-names>LJA</given-names></name><name><surname>Salvi</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Botticelli</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Anti-infective treatment of peri-implant mucositis: a randomized controlled clinical trial</article-title><source>Clin Oral Implant Res</source><year>2011</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>237</fpage><lpage>241</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-0501.2010.02078.x</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="journal">Heitz-Mayfield LJA, Salvi GE, Botticelli D, et al. Anti-infective treatment of peri-implant mucositis: a randomized controlled clinical trial. Clin Oral Implant Res. 2011;22:237&#x02013;41.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR26" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sanz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Herrera</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Importance of keratinized mucosa around dental implants: consensus report of group 1 of the DGI/SEPA/Osteology Workshop</article-title><source>Clin Oral Implant Res</source><year>2022</year><volume>33</volume><issue>Suppl 23</issue><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/clr.13956</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26" publication-type="journal">Sanz M, Schwarz F, Herrera D, et al. Importance of keratinized mucosa around dental implants: consensus report of group 1 of the DGI/SEPA/Osteology Workshop. Clin Oral Implant Res. 2022;33(Suppl 23):47&#x02013;55.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR27" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Tormena</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Matarazzo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ara&#x000fa;jo</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The influence of peri implant keratinized mucosa on brushing discomfort and peri-implant tissue health</article-title><source>Clin Oral Implant Res</source><year>2016</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>650</fpage><lpage>655</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/clr.12703</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27" publication-type="journal">Souza AB, Tormena M, Matarazzo F, Ara&#x000fa;jo MG. The influence of peri implant keratinized mucosa on brushing discomfort and peri-implant tissue health. Clin Oral Implant Res. 2016;27:650&#x02013;5.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article>