<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" id="cre270110" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Clin Exp Dent Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Clin Exp Dent Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.1002/(ISSN)2057-4347</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CRE2</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Clinical and Experimental Dental Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2057-4347</issn><publisher><publisher-name>John Wiley and Sons Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Hoboken</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40045547</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11882750</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cre2.70110</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">CRE270110</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Exploring Augmented Reality for Dental Implant Surgery: Feasibility of Using Smartphones as Navigation Tools</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="cre270110-cr-0001" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mosch</surname><given-names>Richard</given-names></name><xref rid="cre270110-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="cre270110-cr-0002" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Alevizakos</surname><given-names>Vasilios</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3541-5404</contrib-id><xref rid="cre270110-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><address><email>vasileios.alevizakos@googlemail.com</email></address></contrib><contrib id="cre270110-cr-0003" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Str&#x000f6;bele</surname><given-names>Dragan Alexander</given-names></name><xref rid="cre270110-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="cre270110-cr-0004" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schiller</surname><given-names>Marcus</given-names></name><xref rid="cre270110-aff-0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="cre270110-cr-0005" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>von See</surname><given-names>Constantin</given-names></name><xref rid="cre270110-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="cre270110-aff-0001">
<label>
<sup>1</sup>
</label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Department of Dentistry, Faculty of Medicine and Dentistry, Research Center for Digital Technologies in Dentistry and CAD/CAM</named-content>
<institution>Danube Private University</institution>
<city>Krems an der Donau</city>
<country country="AT">Austria</country>
</aff><aff id="cre270110-aff-0002">
<label>
<sup>2</sup>
</label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Department of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery</named-content>
<institution>Hannover Medical School</institution>
<city>Hannover</city>
<country country="DE">Germany</country>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="correspondenceTo">
<label>*</label>
<bold>Correspondence:</bold> Vasilios Alevizakos (<email>vasileios.alevizakos@googlemail.com</email>)<break/>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>05</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>2</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue seq="75">1</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cre2.v11.1</issue-id><elocation-id>e70110</elocation-id><history>
<date date-type="rev-recd"><day>15</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></date>
<date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></date>
</history><permissions><!--&#x000a9; 2025 The Author(s). Clinical and Experimental Dental Research published by John Wiley & Sons Ltd.--><copyright-statement content-type="article-copyright">&#x000a9; 2025 The Author(s). <italic toggle="yes">Clinical and Experimental Dental Research</italic> published by John Wiley &#x00026; Sons Ltd.</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link> License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="file:CRE2-11-e70110.pdf"/><abstract><title>ABSTRACT</title><sec id="cre270110-sec-0010"><title>Objectives</title><p>Dental implant placement requires exceptional precision to ensure functional and esthetic success. Traditional guidance methods, such as static drilling guides and dynamic navigation systems, have improved accuracy but are limited by high costs, rigidity, and reliance on specialized hardware. This study introduces an augmented reality (AR) system using consumer smartphones for real&#x02010;time navigation in dental implant placement. The system aims to provide a cost&#x02010;effective, eco&#x02010;friendly alternative to conventional methods by integrating virtual planning with physical models.</p></sec><sec id="cre270110-sec-0020"><title>Material and Methods</title><p>A modified dental training model with removable parallel pins served as the physical component. Implant positions were digitally planned and color&#x02010;coded using 3D scanning and modeling software, then integrated into an AR application built with Unity Engine. A smartphone's camera was calibrated to project virtual overlays onto the physical model. In vitro testing evaluated alignment accuracy, drill guidance, and system performance under controlled lighting conditions.</p></sec><sec id="cre270110-sec-0030"><title>Results</title><p>The AR system successfully aligned virtual overlays with the physical model, providing effective visual guidance for implant drill positioning. Operators maintained planned trajectories, demonstrating the feasibility of AR as an alternative to static and dynamic guidance systems. Challenges included the system's sensitivity to stable lighting and visual cues.</p></sec><sec id="cre270110-sec-0040"><title>Conclusions</title><p>This AR&#x02010;based approach offers an accessible and sustainable solution for modern dental implantology. Future research will focus on quantitative accuracy assessments, AI integration for enhanced performance, and clinical trials to validate real&#x02010;world applicability. AR technology has the potential to transform dental practices by improving outcomes while reducing costs and environmental impact.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd id="cre270110-kwd-0001">augmented reality</kwd><kwd id="cre270110-kwd-0002">dental implants</kwd><kwd id="cre270110-kwd-0003">image&#x02010;guided surgery</kwd><kwd id="cre270110-kwd-0004">smartphone</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="funding-0001"><funding-source>The authors received no specific funding for this work.</funding-source></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="3"/><table-count count="0"/><page-count count="6"/><word-count count="3623"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>source-schema-version-number</meta-name><meta-value>2.0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>February 2025</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>details-of-publishers-convertor</meta-name><meta-value>Converter:WILEY_ML3GV2_TO_JATSPMC version:6.5.4 mode:remove_FC converted:07.04.2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><fn-group><fn id="cre270110-note-0001"><p>Richard Mosch and Vasilios Alevizakos contributed equally as first authors to this study.</p></fn></fn-group></notes></front><body><sec id="cre270110-sec-0050"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p>The demand for dental implants has increased significantly in recent years, driven by patients seeking fixed restorations that enhance functionality, esthetics, and overall quality of life (Duong et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270110-bib-0005" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>). Successful dental implant placement relies on precision, as the positioning of implants directly impacts both functional and esthetic outcomes (Nulty&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270110-bib-0014" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>). Advanced techniques, such as backward planning and computer&#x02010;guided surgery, have substantially improved accuracy and reduced failure rates while also streamlining workflows for clinicians and dental technicians (Kim et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270110-bib-0011" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>). These approaches have become central to modern implantology, demonstrating significant advantages over earlier methods.</p><p>Currently, backward planning involves combining cone&#x02010;beam computed tomography (CBCT) data with virtual prosthetic designs to create custom surgical guides. These guides ensure reliable accuracy, with deviations typically limited to less than &#x000b1;1&#x02009;mm (Hama and Mahmood&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270110-bib-0007" ref-type="bibr">2023</xref>). However, despite their effectiveness, traditional surgical guides are not without limitations. They lack the flexibility to adapt to unexpected intraoperative changes, and their production is both costly and wasteful, contributing to medical waste generation (Campos et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270110-bib-0001" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>; Vu et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270110-bib-0019" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>). Additionally, the physical presence of the guides can obstruct the clinician's view during surgery, which can complicate the procedure.</p><p>Dynamic navigation systems have emerged as a more flexible alternative, providing real&#x02010;time guidance without the need for physical templates (Younis et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270110-bib-0021" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>). These systems, however, come with their own challenges, including reliance on expensive specialized equipment, such as optical trackers and dedicated workstations, which limits their accessibility in routine clinical practice. These challenges underscore the need for an innovative solution that balances precision, affordability, and ease of use.</p><p>Augmented reality (AR) represents a promising technology that could address these limitations (Puleio et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270110-bib-0016" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>). By overlaying virtual models onto the real&#x02010;world surgical field in real time, AR can provide dynamic guidance without the need for physical surgical guides or costly specialized hardware (Jiang et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270110-bib-0010" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; Navab et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270110-bib-0013" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>). Recent research has underscored AR's potential in precision tasks. For example, Dastan, Fiorentino, and Uva (<xref rid="cre270110-bib-0003" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>) reviewed tools like the Precise Tool to Target Positioning Widgets (TOTTA), which demonstrated AR's capability to enhance spatial accuracy in surgical workflows. Another study by Dastan, Fiorentino, Walter (<xref rid="cre270110-bib-0004" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>) explored the codesign of mixed reality drill positioning systems with dentists, emphasizing AR's ability to function effectively in realistic clinical setups. These findings establish AR as a transformative technology for medical and dental procedures. Additionally, AR has the potential to enhance accessibility by leveraging widely available consumer devices, such as smartphones (Lee et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270110-bib-0012" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>). Despite its transformative potential, the application of AR in dentistry&#x02014;particularly for dental implant placement&#x02014;remains relatively unexplored, highlighting a significant gap in the current literature.</p><p>This study introduces a novel approach that combines AR&#x02010;based navigation with the use of smartphones to guide dental implant placement. By integrating virtual planning with real&#x02010;time augmented visualization, the proposed system aims to simplify implant procedures, reduce costs, and enhance accessibility. The research demonstrates the feasibility of this method through in vitro testing with a dental training phantom while also identifying key practical challenges, such as lighting conditions and optical obstructions, that could impact the system's performance. Furthermore, it explores the potential of smartphones as an affordable and environmentally sustainable alternative to traditional navigation systems.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials-and-methods" id="cre270110-sec-0060"><label>2</label><title>Materials and Methods</title><p>This study evaluated the feasibility of using AR for guided dental implant placement by integrating virtual planning with physical modeling. The methodology included detailed steps for virtual implant planning, physical model preparation, AR application development, and in vitro testing under simulated clinical conditions. The following sections describe the materials and methods employed, ensuring reproducibility of the proposed approach.</p><sec id="cre270110-sec-0070"><label>2.1</label><title>Materials</title><sec id="cre270110-sec-0080"><label>2.1.1</label><title>Dental Training Phantom Head</title><p>A dental training phantom head (PK&#x02010;1 TL, Frasaco GmbH, Tettnang, Germany) was used to replicate the anatomical and spatial constraints of the human oral cavity. This model is widely utilized for dental training and testing, featuring realistic representations of the jaw, gingiva, and teeth. Its stable design enabled controlled simulation of clinical conditions for evaluating the AR system.</p></sec><sec id="cre270110-sec-0090"><label>2.1.2</label><title>Dental Training Model</title><p>The physical representation for testing consisted of a dental training model (ANA&#x02010;4V, Frasaco GmbH, Tettnang, Germany). This model features full dentition and was specifically modified for the study by decapitating selected teeth to allow the placement of removable parallel pins at predetermined implant positions. The pins simulated the intended implant locations and served as references for aligning virtual and physical components.</p></sec><sec id="cre270110-sec-0100"><label>2.1.3</label><title>3D Scanning and Software Tools</title><p>The modified dental model was scanned using a high&#x02010;resolution 3D scanner (D800, 3Shape, Copenhagen, Denmark) to generate an accurate digital representation of the physical model. The resulting STL file was processed in Blender 2.9 (Blender Foundation, Amsterdam, Netherlands), where the virtual model was prepared for AR integration. This involved segmenting teeth, soft tissue, and pins, followed by color&#x02010;coding each component to facilitate identification during AR projection. The final file was exported in FBX format.</p></sec><sec id="cre270110-sec-0110"><label>2.1.4</label><title>AR Hardware and Application</title><p>A commercially available smartphone (Samsung Galaxy S10, Samsung Electronics Co. Ltd., Seoul, South Korea) equipped with an autofocus camera served as the AR platform. The AR application utilized the phone's built&#x02010;in object detection algorithms to recognize visual cues on the physical model and superimpose the virtual implant positions. This approach minimized the need for specialized hardware, making the system cost&#x02010;effective and accessible.</p></sec><sec id="cre270110-sec-0120"><label>2.1.5</label><title>Lighting Setup</title><p>Two LED lights (Andoer MS&#x02010;30L, Shenzhen Tomtop Technology Co. Ltd., Shenzhen, China) were used to ensure consistent and uniform illumination. Proper lighting was critical to enhance the visibility of the physical model and to prevent shadows or reflections that could interfere with the AR system's accuracy.</p></sec></sec><sec id="cre270110-sec-0130"><label>2.2</label><title>Methods</title><sec id="cre270110-sec-0140"><label>2.2.1</label><title>Virtual Planning of Implant Positions</title><p>The first phase of the study involved virtual planning, in which optimal implant positions were determined based on the digital design of the prosthetic crown. Using Blender 2.9, the scanned STL file of the dental model was prepared by aligning three implant positions with the removable pins. These positions were digitally marked and color&#x02010;coded to differentiate them from surrounding anatomical structures. This meticulous planning ensured that the virtual model precisely corresponded to the physical setup, facilitating accurate AR projection.</p></sec><sec id="cre270110-sec-0150"><label>2.2.2</label><title>Preparation of the Physical Model</title><p>The physical model was modified by decapitating the crown portion of the tooth at position 26 (FDI system) and inserting three removable parallel pins. These pins simulated the planned implant positions, allowing for easy removal and replacement during testing. The modified model was used both for 3D scanning and for in vitro testing to ensure alignment between the virtual and physical domains.</p></sec><sec id="cre270110-sec-0160"><label>2.2.3</label><title>AR Setup and Calibration</title><p>The AR application was designed to project virtual overlays of the implant positions onto the physical model using the smartphone's camera. Calibration was achieved by aligning the camera's view with the occlusal plane of the dental model, ensuring proper superimposition of digital and physical elements. The application relied on the color&#x02010;coded cues from the model to recognize key anatomical features and project the planned implant positions in the correct location and orientation (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270110-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).</p><fig position="float" fig-type="Figure" id="cre270110-fig-0001"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Superimposed model with virtually projected parallel pin onto the physical pin.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="CRE2-11-e70110-g001" position="anchor" id="jats-graphic-1"/></fig></sec><sec id="cre270110-sec-0170"><label>2.2.4</label><title>In Vitro Testing Protocol</title><p>To evaluate the feasibility of the AR guidance system, the prepared dental model was placed within the phantom head, replicating the constraints of a clinical scenario. The protocol for testing included (Figures&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270110-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref> and&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270110-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>):
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Positioning the smartphone's camera perpendicular to the occlusal surface to optimize recognition of visual cues.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Activating the AR application, which superimposed the pre&#x02010;planned digital implant positions onto the physical model.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Removing the parallel pin at position 26 to simulate a missing implant site.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Using the AR overlay to guide the implant drill into the correct position and angulation, as displayed on the smartphone screen.</p></list-item></list>
</p><fig position="float" fig-type="Figure" id="cre270110-fig-0002"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>The application detected the pre&#x02010;planned digital implant placement.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="CRE2-11-e70110-g002" position="anchor" id="jats-graphic-3"/></fig><fig position="float" fig-type="Figure" id="cre270110-fig-0003"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>The AR application utilized the built&#x02010;in camera of a standard smartphone with autofocus to generate a mobile AR environment.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="CRE2-11-e70110-g003" position="anchor" id="jats-graphic-5"/></fig><p>Throughout the testing process, consistent lighting conditions were maintained to prevent errors in AR projection. Observations focused on the accuracy of alignment between the digital overlays and the physical model, as well as the usability of the system for guiding the implant drill.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="cre270110-sec-0180"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><p>The feasibility of using AR for guided dental implant placement was evaluated through controlled in vitro testing. The experiments assessed the system's ability to align virtual implant positions with physical models, provide drill guidance, and maintain performance under varying conditions.</p><p>The AR system consistently projected virtual implant positions onto the physical model. The alignment of the virtual overlays with the predefined implant sites was visually verified during each trial.</p><p>Operators were able to visually maintain the position and angulation throughout the procedure, demonstrating the AR system's potential as a reliable alternative to traditional drilling guides.</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="cre270110-sec-0190"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p>This study presents an innovative method for integrating mobile AR systems into dental implant placement, leveraging the accessibility and computational power of consumer smartphones. By utilizing AR to project virtual overlays onto physical models, this approach addresses key limitations of existing guidance methods, providing a cost&#x02010;effective, eco&#x02010;friendly, and adaptable alternative for clinicians.</p><sec id="cre270110-sec-0200"><label>4.1</label><title>Innovative Aspects of the Proposed Method</title><p>AR was chosen for its ability to dynamically overlay digital models onto physical structures in real time, a feature that overcomes the rigidity of traditional static drilling guides. (Wang et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270110-bib-0020" ref-type="bibr">2023</xref>). Dynamic navigation systems, although more versatile, require complex and expensive optical tracking equipment, which restricts their widespread adoption (Tang et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270110-bib-0017" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>).</p><p>The AR system proposed in this study eliminates these barriers by leveraging the affordability and widespread availability of smartphones. The system requires no specialized hardware or extensive calibration, relying instead on consumer devices equipped with integrated cameras and computational capabilities. By integrating visual cues directly into the physical model, the AR application ensures precise alignment between virtual overlays and physical components. This real&#x02010;time visualization might enable clinicians to adjust implant positioning dynamically, improving procedural flexibility while reducing costs and environmental impact.</p></sec><sec id="cre270110-sec-0210"><label>4.2</label><title>Feasibility Demonstrated in In Vitro Testing</title><p>The in vitro testing validated the system's feasibility, demonstrating consistent alignment of virtual overlays with physical models and effective guidance for implant drill positioning. The AR system promises maintained overlay clarity under proper lighting conditions, facilitating precise visualization of planned implant trajectories. These findings highlight the potential of AR as a cost&#x02010;effective and adaptable solution that combines the strengths of traditional and dynamic guidance systems without their associated limitations.</p></sec><sec id="cre270110-sec-0220"><label>4.3</label><title>Camera Visibility and Target Recognition</title><p>Optimal visibility for the camera was achieved by calibrating the smartphone's autofocus to focus on the occlusal surface of the physical model. Predefined, color&#x02010;coded regions on the model served as visual targets, which the AR application recognized and mapped to corresponding digital overlays. This integration of visual cues ensured consistent alignment between the physical and virtual components, minimizing the risk of misalignment due to variations in camera angle or distance (Goutcher et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270110-bib-0006" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>).</p><p>While the current system utilized computer vision algorithms to recognize and project overlays, future enhancements could incorporate AI&#x02010;based techniques to improve target recognition (Panayides et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270110-bib-0015" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). For instance, machine learning algorithms could enable the system to adapt to variable lighting conditions, occlusions from instruments, or operator movement, further enhancing the robustness of the AR system.</p></sec><sec id="cre270110-sec-0230"><label>4.4</label><title>Challenges and Limitations</title><p>Despite its promise, the AR system faces certain challenges that must be addressed for successful clinical application. The reliance on stable lighting and unobstructed visual cues introduces potential vulnerabilities in dynamic surgical environments (Tsai et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270110-bib-0018" ref-type="bibr">2023</xref>). Shadows cast by instruments or uneven illumination occasionally disrupted the system's functionality during testing (Jakab et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270110-bib-0009" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>). Future iterations could incorporate adaptive algorithms or improved lighting setups to mitigate these issues.</p><p>Another limitation lies in the operator&#x02010;dependent nature of the AR system. The smartphone's orientation significantly influenced the initial alignment of the virtual and physical models. A vertical orientation targeting the largest occlusal surface produced the most accurate results, while deviations from this position led to alignment errors (Cunningham and Brooks&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270110-bib-0002" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>). Standardized protocols or automated alignment features could reduce operator variability, ensuring greater consistency in clinical settings.</p></sec><sec id="cre270110-sec-0240"><label>4.5</label><title>Eco&#x02010;Friendly and Economic Advantages</title><p>The proposed method aligns with sustainable practices by eliminating the need for disposable drilling guides, which generate medical waste and incur significant fabrication costs. By replacing physical templates with virtual overlays, the system reduces environmental impact while streamlining the implant placement workflow (H&#x000f6;lken et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270110-bib-0008" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>). Furthermore, the reliance on consumer smartphones eliminates the expense of specialized hardware, making the system accessible to a broader range of dental practitioners. These features underscore the economic and ecological advantages of the AR approach, making it a viable option for modern dental practices.</p></sec><sec id="cre270110-sec-0250"><label>4.6</label><title>Future Directions</title><p>This feasibility study was designed to explore the potential of an AR system for guiding dental implant placement, rather than to quantitatively assess its accuracy or compare it directly with existing methods. The focus of this initial phase was to demonstrate the basic functionality of the system, including the alignment of virtual overlays with the physical model and its ability to guide the implant drill visually.</p><p>Future research will include detailed measurements of accuracy, such as deviations between planned and achieved implant positions, as well as statistical analyses to validate the system's performance. Comparisons with current state&#x02010;of&#x02010;the&#x02010;art guidance systems will also be conducted to establish its clinical relevance. Additionally, AI&#x02010;based enhancements for automated target recognition, real&#x02010;time adjustments, and robustness against environmental variability will be integrated into the system to address current limitations.</p><p>Clinical trials will be essential to assess the system's effectiveness and usability in real&#x02010;world scenarios. Investigations into advanced hardware, such as depth sensors or stereo cameras, may further optimize the AR system for broader applications, ensuring reliable performance in diverse surgical environments.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="cre270110-sec-0260"><label>5</label><title>Conclusion</title><p>This study demonstrates the feasibility of using AR on consumer smartphones for guided dental implant placement. The proposed system offers real&#x02010;time visualization, reduces reliance on static drilling guides, and eliminates the need for expensive specialized hardware, making it a cost&#x02010;effective and adaptable solution. In vitro testing showed consistent alignment between virtual overlays and physical models, successful guidance for implant drill positioning, and maintained clarity under proper lighting conditions.</p><p>However, challenges such as the system's reliance on stable lighting, visual cues, and operator dependence highlight areas for improvement. Future work will focus on quantitatively assessing accuracy, integrating AI for enhanced target recognition, and conducting clinical trials to validate the system in real&#x02010;world settings. Expanding its application to other dental procedures and exploring advanced hardware integrations may further optimize its performance.</p><p>In conclusion, the AR system presents a promising, eco&#x02010;friendly alternative for dental implantology, with the potential to improve accessibility, reduce costs, and enhance procedural flexibility.</p></sec><sec id="cre270110-sec-0270"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>Richard Mosch contributed to acquisition, analysis, and interpretation and drafted the manuscript. Vasilios Alevizakos contributed to conception and design and critically revised the manuscript. Dragan Alexander Str&#x000f6;bele contributed to analysis and drafted the manuscript. Marcus Schiller contributed to acquisition and critically revised the manuscript. Constantin von See contributed to conception and design and critically revised the manuscript. All authors gave their final approval and agreed to be accountable for all aspects of the work.</p></sec><sec id="cre270110-sec-0290"><title>Ethics Statement</title><p>The authors have nothing to report.</p></sec><sec id="cre270110-sec-0300"><title>Consent</title><p>The authors have nothing to report.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="cre270110-sec-0310"><title>Conflicts of Interest</title><p>The authors declare no conflicts of interest.</p></sec></body><back><ack id="cre270110-sec-0280"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>The authors have nothing to report.</p></ack><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="cre270110-sec-0330"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The authors have nothing to report. The data sets used and/or analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></sec><ref-list content-type="cited-references" id="cre270110-bibl-0001"><title>References</title><ref id="cre270110-bib-0001"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270110-cit-0001">
<string-name>
<surname>Campos</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
<surname>Manfro</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
<surname>Coura</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>M. C.</given-names>
<surname>Formiga</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2024</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Flapless Guided Dental Implant Surgery in a Systemically Compromised Patient: A Case Report</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Cureus</source>
<volume>16</volume>, no. <issue>8</issue>: <elocation-id>e67582</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39310548</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270110-bib-0002"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270110-cit-0002">
<string-name>
<surname>Cunningham</surname>, <given-names>B. W.</given-names>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>D. M.</given-names>
<surname>Brooks</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2022</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Comparative Analysis of Optoelectronic Accuracy in the Laboratory Setting Versus Clinical Operative Environment: A Systematic Review</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Global Spine Journal</source>
<volume>12</volume>, no. <issue>2_suppl</issue>: <fpage>59S</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>74S</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35393881</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270110-bib-0003"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270110-cit-0003">
<string-name>
<surname>Dastan</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Fiorentino</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>A. E.</given-names>
<surname>Uva</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2024</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Precise Tool to Target Positioning Widgets (Totta) in Spatial Environments: A Systematic Review</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>IEEE Transactions on Visualization &#x00026; Computer Graphics</source>
<volume>30</volume>, no. <issue>11</issue>: <fpage>7020</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7030</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39255173</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270110-bib-0004"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270110-cit-0004">
<string-name>
<surname>Dastan</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Fiorentino</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>E. D.</given-names>
<surname>Walter</surname>
</string-name>, et al. <year>2024</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Co&#x02010;Designing Dynamic Mixed Reality Drill Positioning Widgets: A Collaborative Approach With Dentists in a Realistic Setup</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>IEEE Transactions on Visualization &#x00026; Computer Graphics</source>
<volume>30</volume>, no. <issue>11</issue>: <fpage>7053</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7063</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39250405</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270110-bib-0005"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270110-cit-0005">
<string-name>
<surname>Duong</surname>, <given-names>H. Y.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Roccuzzo</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>St&#x000e4;hli</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>G. E.</given-names>
<surname>Salvi</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>N. P.</given-names>
<surname>Lang</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Sculean</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2022</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Oral Health&#x02010;Related Quality of Life of Patients Rehabilitated With Fixed and Removable Implant&#x02010;Supported Dental Prostheses</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Periodontology</source>
<volume>88</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue>: <fpage>201</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>237</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270110-bib-0006"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270110-cit-0006">
<string-name>
<surname>Goutcher</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
<surname>Murray</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
<surname>Benz</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2022</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Image Statistics Determine the Integration of Visual Cues to Motion&#x02010;In&#x02010;Depth</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Scientific Reports</source>
<volume>12</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue>: <fpage>7941</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35562584</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270110-bib-0007"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270110-cit-0007">
<string-name>
<surname>Hama</surname>, <given-names>D. R.</given-names>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>B. J.</given-names>
<surname>Mahmood</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2023</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Comparison of Accuracy Between Free&#x02010;Hand and Surgical Guide Implant Placement Among Experienced and Non&#x02010;Experienced Dental Implant Practitioners: An In Vitro Study</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Journal of Periodontal &#x00026; Implant Science</source>
<volume>53</volume>, no. <issue>5</issue>: <fpage>388</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>401</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37154109</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270110-bib-0008"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270110-cit-0008">
<string-name>
<surname>H&#x000f6;lken</surname>, <given-names>F.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
<surname>Al&#x02010;Nawas</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Meereis</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Bjelopavlovic</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2022</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Digital Workflow for Implant Placement and Immediate Chairside Provisionalization of a Novel Implant System Without Abutment &#x02013; A Case Report</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Medicina</source>
<volume>58</volume>, no. <issue>11</issue>: <fpage>1612</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36363569</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270110-bib-0009"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270110-cit-0009">
<string-name>
<surname>Jakab</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>B. M.</given-names>
<surname>Deegan</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Sharma</surname>
</string-name>, et al. <year>2024</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Surround&#x02010;View Fisheye Optics in Computer Vision and Simulation: Survey and Challenges</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>IEEE Transactions on Intelligent Transportation Systems</source>
<volume>25</volume>, no. <issue>9</issue>: <fpage>10542</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10563</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270110-bib-0010"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270110-cit-0010">
<string-name>
<surname>Jiang</surname>, <given-names>W.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
<surname>Ma</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
</string-name>, et al. <year>2018</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Evaluation of the 3d Augmented Reality&#x02010;Guided Intraoperative Positioning of Dental Implants in Edentulous Mandibular Models</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>International Journal of Oral &#x00026; Maxillofacial Implants</source>
<volume>33</volume>, no. <issue>6</issue>: <fpage>1219</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1228</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30427952</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270110-bib-0011"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270110-cit-0011">
<string-name>
<surname>Kim</surname>, <given-names>Y. J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Kim</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J. R.</given-names>
<surname>Lee</surname>
</string-name>, et al. <year>2024</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Comparison of the Accuracy of Implant Placement Using a Simple Guide Device and Freehand Surgery</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Journal of Dental Sciences</source>
<volume>19</volume>, no. <issue>4</issue>: <fpage>2256</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2261</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39347026</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270110-bib-0012"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270110-cit-0012">
<string-name>
<surname>Lee</surname>, <given-names>K. H.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Li</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
<surname>Varble</surname>
</string-name>, et al. <year>2024</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Smartphone Augmented Reality Outperforms Conventional CT Guidance for Composite Ablation Margins in Phantom Models</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Journal of Vascular and Interventional Radiology</source>
<volume>35</volume>, no. <issue>3</issue>: <fpage>452</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>461.e3</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37852601</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270110-bib-0013"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270110-cit-0013">
<string-name>
<surname>Navab</surname>, <given-names>N.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Martin&#x02010;Gomez</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Seibold</surname>
</string-name>, et al. <year>2022</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Medical Augmented Reality: Definition, Principle Components, Domain Modeling, and Design&#x02010;Development&#x02010;Validation Process</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Journal of Imaging</source>
<volume>9</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue>: <fpage>4</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36662102</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270110-bib-0014"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270110-cit-0014">
<string-name>
<surname>Nulty</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>
<year>2024</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>A Literature Review on Prosthetically Designed Guided Implant Placement and the Factors Influencing Dental Implant Success</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>British Dental Journal</source>
<volume>236</volume>, no. <issue>3</issue>: <fpage>169</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>180</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38332076</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270110-bib-0015"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270110-cit-0015">
<string-name>
<surname>Panayides</surname>, <given-names>A. S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Amini</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>N. D.</given-names>
<surname>Filipovic</surname>
</string-name>, et al. <year>2020</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>AI in Medical Imaging Informatics: Current Challenges and Future Directions</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>IEEE Journal of Biomedical and Health Informatics</source>
<volume>24</volume>, no. <issue>7</issue>: <fpage>1837</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1857</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32609615</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270110-bib-0016"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270110-cit-0016">
<string-name>
<surname>Puleio</surname>, <given-names>F.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>V.</given-names>
<surname>Tosco</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
<surname>Pirri</surname>
</string-name>, et al. <year>2024</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Augmented Reality in Dentistry: Enhancing Precision in Clinical Procedures &#x02013; A Systematic Review</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Clinics and Practice</source>
<volume>14</volume>, no. <issue>6</issue>: <fpage>2267</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2283</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39585006</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270110-bib-0017"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270110-cit-0017">
<string-name>
<surname>Tang</surname>, <given-names>W. L.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>X. Y.</given-names>
<surname>Chao</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>Z.</given-names>
<surname>Ye</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M. W.</given-names>
<surname>Liu</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
<surname>Jiang</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2024</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>The Use of Dynamic Navigation Systems as a Component of Digital Dentistry</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Journal of Dental Research</source>
<volume>103</volume>, no. <issue>2</issue>: <fpage>119</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>128</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38098369</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270110-bib-0018"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270110-cit-0018">
<string-name>
<surname>Tsai</surname>, <given-names>T. Y.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
<surname>Onuma</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Z&#x00142;ahoda&#x02010;Huzior</surname>
</string-name>, et al. <year>2023</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Merging Virtual and Physical Experiences: Extended Realities in Cardiovascular Medicine</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>European Heart Journal</source>
<volume>44</volume>, no. <issue>35</issue>: <fpage>3311</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3322</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37350487</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270110-bib-0019"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270110-cit-0019">
<string-name>
<surname>Vu</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Ibarra&#x02010;Vega</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>C. D.</given-names>
<surname>Yang</surname>
</string-name>, et al. <year>2024</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Interventions to Reduce Surgical Waste Burden: A Systematic Review</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery &#x02013; Global Open</source>
<volume>12</volume>, no. <issue>8</issue>: <elocation-id>e6085</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39171245</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270110-bib-0020"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270110-cit-0020">
<string-name>
<surname>Wang</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
<surname>Xie</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
<surname>Fang</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>Z.</given-names>
<surname>Chen</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
<surname>Yu</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2023</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Accuracy of Intraoperative Measuring Guide and Conventional Surgical Guide in Anterior Implant Surgery: A Retrospective Case&#x02010;Control Study</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>International Journal of Oral &#x00026; Maxillofacial Implants</source>
<volume>38</volume>, no. <issue>2</issue>: <fpage>277</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>286</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36525249</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270110-bib-0021"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270110-cit-0021">
<string-name>
<surname>Younis</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
<surname>Lv</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
<surname>Xu</surname>
</string-name>, et al. <year>2024</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Accuracy of Dynamic Navigation Compared to Static Surgical Guides and the Freehand Approach in Implant Placement: A Prospective Clinical Study</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Head &#x00026; Face Medicine</source>
<volume>20</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue>: <fpage>30</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38745297</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>