<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">ACG Case Rep J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">ACG Case Rep J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="coden">ACGCRJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">AC9</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>ACG Case Reports Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2326-3253</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Wolters Kluwer</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Maryland, MD</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11864302</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ACGCR-24-0996</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14309/crj.0000000000001627</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="art-access-id">00002</article-id><article-version vocab="JAV" vocab-identifier="http://www.niso.org/publications/rp/RP-8-2008.pdf" article-version-type="Version of Record">3</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Inflammatory Bowel Disease</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A Pelvic Mass in a Young Patient With Crohn's Disease</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0009-0008-4723-5524</contrib-id><name><surname>Evers</surname><given-names>Charles D.</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ravindran</surname><given-names>Aishwarya</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><email>aravindr@uab.edu</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rosenblum</surname><given-names>Frida</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><email>frosenblum@uabmc.edu</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>Frederick</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref><email>fweber@uabmc.edu</email></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Medicine, Division of Internal Medicine, Heersink School of Medicine, University of Alabama at Birmingham, Birmingham, AL</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Pathology, Heersink School of Medicine, University of Alabama at Birmingham, Birmingham, AL</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Department of Medicine, Division of Gastroenterology and Hepatology, Heersink School of Medicine, University of Alabama at Birmingham, Birmingham, AL</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold>Correspondence:</bold> Charles D. Evers III, MD (<email>cdevers3rd@gmail.com</email>).</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>3</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>26</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><issue>3</issue><elocation-id>e01627</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>29</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2025 The Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. on behalf of The American College of Gastroenterology.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution Licence 4.0 (CC BY)</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="ac9-12-e01627.pdf"/><abstract><title>ABSTRACT</title><p>Castleman disease (CD) is a rare group of lymphoproliferative disorders subdivided based on clinical features. Although not fully understood, the pathogenesis of both CD and Crohn's disease involves a combination of immune dysregulation and infectious and environmental factors. Interleukin-6, a proinflammatory cytokine, is associated with both diseases and can serve as a common therapeutic target in CD. We report a rare case of coexisting unicentric Castleman disease in a young patient with Crohn's disease.</p></abstract><kwd-group><title>KEYWORDS:</title><kwd>Crohn's disease</kwd><kwd>Castleman disease</kwd><kwd>inflammatory bowel disease</kwd><kwd>lymphoproliferative</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name><meta-value>TRUE</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Castleman disease (CD) is a group of lymphoproliferative disorders that share common morphological features on lymph node biopsy and is further classified based on clinical features into unicentric Castleman disease (UCD) or multicentric Castleman disease (MCD).<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> UCD is the most common variant and typically presents as a solitary mass without systemic symptoms. Surgical excision of the affected lymph node region is diagnostic and therapeutic with a low recurrence rate. MCD affects multiple lymph nodes and tissues and typically presents with constitutional symptoms (fever, night sweats, anasarca, and weight loss) and generalized lymphadenopathy with splenomegaly. MCD is further subdivided into idiopathic MCD (iMCD) and Kaposi sarcoma herpesvirus-associated MCD. Although the pathogenesis of CD is poorly understood, data suggest that UCD is a clonal neoplastic process arising from stromal cells, and several associations exist with other autoimmune diseases (Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).<sup><xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> Studies show interleukin-6 (IL-6) plays a role in subsets of CD (particularly iMCD), and anti-IL-6 monoclonal antibodies (mAb) are the first-line therapy for symptomatic patients; however, about half of patients do not respond to IL-6 inhibition, suggesting alternative cytokines are involved.<sup><xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> Interestingly, IL-6 is also implicated in the pathogenesis of Crohn's disease.<sup><xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> However, the infrequency of reported cases of patients with both conditions suggests other factors may be involved. This case provides the third description of Crohn's disease coexisting with CD (Table <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).<sup><xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup></p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Autoimmune associations with CD</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Autoimmune condition</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Association with CD</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Systemic lupus erythematosus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Both commonly present with localized or generalized lymphadenopathy, systemic symptoms<sup><xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rheumatoid arthritis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lymphadenopathy, pathogenesis involves dysregulation of IL-6<sup><xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crohn's disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pathogenesis involves dysregulation of IL-6<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sjogren syndrome</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Both associated with anti-Sjogren-syndrome-related antigen A antibodies<sup><xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult-onset still's disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Similar histopathological findings<sup><xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paraneoplastic pemphigus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reported in patients with CD; UCD &#x0003e; iMCD<sup><xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Psoriasis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reported in patients with iMCD<sup><xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myasthenia gravis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reported in patients with iMCD<sup><xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Autoimmune hemolytic anemia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diagnosed in 30%&#x02013;40% of patients with iMCD at initial presentation<sup><xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Autoimmune thrombocytopenia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diagnosed in 15%&#x02013;20% of patients with iMCD at initial presentation<sup><xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Evan syndrome</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reported in patients with iMCD<sup><xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other"><p>Table 1 includes autoimmune conditions associated with CD. While these associations exist, the exact relationship between CD and autoimmune disorders is not fully understood. This list is not exhaustive.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>CD, Castleman disease; IL-6, interleukin-6; iMCD, idiopathic multicentric Castleman disease; UCD, unicentric Castleman disease.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Case reports with CD and Crohn's disease</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case report</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (y)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Location of CD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diagnosis</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gupta A, et al<sup><xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retroperitoneal Mass (5.7 &#x000d7; 3.5 &#x000d7; 2.0 cm)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unicentric CD, hyaline vascular variant</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gupta R, et al<sup><xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mesenteric lymph nodes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multicentric CD, hyaline vascular variant</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Evers, et al</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retroperitoneal Mass (4.3 &#x000d7; 5.7 &#x000d7; 5.1 cm)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unicentric CD, hyaline vascular variant</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other"><p>CD, Castleman disease.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2"><title>CASE REPORT</title><p>A 32-year-old woman presented with left lower quadrant abdominal pain for 3 weeks. She had a medical history of Crohn's disease, endometriosis, disseminated histoplasmosis, and nephrolithiasis. The pain was intermittent, dull, and radiated to the left flank. Her Crohn's disease had been clinically quiescent for several years, managed at another institution on mesalamine, and she denied recent fevers, night sweats, weight loss, diarrhea, or rectal bleeding. The pain was not associated with oral intake, and her stools were well formed. Further review of systems was entirely negative.</p><p>The patient was diagnosed with Crohn's disease 13 years before presentation (2010). At that time, 75 cm of the jejunum and 10 cm of the terminal ileum, including the ileocecal valve, were surgically resected at an outside facility. She was discharged on mesalamine and sporadically adhered to this regimen; 3 years later (2013), she developed a small bowel obstruction due to a duodenal stricture that required a lengthy hospitalization included jejunal tube placement for nutrition, initiation of adalimumab and methotrexate, and multiple balloon dilations of the duodenal stricture. She remained on methotrexate and adalimumab with excellent disease control for 4 years, but in 2017, she was hospitalized with disseminated histoplasmosis. Methotrexate and adalimumab were transitioned to mesalamine during and after histoplasmosis treatment. Since 2017, her Crohn's disease remained well controlled without other therapy.</p><p>In 2019, she first experienced left lower quadrant pain, and computed tomography (CT) imaging revealed a 5.3 cm &#x000d7; 3.8 cm heterogeneous solid mass (Figure <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Diagnostic laparoscopy soon after showed grade I endometriosis and a retroperitoneal mass. Further evaluation was planned but was disrupted due to the pandemic.</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Radiographic imaging. Radiologically, the differential diagnosis included indolent lymphoma, paraganglioma, nerve sheath tumor, desmoid, or histoplasmosis recurrence. (A) Contrast-enhanced computed tomography, September 2019, (B) magnetic resonance of the abdomen&#x02014;T1-weighted postcontrast, December 2022, (C) contrast-enhanced computed tomography, December 2023, (D) positron emission tomography scan, February 2024.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ac9-12-e01627-g001" position="float"/></fig><p>Physical examination was notable only for mild suprapubic and left lower quadrant tenderness without palpable lymphadenopathy or masses. Notable initial laboratory studies are included in Table <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">3</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T3"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Notable laboratory values at initial presentation</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Result</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference range</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hemoglobin (g/dL)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.7</td><td align="char" char="ndash" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.3&#x02013;15.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">White blood cell count (&#x000d7;10<sup>9</sup>/L)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0</td><td align="char" char="ndash" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0&#x02013;11.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Platelet count (&#x000d7;10<sup>9</sup>/L)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">305</td><td align="char" char="ndash" rowspan="1" colspan="1">150&#x02013;400</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neutrophils (%)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">85</td><td align="char" char="ndash" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35&#x02013;73</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lymphocytes (%)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="char" char="ndash" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15&#x02013;52</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C-reactive protein (mg/L)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.23</td><td align="char" char="ndash" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;10.9</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Magnetic resonance enterography revealed a well-defined, lobulated, avidly enhancing left pelvic sidewall lesion measuring 4.3 cm &#x000d7; 5.7 cm &#x000d7; 5.1 cm felt radiographically consistent with a paraganglioma, peripheral nerve sheath tumor, or desmoid tumor (Figure <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>), and subsequent CT revealed similar findings (Figure <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). No other lesions were noted by radiologic examination (Figure <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Flexible sigmoidoscopy with endoscopic ultrasound-guided biopsy noted a polymorphous population of lymphocytes, but no definitive diagnosis was ascertained. Due to ongoing discomfort, she elected to undergo surgical resection of the mass. She tolerated the procedure well with no complications; histology of the mass is provided in Figures <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> and <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>. The overall histopathologic features and radiologic findings were diagnostic of unicentric Castleman disease, the hyaline vascular variant. A comprehensive next-generation sequencing analysis was negative for pathogenic mutations and fusions.</p><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Histology of the pelvic soft tissue mass. Microscopic evaluation of the specimen on hematoxylin and eosin-stained sections shows portions of lymphoid tissue with somewhat distorted nodal architecture. The lymphoid parenchyma (A, 4&#x000d7;) shows follicles of varying sizes with a somewhat expanded interfollicular area (B, 10&#x000d7;), demonstrating the proliferation of small, hyalinized vessels in a heterogeneous background of small mature lymphocytes, histiocytes, occasional immunoblasts, and a few plasma cells. Dysplastic follicular dendritic cells characterized by hyperchromatic nuclei with multinucleation are present (C, 40&#x000d7;). Some of the follicles demonstrate twinning, regressive changes, lymphocyte depletion, hyaline deposits, and radially penetrating capillaries, surrounded by concentric layers of mantle zone lymphocytes (A 4&#x000d7;; D 20&#x000d7;).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ac9-12-e01627-g002" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Immunophenotypic characterization of the pelvic soft tissue mass. The interfollicular areas are composed of CD3-positive T cells (A, 4&#x000d7;) that are cytologically unremarkable. The lymphoid follicles are composed of CD20-positive B cells (B, 4&#x000d7;). CXCL13 (C, 10&#x000d7;) highlights the FDC meshworks, including the dysplastic FDCs, and these demonstrated coexpression of other FDC markers (CD21 and clusterin (not shown)). Patchy foci in the interfollicular areas are composed of indolent TdT-positive and CD3-positive T lymphoblasts (D, 10&#x000d7;), which are known to be associated with Castleman disease. FDC, follicular dendritic cell.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ac9-12-e01627-g003" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s3"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>UCD usually presents as an enlarging mass, which may be discovered by visualization, palpation, or incidentally found on radiographical imaging. Although some cases are asymptomatic, the most common presenting symptom is pain secondary to the mass effect, which disrupts local structures and compresses nerves. Diagnosis requires surgical excision and histological examination of the entire lymph node. As demonstrated in this case, core needle biopsy/fine-needle aspirate is usually insufficient to confirm the diagnosis of CD because macroscopic architectural features of the lymph node are usually needed for diagnosis. Including a whole-body CT or fluorodeoxyglucose-positron emission tomography may be necessary to evaluate for other lymphoproliferative disorders. Complete surgical excision is curative in a majority of cases of UCD, and overall survival at 5 years exceeds 90%.<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup></p><p>This is the third case report describing concomitant CD and Crohn's disease. As previously mentioned, IL-6 is implicated in the pathogenesis of each, although increased levels are more closely associated with iMCD than UCD. Siltuximab, an anti-IL-6 mAb, is the first-line treatment and only US Food and Drug Administration-approved therapy for iMCD.<sup><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> IL-6 mAbs (tocilizumab, PF-04236921) have been studied for use in Crohn's disease and demonstrate efficacy; however, an association with increased risk of gastrointestinal abscess/perforation and profound immunosuppression has limited their development.<sup><xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> Olamkicept, a fusion protein that inhibits IL-6 trans-signaling, selectively targets the IL-6 pathway responsible for chronic inflammation while sparing the classic IL-6 signaling pathway responsible for intestinal barrier integrity, immune homeostasis, and mucosal regeneration.<sup><xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> According to early studies, olamkicept effectively reduces inflammation and provides clinical remission of inflammatory bowel disease for some patients without an increased risk of perforation.<sup><xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> The IL-6 pathway represents a promising therapeutic target for emerging therapies in inflammatory bowel disease.</p><p>Although the patient's IL-6 levels are normal at present, her level at the time of active Crohn's disease or prior disseminated histoplasmosis is unknown as is whether either played a role in the development of CD. She was not treated with any anti-IL-6 therapies because she lacked systemic symptoms and radiographic evidence to suggest iMCD. Whether chronic immune stimulation in Crohn's disease is the cause of the increased risk of lymphoma and possibly CD in Crohn's disease is unclear.<sup><xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup></p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>DISCLOSURES</title><p>Author contributions: C.D.E.: Primary composer, article guarantor; reviewed case, performed literature reviews, composed first draft, composed revisional draft, corresponding author. A.R., F.R.: Worked together to prepare the pathological report, make the diagnosis, photographed the gross pathology, composed Figures 2 and 3, and provided the legend text for Figures 2 and 3. Both authors reviewed the first draft and revisional draft. F.W.: primary editor, senior author; provided clinical care for the patient. Reviewed the first draft, provided recommendations for revisions, reviewed revisional draft, performed role of senior author.</p><p>Financial disclosure: None to report.</p><p>Informed consent was obtained for this case report.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="R1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carbone</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Borok</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Damania</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Castleman disease</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Dis Primers.</source>
<year>2021</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>84</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34824298</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez Garc&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez-Mart&#x000ed;n</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Robles Marhuenda</surname><given-names>&#x000c1;</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Idiopathic multicentric Castleman disease and associated autoimmune and autoinflammatory conditions: Practical guidance for diagnosis</article-title>. <source>Rheumatology (Oxford).</source>
<year>2023</year>;<volume>62</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1426</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>35</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35997567</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Demirkan</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Do&#x0011f;an</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kalyoncu U&#x000e7;ar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>S&#x000f6;nmez</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aktay Ayaz</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Systemic lupus erythematosus complicated with Castleman disease: A case-based review</article-title>. <source>Rheumatol Int.</source>
<year>2021</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>475</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32797278</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nishimoto</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical studies in patients with Castleman's disease, Crohn's disease, and rheumatoid arthritis in Japan</article-title>. <source>Clin Rev Allergy Immunol.</source>
<year>2005</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>221</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>30</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16129906</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alhendi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Naser</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The dual role of interleukin-6 in Crohn's disease pathophysiology</article-title>. <source>Front Immunol.</source>
<year>2023</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>1295230</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38106420</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ayyar</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zia</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Naina</surname><given-names>HV</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Hyaline-vascular type Castleman's disease, sarcoidosis, and Crohns disease</article-title>. <source>Indian J Hematol Blood Transfus.</source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>Suppl 1</issue>):<fpage>335</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bansal</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A rare triad of Crohn's disease, eosinophilic enteritis, and Castleman's disease</article-title>. <source>J Gastrointest Surg.</source>
<year>2020</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1217</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31485903</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Clinical characteristics and immunological abnormalities of Castleman disease complicated with autoimmune diseases</article-title>. <source>J Cancer Res Clin Oncol.</source>
<year>2021</year>;<volume>147</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>2107</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>15</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33544201</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gakiopoulou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Korkolopoulou</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Paraskevakou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Membranoproliferative glomerulonephritis in the setting of multicentric angiofollicular lymph node hyperplasia (Castleman's disease) complicated by Evan's syndrome</article-title>. <source>J Clin Pathol.</source>
<year>2010</year>;<volume>63</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>552</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20439324</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dispenzieri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fajgenbaum</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Overview of Castleman disease</article-title>. <source>Blood</source>
<year>2020</year>;<volume>135</volume>(<issue>16</issue>):<fpage>1353</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>64</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32106302</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Rhee</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Munshi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Siltuximab for multicentric Castleman's disease: A randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Lancet Oncol.</source>
<year>2014</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>966</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>74</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25042199</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Takazoe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fukuda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>
<article-title>A pilot randomized trial of a human anti-interleukin-6 receptor monoclonal antibody in active Crohn's disease</article-title>. <source>Gastroenterology.</source>
<year>2004</year>;<volume>126</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>989</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>47</lpage>; discussion 947.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15057738</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Danese</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vermeire</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hellstern</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Randomised trial and open-label extension study of an anti-interleukin-6 antibody in Crohn's disease (ANDANTE I and II)</article-title>. <source>Gut.</source>
<year>2019</year>;<volume>68</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>40</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29247068</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamamoto-Furusho</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Parra-Holgu&#x000ed;n</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Emerging therapeutic options in inflammatory bowel disease</article-title>. <source>World J Gastroenterol.</source>
<year>2021</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>48</issue>):<fpage>8242</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>61</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35068868</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Effect of induction therapy with olamkicept vs placebo on clinical response in patients with active ulcerative colitis: A randomized clinical trial</article-title>. <source>JAMA.</source>
<year>2023</year>;<volume>329</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>725</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>34</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36881032</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schreiber</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aden</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bernardes</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Therapeutic interleukin-6 trans-signaling inhibition by olamkicept (sgp130Fc) in patients with active inflammatory bowel disease</article-title>. <source>Gastroenterology.</source>
<year>2021</year>;<volume>160</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>2354</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>66.e11</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33667488</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smedby</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Erichsen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Increasing risk of lymphoma over time in Crohn's disease but not in ulcerative colitis: A Scandinavian cohort study</article-title>. <source>Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol.</source>
<year>2023</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>3132</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>42</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37061104</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>