<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?properties manuscript?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">101724632</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">47465</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Adv Ther (Weinh)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Adv Ther (Weinh)</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Advanced therapeutics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2366-3987</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40012744</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11864751</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/adtp.202400117</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS2011941</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Uncovering the Elusive Structures and Mechanisms of Prevalent Antidepressants</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Jieye</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bu</surname><given-names>Guanhong</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Unge</surname><given-names>Johan</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gonen</surname><given-names>Tamir</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="A2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="A3" ref-type="aff">3</xref><xref rid="CR1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Biological Chemistry, University of California, Los Angeles, 615 Charles E. Young Drive South, Los Angeles, California 90095, United States</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Physiology, University of California, Los Angeles, 615 Charles E. Young Drive South, Los Angeles, California 90095, United States</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Howard Hughes Medical Institute, University of California, Los Angeles, Los Angeles, California 90095, United States</aff><author-notes><corresp id="CR1"><label>*</label>Corresponding Author T.G. <email>tgonen@g.ucla.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>13</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>9</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>7</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>26</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>9</issue><elocation-id>2400117</elocation-id><permissions><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which allows reusers to distribute, remix, adapt, and build upon the material in any medium or format, so long as attribution is given to the creator. The license allows for commercial use.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="https://advanced.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/adtp.202400117"/><abstract id="ABS1"><p id="P1">Most treatments to alleviate major depression work by either inhibiting human monoamine transporters, vital for the reuptake of monoamine neurotransmitters, or by inhibiting monoamine oxidases, which are vital for their degradation. The analysis of the experimental 3D structures of those antidepressants in their drug formulation state is key to precision drug design and development. In this study, we apply microcrystal electron diffraction (MicroED) to reveal the atomic 3D structures for the first time of five of the most prevalent antidepressants (reboxetine, pipofezine, ansofaxine, phenelzine, bifemelane) directly from the commercially available powder of the active ingredients. Their modes of binding are investigated by molecular docking, revealing the essential contacts and conformational changes into the biologically active state. This study underscores the combined use of MicroED and molecular docking to uncover elusive drug structures and mechanisms to aid in further drug development pipelines.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="graphical" id="ABS2"><title>Graphical Abstract</title><p id="P2">
<graphic xlink:href="nihms-2011941-f0006.jpg" position="anchor"/></p><p id="P3">The experimental three-dimensional (3D) structures of five prevalent commercial antidepressants (reboxetine, pipofezine, ansofaxine, phenelzine, and bifemelane) in their drug formulation states were first elucidated by microcrystal electron diffraction (MicroED) directly from powdered materials. Their binding modes, including essential contacts and conformational changes into the biologically active states, were investigated using molecular docking.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="P4">Major depression is a complicated mood disorder caused by biological, psychological and social factors.<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> Based on the monoamine hypothesis,<sup><xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> current therapy manipulates the availability and activity of three monoamine neurotransmitters (norepinephrine, NE; serotonin, 5-HT; and dopamine, DT) in synapses. Normal neuron-neuron communication encompasses the release and binding of monoamine neurotransmitters from the presynaptic neuron to receptors in the postsynaptic neuron. The monoamine neurotransmitters that remain in the synaptic cleft can be subject to reuptake through monoamine transporters (human norepinephrine transporter, hNET; human serotonin transporter, hSERT; human dopamine transporter, hDAT)<sup><xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup>. The excess is degraded by monoamine oxidase A/B (MAO-A/B)<sup><xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> in the presynaptic neuron (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1a</xref>). Antidepressants that inhibit monoamine transporters or oxidases involved in these processes help increase the bioavailability of monoamine neurotransmitters (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1b</xref>). For example, reboxetine is a norepinephrine reuptake inhibitor (NRI) inhibiting the function of hNET.<sup><xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> Pipofezine is a tricyclic antidepressant (TCA) functioning on hSERT<sup><xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> while ansofaxine interacts with hSERT, hNET, hDAT and is a serotonin&#x02013;norepinephrine&#x02013;dopamine reuptake inhibitor (SNDRI).<sup><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> Monoamine oxidase inhibitors (MAOIs) like phenelzine<sup><xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> inhibit the MAO-A/B irreversibly, while bifemelane<sup><xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> interact in a reversible mode.</p><p id="P5">While the solution-state structure may be biologically relevant we note that these drugs exist in a conformational equilibrium where many of these states may be hard to determine. The experimental 3D structures of antidepressants presented here reveal their conformations in the solid state, providing insights into drug formulations. These experimental structures serve as a critical starting point when modeling the energetic and conformational changes needed for drug binding to the protein pocket. In structure-based drug design these insights are essential for precision drug design and development. To date, most of the crystal structures of antidepressants have been solved by single-crystal X-ray diffraction (SC-XRD), like desvenlafaxine,<sup><xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> viloxazine.<sup><xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> A fundamental step needed for SC-XRD is to obtain large enough crystals (&#x0003e;5 &#x003bc;m) to have adequate diffraction.<sup><xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> This is however sometimes unattainable due to the imperfect crystals. Techniques like powder X-ray diffraction (PXRD)<sup><xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> and solid-state nuclear magnetic resonance (ssNMR)<sup><xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup> may be challenging due to peak overlapping and broadening, and extensive calculations may be required. Therefore, several antidepressant compounds remain without a known crystal structure for several years. The cryogenic electron microscopy (Cryo-EM) technique microcrystal electron diffraction (MicroED) serves as a complementary route for experimental crystal structure determination,<sup><xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> which enables the direct analysis of microcrystals from a seemingly amorphous powder, where the crystal size needed is merely a billionth of the size needed for SC-XRD.<sup><xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> Since the advent of this technique already delivered many novel drug structures, like antihistamines<sup><xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> and macrocyclic drugs<sup><xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P6">Despite the variety of antidepressants, the knowledge of their interactions with target proteins remains limited. The biggest hurdle for the determinations of the complex structures is the purification and stabilization of their target receptors: membrane proteins like hNET and hDAT.<sup><xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup> As a result, model proteins such as the drosophila dopamine transporter (dDAT) and the bacterial leucine transporter (LeuT) were used as homology models for the human proteins. Their binding complexes with antidepressants have been reported, such as for reboxetine/dDAT<sup><xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> and sertraline/LeuT.<sup><xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup> Although only the structures have 56% and 25% sequence identity to the human sequences, respectively, they interestingly indicate more than one binding site for the antidepressants on their respective target. However, the human counterparts vary in sequence affecting the exact recapturing the binding mode in humans, possible residue changes in active sites remain unknown and may effect drug binding. Although the complex structures of hSERT and selective serotonin reuptake inhibitor (SSRI) like citalopram or paroxetine have been published (PDB [PDB, <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.rcsb.org/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.rcsb.org/</ext-link>] entries: 5I73, 5I6X),<sup><xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup> the structures of the complexes of hSERT with pipofezine (TCA) or ansofaxine (SNDRI) remain undetermined, as is also the case for the complexes of MAO-A/B to phenelzine and bifemelane (MAOIs).</p><p id="P7">In this study, we applied MicroED to determine the atomic structures of five prevalent commercial antidepressants, reboxetine (Europe, 1997),<sup><xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> pipofezine (Russia, 1960),<sup><xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> ansofaxine (China, 2022),<sup><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> phenelzine (United States, 1961)<sup><xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> and bifemelane (Japan, 1980)<sup><xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> which have remained undetermined for decades although widely prescribed worldwide (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1b</xref>). To uncover their binding mechanism in human targets, molecular docking was applied using the ligand structures determined by MicroED and the receptor structures from either the Protein Data Bank or from AlphaFold predictions.<sup><xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup> The docked target-bound structures were analyzed to show key interactions with the residues in the active sites, and their conformational changes from the drug formulation state.</p></sec><sec id="S2"><title>Results and Discussion</title><sec id="S3"><title>Antidepressant structures in their drug formulation state.</title><p id="P8">For each antidepressant, just a few nanograms of powder were used in MicroED sample preparation without recrystallization (See <xref rid="S18" ref-type="sec">Methods</xref> for more details).<sup><xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> A Thermo-Fisher Talos Arctica transmission electron microscope (TEM) (200&#x0202f;keV) equipped with CetaD CMOS camera (4096 &#x000d7; 4096 pixels) and EPU-D software (Thermo-Fisher) was used for MicroED data collection. The microcrystal screening was conducted in imaging mode (SA 5300x), once suitable nanocrystals were identified, their eucentric heights were adjusted to keep the sample within the beam during rotation. The crystals of five antidepressants all appeared as thin plates or sheets (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2a</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">e</xref>) which are not ideal for SC-XRD, possibly explaining why their X-ray crystal structures have remained elusive for decades. Continuous rotation MicroED data collection<sup><xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> was conducted in the diffraction mode and the parallel electron beam settings using an electron dose rate (exposure) of 0.01 e<sup>&#x02013;</sup>/(&#x000c5;<sup>2</sup>&#x000b7;s). MicroED data were recorded as movies at 0.5 s exposure per frame as the microcrystal was continuously rotated at 2&#x000b0; per second across a 120&#x000b0; angular wedge (from &#x02212;60&#x000b0; to +60&#x000b0;), thus the total dose for each dataset was ~0.6 e<sup>&#x02013;</sup>/&#x000c5;<sup>2</sup>. The MicroED movies were converted to images using mrc2smv.<sup><xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup> The plate or sheet morphology of crystals normally led to a preferred orientation to the carbon film which may restrict the completeness in MicroED if the preferred orientation is systematic. Here, addition of multiple data sets increased completeness indicating that the preferred orientation was not systematic with the exception of 1 data set where the completeness was limited to 86% after indexing, integration and scaling in XDS (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S1</xref>).<sup><xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></sup> The resulting reflection files could be <italic toggle="yes">ab initio</italic> solved by SHELXT<sup><xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup>/SHELXD<sup><xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup> and refined by SHELXL<sup><xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup> (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2f</xref> and <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>, <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S1</xref>).</p><p id="P9">The atomic MicroED structures of five antidepressants: reboxetine mesylate <bold>1</bold>, pipofezine dihydrochloride monohydrate <bold>2</bold>, ansofaxine hydrochloride dihydrate <bold>3</bold>, phenelzine sulfate <bold>4</bold>, and bifemelane hydrochloride <bold>5</bold>, have been solved for the first time (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>). These elusive crystal structures offered detailed structural information about their drug formulation state, including conformers, anhydrous/hydrate forms, and salts, as well as be meaningful in understanding the conformational changes during the binding to the target pockets in their biologically active states.</p><sec id="S4"><label>(1)</label><title>Reboxetine mesylate 1.</title><p id="P10">The racemic MicroED structure <bold>1</bold> was solved in a centrosymmetric monoclinic P 2<sub>1</sub>/c space group at the resolution of 0.73 &#x000c5; (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2a</xref> and <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>), with the unit cell parameters of <bold>a</bold> = 20.00 &#x000c5;, <bold>b</bold> = 5.49 &#x000c5;, <bold>c</bold> = 19.06 &#x000c5;, <bold>&#x003b1;</bold> = 90.000&#x000b0;, <bold>&#x003b2;</bold> = 107.338&#x000b0;, <bold>&#x003b3;</bold> = 90.000&#x000b0;. Two enantiomers, namely <bold>1R</bold> and <bold>1S</bold>, stack their hydrophobic and hydrophilic parts in layers along the <italic toggle="yes">c</italic>-axis so that the layers are parallel with the <italic toggle="yes">a</italic>- and <italic toggle="yes">c</italic>-plane. Within these layers, molecules adopt a head-to-tail orientation along the <italic toggle="yes">a</italic>-axis, linked by mesylate anions (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S1</xref>). The crystal packing is mainly a result of several hydrogen bonds and dipole-dipole interactions along <italic toggle="yes">b</italic>- and c-axes, for instance the N2/N2&#x02032;&#x02012;H&#x000b7;&#x000b7;&#x000b7;O6 (3.30 &#x000c5;) bond to the sulfonyl group (atom O6) and the dipole-dipole interactions involving the CH atoms in reboxetine and O atoms in mesylate. The elongation along <italic toggle="yes">a</italic>-axis is stabilized by T-shaped/parallel-displaced pi-stacking interactions ranging from 4.81 to 5.50 &#x000c5;. In total six torsion angles are freely rotatable, which dramatically impact the whole structure (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S2</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S5"><label>(2)</label><title>Pipofezine dihydrochloride monohydrate 2.</title><p id="P11">The MicroED structure <bold>2</bold> was solved in a monoclinic P 2<sub>1</sub>/c space group at the resolution of 0.82 &#x000c5; (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2b</xref> and <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>), with the unit cell parameters of <bold>a</bold> = 6.88 &#x000c5;, <bold>b</bold> = 15.61 &#x000c5;, <bold>c</bold> = 15.93 &#x000c5;, <bold>&#x003b1;</bold> = 90.000&#x000b0;, <bold>&#x003b2;</bold> = 97.222&#x000b0;, <bold>&#x003b3;</bold> = 90.000&#x000b0;. Two conforms, namely <bold>2a</bold> and <bold>2b</bold> were identified in the uniFig t cell. Each can be transformed by inversion symmetry or 180&#x000b0; rotation of C11&#x02012;N4/C11&#x02032;&#x02012;N4&#x02032; bond. The crystal packing is formed mainly by hydrogen bonds and ion-dipole interactions between <bold>2a/2b</bold> and chloride anions along <italic toggle="yes">b</italic>- and <italic toggle="yes">c</italic>-axes, <italic toggle="yes">i.e.</italic> hydrogen bonds N5/N5&#x02032;&#x02012;H&#x000b7;&#x000b7;&#x000b7;Cl1 (3.01 &#x000c5;) and N3/N3&#x02032;&#x02012;H&#x000b7;&#x000b7;&#x000b7;O2 (2.67 &#x000c5;); ion-dipole interactions between CH atoms and chloride anions (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S3</xref>). The water molecules serve as hydrogen bond donors to Cl1 or Cl2 anions that bridge <bold>2a</bold> and <bold>2b</bold> molecules together (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S3</xref>). The packing along the <italic toggle="yes">a</italic>-axis is facilitated by strong parallel-displaced pi-stacking interactions between the phenyl and pyridazine rings in <bold>2a</bold> and <bold>2b</bold> (3.65 &#x000c5;). In <bold>2</bold>, bond angles are mostly fixed, with only one freely rotating bond (C10&#x02012;C11&#x02012;N4&#x02012;C15 and C10&#x02032;&#x02012;C11&#x02032;&#x02012;N4&#x02032;&#x02012;C15&#x02032;, measured at &#x000b1;178.60&#x000b0; in <bold>2a</bold> and <bold>2b</bold>), generating a co-planar arrangement of piperazine ring and tricyclic moiety (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S4</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S6"><label>(3)</label><title>Ansofaxine hydrochloride dihydrate 3.</title><p id="P12">The racemic MicroED structure <bold>3</bold> was solved in a centrosymmetric monoclinic P 2<sub>1</sub>/c space group at the resolution of 0.83 &#x000c5; (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2c</xref> and <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>), with the unit cell parameters of <bold>a</bold> = 14.80 &#x000c5;, <bold>b</bold> = 10.27 &#x000c5;, <bold>c</bold> = 16.04 &#x000c5;, <bold>&#x003b1;</bold> = 90.000&#x000b0;, <bold>&#x003b2;</bold> = 95.309&#x000b0;, <bold>&#x003b3;</bold> = 90.000&#x000b0;. Two enantiomers, namely <bold>3R</bold> and <bold>3S</bold>, pack as <italic toggle="yes">zig-zag</italic> shaped layers along the <italic toggle="yes">c</italic>-axis. Within each layer, molecules orient head-to-tail along the <italic toggle="yes">a</italic>-axis, interconnected by two water molecules and a chloride anion (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S5</xref>). Each water molecule involves in two hydrogen bonds as the acceptor and another two hydrogen bonds as the donor, the Cl<sup>&#x02013;</sup> anion contains four lone pair electrons that can be the acceptor for four hydrogen bonds, that leads to a dense hydrogen bonding network. The packing along the <italic toggle="yes">b</italic>- and <italic toggle="yes">c</italic>-axes involves extensive hydrogen bonding interactions, <italic toggle="yes">i.e.</italic>, N1/N1&#x02032;&#x02012;H&#x000b7;&#x000b7;&#x000b7;O5 (2.80 &#x000c5;), O5&#x02012;H&#x000b7;&#x000b7;&#x000b7;O1/O1&#x02032; (2.85 &#x000c5;) O4&#x02012;H&#x000b7;&#x000b7;&#x000b7;Cl1 (3.02 &#x000c5;) along the <italic toggle="yes">b</italic>-axis; O3/O3&#x02032;&#x02012;H&#x000b7;&#x000b7;&#x000b7;O4 (2.73 &#x000c5;) and O4&#x02012;H&#x000b7;&#x000b7;&#x000b7;O5 (2.81 &#x000c5;) along the <italic toggle="yes">c</italic>-axis. Although the O5&#x02012;H&#x000b7;&#x000b7;&#x000b7;Cl1 (3.01 &#x000c5;) orients along the <italic toggle="yes">a</italic>-axis, it cannot further elongate the crystal packing, the latter is largely achieved by medium or weak T-shaped pi-stacking interactions between <bold>3R</bold> and <bold>3S</bold> ranging from 5.25 to 5.88 &#x000c5;. In <bold>3</bold>, bond lengths and angles are rather fixed, with six torsion angles exhibit a high degree of rotational freedom (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S6</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S7"><label>(4)</label><title>Phenelzine sulfate 4.</title><p id="P13">The MicroED structure <bold>4</bold> was solved in a centrosymmetric monoclinic P 2<sub>1</sub>/c space group at the resolution of 0.63 &#x000c5; (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2d</xref> and <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>), with the unit cell parameters of <bold>a</bold> = 20.36 &#x000c5;, <bold>b</bold> = 5.46 &#x000c5;, <bold>c</bold> = 20.30 &#x000c5;, <bold>&#x003b1;</bold> = 90.000&#x000b0;, <bold>&#x003b2;</bold> = 111.209&#x000b0;, <bold>&#x003b3;</bold> = 90.000&#x000b0;. Two conformers, namely <bold>4a</bold> and <bold>4b,</bold> were found in the asymmetric unit. As the molecule does not possess a chiral center, the inversion symmetry results in slight differences in the torsion angles (maximum 14&#x000b0; difference, see <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S8</xref>). The positively charged nitrogen containing moieties of <bold>4a</bold> and <bold>4b</bold> forms a hydrophilic network together with the sulfate anions. This network distributes as layers parallel to the b-c plane separated by the hydrophobic layers containing the aromatic and aliphatic part of the molecules. The molecules in the layers adopt a head-to-tail orientation similar to lipid layers. The hydrophilic network is constructed by several hydrogen bonds between <bold>4a/4b</bold> and sulfate anions, such as N1&#x02012;H&#x000b7;&#x000b7;&#x000b7;O5/O8 (2.73 &#x000c5;/2.66 &#x000c5;), N2&#x02012;H&#x000b7;&#x000b7;&#x000b7; O1/O4/O6 (2.73 &#x000c5;/2.73 &#x000c5;/2.67 &#x000c5;), N1&#x02032;&#x02012;H&#x000b7;&#x000b7;&#x000b7;O3/O7 (2.59 &#x000c5;/2.65 &#x000c5;), N2&#x02032;&#x02012;H&#x000b7;&#x000b7;&#x000b7;O2/O4/O5 (2.87 &#x000c5;/2.65 &#x000c5;/2.75 &#x000c5;) (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S7</xref>). The T-shaped/parallel-displaced pi-stacking interactions ranging from 5.02 to 5.93 &#x000c5; facilitate the packing along the <italic toggle="yes">a</italic>-axis. Bond angles are mostly fixed, with three freely rotatable torsion angles corresponding to similar values in two conformers. In the biological state, only the phenylethyl part will covalently bind to the flavin adenine dinucleotide (FAD) cofactor in MAO-A/B, where the C4&#x02012;C7/C4&#x02032;&#x02012;C7&#x02032; is presumed to have 44&#x000b0; to 69&#x000b0; rotations, see details below (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5a</xref>, <xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">b</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S8"><label>(5)</label><title>Bifemelane hydrochloride 5.</title><p id="P14">The MicroED structure <bold>5</bold> was solved in a centrosymmetric orthorhombic P bca space group at the resolution of 0.83 &#x000c5; (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2e</xref> and <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>), with the unit cell parameters of <bold>a</bold> = 12.87 &#x000c5;, <bold>b</bold> = 7.31 &#x000c5;, <bold>c</bold> = 35.10 &#x000c5;, <bold>&#x003b1;</bold> = 90.000&#x000b0;, <bold>&#x003b2;</bold> = 90.000&#x000b0;, <bold>&#x003b3;</bold> = 90.000&#x000b0;. Two conformers, namely <bold>5a</bold> and <bold>5b</bold> forms hydrophobic and hydrophilic layers parallell with the <italic toggle="yes">a</italic>- and <italic toggle="yes">b</italic>-plane. A double-helical extension was observed along the <italic toggle="yes">c</italic>-axis. Complex hydrogen bonds between <bold>5a/5b</bold> and chloride anions dominate the packing along the <italic toggle="yes">a</italic>- and <italic toggle="yes">b</italic>-axes, for example, the N1&#x02012;H1N&#x000b7;&#x000b7;&#x000b7;Cl1 and N1&#x02032;&#x02012;H1N&#x02032;&#x000b7;&#x000b7;&#x000b7;Cl1 (3.04 &#x000c5;) along the <italic toggle="yes">a</italic>-axis; the bifurcated N1&#x02012;H2N&#x000b7;&#x000b7;&#x000b7;Cl1 and N1&#x02032;&#x02012;H2N&#x02032;&#x000b7;&#x000b7;&#x000b7;Cl1 (3.10/3.58 &#x000c5;) are along the <italic toggle="yes">a</italic>- and <italic toggle="yes">b</italic>-axes. However, the packing along the <italic toggle="yes">c</italic>-axis is facilitated by the T-shaped pi-stacking interactions between two phenyl rings (5.09 to 5.98 &#x000c5;). In the bifemelane structure, as many as eight torsion angles are freely rotatable which can significantly change the overall structure (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S10</xref>). The high number of freely rotatable bonds enhance the conformational flexibility, facilitating the binding within the protein pockets.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S9"><title>Binding mechanisms of 1&#x02013;5 predicted by molecular docking.</title><p id="P15">As mentioned above, although the inhibition between <bold>1</bold>&#x02013;<bold>5</bold> and their target proteins were documented, the detailed binding mechanism was undetermined. To uncover this, molecular docking was applied. In the docking setup, the MicroED ligand structures of <bold>1</bold>&#x02013;<bold>3</bold> and <bold>5</bold> were used. Since only the phenethyl part of <bold>4</bold> covalently binds to FAD cofactor in MAO-A/B, a substitute structure <bold>4*</bold> was extracted from PDB entry 2VRM.<sup><xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></sup> Three X-ray structures: hSERT (PDB entry: 5I73),<sup><xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup> MAO-A (PDB entry: 2Z5X),<sup><xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup> MAO-B (PDB entry: 1OJ9),<sup><xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup> along with two AlphaFold structures<sup><xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup>: hNET (PDB entry: AF_AFP23975F1) and hDAT (PDB entry: AF_AFQ01959F1) were utilized. The AlphaFold structures of hNET and hDAT were calculated from human SLC6A2 and SLC6A3 gene sequences respectively with high scores. The binding sites in hNET, hSERT, hDAT and MAO-A/B have been reported in literature describing the complex structures (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S11</xref>, <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S2</xref>).<sup><xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> During the molecular docking, the ligands were set to be flexible while keeping the receptor rigid. The docked complex with the lowest energy was examined Protein-Ligand Interaction Profiler (PLIP) web tool<sup><xref rid="R49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></sup> to illustrate the key contacts and conformational changes from drug formulation state into the biologically active state (see details in <xref rid="S18" ref-type="sec">Methods</xref>).</p><sec id="S10"><label>(1)</label><title>Inhibition of the reuptake process of NE, 5-HT and DA by 1&#x02013;3.</title><sec id="S11"><title>1&#x02012;hNET complexes.</title><p id="P16"><bold>1R</bold> and <bold>1S</bold> were docked at hNET in the central (S1) and allosteric (S2) sites respectively (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S12a</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">b</xref>),<sup><xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup> their binding interactions are similar but differ in certain cyclic moieties. For example, within the S1 site, <bold>1R</bold> is primarily bound by two hydrogen bonds between the morpholine ring and Phe317, Ser419 residues. Another pi-stacking (Tyr152) and nine hydrophobic interactions stabilize the conformation of phenyl and 2-ethoxyphenoxy rings (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4a</xref>). The binding interactions observed in <bold>1R</bold>/dDAT complex (PDB: 4XNX)<sup><xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> exhibit weaker hydrogen bonds and fewer hydrophobic interactions. <bold>1S</bold> in the S1 site is bound by two hydrogen bonds (Asp75, Tyr152), one pi-stacking (Tyr152) and nine hydrophobic interactions (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4b</xref>). The conformation changes of <bold>1R</bold> and <bold>1S</bold> at S1 site were predominantly driven by the rotations of C18&#x02012;O3, C5&#x02012;C9 and C5&#x02032;&#x02012;C9&#x02032; bonds (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S2</xref>).</p><p id="P17">The binding interactions in the S2 site seems comparably &#x0201c;tight&#x0201d; as the one in the S1 site. For instance, <bold>1R</bold> is bound by three hydrogen bonds between the morpholine ring and Trp80, Arg81, Asp473 residues, and five hydrophobic interactions for the rest of structure (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4a</xref>); whereas <bold>1S</bold> is bound by two hydrogen bonds (Ala384 and Asp473), two pi-stacking (Trp80), and five hydrophobic interactions (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4b</xref>). The conformation changes of <bold>1R</bold> and <bold>1S</bold> at S2 site were mainly attributed to the rotations of C18&#x02012;O3, C12&#x02012;O2, C13&#x02032;&#x02012;O3&#x02032; and C9&#x02032;&#x02012;C5&#x02032; bonds (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S2</xref>). The S1 and S2 sites have a comparable amount of interactions with the molecule indicating activity at both suggested sites, which fits well with the reported view of S1 being the central site and S2 an allosteric site. When the central site of <bold>1R</bold>/<bold>1S</bold> is occupied, the hNET is maintained in the outward-open conformation and obstruct the reuptake channel of NE.<sup><xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup></p></sec><sec id="S12"><title>2&#x02012;hSERT complexes.</title><p id="P18"><bold>2</bold> was tested at the central (S1) and allosteric (S2) sites in hSERT (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S12c</xref>),<sup><xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup> however the final docking center was found near S2 site due to the weak binding observed in S1 site (<italic toggle="yes">i.e.</italic> only the hydrophobic interactions). A salt bridge between Asp98 and piperazine ring, together with one pi-stacking (Phe335), one pi-cation interaction (Arg104), three hydrophobic interactions (Phe335, Phe556) to the tricyclic moiety stabilized the binding complex of <bold>2</bold>/hERT (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4c</xref>). The structures of <bold>2</bold> in its drug-formulation state and biologically active state are very similar, with only 3&#x02013;6&#x000b0; rotation C11&#x02032;&#x02012;N4&#x02032; bond (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S4</xref>), and maintain the piperazine ring and tricyclic moiety in a nearly co-planar geometry (C10&#x02012;C11&#x02012;N4&#x02012;C15&#x02248;180&#x000b0;) for both states. The minimum conformational changes ensure small entropy differences upon binding which is beneficial for the binding of <bold>2</bold> to the receptor.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S13"><title>3&#x02012;hSERT, hNET, hDAT complexes.</title><p id="P19"><bold>3R</bold>/<bold>3S</bold> demonstrated inhibitions against hSERT, hNET and hDAT as a triple reuptake inhibitor.<sup><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> Due to their larger molecular occupancy, only the central (S1) site was docked (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S12d</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">i</xref>). The binding interactions between <bold>3R/3S</bold> and hSERT, hNET, hDAT differ because of the structure and sequence variations in their binding pockets.</p><p id="P20">In <bold>3R/3S</bold>&#x02012;hSERT complexes, <bold>3R</bold> is involved in two hydrogen bonds between the dimethyl amine group and Phe335 residue, and between the 1-hydroxycyclohexyl ring and Asp98 residue (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4d</xref>). <bold>3S</bold> also adopts a salt bridge between the dimethyl amine group and Asp98 residue (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4e</xref>). In addition, the binding of <bold>3R/3S</bold> is stabilized by seven and eleven hydrophobic interactions with the target respectively. The above conformation can be reached by a simple rotation of C12&#x02032;&#x02012;C15&#x02032; bond in <bold>3S</bold>, while four bond rotations (C5&#x02012;C8, C9&#x02012;O2, C12&#x02012;C15, C22&#x02012;N11) were required in <bold>3R</bold> during the transition to its biologically active state (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S6</xref>).</p><p id="P21">In <bold>3R/3S</bold>&#x02012;hNET complexes, <bold>3R</bold> is bound by one salt bridge (Asp75), two hydrogen bonds between the dimethyl amine group and Phe72, and the 1-hydroxycyclohexyl ring and Ser419, respectively. The additional pi-stacking (Phe317) and nine hydrophobic interactions stabilized the rest of the structure (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4f</xref>). The similar binding was found for <bold>3S</bold>, where the dimethyl amine group is bound by one salt bridge (Asp75) and one hydrogen bond (Phe317), with the rest of the molecule anchored by one pi-stacking (Phe317) and eight hydrophobic interactions (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4g</xref>). To transition from drug-formulation state to biologically active state, <bold>3R</bold> requires rotations at C5&#x02012;C8, C12&#x02012;C15, and C22&#x02012;N1 bonds, while <bold>3S</bold> requires changes at C5&#x02032;&#x02012;C8&#x02032;, C12&#x02032;&#x02012;C15&#x02032;, and C15&#x02032;&#x02012;C16&#x02032; bonds (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S6</xref>).</p><p id="P22">In <bold>3R/3S</bold>&#x02012;hDAT complexes, <bold>3R</bold> engages in a rigid salt bridge (Asp79) and two hydrogen bonds (Phe76, Ser422) as similar to hNET; the rest of molecule is anchored by one pi-stacking (Trp84) and up to eleven hydrophobic interactions (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4h</xref>); Similarly, <bold>3S</bold> is bonding with a salt bridge between the dimethyl amine group and Asp79 residue, one hydrogen bond between the 1-hydroxycyclohexyl ring and Gly426 residue, and twelve hydrophobic interactions (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4i</xref>). The conformational shifts from drug formulation state to biologically active state needs two major bond rotations, like C12&#x02012;C15 and C22&#x02012;N1 in <bold>3R</bold> and C9&#x02032;&#x02012;O2&#x02019; and C22&#x02032;&#x02012;N1&#x02032; in <bold>3S</bold> (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S6</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S14"><label>(2)</label><title>Inhibition of the degradation process of NE, 5-HT and DA by 4&#x02013;5.</title><sec id="S15"><title>4*&#x02012;MAO-A/B complexes.</title><p id="P23">Under the catalysis of MAO-A/B, the N&#x02012;H bond in <bold>4</bold> will be cleaved to result a diazene intermediate.<sup><xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></sup> The diazene was oxidized to produce an arylalkyl radical, which reacted rapidly with N(5) atom of flavin group (I1 site) and formed an adduct in FAD as <bold>4*</bold> (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S13a</xref>,<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">b</xref>).<sup><xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></sup> The enzyme function can be inhibited because of the inactivation of FAD. The crystal structure of <bold>4*</bold>/MAO-B was reported (PDB entry: 2VRM),<sup><xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></sup> where the major rotation in phenethyl part was found in C4&#x02012;C7/C4&#x02032;&#x02012;C7&#x02032; bond, from 107&#x02013;109&#x000b0; to 176&#x000b0;, leading the co-planar orientation of C7&#x02012;C8 bond and phenyl ring (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S8</xref>). Such conformation was maintained by three hydrophobic interactions between the phenethyl group and Leu171, Phe343, Tyr398 residues (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5b</xref>). Since the position of FAD in MAO-A and MAO-B are highly conserved, the <bold>4*</bold> was extracted and docked in MAO-A. The resulting model is very similar to <bold>4*/</bold>MAO-B, showing the co-planar of C7&#x02012;C8 bond and phenyl ring (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S8</xref>), and five hydrophobic interactions between the phenethyl group and Tyr69, Ile180, Gln215, Phe352, Tyr407 residues (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5a</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S16"><title>5&#x02012;MAO-A/B complexes.</title><p id="P24">The reversible inhibitor <bold>5</bold> was proven to bind with a higher inhibition of MAO-A (K<sub>i</sub>=4.2 &#x003bc;M) than MAO-B (K<sub>i</sub>=46.0 &#x003bc;M).<sup><xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> The binding site of <bold>5</bold>/MAO-A was docked in the active site (R1 site, <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S13c</xref>),<sup><xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup> where <bold>5</bold> was bound by two hydrogen bonds between the <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-methylbutylamine group and the Phe208 residue, and between the phenoxyl ring and Gln215 residue, respectively. One pi-stacking (Tyr407) and up to ten hydrophobic interactions restrain the rest of molecules (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5c</xref>). The above conformational shifts from the drug formulation state were completed by the rotation of C14&#x02012;O1, C14&#x02012;C15 and C16&#x02012;C17, making the molecule be stretched in the large voids of MAO-A (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S10</xref>).</p><p id="P25">In contrary to MAO-A, the active site in MAO-B is surrounded by several hydrophobic residues, and more restricted space at the entrance impede the direct entry of large molecules (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S14</xref>). As a result, <bold>5</bold> was trapped at the R1&#x02032; site (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S13d</xref>),<sup><xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup> which has ~12.3 &#x000c5; distance to the N(5) atom of FAD. Such distance in MAO-A is around 8.8 &#x000c5; (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S14</xref>), which possibly demonstrates the higher affinity of <bold>5</bold> to MAO-A rather than MAO-B. In the R1&#x02032; site, <bold>5</bold> was bound by two hydrogen bonds (Pro102, Thr201) and ten hydrophobic interactions (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5d</xref>), keeping it in a more folded conformation. The above conformation was completed by the rotation of C14&#x02012;O1, C14&#x02012;C15, C16&#x02012;C17, C17&#x02012;N1 in the <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-methylbutylamine group (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S10</xref>).</p></sec></sec></sec></sec><sec id="S17"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="P26">Characterizing the 3D structures of antidepressants from their drug formulation state and the biologically active state are both essential for precision drug design and development. Conventionally, SC-XRD has been the most frequently used technique for drug structure elucidation, which however requires larger well-ordered crystals (&#x0003e;5 &#x003bc;m). Other techniques like PXRD and solid-state NMR have been important for structure determinations of smaller molecules, but larger targets are associated with problems in peak broadening or overlapping, and require extensive computational simulation to deliver an atomic model.<sup><xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup> Several important targets such as the five antidepressants analyzed in this study do not easily yield large enough crystals for SXR-XD or PXRD so their 3D structures remained elusive for decades. The emerging Cryo-EM technique MicroED<sup><xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> serves as a complementary route for experimental structure determination directly from powder-like microcrystals<sup><xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup>, which are the prevalent form of formulated drugs or active pharmaceutical ingredients. Thus, it may bypass the time and resources spent in efforts to produce large crystals for SC-XRD.</p><p id="P27">Analysis of the crystal packing in the five structures <bold>1</bold>&#x02013;<bold>5</bold> revealed a difference in packing interactions along three dimensions in any of the crystals. For example, in <bold>3</bold>, the extensive hydrogen bonding interactions (2.73 to 3.02 &#x000c5;) extend the packing in <italic toggle="yes">b</italic>- and <italic toggle="yes">c</italic>-axes, but T-shaped pi-stacking interactions (5.25 to 5.88 &#x000c5;) mainly correspond for packing elongation along <italic toggle="yes">a</italic>-axis. These differences in packing in different direction in the crystal potentially translate to differences in crystal growth along the different directions and hence may result in crystals being plates or sheets due to a slower growing expansion of the crystals in the third dimension. Such crystal shapes, with a large area but a thickness far below one micron are unsuitable for SC-XRD but ideal for MicroED.</p><p id="P28">Although it is important to obtain protein-ligand complex structures for <bold>1</bold>&#x02013;<bold>5</bold> experimentally, the purification and crystallization of those membrane proteins are extremely difficult and they are too small for single particle Cryo-EM analyses without bulking up their size with deactivating antibodies for example. Instead, molecular docking was used here as an alternative technique to predict the interactions between <bold>1</bold>&#x02013;<bold>5</bold> and their target proteins directly using the MicroED structures of <bold>1</bold>&#x02013;<bold>5</bold>. This approach revealed unknown properties in both drug and proteins, for example, the binding orientations of <bold>3R/3S</bold> in hSERT, hNET, hDAT were determined by a salt bridge between Asp residue and dimethyl amine group (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4d</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">i</xref>); The structural differences found in MAO-A/B led to different selectivity with <bold>5</bold>. The conformational changes of <bold>1</bold>&#x02013;<bold>5</bold> from drug formulation state to the biologically active state were also elucidated, pinpointing to the possible geometric compromises caused by the rotation of dynamic groups within the drugs. This study underscored the combined use of MicroED and molecular docking in uncovering elusive antidepressant drug structures and mechanisms which are crucial for the future drug design and development.</p></sec><sec id="S18"><title>Methods</title><sec id="S19"><title>Materials.</title><p id="P29">All commercial compounds were used as received without further recrystallization. <bold>2</bold>&#x02013;<bold>5</bold> were purchased from InvivoChem LLC. <bold>1</bold> was purchased from Advanced ChemBlocks Inc.</p></sec><sec id="S20"><title>Grid preparation.</title><p id="P30">Sample preparation followed the procedure as described previously.<sup><xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> The carbon-coated copper grid (200-mesh, 3.05 mm O.D., Ted Pella Inc.) was pretreated with glow-discharge plasma at 15 mA on the negative mode for 45 s using PELCO easiGlow (Ted Pella Inc.). Less than 1 mg of each powdery compound were transferred and mixed with a grid in a 10 mL scintillation vial. After gently shaking the vial for 30 s, the grid was clipped using c-ring and autogrid clip (Thermo Fisher) at room temperature.</p></sec><sec id="S21"><title>MicroED data collection.</title><p id="P31">The grids were loaded into the Thermo Fisher Talos Arctica TEM operating at 80 K and 200 keV (~0.0251 &#x000c5; wavelength). The TEM was pre-aligned using a 500 nm diffraction grating replica with latex spheres (Ted Pella Inc.). The CetaD camera (4096 &#x000d7; 4096 pixels) and EPUD software (Thermo Fisher) were used for MicroED data collection. The screening of microcrystals was done in the imaging mode (SA 5300x) (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2a</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">e</xref>). The MicroED datasets were collected in the diffraction mode at the calibrated sample to detector distance of 659 mm and the parallel beam condition (spot size 11, C2 aperture size 70 and C2 intensity 45.2%) which resulted in an illuminating dose rate of 0.01 e<sup>&#x02013;</sup>/(&#x000c5;<sup>2</sup>&#x000b7;s). The selected area aperture (resulting in ~1.4 &#x003bc;m beam region) was inserted to cover the selected microcrystals during data collection to avoid diffraction from other samples in the beam. The typical data collection used a constant rotation rate of ~2&#x000b0; per second over an angular wedge of 120&#x000b0; from &#x02212;60&#x000b0; to +60&#x000b0;, with 0.5 s exposure time per frame. Prior to data collection, selected microcrystals were calibrated to eucentric heights to ensure that they remained inside the beam during the rotation.</p></sec><sec id="S22"><title>MicroED data processing.</title><p id="P32">The MicroED movies were saved in mrc format and converted to smv format using the mrc2smv software (<ext-link xlink:href="https://cryoem.ucla.edu/microed" ext-link-type="uri">https://cryoem.ucla.edu/microed</ext-link>).<sup><xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup> The converted frames were indexed and integrated by XDS.<sup><xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup> The datasets with the highest resolution were scaled using XSCALE.<sup><xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></sup> Multiple diffraction datasets were merged to increase completeness, <italic toggle="yes">i.e.</italic> 86.3% to 99.8% for <bold>1</bold>&#x02013;<bold>3</bold> and <bold>5</bold>. The merged intensities were converted to SHELX hkl format using XDSCONV,<sup><xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></sup> which could be <italic toggle="yes">ab initio</italic> solved by SHELXT<sup><xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup> or SHELXD<sup><xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup> (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S1</xref>). The structures were refined by SHELXL<sup><xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup> graphical interface Shelxle<sup><xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup> to yield the final MicroED structures (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref> and <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S23"><title>Molecular Docking.</title><p id="P33">The ligand structures of <bold>1</bold>&#x02013;<bold>3</bold> and <bold>5</bold> were extracted from their MicroED structures and saved as mol2 files. Anions and water molecules were removed. Charges were kept based on the analysis of pKa values.<sup><xref rid="R43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></sup> Because <bold>4</bold> binds covalently with FAD coenzyme in MAO-A/B, therefore, <bold>4</bold>* extracted from PDB entry 2VRM (resolution: 2.30 &#x000c5;) was used as ligand.<sup><xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></sup> All these ligand structures were imported into AutoDock Tools 1.5.7,<sup><xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,<xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></sup> making all the active torsion bonds rotatable (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S2</xref>).</p><p id="P34">All the protein structures were downloaded from the Protein Data Bank (<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.rcsb.org/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.rcsb.org/</ext-link>). The structures of hSERT (PDB entry 5I73),<sup><xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup> MAO-A (PDB entry 2Z5X),<sup><xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup> and MAO-B (PDB entry 1OJ9)<sup><xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup> are determined by X-ray crystallography, while hNET (AF_AFP23975F1)<sup><xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup> and hDAT (AF_AFQ01959F1)<sup><xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup> are based on AlphaFold predictions with a global pLDDT score above 87. The solvent, ligand, and cofactor were removed using Pymol 2.5.5,<sup><xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></sup> except for the docking between <bold>5</bold> and MAO-A/B where the FAD was kept in the original position. After that, hydrogen atoms and charges were computed and added via AutoDock Tools 1.5.7 (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S2</xref>).<sup><xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,<xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></sup></p><p id="P35">Template structures were obtained in PDB database via the query function in CB-Dock2 webtool<sup><xref rid="R48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></sup> or literatures, considering the similarities in protein and ligand (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S11</xref>). The approximate docking center was determined and positioned with an 18.75 &#x000c5; &#x000d7; 18.75 &#x000c5; &#x000d7; 18.75 &#x000c5; grid box in AutoDock Vina1.1.2.<sup><xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,<xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></sup> During the molecular docking, all active torsion bonds in the ligands were set to be flexible, and the receptor was set to be rigid. The docked complex with the lowest binding energy was analyzed by the Protein-Ligand Interaction Profiler (PLIP) web tool.<sup><xref rid="R49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></sup></p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM1"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="SD1" position="float" content-type="local-data"><label>Supinfo</label><media xlink:href="NIHMS2011941-supplement-Supinfo.docx" id="d67e1342" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S24"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p id="P36">The authors thank Michael W. Martynowycz for support and discussions. This study was funded in part by the National Institutes of Health P41GM136508. Portions of this research or manuscript completion were developed with funding from the Department of Defense grants MCDC-2202&#x02013;002. Effort sponsored by the U.S. Government under Other Transaction number W15QKN-16&#x02013;9-1002 between the MCDC, and the Government. The US Government is authorized to reproduce and distribute reprints for Governmental purposes, notwithstanding any copyright notation thereon. The views and conclusions contained herein are those of the authors and should not be interpreted as necessarily representing the official policies or endorsements, either expressed or implied, of the U.S. Government. The PAH shall flowdown these requirements to its subawardees, at all tiers. The Gonen laboratory is supported by funds from the Howard Hughes Medical Institute.</p></ack><ref-list><title>Reference</title><ref id="R1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Jeon</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Amidfar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y-K</given-names></name>, <source>Major Depressive Disorder: Risk Factors, Characteristics and Treatment Options</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Nova Science Publisher</publisher-name>
<year>2017</year>, <volume>71</volume>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lanni</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Govoni</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lucchelli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Boselli</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <source>Cell. Mol. Life Sci</source>. <year>2009</year>, <volume>66</volume>, <fpage>2985</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19521663</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hirschfeld</surname><given-names>RMA</given-names></name>, <source>J. Clin. Psychiatry</source>. <year>2000</year>, <volume>61</volume>, <fpage>4</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Delgado</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>, <source>J. Clin. Psychiatry</source>. <year>2000</year>, <volume>61</volume>, <fpage>7</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Aggarwal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mortensen</surname><given-names>OV</given-names></name>, <source>Curr. Protoc. Pharmacol</source>. <year>2017</year>, <volume>79</volume>, <fpage>12</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shih</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ridd</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <source>Pol. J. Pharmacol</source>. <year>1999</year>, <volume>51</volume>, <fpage>25</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10389141</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>EHF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sonders</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Amara</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tinholt</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Piercey</surname><given-names>MFP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hyslop</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Franklin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Porsolt</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bonsignori</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <source>Biol. Psychiatry</source>. <year>2000</year>, <volume>47</volume>, <fpage>818</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10812041</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Haj&#x000f3;s</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fleishaker</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Filipiak-Reisner</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>EHF</given-names></name>, <source>CNS Drug Rev</source>. <year>2004</year>, <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>23</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14978512</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Aleeva</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Molodavkin</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Voronina</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>, <source>Bull. Exp. Biol. Med</source>. <year>2009</year>, <volume>148</volume>, <fpage>54</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19902096</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mashkovskii</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Polezhaeva</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vertozgadova</surname><given-names>OP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smulevich</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>, <source>Zh Nevrol Psikhiatr Im S S Korsakova</source>. <year>1969</year>, <volume>69</volume>, <fpage>1234</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mi</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <source>Int. J. Neuropsychopharmacol</source>. <year>2022</year>, <volume>25</volume>, <fpage>252</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34747448</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ramsay</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Basile</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maniquet</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hagenow</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pappalardo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Saija</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bryant</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Albreht</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guccione</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <source>Molecules</source>
<year>2020</year>, <volume>25</volume>, <fpage>5908</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33322203</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Solberg</surname><given-names>CO</given-names></name>, <source>JAMA</source>
<year>1961</year>, <volume>177</volume>, <fpage>572</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Naoi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nomura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ishiki</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nagatsu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Neurochem</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <year>1988</year>, <volume>50</volume>, <fpage>243</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Koide</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Onishi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hashimoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Katayama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yamagami</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <source>Drugs Exp. Clin. Res</source>. <year>1995</year>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>175</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8846747</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Duggirala</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kanniah</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Muppidi</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thaimattam</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Devarakonda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <source>CrystEngComm</source>
<year>2009</year>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>989</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ouhabi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Saux</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carpy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <source>Acta Crystallogr., Sect. C: Cryst. Struct. Commun</source>. <year>1990</year>, <volume>46</volume>, <fpage>2160</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Diederichs</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <source>Protein Crystallography: Methods and Protocols</source>
<year>2017</year>, <volume>239</volume>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>KDM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tremayne</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kariuki</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name>, <source>Angew. Chem. Int. Ed</source>. <year>2001</year>, <volume>40</volume>, <fpage>1626</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cordova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moutzouri</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nilsson Lill</surname><given-names>SO</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cousen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kearns</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Norberg</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Svensk Ankarberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McCabe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pinon</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schantz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <source>Nat. Commun</source>. <year>2023</year>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>5138</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37612269</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Balodis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cordova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hofstetter</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Emsley</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <source>J. Am. Chem. Soc</source>. <year>2022</year>, <volume>144</volume>, <fpage>7215</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35416661</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nannenga</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Iadanza</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gonen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <source>elife</source>
<year>2013</year>, <volume>2</volume>, e01345.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nannenga</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Leslie</surname><given-names>AGW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gonen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <source>Nat. Methods</source>
<year>2014</year>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>927</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25086503</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Martynowycz</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hattne</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fulton</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stoltz</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gonen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <source>ACS Cent. Sci</source>. <year>2018</year>, <volume>4</volume>, <fpage>1587</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30555912</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Karothu</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alhaddad</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>G&#x000f6;b</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sch&#x000fc;rmann</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>B&#x000fc;cker</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Naumov</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <source>Angew. Chem. Int. Ed</source>. <year>2023</year>, <volume>62</volume>, e202303761.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Unge</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gonen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <source>Adv. Sci</source>. <year>2024</year>, <volume>11</volume>, 2306435.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Danelius</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wieske</surname><given-names>LHE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gonen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <source>ACS Chem. Biol</source>. <year>2023</year>, <volume>18</volume>, <fpage>2582</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37944119</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Danelius</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wieske</surname><given-names>LHE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gonen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <source>Adv. Biol</source>. <year>2024</year>, <volume>8</volume>, 2300570.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <source>Protein Chromatography: Methods and Protocols</source>
<year>2017</year>, <volume>389</volume>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Penmatsa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gouaux</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <source>Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol</source>. <year>2015</year>, <volume>22</volume>, <fpage>506</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25961798</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Karpowich</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Law</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reith</surname><given-names>MEA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D-N</given-names></name>, <source>Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol</source>. <year>2009</year>, <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>652</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19430461</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gouaux</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <source>Nature</source>
<year>2016</year>, <volume>532</volume>, <fpage>334</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27049939</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Son</surname><given-names>S-Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kondou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yoshimura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yamashita</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tsukihara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A</source>. <year>2008</year>, <volume>105</volume>, <fpage>5739</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18391214</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Binda</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hub&#x000e1;lek</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Restelli</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Edmondson</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mattevi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A</source>. <year>2003</year>, <volume>100</volume>, <fpage>9750</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12913124</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jumper</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pritzel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Figurnov</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ronneberger</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tunyasuvunakool</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>&#x0017d;&#x000ed;dek</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Potapenko</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <source>Nature</source>
<year>2021</year>, <volume>596</volume>, <fpage>583</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34265844</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hattne</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Martynowycz</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Penczek</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gonen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <source>IUCrJ</source>
<year>2019</year>, <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>921</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kabsch</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <source>Acta Crystallogr., Sect. D: Biol. Crystallogr</source>. <year>2010</year>, <volume>66</volume>, <fpage>125</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20124692</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kabsch</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <source>Acta Crystallogr., Sect. D: Biol. Crystallogr</source>. <year>2010</year>, <volume>66</volume>, <fpage>133</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20124693</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sheldrick</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <source>Acta Crystallogr., Sect. A: Found. Adv</source>. <year>2015</year>, <volume>71</volume>, <fpage>3</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25537383</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sheldrick</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <source>Acta Crystallogr., Sect. D: Biol. Crystallogr</source>. <year>2002</year>, <volume>58</volume>, <fpage>1772</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12351820</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sheldrick</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <source>Acta Crystallogr., Sect. C: Struct. Chem</source>. <year>2015</year>, <volume>71</volume>, <fpage>3</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25567568</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>H&#x000fc;bschle</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sheldrick</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dittrich</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <source>J. Appl. Crystallogr</source>. <year>2011</year>, <volume>44</volume>, <fpage>1281</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22477785</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>JZH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <source>J. Chem. Inf. Model</source>. <year>2021</year>, <volume>61</volume>, <fpage>3159</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34251213</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Binda</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hubalek</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mattevi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Edmondson</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <source>Biochemistry</source>
<year>2008</year>, <volume>47</volume>, <fpage>5616</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18426226</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Trott</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <source>J. Comput. Chem</source>. <year>2010</year>, <volume>31</volume>, <fpage>455</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19499576</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Eberhardt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Santos-Martins</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tillack</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Forli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <source>J. Chem. Inf. Model</source>. <year>2021</year>, <volume>61</volume>, <fpage>3891</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34278794</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schrodinger</surname><given-names>LLC</given-names></name>, <source>Version</source>
<year>2015</year>, <volume>1</volume>, <fpage>8</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>Z-X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <year>2022</year>, <volume>50</volume>, <fpage>W159</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35609983</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Adasme</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Linnemann</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bolz</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kaiser</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Salentin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Haupt</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schroeder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <year>2021</year>, <volume>49</volume>, <fpage>W530</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33950214</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p id="P37">(a) Reuptake and degradation of norepinephrine (NE), serotonin (5-HT) and dopamine (DT) in neuron-neuron communication. (b) The overall workflow in this study. List of five prevalent antidepressants with their structures firstly uncovered by MicroED. Their detailed binding mechanism was illustrated by molecular docking using the MicroED structures as inputs. Created with <ext-link xlink:href="http://BioRender.com" ext-link-type="uri">BioRender.com</ext-link>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms-2011941-f0001" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p id="P38">(a-e) Images of the crystals together with typical MicroED patterns of <bold>1</bold>&#x02013;<bold>5</bold>. (f) MicroED data statistics of <bold>1</bold>&#x02013;<bold>5</bold>, see more details in <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S1</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms-2011941-f0002" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p id="P39">MicroED structures and 2F<sub>o</sub>-F<sub>c</sub> density maps (blue mesh) of <bold>1</bold>&#x02013;<bold>5</bold>. <bold>1R</bold>/<bold>1S</bold>, <bold>2a</bold>/<bold>2b</bold>, <bold>3R</bold>/<bold>3S</bold> and <bold>5a</bold>/<bold>5b</bold> are related by an inversion symmetry in the unit cell, <bold>4a</bold>/<bold>4b</bold> are two conformers observed in one asymmetric unit. Atom color: C, gray; N, blue; O, red; S, yellow; Cl, green; H, light green.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms-2011941-f0003" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p id="P40">The protein-drug interaction diagram of complex between (a) <bold>1R</bold> and hNET; (b) <bold>1S</bold> and hNET; (c) <bold>2</bold> and hSERT; (d) <bold>3R</bold> and hSERT; (e) <bold>3S</bold> and hSERT; (f) <bold>3R</bold> and hNET; (g) <bold>3S</bold> and hNET; (h) <bold>3R</bold> and hDAT; (i) <bold>3S</bold> and hDAT. Hydrogen bonding interactions were colored by the dashed line in paleyellow, pi-stacking interactions were colored by the dashed line in lime, and salt bridges were colored by the dashed line in magenta, hydrophobic interactions were omitted for clarification. The binding sites were marked, see the overall view in <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S12</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms-2011941-f0004" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p id="P41">The protein-drug interaction diagram of complex between (a) <bold>4*</bold> and MAO-A; (b) <bold>4*</bold> and MAO-B; (c) <bold>5</bold> and MAO-A; (d) <bold>5</bold> and MAO-B. Hydrogen bonding interactions were colored by the dashed line in paleyellow, pi-stacking interactions were colored by the dashed line in lime. Hydrophobic interactions were colored by the dashed line in red for <bold>4*</bold> but omitted for <bold>5</bold>. The binding sites were marked, see the overall view in <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S13</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms-2011941-f0005" position="float"/></fig></floats-group></article>