<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39890863</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11785756</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">87284</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-025-87284-1</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A survey of obstetric ultrasound uses and priorities for artificial intelligence-assisted obstetric ultrasound in low- and middle-income countries</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Ginsburg</surname><given-names>Amy Sarah</given-names></name><address><email>messageforamy@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liddy</surname><given-names>Zylee</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Alkan</surname><given-names>Eren</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Matcheck</surname><given-names>Kayla</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>May</surname><given-names>Susanne</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/00cvxb145</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.34477.33</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2298 6657</institution-id><institution>Clinical Trials Center, </institution><institution>University of Washington, </institution></institution-wrap>Building 29, Suite 250, 6200 NE 74th Street, Seattle, WA 98115 USA </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.527887.7</institution-id><institution>Caption Health, GE HealthCare, </institution></institution-wrap>San Mateo, CA USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>31</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>3873</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>7</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>17</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Obstetric ultrasound (OBUS) is recommended as part of antenatal care for pregnant individuals worldwide. To better understand current uses of OBUS in low- and middle-income countries and perceptions regarding potential use of artificial intelligence (AI)-assisted OBUS, we conducted an anonymous online global survey. A total of 176 respondents representing 34 countries participated, including 41% physicians, 49% nurses or midwives, and 6% ultrasound technicians. Most had received OBUS training (72%), reported expertise (60%) and confidence (77%) in OBUS use, and had access to ultrasound (85%). Assessment of gestational age, fetal viability, fetal presentation, and multiple gestation were both the most common OBUS uses and among the most highly prioritized for AI-assisted OBUS development. Most respondents noted ultrasound access was important (84%) and agreed that OBUS improves quality of care (98%) and patient outcomes (97%). Of the 34% expressing reservations associated with using AI-assisted OBUS, healthcare providers not understanding the technology (71%), misdiagnosis (62%), and cost (59%) were the most common. Better understanding the OBUS user, the pregnant individual, and the context, and taking care to ensure responsible, sustainable, and inclusive development and use of AI-assisted OBUS will be critical to successful integration and implementation and to increasing access to OBUS.</p><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1038/s41598-025-87284-1.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Obstetric ultrasound</kwd><kwd>Low- and middle-income countries</kwd><kwd>Point of care</kwd><kwd>Artificial intelligence</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Health care</kwd><kwd>Medical research</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Caption Health/ GE HealthCare</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Springer Nature Limited 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">As part of routine antenatal care, the World Health Organization (WHO) recommends that pregnant individuals have an obstetric ultrasound (OBUS) scan before 24 weeks of pregnancy to estimate gestational age, improve detection of fetal anomalies and multiple pregnancies, reduce induction of labor for post-term pregnancy, and improve a woman&#x02019;s pregnancy experience<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. For those who did not have an early OBUS scan, the WHO recommends considering a later OBUS scan to identify the number of fetuses, fetal presentation, and placental location. However, because of a variety of logistical, infrastructural, human capacity, and financial challenges, implementing and scaling up this recommendation in many resource-constrained settings has been limited<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>. While there are no reliable data on how many pregnant individuals globally receive an OBUS, due to increased portability, durability, usability, and affordability, ultrasound use is increasing, including in low- and middle-income countries (LMIC)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. A versatile and safe imaging technology, ultrasound has a wide variety of applications and uses, with OBUS being the most common indication for ultrasound in LMIC<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par3">However, to obtain and interpret OBUS imaging requires trained healthcare providers, and these healthcare providers are not available in all healthcare settings in LMIC. To facilitate healthcare providers to use OBUS to identify and measure various obstetrical and fetal features and conditions, artificial intelligence (AI)-assisted OBUS algorithms to obtain high-quality images and to automatically interpret them are being developed and evaluated<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. Of particular relevance to resource-constrained settings are AI-assisted OBUS algorithms designed to enable novice OBUS users to assess and monitor maternal and fetal health for guiding obstetric care and decision-making. To better understand the current uses of OBUS in LMIC as well as perceptions regarding the potential use of AI-assisted OBUS, we conducted a global online survey.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><p id="Par4">After reviewing the peer-reviewed and published scientific literature to identify common OBUS uses, we developed and piloted a 23-question anonymous online survey in REDCap, separated into five sections, consisting of (1) respondent and (2) healthcare facility demographics, (3) OBUS training and use, (4) OBUS use priorities, and (5) opinions regarding OBUS and AI-assisted OBUS (Appendix 1). Survey respondent and healthcare facility demographics included country, respondent education, current role(s), and information on healthcare facilities and ultrasound equipment. Information on OBUS training, access, and uses was also collected. Respondents were asked to choose the five highest priority OBUS uses in LMIC, taking into account both prevalence/burden and severity. The final section of the survey asked respondents their opinions regarding the importance and value of OBUS in relation to quality of care and patient outcomes, the potential usefulness of AI-assisted OBUS, and any fears or reservations they might have regarding AI-assisted OBUS.</p><p id="Par5">The online survey was open from November 27, 2023 through May 31, 2024. Multiple strategies were employed to target potential survey respondents. We sent the online survey link to colleagues providing care to pregnant individuals in LMIC and those working and providing training in OBUS in LMIC. We contacted potential LMIC respondents via online searches, obstetric conferences, and through in-country professional societies and networks of obstetricians, maternal-fetal medicine specialists, and midwives (specifically, by LMIC region and country). We also contacted corresponding authors of publications identified during our multiple literature reviews, focusing on OBUS use and research in LMIC (specifically, by LMIC country). We chose to include respondents from high-income countries if they had experience with OBUS use in LMIC; when answering questions, respondents were instructed to focus on their experience with and use of OBUS in LMIC. We used the World Bank Atlas method designations for LMIC vs. high-income countries<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>. To improve the response rate, all professional societies and survey respondents contacted were requested to distribute or forward the survey link to their memberships and listservs and to colleagues who provided care to pregnant individuals in LMIC. No sample size calculation was performed.</p><p id="Par6">The cross-sectional survey responses were analyzed descriptively in R version 4.2.2 with simple statistics. Given this was an anonymous survey, no response rate could be calculated. The initial analysis involved examining the data structure and removing entries that lacked data or contained only demographic information. Columns were then analyzed and summary statistics such as range, mean, and standard deviation were calculated where applicable, while counts and percentages were calculated for categorical data. The data were subsequently grouped by respondent education/training and by region, and summary statistics, counts, and percentages were recalculated. The distribution of the most common uses and highest priorities across these groups were then visualized using bar graphs. No statistical tests were utilized. The study and the waiver of informed consent were reviewed by the University of Washington Human Subjects Division, approved, and determined to be exempt due to no greater than minimal risk. All methods were performed in accordance with the relevant guidelines and regulations.</p><sec id="Sec3"><title>Role of the funding source</title><p id="Par7">The Bill &#x00026; Melinda Gates Foundation had no role in the study design, data collection, data analysis, data interpretation, or writing of the manuscript; the co-authors employed by Caption Health/GE Healthcare had input to the study design, data collection, and review of the manuscript.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Results</title><p id="Par8">A total of 176 respondents participated in this online survey, representing 34 countries (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>), with 96% from LMIC, including 63% from Africa and 32% from Asia (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The mean age of respondents reporting their age was 41 (range 20 to 74) years and 64% of respondents reporting their sex were female. Of those reporting their highest level of education/training, 41% identified as physicians, 49% as nurses or midwives, and 6% as ultrasound/radiology technicians.</p><p id="Par9">
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Survey respondents by country. Map created using ArcMap 10.7.1 (ESRI 2019. ArcGIS Desktop: Release 10.7.1. Redlands, CA: Environmental Systems Research Institute).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_87284_Fig1_HTML" id="d33e264"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par10">
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Survey respondents.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td align="left">Age (<italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;169)</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Mean (standard deviation), minimum, maximum</td><td align="left">40.8 (11.2), 20, 74</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Sex (<italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;174)</td><td align="left">N (%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Female</td><td align="left">112 (64.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Male</td><td align="left">62 (35.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Region (<italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;168)</td><td align="left">N (%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Africa</td><td align="left">106 (63.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Asia</td><td align="left">54 (32.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Other</td><td align="left">8 (4.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Highest education (<italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;176)</td><td align="left">N (%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Physician &#x02013; maternal-fetal medicine specialist</td><td align="left">13 (7.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Physician &#x02013; obstetrician</td><td align="left">46 (26.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Physician &#x02013; general practitioner</td><td align="left">9 (5.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Physician &#x02013; radiologist</td><td align="left">1 (0.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Physician &#x02013; other</td><td align="left">4 (2.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Clinical officer</td><td align="left">1 (0.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Nurse</td><td align="left">35 (19.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Midwife</td><td align="left">52 (29.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Ultrasound/radiology technician</td><td align="left">11 (6.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Other (e.g., Masters, PhD, Program manager)</td><td align="left">4 (2.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Current role(s) (<italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;176)*</td><td align="left">N (%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Physician &#x02013; maternal-fetal medicine specialist</td><td align="left">9 (5.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Physician &#x02013; obstetrician</td><td align="left">14 (8.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Physician &#x02013; general practitioner</td><td align="left">49 (27.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Physician &#x02013; radiologist</td><td align="left">1 (0.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Physician &#x02013; other</td><td align="left">3 (1.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Clinical officer</td><td align="left">3 (1.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Nurse</td><td align="left">36 (20.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Midwife</td><td align="left">57 (32.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Ultrasound/radiology technician</td><td align="left">11 (6.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Hospital administrator</td><td align="left">9 (5.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Community health worker</td><td align="left">6 (3.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Other (e.g., Program advisor, Researcher, Program manager)</td><td align="left">3 (1.7)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>N&#x02009;=&#x02009;number of respondents who answered the question</p><p>*Total percentage for individual question may be over 100% due to &#x0201c;Check all that apply&#x0201d; option for that question on the survey</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par13">Among respondents describing their healthcare facility, 61% worked in hospitals, with 69% at a tertiary or academic hospital, and 28% provided care in health centers (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). More respondents worked in healthcare facilities located in urban settings (51%), than in rural (36%) or peri-urban (16%) settings. More respondents worked in publicly funded (77%) than privately funded (31%) healthcare facilities. Access to ultrasound in their current clinical setting(s) was reported by 85% respondents and 11% reported no access to ultrasound. Portable ultrasounds (of which 56% were handheld) were used by 33%, non-portable ultrasounds by 32%, and 35% used both. Probes used included curved (68%), linear (44%), endocavitary (35%), and multi-use (24%). Concerning storage, 45% reported the ability to store OBUS images, with 44% storing on personal devices such as computers, tablets, phones and/or external hard drives, 40% on picture archiving and communication systems, and 22% in electronic health record systems. Of note, only 52% reported their place of work had policies and/or guidelines for OBUS use.</p><p id="Par14">
<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Healthcare facility and ultrasound equipment.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td align="left">Healthcare facility type (<italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;176)*</td><td align="left"><italic>N</italic> (%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Hospital</td><td align="left">107 (60.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Health center</td><td align="left">50 (28.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Office or clinic</td><td align="left">17 (9.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Community health outpost</td><td align="left">9 (5.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Diagnostic imaging center</td><td align="left">4 (2.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Other (e.g., academic/training institution, non-governmental organization)</td><td align="left">8 (4.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Healthcare facility hospital level (<italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;106)*</td><td align="left">N (%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Specialist/academic/tertiary/referral</td><td align="left">73 (68.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Provincial</td><td align="left">8 (7.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">District</td><td align="left">29 (27.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Sub-district</td><td align="left">3 (2.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Healthcare facility location (<italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;174)*</td><td align="left">N (%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Urban</td><td align="left">88 (50.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Peri-urban</td><td align="left">28 (16.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Rural</td><td align="left">63 (36.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Other</td><td align="left">1 (0.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Healthcare facility funding (<italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;176)*</td><td align="left">N (%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Public</td><td align="left">135 (76.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Private</td><td align="left">55 (31.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Other (e.g., non-governmental organization, parastatal, community support)</td><td align="left">3 (1.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Access to ultrasound (<italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;175)</td><td align="left">N (%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Yes</td><td align="left">149 (85.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">No</td><td align="left">19 (10.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Not applicable</td><td align="left">7 (4.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Number of ultrasound machines (<italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;129)</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Median, mean (standard deviation), minimum, maximum</td><td align="left">2, 3.4 (6.2), 1, 50</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Ultrasound machine types (<italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;148)</td><td align="left">N (%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Portable</td><td align="left">49 (33.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Not portable</td><td align="left">47 (31.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Both portable and not portable</td><td align="left">52 (35.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Handheld portable ultrasound (<italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;99)</td><td align="left">N (%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Yes</td><td align="left">55 (55.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">No</td><td align="left">44 (44.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Ultrasound probes used (<italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;136)*</td><td align="left">N (%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Curved</td><td align="left">93 (68.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Linear</td><td align="left">60 (44.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Endocavitary</td><td align="left">47 (34.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Multi-use probe</td><td align="left">33 (24.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Phased array</td><td align="left">11 (8.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Other (e.g., volumetric, unknown)</td><td align="left">7 (5.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Storage of ultrasound images (<italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;163)</td><td align="left">N (%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Yes</td><td align="left">73 (44.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">No</td><td align="left">70 (42.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Not applicable</td><td align="left">20 (12.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Storage location (<italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;72)*</td><td align="left">N (%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Personal devices, including computers, tablets, phones, and/or external hard drives</td><td align="left">32 (44.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Picture archiving and communication systems (PACS)</td><td align="left">29 (40.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Electronic health record (EHR) systems</td><td align="left">16 (22.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Hard copy</td><td align="left">4 (5.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Ultrasound machine</td><td align="left">4 (5.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Cloud storage</td><td align="left">2 (2.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Other (e.g., unspecified)</td><td align="left">1 (1.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Policies/guidelines for obstetric ultrasound use (<italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;163)</td><td align="left">N (%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Yes</td><td align="left">85 (52.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">No</td><td align="left">54 (33.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Do not know</td><td align="left">24 (14.7)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>N&#x02009;=&#x02009;number of respondents who answered the question</p><p>*Total percentage for individual question may be over 100% due to &#x0201c;Check all that apply&#x0201d; option for that question on the survey</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par17">Of the 72% who received OBUS education and/or training, 56% reported also training others; 28% of respondents reported receiving no OBUS education and/or training (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). Upon asking respondents to rate their OBUS expertise, 60% considered themselves very or somewhat experienced, 20% reported being inexperienced or somewhat inexperienced, and 20% reported no experience. When asked about frequency of OBUS use, 58% reported daily use, 15% weekly, 6% monthly or every few months, and 16% rarely or never. Regarding confidence in their ability to use OBUS in clinical care, 77% felt somewhat confident, confident, or very confident in their ability to use OBUS.</p><p id="Par18">Regarding what they used OBUS for in their clinical setting, when presented with 23 options (including the ability to add other ones), the most commonly selected included assessment of gestational age (92%), fetal viability (92%), fetal presentation (92%), multiple gestation (86%), amniotic fluid volume (84%), ectopic pregnancy (81%), placenta previa or other placental anomaly (79%), and molar pregnancy (76%) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">S2</xref>). When asked to identify only the five highest-priority OBUS uses in their settings, the most commonly chosen were gestational age (79%), fetal viability (69%), ectopic pregnancy (50%), and fetal presentation (50%) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">S2</xref>).</p><p id="Par19">
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Obstetric ultrasound uses and priorities.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_87284_Fig2_HTML" id="d33e854"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par20">Considering OBUS use by respondent&#x02019;s highest education/training, over 90% of physicians and ultrasound technicians used OBUS to assess gestational age, fetal viability, ectopic pregnancy, fetal presentation, amniotic fluid volume, and placental previa or other placental anomaly (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Additionally, maternal-fetal medicine (MFM) specialists and ultrasound technicians utilized OBUS more frequently to assess fetal anomalies and growth restriction (Supplementary Figure <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). MFM specialists (77%) used OBUS for procedures more than general obstetricians (52%), other physicians (36%), and nurses and midwives (13%). Although nurses and midwives made up the largest education/training group of respondents in our survey, compared with physicians, a substantially lower percentage of nurses and midwives utilized OBUS for all use cases except for termination of pregnancy.</p><p id="Par21">
<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Obstetric ultrasound uses by respondent education/training.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Obstetric ultrasound uses*</th><th align="left">Physician, Maternal-fetal medicine specialist (<italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;13)</th><th align="left">Physician, obstetrician (<italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;46)</th><th align="left">Physician, Other (<italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;14)</th><th align="left">Nurse or Midwife (<italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;77)</th><th align="left">Ultrasound/ radiology technician (<italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;11)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Amniotic fluid volume</td><td align="left">13 (100.0)</td><td char="." align="char">44 (95.7)</td><td align="left">13 (92.9)</td><td align="left">56 (72.7)</td><td align="left">11 (100.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Ectopic pregnancy</td><td align="left">12 (92.3)</td><td char="." align="char">44 (95.7)</td><td align="left">13 (92.9)</td><td align="left">50 (64.9)</td><td align="left">11 (100.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Fetal anomalies</td><td align="left">13 (100.0)</td><td char="." align="char">35 (76.1)</td><td align="left">8 (57.1)</td><td align="left">37 (48.1)</td><td align="left">11 (100.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Fetal growth restriction</td><td align="left">13 (100.0)</td><td char="." align="char">36 (78.3)</td><td align="left">9 (64.3)</td><td align="left">39 (50.6)</td><td align="left">11 (100.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Fetal presentation</td><td align="left">13 (100.0)</td><td char="." align="char">43 (93.5)</td><td align="left">14 (100.0)</td><td align="left">66 (85.7)</td><td align="left">11 (100.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Fetal viability</td><td align="left">13 (100.0)</td><td char="." align="char">45 (97.8)</td><td align="left">13 (92.9)</td><td align="left">65 (84.4)</td><td align="left">11 (100.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Gestational age</td><td align="left">13 (100.0)</td><td char="." align="char">43 (93.5)</td><td align="left">14 (100.0)</td><td align="left">66 (85.7)</td><td align="left">11 (100.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Macrosomia</td><td align="left">13 (100.0)</td><td char="." align="char">38 (82.6)</td><td align="left">9 (64.3)</td><td align="left">31 (40.3)</td><td align="left">8 (72.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Molar pregnancy</td><td align="left">11 (84.6)</td><td char="." align="char">40 (87.0)</td><td align="left">12 (85.7)</td><td align="left">52 (67.5)</td><td align="left">10 (90.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Multiple gestation</td><td align="left">13 (100.0)</td><td char="." align="char">44 (95.7)</td><td align="left">12 (85.7)</td><td align="left">59 (76.6)</td><td align="left">11 (100.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Nuchal translucency or thickening</td><td align="left">11 (84.6)</td><td char="." align="char">25 (54.3)</td><td align="left">5 (35.7)</td><td align="left">15 (19.5)</td><td align="left">7 (63.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Pelvic or uterine mass</td><td align="left">10 (76.9)</td><td char="." align="char">39 (84.8)</td><td align="left">11 (78.6)</td><td align="left">30 (39.0)</td><td align="left">11 (100.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Pelvic pain</td><td align="left">11 (84.6)</td><td char="." align="char">36 (78.3)</td><td align="left">7 (50.0)</td><td align="left">22 (28.6)</td><td align="left">11 (100.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Placenta previa or other placental anomaly</td><td align="left">13 (100.0)</td><td char="." align="char">44 (95.7)</td><td align="left">13 (92.9)</td><td align="left">48 (62.3)</td><td align="left">10 (90.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Placental abruption</td><td align="left">9 (69.2)</td><td char="." align="char">36 (78.3)</td><td align="left">8 (57.1)</td><td align="left">39 (50.6)</td><td align="left">9 (81.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Post-term pregnancy</td><td align="left">11 (84.6)</td><td char="." align="char">38 (82.6)</td><td align="left">11 (78.6)</td><td align="left">37 (48.1)</td><td align="left">11 (100.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Premature rupture of membranes or preterm labor</td><td align="left">11 (84.6)</td><td char="." align="char">38 (82.6)</td><td align="left">6 (42.9)</td><td align="left">26 (33.8)</td><td align="left">9 (81.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Procedures: adjunct to amniocentesis, cervical cerclage placement, external cephalic version,or other procedure</td><td align="left">10 (76.9)</td><td char="." align="char">24 (52.2)</td><td align="left">5 (35.7)</td><td align="left">10 (13.0)</td><td align="left">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Retained placenta</td><td align="left">10 (76.9)</td><td char="." align="char">37 (80.4)</td><td align="left">8 (57.1)</td><td align="left">32 (41.6)</td><td align="left">10 (90.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Sex determination</td><td align="left">11 (84.6)</td><td char="." align="char">33 (71.7)</td><td align="left">11 (78.6)</td><td align="left">35 (45.5)</td><td align="left">10 (90.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Termination of pregnancy</td><td align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char">1 (2.2)</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">2 (2.6)</td><td align="left">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Umbilical blood flow</td><td align="left">11 (84.6)</td><td char="." align="char">30 (65.2)</td><td align="left">9 (64.3)</td><td align="left">16 (20.8)</td><td align="left">5 (45.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Vaginal bleeding</td><td align="left">12 (92.3)</td><td char="." align="char">41 (89.1)</td><td align="left">12 (85.7)</td><td align="left">37 (48.1)</td><td align="left">11 (100.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Other (fertility assessment)</td><td align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char">1 (2.2)</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>N&#x02009;=&#x02009;number of respondents who answered the question within each education/training group</p><p>*An additional 9 respondents (not included) completed this question and reported obstetric ultrasound was &#x0201c;Not applicable&#x0201d;</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par24">Upon considering highest-priority OBUS uses by respondent&#x02019;s highest education/training, assessment of gestational age was the only use chosen by a majority (&#x0003e;&#x02009;50%) of respondents across all education/training groups (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). In addition to assessment of gestational age, MFM specialists also identified assessment of multiple gestation (69%), fetal anomalies (62%), ectopic pregnancy (54%), and fetal growth restriction (54%) as the highest OBUS priorities whereas general obstetricians also identified assessment of fetal viability (67%) and ectopic pregnancy (54%), other physicians also chose assessment of fetal viability (69%), and vaginal bleeding (54%), and nurses and midwives also selected assessment of fetal viability (72%), fetal presentation (65%), and multiple gestation (56%) as the highest OBUS priorities (Supplementary Figure <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">S2</xref>). Both the most common and the highest-priority OBUS uses were similar when comparing the respondents from Africa vs. Asia vs. Other (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">S3</xref>).</p><p id="Par25">
<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Obstetric ultrasound use priorities by respondent education/training.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Highest priority obstetric ultrasound uses</th><th align="left">Physician, Maternal-Fetal Medicine Specialist (<italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;13)</th><th align="left">Physician, Obstetrician (<italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;43)</th><th align="left">Physician, Other (<italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;13)</th><th align="left">Nurse or Midwife (<italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;75)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Amniotic fluid volume</td><td align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char">11 (25.6)</td><td align="left">4 (30.8)</td><td align="left">26 (34.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Ectopic pregnancy</td><td align="left">7 (53.8)</td><td char="." align="char">23 (53.5)</td><td align="left">4 (30.8)</td><td align="left">37 (49.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Fetal anomalies</td><td align="left">8 (61.5)</td><td char="." align="char">11 (25.6)</td><td align="left">1 (7.7)</td><td align="left">7 (9.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Fetal growth restriction</td><td align="left">7 (53.8)</td><td char="." align="char">13 (30.2)</td><td align="left">2 (15.4)</td><td align="left">2 (2.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Fetal presentation</td><td align="left">3 (23.1)</td><td char="." align="char">12 (27.9)</td><td align="left">6 (46.2)</td><td align="left">49 (65.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Fetal viability</td><td align="left">5 (38.5)</td><td char="." align="char">29 (67.4)</td><td align="left">9 (69.2)</td><td align="left">54 (72.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Gestational age</td><td align="left">8 (61.5)</td><td char="." align="char">31 (72.1)</td><td align="left">12 (92.3)</td><td align="left">61 (81.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Macrosomia</td><td align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char">2 (4.7)</td><td align="left">2 (15.4)</td><td align="left">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Molar pregnancy</td><td align="left">2 (15.4)</td><td char="." align="char">3 (7.0)</td><td align="left">3 (23.1)</td><td align="left">8 (10.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Multiple gestation</td><td align="left">9 (69.2)</td><td char="." align="char">12 (27.9)</td><td align="left">3 (23.1)</td><td align="left">42 (56.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Nuchal translucency or thickening</td><td align="left">4 (30.8)</td><td char="." align="char">4 (9.3)</td><td align="left">1 (7.7)</td><td align="left">3 (4.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Pelvic or uterine mass</td><td align="left">1 (7.7)</td><td char="." align="char">13 (30.2)</td><td align="left">1 (7.7)</td><td align="left">6 (8.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Pelvic pain</td><td align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char">1 (2.3)</td><td align="left">1 (7.7)</td><td align="left">1 (1.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Placenta previa or other placental anomaly</td><td align="left">4 (30.8)</td><td char="." align="char">15 (34.9)</td><td align="left">1 (7.7)</td><td align="left">22 (29.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Placental abruption</td><td align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char">2 (4.7)</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">11 (14.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Post-term pregnancy</td><td align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char">2 (4.7)</td><td align="left">3 (23.1)</td><td align="left">4 (5.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Premature rupture of membranes or preterm labor</td><td align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char">2 (4.7)</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">6 (8.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Procedures: adjunct to amniocentesis, cervical cerclage placement, external cephalic version, or other procedure</td><td align="left">4 (30.8)</td><td char="." align="char">2 (4.7)</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">2 (2.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Retained placenta</td><td align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char">1 (2.3)</td><td align="left">1 (7.7)</td><td align="left">3 (4.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Sex determination</td><td align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char">2 (4.7)</td><td align="left">2 (15.4)</td><td align="left">6 (8.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Umbilical blood flow</td><td align="left">1 (7.7)</td><td char="." align="char">7 (16.3)</td><td align="left">1 (7.7)</td><td align="left">2 (2.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Vaginal bleeding</td><td align="left">2 (15.4)</td><td char="." align="char">10 (23.3)</td><td align="left">7 (53.8)</td><td align="left">13 (17.3)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>N&#x02009;=&#x02009;number of respondents who answered the question within each education/training group</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par27">The majority of respondents noted that access to ultrasound was very important (80%) or important (4%), with the remainder (16%) believing access was very unimportant (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>). Among respondents, the great majority either strongly agreed or agreed that OBUS improves quality of care (98%) and patient outcomes (97%). When asked about the potential usefulness of AI-assisted OBUS in the care of pregnant patients, 53% believed it would be always or frequently useful, 38% sometimes useful, and 9% infrequently or never useful. When queried about any fears or reservations associated with using AI-assisted OBUS in a clinical setting, two-thirds said they had none. Of those expressing fears or reservations, healthcare providers not understanding the technology (71%), misdiagnosis (62%), cost (59%), patients not understanding the technology (47%), malpractice (43%), and misuse (43%) were the most common.</p><p id="Par28">
<table-wrap id="Tab5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Perceptions of obstetric ultrasound use and artificial intelligence assistance.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td align="left">Ultrasound access importance (<italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;160)</td><td align="left"><italic>N</italic> (%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Very important</td><td align="left">128 (80.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Important</td><td align="left">6 (3.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Neither important nor unimportant</td><td align="left">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Unimportant</td><td align="left">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Very unimportant</td><td align="left">26 (16.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Obstetric ultrasound improves quality of care (<italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;160)</td><td align="left">N (%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Strongly agree</td><td align="left">140 (87.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Agree</td><td align="left">16 (10.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Neither agree nor disagree</td><td align="left">1 (0.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Disagree</td><td align="left">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Strongly disagree</td><td align="left">3 (1.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Obstetric ultrasound improves patient outcomes (<italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;158)</td><td align="left">N (%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Strongly agree</td><td align="left">125 (79.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Agree</td><td align="left">28 (17.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Neither agree nor disagree</td><td align="left">2 (1.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Disagree</td><td align="left">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Strongly disagree</td><td align="left">3 (1.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Artificial intelligence (AI)-assisted obstetric ultrasound potential usefulness (<italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;156)</td><td align="left">N (%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Always</td><td align="left">43 (27.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Frequently</td><td align="left">40 (25.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Sometimes</td><td align="left">59 (37.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Infrequently</td><td align="left">4 (2.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Never</td><td align="left">10 (6.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Fears or reservations associated with AI-assisted obstetric ultrasound (<italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;154)</td><td align="left">N (%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">No</td><td align="left">101 (65.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Yes</td><td align="left">53 (34.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Fears or reservations elaborated (<italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;53)*</td><td align="left">N (%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Healthcare providers not understanding the technology</td><td align="left">38 (71.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Misdiagnosis</td><td align="left">33 (62.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Cost</td><td align="left">31 (58.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Patients not understanding the technology</td><td align="left">25 (47.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Malpractice</td><td align="left">23 (43.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Misuse</td><td align="left">23 (43.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Leadership/administration not supporting use</td><td align="left">11 (20.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Confusion about relationship between AI and obstetric ultrasound</td><td align="left">2 (3.8)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>N&#x02009;=&#x02009;number of respondents who answered the question</p><p>*Total percentage for individual question may be over 100% due to &#x0201c;Check all that apply&#x0201d; option for that question on the survey</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par31">Informed by 176 respondents from 34 countries and including MFM specialists, general obstetricians, other physicians, nurses, midwives and ultrasound technicians, our global online survey showed that OBUS is used in LMIC for many reasons in the care of pregnant individuals. Most survey respondents reported access within their healthcare settings (85%), and that they had received OBUS education and/or training (72%); although only 52% reported their place of work had policies and/or guidelines for OBUS use. Notably, while almost all respondents believed that OBUS is important for patient care, agreeing or strongly agreeing that OBUS improves both quality of care and patient outcomes, and the majority felt that access to ultrasound is important, 16% asserted access was very unimportant. While surprising, this could potentially indicate that these respondents felt they could still do their jobs without the use of OBUS.</p><p id="Par32">Overall, the most common uses of OBUS in LMIC were for assessment of gestational age (92%), fetal viability (92%), fetal presentation (92%), multiple gestation (86%), amniotic fluid volume (84%) and ectopic pregnancy (81%). Our survey found that OBUS use cases varied by respondent education/training level, although not greatly by region (Africa vs. Asia vs. Other). Perhaps due to less access, different training, and/or their job responsibilities, a substantially lower percentage of nurses and midwives than physicians utilized OBUS for most use cases. Despite OBUS being widely viewed as a critical part of antenatal care, ultrasound and/or healthcare providers trained in OBUS use are not always available or accessible in LMIC settings, and there are many pregnant individuals across LMIC who do not receive an OBUS<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. Access inequity has emerged as a major obstacle to receiving the WHO-recommended OBUS<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par33">To help address these constraints and enable lesser-trained healthcare providers to use OBUS, AI-assisted OBUS products are currently being developed, with the goal of increasing equity and ensuring all pregnant individuals have access to OBUS<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. AI-assisted OBUS has the potential to improve the accessibility, accuracy, reliability, generalizability, quality, effectiveness, speed, and delivery of antenatal healthcare services and health outcomes. As well as expanding access to services in resource-constrained, rural, or remote LMIC settings without highly trained healthcare providers with specialized imaging expertise, AI-assisted OBUS could have important cost savings and improve equity of care<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par34">When asked to select which AI-assisted OBUS use cases, considering burden and severity, were highest priority for development in LMIC, no single OBUS use case was prioritized by all respondents. Yet, there was some consensus, and the most commonly prioritized were assessment of gestational age (79%), fetal viability (69%), ectopic pregnancy (50%), fetal presentation (50%), and multiple gestation (44%), generally similar to what was reported as the most common uses. Although potential use of AI-assisted OBUS in patient care was viewed favorably by the majority of respondents, 34% of respondents did note some fears or reservations, specifically around not understanding the technology, misdiagnosis, and cost. While exciting and promising innovations such as less expensive, handheld and AI-assisted OBUS technologies are in development, these concerns need to be anticipated and addressed.</p><p id="Par35">Several limitations and challenges need to be overcome for AI-assisted OBUS to become an effective and useful tool in the care of pregnant individuals. In addition to technology challenges, there are existing or emerging risks such as AI system errors, biases, and data privacy and security breaches that could cause patient harm or propagate health inequities<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>. Issues such as healthcare personnel capacity, maintenance, overuse and misuse of OBUS, miscommunication between healthcare providers and patients, patient diagnosis and care management, among others, require thoughtful consideration<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. Although LMIC have the potential to benefit most from AI, they also are the most vulnerable to potential harm. AI-assisted OBUS is a tool and does not substitute for the strengthening of health systems.</p><p id="Par36">Despite attempting to distribute our survey widely, there were subgroups (e.g., ultrasound technicians, clinicians in training) we were not able to optimally reach and may not be adequately represented; the small number of respondents completing the survey was a limitation and may be subject to sampling bias. Furthermore, not all respondents completed answers to all survey questions, and some questions had smaller numbers of responses, further limiting generalizability. The survey also was only available online and in English, and so likely did not include respondents who did not have easy access or did not understand English. The survey did not define nor provide information about AI-assisted OBUS and so this may have been a gap in the survey language. Given the survey format and length, we were not able to delve deeper into certain responses for better understanding. Discussion through interviews and focus group discussions with a broad range of relevant stakeholders would be beneficial to capture more comprehensive and in-depth insights regarding OBUS use, priorities, and perspectives and understanding of AI-assisted OBUS.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par37">Recommended as part of routine antenatal care for pregnant individuals, OBUS use is increasing in LMIC; however, many still remain without access. The most common use cases &#x02013; assessment of gestational age, fetal viability, fetal presentation &#x02013; are also the ones most highly prioritized by these respondents for potential AI-assisted OBUS development. Better understanding the OBUS user, the pregnant individual, and the context, and taking care to ensure responsible, sustainable, and inclusive development and use of AI-assisted OBUS will be critical to successful integration and implementation of this potentially transformational tool and to increasing access to OBUS.</p><p id="Par38">.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.</p><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41598_2025_87284_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><caption><p>Supplementary Material 1</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="41598_2025_87284_MOESM2_ESM.docx"><caption><p>Supplementary Material 2</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3"><media xlink:href="41598_2025_87284_MOESM3_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Supplementary Material 3</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>ASG conceived, developed, designed, administered, and implemented the survey. EA provided input to survey design and KM helped with identification of potential respondents. ASG, ZL, and SM analyzed and interpreted the data. ASG and ZL wrote the draft of the manuscript with critical input from the co-authors. All authors edited and reviewed the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>Caption Health/GE HealthCare through a grant provided by the Bill &#x00026; Melinda Gates Foundation (INV-059090).</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>Access to data will be provided to researchers subject to submission of a research proposal and signing a Data Use Agreement. Interested researchers can request access to the data by contacting the corresponding author.</p></notes><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par41">ASG receives funding from Caption Health/GE HealthCare. EA was an employee and KM is an employee of Caption Health/GE HealthCare. ZL and SM declare no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">World Health Organization (WHO). USAID, Maternal and Child Survival Program. WHO recommendations on antenatal care for a positive pregnancy experience: ultrasound examination highlights and key messages from the world health organization&#x02019;s 2016 Global Recommendations. (2018).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">WHO antenatal care recommendations for a positive pregnancy experience. <italic>Maternal and Fetal Assessment Update: Imaging Ultrasound before 24 Weeks of Pregnancy</italic> (World Health Organization, 2022).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Noguchi, L., Bucagu, M. &#x00026; Tun&#x000e7;alp, &#x000d6;. Strengthening antenatal care services for all: Implementing imaging ultrasound before 24 weeks of pregnancy. <italic>BMJ Glob Health</italic> ; <bold>8</bold>(5). (2023).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Moran</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Armbruster</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kozuki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Obstetric ultrasound use in low and middle income countries: a narrative review</article-title><source>Reprod. Health</source><year>2018</year><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>129</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12978-018-0571-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30029609</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Kim, E. T., Singh, K., Moran, A., Armbruster, D. &#x00026; Kozuki, N. Obstetric ultrasound use in low and middle income countries: A narrative review. <italic>Reprod. Health</italic>. <bold>15</bold> (1), 129 (2018).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30029609</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yadav</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sayed</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Horton</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Schroeder</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Availability of essential diagnostics in ten low-income and middle-income countries: results from national health facility surveys</article-title><source>Lancet Glob Health</source><year>2021</year><volume>9</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>e1553</fpage><lpage>e60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2214-109X(21)00442-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34626546</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Yadav, H., Shah, D., Sayed, S., Horton, S. &#x00026; Schroeder, L. F. Availability of essential diagnostics in ten low-income and middle-income countries: Results from national health facility surveys. <italic>Lancet Glob Health</italic>. <bold>9</bold> (11), e1553&#x02013;e60 (2021).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34626546</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Groen</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Leow</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sadasivam</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Kushner</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Review: indications for ultrasound use in low- and middle-income countries</article-title><source>Trop. Med. Int. Health</source><year>2011</year><volume>16</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1525</fpage><lpage>1535</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-3156.2011.02868.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21883723</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Groen, R. S., Leow, J. J., Sadasivam, V. &#x00026; Kushner, A. L. Review: Indications for ultrasound use in low- and middle-income countries. <italic>Trop. Med. Int. Health</italic>. <bold>16</bold> (12), 1525&#x02013;1535 (2011).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21883723</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Perceived barriers in the use of ultrasound in developing countries</article-title><source>Crit. Ultrasound J.</source><year>2015</year><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>28</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13089-015-0028-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26123609</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Shah, S. et al. Perceived barriers in the use of ultrasound in developing countries. <italic>Crit. Ultrasound J.</italic><bold>7</bold> (1), 28 (2015).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26123609</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The use of portable ultrasound devices in low- and middle-income countries: a systematic review of the literature</article-title><source>Trop. Med. Int. Health</source><year>2016</year><volume>21</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>294</fpage><lpage>311</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tmi.12657</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26683523</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Becker, D. M. et al. The use of portable ultrasound devices in low- and middle-income countries: A systematic review of the literature. <italic>Trop. Med. Int. Health</italic>. <bold>21</bold> (3), 294&#x02013;311 (2016).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26683523</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Impact of point-of-care ultrasound on clinical decision-making at an urban emergency department in Tanzania</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2018</year><volume>13</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>e0194774</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0194774</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29694406</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Reynolds, T. A. et al. Impact of point-of-care ultrasound on clinical decision-making at an urban emergency department in Tanzania. <italic>PLoS One</italic>. <bold>13</bold> (4), e0194774 (2018).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29694406</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Holden</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Vela</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rathleff</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Point-of-care Ultrasound in General Practice: a systematic review</article-title><source>Ann. Fam Med.</source><year>2019</year><volume>17</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>61</fpage><lpage>69</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1370/afm.2330</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30670398</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Andersen, C. A., Holden, S., Vela, J., Rathleff, M. S. &#x00026; Jensen, M. B. Point-of-care Ultrasound in General Practice: A systematic review. <italic>Ann. Fam Med.</italic><bold>17</bold> (1), 61&#x02013;69 (2019).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30670398</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shokoohi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Assessment of Point-of-care Ultrasound Training for clinical educators in Malawi, Tanzania and Uganda</article-title><source>Ultrasound Med. Biol.</source><year>2019</year><volume>45</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1351</fpage><lpage>1357</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ultrasmedbio.2019.01.019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30904246</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Shokoohi, H. et al. Assessment of Point-of-care Ultrasound Training for clinical educators in Malawi, Tanzania and Uganda. <italic>Ultrasound Med. Biol.</italic><bold>45</bold> (6), 1351&#x02013;1357 (2019).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30904246</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Tran, T. T., Hlaing, M. &#x00026; Krause, M. Point-of-care Ultrasound: Applications in low- and Middle-Income Countries. <italic>Curr. Anesthesiol Rep.</italic> : 1&#x02013;7. (2021).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abrokwa</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruby</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Heuvelings</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x000e9;lard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Task shifting for point of care ultrasound in primary healthcare in low- and middle-income countries-a systematic review</article-title><source>EClinicalMedicine</source><year>2022</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>101333</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eclinm.2022.101333</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35284806</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Abrokwa, S. K., Ruby, L. C., Heuvelings, C. C. &#x00026; B&#x000e9;lard, S. Task shifting for point of care ultrasound in primary healthcare in low- and middle-income countries-a systematic review. <italic>EClinicalMedicine</italic><bold>45</bold>, 101333 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35284806</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ginsburg</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Liddy</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Khazaneh</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>May</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pervaiz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A survey of barriers and facilitators to ultrasound use in low- and middle-income countries</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2023</year><volume>13</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>3322</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-023-30454-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36849625</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Ginsburg, A. S., Liddy, Z., Khazaneh, P. T., May, S. &#x00026; Pervaiz, F. A survey of barriers and facilitators to ultrasound use in low- and middle-income countries. <italic>Sci. Rep.</italic><bold>13</bold> (1), 3322 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36849625</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ibrahimi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mumtaz</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ultrasound imaging and the culture of pregnancy management in low-and middle-income countries: a systematic review</article-title><source>Int. J. Gynaecol. Obstet.</source><year>2024</year><volume>165</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>76</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ijgo.15097</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37743802</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Ibrahimi, J. &#x00026; Mumtaz, Z. Ultrasound imaging and the culture of pregnancy management in low-and middle-income countries: A systematic review. <italic>Int. J. Gynaecol. Obstet.</italic><bold>165</bold> (1), 76&#x02013;93 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37743802</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stanton</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Mwanri</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global Maternal and Child Health outcomes: the role of Obstetric Ultrasound in Low Resource settings</article-title><source>World J. Prev. Med.</source><year>2013</year><volume>1</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>22</fpage><lpage>29</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Stanton, K. &#x00026; Mwanri, L. Global Maternal and Child Health outcomes: The role of Obstetric Ultrasound in Low Resource settings. <italic>World J. Prev. Med.</italic><bold>1</bold> (3), 22&#x02013;29 (2013).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mogren</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Maternal health care professionals&#x02019; experiences and views on the use of obstetric ultrasound in Rwanda: a cross-sectional study</article-title><source>BMC Health Serv. Res.</source><year>2021</year><volume>21</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>789</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12913-021-06758-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34376210</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Mogren, I. et al. Maternal health care professionals&#x02019; experiences and views on the use of obstetric ultrasound in Rwanda: A cross-sectional study. <italic>BMC Health Serv. Res.</italic><bold>21</bold> (1), 789 (2021).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34376210</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Horgan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Nehme</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Abuhamad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Artificial intelligence in obstetric ultrasound: a scoping review</article-title><source>Prenat Diagn.</source><year>2023</year><volume>43</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1176</fpage><lpage>1219</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pd.6411</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37503802</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Horgan, R., Nehme, L. &#x00026; Abuhamad, A. Artificial intelligence in obstetric ultrasound: A scoping review. <italic>Prenat Diagn.</italic><bold>43</bold> (9), 1176&#x02013;1219 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37503802</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gimovsky</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Eke</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Tuuli</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enhancing Obstetric Ultrasonography with Artificial Intelligence in Resource-Limited settings</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2024</year><volume>332</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>626</fpage><lpage>628</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2024.14794</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39088222</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Gimovsky, A. C., Eke, A. C. &#x00026; Tuuli, M. G. Enhancing obstetric ultrasonography with artificial intelligence in resource-limited settings. <italic>JAMA</italic><bold>332</bold> (8), 626&#x02013;628 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39088222</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">The World Bank. World Bank Country and Lending Groups. July, (2022). <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://datahelpdesk.worldbank.org/knowledgebase/articles/906519-world-bank-country-and-lending-groups">https://datahelpdesk.worldbank.org/knowledgebase/articles/906519-world-bank-country-and-lending-groups</ext-link> (accessed.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edvardsson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Physicians&#x02019; experiences and views on the role of obstetric ultrasound in rural and urban Rwanda: a qualitative study</article-title><source>Trop. Med. Int. Health</source><year>2016</year><volume>21</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>895</fpage><lpage>906</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tmi.12718</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27125579</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Edvardsson, K. et al. Physicians&#x02019; experiences and views on the role of obstetric ultrasound in rural and urban Rwanda: A qualitative study. <italic>Trop. Med. Int. Health</italic>. <bold>21</bold> (7), 895&#x02013;906 (2016).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27125579</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>&#x000c5;hman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Without ultrasound you can&#x02019;t reach the best decision&#x02019; - midwives&#x02019; experiences and views of the role of ultrasound in maternity care in Dar Es Salaam, Tanzania</article-title><source>Sex. Reprod. Healthc.</source><year>2018</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>28</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.srhc.2017.11.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29389498</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">&#x000c5;hman, A. et al. Without ultrasound you can&#x02019;t reach the best decision&#x02019; - midwives&#x02019; experiences and views of the role of ultrasound in maternity care in Dar Es Salaam, Tanzania. <italic>Sex. Reprod. Healthc.</italic><bold>15</bold>, 28&#x02013;34 (2018).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29389498</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holmlund</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Health professionals&#x02019; experiences and views on obstetric ultrasound in Rwanda: a cross-sectional study</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2018</year><volume>13</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>e0208387</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0208387</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30513102</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Holmlund, S. et al. Health professionals&#x02019; experiences and views on obstetric ultrasound in Rwanda: A cross-sectional study. <italic>PLoS One</italic>. <bold>13</bold> (12), e0208387 (2018).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30513102</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holmlund</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sub-optimal use of ultrasound examinations may result in underperformance of Vietnamese maternity care - A qualitative study of midwives&#x02019; experiences and views</article-title><source>Sex. Reprod. Healthc.</source><year>2020</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>100508</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.srhc.2020.100508</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32278314</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">Holmlund, S. et al. Sub-optimal use of ultrasound examinations may result in underperformance of Vietnamese maternity care - A qualitative study of midwives&#x02019; experiences and views. <italic>Sex. Reprod. Healthc.</italic><bold>24</bold>, 100508 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32278314</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Artificial Intelligence in Obstetric Ultrasound: an update and future applications</article-title><source>Front. Med. (Lausanne)</source><year>2021</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>733468</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmed.2021.733468</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34513890</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="journal">Chen, Z., Liu, Z., Du, M. &#x00026; Wang, Z. Artificial Intelligence in Obstetric Ultrasound: An update and future applications. <italic>Front. Med. (Lausanne)</italic>. <bold>8</bold>, 733468 (2021).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34513890</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR26" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gomes</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A mobile-optimized artificial intelligence system for gestational age and fetal malpresentation assessment</article-title><source>Commun. Med. (Lond)</source><year>2022</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>128</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s43856-022-00194-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36249461</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26" publication-type="journal">Gomes, R. G. et al. A mobile-optimized artificial intelligence system for gestational age and fetal malpresentation assessment. <italic>Commun. Med. (Lond)</italic>. <bold>2</bold>, 128 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36249461</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR27" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koech</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Acceptability and feasibility of a low-cost device for gestational Age Assessment in a low-resource setting: qualitative study</article-title><source>JMIR Hum. Factors</source><year>2022</year><volume>9</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>e34823</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/34823</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36574278</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27" publication-type="journal">Koech, A. et al. Acceptability and feasibility of a low-cost device for gestational Age Assessment in a low-resource setting: Qualitative study. <italic>JMIR Hum. Factors</italic>. <bold>9</bold> (4), e34823 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36574278</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Pokaprakarn, T. et al. AI estimation of gestational age from Blind Ultrasound sweeps in Low-Resource settings. <italic>NEJM Evid.</italic> ; <bold>1</bold>(5). (2022).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR29" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Development of a machine learning model for Sonographic Assessment of Gestational Age</article-title><source>JAMA Netw. Open.</source><year>2023</year><volume>6</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>e2248685</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.48685</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36598790</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29" publication-type="journal">Lee, C. et al. Development of a machine learning model for Sonographic Assessment of Gestational Age. <italic>JAMA Netw. Open.</italic><bold>6</bold> (1), e2248685 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36598790</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Khanna, N. N. et al. Economics of Artificial Intelligence in Healthcare: Diagnosis vs. treatment. <italic>Healthc. (Basel)</italic> ; <bold>10</bold>(12). (2022).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Price, W. N. Risks and remedies for artificial intelligence in health care. The Brookings Institution&#x02019;s Artificial Intelligence and Emerging Technology Initiative. (2019). <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.brookings.edu/articles/risks-and-remedies-for-artificial-intelligence-in-health-care/">https://www.brookings.edu/articles/risks-and-remedies-for-artificial-intelligence-in-health-care/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR32" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grandjean</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Oster</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dap</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Morel</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Hossu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Artificial intelligence and fetal ultrasound biometry: challenges and perspectives</article-title><source>Diagn. Interv Imaging</source><year>2023</year><volume>104</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>200</fpage><lpage>201</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.diii.2023.01.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36801095</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32" publication-type="journal">Grandjean, G. A., Oster, J., Dap, M., Morel, O. &#x00026; Hossu, G. Artificial intelligence and fetal ultrasound biometry: Challenges and perspectives. <italic>Diagn. Interv Imaging</italic>. <bold>104</bold> (4), 200&#x02013;201 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36801095</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Yang, Y., Zhang, H., Gichoya, J. W., Katabi, D. &#x00026; Ghassemi, M. The limits of fair medical imaging AI in real-world generalization. <italic>Nat. Med.</italic> (2024).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR34" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moncrieff</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>First and second trimester ultrasound in pregnancy: A systematic review and metasynthesis of the views and experiences of pregnant women, partners, and health workers</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2021</year><volume>16</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>e0261096</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0261096</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34905561</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR34" publication-type="journal">Moncrieff, G. et al. First and second trimester ultrasound in pregnancy: A systematic review and metasynthesis of the views and experiences of pregnant women, partners, and health workers. <italic>PLoS One</italic>. <bold>16</bold> (12), e0261096 (2021).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34905561</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article>