<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="brief-report" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Light Sci Appl</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Light Sci Appl</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Light, Science &#x00026; Applications</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2095-5545</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2047-7538</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40000616</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11862125</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1782</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41377-025-01782-5</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>News &#x00026; Views</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Next generation drug clearance insights: real-time tracking in hepatobiliary and renal systems</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hur</surname><given-names>Won</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Seong</surname><given-names>Gi Hun</given-names></name><address><email>ghseong@hanyang.ac.kr</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-7982-6483</contrib-id><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>Hak Soo</given-names></name><address><email>hchoi12@mgh.harvard.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/002pd6e78</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.32224.35</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0386 9924</institution-id><institution>Gordon Center for Medical Imaging, Department of Radiology, </institution><institution>Massachusetts General Hospital and Harvard Medical School, </institution></institution-wrap>Boston, MA 02124 USA </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/046865y68</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.49606.3d</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 1364 9317</institution-id><institution>Department of Bionano Engineering, Center for Bionano Intelligence Education and Research, </institution><institution>Hanyang University, </institution></institution-wrap>Ansan, 426-791 South Korea </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>26</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>26</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>98</elocation-id><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">The integration of spatiotemporally resolved clearance pathway tracking (SRCPT) provides a new lens for evaluating drug clearance pathways, enabling precise mapping of physiological conditions of metabolic organs, such as liver or kidney impairment.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Lasers, LEDs and light sources</kwd><kwd>Optical materials and structures</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>This research was supported by a grant of the Korea-US Collaborative Research Fund (KUCRF), funded by the Ministry of Science and ICT and the Ministry of Health &#x00026; Welfare, Republic of Korea (grant number: RS-2024-00466887).</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Changchun Institute of Optics, Fine Mechanics and Physics (CIOMP), CAS 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p id="Par2">The efficient removal of drugs from the body, primarily through the liver and kidneys, plays a pivotal role in precision medicine. Understanding how drugs are cleared from the body with real-time imaging is vital for developing effective therapies. Traditionally, radioimaging and optical imaging have been used to track drug metabolism in living organisms, but these imaging modalities pose challenges such as radiation exposure or limited depth resolution, respectively. In a recent breakthrough, Lv et al. present a novel spatiotemporally resolved clearance pathway tracking (SRCPT) method<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup> based on photoacoustic tomography (PAT)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>, offering noninvasive, real-time monitoring of drug clearance with relatively high spatial resolution. This innovation provides deeper insights into hepatobiliary vs. renal clearance pathways, which are key processes to understanding drug pharmacokinetics.</p><p id="Par3">Renal and hepatobiliary systems represent the primary routes for drug elimination, each catering to different types of compounds. Figure <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> shows representative dual-channel imaging of renal clearance and hepatobiliary clearance using 700&#x02009;nm emitting ZW700-1 and 800&#x02009;nm emitting indocyanine green (ICG), respectively<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. Renal clearance typically handles hydrophilic compounds or metabolites, eliminating them via glomerular filtration and tubular secretion<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. The physicochemical properties of drugs, including the size, charge and polarity, composition, flexibility, mass-to-charge ratio, and hydrophilicity/lipophilicity, play a dominant role in this excretion pathway<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>. Thus, drugs with higher plasma protein binding tend to favor hepatic metabolism since they are less freely filtered through the kidneys. Nevertheless, physiological factors, including urine flow and renal blood flow, along with the unbound drug fraction and metabolites, also influence this process<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. On the other hand, hepatobiliary clearance is largely responsible for metabolizing lipophilic drugs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup> or highly charged drugs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup> and excreting them into bile through liver enzymes such as cytochrome P450<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. In addition to the physicochemical properties of injected drugs, variations in liver enzyme activity, blood flow, and plasma protein binding heavily influence this pathway, especially for drugs with a high hepatic extraction ratio<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. This pathway can be affected by liver conditions such as cirrhosis or enzyme inhibition, leading to prolonged drug exposure and potential toxicity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>. The choice of clearance pathway has significant clinical implications. For example, drugs cleared predominantly through the kidneys must be dose-adjusted in patients with renal impairment, as inadequate clearance can lead to accumulation and toxicity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>Representative images of renal vs. hepatobiliary clearance pathways.</title><p>Dual-channel near-infrared (NIR) fluorescence imaging of ZW700-1 (700&#x02009;nm) and indocyanine green (ICG; 800&#x02009;nm) in the same animal. 50 nmol of each fluorophore was injected intravenously into a 250-g Sprague-Dawley rat 1&#x02009;h prior to imaging. Bl bladder, Du duodenum, In intestine, Ki kidney, Li liver, Pa pancreas, Re rectum, Sp spleen. TPSA topological polar surface area. Arrows and an arrowhead indicate ureters and bile ducts, respectively. Images were created with Biorender. In silico calculations were calculated using MarvinSketch (ChemAxon, Budapest, Hungary). Adapted from ref. <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41377_2025_1782_Fig1_HTML" id="d33e227"/></fig></p><p id="Par4">Traditional imaging modalities, such as radiolabeling and optical imaging, have complemented each other, providing comprehensive real-time data on hepatobiliary and renal clearance. Radioimaging, including PET and SPECT, provides high sensitivity and quantitative 3D imaging of drug distribution and clearance pathways<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. However, this modality requires radiotracers that may be costly and radioactive. Spatial resolution is typically limited, and repeated radioimaging leads to radiation exposure<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>.On the other hand, optical fluorescence imaging, such as near-infrared imaging (650&#x02013;1700&#x02009;nm), is non-ionizing and allows for real-time high-resolution imaging of drug clearance. However, this modality suffers from the limited penetration depth and phototoxicity risk. In addition, quantification can be less precise than radioimaging<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par5">Lv et al. in the recently published paper in <italic>Light: Science &#x00026; Applications</italic>, leverage the unique capabilities of PAT to visualize drug clearance in real-time, overcoming the limitations of existing radiolabeling techniques<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. SRCPT offers a non-ionizing alternative that penetrates deep tissues, achieving high-resolution, longitudinal monitoring of drug metabolism in organs, such as the liver and kidneys. This technique is enhanced by integrating a Monte Carlo-corrected empiric mathematical model, which addresses the challenge of laser fluence attenuation in deep tissues (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). The result is a powerful imaging tool capable of dynamically mapping drug clearance with unprecedented accuracy. SRCPT was effectively used to track the clearance of mitoxantrone, a chemotherapeutic drug, in normal and liver-injured mice. The findings revealed that in mice with liver injury, hepatic metabolism of mitoxantrone was significantly reduced, leading to prolonged drug accumulation compared to healthy controls. This represents the power of SRCPT to detect subtle physiological changes in drug clearance pathways, offering vital insights for precision medicine. In addition, SRCPT showed its capability to distinguish various levels of renal dysfunction through monitoring immunoglobulin G (IgG) clearance patterns in acute kidney injury (AKI) models, highlighting its exceptional sensitivity in detecting organ-specific pathological conditions. Furthermore, Lv et al. validated the accuracy of the SRCPT technique by comparing it with PET imaging by using a double-labeled probe [68Ga]DFO-IRDye800CW, proving a strong correlation between SRCPT and PET<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><title>Spatiotemporally resolved clearance pathway tracking (SRCPT) method.</title><p><bold>a</bold> Schematic diagram of SRCPT of probes in the major organs. SRCPT of probe perfusion in the liver (<bold>b</bold>) and kidney sections (<bold>c</bold>), respectively. Percent relative enhancement of the quantitative PA signals generated by the injected dose in the whole liver (<bold>d</bold>), abdominal aorta (AA; <bold>e</bold>), and portal vein (PV; <bold>f</bold>), respectively. Adapted from ref. <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41377_2025_1782_Fig2_HTML" id="d33e287"/></fig></p><p id="Par6">The introduction of SRCPT opens new frontiers in drug clearance studies, particularly in distinguishing between renal and hepatobiliary clearance pathways. By providing real-time, detailed insights into how drugs are processed in different organs, SRCPT enables more informed decision-making in drug development, particularly when evaluating pharmacokinetics in disease models. For instance, drugs primarily cleared through the liver may require dose adjustments in patients with hepatic impairment, while renal clearance must be carefully monitored in patients with kidney disease<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. Indeed, in AKI models, drugs accumulate in the kidneys without significant excretion, highlighting the impaired renal function.</p><p id="Par7">The work by Lv et al. introduces a game-changing method for tracking drug clearance in vivo with SRCPT, providing unparalleled insights into the dynamics of hepatobiliary and renal drug elimination. The integration of advanced imaging algorithms further enhances its resolution and accuracy, establishing SRCPT as a critical tool for drug development and disease research (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).</p><p id="Par8">While SRCPT holds immense potential, there are still challenges to address. The accuracy of the method depends heavily on knowledge of optical properties in different tissues, and variations in these parameters can affect the precision of the Monte Carlo-based light fluence corrections. Additionally, the use of exogenous optical tracers in SRCPT means that certain drugs lacking sufficient absorption properties may not be suitable for this method<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par9">Future research should focus on expanding the range of compatible imaging tracers and improving the system&#x02019;s adaptability to different drug types and physiological conditions. Despite these challenges, SRCPT represents a significant leap forward in our ability to study drug clearance and metabolism, offering new possibilities for precision medicine and personalized treatment approaches. By enabling real-time, high-resolution tracking of drug metabolism, SRCPT paves the way for more effective therapies tailored to individual patient needs, ultimately advancing the field of precision medicine.</p></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This research was supported by a grant of the Korea-US Collaborative Research Fund (KUCRF), funded by the Ministry of Science and ICT and the Ministry of Health &#x00026; Welfare, Republic of Korea (grant number: RS-2024-00466887).</p></ack><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p id="Par10">The authors declare no conflict of interest. H.S.C. reports a relationship with Nawoo Vision and Ferrex Therapeutics: Consulting, stock, and royalty.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dynamic synthetic-scanning photoacoustic tracking monitors hepatic and renal clearance pathway of exogeneous probes in vivo</article-title><source>Light Sci. Appl.</source><year>2024</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>304</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41377-024-01644-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39482292</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Lv, J. et al. Dynamic synthetic-scanning photoacoustic tracking monitors hepatic and renal clearance pathway of exogeneous probes in vivo. <italic>Light Sci. Appl.</italic><bold>13</bold>, 304 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39482292</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Photoacoustic molecular imaging-escorted adipose photodynamic-browning synergy for fighting obesity with virus-like complexes</article-title><source>Nat. Nanotechnol.</source><year>2021</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>455</fpage><lpage>465</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41565-020-00844-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33526836</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Chen, R. H. et al. Photoacoustic molecular imaging-escorted adipose photodynamic-browning synergy for fighting obesity with virus-like complexes. <italic>Nat. Nanotechnol.</italic><bold>16</bold>, 455&#x02013;465 (2021).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33526836</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hyun</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>700-nm Zwitterionic near-infrared fluorophores for dual-channel image-guided surgery</article-title><source>Mol. Imaging Biol.</source><year>2016</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>52</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11307-015-0870-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26084246</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Hyun, H. et al. 700-nm Zwitterionic near-infrared fluorophores for dual-channel image-guided surgery. <italic>Mol. Imaging Biol.</italic><bold>18</bold>, 52&#x02013;61 (2016).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26084246</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Renal clearance of quantum dots</article-title><source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source><year>2007</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>1165</fpage><lpage>1170</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt1340</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17891134</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Choi, H. S. et al. Renal clearance of quantum dots. <italic>Nat. Biotechnol.</italic><bold>25</bold>, 1165&#x02013;1170 (2007).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17891134</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>ZW800&#x02010;PEG: a renal clearable Zwitterionic near&#x02010;infrared fluorophore for potential clinical translation</article-title><source>Angew. Chem.</source><year>2021</year><volume>133</volume><fpage>13966</fpage><lpage>13971</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ange.202102640</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Yang, C. G. et al. ZW800&#x02010;PEG: a renal clearable Zwitterionic near&#x02010;infrared fluorophore for potential clinical translation. <italic>Angew. Chem.</italic><bold>133</bold>, 13966&#x02013;13971 (2021).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ikeda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Determination of renal function and injury using near-infrared fluorimetry in experimental cardiorenal syndrome</article-title><source>Am. J. Physiol.-Ren. Physiol.</source><year>2017</year><volume>312</volume><fpage>F629</fpage><lpage>F639</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajprenal.00573.2016</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Ikeda, M. et al. Determination of renal function and injury using near-infrared fluorimetry in experimental cardiorenal syndrome. <italic>Am. J. Physiol.-Ren. Physiol.</italic><bold>312</bold>, F629&#x02013;F639 (2017).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Renal clearable nanochelators for iron overload therapy</article-title><source>Nat. Commun.</source><year>2019</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>5134</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-019-13143-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31723130</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Kang, H. et al. Renal clearable nanochelators for iron overload therapy. <italic>Nat. Commun.</italic><bold>10</bold>, 5134 (2019).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31723130</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Physiological principles underlying the kidney targeting of renal nanomedicines</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Nephrol.</source><year>2024</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>354</fpage><lpage>370</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41581-024-00819-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38409369</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Huang, Y. Y. et al. Physiological principles underlying the kidney targeting of renal nanomedicines. <italic>Nat. Rev. Nephrol.</italic><bold>20</bold>, 354&#x02013;370 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38409369</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Physicochemical descriptors in biodistribution and clearance of contrast agents</article-title><source>Adv. Photon. Res.</source><year>2023</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>2300036</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/adpr.202300036</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Ahn, S. et al. Physicochemical descriptors in biodistribution and clearance of contrast agents. <italic>Adv. Photon. Res.</italic><bold>4</bold>, 2300036 (2023).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>MX</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transport and interactions of nanoparticles in the kidneys</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Mater.</source><year>2018</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>358</fpage><lpage>374</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41578-018-0038-3</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Du, B. J., Yu, M. X. &#x00026; Zheng, J. Transport and interactions of nanoparticles in the kidneys. <italic>Nat. Rev. Mater.</italic><bold>3</bold>, 358&#x02013;374 (2018).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wasan</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Impact of lipoproteins on the biological activity and disposition of hydrophobic drugs: implications for drug discovery</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Drug Discov.</source><year>2008</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>84</fpage><lpage>99</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrd2353</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18079757</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Wasan, K. M. et al. Impact of lipoproteins on the biological activity and disposition of hydrophobic drugs: implications for drug discovery. <italic>Nat. Rev. Drug Discov.</italic><bold>7</bold>, 84&#x02013;99 (2008).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18079757</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Owens</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Highly charged cyanine fluorophores for trafficking scaffold degradation</article-title><source>Biomed. Mater.</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>014109</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/1748-6041/8/1/014109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23353870</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Owens, E. A. et al. Highly charged cyanine fluorophores for trafficking scaffold degradation. <italic>Biomed. Mater.</italic><bold>8</bold>, 014109 (2013).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23353870</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ciut&#x00103;</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Structure of human drug transporters OATP1B1 and OATP1B3</article-title><source>Nat. Commun.</source><year>2023</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>5774</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-023-41552-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37723174</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Ciut&#x00103;, A. D. et al. Structure of human drug transporters OATP1B1 and OATP1B3. <italic>Nat. Commun.</italic><bold>14</bold>, 5774 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37723174</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arrese</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ananthananarayanan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Suchy</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hepatobiliary transport: molecular mechanisms of development and cholestasis</article-title><source>Pediatr. Res.</source><year>1998</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>147</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1203/00006450-199808000-00001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9702905</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Arrese, M., Ananthananarayanan, M. &#x00026; Suchy, F. J. Hepatobiliary transport: molecular mechanisms of development and cholestasis. <italic>Pediatr. Res.</italic><bold>44</bold>, 141&#x02013;147 (1998).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9702905</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kellum</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Acute kidney injury</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Dis. Prim.</source><year>2021</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>52</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41572-021-00284-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34267223</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Kellum, J. A. et al. Acute kidney injury. <italic>Nat. Rev. Dis. Prim.</italic><bold>7</bold>, 52 (2021).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34267223</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A rationally designed nuclei-targeting FAPI 04-based molecular probe with enhanced tumor uptake for PET/CT and fluorescence imaging</article-title><source>Eur. J. Nucl. Med. Mol. Imaging</source><year>2024</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>1593</fpage><lpage>1604</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00259-024-06691-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38512485</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Zhao, X. Y. et al. A rationally designed nuclei-targeting FAPI 04-based molecular probe with enhanced tumor uptake for PET/CT and fluorescence imaging. <italic>Eur. J. Nucl. Med. Mol. Imaging</italic><bold>51</bold>, 1593&#x02013;1604 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38512485</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sajedi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sabet</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intraoperative biophotonic imaging systems for image-guided interventions</article-title><source>Nanophotonics</source><year>2019</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>116</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1515/nanoph-2018-0134</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31187017</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Sajedi, S., Sabet, H. &#x00026; Choi, H. S. Intraoperative biophotonic imaging systems for image-guided interventions. <italic>Nanophotonics</italic><bold>8</bold>, 99&#x02013;116 (2019).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31187017</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multispectral image-guided surgery in patients</article-title><source>Nat. Biomed. Eng.</source><year>2020</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>245</fpage><lpage>246</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41551-020-0536-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32165731</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Choi, H. S. &#x00026; Kim, H. K. Multispectral image-guided surgery in patients. <italic>Nat. Biomed. Eng.</italic><bold>4</bold>, 245&#x02013;246 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32165731</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Hakimian</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pharmacokinetic of antiepileptic drugs in patients with hepatic or renal impairment</article-title><source>Clin. Pharmacokinetics</source><year>2014</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>49</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40262-013-0107-0</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Anderson, G. D. &#x00026; Hakimian, S. Pharmacokinetic of antiepileptic drugs in patients with hepatic or renal impairment. <italic>Clin. Pharmacokinetics</italic><bold>53</bold>, 29&#x02013;49 (2014).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article>