<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" id="tct70051" xml:lang="en" article-type="other"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Clin Teach</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Clin Teach</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.1111/(ISSN)1743-498X</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">TCT</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Clinical Teacher</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1743-4971</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1743-498X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>John Wiley and Sons Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Hoboken</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40008477</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11863177</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tct.70051</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">TCT70051</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="other">TCT-2024-0616.R1</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Clinical Teacher's Toolbox</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Clinical Teacher's Toolbox</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A Guide to Peer Coaching for Health Professions Educators</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="tct70051-cr-0001" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>James</given-names></name><xref rid="tct70051-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><address><email>james.fisher@ncl.ac.uk</email></address></contrib><contrib id="tct70051-cr-0002" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ainsworth</surname><given-names>Anna</given-names></name><xref rid="tct70051-aff-0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="tct70051-cr-0003" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>Richard</given-names></name><xref rid="tct70051-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="tct70051-cr-0004" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Matthan</surname><given-names>Joanna</given-names></name><xref rid="tct70051-aff-0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="tct70051-cr-0005" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nadarajah</surname><given-names>Vishna&#x000a0;Devi&#x000a0;V.</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7126-7189</contrib-id><xref rid="tct70051-aff-0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="tct70051-cr-0006" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Steinert</surname><given-names>Yvonne</given-names></name><xref rid="tct70051-aff-0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="tct70051-aff-0001">
<label>
<sup>1</sup>
</label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">School of Medicine</named-content>
<institution>Newcastle University</institution>
<city>Newcastle upon Tyne</city>
<country country="GB">UK</country>
</aff><aff content-type="private-address" id="tct70051-aff-0002">
<label>
<sup>2</sup>
</label>
<institution>Newcastle University Medicine Malaysia</institution>
<city>Iskander Puteri</city>
<named-content content-type="country-part">Johor</named-content>
<country country="MY">Malaysia</country>
</aff><aff id="tct70051-aff-0003">
<label>
<sup>3</sup>
</label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Department of Family Medicine and Institute of Health Sciences Education, Faculty of Medicine and Health Sciences</named-content>
<institution>McGill University</institution>
<city>Montreal</city>
<country country="CA">Canada</country>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="correspondenceTo">
<label>*</label>
<bold>Correspondence:</bold>
<break/>
James Fisher (<email>james.fisher@ncl.ac.uk</email>)<break/>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>26</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>4</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>22</volume><issue seq="127">2</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tct.v22.2</issue-id><elocation-id>e70051</elocation-id><history>
<date date-type="rev-recd"><day>14</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></date>
<date date-type="received"><day>13</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></date>
</history><permissions><!--&#x000a9; 2025 John Wiley & Sons Ltd and The Association for the Study of Medical Education--><copyright-statement content-type="article-copyright">&#x000a9; 2025 The Author(s). <italic toggle="yes">The Clinical Teacher</italic> published by Association for the Study of Medical Education and John Wiley &#x00026; Sons Ltd.</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link> License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="file:TCT-22-e70051.pdf"/><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-generated"><kwd id="tct70051-kwd-0001">peer coaching</kwd><kwd id="tct70051-kwd-0002">peer observation</kwd><kwd id="tct70051-kwd-0003">faculty development</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="3"/><table-count count="2"/><page-count count="8"/><word-count count="4500"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>source-schema-version-number</meta-name><meta-value>2.0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>April 2025</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>details-of-publishers-convertor</meta-name><meta-value>Converter:WILEY_ML3GV2_TO_JATSPMC version:6.5.4 mode:remove_FC converted:26.02.2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><fn-group id="tct70051-ntgp-0001"><fn fn-type="funding" id="tct70051-note-0001"><p>
<bold>Funding:</bold> The authors received no specific funding for this work.</p></fn></fn-group></notes></front><body id="tct70051-body-0001"><sec id="tct70051-sec-0001"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p>Despite a significant expansion in faculty development programmes for health professional educators [<xref rid="tct70051-bib-0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>], not all teachers have received education about teaching. Many teachers have, instead, learnt solely through teaching, with their educational practice being shaped by their prior experiences as both learners and as teachers.</p><p>Evaluating one's performance as an educator, with a view to improving one's teaching, is also challenging. Firstly, the shortcomings of self&#x02010;assessment are widely recognised and may be compounded by receiving incomplete feedback on one's actions [<xref rid="tct70051-bib-0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Although seeking feedback from students is commonplace, there are limitations with this approach too. &#x02018;Survey fatigue&#x02019; amongst students is recognised, and the consequences of this may be poor response rate [<xref rid="tct70051-bib-0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>], inaccurate evaluations [<xref rid="tct70051-bib-0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] and responder bias, resulting in polarised opinions [<xref rid="tct70051-bib-0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Issues may also arise with how practicable such feedback is. There is often a significant lag between the actual teaching moment and receiving feedback, meaning that the recollection of events may be limited. Furthermore, student feedback is invariably more student&#x02010;centric and not educator&#x02010;focussed.</p><p>Peer coaching is a faculty development approach whereby teachers receive personalised feedback on their teaching from colleagues, with the overarching aim of supporting their growth as educators. Although this approach is well suited to health professions education, and although there is evidence of its benefits, peer coaching is not universally adopted within institutions due to barriers, both perceived and real. In this Clinical Teachers' Toolbox article, we aim to encourage the uptake of peer coaching as a faculty development strategy by:
<list list-type="bullet" id="tct70051-list-0001"><list-item id="tct70051-li-0001"><p>Defining peer coaching and offering a structure for this faculty development activity.</p></list-item><list-item id="tct70051-li-0002"><p>Describing a theoretical basis that underpins peer coaching.</p></list-item><list-item id="tct70051-li-0003"><p>Outlining the benefits and potential barriers to peer coaching, alongside strategies to mitigate against these.</p></list-item><list-item id="tct70051-li-0004"><p>Reflecting on how culture might influence implementation of peer coaching programs.</p></list-item></list>
</p></sec><sec id="tct70051-sec-0002"><label>2</label><title>What Is Peer Coaching?</title><p>Peer coaching has been defined as &#x02018;a collegial process whereby two faculty members voluntarily work together to improve or expand their approaches to teaching&#x02019; [<xref rid="tct70051-bib-0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. The term &#x02018;peer&#x02019; captures a broad remit, with Gosling [<xref rid="tct70051-bib-0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] defining peers as &#x02018;colleagues from the same department, either of a similar status or (with) differentials of status, or &#x02026; from another department&#x02019;. A coach may be defined as &#x02018;an experienced person who supports a learner or client in achieving a specific personal or professional goal by providing training and guidance, with a focus on relatively short term performance&#x02019; [<xref rid="tct70051-bib-0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].</p><p>Peer coaching requires a collaborative, stepwise approach, as outlined in Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="tct70051-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. Firstly, time is set aside before any observation for a dialogue between peer coaches and their colleagues. Colleagues' needs are explored and the focus of the upcoming observation, in terms of developmental goals, is agreed upon. The peer coach then unobtrusively observes their colleague undertaking the teaching session. Afterwards, colleagues meet again for further dialogue, where both share their observations and reflections, whilst working towards ways in which educational practice might be modified. In essence, peer coaching represents a tool for guided self&#x02010;reflection that is centred on individual performance, embedded in the workplace and underpinned by respectful relationships between colleagues.</p><fig position="float" fig-type="FIGURE" id="tct70051-fig-0001"><label>FIGURE 1</label><caption><p>A three&#x02010;step approach to peer coaching.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="TCT-22-e70051-g001" position="anchor" id="jats-graphic-1"/></fig><disp-quote content-type="pull-quote" id="tct70051-blk-0001"><p>&#x0201c;Peer coaching represents a tool for guided self&#x02010;reflection that is centred on individual performance, embedded in the workplace and underpinned by respectful relationships between colleagues.&#x0201d;</p></disp-quote><p>There is much diversity in how peer coaching initiatives can be structured. They may be formal or informal, voluntary or mandated. They may occur as a one&#x02010;off or instead run serially over a prolonged period. Participants may be organised into dyads or may instead form part of a larger group. The observation component may occur in real time or, instead, might employ video recordings to allow observation at a time of one's choosing.</p><p>When describing peer coaching, it is also necessary to acknowledge that other terminology is often employed. The term &#x02018;peer observation&#x02019; is sometimes used, though this term's sole focus on observation risks neglecting the critical before and after elements that are required to translate observation into meaningful change to one's educational practice.</p><p>The term &#x02018;mentoring&#x02019; is also sometimes employed to describe such initiatives. Although peer coaching and mentoring share similarities, there are differences between the two approaches. Mentoring has been defined as &#x02018;a bidirectional relationship &#x02026; which focusses on mentees professional growth&#x02019; [<xref rid="tct70051-bib-0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Such relationships may be deeper, often focusing on personal life, work&#x02013;life balance and career progression [<xref rid="tct70051-bib-0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].</p><p>To conclude our definition of terms, Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="tct70051-tbl-0001" ref-type="table">1</xref> outlines what peer coaching is not and what it ought not to be.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tct70051-tbl-0001" content-type="TABLE"><label>TABLE 1</label><caption><p>What peer coaching is not or ought not to be.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><thead valign="bottom"><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peer coaching is not or ought not to be &#x02026;</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Justification</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solely an observation</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">As per Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="tct70051-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, it is critical that time is invested for colleague&#x02010;coach dialogue both before and after the observation</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reliant on the &#x02018;expert&#x02010;learner&#x02019; model</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The peer coach does not need to be an expert teacher, nor a topic expert, since the crux of observation relates to their colleague's ability to facilitate learning. Peer coaching is not about appraising a colleague's knowledge base</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Summative</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peer coaching ought to be non&#x02010;evaluative, to cultivate a relatively safe space for honest, critical reflection on one's teaching and discussion of topic areas that may be challenging or even controversial</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prescriptive</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Although the use of observation grids may provide a structure for note&#x02010;keeping during observations, rigidly sticking to these may risk drifting from the original focus of the observation, as identified at the pre&#x02010;observation meeting</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mandatory</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Although this is debated, mandating observations risks the participant's engagement with peer coaching becoming extrinsically motivated, which may undermine the potential for meaningful learning about one's teaching</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A one&#x02010;way process</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Discussions before and after ought to be dialogues, not one&#x02010;way transmission of information from coach to colleague. The reciprocity of learning within peer coaching dyads is well recognised</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="tct70051-sec-0003"><label>3</label><title>A Theoretical Basis for Peer Coaching</title><p>Seen through the lens of Kolb's experiential learning cycle [<xref rid="tct70051-bib-0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], peer coaching may be seen as a means of supporting <italic toggle="yes">active experimentation</italic> before, and <italic toggle="yes">reflective observation</italic> after, a teaching episode, thereby creating new (in this case, pedagogical) knowledge through the &#x02018;transformation of experience&#x02019; (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="tct70051-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). By contrast, unobserved teaching is liable to err on the side of familiarity, to repeat errors, to miss opportunities and to stifle educator development. A well&#x02010;structured peer coaching cycle, like a good lesson plan, will encourage teachers to pause and reflect on the outcome they wish to achieve (e.g., active participation of the whole group of learners) and consider strategies to achieve it. This gives the coach a focus for their observations during the teaching episode, which will help their colleagues to reflect afterwards. If this gives rise to a sense of dissatisfaction or curiosity about alternative strategies, <italic toggle="yes">abstract conceptualisation</italic> may follow, for example, if the colleague decides to explore the literature on an alternative teaching strategy. This in turn may give rise to further active <italic toggle="yes">experimentation</italic> (with or without the coach observing) the next time the session is run.</p><fig position="float" fig-type="FIGURE" id="tct70051-fig-0002"><label>FIGURE 2</label><caption><p>Kolb's experiential learning cycle [rectangles] as applied to peer coaching, with the actions of observed colleague [thought bubbles] and peer coach [ovals] depicted.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="TCT-22-e70051-g003" position="anchor" id="jats-graphic-3"/></fig><disp-quote content-type="pull-quote" id="tct70051-blk-0002"><p>&#x0201c;A well&#x02010;structured peer coaching cycle, like a good lesson plan, will encourage teachers to pause and reflect on the outcome they wish to achieve.&#x0201d;</p></disp-quote><p>As we make clear throughout this paper, a challenge in implementing peer coaching is achieving buy&#x02010;in from colleagues, and it is helpful here to consider psychological theories of motivation. We find that self&#x02010;determination theory [<xref rid="tct70051-bib-0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] helps us to explain peer coaching to colleagues and to gauge whether it has been effective (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="tct70051-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Done well, peer coaching engages the colleague's intrinsic motivation to do a good job (competence), to do it their way (autonomy) and to feel part of a teaching and learning community (relatedness). By contrast, if the process is perceived to be a pointless hoop&#x02010;jumping exercise or a covert surveillance operation conducted by the leadership team, colleagues may lose all desire to participate in the initiative (amotivation) or be driven to participate solely by an external locus of control (extrinsic motivation). Both amotivation and extrinsic motivation are associated with poorer performance and well&#x02010;being. If the goal is personal growth, one can readily appreciate that colleagues must therefore find intrinsic motivation to engage, and this principle can guide us on how to cultivate an environment that supports this.</p><fig position="float" fig-type="FIGURE" id="tct70051-fig-0003"><label>FIGURE 3</label><caption><p>Self&#x02010;determination theory: a spectrum of motivation and innate, underlying psychological needs.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="TCT-22-e70051-g002" position="anchor" id="jats-graphic-5"/></fig></sec><sec id="tct70051-sec-0004"><label>4</label><title>The Benefits of Peer Coaching</title><p>Peer coaching builds on the development agendas of colleagues and establishes person&#x02010;centred growth as a foundational principle. This makes it a flexible tool that can be effective across experience and expertise levels [<xref rid="tct70051-bib-0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]; indeed, peer coaching can benefit from diverse participants in a learning community, as the outcomes are co&#x02010;constructed. It is recognised that peer feedback can increase self&#x02010;worth for teachers [<xref rid="tct70051-bib-0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], which, in turn, can promote workforce satisfaction and sustainability [<xref rid="tct70051-bib-0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].</p><p>A bidirectional coaching relationship creates a supportive and collegiate approach, demanding equal participation between partners and mitigating power dynamics between colleagues [<xref rid="tct70051-bib-0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="tct70051-bib-0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. When both colleagues share a teaching context, they can develop a more nuanced understanding of the realities of the education setting, including its dynamism and its challenges.</p><p>Such collaboration fosters development via multiple pathways. A participant can develop new skills by receiving feedback on their own skills and through reflective, developmental dialogue with their peer coach. Peer coaching also brings reciprocal benefits to the peer coach, who, by observing and discussing their colleague's teaching, can develop their own teaching skills. As a collaborative process, peer coaching has the potential to strengthen existing relationships between colleagues or build new ones within the participants' community of practice [<xref rid="tct70051-bib-0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Where institutional values align with peer coaching principles, reflective and developmental practice can become embedded. This may encourage teachers to adopt a more reflective, collaborative approach in their general educational practice [<xref rid="tct70051-bib-0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] and may also facilitate cross&#x02010;pollination of good practice between teams and departments.</p><disp-quote content-type="pull-quote" id="tct70051-blk-0003"><p>&#x0201c;Peer coaching also brings reciprocal benefits to the peer coach, who, by observing and discussing their colleague's teaching, can develop their own teaching skills.&#x0201d;</p></disp-quote><p>We acknowledge that despite these myriad benefits, there may be barriers to implementation of peer coaching initiatives. In Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="tct70051-tbl-0002" ref-type="table">2</xref>, we share, from the perspective of the colleague being observed, these potential barriers alongside strategies we offer to mitigate against these.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tct70051-tbl-0002" content-type="TABLE"><label>TABLE 2</label><caption><p>Potential barriers to peer coaching programmes and how they might be overcome.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><thead valign="bottom"><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02018;This will not work because &#x02026;&#x02019;</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">How to mitigate against this</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02018;I do not have time for this&#x02019;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Institutional&#x02010;level commitment to peer coaching initiatives ought to legitimise the use of time for this purpose; however, we acknowledge that educators are busy people, who often have a myriad of competing interests. The process of peer coaching need not, however, be time consuming. For example, depending on the area of focus for observation that is identified within discussion, the peer observation component itself may not necessarily require the entire session to be viewed</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02018;There'll be too much paperwork&#x02019;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<styled-content style="color:#242424">The steps and rubrics employed within peer coaching should be simple and easy to follow. Employing technology to record these may make their completion more efficient</styled-content>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02018;I feel uneasy about being observed&#x02019;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Observational anxiety with peer coaching is widespread and understandable, and a lack of psychological safety within peer dyads risks undermining their educational value. Rather than ignoring this, we suggest leaders acknowledge its existence and recognise that there is no &#x02018;one size fits all&#x02019; strategy. For example, some teachers may find observation by their peers to be threatening, whereas others may find a familiar face to be less intimidating than a staff member from a different department. Giving staff members agency when it comes to selecting their peer coach may help reduce this sense of unease</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02018;I'll teach differently if I'm being watched&#x02019;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Observer placement within teaching sessions ought to be as unobtrusive as possible, seeking to avoid the eye line of their colleague where feasible. Fostering a collaborative relationship within the pre&#x02010;observation discussion, with a focus on support and development rather than critique, may go some way to minimise the impact of being observed</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02018;My institution must have an agenda for doing this&#x02019;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A &#x02018;top&#x02010;down approach&#x02019; where peer coaching is mandated and seemingly foisted on staff without clarity of purpose risks staff interpreting the scheme as a mechanism of quality control, with potential negative consequences for their career. Leaders should therefore take the time to clearly articulate the rationale for the initiative so that peer coaching is instead conceptualised as a tool for personal development</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02018;The observer being there will interfere with students' learning&#x02019;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Whereas the observer ought to be as unobtrusive as possible in the session, the peer coach should be introduced to the students at the start of the session. Their role should be clearly explained so that students understand that they are there to observe their teacher and not them</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02018;No one else seems to be doing this&#x02019;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hearing real&#x02010;life accounts from staff who have engaged with, and benefitted from, peer coaching may help challenge preconceptions and raise the profile of peer coaching within the department</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02018;I'm unsure if the peer coach is trained to give useful feedback&#x02019;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Observer selection and training requirements ought to be communicated to all stakeholders. There should be opportunities for peers to have the role of being observed and to observe, to benefit from both perspectives</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02018;It's hard to synchronise suitable times&#x02019;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Administrative support to assist with identification of mutually convenient times may help, as might the use of freely accessible online software whereby colleagues can indicate their availability</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02018;I have not received any training for this&#x02019;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peer coaching schemes ought not to be parachuted onto staff without any accompanying training. Providing faculty development to help staff acquire and hone the skills needed for them to observe, and then facilitate discussions, will increase the likelihood of meaningful engagement amongst staff members</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02018;My peer coach is from a very different culture and does not understand the teaching environment I work in&#x02019;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Discussion within the pre&#x02010;observation meeting provides an ideal opportunity for the peer coach to learn about the educational milieu in which their teaching colleague works. Making cultural differences a valid topic for discussion offers the potential for rich bilateral learning with the observer potentially then able to offer more nuanced, context&#x02010;specific observations</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02018;I'm concerned about being asked a question that I cannot answer. What if I get something wrong, or say something stupid?&#x02019;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No teaching session is perfect. This should be acknowledged within the pre&#x02010;observation discussion, where it should also be stated that the observer's role is to watch teaching process, rather than scrutinise sessions for content missteps or slips of the tongue</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02018;I do not see the value in this exercise&#x02019;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Encourage leaders to share their personal reflections of peer coaching to demonstrate its potential impact on teaching. This may encourage those staff members who are sceptical to engage with the initiative regardless, as after completing a discussion&#x02013;observation&#x02013;discussion cycle, the value of peer observation will become apparent</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02018;My audience might think I am not a good educator as I need to be observed&#x02019;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<styled-content style="color:#242424">The purpose of peer coaching programmes needs to be clearly communicated to students. The practice of receiving feedback to enhance competencies is part of reflective practice, and peer coaching is an excellent way for health professionals and faculty to role model this to students</styled-content>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02018;The chemistry between my coach and I means this will not work&#x02019;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Significant personality clashes may render some peer coaching dyads incompatible, but we suggest that this would be infrequently encountered. Giving teachers agency to identify the colleague that they would like to link up with may help in a situation where conflict exists between staff members</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="tct70051-sec-0005"><label>5</label><title>The Impact of Culture</title><p>For educators who are seeking to introduce, or refine, a peer coaching programme in their institution, the influence of &#x02018;departmental culture&#x02019; is likely to be at the forefront of their thinking. Faculty development, and health professions education more generally, is provided within a diverse range of cultural contexts. Yet, it is recognised that culture is somewhat of an amorphous notion that is variably and infrequently defined, thus making it challenging to determine which elements of culture are relevant to faculty development initiatives such as peer coaching [<xref rid="tct70051-bib-0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. We choose to define culture using the &#x02018;three lens&#x02019; approach described by Watling et&#x000a0;al. [<xref rid="tct70051-bib-0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], whose novel theorisation offers a helpful framework for reflecting on how peer coaching initiatives might be embedded.</p><p>The first lens Watling describes is the &#x02018;organisational perspective&#x02019;, where organisational culture is the product of the shared assumptions, beliefs and values that characterise a setting. This is typically considered in retrospect and is often construed as being a barrier to change, rather than as a resource that can itself be a catalyst for change. For example, in the cultural context of hierarchical societies, great trust and respect is placed in authority figures, which can manifest in deference to, and more guarded dialogue with, colleagues with perceived seniority [<xref rid="tct70051-bib-0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Hofstede's cultural dimension theory also recognises this phenomenon. Hofstede's six categories that define culture include &#x02018;power distance&#x02019; [<xref rid="tct70051-bib-0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. In countries where this is large, the culture is one where there is great respect for, and deference to, rank, authority and experience&#x02014;in essence, &#x02018;subordinates expect to be told what to do&#x02019; [<xref rid="tct70051-bib-0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. For peer coaching to be effective, open discourse, where vulnerabilities can be shared, is crucial. One might conclude that a culture with large power distance would therefore be incompatible with peer coaching. Yet, as Watling suggests, this cultural factor may provide potential for change, as the power of positive role&#x02010;modelling is amplified in such a cultural setting [<xref rid="tct70051-bib-0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], making senior colleagues, who are invested in peer coaching, particularly powerful agents for change. Yet, the potency of this cultural phenomenon, and the extent to which it is in entrenched, must not be underestimated when planning peer coaching initiatives.</p><p>Second, Watling refers to the &#x02018;identity perspective&#x02019;, where identity and culture become intertwined. Through this lens, culture is about how people make sense of themselves within a given community or setting. Teacher identity is recognised as an important determinant of excellence in education and something that departments ought to strive to nurture through faculty development initiatives [<xref rid="tct70051-bib-0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. A teacher's identity is not a passive possession; instead, it is dynamic, actively colouring what a teacher values, how they practice and how they develop. Considering peer coaching, an educator whose teacher identity is secure and comfortable may be inclined to perceive peer observation as an opportunity to develop. But an educator whose teacher identity feels more insecure may perceive the same opportunity as a chance to &#x02018;fail&#x02019;. Legitimising discussion about teacher identity within peer coaching initiatives is therefore important and should form part of any accompanying training or briefing.</p><p>Finally, Watling's &#x02018;practice perspective&#x02019;, which, perhaps counterintuitively, eschews culture and instead focuses on practice, that is, what happens, and how is it enacted by people and things? Through this lens, culture does not exist in terms of &#x02018;some unseen force directing people and their practice&#x02019; [<xref rid="tct70051-bib-0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]; there are instead only actions that happen in time and space. For example, consider the educator seeking to implement peer coaching who is encountering resistance to doing so within their department. Rather than drawing on assumptions and interpretations of culture, the practice perspective would encourage this educator to examine the multitude of elements that influence peer coaching practice (e.g., identifying a peer colleague, timetabling and the physical spaces where observation/discussion occurs). A deliberate, analytical examination of all the elements that inform practice may reveal flaws that can be remedied, rather than erroneous assumptions about the individuals or the culture perpetuating sub&#x02010;optimal practice.</p><p>We close this discussion around culture with an acknowledgement that though the three lenses were considered separately, they are in practice, often co&#x02010;existent, either colliding or complementing depending on the educational milieu. Furthermore, aiming for a &#x02018;one size fits all&#x02019; standard for peer coaching is not our aspiration. We have instead sought to moderate our guidance through cultural humility. This approach acknowledges that there are likely to be a variety of effective, contextually appropriate approaches to peer coaching globally [<xref rid="tct70051-bib-0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] and that there is much to be learnt through international collaboration and bidirectional learning [<xref rid="tct70051-bib-0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>].</p><disp-quote content-type="pull-quote" id="tct70051-blk-0004"><p>&#x0201c;There are likely to be a variety of effective, contextually appropriate approaches to peer coaching globally and that there is much to be learnt through international collaboration and bidirectional learning.&#x0201d;</p></disp-quote></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="tct70051-sec-0006"><label>6</label><title>Conclusion</title><p>In this toolbox article, we offer a definition and a structure for embedding peer coaching within a health professions education context. The potential benefits of implementing peer coaching are outlined whilst acknowledging the barriers that exist to doing so and offering mitigation strategies against these. Accessible summaries of relevant educational theory are presented, seeking to illuminate the pedagogy that underpins the three&#x02010;step approach to peer coaching that is suggested. Theory is also used to offer explanations for variable engagement with peer coaching programmes. The impact of the local educational milieu on peer coaching schemes is further considered through discussion about culture.</p></sec><sec id="tct70051-sec-0011"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>
<bold>James Fisher:</bold> conceptualization, writing &#x02013; original draft, writing &#x02013; review and editing, project administration, visualization. <bold>Anna Ainsworth:</bold> conceptualization, writing &#x02013; original draft, writing &#x02013; review and editing, visualization. <bold>Richard Thomson:</bold> conceptualization, writing &#x02013; original draft, writing &#x02013; review and editing, visualization. <bold>Joanna Matthan:</bold> conceptualization, writing &#x02013; review and editing, visualization. <bold>Vishna Devi Nadarajah V:</bold> conceptualization, writing &#x02013; review and editing, visualization. <bold>Yvonne Steinert:</bold> conceptualization, writing &#x02013; review and editing, visualization.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="tct70051-sec-0008"><title>Conflicts of Interest</title><p>The authors declare no conflicts of interest.</p></sec></body><back><ack id="tct70051-sec-0007"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors have nothing to report.</p></ack><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="tct70051-sec-0010"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The authors have nothing to report.</p></sec><ref-list content-type="cited-references" id="tct70051-bibl-0001"><title>References</title><ref id="tct70051-bib-0001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="tct70051-cit-0001">
<string-name>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
<surname>Steinert</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
<surname>Mann</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
<surname>Anderson</surname>
</string-name>, et&#x000a0;al., &#x0201c;<article-title>A Systematic Review of Faculty Development Initiatives Designed to Enhance Teaching Effectiveness: A 10&#x02010;Year Update: BEME Guide No. 40</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Medical Teacher</source>
<volume>38</volume>, no. <issue>8</issue> (<year>2016</year>): <fpage>769</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>786</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/0142159X.2016.1181851</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27420193</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="tct70051-bib-0002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="tct70051-cit-0002">
<string-name>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
<surname>Dunning</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
<surname>Heath</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>J. M.</given-names>
<surname>Suls</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>Flawed Self&#x02010;Assessment:Implications for Health, Education, and the Workplace</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Psychological Science in the Public Interest</source>
<volume>5</volume>, no. <issue>3</issue> (<year>2004</year>): <fpage>69</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>106</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26158995</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="tct70051-bib-0003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="tct70051-cit-0003">
<string-name>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Sch&#x000f6;nrock&#x02010;Adema</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Lubarsky</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
<surname>Chalk</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
<surname>Steinert</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Cohen&#x02010;Schotanus</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>&#x02018;What Would my Classmates Say?&#x02019; An International Study of the Prediction&#x02010;Based Method of Course Evaluation</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Medical Education</source>
<volume>47</volume>, no. <issue>5</issue> (<year>2013</year>): <fpage>453</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>462</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23574058</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="tct70051-bib-0004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="tct70051-cit-0004">
<string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Uijtdehaage</surname>
</string-name> and <string-name>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
<surname>O'Neal</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>A Curious Case of the Phantom Professor: Mindless Teaching Evaluations by Medical Students</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Medical Education</source>
<volume>49</volume>, no. <issue>9</issue> (<year>2015</year>): <fpage>928</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>932</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26296409</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="tct70051-bib-0005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="tct70051-cit-0005">
<string-name>
<given-names>W. Y.</given-names>
<surname>Wong</surname>
</string-name> and <string-name>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
<surname>Moni</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>Teachers' Perceptions of and Responses to Student Evaluation of Teaching: Purposes and Uses in Clinical Education</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Assessment &#x00026; Evaluation in Higher Education</source>
<volume>39</volume>, no. <issue>4</issue> (<year>2014</year>): <fpage>397</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>411</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="tct70051-bib-0006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="tct70051-cit-0006">
<string-name>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
<surname>Huston</surname>
</string-name> and <string-name>
<given-names>C. L.</given-names>
<surname>Weaver</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>Peer Coaching: Professional Development for Experienced Faculty</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Innovative Higher Education</source>
<volume>33</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue> (<year>2008</year>): <fpage>5</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="tct70051-bib-0007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="miscellaneous" id="tct70051-cit-0007">
<string-name>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
<surname>Gosling</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>Models of Peer Observation of Teaching</article-title>,&#x0201d; York, (<year>2002</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="tct70051-bib-0008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="tct70051-cit-0008">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<string-name>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
<surname>Salas</surname>
</string-name>
</person-group>, <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<string-name>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
<surname>Rico</surname>
</string-name>
</person-group>, and <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<string-name>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Passmore</surname>
</string-name>
</person-group>, eds., <source>The Wiley Blackwell Handbook of the Psychology of Team Working and Collaborative Processes</source> (<publisher-name>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons</publisher-name>, <year>2017</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="tct70051-bib-0009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="tct70051-cit-0009">
<string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Ramani</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>R. A.</given-names>
<surname>Kusurkar</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Lyon&#x02010;Maris</surname>
</string-name>, et&#x000a0;al., &#x0201c;<article-title>Mentorship in Health Professions Education &#x02013; An AMEE Guide for Mentors and Mentees: AMEE Guide No. 167</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Medical Teacher</source>
<volume>46</volume>, no. <issue>8</issue> (<year>2023</year>): <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>13</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/0142159x.2023.2273217</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="tct70051-bib-0010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="tct70051-cit-0010">
<string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Boillat</surname>
</string-name> and <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Elizov</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<part-title>Peer Coaching and Mentorship</part-title>,&#x0201d; in <source>Faculty Development in the Health Professions: A Focus on Research and Practice</source>, ed. <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<string-name>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
<surname>Steinert</surname>
</string-name>
</person-group> (<publisher-loc>Dordrecht</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer Netherlands</publisher-name>, <year>2014</year>): <fpage>159</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>179</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="tct70051-bib-0011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="tct70051-cit-0011">
<string-name>
<given-names>D. A.</given-names>
<surname>Kolb</surname>
</string-name>, <source>Experiential Learning: Experience as the Source of Learning and Development</source> (<publisher-name>FT Press</publisher-name>, <year>2014</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="tct70051-bib-0012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="tct70051-cit-0012">
<string-name>
<given-names>E. L.</given-names>
<surname>Deci</surname>
</string-name> and <string-name>
<given-names>R. M.</given-names>
<surname>Ryan</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>The &#x0201c;What&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;Why&#x0201d; of Goal Pursuits: Human Needs and the Self&#x02010;Determination of Behavior</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Psychological Inquiry</source>
<volume>11</volume>, no. <issue>4</issue> (<year>2000</year>): <fpage>227</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>268</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="tct70051-bib-0013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="tct70051-cit-0013">
<string-name>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
<surname>Margalit</surname>
</string-name> and <string-name>
<given-names>A. T.</given-names>
<surname>Pincavage</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>Feedback as Dialogue for Faculty: From Peer Review to Peer&#x02010;to&#x02010;Peer Coaching</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Medical Education</source>
<volume>57</volume>, no. <issue>2</issue> (<year>2023</year>): <fpage>118</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>120</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36419318</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="tct70051-bib-0014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="tct70051-cit-0014">
<string-name>
<given-names>P. B.</given-names>
<surname>Sullivan</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Buckle</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
<surname>Nicky</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>S. H.</given-names>
<surname>Atkinson</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>Peer Observation of Teaching as a Faculty Development Tool</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>BMC Medical Education</source>
<volume>12</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue> (<year>2012</year>): <elocation-id>26</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22559217</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="tct70051-bib-0015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="tct70051-cit-0015">
<string-name>
<given-names>D. A.</given-names>
<surname>Hirsh</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>P. E. S.</given-names>
<surname>Crampton</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>N. Y.</given-names>
<surname>Osman</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>Applying Self&#x02010;Determination Theory to Stem Medical Schools' Clinical Teacher Sustainability Crisis</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Medical Education</source>
<volume>58</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue> (<year>2024</year>): <fpage>118</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>128</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37593835</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="tct70051-bib-0016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="tct70051-cit-0016">
<string-name>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
<surname>Schwellnus</surname>
</string-name> and <string-name>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
<surname>Carnahan</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>Peer&#x02010;Coaching With Health Care Professionals: What Is the Current Status of the Literature and What Are the Key Components Necessary in Peer&#x02010;Coaching? A Scoping Review</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Medical Teacher</source>
<volume>36</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue> (<year>2014</year>): <fpage>38</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>46</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24094039</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="tct70051-bib-0017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="tct70051-cit-0017">
<string-name>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
<surname>Shapiro</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Janjigian</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>V.</given-names>
<surname>Schaye</surname>
</string-name>, et&#x000a0;al., &#x0201c;<article-title>Peer to Peer Observation: Real&#x02010;World Faculty Development</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Medical Education</source>
<volume>53</volume>, no. <issue>5</issue> (<year>2019</year>): <fpage>513</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>514</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30989686</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="tct70051-bib-0018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="tct70051-cit-0018">
<string-name>
<given-names>Z. S.</given-names>
<surname>Siddiqui</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
<surname>Jonas&#x02010;Dwyer</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>S. E.</given-names>
<surname>Carr</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>Twelve Tips for Peer Observation of Teaching</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Medical Teacher</source>
<volume>29</volume>, no. <issue>4</issue> (<year>2007</year>): <fpage>297</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>300</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17786740</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="tct70051-bib-0019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="tct70051-cit-0019">
<string-name>
<given-names>L. D.</given-names>
<surname>Lewis</surname>
</string-name> and <string-name>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
<surname>Steinert</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>How Culture Is Understood in Faculty Development in the Health Professions: A Scoping Review</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Academic Medicine</source>
<volume>95</volume>, no. <issue>2</issue> (<year>2020</year>): <fpage>310</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>319</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31599755</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="tct70051-bib-0020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="tct70051-cit-0020">
<string-name>
<given-names>C. J.</given-names>
<surname>Watling</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
<surname>Ajjawi</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Bearman</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>Approaching Culture in Medical Education: Three Perspectives</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Medical Education</source>
<volume>54</volume>, no. <issue>4</issue> (<year>2020</year>): <fpage>289</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>295</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31872497</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="tct70051-bib-0021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="tct70051-cit-0021">
<string-name>
<given-names>V. D.</given-names>
<surname>Nadarajah</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Claramita</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Findyartini</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
<surname>Samarasekera</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
<surname>Nishigori</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<part-title>The Way Forward: A Multi&#x02010;Directional Global Conversation on Culture and Learning</part-title>,&#x0201d; in <source>Challenges and Opportunities in Health Professions Education: Perspectives in the Context of Cultural Diversity</source>, eds. <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Claramita</surname>
</string-name>
</person-group>, <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Findyartini</surname>
</string-name>
</person-group>, <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<string-name>
<given-names>D. D.</given-names>
<surname>Samarasekera</surname>
</string-name>
</person-group>, and <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<string-name>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
<surname>Nishigori</surname>
</string-name>
</person-group> (<publisher-loc>Singapore</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer Nature Singapore</publisher-name>, <year>2022</year>): <fpage>293</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>308</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="tct70051-bib-0022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="tct70051-cit-0022">
<string-name>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
<surname>Hofstede</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>Dimensionalizing Cultures: The Hofstede Model in Context</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Online Readings in Psychology and Culture</source>
<volume>2</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue> (<year>2011</year>), <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.9707/2307-0919.1014</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="tct70051-bib-0023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="tct70051-cit-0023">
<string-name>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
<surname>Soemantri</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A. P.</given-names>
<surname>Susilo</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
<surname>Mustika</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>L. D.</given-names>
<surname>Leatemia</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<part-title>Nurturing Personal and Professional Development of Health Professionals in the Hierarchical and Collectivism Context</part-title>,&#x0201d; in <source>Challenges and Opportunities in Health Professions Education: Perspectives in the Context of Cultural Diversity</source>, eds. <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Claramita</surname>
</string-name>
</person-group>, <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Findyartini</surname>
</string-name>
</person-group>, <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<string-name>
<given-names>D. D.</given-names>
<surname>Samarasekera</surname>
</string-name>
</person-group>, and <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<string-name>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
<surname>Nishigori</surname>
</string-name>
</person-group> (<publisher-loc>Singapore</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer Nature Singapore</publisher-name>, <year>2022</year>): <fpage>219</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>244</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="tct70051-bib-0024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="tct70051-cit-0024">
<string-name>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
<surname>Steinert</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>P. S.</given-names>
<surname>O'Sullivan</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>D. M.</given-names>
<surname>Irby</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>Strengthening Teachers' Professional Identities Through Faculty Development</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Academic Medicine</source>
<volume>94</volume>, no. <issue>7</issue> (<year>2019</year>): <fpage>963</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>968</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30844931</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="tct70051-bib-0025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="tct70051-cit-0025">
<string-name>
<given-names>A. K.</given-names>
<surname>Wong</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>Culture in Medical Education: Comparing a Thai and a Canadian Residency Programme</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Medical Education</source>
<volume>45</volume>, no. <issue>12</issue> (<year>2011</year>): <fpage>1209</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1219</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21999309</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>