<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">JAMA Netw Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">JAMA Netw Open</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>JAMA Network Open</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2574-3805</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Medical Association</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39729315</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11681374</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.52661</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">zoi241466</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="category" specific-use="electronic"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Investigation</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="online-only"><subject>Online Only</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="subject-area"><subject>Oncology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Circulating Tumor DNA Testing in Curatively Resected Colorectal Cancer and Salvage Resection</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="headline">Circulating Tumor DNA Testing in Curatively Resected CRC and Salvage Resection</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Circulating Tumor DNA Testing in Curatively Resected CRC and Salvage Resection</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>Jingran</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="zoi241466aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Chongkai</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="zoi241466aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Goel</surname><given-names>Ajay</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="zoi241466aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Melstrom</surname><given-names>Kurt</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="zoi241466aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zerhouni</surname><given-names>Yasmin</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="zoi241466aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>Lily</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="zoi241466aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Melstrom</surname><given-names>Laleh</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="zoi241466aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Raoof</surname><given-names>Mustafa</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="zoi241466aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fong</surname><given-names>Yuman</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="zoi241466aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kaiser</surname><given-names>Andreas</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="zoi241466aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Fakih</surname><given-names>Marwan</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="zoi241466aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="zoi241466aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Medical Oncology and Therapeutics Research, City of Hope Comprehensive Cancer Center, Duarte, California</aff><aff id="zoi241466aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Molecular Diagnostics and Experimental Therapeutics, City of Hope Comprehensive Cancer Center, Duarte, California</aff><aff id="zoi241466aff3"><label>3</label>Department of Surgery, City of Hope Comprehensive Cancer Center, Duarte, California</aff><author-notes><title>Article Information</title><p><bold>Accepted for Publication:</bold> October 31, 2024.</p><p content-type="published-online"><bold>Published:</bold> December 27, 2024. doi:<uri content-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.52661</uri></p><p content-type="open-access-note"><bold>Open Access:</bold> This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link xlink:href="https://jamanetwork.com/pages/cc-by-license-permissions" ext-link-type="uri">CC-BY License</ext-link>. &#x000a9; 2024 Ji J et al. <italic>JAMA Network Open</italic>.</p><corresp id="zoi241466cor1"><bold>Corresponding Author:</bold> Marwan Fakih, MD, Department of Medical Oncology and Therapeutics Research, City of Hope Comprehensive Cancer Center, 1500 E Duarte St, Room 3208, Duarte, CA 91010 (<email xlink:href="mfakih@coh.org">mfakih@coh.org</email>).</corresp><p content-type="author-contributions"><bold>Author Contributions:</bold> Dr Fakih had full access to all of the data in the study and takes responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis.</p><p><italic>Concept and design:</italic> Ji, Goel, L. Melstrom, Fong, Fakih.</p><p><italic>Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data:</italic> Wang, K. Melstrom, Zerhouni, Lai, L. Melstrom, Raoof, Kaiser.</p><p><italic>Drafting of the manuscript:</italic> Ji.</p><p><italic>Critical review of the manuscript for important intellectual content:</italic> Wang, Goel, K. Melstrom, Zerhouni, Lai, L. Melstrom, Raoof, Fong, Kaiser, Fakih.</p><p><italic>Statistical analysis:</italic> Ji, Wang.</p><p><italic>Administrative, technical, or material support:</italic> Wang, Lai, Fong.</p><p><italic>Supervision:</italic> K. Melstrom, L. Melstrom, Fakih.</p><p content-type="COI-statement"><bold>Conflict of Interest Disclosures:</bold> Dr Raoof reported receiving funding from Exact Biosciences for an investigator-initiated prospective study outside the submitted work. Dr Fong reported receiving personal fees from Medtronics, Vergent, Theromics, Imugene, Eureka Biologics, and Sovato and receiving royalties from Merck outside the submitted work. Dr Kaiser reported receiving personal fees from Intuitive Surgical and receiving royalties from McGraw-Hill outside the submitted work. Dr Fakih reported receiving personal fees from Abbvie, Adagene, Amgen, Bayer, Bristol Myers Squibb, Merck, Nouscom SRL, Taiho, Totus Medicines, and Tempus; and grants from Mirati, Roche, and AgenusBio outside the submitted work. No other disclosures were reported.</p><p content-type="data-sharing-statement"><bold>Data Sharing Statement:</bold> See <xref rid="note-ZOI241466-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 2</xref>.</p></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2024-12-27T10:00"><day>27</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>12</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>27</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><!--PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>.--><volume>7</volume><issue>12</issue><elocation-id>e2452661</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>7</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>31</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright 2024 Ji J et al. <italic>JAMA Network Open</italic>.</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the CC-BY License.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf-version" xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2452661.pdf">jamanetwopen-e2452661.pdf</self-uri><self-uri content-type="silverchair" xlink:href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamanetworkopen/fullarticle/10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.52661"/><abstract abstract-type="key-points"><title>Key Points</title><sec id="ab-zoi241466-1"><title>Question</title><p>Is surveillance with a serial circulating tumor DNA (ctDNA) assay associated with improved chances of curative interventions in patients with resected colorectal cancer with disease recurrence?</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi241466-2"><title>Findings</title><p>In this cohort study of 184 patients with resected stage II to IV colorectal cancer, incorporating serial ctDNA assays along with National Cancer Center Network&#x02013;guided radiographic surveillance led to curative surgical intervention in 1.6% of patients.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi241466-3"><title>Meaning</title><p>These findings suggest that the addition of serial ctDNA assays to National Cancer Center Network&#x02013;recommended imaging surveillance has limited clinical benefits; more research is needed to determine whether the addition of ctDNA assays to surveillance improves relevant clinical outcomes over the standard of care and what the optimal frequency of testing may be.</p></sec></abstract><abstract abstract-type="teaser" specific-use="electronic"><p>This cohort study examines the potential curative clinical outcomes of adding serial circulating tumor DNA assays to standard-of-care imaging surveillance in patients with resected colorectal cancer (CRC).</p></abstract><abstract><sec id="ab-zoi241466-4"><title>Importance</title><p>Serial circulating tumor DNA (ctDNA) has emerged as a routine surveillance strategy for patients with resected colorectal cancer, but how serial ctDNA monitoring is associated with potential curative outcomes has not been formally assessed.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi241466-5"><title>Objective</title><p>To examine whether there is a benefit of adding serial ctDNA assays to standard-of-care imaging surveillance for potential curative outcomes in patients with resected colorectal cancer.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi241466-6"><title>Design, Setting, and Participants</title><p>In this single-center (City of Hope Comprehensive Cancer Center, Duarte, California), retrospective, case cohort study, patients with stage II to IV colorectal cancer underwent curative resection and were monitored with serial ctDNA assay and National Cancer Center Network (NCCN)&#x02013;guided imaging surveillance from September 20, 2019, to April 3, 2024. The median duration of follow-up was 26 months (range, 2-54 months).</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi241466-7"><title>Interventions</title><p>Serial ctDNA assays were performed every 3 months for 2 years and every 6 months for the 3 following years in conjunction with NCCN-guided radiographic surveillance.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi241466-8"><title>Main Outcomes and Measures</title><p>The primary outcome was the proportion of patients with clinical benefit from ctDNA testing, defined as the proportion of patients with a newly positive ctDNA assay and negative scheduled imaging (most recent or concurrent) that subsequently led to early imaging confirmation of recurrence, followed by curative-intent intervention with no evidence of recurrence at the time of data cutoff. Recurrence was categorized by ctDNA recurrence, radiographic recurrence, or concurrent ctDNA and imaging recurrence. Salvage resections and associated durable remissions were described within each of the 3 categories. Descriptive statistics were used to characterize the patient population.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi241466-9"><title>Results</title><p>In total, 184 patients (median age, 59 years [range, 32-88 years]; 97 female [52.7%]) were included in this study, and 129 (70.1%) had stage II to III disease. Forty-five patients (24.5%) had ctDNA or imaging-confirmed recurrence. Of these 45 patients, 14 had radiographic recurrence with negative ctDNA, and 11 had concurrent ctDNA and imaging recurrence. Twenty of 45 patients had ctDNA positivity with negative imaging at first ctDNA positivity; 6 had reflex imaging that was positive for recurrence, and 14 continued with serial imaging and ctDNA monitoring. Ten of 14 patients had subsequent recurrent disease, 3 patients had a spontaneous clearance of ctDNA, and 1 patient remained imaging negative 7 months after positive ctDNA, after which she was lost to follow-up. Altogether, 11 of 20 patients with ctDNA recurrence without initial concurrent imaging recurrence had subsequent metastasectomy, and only 3 were disease-free at the cutoff date in April 2024, representing 1.6% of the surveilled population.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi241466-10"><title>Conclusions and Relevance</title><p>In this cohort study of patients with stage II to IV colorectal cancer who underwent curative-intent resection, the addition of serial tumor-informed ctDNA assay to the standard NCCN-recommended surveillance had limited clinical benefits. Additional prospective research is needed to clarify the value of ctDNA testing in the surveillance setting.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="H1-1-ZOI241466"><title>Introduction</title><p>Despite advances in surgical techniques and adjuvant therapy for patients with resected colorectal cancer (CRC), a substantial number of patients continue to have disease recurrence with poor outcomes.<sup><xref rid="zoi241466r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="zoi241466r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="zoi241466r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="zoi241466r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> As a result, the surveillance strategy for patients with resected locoregional and metastatic CRC remains an important area of study. Although there is some continued disagreement in the existing literature regarding the optimal surveillance schedule,<sup><xref rid="zoi241466r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="zoi241466r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="zoi241466r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="zoi241466r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="zoi241466r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="zoi241466r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> the National Comprehensive Cancer Network (NCCN) recommendation for imaging surveillance for patients with high-risk stage II and stage III disease is computed tomography (CT) of the chest, abdomen, and pelvis every 6 to 12 months for 2 years, then yearly imaging for 3 years.<sup><xref rid="zoi241466r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> For resected stage IV disease, the recommendation is CT imaging every 3 to 6 months for 2 years, then every 6 to 12 months for 3 years. The European Society of Medical Oncology recommends a similar surveillance strategy.<sup><xref rid="zoi241466r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup></p><p>With the recent clinical availability of circulating tumor DNA (ctDNA) assays, there has been substantial interest in the benefit of incorporating ctDNA assays into the surveillance strategy for patients with stage II to III and resected stage IV CRC. One such assay that has received considerable attention is Signatera (Natera), a personalized next-generation sequencing assay for ctDNA detection that is informed by patient-specific tumor DNA. Studies examining ctDNA after curative intent resection demonstrated that ctDNA positivity is associated with an increased risk for clinical relapse, even after completion of adjuvant chemotherapy.<sup><xref rid="zoi241466r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="zoi241466r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="zoi241466r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="zoi241466r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> Preliminary results from more recent prospective trials<sup><xref rid="zoi241466r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="zoi241466r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="zoi241466r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="zoi241466r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> have further confirmed that ctDNA positivity both before and after resection is a robust prognostic indicator of disease recurrence and time to recurrence. Furthermore, sustained clearance of ctDNA is associated with high rates of disease-free survival, and ctDNA positivity after surgery was associated with benefit from adjuvant chemotherapy.<sup><xref rid="zoi241466r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="zoi241466r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup></p><p>Yet, there remain limited data on how the use of serial ctDNA assays in the surveillance setting is associated with clinically meaningful outcomes in patients with resected CRC. The initial observational study that led to the enthusiasm behind the implementation of the ctDNA assay into longitudinal surveillance showed that serial evaluation with ctDNA assays every 3 months for 36 months after definitive treatment for stage II to III CRC led to the detection of recurrent disease at a median of 8.7 months before imaging findings.<sup><xref rid="zoi241466r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup> However, the imaging surveillance used in that previous study was done at years 1 and 3 after definitive treatment, which is far less frequent than the current NCCN and European Society of Medical Oncology guidelines. We have previously evaluated the sensitivity of ctDNA in detecting a confirmed recurrence of disease compared with imaging alone using an NCCN-compliant imaging schedule. We found that the sensitivity of the 2 modalities was similar and that the time to detection of disease recurrence was the same.<sup><xref rid="zoi241466r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> More recent data from the BESPOKE trial<sup><xref rid="zoi241466r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> suggested that ctDNA may detect recurrence before imaging in a subset of patients, but the clinical outcomes of this early detection are not clear. Here, we describe a single institutional experience regarding the potential curative clinical outcomes with the addition of serial ctDNA assays to standard-of-care imaging surveillance, as recommended by NCCN guidelines.</p></sec><sec id="H1-2-ZOI241466"><title>Methods</title><p>We performed a retrospective cohort study at a single academic center (City of Hope Comprehensive Cancer Center, Duarte, California) to assess the outcomes of adding serial ctDNA testing with a Clinical Laboratory Improvement Amendments&#x02013;certified ctDNA assay on the potential for curative intervention at the time of recurrence among patients with resected stage II to IV CRC. This study was approved by the institutional review board at the City of Hope National Comprehensive Cancer Center. A waiver of informed consent was obtained, because the data were deidentified, in accordance with 45 CFR &#x000a7;46. The results reporting adheres to Strengthening the Reporting of Observational Studies in Epidemiology (<ext-link xlink:href="http://www.equator-network.org/reporting-guidelines/strobe/" ext-link-type="uri">STROBE</ext-link>) reporting guidelines.</p><p>All patients with CRC who had ctDNA testing as part of their surveillance schedule from September 20, 2019, to April 3, 2024, were identified. All patients included were monitored with serial ctDNA testing every 3 months for 2 years, then every 6 months for 3 years after curative-intent surgery. Surveillance CT scans were performed, per NCCN guidelines, every 6 months for 2 years and then every year for 3 years for patients with high-risk stage II and III disease. Imaging studies were performed every 3 to 4 months for 2 years and then every 6 months for 3 years for those with resected stage IV disease. For those with low-risk stage II disease, imaging was performed every year for 5 years. If a patient had a positive ctDNA assay prior to scheduled imaging, a reflex CT or positron emission tomography&#x02013;CT scan was done and then repeated every 3 months as long as ctDNA remained positive or until confirmed recurrent disease.</p><p>Recurrent disease was defined as evidence of recurrence on imaging or ctDNA positivity. We divided the study population into 4 cohorts (<xref rid="zoi241466f1" ref-type="fig">Figure</xref>): (1) those with negative ctDNA assays and negative scheduled imaging (either concurrent or most recent imaging), (2) those with a positive ctDNA assay and negative scheduled imaging, (3) those with a negative ctDNA assay and positive scheduled imaging, and (4) those with a concurrently positive ctDNA assay and scheduled imaging. Patients with a positive ctDNA assay and negative scheduled imaging were further divided into those with reflex imaging (additional imaging triggered by ctDNA positivity) positive or negative for recurrence. All patients were evaluated for recurrence, metastasectomy, recurrence following metastasectomy, and ctDNA clearance in those without radiographic recurrence.</p><fig position="float" id="zoi241466f1" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure. </label><caption><title>Recurrence Patterns During Surveillance With Circulating Tumor DNA (ctDNA) Assay and Imaging for Stage II to IV Colorectal Cancer</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2452661-g001" position="float"/></fig><sec id="H2-1-ZOI241466"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>The number of patients included in this study was determined by the number of eligible patients who had resected CRC and underwent serial ctDNA testing during surveillance from 2019 to 2024. The primary outcome was the proportion of patients with clinical benefit from ctDNA testing, defined as the proportion of patients with a newly positive ctDNA assay and negative scheduled imaging (most recent or concurrent) that subsequently led to early imaging confirmation of recurrence, followed by curative-intent intervention with no evidence of recurrence at the time of data cutoff. The study cohort was evaluated as a whole and then separately for patients with stage II to III disease and those with resected stage IV disease. We used descriptive statistics to characterize the patient population. Excel software version 2410 (Microsoft) was used to manage the data.</p></sec></sec><sec id="H1-3-ZOI241466"><title>Results</title><sec id="H2-2-ZOI241466"><title>Patient Characteristics</title><p>A total of 184 patients (median age, 59 years [range, 32-88 years]; 97 female [52.7%]) with resected stage II to IV CRC underwent surveillance with serial ctDNA assays and were included in this study; 129 (70.1%) had stage II to III disease (<xref rid="zoi241466t1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Surveillance was conducted for a median duration of 26 months (range, 2-54 months) at the time of data cutoff.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="zoi241466t1"><label>Table 1. </label><caption><title>Patient Demographics and Disease Characteristics</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="65.78%" span="1"/><col width="34.22%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristic</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients, No. (%) (N&#x02009;=&#x02009;184)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, median (range), y</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59 (32-88)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Male</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87 (47.3)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Female</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97 (52.7)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cancer stage</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> II-III</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">129 (70.1)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> IV</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55 (29.9)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tumor location</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Left colon and rectum</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">129 (70.1)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Right colon and transverse</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52 (28.3)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Unknown</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (1.6)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="H2-3-ZOI241466"><title>Recurrence During Surveillance</title><p>Of the 184 patients in this study, 45 (24.5%) had imaging-confirmed or ctDNA-confirmed recurrence of disease (<xref rid="zoi241466f1" ref-type="fig">Figure</xref>). Of the 45 patients who had recurrent disease, 11 had recurrence with concurrently positive ctDNA and imaging findings, 14 had recurrence by imaging with a negative ctDNA assay, and 20 had a positive ctDNA-recurrence with negative imaging studies (either prior or concurrent). As expected, the relative recurrence rate was higher among those with surveilled resected stage IV disease (24 of 45 patients [43.6%]) compared with those with resected stage II to III disease (21 of 129 patients [16.3%]) (<xref rid="zoi241466t2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="zoi241466t2"><label>Table 2. </label><caption><title>Recurrence Patterns During Surveillance With ctDNA Assay and Imaging for Stage II to III vs Resected Stage IV Disease</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="49.99%" span="1"/><col width="27.2%" span="1"/><col width="22.81%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1">Surveillance cohort</th><th colspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Patients, No. (%) </th></tr><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Stage II-III (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;129)</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage IV (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;55)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ctDNA positive, imaging negative</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (7.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (18.2)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Reflex imaging positive</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (2.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (5.5)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Nonresectable</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.8)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Resectable oligometastasis</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (2.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (3.6)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No evidence of disease</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.8)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Concurrent imaging negative</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (5.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (1.3)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Subsequent imaging positive</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (2.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (1.3)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Resectable oligometastasis</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (9.1)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No evidence of disease</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Subsequent ctDNA negative</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (1.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.8)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No evidence of disease</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (1.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.8)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Subsequent ctDNA positive, imaging negative</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ctDNA negative, imaging positive</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (6.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (10.9)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ctDNA positive, imaging positive</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (2.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (14.5)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ctDNA negative, imaging negative</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">108 (83.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (56.4)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Abbreviation: ctDNA, circulating tumor DNA.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="H2-4-ZOI241466"><title>Clinical Benefit of ctDNA Assay in Surveillance</title><p>Among the 20 patients with ctDNA positivity and negative imaging, 14 had concurrently negative imaging, and 6 had early reflex imaging showing evidence of recurrent disease (<xref rid="zoi241466f1" ref-type="fig">Figure</xref>). This cohort included patients with both stage II to III and resected stage IV disease, and most had received some form of systemic therapy before definitive surgical resection (<xref rid="zoi241466t3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). The median time from surgery to ctDNA positivity was 11 months (range, 0-39 months), and the most common site of recurrence was in the liver (8 patients [40.0%]), followed by lungs (4 patients [20.0%]) and distant lymph nodes (3 patients [15.0%]). Ultimately, 5 of the 6 patients with early reflex imaging underwent salvage resection or ablative therapy, but only 2 remained without evidence of disease.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="zoi241466t3"><label>Table 3. </label><caption><title>Surveillance Details for Patients in the ctDNA-Positive, Imaging-Negative Cohort</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="7.66%" span="1"/><col width="9.22%" span="1"/><col width="12.06%" span="1"/><col width="9.58%" span="1"/><col width="22.88%" span="1"/><col width="19.3%" span="1"/><col width="8.77%" span="1"/><col width="10.53%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patient No.</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage at diagnosis</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neoadjuvant or adjuvant chemotherapy</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time from surgery to ctDNA positive, mo</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time from ctDNA positive to imaging positive, mo</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site of recurrence</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Resectable disease</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recurrence after resection</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Imaging negative</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ctDNA cleared</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reflex imaging positive</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Liver</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lung and liver</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ovary</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reflex imaging positive</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lymph nodes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reflex imaging positive</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Liver</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ctDNA cleared</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retroperitoneum</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lymph nodes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lung</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Liver</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peritoneum</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Liver</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Liver</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reflex imaging positive</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lung</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lung</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ctDNA cleared</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reflex imaging positive</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lymph nodes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reflex imaging positive</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Liver</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Abbreviations: ctDNA, circulating tumor DNA; NA, not applicable.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Of the 14 patients with concurrent negative imaging, 10 had subsequent imaging that eventually showed recurrent disease, and 6 of these patients underwent local therapy for oligometastatic disease. Among these 6 patients, 2 had recurrence in the liver, 2 in the lung, 1 in the ovary, and 1 in the retroperitoneum. Ultimately, only 1 patient in this cohort remained without evidence of disease as of the cutoff date. Of the remaining 4 patients who did not have subsequent imaging recurrence, 1 patient had continued ctDNA positivity on serial testing with persistently negative scans at the time of data cutoff. This patient had resected stage II disease and a first positive ctDNA assay 13 months after definitive surgery and was lost to follow-up after a negative scan 7 months later. Three patients spontaneously cleared their ctDNA and continued to be ctDNA, imaging negative 27, 24, and 23 months, respectively, after initial clearance. Altogether, ctDNA testing led to further reflex or intensive imaging with 11 patients undergoing surgical or ablative therapy, but only 3 of whom remained without disease recurrence as of the cutoff date, corresponding to a potential curative outcome in 1.6% of the entire screened population (3 of 184 patients).</p></sec><sec id="H2-5-ZOI241466"><title>Patients With Imaging Recurrence and Negative ctDNA Assays</title><p>Fourteen patients (7.6%) from the overall cohort had a negative ctDNA assay at the time of imaging detected recurrence (<xref rid="zoi241466t4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref> and eFigure, panel A, in <xref rid="note-ZOI241466-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>). Of the 14 patients, most had stage II to III disease (10 patients [71.4%]), and the majority had lung-only recurrences (10 patients [71.4%]). One patient had a recurrence in the peritoneum, 1 in the abdominal wall, 1 in a pelvic lymph node, and 1 in the liver. The median time from surgery to recurrence was 14 months (range, 2-21 months). Of the patients identified with recurrence by imaging and without ctDNA positivity, 6 underwent salvage surgery or ablative procedures, and 4 remained without evidence of disease.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="zoi241466t4"><label>Table 4. </label><caption><title>Surveillance Details for Patients in the Circulating Tumor DNA&#x02013;Negative and Imaging-Positive Cohort</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="9.9%" span="1"/><col width="20.78%" span="1"/><col width="25.45%" span="1"/><col width="22.81%" span="1"/><col width="21.06%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patient No.</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage at diagnosis</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neoadjuvant or adjuvant chemotherapy</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time from surgery to imaging positive, mo</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site of recurrence</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abdominal wall</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lung</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lung</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lung</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pelvis or peritoneum</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lung</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lung</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pelvic lymph node</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lung</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lung</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lung</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lung</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lung</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Liver</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="H2-6-ZOI241466"><title>Patients With Concurrent Imaging Recurrence and Positive ctDNA Assays</title><p>Eleven patients (6.0%) had both a positive ctDNA assay as well as positive imaging at the time of recurrence (eFigure, panel B, in <xref rid="note-ZOI241466-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>). Of these 11 patients, most had stage IV disease (8 patients [72.7%]) and had recurrences in the liver (6 patients [54.5%]). The median time from surgery to recurrence was 7 months (range, 1-36 months); 6 patients underwent surgery or ablative procedures, with 3 remaining without evidence of disease.</p></sec><sec id="H2-7-ZOI241466"><title>ctDNA Recurrence and Lag Time From Radiographic Recurrence</title><p>When analyzing the overall population, the median time to recurrence was similar for ctDNA and imaging. When focusing on the recurrent population by ctDNA testing (31 patients), the median time from recurrence by imaging from ctDNA positivity was less than 1 month, as 11 patients were concurrently recurrent by imaging and 6 were recurrent by reflex imaging. When limiting the analysis to the 20 patients who were ctDNA positive without concurrent positive imaging, the median time to evidence of disease recurrence was 3 months (range, 1-18 months).</p></sec></sec><sec id="H1-4-ZOI241466"><title>Discussion</title><p>In this single-institution, retrospective cohort study, we found that a surveillance strategy for stage II to III and resected stage IV CRC incorporating serial ctDNA assays provided potential curative clinical benefit for 1.6% of the study population. Although 20 patients had early ctDNA detection of recurrence prior to imaging findings, only 3 of 11 patients had oligometastatic recurrences that were addressed with curative intent and did not recur at the time of analysis. Furthermore, it is possible that these 3 patients would have been identified by subsequent NCCN-recommended imaging and still may have derived a curative outcome. In comparison, 12 of 25 patients identified by imaging as the first evidence of recurrence, with or without concurrent ctDNA positivity, underwent curative intent resections or ablative procedures, and 7 of them remained without evidence of disease as of the cutoff date.</p><p>These results contrast with the conclusions of the prospective Danish trial,<sup><xref rid="zoi241466r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup> which indicated that ctDNA allowed for much earlier detection of recurrence compared with imaging alone. Our findings suggest that there may be a more limited role for serial ctDNA testing in the surveillance setting when using a more frequent imaging schedule, as recommended by the current NCCN guidelines. More robust prospective studies, including cost-effectiveness studies, are needed to determine the value of serial ctDNA testing in the surveillance setting and to justify the incorporation of such assays in routine clinical practice. Recent preliminary data from the ongoing BESPOKE trial<sup><xref rid="zoi241466r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> showed that ctDNA positivity may precede radiographic recurrence detection and increase targeted therapy for oligometastatic disease. However, the data are not yet mature, and the case-control design and the variable surveillance regimens in that study limit the interpretation of the findings.</p><p>Even if ctDNA assays can detect earlier recurrences compared with conventional imaging, limited data suggest that further intensifying surveillance and pushing for earlier detection of recurrence is directly correlated with improvements in survival. Studies done with older surveillance strategies do suggest that patients with disease recurrence picked up on routine testing are more likely to undergo successful curative-intent resection compared with those who are found to have recurrence after presenting with symptoms.<sup><xref rid="zoi241466r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="zoi241466r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="zoi241466r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> Although a few studies have shown a modest survival benefit of more frequent follow-up during surveillance,<sup><xref rid="zoi241466r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="zoi241466r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> several other randomized trials have failed to demonstrate that more-intensive surveillance regimens lead to a substantial survival benefit compared with less-intensive regimens.<sup><xref rid="zoi241466r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="zoi241466r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="zoi241466r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="zoi241466r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="zoi241466r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="zoi241466r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup> Indeed, these mixed results suggest that the clinical benefit of early detection of recurrence may plateau after a certain threshold, and further improvements to the timing of detection may not be worth the added cost of more frequent or, in the case of ctDNA assays, more novel testing.</p><p>In addition, the value of adding a blood-based marker for recurrence in combination with CT imaging has been extensively explored with the introduction of carcinoembryonic antigen (CEA) testing. CEA by itself is not highly sensitive or specific for CRC,<sup><xref rid="zoi241466r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> but when measured serially in the setting of surveillance for recurrent CRC, it has been shown to detect recurrence several months before other modalities, including CT imaging alone.<sup><xref rid="zoi241466r31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="zoi241466r32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="zoi241466r33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup> Although CEA has been shown to be potentially cost-effective,<sup><xref rid="zoi241466r34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup> there remain no prospective data demonstrating that a clear survival benefit can be attributed to the addition of serial serum CEA measurements. Thus, it is difficult to justify the value of adding ctDNA assays, which are much more costly than CEA assays, to the current NCCN-recommended surveillance strategy of serial CEA testing and CT imaging. In addition, there is no definitive evidence to date that the implementation of systemic chemotherapy will have a curative outcome in patients with ctDNA recurrence and negative imaging in a surveillance setting. Hence, no treatment strategies can be recommended at this time for patients with ctDNA recurrent, imaging-negative CRC. Until novel treatment strategies are developed and validated for these patients who harbor microscopic disease, further intensifying surveillance is unlikely to translate into improvements in key clinical outcomes.</p><p>More recent data suggest that ctDNA assays may be more clinically useful when used instead as a biomarker of minimal residual disease after curative-intent surgery to guide systemic therapy. Previous studies and preliminary results from ongoing studies have established the prognostic value of ctDNA in this setting, where patients with persistent ctDNA positivity after surgery have substantially higher rates of relapse.<sup><xref rid="zoi241466r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="zoi241466r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="zoi241466r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="zoi241466r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="zoi241466r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup> Both the BESPOKE and GALAXY trials have also reported the benefit of adjuvant chemotherapy among those with ctDNA positivity, even after controlling for other relevant clinical risk factors such as stage.<sup><xref rid="zoi241466r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="zoi241466r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> Furthermore, patients who are ctDNA negative may not benefit as much from adjuvant chemotherapy, and ctDNA may be used to guide the decision of adjuvant therapy in clinically lower-risk patients.<sup><xref rid="zoi241466r35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup></p><sec id="H2-8-ZOI241466"><title>Limitations</title><p>There are several limitations to this study. First, the retrospective nature of this study limits the interpretation of our findings, and not all patients were followed for a prespecified period of time. Thus, only a short duration of the surveillance schedule was captured for some of the included patients, contributing to a relatively low prevalence of disease recurrence in this cohort. Second, the relatively small sample size may have led to an underestimation of the clinical impact of serial ctDNA assays. Third, our patients who underwent resection without recurrence have not completed 5-year follow-up; hence, we may have overestimated the clinical benefit. Fourth, because this was a single-institution experience, our surveillance strategy may vary from other institutions or community practices where practice patterns and resource limitations may result in less frequent imaging and increase the utility of serial ctDNA testing.</p></sec></sec><sec id="H1-5-ZOI241466"><title>Conclusions</title><p>The findings of this retrospective cohort study suggest that the addition of serial ctDNA assays to NCCN-recommended imaging surveillance of resected stage II to IV CRC may have limited clinical benefit. Future prospective trials are needed to evaluate whether the addition of ctDNA to surveillance improves relevant clinical outcomes, including patient-reported outcomes, over the standard of care and whether the frequency of testing is worth the cost and psychological impact on patients.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="REF-ZOI241466"><title>References</title><ref id="zoi241466r1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Osterman</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Glimelius</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Recurrence risk after up-to-date colon cancer staging, surgery, and pathology: analysis of the entire Swedish population</article-title>. <source>Dis Colon Rectum</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>61</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1016</fpage>-<lpage>1025</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/DCR.0000000000001158</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30086050</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241466r2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>B&#x000f6;ckelman</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Engelmann</surname>
<given-names>BE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kaprio</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hansen</surname>
<given-names>TF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Glimelius</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Risk of recurrence in patients with colon cancer stage II and III: a systematic review and meta-analysis of recent literature</article-title>. <source>Acta Oncol</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>54</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>5</fpage>-<lpage>16</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/0284186X.2014.975839</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25430983</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241466r3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>O&#x02019;Connell</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Campbell</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Goldberg</surname>
<given-names>RM</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Survival following recurrence in stage II and III colon cancer: findings from the ACCENT data set</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>14</issue>):<fpage>2336</fpage>-<lpage>2341</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/JCO.2007.15.8261</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18467725</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241466r4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Siegel</surname>
<given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Giaquinto</surname>
<given-names>AN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jemal</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Cancer statistics, 2024</article-title>. <source>CA Cancer J Clin</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>74</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>12</fpage>-<lpage>49</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3322/caac.21820</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38230766</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241466r5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Secco</surname>
<given-names>GB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fardelli</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gianquinto</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Efficacy and cost of risk-adapted follow-up in patients after colorectal cancer surgery: a prospective, randomized and controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Eur J Surg Oncol</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>418</fpage>-<lpage>423</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/ejso.2001.1250</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12099653</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241466r6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez-Moranta</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sal&#x000f3;</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Arcusa</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Postoperative surveillance in patients with colorectal cancer who have undergone curative resection: a prospective, multicenter, randomized, controlled trial</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>386</fpage>-<lpage>393</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/JCO.2005.02.0826</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16365182</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241466r7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Primrose</surname>
<given-names>JN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Perera</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gray</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal/>; <collab>FACS Trial Investigators</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of 3 to 5 years of scheduled CEA and CT follow-up to detect recurrence of colorectal cancer: the FACS randomized clinical trial</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>311</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>263</fpage>-<lpage>270</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2013.285718</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24430319</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241466r8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Kishiki</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lapin</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Matsuoka</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Optimal surveillance protocols after curative resection in patients with stage IV colorectal cancer: a multicenter retrospective study</article-title>. <source>Dis Colon Rectum</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>61</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>51</fpage>-<lpage>57</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/DCR.0000000000000950</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29215480</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241466r9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Wille-J&#x000f8;rgensen</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Syk</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smedh</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <etal/>; <collab>COLOFOL Study Group</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of more vs less frequent follow-up testing on overall and colorectal cancer-specific mortality in patients with stage II or III colorectal cancer: the COLOFOL randomized clinical trial</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>319</volume>(<issue>20</issue>):<fpage>2095</fpage>-<lpage>2103</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2018.5623</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29800179</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241466r10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Rosati</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ambrosini</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barni</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <etal/>; <collab>GILDA working Group</collab></person-group>. <article-title>A randomized trial of intensive versus minimal surveillance of patients with resected Dukes B2-C colorectal carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Ann Oncol</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>274</fpage>-<lpage>280</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/annonc/mdv541</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26578734</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241466r11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group><collab>National Comprehensive Cancer Network</collab></person-group>. NCCN clinical practice guidelines in oncology. <year>2024</year>. Accessed May 27, 2024. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.nccn.org/guidelines/category_1" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.nccn.org/guidelines/category_1</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241466r12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Argil&#x000e9;s</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tabernero</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Labianca</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <etal/>; <collab>ESMO Guidelines Committee</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Localised colon cancer: ESMO clinical practice guidelines for diagnosis, treatment and follow-up</article-title>. <source>Ann Oncol</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1291</fpage>-<lpage>1305</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.annonc.2020.06.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32702383</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241466r13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Parikh</surname>
<given-names>AR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Seventer</surname>
<given-names>EE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Siravegna</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Minimal residual disease detection using a plasma-only circulating tumor DNA assay in patients with colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source>Clin Cancer Res</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>20</issue>):<fpage>5586</fpage>-<lpage>5594</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-21-0410</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33926918</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241466r14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Overman</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vauthey</surname>
<given-names>JN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aloia</surname>
<given-names>TA</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Circulating tumor DNA (ctDNA) utilizing a high-sensitivity panel to detect minimal residual disease post liver hepatectomy and predict disease recurrence</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>15</issue>)(<supplement>suppl</supplement>):<fpage>3522</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/JCO.2017.35.15_suppl.3522</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241466r15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Tie</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cohen</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Serial circulating tumour DNA analysis during multimodality treatment of locally advanced rectal cancer: a prospective biomarker study</article-title>. <source>Gut</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>68</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>663</fpage>-<lpage>671</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/gutjnl-2017-315852</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29420226</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241466r16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Tie</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cohen</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Circulating tumor DNA analyses as markers of recurrence risk and benefit of adjuvant therapy for stage III colon cancer</article-title>. <source>JAMA Oncol</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1710</fpage>-<lpage>1717</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamaoncol.2019.3616</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31621801</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241466r17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Kasi</surname>
<given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aushev</surname>
<given-names>VN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ensor</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Circulating tumor DNA (ctDNA) for informing adjuvant chemotherapy (ACT) in stage II/III colorectal cancer (CRC): interim analysis of BESPOKE CRC study</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>3</issue>)(<supplement>suppl</supplement>):<fpage>9</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/JCO.2024.42.3_suppl.9</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241466r18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Kotani</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Oki</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nakamura</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Molecular residual disease and efficacy of adjuvant chemotherapy in patients with colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source>Nat Med</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>127</fpage>-<lpage>134</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41591-022-02115-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36646802</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241466r19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Tie</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cohen</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Circulating tumor DNA analysis informing adjuvant chemotherapy in locally advanced rectal cancer: the randomized AGITG DYNAMIC-Rectal study</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>3</issue>)(<supplement>suppl</supplement>):<fpage>12</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/JCO.2024.42.3_suppl.12</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241466r20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Benhaim</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bouch&#x000e9;</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Normand</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Circulating tumor DNA is a prognostic marker of tumor recurrence in stage II and III colorectal cancer: multicentric, prospective cohort study (ALGECOLS)</article-title>. <source>Eur J Cancer</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>159</volume>:<fpage>24</fpage>-<lpage>33</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejca.2021.09.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34731746</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241466r21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Reinert</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Henriksen</surname>
<given-names>TV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Christensen</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Analysis of plasma cell-free DNA by ultradeep sequencing in patients with stages I to III colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source>JAMA Oncol</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1124</fpage>-<lpage>1131</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamaoncol.2019.0528</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31070691</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241466r22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Fakih</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sandhu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of comparative surveillance strategies of circulating tumor DNA, imaging, and carcinoembryonic antigen levels in patients with resected colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source>JAMA Netw Open</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<elocation-id>e221093</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.1093</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35258578</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241466r23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Goldberg</surname>
<given-names>RM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fleming</surname>
<given-names>TR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tangen</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Surgery for recurrent colon cancer: strategies for identifying resectable recurrence and success rates after resection. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group, the North Central Cancer Treatment Group, and the Southwest Oncology Group</article-title>. <source>Ann Intern Med</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>129</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>27</fpage>-<lpage>35</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/0003-4819-129-1-199807010-00007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9652996</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241466r24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Quentmeier</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schlag</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smok</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Herfarth</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Re-operation for recurrent colorectal cancer: the importance of early diagnosis for resectability and survival</article-title>. <source>Eur J Surg Oncol</source>. <year>1990</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>319</fpage>-<lpage>325</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2379591</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241466r25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Pita-Fern&#x000e1;ndez</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alhayek-A&#x000ed;</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez-Mart&#x000ed;n</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>L&#x000f3;pez-Calvi&#x000f1;o</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Seoane-Pillado</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>P&#x000e9;rtega-D&#x000ed;az</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Intensive follow-up strategies improve outcomes in nonmetastatic colorectal cancer patients after curative surgery: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Ann Oncol</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>644</fpage>-<lpage>656</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/annonc/mdu543</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25411419</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241466r26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Pietra</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sarli</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Costi</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ouchemi</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grattarola</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peracchia</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Role of follow-up in management of local recurrences of colorectal cancer: a prospective, randomized study</article-title>. <source>Dis Colon Rectum</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1127</fpage>-<lpage>1133</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02239434</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9749496</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241466r27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>M&#x000e4;kel&#x000e4;</surname>
<given-names>JT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Laitinen</surname>
<given-names>SO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kairaluoma</surname>
<given-names>MI</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Five-year follow-up after radical surgery for colorectal cancer: results of a prospective randomized trial</article-title>. <source>Arch Surg</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>130</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1062</fpage>-<lpage>1067</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archsurg.1995.01430100040009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7575117</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241466r28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Kjeldsen</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kronborg</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fenger</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>J&#x000f8;rgensen</surname>
<given-names>OD</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>A prospective randomized study of follow-up after radical surgery for colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source>Br J Surg</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>84</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>666</fpage>-<lpage>669</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9171758</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241466r29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Schoemaker</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Black</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Giles</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Toouli</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Yearly colonoscopy, liver CT, and chest radiography do not influence 5-year survival of colorectal cancer patients</article-title>. <source>Gastroenterology</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>114</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>7</fpage>-<lpage>14</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0016-5085(98)70626-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9428212</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241466r30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Nicholson</surname>
<given-names>BD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shinkins</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pathiraja</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Blood CEA levels for detecting recurrent colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>2015</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<elocation-id>CD011134</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD011134.pub2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26661580</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241466r31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>McCall</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Black</surname>
<given-names>RB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rich</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The value of serum carcinoembryonic antigen in predicting recurrent disease following curative resection of colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source>Dis Colon Rectum</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>875</fpage>-<lpage>881</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02052591</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8076486</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241466r32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Hine</surname>
<given-names>KR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dykes</surname>
<given-names>PW</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Serum CEA testing in the post-operative surveillance of colorectal carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Br J Cancer</source>. <year>1984</year>;<volume>49</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>689</fpage>-<lpage>693</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/bjc.1984.109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6733018</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241466r33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Bruinvels</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stiggelbout</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kievit</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>van Houwelingen</surname>
<given-names>HC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Habbema</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>van de Velde</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Follow-up of patients with colorectal cancer: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Ann Surg</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>219</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>174</fpage>-<lpage>182</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00000658-199402000-00009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8129488</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241466r34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Graham</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Catalano</surname>
<given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Haller</surname>
<given-names>DG</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Postsurgical surveillance of colon cancer: preliminary cost analysis of physician examination, carcinoembryonic antigen testing, chest x-ray, and colonoscopy</article-title>. <source>Ann Surg</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>228</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>59</fpage>-<lpage>63</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00000658-199807000-00009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9671067</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241466r35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Tie</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cohen</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lahouel</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <etal/>; <collab>DYNAMIC Investigators</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Circulating tumor DNA analysis guiding adjuvant therapy in stage II colon cancer</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>386</volume>(<issue>24</issue>):<fpage>2261</fpage>-<lpage>2272</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa2200075</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35657320</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list><notes notes-type="supplementary-material" id="note-ZOI241466-1"><supplementary-material id="note-ZOI241466-1-s" position="float" content-type="local-data"><label>Supplement 1.</label><caption><p><bold>eFigure.</bold> Disease outcomes for patients with recurrence in the setting of positive imaging (A) without concurrently positive ctDNA and (B) with concurrently positive ctDNA</p></caption><media xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2452661-s001.pdf"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material position="float" content-type="local-data"><label>Supplement 2.</label><caption><p>
Data Sharing Statement
</p></caption><media xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2452661-s002.pdf"/></supplementary-material></notes></back></article><!--requester-ID rluttrel-->