<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">JMIR Aging</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">JMIR Aging</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">JA</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">aging</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="index">31</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>JMIR Aging</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2561-7605</issn><publisher><publisher-name>JMIR Publications</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Toronto, Canada</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40367490</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12094531</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/65636</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">65636</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="primary-section"><subject>Physical Activity for Older People</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="secondary-section"><subject>Innovations and Technology for Physical Activity Education</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="secondary-section"><subject>Prevention and Health Promotion</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="secondary-section"><subject>Frailty Detection, Assessment and Prediction</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="secondary-section"><subject>Aging in Place</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Paper</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Frailty, Fitness, and Quality of Life Outcomes of a Healthy and Productive Aging Program (GrandMove) for Older Adults With Frailty or Prefrailty: Cluster Randomized Controlled Trial</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-4160-1713</contrib-id><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Jennifer Yee Man</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><email>jymtang@cuhk.edu.hk</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-4261-3414</contrib-id><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Hao</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref><email>hao.luo1@uwaterloo.ca</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6712-6466</contrib-id><name><surname>Tse</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">4</xref><email>matse@hku.hk</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-4635-3322</contrib-id><name><surname>Kwan</surname><given-names>Joseph</given-names></name><degrees>MBChB, MD</degrees><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">5</xref><email>joseph.kwan@nhs.net</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-9836-1925</contrib-id><name><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>Angela Yee Man</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">6</xref><email>angela.ym.leung@polyu.edu.hk</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0009-0002-0688-6124</contrib-id><name><surname>Tsien Wong</surname><given-names>Teresa Bik-kwan</given-names></name><degrees>MSc</degrees><xref rid="aff7" ref-type="aff">7</xref><email>bik-kwan.teresa.tsien.wong@connect.polyu.hk</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-1196-5345</contrib-id><name><surname>Lum</surname><given-names>Terry Yat Sang</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref><email>tlum@hku.hk</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1331-942X</contrib-id><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>Gloria Hoi Yan</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref><xref rid="aff8" ref-type="aff">8</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"/><email>hoiyangloria.wong@reading.ac.uk</email></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution content-type="department">Department of Educational Psychology</institution>, <institution>The Chinese University of Hong Kong</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Shatin</addr-line>, <country>China (Hong Kong)</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution content-type="department">School of Public Health Sciences</institution>, <institution>University of Waterloo</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Waterloo</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">ON</addr-line>, <country>Canada</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution content-type="department">Department of Social Work and Social Administration</institution>, <institution>The University of Hong Kong, Hong Kong</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Pok Fu Lam</addr-line>, <country>China (Hong Kong)</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><institution>Centre for Sports and Exercise, The University of Hong Kong, Hong Kong</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Pok Fu Lam</addr-line>, <country>China (Hong Kong)</country></aff><aff id="aff5"><label>5</label><institution content-type="department">Department of Brain Sciences</institution>, <institution>Imperial College London</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">London</addr-line>, <country>United Kingdom</country></aff><aff id="aff6"><label>6</label><institution content-type="department">School of Nursing</institution>, <institution>The Hong Kong Polytechnic University</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Hong Kong</addr-line>, <country>China (Hong Kong)</country></aff><aff id="aff7"><label>7</label><institution>Institute of Active Ageing, The Hong Kong Polytechnic University</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Hong Kong</addr-line>, <country>China (Hong Kong)</country></aff><aff id="aff8"><label>8</label><institution content-type="department">School of Psychology and Clinical Language Sciences</institution>, <institution>University of Reading</institution>, <addr-line>Earley Gate, Whiteknights Campus</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="city">Reading</addr-line>, <addr-line>RG6 6ES</addr-line>, <country>United Kingdom</country>, <phone>44 118 378 8523</phone></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>Michelle</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>None declared.</p></fn><corresp id="cor1">Gloria Hoi Yan Wong, PhD, School of Psychology and Clinical Language Sciences, University of Reading, Earley Gate, Whiteknights Campus, Reading, RG6 6ES, United Kingdom, <phone>44 118 378 8523</phone>; <email xlink:href="hoiyangloria.wong@reading.ac.uk">hoiyangloria.wong@reading.ac.uk</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>e65636</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>11</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; Jennifer Yee Man Tang, Hao Luo, Michael Tse, Joseph Kwan, Angela Yee Man Leung, Teresa Bik-kwan Tsien Wong, Terry Yat-sang Lum, Gloria Hoi-yan Wong. Originally published in JMIR Aging (https://aging.jmir.org)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work, first published in JMIR Aging, is properly cited. The complete bibliographic information, a link to the original publication on <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://aging.jmir.org">https://aging.jmir.org</ext-link>, as well as this copyright and license information must be included.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="aging-v8-e65636.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><sec><title>Background</title><p>Exercise interventions can reverse frailty. However, their scalability and sustainability are limited by manpower, which is reducing due to population aging. GrandMove is a program that combines healthy and productive aging strategies to (1) train and employ robust older adults as exercise coaches and (2) improve fitness and motivate the adoption of an exercise habit in older adults with frailty and prefrailty.</p></sec><sec><title>Objective</title><p>The aim of this study is to examine the effectiveness of GrandMove in improving frailty, fitness, and quality of life in older adults with frailty and prefrailty.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>This cluster randomized controlled trial recruited older adults with frailty and prefrailty (N=390) living in the community. The 18-month exercise program consisted of three 6-month phases of lifestyle education (E), resistance exercise (R), and aerobic exercise (A). Each group of participants was randomized into 3 intervention sequence arms: the E-R-A group, the A-R-E group, and the R-A-E group.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>At 6, 12, and 18 months, 346, 305, and 264 participants completed the frailty assessment, respectively. At 6 months, 100 of 346 participants (28.9%) were robust. A-R-E and R-A-E were no better than E-R-A as the active control in addressing frailty over the first 6 months (A-R-E: interaction coefficient 0.07, 95% CI &#x02212;0.35 to 0.49, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=.68; R-A-E: interaction coefficient &#x02212;0.02, 95% CI &#x02212;0.42 to 0.38, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=.90). Compared to lifestyle education, resistance training and aerobic training over the first 6 months were associated with greater improvement in fitness measures of grip strength for the left hand (A-R-E: interaction coefficient 2.99, 95% CI 0.76 to 5.23, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=.009; R-A-E: interaction coefficient 2.21, 95% CI 0.63 to 4.36, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=.04) and right hand (A-R-E: interaction coefficient 3.75, 95% CI 1.54 to 5.97, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=.001; R-A-E: interaction coefficient 2.29, 95% CI 0.16 to 4.42, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=.04) and arm curl test (A-R-E: interaction coefficient 1.42, 95% CI 0.39 to 2.46, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=.007; R-A-E: interaction coefficient 1.11, 95% CI 0.12 to 2.11, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=.03). The sequence of exercise interventions (R-A-E vs A-R-E) did not make a difference in primary outcomes at 12 months, but the R-A-E group showed better quality of life (interaction coefficient 4.50, 95% CI 0.12 to 8.88, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=.008). Improved frailty outcomes were maintained by the end of the study, but the change in overall physical activity level was limited.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Combining healthy and productive aging strategies is a scalable and sustainable way to improve frailty, fitness, and quality of life in older adults with frailty and prefrailty. Different combinations of lifestyle education and physical interventions improved frailty.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-keywords"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>physical activity</kwd><kwd>physical exercise</kwd><kwd>exercising</kwd><kwd>gerontology</kwd><kwd>geriatric</kwd><kwd>older adult</kwd><kwd>older person</kwd><kwd>older people</kwd><kwd>active aging</kwd><kwd>postretirement work</kwd><kwd>cluster randomized controlled trial</kwd><kwd>RCT</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Frailty, a common condition that increases with age, is a dynamic clinical state that can improve or worsen over time [<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref><xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. About 1 in 10 older adults are frail and 46% are prefrail, a state with higher risk of progression to frailty [<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Frailty is known to predict disability, mortality, risk of fractures, and many other adverse health outcomes [<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. To date, evidence for the management of frailty is the strongest with physical activity [<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref><xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. In older adults who are very frail, even small gains in strength can result in important functioning benefits and promote independence [<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Evidence suggested superior outcomes with training carried out 3 or more times per week, for 30-45 minutes per session, and lasting at least 3-5 months [<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Adherence to exercise training is good even in older adults with frailty, with few adverse events or safety concerns [<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].</p><p>Practice guidelines widely recommend multicomponent exercise programs for the management of frailty [<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Many programs concurrently prescribe multimodal exercise components, even though sequential prescription may promote adherence and minimize attrition [<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref><xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. The optimal sequence is yet to be investigated. Theoretically, strength and aerobic training contribute in different ways by slowing or compensating for muscle wasting and loss of endurance, as well as preventing other diseases and resisting the cascade of disability [<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. These exercise modalities impact on the older person&#x02019;s quality of life by affecting their ability to lift load (eg, arising from a chair) and endurance in performing activities of daily living (eg, walking), allowing them to take control and lead a purposeful life. These may have implications for the design of exercise training protocols for frailty intervention.</p><p>Past development of exercise programs put a greater emphasis on maximizing physical benefits, while less focus was put on the scalability and sustainability of the program. It is foreseeable that the health care manpower gap as a result of population aging is increasing [<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] and heavy reliance on professionally led formal health care services for addressing frailty is unviable and unsustainable. Our team developed a multicomponent exercise program, namely the GrandMove program, which has a group of trained coaches in their 50s to 60s deliver the interventions. Delivery of exercise interventions by peer coaches rather than health professionals is a key to the long-term scalability and sustainability of such programs in the context of population aging. Our program incorporated both healthy and productive aging strategies. Although the program had clear goals of improving frailty, fitness, and quality of life in older adults with frailty and prefrailty, our peer coaches took on their own path to successful aging by adopting an active lifestyle and engaging in postretirement paid work. A detailed description of the program design is provided in the Methods and <xref rid="SAP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Multimedia Appendix 1</xref>.</p><p>In this study, three intervention sequences were designed to (1) examine the effectiveness of a 6-month aerobic or resistance training program compared with lifestyle education as the active control intervention at 6 months, (2) investigate any order effect in resistance and aerobic training in older adults with frailty and prefrailty at 12 months, and (3) evaluate exercise habit formation over 18 months.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="s2-1"><title>Study Design and Participants</title><p>This is an 18-month, multicenter, cluster randomized controlled trial with 3 intervention arms. A cluster design was used because of the logistical issues associated with the implementation of the interventions. The study sites included 14 community service centers for older adults and 15 public rental estates in Hong Kong. The staff from the participating sites referred potential participants based on their age and frailty status at screening.</p></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>Ethical Considerations</title><p>Designated research assistants, who were not involved in the intervention, obtained written informed consent and conducted screening interviews with the participants. The study protocol was approved by the institutional ethics committee (reference number EA1511048). The study was registered with the HKU Clinical Trials Registry (reference number HKUCTR-1964). All data used in this study were deidentified before analysis. Participants did not receive any compensation for their involvement.</p></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title>Participants</title><p>Target study participants were older adults living in the community who did not have any contradictions to participation in a moderate level of physical activity. Between February 2016 and May 2017, older adults were invited to take part in this study if they were aged 65 years or older and were screened as either prefrail (scores of 1&#x02010;2 on the FRAIL [Fatigue, Resistance, Ambulation, Illness, and Loss of weight] scale) or frail (scores of 3&#x02010;5 on the FRAIL scale) [<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. To ensure the safety of the participants, older adults were excluded from participating if they reported having specific conditions. Specific exclusion criteria are described in <xref rid="SAP2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Multimedia Appendix 2</xref>.</p><p>The sample size was calculated based on an estimated 0.5-point improvement in the FRAIL score (SD 1) between an exercise condition versus lifestyle education, using a 2-sided test at 1% significance level with 80% power. Assuming a 20% dropout rate, the minimum sample size is 120 per arm. It was estimated that about 1 in 10 older adults was frail. To allow subgroup analysis by frailty status, the ratio of participants with prefrailty to those with frailty was set at about 6:4 (<xref rid="SAP2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Multimedia Appendix 2</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2-4"><title>Randomization and Masking</title><p>As shown in <xref rid="SAP3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Multimedia Appendix 3</xref>, each group of participants was randomly assigned into one of three parallel arms with different intervention sequences: (1) lifestyle education &#x02013; resistance training &#x02013; aerobic training (E-R-A); (2) aerobic training &#x02013; resistance training &#x02013; lifestyle education (A-R-E); and (3) resistance training &#x02013; aerobic training &#x02013; lifestyle education (R-A-E). Each intervention component lasted for 6 months, totaling up to 18 months. The sequence of the intervention components was designed to address the three research aims: (1) to evaluate the effectiveness of aerobic and resistance training at 6 months compared to lifestyle education, (2) to investigate the order effect of aerobic and resistance training at 12 months, and (3) to evaluate exercise habit formation over 18 months.</p><p>Randomization (1:1:1) was done by a research assistant using computer-generated random numbers stratified by frailty status. The person who was responsible for generating the random allocation sequence was not involved in any other parts of the research. Each group of consecutive participants was assigned to one of the 3 arms. Group allocation could not be masked for persons delivering or receiving the interventions. Our program exercise physiologists, who were responsible for developing the exercise protocols, training exercise coaches, and conducting the fitness tests with participants, were blind to the group assignment. Research assistants designated to assess outcomes were blind to group assignment and had no involvement in the delivery of interventions.</p></sec><sec id="s2-5"><title>Intervention Program: GrandMove</title><p>The GrandMove program is a structured exercise training program that contains 2 protocols, one focusing on aerobic exercise and the other on resistance exercise. Two protocols for aerobic training and resistance training were designed by our program exercise physiologists with certified training in strength and conditioning and tailored for older adults with prefrailty and frailty in Hong Kong. Robust older people were trained as exercise coaches to deliver the exercise protocols. The design of the program was guided by social learning theory [<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] and behavioral principles [<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] (see <xref rid="SAP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Multimedia Appendix 1</xref> for program characteristics). Both protocols were designed to be workable in a small home or group, using only small training implements such as rubber bands, towels, and water bottles for exercising. Each protocol had 5 levels, which indicate different levels of intensity. Based on the initial assessment, participants would start at a level that was realistic and attainable. A participant who reached a standard of fitness and strength in that level would continue with the next level.</p><p>The lifestyle education condition was comprised of 12 group sessions of health talks and 36 telehealth sessions. All health talks that covered different topics were delivered in a small group format by a retired nurse. Telehealth sessions involved a research assistant reviewing the health topics with participants and consolidating their understanding over the phone.</p><p>Each exercise intervention component lasted for 6 months (<xref rid="SAP4" ref-type="supplementary-material">Multimedia Appendix 4</xref>). The 6-month schedule was designed to provide active coaching in the first 3 months, followed by monitoring and supervision (4th and 5th month), and self-sustained practice (6th month). Group sessions were provided in a small group format (8&#x02010;10 older adults per group led by 2 coaches). Lifestyle education was designed to match the frequency of contacts with the exercise interventions.</p></sec><sec id="s2-6"><title>Measures</title><p>The participants were assessed at baseline, 6 months, 12 months, and 18 months. Each assessment included a battery of self-report instruments administered through a structured interview and physical tests. Basic demographic characteristics were obtained, including age, gender, education level, marital status, and living arrangement.</p></sec><sec id="s2-7"><title>Primary Outcomes</title><p>There were 3 primary outcomes. First, the frailty score was calculated using the 5-item FRAIL scale [<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. The items cover areas of fatigue, resistance, aerobic fitness, illnesses, and loss of weight. FRAIL scores are classified into three categories: robust (score of 0), prefrail (score of 1-2), and frail (score of 3-5). Second, physical performance was measured using the Short Physical Performance Battery (SPPB) [<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. The SPPB score ranges from 0&#x02010;12, with a higher score indicating better performance. Third, quality of life was measured using the World Health Organization Quality of Life &#x02013; Older adults module (WHOQoL-OLD) scale validated in a Chinese population [<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The total score ranges from 0&#x02010;100, with a higher score indicating better quality of life.</p></sec><sec id="s2-8"><title>Secondary Outcomes</title><p>There were 3 fitness performance measures including isometric handgrip strength as measured by a digital hand dynamometer (Jamar Plus+), the 30-second arm curl test [<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], and the 2-minute step test [<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. The hand grip strength of each hand was the average score of 3 trials. Higher fitness scores indicate better performance.</p><p>Other secondary outcomes included instrumental activities of daily living (IADL) as measured using the Lawton IADL scale (score range 0&#x02010;100, with higher scores indicating a lower level of disability) [<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], level of physical activity as measured using the Physical Activity Scale for the Elderly (PASE; higher scores indicate a higher level of physical activity) [<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], sleep quality as measured using the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI; higher scores indicate worse overall sleep quality) [<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], social functioning as measured using the Lubben Social Network Scale (LSNS; higher scores indicate a greater level of social support) [<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], and depressive symptoms as measured using the Patient Health Questionnaire-9 (PHQ-9; score range 0&#x02010;27, with higher scores indicating greater symptom severity) [<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s2-9"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>We conducted all analyses on an intention-to-treat basis. We generated descriptive statistics for baseline characteristics. The proportions of participants who achieved a robust or an improved frailty status (from frail to prefrail/robust or from prefrail to robust) at each follow-up were described. Within-group changes in proportions of robust or improved frailty outcome were tested using mixed effect logistic regression models.</p><p>The difference in outcome measures between intervention groups was estimated at each follow-up time point using repeated measures mixed effect linear regression models, adjusting for the fixed effects of gender and age at baseline. The main analysis using mixed models in the whole sample will further adjust for other baseline covariates that were found to be significantly different between groups. To examine the effectiveness of 6-month aerobic or resistance training, outcomes in the A-R-E group and R-A-E group were compared to the E-R-A group. To investigate the order effect in aerobic and resistance training, we compared 12-month outcomes between the R-A-E group and the A-R-E group (reference group). To evaluate the maintenance of exercise effect and habit formation, we compared the outcomes including the level of physical activity between groups at 18 months. As intervention components were switched at the 6th and 12th month, time was treated as a categorical variable instead of continuous to account for the possible nonlinear relationship between time and outcome variables. Treatment effect referred to the coefficient of the intervention group &#x000d7; time interaction. Subgroup analyses by baseline frailty status and gender were individually made to delineate the differential treatment effects. Since 12 outcomes were examined in this study, we set the significance level at 1% and reported the 99% CIs for the primary outcomes to account for multiple comparison bias. The significance level for the secondary outcomes was set at 5%. All analyses were conducted using Stata/MP (version 17.0; StataCorp LLC).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec id="s3-1"><title>Sample Characteristics</title><p>In total, 723 potential participants were assessed for eligibility, of whom 390 (53.9%) were randomized (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). Of the 390 participants included in the study, 132 (33.8%) were assigned to the E-R-A group, 124 (31.8%) to A-R-E, and 134 (34.4%) to R-A-E.</p><fig position="float" id="F1" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><title> Study flow chart. All participants were analyzed in repeated measures mixed-effect regression models.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="aging-v8-e65636-g001" position="float"/></fig><p>Baseline characteristics for participants by intervention group are shown in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. The average FRAIL score, SPPB score, and overall quality of life at baseline were 2.1 (SD 0.9), 7.8 (SD 2.8), and 91.6 (SD 13.1), respectively. Characteristics of participants in the 3 groups were similar, except for the quality of life (<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>2,385</sub>=3.26, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=.04) and arm curl test scores (<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>2,382</sub>=5.47, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=.005). As suggested by the mean PASE scores, all 3 groups were considered as having low activity levels in general [<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. No reports of adverse events that led to death, hospitalization, or medical attendance were received by the end of the program.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><title> Baseline characteristics of the study population (n=390).</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E<xref rid="T1_FN4" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref>-R<xref rid="T1_FN3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref>-A<xref rid="T1_FN2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref> group (n=132)</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A-R-E group (n=124)</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R-A-E group (n=134)</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">F</italic>/&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup> (df)</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years), mean (SD)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.5 (7.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.9 (7.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.2 (7.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">F</italic>=0.25 (2, 387)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.78</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender, female, n (%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">106 (80.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97 (78.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105 (78.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>=0.21 (2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.90</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Education, n (%)</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>=6.15 (6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.41</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003; No formal education</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79 (59.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66 (53.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73 (54.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003; Primary school</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (20.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (23.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (22.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003; Junior middle school</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (8.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (8.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (14.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003; High school or above</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (11.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (15.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Marital status, n (%)</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>=2.04 (4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.73</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003; Married</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47 (35.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 (40.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 (33.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003; Widowed</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75 (56.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62 (50.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79 (59.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003; Others</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (7.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (6.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Living alone</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (28.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (37.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47 (35.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>=2.34 (2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.31</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Frailty status, n (%)</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>=0.70 (2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.70</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003; Prefrail</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80 (60.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80 (64.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80 (59.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003; Frail</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52 (39.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44 (35.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 (40.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5-item FRAIL<xref rid="T1_FN12" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref> scale, mean (SD)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2 (0.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1 (0.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1 (1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">F</italic>=0.27 (2, 387)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.76</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SPPB<xref rid="T1_FN10" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>e</sup></xref>, mean (SD)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (2.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5 (2.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.8 (2.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">F</italic>=1.14 (2, 387)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.32</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WHOQoL-OLD<xref rid="T1_FN11" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>f</sup></xref>, mean (SD)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.5 (12.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.9 (12.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.4 (14.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">F</italic>=3.26 (2, 385)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.04</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grip strength (left hand), mean (SD)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.5 (11.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.6 (12.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (14.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">F</italic>=0.46 (2, 381)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.63</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grip strength (right hand), mean (SD)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.2 (12.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.7 (13)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.7 (14.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">F</italic>=0.06 (2, 382)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.94</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30-s arm curl test, mean (SD)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.1 (4.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.6 (4.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.5 (4.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">F</italic>=5.47 (2, 382)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.005</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2-min step test, mean (SD)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.2 (28.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.3 (28.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.6 (30.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">F</italic>=0.60 (2, 382)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.55</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IADL<xref rid="T1_FN5" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>g</sup></xref>, mean (SD)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.8 (2.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.2 (3.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.2 (2.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">F</italic>=0.99 (2, 385)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.37</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PASE<xref rid="T1_FN7" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>h</sup></xref>, mean (SD)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.6 (41.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.1 (41.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.3 (47.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">F</italic>=0.11 (2, 382)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.90</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LSNS<xref rid="T1_FN6" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>i</sup></xref>, mean (SD)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.1 (9.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.8 (9.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.4 (9.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">F</italic>=0.14 (2, 385)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.87</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI<xref rid="T1_FN9" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>j</sup></xref>, mean (SD)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.3 (4.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.1 (3.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.3 (3.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">F</italic>=0.10 (2, 356)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.91</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PHQ-9<xref rid="T1_FN8" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>k</sup></xref>, mean (SD)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (4.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.8 (4.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3 (4.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">F</italic>=0.86 (2, 384)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.42</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="T1_FN4" fn-type="other"><label>a</label><p>E: lifestyle education.</p></fn><fn id="T1_FN3" fn-type="other"><label>b</label><p>R: resistance training.</p></fn><fn id="T1_FN2" fn-type="other"><label>c</label><p>A: aerobic training.</p></fn><fn id="T1_FN12" fn-type="other"><label>d</label><p>FRAIL: Fatigue, Resistance, Ambulation, Illness, and Loss of weight.</p></fn><fn id="T1_FN10" fn-type="other"><label>e</label><p>SPPB: Short Physical Performance Battery.</p></fn><fn id="T1_FN11" fn-type="other"><label>f</label><p>WHOQoL-OLD: Cantonese version of the World Health Organization Quality of Life &#x02013; Older adults module.</p></fn><fn id="T1_FN5" fn-type="other"><label>g</label><p>IADL: Lawton&#x02019;s Instrumental Activities of Daily Living scale.</p></fn><fn id="T1_FN7" fn-type="other"><label>h</label><p>PASE: Physical Activity Scale for the Elderly.</p></fn><fn id="T1_FN6" fn-type="other"><label>i</label><p>LSNS: Lubben Social Network Scale.</p></fn><fn id="T1_FN9" fn-type="other"><label>j</label><p>PSQI: Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index.</p></fn><fn id="T1_FN8" fn-type="other"><label>k</label><p>PHQ-9: Patient Health Questionnaire-9.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3-2"><title>Change in Frailty Status</title><p>We found a substantial overall improvement in frailty status (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref> and <xref rid="SAP5" ref-type="supplementary-material">MultimediaAppendices 5 </xref><xref rid="SAP6" ref-type="supplementary-material"> 6</xref>), both in terms of achieving a robust status and an improved status (from frail to prefrail/robust or from prefrail to robust).</p><fig position="float" id="F2" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><title>Percentage of older participants obtaining robust status at the follow-up assessment time points. Absolute numbers are reported in Multimedia Appendix 5. The intervention only targeted older adults with frailty and prefrailty, and thus no robust participants were included at baseline. Asterisks (*) indicate a further significant increase (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x0003c;.05) in the proportion of robust status from 6 months. A: aerobic training; E: lifestyle education; R: resistance training.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="aging-v8-e65636-g002" position="float"/></fig><p>In the prefrail sample, 35.8% (76/212) of all participants became robust after 6 months. The proportion of robust participants increased to 51.0% (98/192) at 12 months and remained stable (83/164, 50.6%) at 18 months. In the frail sample, 17.9% (24/134) of participants became robust at 6 months. The proportion increased to 20.4% (23/113) at 12 months and continually increased to 25% (25/100) at 18 months. In terms of within-group changes, participants from the E-R-A group and A-R-E group (prefrail sample only) continued to have a significant improvement in frailty beyond 6 months (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref> and <xref rid="SAP5" ref-type="supplementary-material">MultimediaAppendices 5 </xref><xref rid="SAP6" ref-type="supplementary-material"> 6</xref>). Although a smaller proportion of participants with frailty obtained a robust status within the first 6 months, the majority of them progressed to prefrailty.</p></sec><sec id="s3-3"><title>Aerobic Versus Resistance Training: 6-Month Outcomes</title><p>As shown in <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, there was an overall improvement (having a significant time effect) in FRAIL score (coefficient &#x02212;0.81, 95% CI &#x02212;1.09 to &#x02013;0.52; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x0003c;.001), IADL (coefficient 0.48, 95% CI 0.04 to 0.91; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=.03), PSQI (coefficient &#x02212;0.74, 95% CI &#x02212;1.34 to &#x02013;0.14; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=.02), and PHQ-9 (coefficient &#x02212;0.98, 95% CI &#x02212;1.81 to &#x02212;0.16; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=.02) in all groups over 6 months, suggesting that participants had improved frailty and functional and psychological outcomes.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><title>Summary of time and group &#x000d7; time interaction effects on primary and secondary outcomes (whole sample).</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th colspan="2" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">Baseline to 6 months</th><th colspan="2" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">Baseline to 12 months</th><th colspan="2" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">Baseline to 18 months</th></tr><tr><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coefficient (95% or 99% CI)</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coefficient (95% or 99% CI)</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coefficient (95% or 99% CI)</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" colspan="7" rowspan="1"><bold>5-item FRAIL</bold><xref rid="T2_FN11" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref>
<bold>scale</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Time effect</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.81 (&#x02212;1.09 to &#x02212;0.52)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;.001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.10 (&#x02212;1.40 to &#x02212;0.80)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;.001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.06 (&#x02212;1.36 to &#x02212;0.75)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;A-R-E<xref rid="T2_FN2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref> group &#x000d7; time</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07 (&#x02212;0.35 to 0.49)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.68</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16 (&#x02212;0.27 to 0.60)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.33</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16 (&#x02212;0.29 to 0.62)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.35</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;R-A-E group &#x000d7; time</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.02 (&#x02212;0.42 to 0.38)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.90</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25 (&#x02212;0.17 to 0.67)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.13</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20 (&#x02212;0.23 to 0.64)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.23</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<bold>SPPB</bold>
<xref rid="T2_FN8" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>c</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Time effect</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.22 (&#x02212;0.66 to 0.31)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.20</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.61 (&#x02212;1.08 to &#x02212;0.15)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.003</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.64 (&#x02212;1.11 to &#x02212;0.16)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.002</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;A-R-E group &#x000d7; time</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15 (&#x02212;0.51 to 0.80)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.57</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27 (&#x02212;0.41 to 0.95)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.31</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34 (&#x02212;0.25 to 1.34)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.22</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;R-A-E group &#x000d7; time</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03 (&#x02212;0.60 to 0.65)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.91</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04 (&#x02212;0.62 to 0.70)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.88</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.22 (&#x02212;0.90 to 0.46)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.52</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<bold>WHOQoL-OLD</bold>
<xref rid="T2_FN9" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>d</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Time effect</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22 (&#x02212;2.62 to 3.07)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.84</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.66 (&#x02212;1.31 to 4.63)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.15</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52 (&#x02212;2.53 to 3.57)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.66</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;A-R-E group &#x000d7; time</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.34 (&#x02212;0.85 to 7.52)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.04</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.73 (&#x02212;5.10 to 3.63)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.66</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.85 (&#x02212;2.75 to 6.45)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.30</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;R-A-E group &#x000d7; time</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.23 (1.21 to 9.24)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.77 (&#x02212;0.47 to 8.01)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.02</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.13 (&#x02212;0.23 to 8.49)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.02</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<bold>Grip strength (left)</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Time effect</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2.81 (&#x02212;4.31 to &#x02212;1.30)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;.001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.22 (&#x02212;1.81 to 1.36)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.78</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not reported</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;A-R-E group &#x000d7; time</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.99 (0.76 to 5.23)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.009</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20 (&#x02212;2.14 to 2.54)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.87</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;R-A-E group &#x000d7; time</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.21 (0.63 to 4.36)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.04</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.55 (&#x02212;2.82 to 1.72)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.63</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<bold>Grip strength (right)</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Time effect</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;3.12 (&#x02212;4.62, to &#x02013;1.63)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;.001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.12 (&#x02212;1.12 to 0.45)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.16</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not reported</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;A-R-E group &#x000d7; time</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.75 (1.54 to 5.97)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06 (&#x02212;1.25 to 3.38)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.37</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;R-A-E group &#x000d7; time</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.29 (0.16 to 4.42)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.04</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.50 (&#x02212;2.75 to 1.75)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.66</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<bold>30-s arm curl</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Time effect</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.77 (&#x02212;0.78 to 0.63)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.83</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12 (&#x02212;0.62 to 0.85)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.76</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12 (&#x02212;0.63 to 0.88)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.75</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;A-R-E group &#x000d7; time</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.42 (0.39 to 2.46)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.007</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.46 (0.38 to 2.54)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.008</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52 (&#x02212;0.63 to 1.66)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.38</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;R-A-E group &#x000d7; time</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.11 (0.12 to 2.11)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.03</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03 (&#x02212;0.02 to 2.09)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.054</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65 (&#x02212;0.44 to 1.73)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.24</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<bold>2-min step test</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Time effect</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.75 (&#x02212;1.81 to 7.31)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.24</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.46 (3.69 to 13.24)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.99 (2.99 to 12.85)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.002</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;A-R-E group &#x000d7; time</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.51 (&#x02212;1.23 to 12.25)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.11</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.49 (&#x02212;4.57 to 9.54)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.49</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10 (&#x02212;6.32 to 8.52)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.77</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;R-A-E group &#x000d7; time</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.38 (&#x02212;5.09 to 7.84)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.68</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;3.17 (&#x02212;9.99 to 3.66)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.36</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;4.46 (&#x02212;11.50 to 2.59)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.22</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<bold>IADL</bold>
<xref rid="T2_FN3" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>e</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Time effect</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48 (0.04 to 0.91)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.03</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64 (0.19 to 1.09)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.006</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74 (0.27 to 1.20)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.002</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;A-R-E group &#x000d7; time</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.32 (&#x02212;0.95 to 0.32)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.33</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.77 (&#x02212;1.43 to &#x02212;0.11)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.02</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.88 (&#x02212;1.59 to &#x02212;0.18)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.01</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;R-A-E group &#x000d7; time</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.38 (&#x02212;0.99 to 0.24)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.23</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.09 (&#x02212;1.74 to 0.45)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.22 (&#x02212;1.89 to &#x02212;0.56)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<bold>PASE</bold>
<xref rid="T2_FN7" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>h</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Time effect</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.25 (&#x02212;6.18 to 10.67)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.60</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.11 (&#x02212;5.67 to 11.89)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.49</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.99 (2.06 to 19.90)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.02</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;A-R-E group &#x000d7; time</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.65 (&#x02212;7.70 to 17.00)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.46</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37 (&#x02212;12.45 to 13.19)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.96</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;3.29 (&#x02212;16.72 to 10.14)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.63</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;R-A-E group &#x000d7; time</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.32 (&#x02212;9.59 to 14.24)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.70</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88 (&#x02212;11.60 to 13.36)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.89</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;3.00 (&#x02212;15.76 to 9.77)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.64</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<bold>LSNS</bold>
<xref rid="T2_FN4" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>f</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Time effect</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89 (&#x02212;0.66 to 2.44)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.26</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.43 (0.81 to 4.06)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.003</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.39 (&#x02212;0.27 to 3.06)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.10</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;A-R-E group &#x000d7; time</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.73 (&#x02212;4.02 to 055)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.14</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.82 (&#x02212;4.21 to 0.56)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.13</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.68 (&#x02212;3.20 to 1.83)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.60</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;R-A-E group &#x000d7; time</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.48 (&#x02212;2.67 to 1.72)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.67</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.28 (&#x02212;3.60 to 1.04)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.28</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23 (&#x02212;2.15 to 2.62)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.85</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<bold>PSQI</bold>
<xref rid="T2_FN5" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>g</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Time effect</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.74 (&#x02212;1.34 to &#x02212;0.14)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.02</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.96 (&#x02212;1.59 to &#x02212;0.33)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.003</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17 (&#x02212;0.48 to 0.81)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.61</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;A-R-E group &#x000d7; time</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47 (&#x02212;0.43 to 1.36)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.31</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.16 (0.23 to 2.09)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.02</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.31 (&#x02212;1.29 to 0.68)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.54</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;R-A-E group &#x000d7; time</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58 (&#x02212;0.28 to 1.44)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.19</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94 (0.03 to 1.85)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.04</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64 (&#x02212;0.29 to 1.57)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.18</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<bold>PHQ-9</bold>
<xref rid="T2_FN6" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>i</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Time effect</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.98 (&#x02212;1.81 to &#x02212;0.16)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.02</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.14 (&#x02212;2.00 to &#x02212;0.27)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.01</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.19 (&#x02212;2.38 to &#x02212;0.61)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;A-R-E group &#x000d7; time</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43 (&#x02212;0.79 to 1.65)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.49</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49 (&#x02212;0.78 to 1.76)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.45</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69 (&#x02212;0.65 to 2.03)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.31</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;R-A-E group &#x000d7; time</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.34 (0.17 to 2.52)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.02</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.51 (0.27 to 2.75)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.02</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.14 (0.87 to 3.41)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="T2_FN11" fn-type="other"><label>a</label><p>FRAIL: Fatigue, Resistance, Ambulation, Illness, and Loss of weight.</p></fn><fn id="T2_FN2" fn-type="other"><label>b</label><p>A: aerobic training, R: resistance training, E: lifestyle education.</p></fn><fn id="T2_FN8" fn-type="other"><label>c</label><p>SPPB: Short Physical Performance Battery.</p></fn><fn id="T2_FN9" fn-type="other"><label>d</label><p>WHOQoL-OLD: Cantonese version of the World Health Organization Quality of Life - Older adults module.</p></fn><fn id="T2_FN3" fn-type="other"><label>e</label><p>IADL: Lawton&#x02019;s Instrumental Activities of Daily Living scale.</p></fn><fn id="T2_FN4" fn-type="other"><label>f</label><p>LSNS: Lubben Social Network Scale.</p></fn><fn id="T2_FN5" fn-type="other"><label>g</label><p>PASE: Physical Activity Scale for the Elderly.</p></fn><fn id="T2_FN7" fn-type="other"><label>h</label><p>PSQI: Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index.</p></fn><fn id="T2_FN6" fn-type="other"><label>i</label><p>PHQ-9: Patient Health Questionnaire-9.</p></fn><fn id="T2_FN10" fn-type="other"><label>j</label><p>Measurements reporting 99% CI: 5-item FRAIL scale, SPPB, and WHOQoL-OLD. All other scales used 95% CI.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>At 6 months, participants with resistance training (R-A-E group) compared with those with lifestyle education (E-R-A group) had greater improvement in quality of life (interaction coefficient 5.23, 99% CI 1.21 to 9.24; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x0003c;.001) but not in FRAIL score and SPPB. Similar findings were observed in the prefrail subsample (<xref rid="SAP7" ref-type="supplementary-material">Multimedia Appendix 7</xref>). Aerobic training (A-R-E group) was not different from lifestyle education in the primary outcomes.</p><p>For the secondary outcomes, both aerobic training (A-R-E group) and resistance training (R-A-E group) performed better in several fitness outcomes than the E-R-A group. The A-R-E group was associated with greater improvement in left hand grip strength (interaction coefficient 2.99, 95% CI 0.76 to 5.23; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=.009), right hand grip strength (interaction coefficient 3.75, 95% CI 1.54 to 5.97; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=.001), and the arm curl test (interaction coefficient 1.42, 95% CI 0.39 to 2.46; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=.007) than lifestyle education (E-R-A group). The R-A-E group was also associated with greater improvement in the 3 outcomes (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). The A-R-E and R-A-E groups did not differ from the E-R-A group in all other nonfitness measures including the 2-minute step test, IADL, PASE, LSNS, and PSQI over 6 months. The R-A-E group had a significantly higher level of PHQ-9 scores (interaction coefficient 1.34, 95% CI 0.17 to 2.52; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=.02). Results of the subgroup analysis by frailty status were summarized in <xref rid="SAP7" ref-type="supplementary-material">MultimediaAppendices 7 </xref><xref rid="SAP8" ref-type="supplementary-material"> 8</xref>, whereas results of the subgroup analysis by gender were summarized in <xref rid="SAP9" ref-type="supplementary-material">MultimediaAppendices 9 </xref><xref rid="SAP10" ref-type="supplementary-material"> 10</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s3-4"><title>Aerobic and Resistance Training: The Order Effect (12-Month Outcomes)</title><p>To compare the order effect, we also compared the R-A-E group with the A-R-E group (reference group) on 12-month outcomes (<xref rid="SAP11" ref-type="supplementary-material">Multimedia Appendix 11</xref>). The 2 groups did not differ in all outcomes except that the R-A-E group was associated with greater improvement in WHOQoL-OLD (interaction coefficient 4.50, 95% CI 0.12 to 8.88; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=.008). The result was similar when the analysis was applied in the prefrail subsample. Participants with frailty in the R-A-E group achieved significantly fewer steps in the 2-minute step test compared to their counterparts in the A-R-E group at 12 months (interaction coefficient &#x02212;12.48, 95% CI &#x02212;24.78 to &#x02212;0.18; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=.047).</p><p>In sum, the findings suggested that the order of aerobic and resistance training did not have an impact on fitness outcome at 12 months, although some preliminary data suggested that undergoing resistance training before aerobic training might improve quality of life.</p></sec><sec id="s3-5"><title>Maintenance of Exercise Effect and Habit Formation</title><p>The A-R-E and R-A-E groups did not receive a physical intervention between 12 and 18 months. If exercise effects were maintained, we expected to observe gains to be maintained by the end of the study. As shown in <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, the improvement in WHOQoL-OLD seemed to be maintained at 18 months in these 2 groups compared to the E-R-A group but the <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value did not reach the .01 threshold (interaction coefficient 4.13, 95% CI &#x02212;0.23 to 8.49; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=.02).</p><p>However, the gains in IADL appeared to reduce in the A-R-E (interaction coefficient &#x02212;0.88, 95% CI &#x02212;1.59 to &#x02212;0.18; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=.013) and the R-A-E groups (interaction coefficient &#x02212;1.22, 95% CI &#x02212;1.89 to &#x02212;0.56; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x0003c;.001) and also for PHQ-9 in the R-A-E group (interaction coefficient 2.14, 95% CI 0.87 to 3.41; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=.001).</p><p>Neither aerobic training nor resistance training improved PASE at 6 months compared to lifestyle education. We observed a significant time effect on PASE over 18 months in the whole sample (coefficient 10.99, 95% CI 2.06 to 19.90; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=.02) and in the frail subsample (coefficient 14.6, 95% CI 1.39 to 27.81; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=.03), indicating that combined exercise and lifestyle education, regardless of intervention sequence, might improve individuals&#x02019; level of physical activity.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="s4-1"><title>Principal Findings</title><p>This study examined the effectiveness of both aerobic training and resistance training using a sequential cluster randomized controlled trial design, which enabled us to examine how these physical activity interventions and their sequence might influence frailty outcomes. Although lifestyle education was initially added as a comparator intervention, our findings have demonstrated that the 18-month intervention combining lifestyle education and physical interventions is a viable strategy to address frailty and is health-promoting. The frailty score improved across groups, providing further evidence that physical frailty is reversible. Our study also produced a few other key findings. Aerobic training or resistance training tended to improve fitness performance but was not superior to an intensive lifestyle education program in addressing frailty. It is possible that 6 months of resistance training followed by another 6 months of aerobic training might be better at improving quality of life. Although the overall improvement in frailty outcome was maintained over 18 months, IADL and PHQ-9 appeared to worsen over the post&#x02013;physical intervention period. We observed a small increase in the level of physical activity over 18 months, but its relation to the formation of exercise habits and an active lifestyle is yet to be determined.</p><p>Despite physical activity intervention being the most widely studied and recommended approach for the management of frailty [<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], we found that a single-mode exercise program (aerobic or resistance) for 6 months was no better than lifestyle education in addressing frailty. The findings coincided with a recent systematic review suggesting that physical activity intervention, when compared with an active control intervention, was not associated with a significant reduction in frailty [<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. We found that the administration of 2 physical interventions in sequence did not further improve frailty scores but participants were able to maintain the gain accrued over the first 6 months. The 3 study arms approximated a multifaceted intervention that incorporated physical, psychosocial, and educational components. There were a few multifaceted studies [<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26-28</xref>] but cross-study comparison was difficult due to their different designs and the lack of frailty as an outcome. The Hatoyama Cohort Study [<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] found that resistance exercise in combination with nutritional education and psychosocial programs for 3 months successfully reduced the prevalence of frailty by 24%. Our study further added that the sequence of intervention components, if not delivered concurrently, might not make a significant difference. Nonetheless, older adults with frailty may find the program more acceptable if they have greater control over the sequence of interventions.</p><p>We added to the literature that psychosocial intervention might be complementary to physical activity intervention for the management of frailty. Following the lifestyle education program, the subsequent addition of physical intervention appeared to generate further gain. Participants from the E-R-A group were observed to have continued improvement in frailty outcomes after switching from lifestyle education to resistance training. There were only a few known studies to date exploring the effectiveness of psychosocial interventions on frailty. A Swedish study evaluated a 4-week senior group program similar to our lifestyle education program, which introduced and discussed various healthy lifestyle topics [<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. The senior group program had no impact on frailty outcomes, but it was reported to delay activities of daily living deterioration. Our lifestyle education program was more intensive in terms of frequency and duration than the senior group program. Further studies may explore whether shorter or longer combined interventions may make a difference in frailty outcomes.</p><p>Since frailty is suggested to result from cumulative declines in multiple physiologic systems [<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>], it is not surprising that interventions targeting different systems may yield similar positive results (ie, the equifinality principle). There might be common factors across the intervention approaches that mitigate frailty, such as social support from peers (exercise coaches and retired nurses). In our study, all 3 intervention components encouraged social engagement through the group sessions and peer coaching. Previous studies have suggested that social support might directly or indirectly contribute to higher levels of physical activity in older adults [<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30-32</xref>] and could therefore be health-promoting and lead to a healthier lifestyle. Further studies should include a comparison group without social influence and a measure of perceived social support to allow for an estimation of its impact on frailty and quality of life. Future studies may also include measures of other psychological mediators such as self-efficacy, enjoyment, and the use of behavioral and cognitive processes [<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>] for mediation analyses.</p><p>The subgroup analysis by frailty status showed that participants with frailty appeared to have a greater magnitude of reduction in FRAIL score, further demonstrating that frailty is a modifiable condition. The frail subgroup also had consistently reported increased social engagement and some reduction in depressive symptoms over 18 months. Some improvements in physical fitness were observed but may not have been sustained beyond the active intervention period. The results echoed our hypothesis that active physical or psychosocial interventions might enhance social support for older adults at high risk of vulnerability and social isolation [<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Physical activity guidelines should recommend older adults with frailty to engage in moderate-intensity exercise regularly [<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. The design of physical activity interventions should incorporate social or group elements that enhance social learning and reinforcement. With a sample predominantly comprised of female older adults (~80%), the results for the female subsample were largely consistent with those in the full sample. There may be a lack of power to detect significant intervention effects in the male subsample. These results should be interpreted with caution.</p><p>We observed a significant increase in the level of physical activity over 18 months, probably due in part to the significant change within the frail subsample. No evidence showed that participants with prefrailty increased their level of physical activity after interventions. It might take as long as 18 months to observe an overall increase in the level of physical activity. The potential of exercise and lifestyle interventions to modify long-term exercise habits remains unclear. It is common to observe a relapse pattern in health behavior once an intervention has ended [<xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Program effectiveness and acceptability are equally important as pain and discomfort associated with physical activity could be an obstacle to engaging in further physical activity [<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. In addition, a physical intervention combined with smartphone-assisted e-reminders, an activity tracker, and e-coaching may help habit formation [<xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. It is equally important to implement strategies to discourage unhealthy habits simultaneously. It is possible that our lifestyle education program helped increase participants&#x02019; awareness about unhealthy habits and alternative healthy options in the environment. Further investigation to determine the optimal form of intervention(s) that best maintains exercise habit formation is warranted.</p><p>We consider the delivery of exercise interventions by peer coaches to be the key to long-term scalability and sustainability in the context of population aging. More research is needed to formally evaluate the sustainability and cost-effectiveness of the intervention model. Future research should consider the productive aging component for engaging retired older adults in productive activities, task shifting from health professionals to more available human resources (ie, peer coaches), and the implications of an increased number of robust older people in the community. Health care utilization associated with a positive change in frailty outcomes has not been explored, but it is worth further investigation.</p></sec><sec id="s4-2"><title>Limitations</title><p>Due to the complexity of the study design, we lacked a care-as-usual comparator group. The active control group only abstained from physical intervention in the first 6 months. Therefore, we were unable to evaluate the effectiveness of physical activity interventions for 12 months compared with an active control intervention. Further multifaceted intervention studies may include both psychoeducational components in combination with physical interventions. An accelerometer-based measure of physical activity level may be better than a self-reported one in estimating the effect of a physical intervention on habit formation [<xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Similar to other physical intervention programs, the generalization of results might be limited by attrition bias and a predominantly female sample. This program was tested in a densely populated community. This setting may enhance the viability and cost-effectiveness of delivering both group and home sessions via peer coaches. Adaptations may be needed if the model is applied in other contexts, for example, in rural areas, which will require a separate evaluation of feasibility and effectiveness.</p></sec><sec id="s4-3"><title>Conclusions</title><p>In contrast to most previous trials, we attempted to address frailty by examining physical interventions in comparison with a novel comparator, that is, lifestyle education. Both tested physical interventions and lifestyle education were effective in improving frailty status. A simultaneous improvement in quality of life was observed. Participants with frailty appeared to benefit beyond a frailty outcome. Despite the positive findings, the impact of the interventions on exercise habit formation is yet to be investigated.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>Supplementary material</title><supplementary-material id="SAP1" position="float" content-type="local-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/65636</object-id><label>Multimedia Appendix 1</label><caption><title>Program design.</title></caption><media xlink:href="aging-v8-e65636-s001.docx" xlink:title="DOCX File, 36 KB" id="d67e1891" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SAP2" position="float" content-type="local-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/65636</object-id><label>Multimedia Appendix 2</label><caption><title>Additional information about study methods and attendance.</title></caption><media xlink:href="aging-v8-e65636-s002.docx" xlink:title="DOCX File, 32 KB" id="d67e1898" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SAP3" position="float" content-type="local-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/65636</object-id><label>Multimedia Appendix 3</label><caption><title>Components and sequence of the 3-arm trial.</title></caption><media xlink:href="aging-v8-e65636-s003.png" xlink:title="PNG File, 72 KB" id="d67e1905" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SAP4" position="float" content-type="local-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/65636</object-id><label>Multimedia Appendix 4</label><caption><title>Schedule for each intervention component.</title></caption><media xlink:href="aging-v8-e65636-s004.docx" xlink:title="DOCX File, 33 KB" id="d67e1912" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SAP5" position="float" content-type="local-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/65636</object-id><label>Multimedia Appendix 5</label><caption><title>Percentage of participants achieving robust status (from prefrail or frail to robust).</title></caption><media xlink:href="aging-v8-e65636-s005.docx" xlink:title="DOCX File, 37 KB" id="d67e1919" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SAP6" position="float" content-type="local-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/65636</object-id><label>Multimedia Appendix 6</label><caption><title>Percentage of older participants obtaining an improved frailty status at the follow-up assessment time points. The intervention only targeted older adults with prefrailty and frailty, and thus no robust participants were included at baseline. Asterisks (*) indicate a further significant increase (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x0003c;.05) in the proportion of improved frailty status from 6 months.</title></caption><media xlink:href="aging-v8-e65636-s006.png" xlink:title="PNG File, 1647 KB" id="d67e1930" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SAP7" position="float" content-type="local-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/65636</object-id><label>Multimedia Appendix 7</label><caption><title>Summary of time and group &#x000d7; time interaction effects on primary and secondary outcomes (participants with prefrailty only).</title></caption><media xlink:href="aging-v8-e65636-s007.docx" xlink:title="DOCX File, 41 KB" id="d67e1937" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SAP8" position="float" content-type="local-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/65636</object-id><label>Multimedia Appendix 8</label><caption><title>Summary of time and group &#x000d7; time interaction effects on primary and secondary outcomes (participants with frailty only).</title></caption><media xlink:href="aging-v8-e65636-s008.docx" xlink:title="DOCX File, 43 KB" id="d67e1944" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SAP9" position="float" content-type="local-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/65636</object-id><label>Multimedia Appendix 9</label><caption><title>Summary of time and group &#x000d7; time interaction effects on primary and secondary outcomes (female participants only).</title></caption><media xlink:href="aging-v8-e65636-s009.docx" xlink:title="DOCX File, 44 KB" id="d67e1951" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SAP10" position="float" content-type="local-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/65636</object-id><label>Multimedia Appendix 10</label><caption><title>Summary of time and group &#x000d7; time interaction effects on primary and secondary outcomes (male participants only).</title></caption><media xlink:href="aging-v8-e65636-s010.docx" xlink:title="DOCX File, 44 KB" id="d67e1958" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SAP11" position="float" content-type="local-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/65636</object-id><label>Multimedia Appendix 11</label><caption><title>Comparison of outcomes between the R-A-E group and A-R-E group (reference) at the 12-month follow-up.</title></caption><media xlink:href="aging-v8-e65636-s011.docx" xlink:title="DOCX File, 36 KB" id="d67e1966" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SCHL1" position="float" content-type="local-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/65636</object-id><label>Checklist 1</label><caption><title>CONSORT checklist. CONSORT: Consolidated Standards of Reporting Trials.</title></caption><media xlink:href="aging-v8-e65636-s012.pdf" xlink:title="PDF File, 100 KB" id="d67e1973" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>This work was supported by theSimon KY Lee Foundation, Hong Kong. The funding body had no role in the design, methods, subject recruitment, data collection, analysis, or preparation of the paper.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Authors&#x02019; Contributions:</bold> All authors, led by GHYW and TYSL, developed the study concept and design. MT, TYSL, and GHYW were directly involved in activities related to the acquisition of data. JYMT, HL, and GHYW conducted data analysis, and all authors participated in the interpretation of the data. JYMT, HL, and GHYW drafted the manuscript. All authors critically revised the manuscript for important intellectual content.</p></fn></fn-group><notes><def-list><title>Abbreviations</title><def-item><term>A-R-E</term><def><p>aerobic training - resistance training - lifestyle education</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>E-R-A</term><def><p>lifestyle education - resistance training - aerobic training</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FRAIL</term><def><p> Fatigue, Resistance, Ambulation, Illnesses, and Loss of weight</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IADL</term><def><p>Instrumental Activities of Daily Living</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LSNS</term><def><p>Lubben Social Network Scale</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PASE</term><def><p>Physical Activity Scale for the Elderly</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PHQ-9</term><def><p>Patient Health Questionnaire-9</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PSQI</term><def><p>Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>R-A-E</term><def><p>resistance training - aerobic training - lifestyle education</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SPPB</term><def><p>Short Physical Performance Battery</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>WHOQoL-OLD</term><def><p>World Health Organization Quality of Life &#x02013; Older adults module</p></def></def-item></def-list></notes><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fried</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tangen</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Walston</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Frailty in older adults: evidence for a phenotype</article-title><source>J Gerontol A Biol Sci Med Sci</source><month>Mar</month><year>2001</year><volume>56</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>M146</fpage><lpage>56</lpage><comment>doi</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gerona/56.3.m146</pub-id><comment>Medline</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11253156</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Morley</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Malmstrom</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>A simple frailty questionnaire (FRAIL) predicts outcomes in middle aged African Americans</article-title><source>J Nutr Health Aging</source><month>07</month><year>2012</year><volume>16</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>601</fpage><lpage>608</lpage><comment>doi</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12603-012-0084-2</pub-id><comment>Medline</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22836700</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>O&#x02019;Caoimh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sezgin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>O&#x02019;Donovan</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Prevalence of frailty in 62 countries across the world: a systematic review and meta-analysis of population-level studies</article-title><source>Age Ageing</source><month>01</month><day>8</day><year>2021</year><volume>50</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>96</fpage><lpage>104</lpage><comment>doi</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ageing/afaa219</pub-id><comment>Medline</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33068107</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vermeiren</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vella-Azzopardi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Beckw&#x000e9;e</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Frailty and the prediction of negative health outcomes: a meta-analysis</article-title><source>J Am Med Dir Assoc</source><month>Dec</month><day>1</day><year>2016</year><volume>17</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1163</fpage><comment>doi</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jamda.2016.09.010</pub-id><comment>Medline</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27886869</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Merchant</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morley</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Izquierdo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Editorial: Exercise, aging and frailty: guidelines for increasing function</article-title><source>J Nutr Health Aging</source><year>2021</year><volume>25</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>405</fpage><lpage>409</lpage><comment>doi</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12603-021-1590-x</pub-id><comment>Medline</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33786554</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Travers</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Romero-Ortuno</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cooney</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Delaying and reversing frailty: a systematic review of primary care interventions</article-title><source>Br J Gen Pract</source><month>01</month><year>2019</year><volume>69</volume><issue>678</issue><fpage>e61</fpage><lpage>e69</lpage><comment>doi</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3399/bjgp18X700241</pub-id><comment>Medline</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30510094</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>2018 Physical Activity Guidelines Advisory Committee scientific report</article-title><source>Office of Disease Prevention and Health Promotion</source><year>2018</year><comment>URL</comment><ext-link xlink:href="https://health.gov/sites/default/files/2019-09/PAG_Advisory_Committee_Report.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://health.gov/sites/default/files/2019-09/PAG_Advisory_Committee_Report.pdf</ext-link><comment>Accessed</comment><date-in-citation>30-04-2025</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Izquierdo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Merchant</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morley</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>International exercise recommendations in older adults (ICFSR): expert consensus guidelines</article-title><source>J Nutr Health Aging</source><year>2021</year><volume>25</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>824</fpage><lpage>853</lpage><comment>doi</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12603-021-1665-8</pub-id><comment>Medline</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34409961</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>de Labra</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guimaraes-Pinheiro</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maseda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lorenzo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mill&#x000e1;n-Calenti</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Effects of physical exercise interventions in frail older adults: a systematic review of randomized controlled trials</article-title><source>BMC Geriatr</source><month>Dec</month><day>2</day><year>2015</year><volume>15</volume><issue>154</issue><elocation-id>154</elocation-id><comment>doi</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12877-015-0155-4</pub-id><comment>Medline</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26626157</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tseng</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marsh</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Booth</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Strength and aerobic training attenuate muscle wasting and improve resistance to the development of disability with aging</article-title><source>J Gerontol A Biol Sci Med Sci</source><month>Nov</month><year>1995</year><volume>50 Spec No</volume><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>119</lpage><comment>doi</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gerona/50a.special_issue.113</pub-id><comment>Medline</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7493203</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>Report of the strategic review on healthcare manpower planning and professional development</article-title><source>Health Bureau</source><year>2017</year><comment>URL</comment><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.healthbureau.gov.hk/en/press_and_publications/otherinfo/180500_sr/srreport.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.healthbureau.gov.hk/en/press_and_publications/otherinfo/180500_sr/srreport.html</ext-link><comment>Accessed</comment><date-in-citation>30-04-2025</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bandura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Social Learning Theory</source><publisher-name>Prentice-Hall</publisher-name><year>1977</year><comment>ISBN</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="isbn">0138167516</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lally</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Promoting habit formation</article-title><source>Health Psychol Rev</source><month>05</month><year>2013</year><volume>7</volume><issue>sup1</issue><fpage>S137</fpage><lpage>S158</lpage><comment>doi</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/17437199.2011.603640</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Guralnik</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Simonsick</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ferrucci</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>A short physical performance battery assessing lower extremity function: association with self-reported disability and prediction of mortality and nursing home admission</article-title><source>J Gerontol</source><month>Mar</month><year>1994</year><volume>49</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>M85</fpage><lpage>94</lpage><comment>doi</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/geronj/49.2.m85</pub-id><comment>Medline</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8126356</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>The Chinese version of the World Health Organization Quality of Life instrument-older adults module (WHOQOL-OLD): psychometric evaluation</article-title><source>Health Qual Life Outcomes</source><month>Sep</month><day>16</day><year>2013</year><volume>11</volume><issue>156</issue><fpage>24034698</fpage><comment>doi</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1477-7525-11-156</pub-id><comment>Medline</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24034698</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>James</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The 30-second arm curl test as an indicator of upper body strength in older adults [Dissertation]</article-title><publisher-name>California State University</publisher-name><year>1999</year><comment>URL</comment><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.proquest.com/dissertations-theses/30-second-arm-curl-test-as-indicator-upper-body/docview/304580972/se-2" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.proquest.com/dissertations-theses/30-second-arm-curl-test-as-indicator-upper-body/docview/304580972/se-2</ext-link><comment>Accessed</comment><date-in-citation>30-04-2025</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rikli</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Functional fitness normative scores for community-residing older adults, ages 60-94</article-title><source>J Aging Phys Act</source><year>1999</year><volume>7</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>162</fpage><lpage>181</lpage><comment>doi</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1123/japa.7.2.162</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lawton</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brody</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Assessment of older people: self-maintaining and instrumental activities of daily living</article-title><source>Gerontologist</source><year>1969</year><volume>9</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>179</fpage><lpage>186</lpage><comment>Medline</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5349366</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Washburn</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McAuley</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Katula</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mihalko</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Boileau</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The physical activity scale for the elderly (PASE): evidence for validity</article-title><source>J Clin Epidemiol</source><month>07</month><year>1999</year><volume>52</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>643</fpage><lpage>651</lpage><comment>doi</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0895-4356(99)00049-9</pub-id><comment>Medline</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10391658</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Buysse</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>CF</given-names><suffix>3rd</suffix></name>
<name><surname>Monk</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hoch</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yeager</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kupfer</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Quantification of subjective sleep quality in healthy elderly men and women using the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI)</article-title><source>Sleep</source><month>Aug</month><year>1991</year><volume>14</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>331</fpage><lpage>338</lpage><comment>doi</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/14.4.331</pub-id><comment>Medline</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1947597</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lubben</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Blozik</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gillmann</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Performance of an abbreviated version of the Lubben Social Network Scale among three European community-dwelling older adult populations</article-title><source>Gerontologist</source><month>Aug</month><year>2006</year><volume>46</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>503</fpage><lpage>513</lpage><comment>doi</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/geront/46.4.503</pub-id><comment>Medline</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16921004</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kroenke</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Spitzer</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The PHQ-9: validity of a brief depression severity measure</article-title><source>J Gen Intern Med</source><month>Sep</month><year>2001</year><volume>16</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>606</fpage><lpage>613</lpage><comment>doi</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1525-1497.2001.016009606.x</pub-id><comment>Medline</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11556941</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Laddu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Parimi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cauley</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>The association between trajectories of physical activity and all-cause and cause-specific mortality</article-title><source>J Gerontol A Biol Sci Med Sci</source><month>Nov</month><day>10</day><year>2018</year><volume>73</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1708</fpage><lpage>1713</lpage><comment>doi</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gerona/gly037</pub-id><comment>Medline</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29529273</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><article-title>Fit for frailty: consensus best practice guidance for the care of older people living with frailty in community and outpatient settings</article-title><publisher-name>British Geriatrics Society</publisher-name><year>2014</year><comment>URL</comment><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.bgs.org.uk/sites/default/files/content/resources/files/2018-05-14/fff2_short_0.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.bgs.org.uk/sites/default/files/content/resources/files/2018-05-14/fff2_short_0.pdf</ext-link><comment>Accessed</comment><date-in-citation>30-04-2025</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Negm</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thabane</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Management of frailty: a systematic review and network meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials</article-title><source>J Am Med Dir Assoc</source><month>Oct</month><year>2019</year><volume>20</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1190</fpage><lpage>1198</lpage><comment>doi</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jamda.2019.08.009</pub-id><comment>Medline</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31564464</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Woo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Effects of an integrated health education and elastic band resistance training program on physical function and muscle strength in community-dwelling elderly women: Healthy Aging and Happy Aging&#x02009;II study</article-title><source>Geriatr Gerontol Int</source><month>05</month><year>2017</year><volume>17</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>825</fpage><lpage>833</lpage><comment>doi</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ggi.12795</pub-id><comment>Medline</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27138245</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Seino</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nishi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Murayama</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Effects of a multifactorial intervention comprising resistance exercise, nutritional and psychosocial programs on frailty and functional health in community-dwelling older adults: a randomized, controlled, cross-over trial</article-title><source>Geriatr Gerontol Int</source><month>Nov</month><year>2017</year><volume>17</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>2034</fpage><lpage>2045</lpage><comment>doi</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ggi.13016</pub-id><comment>Medline</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28393440</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Spoorenberg</surname><given-names>SLW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wynia</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Uittenbroek</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kremer</surname><given-names>HPH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reijneveld</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Effects of a population-based, person-centred and integrated care service on health, wellbeing and self-management of community-living older adults: a randomised controlled trial on Embrace</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2018</year><volume>13</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>e0190751</elocation-id><comment>doi</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0190751</pub-id><comment>Medline</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29351295</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gustafsson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wilhelmson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eklund</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Health-promoting interventions for persons aged 80 and older are successful in the short term--results from the randomized and three-armed Elderly Persons in the Risk Zone study</article-title><source>J Am Geriatr Soc</source><month>Mar</month><year>2012</year><volume>60</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>447</fpage><lpage>454</lpage><comment>doi</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1532-5415.2011.03861.x</pub-id><comment>Medline</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22409735</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lieber</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moxley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mandl</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Czaja</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Social support and physical activity: does general health matter?</article-title><source>Eur Rev Aging Phys Act</source><month>Jun</month><day>20</day><year>2024</year><volume>21</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>16</elocation-id><comment>doi</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s11556-024-00347-6</pub-id><comment>Medline</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38902616</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Resnick</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Orwig</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Magaziner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wynne</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The effect of social support on exercise behavior in older adults</article-title><source>Clin Nurs Res</source><month>Feb</month><year>2002</year><volume>11</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>52</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><comment>doi</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/105477380201100105</pub-id><comment>Medline</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11845515</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>GSE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moyle</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Burton</surname><given-names>NW</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The relationship between social support for physical activity and physical activity across nine years in adults aged 60-65 years at baseline</article-title><source>Int J Environ Res Public Health</source><month>Mar</month><day>3</day><year>2023</year><volume>20</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>36901538</fpage><comment>doi</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph20054531</pub-id><comment>Medline</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36901538</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marcus</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pate</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Psychosocial mediators of physical activity behavior among adults and children</article-title><source>Am J Prev Med</source><month>Aug</month><year>2002</year><volume>23</volume><issue>2 Suppl</issue><fpage>26</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><comment>doi</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0749-3797(02)00471-3</pub-id><comment>Medline</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12133735</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lindsay Smith</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Banting</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eime</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>O&#x02019;Sullivan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>van Uffelen</surname><given-names>JGZ</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The association between social support and physical activity in older adults: a systematic review</article-title><source>Int J Behav Nutr Phys Act</source><month>Apr</month><day>27</day><year>2017</year><volume>14</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>56</elocation-id><comment>doi</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12966-017-0509-8</pub-id><comment>Medline</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28449673</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Izquierdo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Duque</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morley</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Physical activity guidelines for older people: knowledge gaps and future directions</article-title><source>Lancet Healthy Longev</source><month>Jun</month><year>2021</year><volume>2</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>e380</fpage><lpage>e383</lpage><comment>doi</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2666-7568(21)00079-9</pub-id><comment>Medline</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36098146</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Neal</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Healthy through habit: interventions for initiating &#x00026; maintaining health behavior change</article-title><source>Behavioral Science &#x00026; Policy</source><month>Apr</month><year>2016</year><volume>2</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><comment>doi</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/237946151600200109</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>PSF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>FY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The changes in levels and barriers of physical activity among community-dwelling older adults during and after the fifth wave of COVID-19 outbreak in Hong Kong: repeated random telephone surveys</article-title><source>JMIR Aging</source><month>01</month><day>23</day><year>2023</year><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>e42223</elocation-id><comment>doi</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/42223</pub-id><comment>Medline</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36599172</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kwan</surname><given-names>RY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Effects of an mHealth brisk walking intervention on increasing physical activity in older people with cognitive frailty: pilot randomized controlled trial</article-title><source>JMIR mHealth uHealth</source><month>07</month><day>31</day><year>2020</year><volume>8</volume><issue>7</issue><elocation-id>e16596</elocation-id><comment>doi</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/16596</pub-id><comment>Medline</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32735218</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Valenti</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bonomi</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Westerterp</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Walking as a contributor to physical activity in healthy older adults: 2 week longitudinal study using accelerometry and the doubly labeled water method</article-title><source>JMIR mHealth uHealth</source><month>Jun</month><day>7</day><year>2016</year><volume>4</volume><issue>2</issue><elocation-id>e56</elocation-id><comment>doi</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/mhealth.5445</pub-id><comment>Medline</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27268471</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>