<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39730597</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11681007</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">81539</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-024-81539-z</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Progesterone level in assisted reproductive technology: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>Yee Cherng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hamdan</surname><given-names>Mukhri</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Maheshwari</surname><given-names>Abha</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Cheong</surname><given-names>Ying</given-names></name><address><email>y.cheong@soton.ac.uk</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/02yjksy18</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.415216.5</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0641 6277</institution-id><institution>Complete Fertility, </institution><institution>Princess Anne Hospital, </institution></institution-wrap>Level F, Coxford Road, Southampton, SO16 5YA UK </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/00rzspn62</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.10347.31</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2308 5949</institution-id><institution>Department of Obstetrics and Gynaecology, </institution><institution>Universiti Malaya, </institution></institution-wrap>50603 Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Aberdeen Centre of Reproductive Medicine, Aberdeen, UK </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/01ryk1543</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5491.9</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 9297</institution-id><institution>Human Development and Health Unit, Institute of Life Sciences, Faculty of Medicine, </institution><institution>University of Southampton, </institution></institution-wrap>Southampton, SO16 6YD UK </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>28</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>30826</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>25</day><month>2</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2024</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Elevated progesterone (EP) or inadequate progesterone levels during ART cycle monitoring may lead to cycle cancellations or further progesterone supplementation, but practice varies. It remains controversial whether modifying clinical practice in the presence or absence of EP improves clinical outcomes. This systematic review aims to investigate if progesterone levels at different phases of fresh and frozen ART cycles influence pregnancy outcomes, in particular, that pertaining to day 3 versus day 5 embryo transfers. A systematic search of EMBASE, MEDLINE, CINAHL, PubMed, SCOPUS and Web of Science identified studies from the year 2000. We included studies with women undergoing fresh and frozen IVF/ICSI cycles; with extractable per woman data on pregnancy outcomes where serum progesterone measurement was performed. We excluded interventional studies that influence clinical decisions or studies with donor cycles. The Newcastle Ottawa Scale (NOS) was used to determine the risk of bias. The primary outcome was LBR, and the secondary outcomes were OPR, CPR and MR. PICOS study protocol was used to include non-randomized studies of interventions (NRSI). Analysis was done using RevMan5 and the studies were pooled using the DerSimonian and Laird for random effects meta-analysis. The study was registered with PROSPERO (registration ID CRD42022382423). 64 studies (N&#x02009;=&#x02009;57,988 women) were included. In fresh cycles, there is no evidence that at baseline EP impacts LBR (P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.5&#x000a0;ng/ml, OR 0.76 [95% CI 0.39&#x02013;1.49], 2 studies, N&#x02009;=&#x02009;309) and CPR (P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.5&#x000a0;ng/ml, OR 0.81 [0.38&#x02013;1.71], 2 studies, N&#x02009;=&#x02009;309). EP at ovulation trigger is associated with a lower LBR (P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.0&#x000a0;ng/ml, OR 0.40 [0.23&#x02013;0.69], 2 studies, N&#x02009;=&#x02009;2805) and CPR (P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.0&#x000a0;ng/ml, OR 0.49 [0.42&#x02013;0.58], 3 studies, N&#x02009;=&#x02009;3323; P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.1&#x000a0;ng/ml, OR 0.66 [0.53&#x02013;0.83], 2 studies, N&#x02009;=&#x02009;2444; P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.2&#x000a0;ng/ml, OR 0.61 [0.39&#x02013;0.96], 6 studies, N&#x02009;=&#x02009;844; P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.5&#x000a0;ng/ml, OR 0.37 [0.17&#x02013;0.81], 6 studies, N&#x02009;=&#x02009;13,870; P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;2.0&#x000a0;ng/ml, OR 0.43 [0.31&#x02013;0.59], 3 studies, N&#x02009;=&#x02009;1949) with D3 embryo but not D5 [LBR (P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.5&#x000a0;ng/ml, OR 1.02 [0.74&#x02013;1.39], 3 studies, N&#x02009;=&#x02009;5174) and CPR (P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.5&#x000a0;ng/ml, OR 0.88 [0.67&#x02013;1.14], 6 studies, N&#x02009;=&#x02009;5705)]. We could not meaningfully meta-analyse studies on the day of egg collection in fresh cycles, embryo transfer in fresh cycles, at ovulation trigger or before ovulation in natural FET cycles and FET cycles due to significant study heterogeneity. We acknowledged the limitations on including studies post year 2000 and the exclusion of studies with multiple observations, which may result in inherent publication bias and some confounding factors uncontrolled for. In conclusion, in controlled ovarian stimulation, EP at baseline did not impact on LBR; EP at ovulation trigger is associated with a lower LBR for D3 but not for D5 embryo transfer. In FET cycles, as the studies were heterogeneous, we were unable to combine the data in a meaningful way. This review is sponsored by Complete Fertility and the Ministry of Health, Malaysia.</p><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1038/s41598-024-81539-z.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Assisted reproductive technology</kwd><kwd>Embryo transfer</kwd><kwd>Intracytoplasmic sperm injection</kwd><kwd>In vitro fertilization</kwd><kwd>Pregnancy outcomes</kwd><kwd>Serum progesterone</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Endocrinology</kwd><kwd>Health care</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Ministry of Health Malaysia</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Complete Fertility</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Springer Nature Limited 2024</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Progesterone level can be elevated (EP) (follicular phase or at ovulation trigger) or inadequate (luteal phase), both of which may be linked to reduced pregnancy rates. The optimization of progesterone level is therefore a key focus in clinical practice.</p><p id="Par3">During ovarian stimulation, EP during the follicular phase up to the point of ovulation trigger, is postulated to cause premature advancement of the endometrium, thereby causing uterine embryo asynchrony and affecting endometrial receptivity (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Nevertheless, EP as an entity is critiqued due to methodological challenges in defining what constitutes an &#x02018;optimal&#x02019; progesterone level<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. Previous systematic reviews on EP have reported conflicting results<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. Progesterone supplementation is used in the luteal phase of modified natural and medicated frozen embryo transfer (FET) cycles to ensure a sufficient hormonal environment. However, what constitute an adequate luteal phase progesterone level is also not well defined<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. Current practice now involves blastocyst transfer; day 5 embryos are known to be more robust but studies evaluating the impact of progesterone monitoring do not differentiate day 3 versus day 5 transfers.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Biological basis and possible impact of progesterone monitoring in a fresh ovarian stimulation cycle and frozen embryo transfer cycle. <italic>COS</italic> controlled ovarian stimulation, <italic>D5</italic> day 5, <italic>EP</italic> elevated progesterone, <italic>FET</italic> frozen embryo transfer, <italic>GnRH</italic> gonadotropin-releasing hormone, <italic>LBR</italic> live birth rate, <italic>LH</italic> luteinising hormone, <italic>P4</italic> progesterone, <italic>TVOR</italic> transvaginal oocyte retrieval.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2024_81539_Fig1_HTML" id="d33e266"/></fig></p><p id="Par4">This review aims to investigate if progesterone levels at different phases of fresh and frozen ART cycles influence pregnancy outcomes, in particular, that on cleavage-stage versus blastocyst embryo transfers. The main outcome is live birth rate (LBR). Additional outcome measures are the ongoing pregnancy rate (OPR), clinical pregnancy rate (CPR) and miscarriage rate (MR).</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Search strategy</title><p id="Par5">A systematic search was performed on all published studies in EMBASE, MEDLINE, CINAHL, PubMed, SCOPUS and Web of Science following PRISMA and the MOOSE guidelines (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>) by starting the search after the year 2000. The search from the year 2000 was chosen due to a change of practice in IVF with the introduction of GnRH antagonists. The study was registered with PROSPERO (registration ID CRD42022382423).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>PRISMA flow diagram.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2024_81539_Fig2a_HTML" id="d33e284"/><graphic xlink:href="41598_2024_81539_Fig2b_HTML" id="d33e286"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Selection of studies</title><p id="Par6">The titles and abstracts retrieved were initially screened by two reviewers independently (Y.C.L and M.H.) and the full texts that meet the predefined criteria were examined for compliance with the inclusion criteria. Studies eligible for inclusion were selected. In cases of duplicate publication, the most recent version was selected. Studies that specified reporting per woman data were reported to reduce confounding.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Study protocol PICOS</title><sec id="Sec6"><title>Population</title><p id="Par7">The inclusion criteria included (a) studies on fresh IVF/ICSI cycles or natural/modified natural/medicated FET cycles, (b) controlled ovarian stimulation (COS) with gonadotrophins and GnRH analogues in fresh cycle, or using trigger in modified natural FET cycle, or using hormonal replacement therapy in medicated FET cycle (c) the study provided extractable per woman data on pregnancy outcomes which included live birth rate (LBR), ongoing pregnancy rate (OPR), clinical pregnancy rate (CPR), miscarriage rate (MR) and (d) where serum progesterone was monitored.</p><p id="Par8">The exclusion criteria included (a) any intervention that leads to cycle cancellation or freeze-all embryos in the follicular phase or further progesterone supplementation in the luteal phase of fresh and frozen embryo transfer cycles, (b) studies involving donor cycles, (c) studies without control groups and (d) studies providing per cycle data on pregnancy outcomes. Any intervention in the studies that influence the clinical decision and change the pregnancy outcome is excluded from the review.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Comparisons</title><p id="Par9">We made the following comparisons:<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>(A)</label><p id="Par10">Fresh ovarian stimulation cycle with embryo transfer (ET)<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>i.</label><p id="Par11"> Basal follicular phase comparing EP versus non-elevated progesterone (NEP)</p></list-item><list-item><label>ii.</label><p id="Par12">At ovulation trigger comparing EP versus NEP</p></list-item><list-item><label>iii.</label><p id="Par13">At egg collection comparing EP versus NEP</p></list-item><list-item><label>iv.</label><p id="Par14">Luteal phase comparing adequate versus inadequate progesterone level</p></list-item></list></p></list-item><list-item><label>(B)</label><p id="Par15">Frozen embryo transfer (FET) cycle<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>i.</label><p id="Par16"> Modified natural cycle FET (NC-FET) at trigger comparing EP versus NEP</p></list-item><list-item><label>ii.</label><p id="Par17"> NC-FET: comparing EP versus NEP on the day before ovulation</p></list-item><list-item><label>iii.</label><p id="Par18">Luteal phase comparing adequate versus inadequate progesterone level<list list-type="alpha-lower"><list-item><p id="Par19">Natural cycle with or without progesterone supplementation</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par20"> Medicated FET cycle</p></list-item></list></p></list-item></list></p></list-item></list></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Outcome measures</title><p id="Par21">The primary outcome was LBR and the secondary outcomes were OPR, CPR and MR. The definitions for these outcomes were in accordance with the ICMART glossary<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par22">Comparative pregnancy outcomes were assessed based on the authors&#x02019; predefined progesterone threshold. In studies using multiple threshold ranges, the outcome data were dichotomized based on all the reported thresholds in the individual study. The conversion factor of 3.18 was used to convert units in nmol/l to units ng/ml.</p><p id="Par23">We included results from published cohort or case&#x02013;control studies (retrospective or prospective), and data from randomised control trials (RCT) where EP and NEP were analysed as subgroups. The data for EP and NEP groups in both arms of intervention were pooled together and analysed as cohort studies. Systematic reviews and meta-analyses were included for qualitative and quantitative data where appropriate. The studies were initially analysed together regardless of Day 3 or Day 5 embryos. We then performed subgroup analysis on the studies that measured either Day 3 or Day 5 embryos individually. We did not compare pregnancy outcomes between Day 3 and Day 5 embryos.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Assessment of study quality and data extraction</title><p id="Par24">The Newcastle Ottawa Scale (NOS) was used to determine bias in the non-randomised comparative cohort studies. Each study was judged based on eight items categorised into three domains: the study group selection, the comparability of the groups, and the ascertainment of the outcome of interest. Scores were represented with stars for each quality item and a maximum of nine stars awarded if they fulfilled all the quality items<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>. The Newcastle Ottawa Scale is derived to assess non-randomized controlled trials. We chose NOS as it is one of the most known scales for assessing quality and risk of bias in observational studies. It is easily adaptable and validated for case&#x02013;control and long-term studies, although the authors acknowledge its drawbacks<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par25">Data were extracted by 2 independent reviewers (Y.C.L. and M.H.). Any disagreements were resolved by a third author (Y.C.). Data retrieved included study characteristics and their various outcomes data. Both reviewers counterchecked these extracted data repeatedly. Authors were contacted for further data through email. Data were extracted into RevMan5 for further analysis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Data analysis and assessment of heterogeneity</title><p id="Par26">Data were extracted in 2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;2 tables for dichotomous outcomes. The odds ratio (OR) for dichotomous outcomes with 95% CI for each study were estimated. The estimates were pooled using the DerSimonian and Laird random-effects model, which uses inverse variance weighting for random effects meta-analysis. The random effects model was chosen a priori to pool the results from individual studies given the increased clinical heterogeneity of the population assessed, the wide variation of thresholds adopted by studies, different responder types, different types of protocols, different stages of embryo development transfer and in fresh and frozen cycles with variable outcomes. Meta-analysis was not performed on single studies and studies where progesterone thresholds were too variable for meaningful meta-analysis. A p-value of&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 is considered statistically significant.</p><p id="Par27">We considered whether the clinical and methodological characteristics of the included studies were sufficiently similar for meta-analysis to provide a clinically meaningful summary. Statistical heterogeneity was assessed by the measure of the I<sup>2</sup>. Scores below 50% were considered to represent low or moderate heterogeneity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. The incorporation of a random-effects meta-analysis model involved an assumption that the effects being estimated in the different studies are not identical but follow some distribution.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Rating quality of evidence and strength of evidence (GRADE)</title><p id="Par28">The GRADE tool was used to assess the strength of evidence for significant outcomes. There were four categories of evidence quality based on the overall GRADE scores for each comparison as per the GRADE recommendations (high, moderate, low and very low)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Ethics application</title><p id="Par29">Ethics application was not required for this study.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Results</title><p id="Par30">The systematic search retrieved 7766 titles after removal of duplicates. One hundred eighty-two eligible studies had their full texts reviewed. One hundred five studies met our inclusion criteria and were included into the qualitative meta-analysis. A further forty-one studies that did not report per woman data were excluded, leaving a total of sixty-four eligible studies (N&#x02009;=&#x02009;57,988 women) for quantitative meta-analysis. Study identification and selection process is shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>.</p><p id="Par31">For fresh COS cycle, three studies reported progesterone monitoring during the start of the menstrual cycle, forty-three studies reported monitoring during the day of trigger, three studies reported monitoring during egg collection day and three studies reported monitoring progesterone during the luteal phase. For FET cycles, one study reported monitoring on the day of trigger in modified NC-FET, two studies reported progesterone monitoring in NC-FET on the day before ovulation and nine studies reported monitoring progesterone during luteal phase in natural cycle FET with and without progesterone supplementation and medicated HRT cycle (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref> shows assessment for bias using NOS.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Tables of included studies.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Author/Year</th><th align="left">Country</th><th align="left">Study duration</th><th align="left">Study design</th><th align="left">Type of cycle</th><th align="left">Total number (patient/cycle)</th><th align="left">Threshold/reason for choosing</th><th align="left">Day of ET</th><th align="left">Conclusion</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="9">Fresh COS cycle&#x02014;Basal follicular phase</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Hamdine et al., 2014</td><td align="left">Netherlands</td><td align="left">Mar&#x02019;09 to Jul&#x02019;11</td><td align="left">Prospective</td><td align="left">IVF/ICSI</td><td align="left">158/158</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.5&#x000a0;ng/ml/literature</td><td align="left">Day 3</td><td align="left">LBR, OPR and CPR NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Mahapatro and Radhakrishan, 2017</td><td align="left">India</td><td align="left">Jan&#x02019;13 to Mar&#x02019;14</td><td align="left">Retrospective</td><td align="left">ICSI</td><td align="left">151/151</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.5&#x000a0;ng/ml/literature</td><td align="left">Day 2&#x02013;3</td><td align="left">LBR and CPR NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Mutlu et al., 2017</td><td align="left">Turkey</td><td align="left">Dec&#x02019;14 and Feb&#x02019;16</td><td align="left">Prospective</td><td align="left">ICSI</td><td align="left">464/464</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;0.65&#x000a0;ng/ml/ROC analysis</td><td align="left">Day 2,3 or 5</td><td align="left">Similar OPR and CPR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="9">Fresh COS cycle&#x02014;Pre trigger</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Bosch et al., 2003</td><td align="left">Spain</td><td align="left">NA</td><td align="left">Prospective</td><td align="left">IVF/ICSI</td><td align="left">81/81</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.2&#x000a0;ng/ml/ROC analysis</td><td align="left">Day 3</td><td align="left">CPR &#x02193;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Martinez et al., 2003</td><td align="left">Spain</td><td align="left">Jul&#x02019;2 to Jan&#x02019;03</td><td align="left">Retrospective</td><td align="left">IVF/ICSI</td><td align="left">377/377</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.9&#x000a0;ng/ml/ROC analysis</td><td align="left">Day 2&#x02013;3</td><td align="left">CPR and MR NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Anderson et al., 2006</td><td align="left">Belgium</td><td align="left">Feb&#x02019;04 to Dec&#x02019;04</td><td align="left">RCT</td><td align="left">IVF</td><td align="left">731/731</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;4&#x000a0;nmol/L (1.25&#x000a0;ng/ml)/literature</td><td align="left">Day 3</td><td align="left">COC &#x02191;, OPR &#x02193;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Seow KM et al., 2007</td><td align="left">Taiwan</td><td align="left">Jan&#x02019;03 to Jan&#x02019;05</td><td align="left">Prospective</td><td align="left">IVF/ICSI</td><td align="left">95/95</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;1.2&#x000a0;ng/ml/literature</td><td align="left">Day 2&#x02013;3</td><td align="left">CPR NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Lee F et al., 2008</td><td align="left">China</td><td align="left">Mar&#x02019;03 to Apr&#x02019;07</td><td align="left">Retrospective</td><td align="left">IVF/ICSI</td><td align="left">223/223</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;2.0&#x000a0;ng/ml/arbitrary</td><td align="left">Day 2&#x02013;3</td><td align="left">CPR &#x02193;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Li R et al., 2008</td><td align="left">China</td><td align="left">Jul&#x02019;06 to Dec&#x02019;06</td><td align="left">Prospective</td><td align="left">IVF/ICSI</td><td align="left">251/251</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;3.97&#x000a0;nmol/L (1.25&#x000a0;ng/ml)/sensitivity&#x02013;specificity analysis</td><td align="left">Day 3</td><td align="left">CPR &#x02193; in fresh cycle, CPR NS in FET</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Kili&#x000e7;dag et al., 2009</td><td align="left">Turkey</td><td align="left">Oct&#x02019;04 to May&#x02019;08</td><td align="left">Retrospective</td><td align="left">ICSI</td><td align="left">1045/1045</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.1&#x000a0;ng/ml/sensitivity&#x02013;specificity analysis</td><td align="left">Day 3</td><td align="left">LBR, OPR and CPR &#x02193;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Papanikolaou et al., 2009</td><td align="left">Belgium</td><td align="left">May&#x02019;04 to Feb&#x02019;05</td><td align="left">Prospective</td><td align="left">IVF/ICSI</td><td align="left">482/482</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.5&#x000a0;ng/ml/literature</td><td align="left">Day 3 or 5</td><td align="left">CPR &#x02193; in D3, similar CPR in D5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Rezaee et al., 2009</td><td align="left">Iran</td><td align="left">1&#x000a0;year (2009)</td><td align="left">Prospective</td><td align="left">Fresh cycle</td><td align="left">38/38</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.2&#x000a0;ng/ml/literature</td><td align="left">Day 2</td><td align="left">CPR &#x02191; but NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Seow KM et al., 2010</td><td align="left">Taiwan</td><td align="left">Jun&#x02019;04 to Jun&#x02019;07</td><td align="left">Prospective</td><td align="left">IVF/ICSI</td><td align="left">233/233</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.2&#x000a0;ng/ml/ROC analysis</td><td align="left">Day 3</td><td align="left">CPR &#x02193;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Elgindy, 2011</td><td align="left">Egypt</td><td align="left">Aug&#x02019;08 to Jun&#x02019;10</td><td align="left">Prospective</td><td align="left">ICSI</td><td align="left">240/240</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.5&#x000a0;ng/ml/ROC analysis</td><td align="left">Day 3 or 5</td><td align="left">CPR &#x02193; in Day 3 embryo, CPR NS in day 5 embryo</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Lahoud et al., 2011</td><td align="left">Australia</td><td align="left">Jan&#x02019;03 to Dec&#x02019;03</td><td align="left">Retrospective</td><td align="left">IVF/ICSI</td><td align="left">582/582</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;1.7&#x000a0;ng/ml/arbitrary</td><td align="left">Day 2,3 or 5</td><td align="left">CPR and MR NS, LBR &#x02193; in fresh cycle, similar LBR, CPR and MR in FET</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Yding Anderson et al., 2011</td><td align="left">Denmark</td><td align="left">Aug&#x02019;03 to Nov&#x02019;04</td><td align="left">Secondary data analysis from prospective RCT</td><td align="left">IVF/ICSI</td><td align="left">475/475</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.25&#x000a0;ng/ml/arbitrary</td><td align="left">NA</td><td align="left">Similar CPR</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Huang R et al., 2012</td><td align="left">China</td><td align="left">Jan&#x02019;02, to Dec&#x02019;07</td><td align="left">Retrospective</td><td align="left">IVF/ICSI</td><td align="left">2566/2566</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.2&#x000a0;ng/ml/arbitrary</td><td align="left">Day 3</td><td align="left">LBR &#x02193;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Kyrou et al., 2012</td><td align="left">Belgium</td><td align="left">Oct&#x02019;07 to Dec&#x02019;08</td><td align="left">Prospective</td><td align="left">IVF/ICSI</td><td align="left">207/207</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.5&#x000a0;ng/ml/literature</td><td align="left">NA</td><td align="left">CPR &#x02193;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Papanikolaou et al., 2012</td><td align="left">Greece</td><td align="left">Aug&#x02019;07 to Dec&#x02019;09</td><td align="left">RCT</td><td align="left">IVF/ICSI</td><td align="left">190/190</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.5&#x000a0;ng/ml/literature</td><td align="left">Day 2,3 or 5</td><td align="left">LBR &#x02193;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Peng C et al., 2012</td><td align="left">China</td><td align="left">Jun&#x02019;08 to Feb&#x02019;10</td><td align="left">Retrospective</td><td align="left">IVF</td><td align="left">180/180</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;1.2&#x000a0;ng/ml/literature</td><td align="left">Day 3</td><td align="left">CPR NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Ochsenkuhn et al., 2012</td><td align="left">Germany</td><td align="left">Jan&#x02019;06 to Jan&#x02019;11</td><td align="left">Retrospective</td><td align="left">IVF/ICSI</td><td align="left">2555/2555</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.5&#x000a0;ng/ml/literature</td><td align="left">Day 5</td><td align="left">LBR &#x02193;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Wu Z et al., 2012</td><td align="left">China</td><td align="left">Apr&#x02019;08 to Apr&#x02019;09</td><td align="left">Retrospective</td><td align="left">IVF/ICSI</td><td align="left">2921/2921</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;1.05&#x000a0;ng/ml/literature</td><td align="left">Day 3</td><td align="left"><p>LBR and CPR &#x02193; in fresh cycles,</p><p>CPR NS in FET</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Corti et al., 2013</td><td align="left">Italy</td><td align="left">Jan&#x02019;12 to Dec&#x02019;12</td><td align="left">Retrospective</td><td align="left">IVF/ICSI</td><td align="left">204/204</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.5&#x000a0;ng/ml/literature</td><td align="left">Day 5</td><td align="left">OPR and CPR &#x02193;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Griesinger et al., 2013</td><td align="left">Germany</td><td align="left">NA</td><td align="left">Pooled analysis of 6 RCTs</td><td align="left">IVF/ICSI</td><td align="left">1866/1866</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.5&#x000a0;ng/ml/literature</td><td align="left">Day 3</td><td align="left">OPR &#x02193;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Orvieto et al., 2013</td><td align="left">Israel</td><td align="left">10-year period</td><td align="left">Retrospective</td><td align="left">IVF</td><td align="left">2244/2244</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.5&#x000a0;ng/ml/literature</td><td align="left">NA</td><td align="left">CPR &#x02193;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Papaleo et al., 2014</td><td align="left">Italy</td><td align="left">Aug&#x02019;11 and Jan&#x02019;12</td><td align="left">Retrospective</td><td align="left">IVF/ICSI</td><td align="left">303/303</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.35&#x000a0;ng/ml/ROC analysis</td><td align="left">Day 3</td><td align="left">CPR &#x02193;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Acet et al., 2015</td><td align="left">Turkey</td><td align="left">Nov&#x02019;12 to Feb&#x02019;14</td><td align="left">Retrospective</td><td align="left">IVF/ICSI</td><td align="left">101/101</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;1.3&#x000a0;ng/ml/literature</td><td align="left">Day 5</td><td align="left">similar LBR, CPR and MR</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Huang P et al., 2015</td><td align="left">Taiwan</td><td align="left">Jan&#x02019;10 to Dec&#x02019;12</td><td align="left">Retrospective</td><td align="left">IVF/ICSI</td><td align="left">599/599</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.5&#x000a0;ng/ml/literature</td><td align="left">Day 2,3 or 5</td><td align="left">LBR and CPR &#x02191;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Huang Y et al., 2015</td><td align="left">China</td><td align="left">Jan&#x02019;10 to Oct&#x02019;14</td><td align="left">Retrospective</td><td align="left">IVF/ICSI</td><td align="left">12,010/12,010</td><td align="left">Day 3, P&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;1.5&#x000a0;ng/ml; Day 5 P&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;1.75&#x000a0;ng/ml/arbitrary</td><td align="left">Day 3 or 5</td><td align="left">CPR &#x02193;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Koo et al., 2015</td><td align="left">Korea</td><td align="left">May&#x02019;12 to Jul&#x02019;13</td><td align="left">Prospective</td><td align="left">IVF/ICSI</td><td align="left">200/200</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.9&#x000a0;ng/ml/arbitrary</td><td align="left">Day 3</td><td align="left">CPR &#x02193;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Singh et al., 2015</td><td align="left">India</td><td align="left">Jan&#x02019;12 to Jul&#x02019;14</td><td align="left">Retrospective</td><td align="left">IVF/ICSI</td><td align="left">681/681</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.0&#x000a0;ng/ml/ROC analysis</td><td align="left">Day 3 or 5</td><td align="left">CPR &#x02193;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Tsai Y et al., 2015</td><td align="left">Taiwan</td><td align="left">Jan&#x02019;00 to Dec&#x02019;12</td><td align="left">Retrospective</td><td align="left">IVF/ICSI</td><td align="left">1508/1508</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.94&#x000a0;ng/ml/ROC analysis</td><td align="left">Day 3 or 5</td><td align="left">LBR, OPR and CPR &#x02193;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Demir et al., 2016</td><td align="left">Turkey</td><td align="left">Jan&#x02019;12 to Jun&#x02019;14</td><td align="left">Prospective</td><td align="left">ICSI</td><td align="left">201/201</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;2&#x000a0;ng/ml/arbitrary</td><td align="left">Day 3 or 5</td><td align="left">CPR NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Healy et al., 2016</td><td align="left">USA</td><td align="left">2011 to 2013</td><td align="left">Retrospective</td><td align="left">IVF/ICSI and FET</td><td align="left">608/608</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;2&#x000a0;ng/ml/literature</td><td align="left">Day 3 or 5</td><td align="left">LBR &#x02193; in fresh cycle, LBR similar in FET</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Ashmita et al., 2018</td><td align="left">India</td><td align="left">Jan&#x02019;16 to Dec&#x02019;16</td><td align="left">Prospective</td><td align="left">IVF/ICSI</td><td align="left">235/235</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.5&#x000a0;ng/ml/arbitrary</td><td align="left">Day 3</td><td align="left">CPR &#x02193;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Simon et al., 2019</td><td align="left">France</td><td align="left">Sep&#x02019;12 and Jul&#x02019;17</td><td align="left">Retrospective</td><td align="left">IVF/ICSI</td><td align="left">1399/1399</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.10&#x000a0;ng/ml/arbitrary</td><td align="left">Day 2&#x02013;3</td><td align="left">CPR &#x02193;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Wu et al., 2019</td><td align="left">China</td><td align="left">Jan&#x02019;08 to Mar&#x02019;11</td><td align="left">Retrospective</td><td align="left">IVF/ICSI</td><td align="left">2351/2351</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.0&#x000a0;ng/ml in low ovarian response/arbitrary; P&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;2.0&#x000a0;ng/ml in intermediate ovarian response/arbitrary</td><td align="left">Day 3</td><td align="left">LBR and CPR&#x02193; in low and intermediate ovarian response</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Lee C et al., 2020</td><td align="left">Taiwan</td><td align="left">Feb&#x02019;11 to Oct&#x02019;16</td><td align="left">Retrospective</td><td align="left">IVF/ICSI</td><td align="left">337/337</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.5&#x000a0;ng/ml/literature</td><td align="left">Day 3</td><td align="left">LBR &#x02193;, CPR and MR NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Yu Y et al., 2020</td><td align="left">China</td><td align="left">2013 to 2017</td><td align="left">Secondary analysis of 3 RCTs</td><td align="left">IVF/ICSI and natural cycle/HRT FET</td><td align="left">5137/5137</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.14&#x000a0;ng/ml/ROC analysis</td><td align="left">Day 3 or 5</td><td align="left">LBR and CPR in FET &#x02191; than fresh cycle</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Benmachiche et al., 2021</td><td align="left">Denmark</td><td align="left">2014 to 2016</td><td align="left">Retrospective</td><td align="left">IVF/ICSI</td><td align="left">328/328</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.3&#x000a0;ng/ml/arbitrary</td><td align="left">Day 2&#x02013;3</td><td align="left">CPR and LBR NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Mahran et al., 2021</td><td align="left">Egypt</td><td align="left">Oct&#x02019;16 to May&#x02019;18</td><td align="left">Prospective</td><td align="left">IVF/ICSI</td><td align="left">200/200</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1&#x000a0;ng/ml/ROC analysis</td><td align="left">Day 3 or 5</td><td align="left">CPR NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Mirta et al., 2021</td><td align="left">India</td><td align="left">Jan&#x02019;13 to Jun&#x02019;16</td><td align="left">Retrospective</td><td align="left">IVF/ICSI</td><td align="left">273/273</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.5&#x000a0;ng/ml/literature</td><td align="left">Day 2&#x02013;3 or Day5-6</td><td align="left">CPR and MR NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Yang et al., 2021</td><td align="left">China</td><td align="left">Jun&#x02019;13 and Sep&#x02019;20</td><td align="left">Retrospective</td><td align="left">IVF/ICSI</td><td align="left">1254/1254</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;0.9&#x000a0;ng/ml/ROC analysis</td><td align="left">Day 3 or 5</td><td align="left">LBR, CPR and MR NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Jiang W et al., 2022</td><td align="left">China</td><td align="left">Jan&#x02019;16 to Oct&#x02019;16</td><td align="left">Retrospective</td><td align="left">IVF/ICSI</td><td align="left">2550/2550</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.5&#x000a0;ng/ml/literature</td><td align="left">Day 5</td><td align="left">LBR and CPR &#x02193;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Kong N et al., 2022</td><td align="left">China</td><td align="left">Jan&#x02019;18 to Dec&#x02019;20</td><td align="left">Retrospective</td><td align="left">IVF</td><td align="left">1951/1951</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.5&#x000a0;ng/ml/literature</td><td align="left">Day 3 or 5</td><td align="left">LBR, CPR and MR NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Zhao et al., 2022</td><td align="left">China</td><td align="left">Jan&#x02019;20 to Apr&#x02019;21</td><td align="left">Retrospective</td><td align="left">IVF/ICSI</td><td align="left">455/455</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;1.0&#x000a0;ng/ml/arbitrary</td><td align="left">Day 3</td><td align="left">CPR &#x02193;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="9">Fresh COS cycle&#x02014;Day of transvaginal oocyte retrieval</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Niu Z et al., 2008</td><td align="left">China</td><td align="left">May&#x02019;05 to May&#x02019;07</td><td align="left">NA</td><td align="left">ICSI</td><td align="left">289/289</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;11.7&#x000a0;ng/ml sensitivity&#x02013;specificity analysis</td><td align="left">Day 3</td><td align="left">OPR and CPR NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Nayak et al., 2014</td><td align="left">USA</td><td align="left">Feb&#x02019;10 and May&#x02019;12</td><td align="left">Prospective</td><td align="left">IVF/ICSI</td><td align="left">186/186</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;12&#x000a0;ng/ml/arbitrary</td><td align="left">Day 3</td><td align="left">CPR &#x02193;, MR NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Tulic et al., 2020</td><td align="left">Serbia</td><td align="left">Jan&#x02019;15 to Dec&#x02019;15</td><td align="left">Prospective</td><td align="left">IVF/ICSI</td><td align="left">164/164</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;2&#x000a0;ng/ml/ROC analysis</td><td align="left">Day 2&#x02013;3</td><td align="left">LBR &#x02193;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="9">Fresh COS cycle&#x02014;luteal phase</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Kim et al., 2017</td><td align="left">S. Korea</td><td align="left">NA</td><td align="left">Prospective</td><td align="left">IVF-ET</td><td align="left">148/148</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;25.2&#x000a0;ng/ml (ROC analysis)</td><td align="left">Day 3</td><td align="left">OPR &#x02191;, MR &#x02193;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Thomsen et al., 2018</td><td align="left">Denmark</td><td align="left">May&#x02019;14 to Jun&#x02019;17</td><td align="left">Prospective</td><td align="left">IVF/ICSI-ET</td><td align="left"><p>602/602</p><p>Early luteal phase&#x02014;432</p><p>Mid-luteal phase&#x02014;170</p></td><td align="left"><p>Early luteal phase -</p><p>P&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;18.9&#x000a0;ng/ml; P&#x02009;=&#x02009;18.9 -31.4&#x000a0;ng/ml; P&#x02009;=&#x02009;31.8&#x02013;125.8&#x000a0;ng/ml; P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;125.8&#x000a0;ng/ml</p><p>Mid-luteal phase -</p><p>P&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;47.2&#x000a0;ng/ml; P&#x02009;=&#x02009;47.2&#x02013;78.6&#x000a0;ng/ml;</p><p>P&#x02009;=&#x02009;78.6&#x02013;125.8&#x000a0;ng/ml; P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;125.8&#x000a0;ng/ml</p></td><td align="left">Day 2,3 or 5</td><td align="left">Optimal chance of pregnancy P&#x02009;=&#x02009;60&#x02013;100&#x000a0;nmol/L (early luteal phase) and P&#x02009;=&#x02009;150- 250&#x000a0;nmol/L (mid-luteal phase)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Netter et al., 2019</td><td align="left">France</td><td align="left">Jul&#x02019;17 and Jun&#x02019;18</td><td align="left">Retrospective</td><td align="left">IVF/ICSI-ET</td><td align="left">242/242</td><td align="left"><p>P&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;36.1&#x000a0;ng/ml</p><p>P&#x02009;=&#x02009;36.1&#x02013;79.2&#x000a0;ng/ml</p><p>P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;79.2&#x000a0;ng/ml</p></td><td align="left">Day 2&#x02013;3</td><td align="left">LBR &#x02191; when P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;252&#x000a0;nmol/L</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="9">FET cycle&#x02014;day of trigger in modified FET cycle</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Groenewoud et al., 2017</td><td align="left">Netherlands</td><td align="left">Part of &#x0201c;ANTARTICA&#x0201d; trial</td><td align="left">Secondary analysis of RCT</td><td align="left">Modified NC FET</td><td align="left">271/271</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.47&#x000a0;ng/ml/ROC analysis</td><td align="left">Day 3 or 5</td><td align="left">LBR NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="9">FET cycle&#x02014;at day before ovulation</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Lee VC et al., 2014</td><td align="left">China</td><td align="left">Jan&#x02019;06 and Dec&#x02019;11</td><td align="left">Retrospective</td><td align="left">NC FET</td><td align="left">610/610</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.57&#x000a0;ng/ml arbitrary</td><td align="left">Day 3</td><td align="left">OPR and CPR NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Wu D et al., 2022</td><td align="left">China</td><td align="left">Jan&#x02019;18 to Apr&#x02019;20</td><td align="left">Retrospective</td><td align="left">NC FET</td><td align="left">1159/1159</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.0&#x000a0;ng/ml</td><td align="left">Day 3 or 5</td><td align="left"><p>LBR NS, CPR &#x02191;, MR NS in day 3</p><p>LBR, CPR and MR NS in day 5</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="9">FET cycle&#x02014;luteal phase</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Akaeda et al., 2019</td><td align="left">Japan</td><td align="left">Sep&#x02019;10 to Sep&#x02019;15</td><td align="left">Retrospective</td><td align="left">HRT FET</td><td align="left">123/123</td><td align="left"><p>P&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;5&#x000a0;ng/ml; P&#x02009;=&#x02009;5&#x02013;9.9&#x000a0;ng/ml</p><p>P&#x02009;=&#x02009;10&#x02013;14.9&#x000a0;ng/ml; P&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;15&#x000a0;ng/ml</p></td><td align="left">Day 2,3 or 5</td><td align="left">Optimal chance of pregnancy P&#x02009;=&#x02009;5-15&#x000a0;ng/ml</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Boynukalin et al., 2019</td><td align="left">Turkey</td><td align="left">Mar&#x02019;18 to Aug&#x02019;18</td><td align="left">Prospective</td><td align="left">HRT FET</td><td align="left">168/168</td><td align="left"><p>P&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;13.6&#x000a0;ng/ml; P&#x02009;=&#x02009;13.6&#x02013;24.3&#x000a0;ng/ml</p><p>P&#x02009;=&#x02009;24.4&#x02013;53.2&#x000a0;ng/ml; P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;53.2&#x000a0;ng/ml</p></td><td align="left">Day 5</td><td align="left">OPR &#x02191;, MR &#x02193;when P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;13.6&#x000a0;ng/ml</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Alsbjerg et al., 2020</td><td align="left">Denmark</td><td align="left">Mar&#x02019;18 and Apr&#x02019;19</td><td align="left">Prospective</td><td align="left">HRT FET</td><td align="left">239/239</td><td align="left"><p>P&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;8.8&#x000a0;ng/ml; P&#x02009;=&#x02009;8.8&#x02013;14.2&#x000a0;ng/ml</p><p>P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;14.2&#x000a0;ng/ml</p></td><td align="left">Day 5&#x02013;6</td><td align="left">OPR, MR NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Liu and Wu, 2020</td><td align="left">China</td><td align="left">Jan&#x02019;15 to Dec&#x02019;18</td><td align="left">Retrospective</td><td align="left">HRT FET</td><td align="left">856/262 (only IM group)</td><td align="left">P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;13.15&#x000a0;ng/ml (arbitrary)</td><td align="left">Day 2&#x02013;3</td><td align="left">LBR NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Polat et al., 2020</td><td align="left">Turkey</td><td align="left">Oct&#x02019;17 to Oct&#x02019;19</td><td align="left">Retrospective</td><td align="left">HRT FET</td><td align="left">475/475</td><td align="left"><p>PV only:</p><p>P&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;8.75&#x000a0;ng/ml; P&#x02009;=&#x02009;8.76&#x02013;12.94&#x000a0;ng/ml; P&#x02009;=&#x02009;12.95&#x02013;20.42&#x000a0;ng/ml; P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;20.42&#x000a0;ng/ml</p><p>PV&#x02009;+&#x02009;IM:</p><p>P&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;11.75&#x000a0;ng/ml; P&#x02009;=&#x02009;11.76&#x02013;19.86&#x000a0;ng/ml; P&#x02009;=&#x02009;19.87&#x02013;31.79&#x000a0;ng/ml; P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;31.79&#x000a0;ng/ml</p></td><td align="left">Day 5&#x02013;6</td><td align="left">No correlation between serum P level and OPR, CPR or MR</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Shiba et al., 2021</td><td align="left">Japan</td><td align="left">Dec&#x02019;16 to Dec&#x02019;17</td><td align="left">Secondary analysis of RCT</td><td align="left">HRT FET</td><td align="left">235/235</td><td align="left"><p>P&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;7.8&#x000a0;ng/ml; P&#x02009;=&#x02009;7.8&#x02013;10.8&#x000a0;ng/ml</p><p>P&#x02009;=&#x02009;10.8&#x02013;13.7&#x000a0;ng/ml; P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;13.7&#x000a0;ng/ml</p></td><td align="left">Day 3 or 5</td><td align="left">LBR, CPR and MR NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Alyasin et al., 2021</td><td align="left">Iran</td><td align="left">Feb&#x02019;19 and Feb&#x02019;20</td><td align="left">Prospective</td><td align="left">HRT FET</td><td align="left">258/258</td><td align="left"><p>P&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;19&#x000a0;ng/ml; P&#x02009;=&#x02009;19&#x02013;29&#x000a0;ng/ml</p><p>P&#x02009;=&#x02009;29&#x02013;49&#x000a0;ng/ml; P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;49&#x000a0;ng/ml</p></td><td align="left">Day 5</td><td align="left">LBR and CPR significantly lower in 4th quartile, MR NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Maignien et al., 2022</td><td align="left">France</td><td align="left">Jan&#x02019;19 and Mar&#x02019;20</td><td align="left">Retrospective</td><td align="left">HRT FET</td><td align="left">915/915</td><td align="left">&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;9.8&#x000a0;ng/ml (previous study)</td><td align="left">Day 5</td><td align="left">LBR &#x02193;, CPR NS and MR &#x02191;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Melo et al., 2022</td><td align="left">UK</td><td align="left">January 2020</td><td align="left">Prospective</td><td align="left">NC FET/HRT FET</td><td align="left">402/402</td><td align="left">&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;7.8&#x000a0;ng/ml (10th centile)</td><td align="left">Day 5</td><td align="left">LBR&#x02191;, CPR &#x02191; and MR &#x02193; when P4 increasing trend</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Table showing characteristics of included studies with their progesterone threshold/range and the summary of pregnancy outcomes reported in each studies.</p><p><italic>COS</italic> controlled ovarian stimulation, <italic>CPR</italic> clinical pregnancy rate, <italic>ET</italic> embryo transfer, <italic>EP</italic> elevated progesterone, <italic>FET</italic> frozen embryo transfer, <italic>HRT</italic> hormone replacement therapy, <italic>ICSI</italic> intracytoplasmic sperm injection, <italic>IM</italic> intramuscular, <italic>IVF</italic> in vitro fertilization, <italic>LBR</italic> live birth rate, <italic>MR</italic> miscarriage rate, <italic>NC</italic> natural cycle, <italic>NEP</italic> non-elevated progesterone, <italic>NS</italic> non-significant, <italic>OPR</italic> ongoing pregnancy rate, <italic>P/P4</italic> progesterone, <italic>RCT</italic> randomized-controlled trial, <italic>TVOR</italic> transvaginal oocyte retrieval.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><sec id="Sec14"><title>Study characteristics</title><sec id="Sec15"><title>Fresh ovarian stimulation cycle with ET</title><sec id="Sec16"><title>i. At basal follicular phase</title><p id="Par32">Three studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup> reported progesterone monitoring in this category. Serum progesterone was measured on day 2 of the menstrual cycle. Two thresholds were identified, P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.65&#x000a0;ng/ml and P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.5&#x000a0;ng/ml. Two studies reported using D3 embryos<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup> and one study reported both D3 and D5 embryos<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup> (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>ii. At day of ovulation trigger</title><p id="Par33">Forty-three studies had progesterone monitoring in this category<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup>. The trigger used were HCG or agonist trigger. The progesterone threshold ranged from 0.9 to 2.0&#x000a0;ng/ml. Twenty-one studies reported using D3 embryos<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup>, four studies reported using D5 embryos<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref></sup>, eighteen studies reported using both D3 and D5 embryos<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup> and three studies did not specify the stages of embryo used<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup> (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>iii. At egg collection</title><p id="Par34">Three studies reported progesterone monitoring in this category<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref></sup>. The progesterone threshold level used ranged from 2 to 12&#x000a0;ng/ml. All three studies reported using D3 embryos (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>iv. At luteal phase</title><p id="Par35">Three studies reported progesterone monitoring in this category<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref></sup>. The timing of serum progesterone measurements varied widely from the day of ET (two studies)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref></sup> and after ET (one study)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref></sup>. Two studies used vaginal suppositories<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref></sup> and one study used oral progesterone<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref></sup>. One study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref></sup> reported a single progesterone threshold level (&#x0003c;&#x02009;25.2&#x000a0;ng/ml) and the other two studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref></sup> reported progesterone level in ranges (&#x0003c;&#x02009;115&#x000a0;nmol/L, 115&#x02013;252&#x000a0;nmol/L and &#x0003e;&#x02009;252&#x000a0;nmol/L<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref></sup>; 10th/50th/90th percentile for early luteal phase and 25th/50th/75th percentile in mid luteal phase<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref></sup> ). Two studies reported the use of D3 embryos<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref></sup> and one study reported using both D3 and D5 embryos<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref></sup> (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>FET cycle</title><sec id="Sec21"><title>i. At ovulation trigger in modified NC-FET cycle</title><p id="Par36">One study reported EP at ovulation trigger<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref></sup>. The progesterone threshold level was &#x0003e;&#x02009;1.47&#x000a0;ng/ml (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>ii. Before ovulation in NC-FET cycle</title><p id="Par37">Two studies reported EP in this category<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref></sup>, and ovulation was determined by either monitoring of LH surge or when the collapse of the dominant follicle was observed during transvaginal scan. The progesterone threshold levels were &#x0003e;&#x02009;1.0&#x000a0;ng/ml and &#x0003e;&#x02009;1.57&#x000a0;ng/ml. One study reported the use of D3 embryos<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref></sup> and the other study reported using both D3 and D5 embryos<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref></sup> (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title>iii. At luteal phase</title><p id="Par38">Nine studies reported progesterone monitoring in this category<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref></sup>. All the studies apart from one<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref></sup> were medicated FET cycles. No studies reported progesterone monitoring in natural FET cycle with or without progesterone supplementation. Melo et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref></sup> included women from natural, and medicated FET cycles. The timing of serum progesterone measurements varied widely from the day of ET (seven studies)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref></sup> and after ET (two studies)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref></sup>. Three studies used vaginal suppositories<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref></sup>, two studies used intramuscular injections<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref></sup> and four studies used a combination of progesterone support<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref></sup>. Three studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref></sup> reported single progesterone threshold level (&#x0003c;&#x02009;7.8&#x000a0;ng/ml, &#x0003c;&#x02009;9.8&#x000a0;ng/ml and &#x0003c;&#x02009;13.15&#x000a0;ng/ml) and the remaining six studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref></sup> reported progesterone value according to quartiles or percentiles. One study reported the use of D3 embryos<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref></sup>, six studies reported using D5 embryos<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref></sup> and two studies reported using both D3 and D5 embryos<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref></sup> (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec24"><title>Outcomes: fresh ovarian stimulation cycle with ET</title><sec id="Sec25"><title>A. At basal follicular phase</title><p id="Par39">There was no difference in LBR in the EP compared to the NEP at threshold level &#x0003e;&#x02009;1.5&#x000a0;ng/ml, (OR 0.76, 95% CI 0.39&#x02013;1.49, I<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0%, 2 studies, N&#x02009;=&#x02009;309, very low quality) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>EP vs NEP at basal follicular phase, outcome: LBR and CPR. Forest plot of comparison between EP group and NEP group on LBR and CPR at basal follicular phase in fresh COS cycle. <italic>COS</italic> controlled ovarian stimulation, <italic>CPR</italic> clinical pregnancy rate, <italic>EP</italic> elevated progesterone, <italic>LBR</italic> live birth rate, <italic>NEP</italic> non-elevated progesterone.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2024_81539_Fig3_HTML" id="d33e2210"/></fig></p><p id="Par40">Three studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup> reported CPR over two different threshold levels (&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.65&#x000a0;ng/ml and&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.5&#x000a0;ng/ml). There was no difference in CPR in the EP compared to the NEP (P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.65&#x000a0;ng/ml, OR 1.41, 95% CI 0.93&#x02013;2.13, 1 study, N&#x02009;=&#x02009;464; P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.5&#x000a0;ng/ml, OR 0.81, 95% CI 0.38-1.71, I<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;23%, 2 studies, N&#x02009;=&#x02009;309, very low quality) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).</p><p id="Par41">We were unable to meta-analyse OPR and MR in a meaningful way as they are single studies. Data from single studies were summarised in Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec26"><title>B. At day of ovulation trigger</title><p id="Par42">Seventeen studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup> reported LBR. The threshold levels ranged between &#x0003e;&#x02009;0.9&#x000a0;ng/ml to &#x0003e;&#x02009;2.0&#x000a0;ng/ml. EP on the day of trigger was associated with decreased LBR across 3 threshold levels (P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.0&#x000a0;ng/ml, OR 0.40, 95% CI 0.23&#x02013;0.69, I<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;48%, 2 studies, N&#x02009;=&#x02009;2805, very low quality; P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.1&#x000a0;ng/ml: OR 0.70, 95% CI 0.53&#x02013;0.93, I<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;42%, 2 studies, N&#x02009;=&#x02009;3186, very low quality; P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;2.0&#x000a0;ng/ml: OR 0.37, 95% CI 0.24-0.58, I<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0%, 2 studies, N&#x02009;=&#x02009;2257, very low quality) and no difference in LBR at 2 thresholds (P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.3&#x000a0;ng/ml, OR 0.89, 95% CI 0.56&#x02013;1.41, I<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0%, 2 studies, N&#x02009;=&#x02009;429, very low quality; P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.5&#x000a0;ng/ml: OR 0.83, 95% CI 0.66-1.05, I<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;52%, 6 studies, N&#x02009;=&#x02009;8170, very low quality) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>a).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>(<bold>a</bold>) EP vs NEP at ovulation trigger, outcome: LBR. (<bold>b</bold>) EP vs NEP at ovulation trigger, outcome: OPR. (<bold>c</bold>) EP vs NEP at ovulation trigger, outcome: CPR. (<bold>d</bold>) EP vs NEP at day of ovulation trigger, outcome: MR. (<bold>a</bold>&#x02013;<bold>d</bold>) Forest plot of comparison between EP group and NEP group on LBR, OPR, CPR and MR at day of ovulation trigger in fresh COS cycle. <italic>COS</italic> controlled ovarian stimulation, <italic>CPR</italic> clinical pregnancy rate, <italic>EP</italic> elevated progesterone, <italic>Intermediate R</italic> intermediate ovarian response, <italic>LBR</italic> live birth rate, <italic>Low R</italic> low ovarian response, <italic>MR</italic> miscarriage rate, <italic>NEP</italic> non-elevated progesterone, <italic>OPR</italic> ongoing pregnancy rate. (<bold>e</bold>) EP vs NEP at day of ovulation trigger (Day 3 embryo), outcome: LBR. (<bold>f</bold>) EP vs NEP at day of ovulation trigger (Day 3 embryo), outcome: CPR. (<bold>e</bold>,<bold>f</bold>) Subgroup analysis on Day 3 embryo, Forest plot of comparison between EP group and NEP group on LBR and CPR at day of ovulation trigger in fresh COS cycle. <italic>COS</italic> controlled ovarian stimulation, <italic>CPR</italic> clinical pregnancy rate, <italic>EP</italic> elevated progesterone, <italic>LBR</italic> live birth rate, <italic>Low R</italic> low responder, <italic>NEP</italic> non-elevated progesterone. (<bold>g</bold>) EP vs NEP at day of ovulation trigger (Day 5 embryo), outcome: LBR and CPR. Subgroup analysis on Day 5 embryo, Forest plot of comparison between EP group and NEP group on LBR and CPR at day of ovulation trigger in fresh COS cycle. <italic>COS</italic> controlled ovarian stimulation, <italic>CPR</italic> clinical pregnancy rate, <italic>EP</italic> elevated progesterone, <italic>LBR</italic> live birth rate, <italic>NEP</italic> non-elevated progesterone.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2024_81539_Fig4a_HTML" id="d33e2401"/><graphic xlink:href="41598_2024_81539_Fig4b_HTML" id="d33e2403"/><graphic xlink:href="41598_2024_81539_Fig4c_HTML" id="d33e2405"/><graphic xlink:href="41598_2024_81539_Fig4d_HTML" id="d33e2407"/><graphic xlink:href="41598_2024_81539_Fig4e_HTML" id="d33e2409"/></fig></p><p id="Par43">Five studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup> reported OPR. The threshold levels ranged between &#x0003e;&#x02009;1.1 to &#x0003e;&#x02009;1.9&#x000a0;ng/ml. Elevated progesterone level on the day of trigger was associated with decreased OPR in P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.5&#x000a0;ng/ml compared to those with NEP (OR 0.61, 95% CI 0.44&#x02013;0.84, I<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0%, 2 studies, N&#x02009;=&#x02009;2070, very low quality) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>b).</p><p id="Par44">Forty studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup> reported CPR. The threshold levels ranged between &#x0003e;&#x02009;0.9 to &#x0003e;&#x02009;2.0&#x000a0;ng/ml. EP on the day of trigger was associated with decreased CPR across 4 threshold levels: P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.0&#x000a0;ng/ml; P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.1&#x000a0;ng/ml; P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.5&#x000a0;ng/ml and P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;2.0&#x000a0;ng/ml (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>c) and no difference in CPR over 4 thresholds: P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.9&#x000a0;ng/ml; P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.2&#x000a0;ng/ml; P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.3&#x000a0;ng/ml; P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.7&#x000a0;ng/ml.</p><p id="Par45">Nine studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup> reported MR. The threshold levels ranged between&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.9 to &#x0003e;&#x02009;1.7&#x000a0;ng/ml. There was no difference in MR in EP compared to NEP across all threshold levels: P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.9&#x000a0;ng/ml and P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.5&#x000a0;ng/ml (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>d). Data from single studies were summarised in Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec27"><title>Subgroup analysis on Day 3 embryo at ovulation trigger</title><p id="Par46">When we analysed studies which reported on only D3 embryos, there was a decreased LBR at threshold level&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.0&#x000a0;ng/ml (OR 0.40, 95% CI 0.23&#x02013;0.69, I<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;48%, 2 studies, N&#x02009;=&#x02009;2805, low quality) and no difference in LBR at &#x0003e;&#x02009;1.5&#x000a0;ng/ml (OR 0.69, 95% CI 0.46&#x02013;1.05, I<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;19%, 2 studies, N&#x02009;=&#x02009;867, low quality) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>e). There was a decreased CPR at threshold levels (P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.0&#x000a0;ng/ml; OR 0.49, 95% CI 0.42&#x02013;0.58, I<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3%, 3 studies, N&#x02009;=&#x02009;3323, very low quality; P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.1&#x000a0;ng/ml; OR 0.66, 95% CI 0.53&#x02013;0.83, I<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0%, 2 studies, N&#x02009;=&#x02009;2444, low quality; P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.2&#x000a0;ng/ml; OR 0.61, 95% CI 0.39&#x02013;0.96, I<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;49%, 6 studies, N&#x02009;=&#x02009;844, very low quality; P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.5&#x000a0;ng/ml; OR 0.37, 95% CI 0.17&#x02013;0.81, I<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;93%, 6 studies, N&#x02009;=&#x02009;13,870, moderate quality; P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;2.0&#x000a0;ng/ml; OR 0.43, 95% CI 0.31&#x02013;0.59, I<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0%, 3 studies, N&#x02009;=&#x02009;1949, very low quality) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>f) except at threshold levels &#x0003e;&#x02009;0.9&#x000a0;ng/ml and &#x0003e;&#x02009;1.3&#x000a0;ng/ml.</p></sec><sec id="Sec28"><title>Subgroup analysis on Day 5 embryo at ovulation trigger</title><p id="Par47">When we analysed studies which reported on only D5 embryos, there was no difference in LBR (P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.5&#x000a0;ng/ml; OR 1.02, 95% CI 0.74&#x02013;1.39, I<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;55%, 3 studies, N&#x02009;=&#x02009;5174, very low quality) and CPR (P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.5&#x000a0;ng/ml; OR 0.88, 95% CI 0.67&#x02013;1.14, I<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;50%, 6 studies, N&#x02009;=&#x02009;5705, very low quality) between EP and NEP groups (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>g).</p><sec id="Sec29"><title>C. At egg collection</title><p id="Par48">One study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref></sup> reported LBR at threshold level &#x0003e;&#x02009;2&#x000a0;ng/ml; one study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup> reported OPR at threshold level &#x0003e;&#x02009;11.7&#x000a0;ng/ml; three studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref></sup> reported CPR at different threshold levels &#x0003e;&#x02009;2&#x000a0;ng/ml, &#x0003e;&#x02009;11.7&#x000a0;ng/ml and &#x0003e;&#x02009;12&#x000a0;ng/ml; two studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref></sup> reported MR at threshold levels &#x0003e;&#x02009;2&#x000a0;ng/ml and &#x0003e;&#x02009;12&#x000a0;ng/ml. Data from single studies were summarised in Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec30"><title>D. Luteal phase</title><p id="Par49">Two studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref></sup> reported LBR at threshold value &#x0003c;&#x02009;18.9&#x000a0;ng/ml, &#x0003c;&#x02009;31.4&#x000a0;ng/ml, &#x0003c;&#x02009;125.8&#x000a0;ng/ml, &#x0003c;&#x02009;47.2&#x000a0;ng/, &#x0003c;&#x02009;78.6&#x000a0;ng/ml, &#x0003c;&#x02009;125.8&#x000a0;ng/ml, &#x0003c;&#x02009;36.1&#x000a0;ng/ml and &#x0003c;&#x02009;79.2&#x000a0;ng/ml. No studies reported on OPR, three studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref></sup> reported CPR and MR. The threshold value used were &#x0003c;&#x02009;18.9&#x000a0;ng/ml, &#x0003c;&#x02009;31.4&#x000a0;ng/ml, &#x0003c;&#x02009;125.8&#x000a0;ng/ml, &#x0003c;&#x02009;25.2&#x000a0;ng/ml, &#x0003c;&#x02009;47.2&#x000a0;ng/ml, &#x0003c;&#x02009;78.6&#x000a0;ng/ml, &#x0003c;&#x02009;125.8&#x000a0;ng/ml, &#x0003c;&#x02009;36.1&#x000a0;ng/ml and &#x0003c;&#x02009;79.2&#x000a0;ng/ml (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). Data from various threshold values were summarised in Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Inadequate vs adequate P during luteal phase of fresh COS cycle; outcome: LBR, CPR and MR. Forest plot of comparison on single studies between adequate progesterone group and inadequate progesterone group on LBR, CPR and MR during luteal phase in fresh COS cycle. <italic>CPR</italic> clinical pregnancy rate, <italic>LBR</italic> live birth rate, <italic>MR</italic> miscarriage rate, <italic>P</italic> progesterone.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2024_81539_Fig5_HTML" id="d33e2615"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec31"><title>Outcomes: FET cycle</title><sec id="Sec32"><title>A. Before ovulation in a natural FET cycle</title><p id="Par50">One study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref></sup> reported LBR at threshold level &#x0003e;&#x02009;1.0&#x000a0;ng/ml; one study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref></sup> reported OPR at threshold level &#x0003e;&#x02009;1.57&#x000a0;ng/ml; two studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref></sup> reported CPR and MR at threshold levels &#x0003e;&#x02009;1.0&#x000a0;ng/ml and &#x0003e;&#x02009;1.57&#x000a0;ng/ml. (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec33"><title>B. Luteal phase</title><p id="Par51">In medicated FET cycles, four studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref></sup> reported on LBR, three studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref></sup> reported on OPR, seven studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref></sup> reported on CPR and six studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref></sup> reported on MR at various threshold values (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). There were no similarities between the threshold values used and wide variation of the timing of progesterone measurement. Data from various threshold values were summarised in Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref>. In both natural cycle and medicated FET cycle, Melo et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref></sup> reported LBR, CPR and MR as summarised in Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S6</xref>.<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Inadequate vs adequate P during luteal phase of medicated FET cycle; outcome: LBR, OPR, CPR and MR. Forest plot of comparison on single studies between adequate progesterone group and inadequate progesterone group on LBR, OPR, CPR and MR during luteal phase in medicated FET cycle. <italic>CPR</italic> clinical pregnancy rate, <italic>FET</italic> frozen embryo transfer, <italic>LBR</italic> live birth rate, <italic>MR</italic> miscarriage rate, OPR ongoing pregnancy rate<italic>,&#x000a0;P</italic> progesterone.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2024_81539_Fig6_HTML" id="d33e2726"/></fig></p></sec></sec></sec></sec><sec id="Sec34"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="Sec35"><title>Main findings</title><p id="Par52">We set to examine whether serum progesterone level at different stages of the treatment impact on the outcomes. In controlled ovarian stimulation cycle with fresh embryo transfer, elevated progesterone at baseline did not impact on LBR/CPR. EP on the day of ovulation trigger in all studies (both D3 and D5) is associated with a decreased LBR/OPR/CPR and no significant difference in miscarriage. However, in a subgroup analysis, EP at ovulation trigger is associated with a lower LBR/CPR when D3 embryos were transferred. EP did not impact LBR/CPR when D5 embryos were transferred. There were insufficient studies to allow meaningful analysis for EP on the day of oocyte retrieval and on the day of embryo transfer.</p><p id="Par53">In FET cycles, as the studies were heterogeneous with various threshold levels used and timing of serum progesterone monitoring, we were unable to combine the data in a meaningful way to give a definitive answer.</p><p id="Par54">We have provided a summary of our results in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>.<fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Summary of pregnancy outcomes. A summary of pregnancy outcomes according to different timing of progesterone monitoring at different threshold levels. <italic>CPR</italic> clinical pregnancy rate, <italic>EP</italic> elevated progesterone, <italic>FET</italic> frozen embryo transfer, <italic>LBR</italic> live birth rate, <italic>MR</italic> miscarriage rate, <italic>NEP</italic> non-elevated progesterone, <italic>OPR</italic> ongoing pregnancy rate.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2024_81539_Fig7_HTML" id="d33e2769"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec36"><title>Meaning of the findings</title><p id="Par55">Whilst multiple theories exist to explain why EP in COS is harmful, the real mechanism is unknown. Recent data suggests that after the hCG trigger, progesterone levels peak from day 2 to 4&#x000a0;days after egg retrieval, at a level 10 times higher than natural cycles and several fold higher than levels achieved with luteal phase support, and the progesterone levels fall rapidly (in hours) after the peak<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref></sup>. One possible explanation for the harmful impact of EP may be related to the transient detrimental impact of acute progesterone withdrawal on the endometrium<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref></sup>, an event salvageable to an extent with progesterone replacement<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref></sup>; the latter theoretically having more impact on day 3 rather than day 5 embryos as the endometrium recovers. Another explanation of our findings may simply relate to the more robust nature of the blastocyst. Even after introducing the freeze-all strategy after a cycle of elevated progesterone, twenty-one studies evaluated the effect of elevated progesterone in ART cycles with nineteen studies using cleavage-stage embryos and twelve studies using blastocyst embryo transfer.</p><p id="Par56">Hence findings must be viewed with caution.</p></sec><sec id="Sec37"><title>Strength of this review</title><p id="Par57">This systematic review with meta-analysis examined the impact of serum progesterone measurement in all the phases of ART in fresh and frozen cycles. The strength of this systematic review is the inclusion of a large number of studies (64 studies, N&#x02009;=&#x02009;57,988 women) and the fact that we only included studies analysing data per woman rather than per cycle, which reduces confounding. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first systematic review looking at progesterone elevation at different stages of cycle and a subgroup analysis based on day 3 and day 5 embryos.</p></sec><sec id="Sec38"><title>Limitations</title><p id="Par58">The limitation of this review is that the included studies were observational studies and thus are subjected to confounding and prone to bias. Studies which are non-English and studies with multiple observations were also excluded. The included studies also exhibit increased clinical heterogeneity given the wide variation of thresholds adopted by studies with different types of responders, protocols, stages of embryo development transfer and in fresh and frozen cycles with variable outcomes; we are unable to perform meta-analysis in a meaningful way for several of our comparisons. Attempts were made to contact authors for their raw data, however we did not have any response.</p><p id="Par59">We acknowledged the limitations on including studies post year 2000 and the exclusion of studies with multiple observations, which may result in inherent publication bias and some confounding factors uncontrolled for.</p></sec><sec id="Sec39"><title>Comparison with existing meta-analyses</title><p id="Par60">One meta-analysis examined serum progesterone levels at baseline<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>, which reported a 15% reduction of OPR in women with EP. However, interventional studies were included, in which the initiation of COS was delayed until progesterone was normalised. In contrast, our current meta-analysis included studies that started the COS regardless of the progesterone level at baseline. We found similar LBR in both groups.</p><p id="Par61">Three meta-analyses evaluated the association of EP on the day of HCG trigger<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. Venetis et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup> found no association between EP and CPR, whilst Kolibianakis et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup> reported a significant decrease in CPR in the EP group. Venetis et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup> later reported a lower pregnancy rate in women with EP on the day of the trigger during the fresh embryo transfer cycle but did not find any association in subsequent FET cycles. Subsequent studies published after that included pregnancy outcomes from blastocyst embryo transfer<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref></sup> showing mixed results with some studies showing poorer pregnancy outcomes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref></sup> and some studies showing similar<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup> or better<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup> pregnancy outcomes. The very real change in practice with most clinics not transferring fresh embryos in the event of elevated progesterone means that the evidence regarding the effect of elevated progesterone in blastocysts transfers is quite limited and prone to publication bias.</p><p id="Par62">One recent meta-analysis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup> assessed PV progesterone supplementation in medicated FET cycles and reported a higher live birth rate in women with a higher progesterone level when compared to lower progesterone level (P&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;10&#x000a0;ng/ml). While a minimum serum concentration of progesterone is required, the optimal level remains to be determined.</p></sec><sec id="Sec40"><title>Clinical implications</title><p id="Par63">We do not recommend doing progesterone testing at baseline. While testing on the day of trigger is widely practiced, it needs to be interpreted with caution. It would be good practice for clinics to audit their clinical data to make decisions on the level of progesterone cut-off. In addition, progesterone levels should contribute but should not be the only decision making factor for freeze all. While most data on frozen embryo transfer comes from the medicated cycle, a shift to the natural cycle due to data on obstetric and perinatal outcomes may make progesterone testing a non question going forward.</p></sec><sec id="Sec41"><title>Implications for future research</title><p id="Par64">Future research should take a two-step approach. First, the normal variation of serum progesterone levels in the normal population undergoing ART treatment in both fresh and frozen cycles should be determined. Second, by taking knowledge and experience gained from AMH testing, researchers can facilitate the creation of a nomogram on which future treatment and research can be based. Results from interventional trials can then advise if progesterone monitoring in a routine manner can be clinically beneficial.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec42"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par65">This review shows that there is no evidence that EP at baseline and oocyte retrieval impacts LBR. EP at the time of ovulation trigger decreases LBR only when day 3 embryo transfers are included; EP did not impact LBR with D5 embryos. Significant heterogeneity exists in the studies examined, and the evidence is of very low to low quality (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S7</xref>). Further good quality studies are needed to give a definitive answer.</p></sec><sec id="Sec260" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.</p><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41598_2024_81539_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><caption><p>Supplementary Material 1</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We would like to express our heartfelt gratitude to Dr Jeevitha Mariapun from Monash University Malaysia and Dr Cindy Lee Ik Sing from Newcastle University Medicine Malaysia for their invaluable assistance in the statistical analysis of our meta-analysis. Their expertise and guidance were crucial in ensuring the accuracy and reliability of our findings. We deeply appreciate their patience and insightful contributions, which significantly enhanced the quality of our work.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>Y.C. conceived and designed the study, performed the analysis, and drafted and revised the manuscript. Y.C.L. developed the search strategy for the identification of articles, identified the articles, acquired and analysed the data, and drafted the manuscript. M.H. identified the articles, acquired and analysed the data, and revised the manuscript. A.M. revised the manuscript. All authors approved the final version of the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>Y.C.L. is sponsored through Complete Fertility and the Ministry of Health, Malaysia.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>Data can be shared according to data protection legislation upon reasonable request to Y.C.L.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par66">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hill, M. J. <italic>et al.</italic> Defining thresholds for abnormal premature progesterone levels during ovarian stimulation for assisted reproduction technologies. <italic>Fertil. Steril.</italic><bold>110</bold>, 671&#x02013;679 e672. 10.1016/j.fertnstert.2018.05.007 (2018).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Venetis</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tarlatzis</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trying to define the optimal progesterone elevation cut-off in fresh in vitro fertilization cycles: time to evolve our way of thinking</article-title><source>Fertil. Steril.</source><year>2018</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>634</fpage><lpage>635</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fertnstert.2018.06.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30196953</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Venetis, C. A. &#x00026; Tarlatzis, B. C. Trying to define the optimal progesterone elevation cut-off in fresh in vitro fertilization cycles: time to evolve our way of thinking. <italic>Fertil. Steril.</italic><bold>110</bold>, 634&#x02013;635. 10.1016/j.fertnstert.2018.06.006 (2018).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30196953</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hamdine, O. <italic>et al.</italic> Elevated early follicular progesterone levels and in vitro fertilization outcomes: a prospective intervention study and meta-analysis. <italic>Fertil. Steril.</italic><bold>102</bold>, 448&#x02013;454 e441. 10.1016/j.fertnstert.2014.05.002 (2014).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kolibianakis</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Venetis</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bontis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tarlatzis</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Significantly lower pregnancy rates in the presence of progesterone elevation in patients treated with GnRH antagonists and gonadotrophins: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Curr. Pharm. Biotechnol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>464</fpage><lpage>470</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/138920112799361927</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21657997</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Kolibianakis, E. M., Venetis, C. A., Bontis, J. &#x00026; Tarlatzis, B. C. Significantly lower pregnancy rates in the presence of progesterone elevation in patients treated with GnRH antagonists and gonadotrophins: a systematic review and meta-analysis. <italic>Curr. Pharm. Biotechnol.</italic><bold>13</bold>, 464&#x02013;470. 10.2174/138920112799361927 (2012).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21657997</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Venetis</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Is progesterone elevation on the day of human chorionic gonadotrophin administration associated with the probability of pregnancy in in vitro fertilization? A systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Hum. Reprod. Update</source><year>2007</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>343</fpage><lpage>355</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/humupd/dmm007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17405832</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Venetis, C. A. et al. Is progesterone elevation on the day of human chorionic gonadotrophin administration associated with the probability of pregnancy in in vitro fertilization? A systematic review and meta-analysis. <italic>Hum. Reprod. Update</italic><bold>13</bold>, 343&#x02013;355. 10.1093/humupd/dmm007 (2007).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17405832</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Venetis</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolibianakis</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bosdou</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Tarlatzis</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Progesterone elevation and probability of pregnancy after IVF: a systematic review and meta-analysis of over 60 000 cycles</article-title><source>Hum. Reprod. Update</source><year>2013</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>433</fpage><lpage>457</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/humupd/dmt014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23827986</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Venetis, C. A., Kolibianakis, E. M., Bosdou, J. K. &#x00026; Tarlatzis, B. C. Progesterone elevation and probability of pregnancy after IVF: a systematic review and meta-analysis of over 60 000 cycles. <italic>Hum. Reprod. Update</italic><bold>19</bold>, 433&#x02013;457. 10.1093/humupd/dmt014 (2013).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23827986</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Melo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Serum luteal phase progesterone in women undergoing frozen embryo transfer in assisted conception: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Fertil. Steril.</source><year>2021</year><volume>116</volume><fpage>1534</fpage><lpage>1556</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fertnstert.2021.07.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34384594</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Melo, P. et al. Serum luteal phase progesterone in women undergoing frozen embryo transfer in assisted conception: a systematic review and meta-analysis. <italic>Fertil. Steril.</italic><bold>116</bold>, 1534&#x02013;1556. 10.1016/j.fertnstert.2021.07.002 (2021).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34384594</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zegers-Hochschild</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The ICMART glossary on ART terminology</article-title><source>Hum. Reprod.</source><year>2006</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>1968</fpage><lpage>1970</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/humrep/del171</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16864610</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Zegers-Hochschild, F. et al. The ICMART glossary on ART terminology. <italic>Hum. Reprod.</italic><bold>21</bold>, 1968&#x02013;1970. 10.1093/humrep/del171 (2006).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16864610</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wells, G. et al. <italic>The Newcastle-Ottawa Scale (NOS) for Assessing the Quality of Nonrandomised Studies in Meta-Analyses</italic> (Ottawa Hospital Research Institute).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Luchini, C., Stubbs, B., Solmi, M. &#x00026; Veronese, N. Assessing the quality of studies in meta-analyses: Advantages and limitations of the Newcastle Ottawa Scale. <italic>World J. Meta-Anal.</italic><bold>5</bold>, 80. 10.13105/wjma.v5.i4.80 (2017).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Deeks, J. J., Higgins, J. P. T. &#x00026; Altman, D. G. In <italic>Cochrane Handbook for Systematic Reviews of Interventions version 6.3 (updated February 2022)</italic> (eds Higgins, T. J. et al.) (Cochrane, 2022).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Guyatt, G. <italic>et al.</italic> GRADE guidelines: 1. Introduction-GRADE evidence profiles and summary of findings tables. <italic>J. Clin. Epidemiol.</italic><bold>64</bold>, 383&#x02013;394. 10.1016/j.jclinepi.2010.04.026 (2011).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mahapatro, A. K. &#x00026; Radhakrishan, A. Day-2 serum progesterone level and IVF/ICSI outcome: a comparative study. <italic>Int. J. Reprod. Contracept. Obstet. Gynecol.</italic><bold>6</bold>(5), 1871&#x02013;1874. 10.18203/2320-1770.ijrcog20171939 (2017).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mutlu</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Erdem</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mutlu</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Bulut</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Erdem</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Elevated basal progesterone levels are associated with increased preovulatory progesterone rise but not with higher pregnancy rates in ICSI cycles with GnRH antagonists</article-title><source>Eur. J. Obstet. Gynecol. Reprod. Biol.</source><year>2017</year><volume>216</volume><fpage>46</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejogrb.2017.06.044</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28715660</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Mutlu, M. F., Erdem, M., Mutlu, I., Bulut, B. &#x00026; Erdem, A. Elevated basal progesterone levels are associated with increased preovulatory progesterone rise but not with higher pregnancy rates in ICSI cycles with GnRH antagonists. <italic>Eur. J. Obstet. Gynecol. Reprod. Biol.</italic><bold>216</bold>, 46&#x02013;50. 10.1016/j.ejogrb.2017.06.044 (2017).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28715660</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bosch</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Premature luteinization during gonadotropin-releasing hormone antagonist cycles and its relationship with in vitro fertilization outcome</article-title><source>Fertil. Steril.</source><year>2003</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>1444</fpage><lpage>1449</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fertnstert.2003.07.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14667881</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Bosch, E. et al. Premature luteinization during gonadotropin-releasing hormone antagonist cycles and its relationship with in vitro fertilization outcome. <italic>Fertil. Steril.</italic><bold>80</bold>, 1444&#x02013;1449. 10.1016/j.fertnstert.2003.07.002 (2003).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14667881</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Serum progesterone concentrations on the day of HCG administration cannot predict pregnancy in assisted reproduction cycles</article-title><source>Reprod. Biomed. Online</source><year>2004</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>183</fpage><lpage>190</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s1472-6483(10)60514-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14989795</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Martinez, F. et al. Serum progesterone concentrations on the day of HCG administration cannot predict pregnancy in assisted reproduction cycles. <italic>Reprod. Biomed. Online</italic><bold>8</bold>, 183&#x02013;190. 10.1016/s1472-6483(10)60514-7 (2004).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14989795</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Devroey</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Arce</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical outcome following stimulation with highly purified hMG or recombinant FSH in patients undergoing IVF: a randomized assessor-blind controlled trial</article-title><source>Hum. Reprod.</source><year>2006</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>3217</fpage><lpage>3227</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/humrep/del284</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16873892</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Andersen, A. N., Devroey, P. &#x00026; Arce, J. C. Clinical outcome following stimulation with highly purified hMG or recombinant FSH in patients undergoing IVF: a randomized assessor-blind controlled trial. <italic>Hum. Reprod.</italic><bold>21</bold>, 3217&#x02013;3227. 10.1093/humrep/del284 (2006).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16873892</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seow</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Subtle progesterone rise in the single-dose gonadotropin-releasing hormone antagonist (cetrorelix) stimulation protocol in patients undergoing in vitro fertilization or intracytoplasmic sperm injection cycles</article-title><source>Gynecol. Endocrinol.</source><year>2007</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>338</fpage><lpage>342</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09513590701403629</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17616858</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Seow, K. M. et al. Subtle progesterone rise in the single-dose gonadotropin-releasing hormone antagonist (cetrorelix) stimulation protocol in patients undergoing in vitro fertilization or intracytoplasmic sperm injection cycles. <italic>Gynecol. Endocrinol.</italic><bold>23</bold>, 338&#x02013;342. 10.1080/09513590701403629 (2007).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17616858</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Qiao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Serum progesterone concentration on day of HCG administration and IVF outcome</article-title><source>Reprod. Biomed. Online</source><year>2008</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>627</fpage><lpage>631</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s1472-6483(10)60475-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18492365</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Li, R., Qiao, J., Wang, L., Zhen, X. &#x00026; Lu, Y. Serum progesterone concentration on day of HCG administration and IVF outcome. <italic>Reprod. Biomed. Online</italic><bold>16</bold>, 627&#x02013;631. 10.1016/s1472-6483(10)60475-0 (2008).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18492365</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>FK</given-names></name><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><name><surname>Horng</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relationship of progesterone/estradiol ratio on day of hCG administration and pregnancy outcomes in high responders undergoing in vitro fertilization</article-title><source>Fertil. Steril.</source><year>2009</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>1284</fpage><lpage>1289</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fertnstert.2008.08.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18829018</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">Lee, F. K., Lai, T. H., Lin, T. K., Horng, S. G. &#x00026; Chen, S. C. Relationship of progesterone/estradiol ratio on day of hCG administration and pregnancy outcomes in high responders undergoing in vitro fertilization. <italic>Fertil. Steril.</italic><bold>92</bold>, 1284&#x02013;1289. 10.1016/j.fertnstert.2008.08.024 (2009).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18829018</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Papanikolaou</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Progesterone rise on the day of human chorionic gonadotropin administration impairs pregnancy outcome in day 3 single-embryo transfer, while has no effect on day 5 single blastocyst transfer</article-title><source>Fertil. Steril.</source><year>2009</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>949</fpage><lpage>952</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fertnstert.2006.12.064</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17555751</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Papanikolaou, E. G. et al. Progesterone rise on the day of human chorionic gonadotropin administration impairs pregnancy outcome in day 3 single-embryo transfer, while has no effect on day 5 single blastocyst transfer. <italic>Fertil. Steril.</italic><bold>91</bold>, 949&#x02013;952. 10.1016/j.fertnstert.2006.12.064 (2009).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17555751</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kilicdag</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name><surname>Haydardedeoglu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Cok</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hacivelioglu</surname><given-names>SO</given-names></name><name><surname>Bagis</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Premature progesterone elevation impairs implantation and live birth rates in GnRH-agonist IVF/ICSI cycles</article-title><source>Arch. Gynecol. Obstet.</source><year>2010</year><volume>281</volume><fpage>747</fpage><lpage>752</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00404-009-1248-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19862542</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">Kilicdag, E. B., Haydardedeoglu, B., Cok, T., Hacivelioglu, S. O. &#x00026; Bagis, T. Premature progesterone elevation impairs implantation and live birth rates in GnRH-agonist IVF/ICSI cycles. <italic>Arch. Gynecol. Obstet.</italic><bold>281</bold>, 747&#x02013;752. 10.1007/s00404-009-1248-0 (2010).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19862542</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seow</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Characteristics of progesterone changes in women with subtle progesterone rise in recombinant follicle-stimulating hormone and gonadotropin-releasing hormone antagonist cycle</article-title><source>Gynecol. Obstet. Investig.</source><year>2010</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>64</fpage><lpage>68</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000290062</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20203521</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Seow, K. M. et al. Characteristics of progesterone changes in women with subtle progesterone rise in recombinant follicle-stimulating hormone and gonadotropin-releasing hormone antagonist cycle. <italic>Gynecol. Obstet. Investig.</italic><bold>70</bold>, 64&#x02013;68. 10.1159/000290062 (2010).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20203521</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rezaee</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghaseminejad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Forootan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hosseinipoor</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Forghani</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of serum progesterone level on the day of hCG injection in infertile polycystic ovarian syndrome patients referred to Women&#x02019;s Hospital, Tehran, 2009</article-title><source>Int. J. Fertil. Steril.</source><year>2012</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>231</fpage><lpage>234</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25210608</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">Rezaee, Z., Ghaseminejad, A., Forootan, M., Hosseinipoor, T. &#x00026; Forghani, F. Assessment of serum progesterone level on the day of hCG injection in infertile polycystic ovarian syndrome patients referred to Women&#x02019;s Hospital, Tehran, 2009. <italic>Int. J. Fertil. Steril.</italic><bold>5</bold>, 231&#x02013;234 (2012).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25210608</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elgindy</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Progesterone level and progesterone/estradiol ratio on the day of hCG administration: detrimental cutoff levels and new treatment strategy</article-title><source>Fertil. Steril.</source><year>2011</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>1639</fpage><lpage>1644</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fertnstert.2010.12.065</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21324450</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="journal">Elgindy, E. A. Progesterone level and progesterone/estradiol ratio on the day of hCG administration: detrimental cutoff levels and new treatment strategy. <italic>Fertil. Steril.</italic><bold>95</bold>, 1639&#x02013;1644. 10.1016/j.fertnstert.2010.12.065 (2011).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21324450</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR26" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lahoud</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Elevated progesterone in GnRH agonist down regulated in vitro fertilisation (IVFICSI) cycles reduces live birth rates but not embryo quality</article-title><source>Arch. Gynecol. Obstet.</source><year>2012</year><volume>285</volume><fpage>535</fpage><lpage>540</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00404-011-2045-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21853250</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26" publication-type="journal">Lahoud, R. et al. Elevated progesterone in GnRH agonist down regulated in vitro fertilisation (IVFICSI) cycles reduces live birth rates but not embryo quality. <italic>Arch. Gynecol. Obstet.</italic><bold>285</bold>, 535&#x02013;540. 10.1007/s00404-011-2045-0 (2012).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21853250</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Yding Andersen, C., Bungum, L., Nyboe Andersen, A. &#x00026; Humaidan, P. Preovulatory progesterone concentration associates significantly to follicle number and LH concentration but not to pregnancy rate. <italic>Reprod. Biomed. Online</italic><bold>23</bold>, 187&#x02013;195. 10.1016/j.rbmo.2011.04.003 (2011).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Huang, R., Fang, C., Xu, S., Yi, Y. &#x00026; Liang, X. Premature progesterone rise negatively correlated with live birth rate in IVF cycles with GnRH agonist: an analysis of 2,566 cycles. <italic>Fertil. Steri.l</italic><bold>98</bold>, 664&#x02013;670 e662. 10.1016/j.fertnstert.2012.05.024 (2012).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR29" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kyrou</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The relationship of premature progesterone rise with serum estradiol levels and number of follicles in GnRH antagonist/recombinant FSH-stimulated cycles</article-title><source>Eur. J. Obstet. Gynecol. Reprod. Biol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>162</volume><fpage>165</fpage><lpage>168</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejogrb.2012.02.025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22425288</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29" publication-type="journal">Kyrou, D. et al. The relationship of premature progesterone rise with serum estradiol levels and number of follicles in GnRH antagonist/recombinant FSH-stimulated cycles. <italic>Eur. J. Obstet. Gynecol. Reprod. Biol.</italic><bold>162</bold>, 165&#x02013;168. 10.1016/j.ejogrb.2012.02.025 (2012).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22425288</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR30" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Papanikolaou</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>GnRH-agonist versus GnRH-antagonist IVF cycles: is the reproductive outcome affected by the incidence of progesterone elevation on the day of HCG triggering? A randomized prospective study</article-title><source>Hum. Reprod.</source><year>2012</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>1822</fpage><lpage>1828</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/humrep/des066</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22422777</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30" publication-type="journal">Papanikolaou, E. G. et al. GnRH-agonist versus GnRH-antagonist IVF cycles: is the reproductive outcome affected by the incidence of progesterone elevation on the day of HCG triggering? A randomized prospective study. <italic>Hum. Reprod.</italic><bold>27</bold>, 1822&#x02013;1828. 10.1093/humrep/des066 (2012).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22422777</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR31" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Progesterone levels on the hCG day and outcomes in vitro fertilization in women with polycystic ovary syndrome</article-title><source>J. Assist. Reprod. Genet.</source><year>2012</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>603</fpage><lpage>607</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10815-012-9762-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22552733</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR31" publication-type="journal">Peng, C., Guo, Z., Long, X. &#x00026; Lu, G. Progesterone levels on the hCG day and outcomes in vitro fertilization in women with polycystic ovary syndrome. <italic>J. Assist. Reprod. Genet.</italic><bold>29</bold>, 603&#x02013;607. 10.1007/s10815-012-9762-6 (2012).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22552733</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR32" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ochsenkuhn</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Subtle progesterone rise on the day of human chorionic gonadotropin administration is associated with lower live birth rates in women undergoing assisted reproductive technology: a retrospective study with 2,555 fresh embryo transfers</article-title><source>Fertil. Steril.</source><year>2012</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>347</fpage><lpage>354</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fertnstert.2012.04.041</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22633265</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32" publication-type="journal">Ochsenkuhn, R. et al. Subtle progesterone rise on the day of human chorionic gonadotropin administration is associated with lower live birth rates in women undergoing assisted reproductive technology: a retrospective study with 2,555 fresh embryo transfers. <italic>Fertil. Steril.</italic><bold>98</bold>, 347&#x02013;354. 10.1016/j.fertnstert.2012.04.041 (2012).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22633265</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR33" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effect of HCG-day serum progesterone and oestradiol concentrations on pregnancy outcomes in GnRH agonist cycles</article-title><source>Reprod. Biomed. Online</source><year>2012</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>511</fpage><lpage>520</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rbmo.2012.02.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22417667</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR33" publication-type="journal">Wu, Z. et al. Effect of HCG-day serum progesterone and oestradiol concentrations on pregnancy outcomes in GnRH agonist cycles. <italic>Reprod. Biomed. Online</italic><bold>24</bold>, 511&#x02013;520. 10.1016/j.rbmo.2012.02.003 (2012).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22417667</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR34" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Corti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Fresh blastocyst transfer as a clinical approach to overcome the detrimental effect of progesterone elevation at hCG triggering: a strategy in the context of the Italian law</article-title><source>Eur. J. Obstet. Gynecol. Reprod. Biol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>171</volume><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>77</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejogrb.2013.08.017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24012449</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR34" publication-type="journal">Corti, L. et al. Fresh blastocyst transfer as a clinical approach to overcome the detrimental effect of progesterone elevation at hCG triggering: a strategy in the context of the Italian law. <italic>Eur. J. Obstet. Gynecol. Reprod. Biol.</italic><bold>171</bold>, 73&#x02013;77. 10.1016/j.ejogrb.2013.08.017 (2013).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24012449</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR35" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Griesinger</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Progesterone elevation does not compromise pregnancy rates in high responders: a pooled analysis of in vitro fertilization patients treated with recombinant follicle-stimulating hormone/gonadotropin-releasing hormone antagonist in six trials</article-title><source>Fertil. Steril.</source><year>2013</year><volume>100</volume><issue>1622&#x02013;1628</issue><fpage>e1621</fpage><lpage>1623</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fertnstert.2013.08.045</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR35" publication-type="journal">Griesinger, G. et al. Progesterone elevation does not compromise pregnancy rates in high responders: a pooled analysis of in vitro fertilization patients treated with recombinant follicle-stimulating hormone/gonadotropin-releasing hormone antagonist in six trials. <italic>Fertil. Steril.</italic><bold>100</bold>(1622&#x02013;1628), e1621-1623. 10.1016/j.fertnstert.2013.08.045 (2013).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR36" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Orvieto</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>GnRH agonist versus GnRH antagonist in ovarian stimulation: the role of elevated peak serum progesterone levels</article-title><source>Gynecol. Endocrinol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>843</fpage><lpage>845</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/09513590.2013.808328</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23802563</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR36" publication-type="journal">Orvieto, R. et al. GnRH agonist versus GnRH antagonist in ovarian stimulation: the role of elevated peak serum progesterone levels. <italic>Gynecol. Endocrinol.</italic><bold>29</bold>, 843&#x02013;845. 10.3109/09513590.2013.808328 (2013).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23802563</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR37" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Papaleo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Basal progesterone level as the main determinant of progesterone elevation on the day of hCG triggering in controlled ovarian stimulation cycles</article-title><source>Arch. Gynecol. Obstet.</source><year>2014</year><volume>290</volume><fpage>169</fpage><lpage>176</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00404-014-3167-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24549270</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR37" publication-type="journal">Papaleo, E. et al. Basal progesterone level as the main determinant of progesterone elevation on the day of hCG triggering in controlled ovarian stimulation cycles. <italic>Arch. Gynecol. Obstet.</italic><bold>290</bold>, 169&#x02013;176. 10.1007/s00404-014-3167-y (2014).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24549270</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR38" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Acet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Premature progesterone elevation does not affect pregnancy outcome in high-responder patients undergoing short-interval coasting in IVF cycles</article-title><source>Med. Sci. Monit. Basic Res.</source><year>2015</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>247</fpage><lpage>252</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12659/MSMBR.896244</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26634938</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR38" publication-type="journal">Acet, M. et al. Premature progesterone elevation does not affect pregnancy outcome in high-responder patients undergoing short-interval coasting in IVF cycles. <italic>Med. Sci. Monit. Basic Res.</italic><bold>21</bold>, 247&#x02013;252. 10.12659/MSMBR.896244 (2015).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26634938</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR39" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effect of premature serum progesterone rise on embryo transfer outcomes and the role of blastocyst culture and transfer in assisted reproductive technology cycles with premature progesterone rise</article-title><source>Taiwan. J. Obstet. Gynecol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>641</fpage><lpage>646</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tjog.2014.03.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26700978</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR39" publication-type="journal">Huang, P. C. et al. Effect of premature serum progesterone rise on embryo transfer outcomes and the role of blastocyst culture and transfer in assisted reproductive technology cycles with premature progesterone rise. <italic>Taiwan. J. Obstet. Gynecol.</italic><bold>54</bold>, 641&#x02013;646. 10.1016/j.tjog.2014.03.014 (2015).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26700978</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR40" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Progesterone elevation on the day of human chorionic gonadotropin administration adversely affects the outcome of IVF with transferred embryos at different developmental stages</article-title><source>Reprod. Biol. Endocrinol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>82</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12958-015-0075-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26238449</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR40" publication-type="journal">Huang, Y. et al. Progesterone elevation on the day of human chorionic gonadotropin administration adversely affects the outcome of IVF with transferred embryos at different developmental stages. <italic>Reprod. Biol. Endocrinol.</italic><bold>13</bold>, 82. 10.1186/s12958-015-0075-3 (2015).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26238449</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR41" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koo</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A high response to controlled ovarian stimulation induces premature luteinization with a negative impact on pregnancy outcomes in a gonadotropin-releasing hormone antagonist cycle</article-title><source>Clin. Exp. Reprod. Med.</source><year>2015</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>155</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5653/cerm.2015.42.4.149</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26816874</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR41" publication-type="journal">Koo, H. S. et al. A high response to controlled ovarian stimulation induces premature luteinization with a negative impact on pregnancy outcomes in a gonadotropin-releasing hormone antagonist cycle. <italic>Clin. Exp. Reprod. Med.</italic><bold>42</bold>, 149&#x02013;155. 10.5653/cerm.2015.42.4.149 (2015).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26816874</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR42" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Malik</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Malhotra</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanamail</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of progesterone (on hCG day)/oocyte ratio on pregnancy outcome in long agonist non donor fresh IVF/ICSI cycles</article-title><source>Taiwan. J. Obstet. Gynecol.</source><year>2016</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>503</fpage><lpage>506</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tjog.2015.09.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27590371</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR42" publication-type="journal">Singh, N., Malik, N., Malhotra, N., Vanamail, P. &#x00026; Gupta, M. Impact of progesterone (on hCG day)/oocyte ratio on pregnancy outcome in long agonist non donor fresh IVF/ICSI cycles. <italic>Taiwan. J. Obstet. Gynecol.</italic><bold>55</bold>, 503&#x02013;506. 10.1016/j.tjog.2015.09.005 (2016).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27590371</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR43" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>YR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Progesterone elevation on the day of human chorionic gonadotropin administration is not the only factor determining outcomes of in vitro fertilization</article-title><source>Fertil. Steril.</source><year>2015</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>106</fpage><lpage>111</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fertnstert.2014.10.019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25455869</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR43" publication-type="journal">Tsai, Y. R. et al. Progesterone elevation on the day of human chorionic gonadotropin administration is not the only factor determining outcomes of in vitro fertilization. <italic>Fertil. Steril.</italic><bold>103</bold>, 106&#x02013;111. 10.1016/j.fertnstert.2014.10.019 (2015).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25455869</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR44" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Demir</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Progesterone change in the late follicular phase affects pregnancy rates both agonist and antagonist protocols in normoresponders: a case-controlled study in ICSI cycles</article-title><source>Gynecol. Endocrinol.</source><year>2016</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>361</fpage><lpage>365</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/09513590.2015.1121226</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26654315</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR44" publication-type="journal">Demir, B. et al. Progesterone change in the late follicular phase affects pregnancy rates both agonist and antagonist protocols in normoresponders: a case-controlled study in ICSI cycles. <italic>Gynecol. Endocrinol.</italic><bold>32</bold>, 361&#x02013;365. 10.3109/09513590.2015.1121226 (2016).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26654315</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Healy, M. W. <italic>et al.</italic> Does a frozen embryo transfer ameliorate the effect of elevated progesterone seen in fresh transfer cycles? <italic>Fertil. Steril.</italic><bold>105</bold>, 93&#x02013;99 e91. 10.1016/j.fertnstert.2015.09.015 (2016).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR46" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ashmita</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Vikas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Swati</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The impact of progesterone level on day of hCG injection in IVF cycles on clinical pregnancy rate</article-title><source>J. Hum. Reprod. Sci.</source><year>2017</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>265</fpage><lpage>270</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0974-1208.223278</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29430153</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR46" publication-type="journal">Ashmita, J., Vikas, S. &#x00026; Swati, G. The impact of progesterone level on day of hCG injection in IVF cycles on clinical pregnancy rate. <italic>J. Hum. Reprod. Sci.</italic><bold>10</bold>, 265&#x02013;270. 10.4103/0974-1208.223278 (2017).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29430153</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR47" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Impact of estradiol and progesterone levels during the late follicular stage on the outcome of GnRH antagonist protocols</article-title><source>Gynecol. Endocrinol.</source><year>2019</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>481</fpage><lpage>484</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09513590.2018.1538346</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30600726</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR47" publication-type="journal">Simon, C. et al. Impact of estradiol and progesterone levels during the late follicular stage on the outcome of GnRH antagonist protocols. <italic>Gynecol. Endocrinol.</italic><bold>35</bold>, 481&#x02013;484. 10.1080/09513590.2018.1538346 (2019).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30600726</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR48" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Progesterone elevation on the day of hCG trigger has detrimental effect on live birth rate in low and intermediate ovarian responders, but not in high responders</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2019</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>5127</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-41499-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30914679</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR48" publication-type="journal">Wu, Z. et al. Progesterone elevation on the day of hCG trigger has detrimental effect on live birth rate in low and intermediate ovarian responders, but not in high responders. <italic>Sci. Rep.</italic><bold>9</bold>, 5127. 10.1038/s41598-019-41499-1 (2019).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30914679</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lee, C. I. <italic>et al.</italic> Early progesterone change associated with pregnancy outcome after fresh embryo transfer in assisted reproduction technology cycles with progesterone level of &#x0003e;1.5 ng/ml on human chorionic gonadotropin trigger day. <italic>Front. Endocrinol. (Lausanne)</italic><bold>11</bold>, 653. 10.3389/fendo.2020.00653 (2020).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR50" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Live birth after a freeze-only strategy versus fresh embryo transfer in three randomized trials considering progesterone concentration</article-title><source>Reprod. Biomed. Online</source><year>2020</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>395</fpage><lpage>401</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rbmo.2020.04.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32600942</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR50" publication-type="journal">Yu, Y. et al. Live birth after a freeze-only strategy versus fresh embryo transfer in three randomized trials considering progesterone concentration. <italic>Reprod. Biomed. Online</italic><bold>41</bold>, 395&#x02013;401. 10.1016/j.rbmo.2020.04.021 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32600942</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR51" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benmachiche</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Benbouhedja</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zoghmar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Al Humaidan</surname><given-names>PSH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The impact of preovulatory versus midluteal serum progesterone level on live birth rates during fresh embryo transfer</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2021</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>e0246440</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0246440</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33571260</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR51" publication-type="journal">Benmachiche, A., Benbouhedja, S., Zoghmar, A. &#x00026; Al Humaidan, P. S. H. The impact of preovulatory versus midluteal serum progesterone level on live birth rates during fresh embryo transfer. <italic>PLoS One</italic><bold>16</bold>, e0246440. 10.1371/journal.pone.0246440 (2021).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33571260</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR52" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mahran</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The value of serum progesterone level on day of human chorionic gonadotrophin administration/metaphase II oocyte ratio in predicting IVF/ICSI outcome in patients with normal ovarian reserve</article-title><source>J. Ovarian Res.</source><year>2021</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>52</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13048-021-00800-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33794989</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR52" publication-type="journal">Mahran, A. et al. The value of serum progesterone level on day of human chorionic gonadotrophin administration/metaphase II oocyte ratio in predicting IVF/ICSI outcome in patients with normal ovarian reserve. <italic>J. Ovarian Res.</italic><bold>14</bold>, 52. 10.1186/s13048-021-00800-5 (2021).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33794989</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR53" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mitra</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Patil</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Patil</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nayak</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pre-ovulatory hormones on day of human chorionic gonadotropin trigger and assisted reproductive technique outcomes in different ovarian response groups</article-title><source>J. Hum. Reprod. Sci.</source><year>2021</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>406</fpage><lpage>414</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/jhrs.jhrs_91_21</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35197687</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR53" publication-type="journal">Mitra, S., Patil, M., Patil, M. &#x00026; Nayak, P. K. Pre-ovulatory hormones on day of human chorionic gonadotropin trigger and assisted reproductive technique outcomes in different ovarian response groups. <italic>J. Hum. Reprod. Sci.</italic><bold>14</bold>, 406&#x02013;414. 10.4103/jhrs.jhrs_91_21 (2021).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35197687</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR54" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exploration of the value of progesterone and progesterone/estradiol ratio on the hCG trigger day in predicting pregnancy outcomes of PCOS patients undergoing IVF/ICSI: a retrospective cohort study</article-title><source>Reprod. Biol. Endocrinol.</source><year>2021</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>184</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12958-021-00862-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34893087</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR54" publication-type="journal">Yang, Y., Liu, B., Wu, G. &#x00026; Yang, J. Exploration of the value of progesterone and progesterone/estradiol ratio on the hCG trigger day in predicting pregnancy outcomes of PCOS patients undergoing IVF/ICSI: a retrospective cohort study. <italic>Reprod. Biol. Endocrinol.</italic><bold>19</bold>, 184. 10.1186/s12958-021-00862-6 (2021).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34893087</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Jiang, W. <italic>et al.</italic> Elevated serum progesterone levels on the hCG trigger day have a negative impact on the live birth rate in the first fresh IVF-ET cycle. <italic>J. Obstet. Gynaecol</italic>., 2151345. 10.1080/01443615.2022.2151345 (2022).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR56" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Adverse impact of elevated progesterone levels on human chorionic gonadotropin trigger day on blastocyst transfer outcomes in gonadotropin-releasing hormone agonist cycles</article-title><source>Eur. J. Obstet. Gynecol. Reprod. Biol.</source><year>2022</year><volume>276</volume><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>112</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejogrb.2022.07.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35853270</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR56" publication-type="journal">Kong, N. et al. Adverse impact of elevated progesterone levels on human chorionic gonadotropin trigger day on blastocyst transfer outcomes in gonadotropin-releasing hormone agonist cycles. <italic>Eur. J. Obstet. Gynecol. Reprod. Biol.</italic><bold>276</bold>, 107&#x02013;112. 10.1016/j.ejogrb.2022.07.007 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35853270</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR57" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of slightly elevated progesterone on hCG trigger day on clinical pregnancy rate in GnRH-ant IVF/ICSI cycles</article-title><source>Reprod. Health</source><year>2022</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>66</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12978-022-01371-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35287707</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR57" publication-type="journal">Zhao, J., Hao, J., Xu, B., Wang, Y. &#x00026; Li, Y. Effect of slightly elevated progesterone on hCG trigger day on clinical pregnancy rate in GnRH-ant IVF/ICSI cycles. <italic>Reprod. Health</italic><bold>19</bold>, 66. 10.1186/s12978-022-01371-4 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35287707</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR58" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Progesterone levels on oocyte retrieval day can predict the quantity of viable embryos but not pregnancy outcome of intracytoplasmic sperm injection</article-title><source>Gynecol. Endocrinol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>452</fpage><lpage>458</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09513590802196247</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18850383</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR58" publication-type="journal">Niu, Z., Feng, Y., Zhang, A., Sun, Y. &#x00026; Zhang, H. Progesterone levels on oocyte retrieval day can predict the quantity of viable embryos but not pregnancy outcome of intracytoplasmic sperm injection. <italic>Gynecol. Endocrinol.</italic><bold>24</bold>, 452&#x02013;458. 10.1080/09513590802196247 (2008).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18850383</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR59" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nayak</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Progesterone level at oocyte retrieval predicts in vitro fertilization success in a short-antagonist protocol: a prospective cohort study</article-title><source>Fertil. Steril.</source><year>2014</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>676</fpage><lpage>682</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fertnstert.2013.11.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24355049</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR59" publication-type="journal">Nayak, S. et al. Progesterone level at oocyte retrieval predicts in vitro fertilization success in a short-antagonist protocol: a prospective cohort study. <italic>Fertil. Steril.</italic><bold>101</bold>, 676&#x02013;682. 10.1016/j.fertnstert.2013.11.022 (2014).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24355049</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR60" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tulic</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Correlation of progesterone levels on the day of oocyte retrieval with basal hormonal status and the outcome of ART</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2020</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>22291</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-79347-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33339878</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR60" publication-type="journal">Tulic, L. et al. Correlation of progesterone levels on the day of oocyte retrieval with basal hormonal status and the outcome of ART. <italic>Sci. Rep.</italic><bold>10</bold>, 22291. 10.1038/s41598-020-79347-2 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33339878</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR61" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Predictive value of serum progesterone level on beta-hCG check day in women with previous repeated miscarriages after in vitro fertilization</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2017</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>e0181229</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0181229</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28708875</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR61" publication-type="journal">Kim, Y. J. et al. Predictive value of serum progesterone level on beta-hCG check day in women with previous repeated miscarriages after in vitro fertilization. <italic>PLoS One</italic><bold>12</bold>, e0181229. 10.1371/journal.pone.0181229 (2017).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28708875</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR62" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomsen</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The impact of luteal serum progesterone levels on live birth rates-a prospective study of 602 IVF/ICSI cycles</article-title><source>Hum. Reprod.</source><year>2018</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>1506</fpage><lpage>1516</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/humrep/dey226</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29955789</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR62" publication-type="journal">Thomsen, L. H. et al. The impact of luteal serum progesterone levels on live birth rates-a prospective study of 602 IVF/ICSI cycles. <italic>Hum. Reprod.</italic><bold>33</bold>, 1506&#x02013;1516. 10.1093/humrep/dey226 (2018).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29955789</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR63" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Netter</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Do early luteal serum progesterone levels predict the reproductive outcomes in IVF with oral dydrogesterone for luteal phase support?</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2019</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>e0220450</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0220450</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31361764</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR63" publication-type="journal">Netter, A. et al. Do early luteal serum progesterone levels predict the reproductive outcomes in IVF with oral dydrogesterone for luteal phase support?. <italic>PLoS One</italic><bold>14</bold>, e0220450. 10.1371/journal.pone.0220450 (2019).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31361764</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Groenewoud, E. R., Macklon, N. S., Cohlen, B. J. &#x00026; Group, A. S. The effect of elevated progesterone levels before HCG triggering in modified natural cycle frozen-thawed embryo transfer cycles. <italic>Reprod. Biomed. Online</italic><bold>34</bold>, 546&#x02013;554. 10.1016/j.rbmo.2017.02.008 (2017).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR65" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>VC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effect of preovulatory progesterone elevation and duration of progesterone elevation on the pregnancy rate of frozen-thawed embryo transfer in natural cycles</article-title><source>Fertil. Steril.</source><year>2014</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>1288</fpage><lpage>1293</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fertnstert.2014.01.040</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24602752</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR65" publication-type="journal">Lee, V. C. et al. Effect of preovulatory progesterone elevation and duration of progesterone elevation on the pregnancy rate of frozen-thawed embryo transfer in natural cycles. <italic>Fertil. Steril.</italic><bold>101</bold>, 1288&#x02013;1293. 10.1016/j.fertnstert.2014.01.040 (2014).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24602752</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR66" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of elevated progesterone levels the day before ovulation on pregnancy outcomes in natural cycles of frozen thawed embryo transfer</article-title><source>Gynecol. Endocrinol.</source><year>2022</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>726</fpage><lpage>730</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09513590.2022.2103671</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35901839</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR66" publication-type="journal">Wu, D., Yu, T., Shi, H. &#x00026; Zhai, J. Effect of elevated progesterone levels the day before ovulation on pregnancy outcomes in natural cycles of frozen thawed embryo transfer. <italic>Gynecol. Endocrinol.</italic><bold>38</bold>, 726&#x02013;730. 10.1080/09513590.2022.2103671 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35901839</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Akaeda S., K. D., Shioda K., Momoeda M. Relationship between serum progesterone concentrations and pregnancy rates in hormone replacement treatment-frozen embryo transfer using progesterone vaginal tablets. <italic>Clin. Exp. Obstet. Gynecol</italic>. <bold>XLVI</bold>(5). 10.12891/ceog4360.2019 (2019).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR68" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boynukalin</surname><given-names>FK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Measuring the serum progesterone level on the day of transfer can be an additional tool to maximize ongoing pregnancies in single euploid frozen blastocyst transfers</article-title><source>Reprod. Biol. Endocrinol.</source><year>2019</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>102</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12958-019-0549-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31783865</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR68" publication-type="journal">Boynukalin, F. K. et al. Measuring the serum progesterone level on the day of transfer can be an additional tool to maximize ongoing pregnancies in single euploid frozen blastocyst transfers. <italic>Reprod. Biol. Endocrinol.</italic><bold>17</bold>, 102. 10.1186/s12958-019-0549-9 (2019).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31783865</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR69" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alsbjerg</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Can combining vaginal and rectal progesterone achieve the optimum progesterone range required for implantation in the HRT-FET model?</article-title><source>Reprod. Biomed. Online</source><year>2020</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>805</fpage><lpage>811</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rbmo.2020.02.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32376312</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR69" publication-type="journal">Alsbjerg, B. et al. Can combining vaginal and rectal progesterone achieve the optimum progesterone range required for implantation in the HRT-FET model?. <italic>Reprod. Biomed. Online</italic><bold>40</bold>, 805&#x02013;811. 10.1016/j.rbmo.2020.02.007 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32376312</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Liu, Y. &#x00026; Wu, Y. Progesterone intramuscularly or vaginally administration may not change live birth rate or neonatal outcomes in artificial frozen-thawed embryo transfer cycles. <italic>Front. Endocrinol. (Lausanne)</italic><bold>11</bold>, 539427. 10.3389/fendo.2020.539427 (2020).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR71"><label>71.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR71" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Polat</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Addition of intramuscular progesterone to vaginal progesterone in hormone replacement therapy in vitrified-warmed blastocyst transfer cycles</article-title><source>Reprod. Biomed. Online</source><year>2020</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>812</fpage><lpage>818</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rbmo.2020.01.031</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32362573</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR71" publication-type="journal">Polat, M. et al. Addition of intramuscular progesterone to vaginal progesterone in hormone replacement therapy in vitrified-warmed blastocyst transfer cycles. <italic>Reprod. Biomed. Online</italic><bold>40</bold>, 812&#x02013;818. 10.1016/j.rbmo.2020.01.031 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32362573</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR72"><label>72.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR72" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shiba</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Serum progesterone levels with the use of four different types of vaginal progesterone in frozen-thawed embryo transfer cycles and related pregnancy outcomes</article-title><source>Int. J. Fertil. Steril.</source><year>2021</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>34</fpage><lpage>39</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.22074/ijfs.2021.6235</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33497045</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR72" publication-type="journal">Shiba, R. et al. Serum progesterone levels with the use of four different types of vaginal progesterone in frozen-thawed embryo transfer cycles and related pregnancy outcomes. <italic>Int. J. Fertil. Steril.</italic><bold>15</bold>, 34&#x02013;39. 10.22074/ijfs.2021.6235 (2021).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33497045</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR73"><label>73.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Alyasin, A., Agha-Hosseini, M., Kabirinasab, M., Saeidi, H. &#x00026; Nashtaei, M. S. Serum progesterone levels greater than 32.5 ng/ml on the day of embryo transfer are associated with lower live birth rate after artificial endometrial preparation: a prospective study. <italic>Reprod. Biol. Endocrinol.</italic><bold>19</bold>, 24. 10.1186/s12958-021-00703-6 (2021).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR74"><label>74.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR74" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maignien</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clinical factors associated with low serum progesterone levels on the day of frozen blastocyst transfer in hormonal replacement therapy cycles</article-title><source>Hum. Reprod.</source><year>2022</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>2570</fpage><lpage>2577</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/humrep/deac199</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36125015</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR74" publication-type="journal">Maignien, C. et al. Clinical factors associated with low serum progesterone levels on the day of frozen blastocyst transfer in hormonal replacement therapy cycles. <italic>Hum. Reprod.</italic><bold>37</bold>, 2570&#x02013;2577. 10.1093/humrep/deac199 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36125015</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR75"><label>75.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Melo, P. <italic>et al.</italic> The effect of frozen embryo transfer regimen on the association between serum progesterone and live birth: a multicentre prospective cohort study (ProFET). <italic>Hum. Reprod. Open</italic><bold>2022</bold>, hoac054. 10.1093/hropen/hoac054 (2022).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR76"><label>76.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR76" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vuong</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The early luteal hormonal profile in IVF patients triggered with hCG</article-title><source>Hum. Reprod.</source><year>2020</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>157</fpage><lpage>166</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/humrep/dez235</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31967304</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR76" publication-type="journal">Vuong, L. N. et al. The early luteal hormonal profile in IVF patients triggered with hCG. <italic>Hum. Reprod.</italic><bold>35</bold>, 157&#x02013;166. 10.1093/humrep/dez235 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31967304</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR77"><label>77.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR77" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Critchley</surname><given-names>HO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cytokine control in human endometrium</article-title><source>Reproduction</source><year>2001</year><volume>121</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1530/rep.0.1210003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11226025</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR77" publication-type="journal">Kelly, R. W., King, A. E. &#x00026; Critchley, H. O. Cytokine control in human endometrium. <italic>Reproduction</italic><bold>121</bold>, 3&#x02013;19. 10.1530/rep.0.1210003 (2001).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11226025</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR78"><label>78.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Slayden, O. D. &#x00026; Brenner, R. M. A critical period of progesterone withdrawal precedes menstruation in macaques. <italic>Reprod. Biol. Endocrinol.</italic><bold>4 Suppl 1</bold>, S6, 10.1186/1477-7827-4-S1-S6 (2006).</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>