<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39890856</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11785773</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">87668</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-025-87668-3</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Emergence of <italic>Fusarium incarnatum</italic> and <italic>Fusarium avenaceum</italic> in wilt affected solanaceous crops of the Northern Himalayas</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Parihar</surname><given-names>Tasmeen J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Naik</surname><given-names>Madeeha</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mehraj</surname><given-names>Shafqat</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Inam ul Haq</surname><given-names>Syed</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Perveen</surname><given-names>Maqsooda</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Malla</surname><given-names>Ishfaq Ahmed</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Abid</surname><given-names>Taniya</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Gul</surname><given-names>Nadia</given-names></name><address><email>gulnadiagul@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Masoodi</surname><given-names>Khalid Z.</given-names></name><address><email>masoodikz@skuastkashmir.ac.in</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/00jgwn197</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.444725.4</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0500 6225</institution-id><institution>Transcriptomics Laboratory (K-Lab), Division of Plant Biotechnology, </institution><institution>Sher-e-Kashmir University of Agricultural Sciences and Technology of Kashmir, </institution></institution-wrap>Shalimar, Srinagar, Jammu and Kashmir 190025 India </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/00jgwn197</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.444725.4</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0500 6225</institution-id><institution>College of Temperate Sericulture, </institution><institution>Sher-e-Kashmir University of Agricultural Sciences and Technology of Kashmir, </institution></institution-wrap>Shalimar, Srinagar, Jammu and Kashmir 190025 India </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>31</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>3855</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>27</day><month>5</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">The objective of this study was to identify and characterize the fungal pathogens responsible for wilt diseases in solanaceous crops, specifically tomato, brinjal, and chili, in the Kashmir valley. Through both morphological and molecular analyses, including DNA barcoding of the ITS, TEF, RPB1, and RPB2 genomic regions, <italic>Fusarium incarnatum</italic> and <italic>Fusarium avenaceum</italic> were identified as the primary causal agents of wilt in tomato and brinjal, and chili, respectively. Pathogenicity tests confirmed the virulence of these pathogens, with typical wilt symptoms observed upon inoculation. This represents the first report of <italic>F. incarnatum</italic> and <italic>F. avenaceum</italic> as wilt pathogens in solanaceous crops in India. Phylogenetic analysis further confirmed the genetic variability of these pathogens, revealing their expanding host range. The findings underscore the growing adaptability of these <italic>Fusarium</italic> species to diverse agricultural systems and highlight the urgent need for targeted disease management strategies to mitigate the significant yield losses caused by <italic>Fusarium</italic> wilt in solanaceous vegetable production.</p></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd><italic>Fusarium</italic> wilt</kwd><kwd>Solanaceous crops</kwd><kwd>Molecular techniques</kwd><kwd><italic>Fusarium incarnatum</italic></kwd><kwd><italic>Fusarium avenaceum</italic></kwd><kwd>Crop pathogens</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Biotechnology</kwd><kwd>Microbiology</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100001409</institution-id><institution>Department of Science and Technology, Ministry of Science and Technology, India</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>PURSE Grant- SR/PURSE/2022/124</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Gul</surname><given-names>Nadia</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Anusandhan national research foundation</institution></funding-source><award-id>CRG/2022/000207</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Gul</surname><given-names>Nadia</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Springer Nature Limited 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">The family Solanaceae comprises several economically important flowering plants, including crops that serve various purposes such as food, medicine, and ornamentals. Among the most significant solanaceous vegetables are tomato, eggplant, and pepper, which are known for their numerous health benefits<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. However, these crops are highly susceptible to a range of diseases, with fungal wilt being one of the most destructive, both in terms of incidence and yield loss<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. In India, wilt disease in solanaceous crops has emerged as a severe threat, with disease incidence ranging from 5 to 93%, and yield losses between 45 and 60% due to the invasion of <italic>Fusarium pallidoroseum</italic> in the Kashmir valley<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. Notably, <italic>Fusarium solani sp. melongenae</italic> has been confirmed as the causal agent of wilt in brinjal in Jammu and Kashmir<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>, and several other <italic>Fusarium</italic> species, including <italic>Fusarium chlamydosporum, Fusarium equiseti</italic>, and <italic>Fusarium flocciferum</italic>, have been recently reported as pathogens in chili and brinjal in the Kashmir region<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. The occurrence of wilt disease in the Kashmir valley has been frequent, leading to yield losses ranging from 11.67 to 96.67%<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. <italic>Fusarium</italic> wilt has thus become a major concern in solanaceous crops, especially as the pathogens responsible have diversified across different host species. The current study focuses on the incursion of these wilt-causing pathogens in the Kashmir valley, particularly the movement of <italic>Fusarium</italic> species between various host crops. Traditional identification of <italic>Fusarium</italic> pathogens based on morphological features, such as macroconidia, microconidia, and chlamydospores, has been insufficient due to the complex nature of the Fusarium genus<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>. Thus, DNA sequence-based identification has become an invaluable tool for accurately identifying <italic>Fusarium</italic> species. Molecular techniques, such as DNA barcoding using the internal transcribed spacer (ITS) and translation elongation factor (TEF) genomic regions, as well as the RPB1 and RPB2 genes, have provided clearer insights into the diversity of these pathogens<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. Previous studies have used ITS as a DNA barcoding marker to identify <italic>Fusarium</italic> species, but it has been noted that ITS may not be reliable for closely related species<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. Consequently, conserved genes like TEF have been increasingly employed for phylogenetic analyses in combination with ITS to better resolve species relationships<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. For instance, the TEF gene has proven effective in distinguishing subspecies and has been used by several researchers to clarify species identities within the <italic>Fusarium</italic> genus<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>. In this investigation, we identified <italic>Fusarium avenaceum</italic> as the predominant wilt-causing pathogen in chili and <italic>Fusarium incarnatum</italic> as the primary pathogen in brinjal and tomato. This finding represents a new report of <italic>F. incarnatum</italic> and <italic>F. avenaceum</italic> as causal agents of wilt in solanaceous crops in India. The increasing rate of pathogen invasions, exacerbated by changes in agricultural practices, habitat disturbances, climate change,&#x000a0;and pathogen introduction through trade, further complicates the management of these diseases. This study contributes to the understanding of <italic>Fusarium</italic> species&#x02019; geographical spread and their potential for cross-host infection in solanaceous crops.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Material and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Sample collection and maintenance of cultures</title><p id="Par3">Diseased plants of chili, tomato, and brinjal, showing typical symptoms of wilt disease, were collected from different districts of the Kashmir region, including Pulwama, Srinagar, Baramulla, and Anantnag, during July and August 2020. Samples were randomly selected from various districts of the Kashmir valley. The tissue bit technique was used to isolate the fungus from the infected samples, which were then purified using the single-spore technique. The pure cultures obtained were maintained at 25&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C and stored at 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Morphological and cultural characteristics of the isolated pathogen(s)</title><p id="Par4">The pathogens were cultured on Potato Dextrose Agar (PDA) medium at 25&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C to obtain pure cultures, which were then subjected to morphological studies. Cultures that were 10&#x02013;15&#x000a0;days old were used to prepare semi-permanent slides for microscopic observation. The key characteristics examined included the shape, size, and septation of microconidia, macroconidia, and mycelium.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Identification and pathogenicity test</title><p id="Par5">The pathogens were identified based on their pathological and morphological characteristics. Seedlings of chili (cv. Kashmir Long-1), tomato (cv. Shalimar Hybrid Tomato-1), and brinjal (cv. Local Long) were uprooted and transplanted into the infected potting mixture. The plants were continuously monitored for symptom development until they eventually died, thereby fulfilling Koch&#x02019;s postulates<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>DNA extraction</title><p id="Par6">For DNA extraction, mycelia were crushed in 400&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l of extraction buffer using a mortar and pestle, and the resulting slurry was incubated at 65&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 1&#x000a0;h. After the addition of RNase and a subsequent incubation, sodium acetate was introduced, and the sample was chilled. The lysate was then centrifuged, and DNA was precipitated with isopropanol, pelleted, washed with 70% ethanol, air-dried, and resuspended in Tris&#x02013;EDTA buffer.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>PCR amplification</title><p id="Par7">For PCR amplification, a 25&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l reaction mixture was prepared, with an initial denaturation at 95&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 8&#x000a0;min, followed by 35 cycles of denaturation at 95&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 15&#x000a0;s, annealing based on primer Tm, first extension at 72&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 1&#x000a0;min and a final extension at 72&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 25&#x000a0;min. PCR products were run on a 1% agarose gel with SYBER green dye in 1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;TAE buffer, visualized with a gel documentation system, and compared to a 100&#x000a0;bp DNA ladder. Amplified products from ITS, TEF, RPB1, (Tables <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> and <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>) and RPB2 primers were sequenced by Bionivid Technology for DNA barcoding to analyze genetic variability.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Primers along with sequences and Tm used for amplification of ITS regions.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">S. no</th><th align="left">Primer name</th><th align="left">Primer sequence</th><th align="left">Tm &#x000b0;C</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">K-Lab-FusOxy-ITS1F2 Primer</td><td align="left">5&#x02019;CCTGCGGAGGATCATTA 3&#x02019;</td><td char="." align="char">63.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">K-Lab-FusOxy-ITS4R2 Primer</td><td align="left">5&#x02019;TCCTCCGCTTATTGAT3&#x02019;</td><td char="." align="char">53.6</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Primers along with sequences and Tm used for amplification of TEF region.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">S. no</th><th align="left">Primer name</th><th align="left">Primer sequence</th><th align="left">Tm &#x000b0;C</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">K-Lab-TEF-Fu3-F</td><td align="left">5&#x02019;GGTATCGACAAGCGAACCAT3&#x02019;</td><td char="." align="char">63.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">K-Lab-TEF-Fu3-R</td><td align="left">5&#x02019;TAGTAGCGGGAGTCTCGAA3</td><td char="." align="char">63.8</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Primers along with sequences and Tm used for amplification of RPB1 and RPB2 gene.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">S. no</th><th align="left">Primer name</th><th align="left">Primer sequence</th><th align="left">Tm &#x000b0;C</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">K-Lab-RPB1 -Fa -F</td><td align="left">5&#x02019;CAYAARGARTCYATGATGGGWC3&#x02019;</td><td align="left">55</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">K-Lab-RPB1-G2R -R</td><td align="left">5&#x02019;GTCATYTGDGTDGCDGGYTCDCC3&#x02019;</td><td align="left">55</td></tr><tr><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">K-Lab-RPB2-5F2 -F</td><td align="left">5&#x02019;GGGGWGAYCAGAAGAAGGC3&#x02019;</td><td align="left">55</td></tr><tr><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">K-Lab-RPB2-7CR -R</td><td align="left">5&#x02019;CCCATRGCTTGYTTRCCCAT3&#x02019;</td><td align="left">55</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Sequencing and DNA barcoding</title><p id="Par8">Amplified PCR products using ITS1F2 / ITS4R2 and TEF Fu3 F/ TEF Fu3, RPB1 and RPB2 were outsourced to Bionivid Technology [P] Limited, Bangalore. The genetic variability among collective samples was ascertained through DNA barcoding of ITS, TEF, RPB1 and RPB2 regions. A dendrogram was constructed using Cluster W software.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Results</title><p id="Par9">Tomato and brinjal plants showing wilt symptoms were collected from various regions of Kashmir, including Anantnag, Srinagar, Pulwama, and Baramulla, during July and August 2020. The observed symptoms included yellowing of the plant, lesions on the roots and stems, and wilting or death of the plant. The collected samples were isolated on PDA medium, and pure cultures were maintained at 25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C and stored at 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Cultural characterisation of <italic>Fusarium incarnatum</italic> and <italic>Fusarium avenaceum</italic> infecting tomato, brinjal and chili. (<bold>b</bold>) Morphological characteristics of <italic>Fusarium incarnatum</italic> and <italic>Fusarium avenaceum</italic> causing wilt solanaceous host crops.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_87668_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><sec id="Sec10"><title>Morpho-cultural identification</title><p id="Par10">To identify the pathogen on the host, pure cultures were established on PDA medium, and both were analyzed based on their morphological characteristics. The key features studied included the shape, size, and septation of microconidia, macroconidia, and mycelium (Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). <italic>Fusarium incarnatum</italic>, isolated from tomato and brinjal, initially produced white colonies that gradually turned yellow at the agar base, with a growth of 90&#x000a0;mm after 18&#x000a0;days of incubation at 25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. Microscopic observations revealed that the mycelium was branched and cylindrical, with a width of 3.20&#x02013;4.20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;m. Microconidia were single-celled, hyaline, with 0&#x02013;1 septa, and measured 10&#x02013;12&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;3&#x02013;4&#x000a0;&#x000b5;m. Macroconidia were sickle-shaped, hyaline, 4&#x02013;5 septate, and measured 28&#x02013;31&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;3&#x02013;5&#x000a0;&#x000b5;m. <italic>Fusarium avenaceum</italic>, isolated from the chili host, initially produced white colonies that gradually turned brownish-yellow at the agar base. The fungal culture reached a growth of 90&#x000a0;mm after 18&#x000a0;days of incubation at 25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. The average measurements indicated that the mycelium was branched and cylindrical, measuring 53&#x02013;4.98&#x000a0;&#x000b5;m in diameter. Microconidia were curved, hyaline, with 0&#x02013;2 septa, and measured 11&#x02013;20.2&#x000a0;&#x000b5;m&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;4&#x02013;5&#x000a0;&#x000b5;m. Macroconidia were curved, hyaline, with 5&#x02013;7 septa, and measured 49.9&#x02013;78&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;3.6&#x02013;4.7&#x000a0;&#x000b5;m (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>b).<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Morphological characteristics of the <italic>Fusarium</italic> infecting chili, tomato and brinjal collected from different regions of Kashmir valley.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">S. no</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">Isolate name</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">Mycelium</th><th align="left" colspan="3">Microconidia</th><th align="left" colspan="3">Macroconidia</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Shape</th><th align="left">Size (&#x000b5;m)</th><th align="left">Septation</th><th align="left">Shape</th><th align="left">Size (&#x000b5;m)</th><th align="left">Septation</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">1</td><td align="left"><italic>Fusarium incarnatum</italic></td><td align="left">Branched, cylindrical mycelium</td><td align="left">Single celled</td><td align="left">10&#x02013;12&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;3&#x02013;4&#x000a0;&#x000b5;m</td><td align="left">0&#x02013;1 septate</td><td align="left">Sickle shaped</td><td align="left">28&#x02013;31&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;3&#x02013;5&#x000a0;&#x000b5;m</td><td align="left">4&#x02013;5 Septate</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2</td><td align="left"><italic>Fusarium avenaceum</italic></td><td align="left">Cylindrical</td><td align="left">Curved</td><td align="left">11&#x02013;20.2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;4&#x02013;5</td><td align="left">1&#x02013;2 Septate</td><td align="left">Curved</td><td align="left">49.9&#x02013;78&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;3.6&#x02013;4.7</td><td align="left">5&#x02013;7 Septate</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Pathogenicity test</title><p id="Par11">The seedlings of chili (cv. Kashmir Long-1), tomato (cv. Shalimar Hybrid Tomato-1), and brinjal (cv. Local Long) were potted in the greenhouse. <italic>Fusarium incarnatum</italic>, obtained from the respective crop plant, was used to infect the same potted plant to fulfill Koch&#x02019;s postulates<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. The incubation period for <italic>Fusarium incarnatum</italic> was recorded as four weeks for symptom development, while <italic>F. avenaceum</italic> took six weeks for symptom appearance (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Infected plants exhibited initial symptoms, with leaves discoloring from light green to yellow, followed by drooping, shriveling, and eventually death. The collar region of the plants was cut vertically, revealing brownish spots and discoloration in the vascular bundles, indicating wilt as the cause of death. The pathogens were re-isolated and inoculated from all infected plants. These were compared with the original pure culture inoculates, and the re-isolates resembled the original cultures based on morphological, cultural, and pathogenic characteristics.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Pathogenicity test of different <italic>Fusarium incarnatum and Fusarium avenaceum</italic> species with respect to tomato, brinjal and chili.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_87668_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>DNA Extraction PCR amplification</title><p id="Par12">DNA extraction of isolates followed by PCR amplification was performed for ITS1 and ITS4, TEF, RPB1 and RPB2 primer pairs, and the amplified products were run on 1% agarose gel (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a&#x02013;c). Amplified PCR products were outsourced for sequencing to Bionivid Technology [P] Limited, Bangalore. BLAST was used to find regions of similarity between the query sequence and the sequence present in the NCBI (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.in">www.ncbi.nlm.in</ext-link>) database. The sequences were successfully submitted and Accessioned in GenBank (Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>). <italic>Fusarium incarnatum</italic> and <italic>Fusarium avenaceum</italic> have been first time reported as wilt pathogens of solanaceous host crops (Table <xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref>).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>(<bold>a</bold>) PCR amplification of isolates using ITS&#x000a0;( Lane 4, 7 and 9). (<bold>b</bold>) PCR amplification of isolates using TEF&#x000a0;( Lane 2, 9&#x000a0;and 14). (<bold>c</bold>) PCR amplification of isolates using RPB1 and RPB2 genes. M is 100&#x000a0;bp ladder.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_87668_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Accession numbers of <italic>Fusarium incarnatum</italic> and <italic>Fusarium avenaceum</italic> in NCBI Genbank collected from different districts of Kashmir valley.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">S. no</th><th align="left">Place of collection</th><th align="left">Pathogen identified</th><th align="left">Host plant</th><th align="left">Accession number (ITS)</th><th align="left">Accession number (TEF)</th><th align="left">Accession number (RPB1)</th><th align="left">Accession number (RPB2)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">Pulwama (koel)</td><td align="left"><italic>Fusarium incarnatum</italic></td><td align="left">Brinjal</td><td align="left">OM189449</td><td align="left">OM441190</td><td align="left">OR484033</td><td align="left">OR484035</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">Srinagar (Shalimar)</td><td align="left"><italic>Fusarium incarnatum</italic></td><td align="left">Tomato</td><td align="left">OM189460</td><td align="left">OM441201</td><td align="left">OR484034</td><td align="left">OR484036</td></tr><tr><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">Anantnag (Kokarnag)</td><td align="left"><italic>Fusarium avenaceum</italic></td><td align="left">Chili</td><td align="left">OM189456</td><td align="left">OM441197</td><td align="left">OR640336</td><td align="left">OR640337</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab6"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Diversification of <italic>Fusarium incarnatum</italic> previously reported and new reports with respect to host crops.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Species</th><th align="left">Initially reported in (Host plant)</th><th align="left">New report (Host plant)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4"><italic>Fusarium incarnatum</italic></td><td align="left">Sorghum (<italic>Sorghum bicolor</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="3">Brinjal (<italic>Solanum melongena</italic>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Maize (<italic>Zea mays</italic>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Bell pepper (<italic>Capsicum annuum</italic> L.)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup></td><td align="left">Tomato (<italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>Fusarium avenaceum</italic></td><td align="left">Wheat (<italic>Triticum</italic>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Chili (<italic>Capsicum annuum</italic>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Soybean (<italic>Glycine max</italic>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Phylogenetic analysis</title><p id="Par13">A dendrogram was generated using Cluster W software. The phylogenetic analysis using ITS, TEF and RPB1, RPB2 sequences were carried out (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Phylogenetic relationship of <italic>Fusarium incarnatum</italic> and <italic>Fusarium avenaceum</italic> causing wilt in solanaceous crops using Cluster W.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_87668_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par14">The major solanaceous vegetable crops include tomato, eggplant, chili, and pepper<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. These crops offer numerous health benefits and help combat various diseases. However, the most devastating disease, which is becoming increasingly widespread, is wilt, particularly in terms of incidence and yield loss. <italic>Fusarium</italic> wilt leads to 50&#x02013;80% yield losses annually<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. In the present study, fungi associated with wilt in tomato and brinjal were identified as <italic>Fusarium incarnatum</italic>, while <italic>Fusarium avenaceum</italic> was identified as the pathogen in chili, based on both morphological and molecular characteristics of the pathogens<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. When artificially inoculated using the single-spore technique on the respective hosts, with rhizosphere inoculation on wilted plants, the fungal pathogens isolated from wilted plants exhibited typical disease symptoms. The plants developed initial symptoms by the second week of inoculation. The plants showed complete wilting, beginning with light green to yellowish discoloration of the leaves, followed by drooping, shriveling, and, finally, death of the entire plant by the sixth week of inoculation. Upon vertical cutting of the collar region, the vascular bundles showed brownish discoloration.</p><p id="Par15">Amplification of the internal transcribed spacer (ITS) region using genus- and species-specific ITS primers identified <italic>Fusarium incarnatum</italic> and <italic>Fusarium avenaceum</italic> using primer combinations such as K-Lab-FusOxy-ITS1F2 and Lab-FusOxy-ITS4R2. To further confirm these results, transcription elongation factor (TEF Fu3) amplification was performed with the TEF primer combination (TEF-Fu3-F and TEF-Fu3-R), as well as RPB1 and RPB2 genes. The PCR products of the ITS1-5.8S-ITS4 region, TEF Fu3, and RPB1 and RPB2 genes were sequenced, and the pathogens identified through sequencing were published in GenBank. Sequence alignment using Cluster W revealed that the similarity level among sequences was independent of their geographical origin<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. Furthermore, <italic>Fusarium incarnatum</italic> has previously been reported in crops such as sorghum, rice, maize, and bell pepper, while <italic>Fusarium avenaceum</italic> has been identified in wheat and soybean<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>. In solanaceous crops, these species have been identified as wilt pathogens for the first time in India and the World, highlighting the diversifying nature of <italic>F. incarnatum</italic> and <italic>F. avenaceum</italic> with respect to their host crops, both within solanaceous crops and other host crops. In the phylogenetic study, the ITS, TEF, RPB1, and RPB2 genes were grouped into four distinct clusters. Sequences were compared with their respective hits retrieved from the NCBI database.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par16">This study provides significant insights into the fungal pathogens causing wilt in major solanaceous crops, identifying <italic>Fusarium incarnatum</italic> and <italic>Fusarium avenaceum</italic> as the causal agents in tomato, brinjal, and chili, respectively. These findings were confirmed through morphological analysis, molecular characterization using ITS, TEF, RPB1, and RPB2 gene markers, and pathogenicity testing via artificial inoculation. The phylogenetic analysis and sequencing revealed that these pathogens, though previously reported in other crops like sorghum, rice, maize, wheat, and soybean, are reported for the first time in solanaceous crops in India. This highlights the expanding host range of <italic>F. incarnatum</italic> and <italic>F. avenaceum</italic>, suggesting their evolving adaptability to diverse agricultural systems. The study emphasizes the need for ongoing research and monitoring of <italic>Fusarium</italic> species to understand their host specificity, geographical distribution, and impact on solanaceous crops. Such efforts are crucial for developing targeted management strategies to mitigate the devastating yield losses caused by <italic>Fusarium</italic> wilt in solanaceous vegetable production.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The cost of consumables and research incurred in the investigation was funded by PURSE grant and DST-SERB funding (SR/PURSE/2022/124) and CRG/2022/000207 to Dr. Khalid Z. Masoodi. We thank Dr. Zahoor A. Bhat, Professor, Division of Plant Pathology, SKUAST-Kashmir for Morphological identification and Prof. Nayeema Jabeen,&#x000a0;Head,&#x000a0;Division of Vegetable Science, SKUAST-Kashmir for providing vegetable seeds.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>Funding acquisition K.Z.M. conceptualization K.Z.M. methodology, T.J.P. Supervision, K.Z.M. formal analysis, K.Z.M. data curation, T.J.P, K.Z.M, writing-original draft preparation, T.J.P, M.N. Bioinformatic analysis, K.Z.M, Review and editing K.Z.M., T.P., S.M., S.I.H., M.P., I.A.M., T.A., N.G., All authors have read and approved the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>The cost of consumables incurred and equipment used in the investigation were funded by DST-PURSE grant and DST-ANRF, funding (SR/PURSE/2022/124) and CRG/2022/000207 to Dr. Khalid Z. Masoodi.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The sequencing data is available on the NCBI database. The sequence of ITS with accession numbers OM189449, OM189460, OM189456 were successfully deposited in GenBank (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.in">www.ncbi.nlm.in</ext-link>). The sequence of TEF has been provided Accession Numbers OM441190, OM441201, and OM441197 were successfully deposited in GenBank <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.in">www.ncbi.nlm.in</ext-link>. The sequence of RPB1 and RPB2 with accession numbers OR484033, OR484034, OR484035, OR484036, OR640336 and OR640337 were successfully deposited in GenBank <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.in">www.ncbi.nlm.in</ext-link>. The Fungal material was formally identified by Dr. Zahoor Bhat Plant Pathologist and Dr. Khalid Z. Masoodi Plant Biotechnologist. No voucher specimen is required to be deposited in a publicly accessible herbarium for this study.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par17">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Ethical approval</title><p id="Par18">Molecular identification was done by Dr. K.Z. Masoodi. Voucher specimen have been deposited at K-Lab pathogen repository Division of Plant Biotechnology, SKUAST-K, Shalimar. The experimental research and field studies were carried out in the present investigation and plant collections are in accordance with local legislation and comply with institutional, national, and international guidelines.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Morris, W. &#x00026; Taylor, M. <italic>The solanaceous vegetable crops: Potato, tomato, pepper, and eggplant.</italic> (2017).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manda</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Addanki</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name><surname>Srivastava</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bacterial wilt of solanaceous crops</article-title><source>Int. J. Chem. Stud</source><year>2020</year><volume>8</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1048</fpage><lpage>1057</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.22271/chemi.2020.v8.i6o.10903</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Manda, R. R., Addanki, V. A. &#x00026; Srivastava, S. Bacterial wilt of solanaceous crops. <italic>Int. J. Chem. Stud</italic><bold>8</bold>(6), 1048&#x02013;1057 (2020).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Naik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rani</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Madhukar</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of resistant sources against wilt of chilli (<italic>Capsicum annuum</italic> L.) caused by <italic>Fusarium solani</italic> (Mart.) Sacc</article-title><source>J. Mycopathol. Res</source><year>2008</year><volume>46</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>96</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Naik, M., Rani, G. &#x00026; Madhukar, H. Identification of resistant sources against wilt of chilli (<italic>Capsicum annuum</italic> L.) caused by <italic>Fusarium solani</italic> (Mart.) Sacc. <italic>J. Mycopathol. Res</italic><bold>46</bold>(1), 93&#x02013;96 (2008).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lolpuri, Z., Management of fungal wilt complex of brinjal (<italic>Solanum melongena</italic> L.). Sc.(Ag.) Thesis, SK University of Agricultural Science and Technology. Kashmir, <bold>63</bold>, (2002).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parihar</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Fusarium chlamydosporum, causing wilt disease of chili (<italic>Capsicum annum</italic> L.) and brinjal (<italic>Solanum melongena</italic> L.) in Northern Himalayas: A first report</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2022</year><volume>12</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>20392</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-022-23259-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36437280</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Parihar, T. J. et al. Fusarium chlamydosporum, causing wilt disease of chili (<italic>Capsicum annum</italic> L.) and brinjal (<italic>Solanum melongena</italic> L.) in Northern Himalayas: A first report. <italic>Sci. Rep.</italic><bold>12</bold>(1), 20392 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36437280</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Parihar, T. J., et al., Fusarium flocciferum, causing wilt disease of chili (<italic>Capsicum annuum</italic> L.) in Northern Himalayas: A first report. Plant Disease, (2023).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">WANI, A.H., <italic>Biological control of wilt of brinjal caused by Fusarium oxysporum with some fungal antagonists.</italic> Indian Phytopathology, 2012. 58(2): p. 228&#x02013;231.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hami</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Morpho-molecular identification and first report of <italic>Fusarium equiseti</italic> in causing chilli wilt from Kashmir (Northern Himalayas)</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2021</year><volume>11</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>3610</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-021-82854-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33574410</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Hami, A. et al. Morpho-molecular identification and first report of <italic>Fusarium equiseti</italic> in causing chilli wilt from Kashmir (Northern Himalayas). <italic>Sci. Rep.</italic><bold>11</bold>(1), 3610 (2021).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33574410</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O&#x02019;Donnell</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>DNA sequence-based identification of Fusarium: A work in progress</article-title><source>Plant Disease</source><year>2022</year><volume>106</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1597</fpage><lpage>1609</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/PDIS-09-21-2035-SR</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34907805</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">O&#x02019;Donnell, K. et al. DNA sequence-based identification of Fusarium: A work in progress. <italic>Plant Disease</italic><bold>106</bold>(6), 1597&#x02013;1609 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34907805</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schoch</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Nuclear ribosomal internal transcribed spacer (ITS) region as a universal DNA barcode marker for Fungi</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci.</source><year>2012</year><volume>109</volume><issue>16</issue><fpage>6241</fpage><lpage>6246</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1117018109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22454494</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Schoch, C. L. et al. Nuclear ribosomal internal transcribed spacer (ITS) region as a universal DNA barcode marker for Fungi. <italic>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci.</italic><bold>109</bold>(16), 6241&#x02013;6246 (2012).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22454494</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O&#x02019;Donnell</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>DNA sequence-based identification of Fusarium: Current status and future directions</article-title><source>Phytoparasitica</source><year>2015</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>583</fpage><lpage>595</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12600-015-0484-z</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">O&#x02019;Donnell, K. et al. DNA sequence-based identification of Fusarium: Current status and future directions. <italic>Phytoparasitica</italic><bold>43</bold>, 583&#x02013;595 (2015).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramdial</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Phylogeny and haplotype analysis of fungi within the Fusarium incarnatum-equiseti species complex</article-title><source>Phytopathology</source><year>2017</year><volume>107</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>120</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/PHYTO-05-16-0209-R</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27901448</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Ramdial, H. et al. Phylogeny and haplotype analysis of fungi within the Fusarium incarnatum-equiseti species complex. <italic>Phytopathology</italic><bold>107</bold>(1), 109&#x02013;120 (2017).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27901448</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dita</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A molecular diagnostic for tropical race 4 of the banana Fusarium wilt pathogen</article-title><source>Plant pathology</source><year>2010</year><volume>59</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>348</fpage><lpage>357</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-3059.2009.02221.x</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Dita, M. A. et al. A molecular diagnostic for tropical race 4 of the banana Fusarium wilt pathogen. <italic>Plant pathology</italic><bold>59</bold>(2), 348&#x02013;357 (2010).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Divakara</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular identification and characterization of Fusarium spp. associated with sorghum seeds</article-title><source>J. Sci. Food Agric.</source><year>2014</year><volume>94</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1132</fpage><lpage>1139</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jsfa.6380</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24003016</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Divakara, S. T. et al. Molecular identification and characterization of Fusarium spp. associated with sorghum seeds. <italic>J. Sci. Food Agric.</italic><bold>94</bold>(6), 1132&#x02013;1139 (2014).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24003016</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferniah</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Characterization and pathogenicity of <italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic> as the causal agent of fusarium wilt in chili (<italic>Capsicum annuum</italic> L.)</article-title><source>Microbiol. Indonesia</source><year>2014</year><volume>8</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>5</fpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Ferniah, R. S. et al. Characterization and pathogenicity of <italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic> as the causal agent of fusarium wilt in chili (<italic>Capsicum annuum</italic> L.). <italic>Microbiol. Indonesia</italic><bold>8</bold>(3), 5 (2014).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davey</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Papavizas</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of methods for isolating Rhizoctonia from soil</article-title><source>Can. J. Microbiol.</source><year>1962</year><volume>8</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>847</fpage><lpage>853</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/m62-111</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Davey, C. &#x00026; Papavizas, G. Comparison of methods for isolating Rhizoctonia from soil. <italic>Can. J. Microbiol.</italic><bold>8</bold>(6), 847&#x02013;853 (1962).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sridhar</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajesh</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Omprakash</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A critical review on agronomic management of pests and diseases in chilli</article-title><source>Int. J. Plant Anim. Environ. Sci</source><year>2014</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>284</fpage><lpage>289</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Sridhar, K., Rajesh, V. &#x00026; Omprakash, S. A critical review on agronomic management of pests and diseases in chilli. <italic>Int. J. Plant Anim. Environ. Sci</italic><bold>4</bold>, 284&#x02013;289 (2014).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Thomas, S., Kumar, D. &#x00026; Ali, A. Marketing of Green Chilli in Kaushambi District of Uttar Pradesh, India<italic>.</italic><italic>Int. J. Scientific Engin. Res</italic>., 47&#x02013;48 (2015).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Booth, C., The genus Fusarium commonwealth mycological institute. Kew, Surrey, <bold>237</bold>, (1971)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramdial</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hosein</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Rampersad</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>First report of <italic>Fusarium incarnatum</italic> associated with fruit disease of bell peppers in Trinidad</article-title><source>Plant Disease</source><year>2016</year><volume>100</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>526</fpage><lpage>526</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/PDIS-05-15-0550-PDN</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">Ramdial, H., Hosein, F. &#x00026; Rampersad, S. First report of <italic>Fusarium incarnatum</italic> associated with fruit disease of bell peppers in Trinidad. <italic>Plant Disease</italic><bold>100</bold>(2), 526&#x02013;526 (2016).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gupta, R. Foodborne infectious diseases. In <italic>Food Safety in the 21st Century</italic>, 13&#x02013;28, (Elsevier, 2017)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Uhlig</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jestoi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Parikka</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fusarium avenaceum&#x02014;the North European situation</article-title><source>Int. J. Food Microbiol.</source><year>2007</year><volume>119</volume><issue>1&#x02013;2</issue><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2007.07.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17884217</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">Uhlig, S., Jestoi, M. &#x00026; Parikka, P. Fusarium avenaceum&#x02014;the North European situation. <italic>Int. J. Food Microbiol.</italic><bold>119</bold>(1&#x02013;2), 17&#x02013;24 (2007).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17884217</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>First report of <italic>Fusarium proliferatum</italic> causing root rot in soybean (<italic>Glycine max</italic> L.) in Canada</article-title><source>Crop Protection</source><year>2015</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>52</fpage><lpage>58</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cropro.2014.09.020</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Chang, K. et al. First report of <italic>Fusarium proliferatum</italic> causing root rot in soybean (<italic>Glycine max</italic> L.) in Canada. <italic>Crop Protection</italic><bold>67</bold>, 52&#x02013;58 (2015).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article>