<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Med Internet Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Med Internet Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JMIR</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Medical Internet Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1439-4456</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1438-8871</issn><publisher><publisher-name>JMIR Publications</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Toronto, Canada</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39932775</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11862765</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">v27i1e63824</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/63824</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Paper</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Original Paper</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Understanding Citizens&#x02019; Response to Social Activities on Twitter in US Metropolises During the COVID-19 Recovery Phase Using a Fine-Tuned Large Language Model: Application of AI</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Mavragani</surname><given-names>Amaryllis</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="reviewer"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Hanyin</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="reviewer"><name><surname>Rawat</surname><given-names>Keshav Singh</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib id="contrib1" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>Ryuichi</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0940-3570</contrib-id><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><address><institution/><institution>Institute of Systems and Information Engineering</institution><institution>University of Tsukuba</institution><addr-line>1-1-1 Tennodai</addr-line><addr-line>Tsukuba, 305-8577</addr-line><country>Japan</country><phone>81 08055751714</phone><email>saito.ryuichi.tkb_gw@u.tsukuba.ac.jp</email></address></contrib><contrib id="contrib2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tsugawa</surname><given-names>Sho</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7837-2857</contrib-id></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<institution>Institute of Systems and Information Engineering</institution>
<institution>University of Tsukuba</institution>
<addr-line>Tsukuba</addr-line>
<country>Japan</country>
</aff><author-notes><corresp>Corresponding Author: Ryuichi Saito <email>saito.ryuichi.tkb_gw@u.tsukuba.ac.jp</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>11</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>27</volume><elocation-id>e63824</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>1</day><month>7</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="rev-request"><day>18</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>8</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9;Ryuichi Saito, Sho Tsugawa. Originally published in the Journal of Medical Internet Research (https://www.jmir.org), 11.02.2025.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ext-link-type="uri">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work, first published in the Journal of Medical Internet Research (ISSN 1438-8871), is properly cited. The complete bibliographic information, a link to the original publication on <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.jmir.org/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.jmir.org/</ext-link>, as well as this copyright and license information must be included.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="https://www.jmir.org/2025/1/e63824"/><abstract><sec sec-type="background"><title>Background</title><p>The COVID-19 pandemic continues to hold an important place in the collective memory as of 2024. As of March 2024, &#x0003e;676 million cases, 6 million deaths, and 13 billion vaccine doses have been reported. It is crucial to evaluate sociopsychological impacts as well as public health indicators such as these to understand the effects of the COVID-19 pandemic.</p></sec><sec sec-type="objective"><title>Objective</title><p>This study aimed to explore the sentiments of residents of major US cities toward restrictions on social activities in 2022 during the transitional phase of the COVID-19 pandemic, from the peak of the pandemic to its gradual decline. By illuminating people&#x02019;s susceptibility to COVID-19, we provide insights into the general sentiment trends during the recovery phase of the pandemic.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p>To analyze these trends, we collected posts (N=119,437) on the social media platform Twitter (now X) created by people living in New York City, Los Angeles, and Chicago from December 2021 to December 2022, which were impacted by the COVID-19 pandemic in similar ways. A total of 47,111 unique users authored these posts. In addition, for privacy considerations, any identifiable information, such as author IDs and usernames, was excluded, retaining only the text for analysis. Then, we developed a sentiment estimation model by fine-tuning a large language model on the collected data and used it to analyze how citizens&#x02019; sentiments evolved throughout the pandemic.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p>In the evaluation of models, GPT-3.5 Turbo with fine-tuning outperformed GPT-3.5 Turbo without fine-tuning and Robustly Optimized Bidirectional Encoder Representations from Transformers Pretraining Approach (RoBERTa)&#x02013;large with fine-tuning, demonstrating significant accuracy (0.80), recall (0.79), precision (0.79), and <italic>F</italic><sub>1</sub>-score (0.79). The findings using GPT-3.5 Turbo with fine-tuning reveal a significant relationship between sentiment levels and actual cases in all 3 cities. Specifically, the correlation coefficient for New York City is 0.89 (95% CI 0.81-0.93), for Los Angeles is 0.39 (95% CI 0.14-0.60), and for Chicago is 0.65 (95% CI 0.47-0.78). Furthermore, feature words analysis showed that COVID-19&#x02013;related keywords were replaced with non&#x02013;COVID-19-related keywords in New York City and Los Angeles from January 2022 onward and Chicago from March 2022 onward.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>The results show a gradual decline in sentiment and interest in restrictions across all 3 cities as the pandemic approached its conclusion. These results are also ensured by a sentiment estimation model fine-tuned on actual Twitter posts. This study represents the first attempt from a macro perspective to depict sentiment using a classification model created with actual data from the period when COVID-19 was prevalent. This approach can be applied to the spread of other infectious diseases by adjusting search keywords for observational data.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>COVID-19</kwd><kwd>restriction</kwd><kwd>United States</kwd><kwd>X</kwd><kwd>Twitter</kwd><kwd>sentiment analysis</kwd><kwd>large language model</kwd><kwd>LLM</kwd><kwd>GPT-3.5</kwd><kwd>fine-tuning</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><sec><title>Background</title><p>The global SARS-CoV-2 outbreak, which began in 2020, remains vivid in the collective memory of humanity as of 2024. It is beyond dispute that it was an unprecedented pandemic in human history. For &#x0003e;3 years since the World Health Organization declared the novel COVID-19 a Public Health Emergency of International Concern on January 30, 2020 [<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>], humanity has grappled with COVID-19 as a major social challenge. As of March 2024, the total number of COVID-19 cases has surpassed 676 million, &#x0003e;6 million people have died, and &#x0003e;13 billion vaccine doses have been administered [<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. To assess the scale and severity of the COVID-19 pandemic, it is crucial to confirm public health indicators such as these. While numerous studies have been undertaken to address the pandemic, from artificial intelligence and medical imaging to printing technology [<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], it is also important to conduct sociopsychological observations to understand how citizens have perceived the COVID-19 pandemic.</p><p>We assess public sentiment during the pandemic by analyzing social media posts using natural language processing (NLP) techniques, which have significantly advanced since the 2010s. An NLP-based approach can address the limitations of traditional social science research methods, which are often constrained by limited observational data and the potential for indirect bias from nonrespondents [<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Previous studies that analyzed sentiment during the COVID-19 pandemic can be categorized into 2 main groups. One group focused its investigations on the initial outbreak that occurred in March 2020 [<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>-<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], while the other focused on specific thematic areas, such as vaccination efforts [<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>-<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. However, no study to date has captured the cyclic fluctuations in social sentiment from macro and long-term perspectives because these studies are based on data collected using keywords related to COVID-19, and these words usually reflect negative feelings. Furthermore, despite variations in the spread of COVID-19 between urban and rural areas [<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], many studies have focused on sentiment analysis at the level of language or country, thereby limiting the extraction of insights considering local infection status, which is crucial from a public health perspective.</p><p>Our previous study [<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] analyzed social media posts about citizens&#x02019; activities that were constrained by the pandemic, and the degree of sentiment changed depending on the context of the source observational data instead of COVID-19&#x02013;related texts. In addition, we focused on major American cities such as New York City, Los Angeles, and Chicago, which have similar social conditions. Using this approach, we addressed the problems of previous studies and revealed the general trends of citizens&#x02019; sentiments from December 2019 to December 2021 during the COVID-19 pandemic.</p><p>This study further develops this research and examines the period from December 2021, when the Omicron variants surged, to December 2022, a period when public interest in COVID-19 generally waned. In the United States in 2021, outbreaks caused by the Omicron variant strain continued intermittently, starting with BA.1 at the end of 2021, followed by BA.2 and BA.3 [<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], prompting state governments to issue repeated warnings and subsequently rescind them. The World Health Organization&#x02019;s Public Health Emergency of International Concern ended in May 2023 [<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>], and thus, 2022 can be considered a transition period from the pandemic period to the postpandemic period. We believe it is important to observe citizens&#x02019; sentiments in the United States during this period. In addition, because previous research involving sentiment classification models relied on lexicon dictionaries or training datasets before 2020 when SARS-CoV-2 emerged, the domain adaption between the lexicon dictionary or training data (source domain) and the observational data (target domain) [<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] was not sufficiently considered in NLP. To address this problem, we constructed a sentiment classification model fine-tuned using data extracted under conditions identical to those of the actual observational dataset. Using these methodologies, we propose a definitive approach for estimating social sentiment during the COVID-19 pandemic.</p></sec><sec><title>Objectives</title><p>Sentiment classification methods based on algorithms can be broadly divided as follows: lexicon-based approaches that infer text sentiment from tokens that have been assigned sentiment scores in advance and machine learning approaches that infer text sentiment from models trained on datasets [<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. There are several studies on lexicon-based sentiment analysis during a crisis. A study in Wuhan, China, tracked the change in public sentiment during the first 12 weeks after the identification of COVID-19 by examining posts on Weibo. The study revealed the pattern of trajectories&#x02014;from confusion and fear, through disappointment, frustration, depression, and anxiety, and finally to happiness and gratitude&#x02014;using the Emotion Vocabulary of the Dalian University of Technology [<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. A study in Europe and the United States measured the sentiment toward immigration by examining related tweets in Germany, Italy, Spain, the United Kingdom, and the United States during the early stages of the COVID-19 pandemic. The study estimated the sentiment scores of tweets, using Valence Aware Dictionary and Sentiment Reasoner, and revealed various themes regarding immigration for each country through topic modeling [<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>].</p><p>Some studies on sentiment analysis during crises use machine learning approaches. An analysis in the United States investigated the communication patterns of provaccine and antivaccine users on Twitter (now called X) by visualizing a retweet network related to the measles, mumps, and rubella vaccine during the 2015 California Disneyland measles outbreak. The study classified the users into provaccination, antivaccination, and neutral groups using a support vector machine. The results showed that most of the users were overwhelmingly provaccination, while antivaccine users resided in their own enclosed structural community [<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. A study in the United States also analyzed public perceptions of gig work on Twitter for 2 weeks before and after the COVID-19 emergency declaration. The study trained a machine learning model based on 10 different labels. The results showed that tweets reflected an increased sense of community and concern toward gig workers during the pandemic [<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. An investigation on Instagram demonstrated the changes in hate and misinformation against East Asians that occurred through Meta&#x02019;s content moderation early in the COVID-19 pandemic. The study used supervised machine learning methods to estimate text emotions associated with human faces in posts with the hashtag #coronavirus [<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. A study on Twitter and Weibo revealed a pattern in which negative sentiment peaked before the 2020 lockdowns in many countries, followed by a gradual recovery in sentiment [<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. A study in China examined the psychological impacts of the COVID-19 epidemic declaration on individuals using Weibo data. Findings revealed an increase in negative emotions, such as anxiety and depression, alongside a decrease in life satisfaction and positive emotions using the pretrained psychological prediction model [<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].</p><p>The disadvantage of lexicon-based approaches is that they are highly domain oriented [<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Then, to predict sentiment in a specific domain, such as the discourse space of Twitter during the COVID-19 pandemic, a machine learning&#x02013;based approach using training data, especially a neural network approach, is reasonable in terms of accuracy. This approach involves Transformer-based models with attention mechanisms [<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], which assign weights to tokens based on their relationships, without processing time-series data sequentially, as is done in natural language. Language models such as GPT-1 [<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] and Bidirectional Encoder Representations from Transformers (BERT) [<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], which leverage the Transformer architecture and have undergone extensive pretraining on large datasets, have become readily available tools for NLP tasks.</p><p>A study on Twitter examined how users with different ideological views and follower bases expressed vaccine favorability and specific vaccine-related concerns. Users&#x02019; perception of the vaccine was classified by a fine-tuned BERT model using training data that were coded by the authors. The results from linear mixed-effects models showed a contrast in vaccines between conservative and liberal users, and users with large numbers of followers tended to be more favorable toward vaccines, while those with an average number of followers were prone to be more concerned about vaccines [<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. A study from January 2021 to January 2022 on Twitter used a change-point detection algorithm to identify significant shifts in public sentiment regarding the pandemic. Validation of these findings was accomplished by cross-referencing with contemporaneous news reports. Furthermore, the estimation used BERT fine-tuned with labeled tweets from Kaggle to gauge public attitudes [<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. A study on Twitter and Reddit investigates public sentiment regarding COVID-19 vaccines from January 2020 to March 2022. Using a fine-tuned DistilRoBERTa model, augmented with back-translation, it reveals that Twitter sentiment was predominantly negative, whereas Reddit sentiment was mostly positive [<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. A study in the United Kingdom used a hybrid model, combining Valence Aware Dictionary and Sentiment Reasoner, TextBlob, and BERT, to analyze public perceptions of COVID-19 contact tracing apps on Twitter and Facebook. Results indicated varying sentiments influenced by debates on centralized versus decentralized data handling in app-based contact tracing [<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>].</p><p>In a language model based on the Transformer architecture, there is a pretraining stage in which initial parameters are set and a fine-tuning stage in which parameters are adapted for a specific target task or domain. Given that language models may not possess adequate pretraining on social discourse after major transformative events such as the COVID-19 pandemic, it is appropriate to fine-tune the model using training data with conditions similar to the observed data. Therefore, the following research question (RQ) initially guided our study: <italic>To what extent can the performance of classification tasks be enhanced through the use of posts on Twitter during the pandemic as training data? (RQ1)</italic></p><p>In addition, since 2020, there have been advancements in large language models (LLMs) such as GPT-3, making them capable of not only understanding but also generating sentences [<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. In this paper, we use GPT-3.5 Turbo [<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], which is the latest version that allows fine-tuning, and we ask the following question: <italic>To what extent does GPT-3.5 Turbo enhance the performance of sentiment classification tasks in comparison with conventional Transformer-based models? (RQ2)</italic></p><p>Previous studies have focused mainly on the several months of lockdown starting in April 2020 and the rollout of vaccinations from late 2020 onward, but no study has captured the long-term trend in social sentiment for specific regions during the COVID-19 pandemic period from 2020 to 2023. These tendencies simultaneously indicate the difficulty of analyzing public sentiment during the COVID-19 pandemic from a macro and diachronic perspective. We intend to undertake a long-term and macroscopic observation by targeting text that discusses the social activities of citizens restricted by lockdowns and similar measures implemented in response to the spread of COVID-19, rather than focusing solely on text explicitly containing keywords such as &#x0201c;COVID-19,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;virus,&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;lockdown,&#x0201d; as was the case in the previous studies. According to a study about adaptation to the &#x0201c;new normal,&#x0201d; the term &#x0201c;the new normal&#x0201d; first emerged during the 2008 financial crisis and was used again to point out how the COVID-19 pandemic had changed essential aspects of human life [<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. A study compared risk perception in a sample in April 2021 and January 2022, based on the assumption that the &#x0201c;new normal&#x0201d; involved ongoing restrictions starting with widespread vaccine access and the vaccination of populations considered vulnerable. The study found that people tend to overestimate COVID-19 risks, particularly for children and healthy individuals [<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. This study considers this &#x0201c;new normal&#x0201d; period in the time frame from December 2021 to December 2022 and asks the following question: <italic>To what extent will the cyclical sentiment of citizens toward restricted activities in major US cities during the &#x0201c;new normal&#x0201d; period weaken over time following its peak in December 2021? (RQ3)</italic></p><p>Previous studies focused on observations from countries and language areas such as the English-speaking world. However, a geospatial study showed that the spread of COVID-19 in the United States differed between urban and rural areas even within the same state and that infection status was correlated with each county&#x02019;s social vulnerability and community resilience [<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Moreover, a study that surveyed rural and urban areas during the pandemic showed that rural residents were less sensitive to preventive health behaviors compared with urban residents due to the influence of political ideology or demographic factors [<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. On the basis of these findings, it is imperative to distinguish and analyze urban and rural areas separately, particularly within the US context. Therefore, in this study, we intentionally focused on major urban centers within the United States to estimate social sentiment and asked the following question: <italic>In comparing citizens&#x02019; sentiments across major metropolitan areas in the United States, namely, New York City, Los Angeles, and Chicago, between December 2021 and December 2022, what differences or similarities in sentiment were there? (RQ4)</italic></p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Overview</title><p>We collected posts on Twitter related to restricted activities during the COVID-19 pandemic in New York City, Los Angeles, and Chicago from October 2021 to December 2022. Posts from October 2021 to November 2021 were used to train the sentiment classification model, while posts from December 2021 to December 2022 were used to estimate sentiment and extract feature words. Then, the correlation coefficient between estimated sentiment and actual infected cases was determined. In addition, the complete code for this study is available on the GitHub repository [<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Data Collection</title><p>In this study, we chose the 3 largest cities in the United States according to the US Census Bureau [<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]: New York City, Los Angeles, and Chicago. Specifically, New York County, Los Angeles County, and Cook County were selected as observation targets. In the data collection process, the Full-archive Search Application Programming Interface (API) of Twitter API v2 [<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] was used to retrieve messages posted within a 25-mile radius of the latitude and longitude of the city hall for each city. This radius is the upper limit of the Full-archive Search API, ensuring comprehensive coverage of the urban core. Our observation period was from December 2021, when the emergence of the Omicron variant led to record-high number of cases in the United States, to December 2022, when interest in COVID-19 had waned; this builds on the author&#x02019;s previous study [<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] that estimated sentiment in the same 3 cities from December 2019 to January 2022. Posts from October 2021 to November 2021 were also used as training data for neural network models.</p><p>The search string used for retrieving posts on Twitter uses keywords associated with citizens&#x02019; activities that were constrained by lockdowns and similar measures implemented in response to the COVID-19 pandemic, as described in the study by Saito and Haruyama [<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. These keywords are shown in <xref rid="app1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Multimedia Appendix 1</xref>. The use of these specific keywords enables a coherent overview of the citizens&#x02019; psychological landscape from a macro perspective. These keywords are categorized by restriction type (ie, stay-at-home order, restrictions on gatherings, and travel restrictions) and are specified as arguments for the Twitter API version 2&#x02019;s Search API, using &#x0201c;OR&#x0201d; conditions. In addition, retweets were excluded from the search, and only English posts were retrieved. The retrieved posts were processed to remove noise, including URLs, mentions, and hashtags, followed by text normalization and deduplication, before being used for training and classification with neural networks.</p></sec><sec><title>Observational Data</title><p>We obtained posts from December 2021 to December 2022 using the Search API of Twitter API v2. The total number of posts was 119,437, and the total file size was 34.4 MB. <xref rid="table1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> shows the number of posts by restriction type, and the number of unique users. Moreover, this data collection was conducted during the period from June 15, 2023, to June 22, 2023. For privacy protection, identifying information such as author IDs and usernames was removed, retaining only the text for analysis.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="table1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Number of posts and unique users collected from Twitter between December 2021 and December 2022.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="1000" cellpadding="5" cellspacing="0" border="1"><col width="30" span="1"/><col width="380" span="1"/><col width="210" span="1"/><col width="210" span="1"/><col width="170" span="1"/><thead><tr valign="top"><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">New York City</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Los Angeles</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chicago</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr valign="top"><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">
<bold>Posts, n (%)</bold>
</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stay-at-home order</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12,969 (23.97)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9622 (21.98)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5308 (24.64)</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Restrictions on gatherings</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14,095 (26.05)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13,448 (30.71)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5803 (26.94)</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Travel restrictions</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27,045 (49.98)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20,715 (47.31)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,432 (48.42)</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54,109 (100.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43,785 (100.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21,543 (100.00)</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Unique users, n</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20,575<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17,588</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8948</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table1fn1"><p><sup>a</sup>For 113 tweets in New York City, unique users could not be identified because the author ID could not be obtained. Therefore, they were excluded from this table.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Neural Network Model</title><p>To create a sentiment classifier, we used a Transformer-based neural network model using training data that are searched on the same data source, keywords, geolocation information, and language except for a period as actual observed data.</p><sec><title>Training Data</title><p>As training data, we used Twitter posts obtained using Search API of Twitter API v2.0 under the same search keywords, geolocation, and language as observed data during the period from October 31, 2021, to November 27, 2021. This period was chosen to prevent any overlap with the observation data. The total number of results obtained was 3149, and the retrieved posts were preprocessed, such as noise removal, text normalization, and deduplication. For these pieces of data, an author and 2 Amazon Mechanical Turk (MTurk) workers labeled them as positive, negative, or neutral based on the instructions shown in <xref rid="box1" ref-type="boxed-text">Textbox 1</xref>, and the final label was determined by a majority vote. Tweets that could not be decided by a majority vote because each of the 3 people indicated different opinions were labeled as neutral. Concerning the instructions in <xref rid="box1" ref-type="boxed-text">Textbox 1</xref>, positive and negative sentiments were defined based on the available sentiment by [<xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>], and neutral sentiments were defined by the authors according to the characteristics of the Twitter posts obtained. We also selected workers with master&#x02019;s qualifications who have consistently been recognized for their high performance on Amazon MTurk. In addition, only texts were extracted for individual privacy measures, and due to Amazon MTurk&#x02019;s inability to display 4-byte Unicode Transformation Format-8 emojis, we converted them to HTML spans in the task instructions, ensuring that the workers considered emojis when evaluating emotions. After labeling 3149 posts, the unanimous agreement rate among all 3 evaluators was 55.22% (1739/3149), and the 2-out-of-3 agreement rate was 28.74% (905/3149). The remaining 16.04% (505/3149) of posts were marked as neutral because they were of different values.</p><p>Labeled posts were shuffled and then filtered to extract 2400 instances for training the neural network model. These were then partitioned into training (1800/2400, 75%) and validation (600/2400, 25%) datasets. The remaining 749 instances were reserved for testing purposes. <xref rid="table2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> shows the number of divided posts for each sentiment.</p><boxed-text id="box1" position="float"><caption><title>Instructions for 3 evaluators to create training data and the prompt for GPT-3.5 Turbo for classifying sentiment. In the prompt in GPT-3.5 Turbo, this instruction was modified only to return numerical values such as positive to 0, neutral to 1, and negative to 2.</title></caption><p>
<bold>You are requested to perform sentiment classification (positive, negative, or neutral) for each tweet based on the following rules. These tweets have been collected for the purpose of scientific research.</bold>
</p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Positive sentiments: admire, amazing, assure, celebration, charm, eager, enthusiastic, excellent, fancy, fantastic, frolic, graceful, happy, joy, luck, majesty, mercy, nice, patience, perfect, proud, rejoice, relief, respect, satisfactorily, sensational, super, terrific, thank, vivid, wise, wonderful, zest, expectations, etc.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Negative sentiments: abominable, anger, anxious, bad, catastrophe, cheap, complaint, condescending, deceit, defective, disappointment, embarrass, fake, fear, filthy, fool, guilt, hate, idiot, inflict, lazy, miserable, mourn, nervous, objection, pest, plot, reject, scream, silly, terrible, unfriendly, vile, wicked, etc.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Neutral sentiments: neither positive nor negative, such as text without sentiment, stating a fact, question, news article, advertisement, solicitation, request, quote, unintelligible text, etc.</p></list-item><list-item><p>When the sentiment is mixed, such as expressing both joy and sadness, use your judgment and choose the more strongly expressed emotion.</p></list-item></list></boxed-text><table-wrap position="float" id="table2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Training, validation, and test data for creating the neural network models.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="1000" cellpadding="5" cellspacing="0" border="1"><col width="340" span="1"/><col width="220" span="1"/><col width="210" span="1"/><col width="230" span="1"/><thead><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Data types</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neutral, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative, n (%)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Training data (n=1800)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">648 (36)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">515 (28.61)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">637 (35.39)</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Validation data (n=600)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">225 (37.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">159 (26.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">216 (36)</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test data (n=749)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">270 (36.05)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">214 (28.57)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">265 (35.38)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Training of the Neural Network Model</title><p>For sentiment classification in this research, we adopted GPT-3.5 Turbo, the latest version of GPT-3 that is trained using huge parameters and can be fine-tuned using real data. GPT-3.5 was trained on data up to September 2021, marking a distinction from GPT-3, which used training data through 2019. This difference suggests a substantial potential contribution to the contextual analysis of the globally prevalent COVID-19 pandemic since 2020. In the development of our model, we used gpt-3.5-turbo-1106 as the base model, subsequently fine-tuning it with the training data described in the Training Data section. The model was created using the following hyperparameters: a learning rate multiplier of 2, a batch size of 3, and a total of 3 epochs. These values were automatically optimized by the fine-tuning API based on the size of the training dataset. <xref rid="figure1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref> presents the learning curve, where the x-axis represents the number of steps and the y-axis represents the loss, which indicates how closely the model&#x02019;s predictions align with the actual outcomes. The validation loss, which reflects the model&#x02019;s performance on unseen data, decreases until approximately step 500 but then fluctuates intermittently up to step 1500, suggesting potential overfitting to the training data. Toward the final step, however, the validation loss decreases to 0.39, indicating that the model stabilizes and improves its generalization performance.</p><fig position="float" id="figure1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>The learning curve of fine-tuning GPT-3.5 Turbo.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jmir_v27i1e63824_fig1" position="float"/></fig></sec></sec><sec><title>Ethical Considerations</title><p>The study was conducted using publicly posted large volumes of Twitter data collected via the Twitter API, which is permitted only for academic research but does not involve any human subject research. Furthermore, these posts are not produced within a virtual community on Twitter. Data collection, creation of training and test datasets, and analysis were carried out following Twitter&#x02019;s terms and conditions. In addition, all identifying information, such as author IDs, tweet IDs, display names, and usernames, was excluded, with only the tweet content used for the research. This study also ensures adherence to the guidelines outlined in the study by Luo et al [<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Evaluation of Sentiment Estimation Models</title><p>To evaluate the developed classification model, we compared it with the model Robustly Optimized BERT Pretraining Approach (RoBERTa)&#x02013;large [<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>], which was fine-tuned using the same training data as the developed model, as well as GPT-3.5 Turbo, which was deliberately not fine-tuned. In addition, the following hyperparameters were used in fine-tuning a RoBERTa-large model: a learning rate of 5e-5, a batch size of 16 for training and 64 for validation, and a total of 3 epochs. In both GPT-3.5 Turbo and GPT-3.5 Turbo with fine-tuning, the same prompt (the role&#x02019;s system parameter of the API) was set based on <xref rid="box1" ref-type="boxed-text">Textbox 1</xref>, with the only change being the modification to return numerical values, such as 0 for positive, 1 for neutral, and 2 for negative. Both models also implemented exception handling to skip the output as a value error if the generated text is not numeric. (There was only 1 value error in this evaluation when using GPT-3.5 Turbo with fine-tuning.)</p><p><xref rid="table3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> shows the performance evaluation of each model. Accuracy is the proportion of correctly predicted instances out of all the cases in the test data. Recall is the proportion of correctly predicted instances out of all actual instances for each class (positive, neutral, and negative). Precision is the proportion of correctly predicted instances out of all the cases predicted as each class. Although the neutral class recall was low for all models, with precision remaining relatively stable across all models, GPT-3.5 Turbo with fine-tuning still significantly outperformed the other models in the recall. This difference might have a significant impact on the accuracy difference. <italic>F</italic><sub>1</sub>-score is a metric generally used to evaluate the performance of neural network models, and it provides a balanced assessment by considering both recall and precision. In both models, the <italic>F</italic><sub>1</sub>-score value for the neutral label was much lower than the values for the other labels, which means that the subtle nuances of the boundaries between negative and neutral and between neutral and positive were not sufficiently trained. However, in both models, the <italic>F</italic><sub>1</sub>-scores for the positive and negative labels exceeded 0.80, so we assume that there was no fatal effect on the results. Comparing the 2 models, RoBERTa-large and GPT-3.5 Turbo showed small differences in accuracy and average <italic>F</italic><sub>1</sub>-score, but it can be said that GPT-3.5 Turbo without fine-tuning showed the same performance as RoBERTa-large with fine-tuning.</p><p>RQ1 asks to what extent the performance of classification tasks can be enhanced through the use of Twitter&#x02019;s posts during the pandemic as training data. As shown in <xref rid="table3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>, GPT-3.5 Turbo with fine-tuning had a 5% higher accuracy and a 6% higher <italic>F</italic><sub>1</sub>-score compared with GPT-3.5 Turbo without fine-tuning, which clearly demonstrates the improvement in performance because of fine-tuning. RQ2 asks to what extent GPT-3.5 Turbo enhances the performance of sentiment classification tasks compared with conventional Transformer-based models. GPT-3.5 Turbo with fine-tuning had a 4% higher accuracy and a 7% higher <italic>F</italic><sub>1</sub>-score compared with RoBERTa-large with fine-tuning, which distinctly demonstrates the performance improvement because of large-scale learning. On the basis of the abovementioned results, this study used GPT-3.5 Turbo with fine-tuning.</p><p><xref rid="table4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref> shows examples of sentiments classified and indexed by GPT-3.5 Turbo with fine-tuning. Each tweet is classified as &#x02013;1 for positive, 0 for neutral, or 1 for negative. The higher the value of the index, the more pessimistic the sentiment is throughout the week, and the lower the value, the more optimistic the sentiment.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="table3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Performance evaluation of the neural network models for sentiment classification.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="1000" cellpadding="5" cellspacing="0" border="1"><col width="90" span="1"/><col width="390" span="1"/><col width="150" span="1"/><col width="100" span="1"/><col width="150" span="1"/><col width="120" span="1"/><thead><tr valign="top"><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Model and class</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Accuracy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recall</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Precision</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>F</italic><sub>1</sub>-score</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr valign="top"><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<bold>RoBERTa<sup>a</sup>-large with fine-tuning</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neutral</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<bold>GPT-3.5 Turbo without fine-tuning</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neutral</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<bold>GPT-3.5 Turbo with fine-tuning</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neutral</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table3fn1"><p><sup>a</sup>RoBERTa: Robustly Optimized BERT Pretraining Approach.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="table4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Sample of tweets classified by GPT-3.5 Turbo with fine-tuning.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="1000" cellpadding="5" cellspacing="0" border="1"><col width="820" span="1"/><col width="70" span="1"/><col width="110" span="1"/><thead><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tweets</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sentiment</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0201c;I get you. I feel like masks block my turkey gobbler neck, so, sometimes I don't mind wearing them. That, and they keep my face warm in the winter when I go out. <inline-graphic xlink:href="jmir_v27i1e63824_fig5.jpg"/>.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0201c;teaches you how to be an effective, empathetic leader in 0 lessons that you can find at Shot at our Level-0 complex of stages in Sunset Park! <inline-graphic xlink:href="jmir_v27i1e63824_fig6.jpg"/>. T&#x000f4; learn more about our stages, please visit <inline-graphic xlink:href="jmir_v27i1e63824_fig7.jpg"/>
<inline-graphic xlink:href="jmir_v27i1e63824_fig8.jpg"/>.&#x0201d;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neutral</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0201c;I have both vaccines and just got the booster (which takes a while to kick in). Unfortunately, there are a lot of people who go out unmasked when they&#x02019;re sick and are spreading it like crazy,&#x0201d;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Result of Sentiment Estimation</title><sec><title>Overview</title><p>To answer RQ3 and RQ4, the sentiment was extracted from posts made between November 28, 2021, and December 31, 2022, in New York City, Los Angeles, and Chicago. Similarly, the number of new cases in New York City, Los Angeles, and Chicago between November 28, 2021, and December 31, 2022, was taken from the New York Times COVID-19 data [<xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. The research about the cyclicity of COVID-19 cases reported that in the United States in 2020, the number of new cases was lower on weekends than on weekdays [<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Therefore, the sentiment was expressed as the weekly arithmetic mean of the sentiment score in each period, which was classified as &#x02013;1 for positive, 0 for neutral, and 1 for negative. In addition, a 4-week moving average was applied to the sentiment data to smooth out random fluctuations or noise and to account for sentiment trends preceding the number of infected cases [<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. This value is defined as the sentiment index. At the same time, new cases were aggregated weekly to offset the weekend&#x02019;s effects. The cases were described as a logarithm of 10 to normalize extreme increases due to specific mutant strains. Moreover, these time-series data were plotted on the graph to understand the patterns and trends and to confirm the relevance of each city&#x02019;s timeline. To quantify the degree and confirm the direction of the linear relationship between the sentiment index and new cases, the correlation coefficient was used to extract the main topics and themes that characterize each period when the number of cases increased or decreased.</p></sec><sec><title>New York City</title><p>The left axis of <xref rid="figure2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref> shows the number of cases represented by a logarithmic scale in New York County, New York, and the right axis shows the average sentiment over 4 weeks extracted by GPT-3.5 Turbo fine-tuned with training data. In December 2021, citizens in New York were exposed to a surge in Omicron variant [<xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] cases and subsequently experienced cyclical waves of infections from subvariants such as Omicron BA.2 [<xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>] and Omicron XBB.1.5 [<xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], which became predominant, particularly in the Northeast, by January 2023. Unlike in 2020, when COVID-19 had a high death rate, measures such as stay-at-home orders, bans on large gatherings, and travel restrictions were not enforced by the state government during this period, although mandates such as vaccinations [<xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>] for specific workers and indoor mask wearing [<xref rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>] in clinics were implemented or recommended.</p><p>Here, we performed a statistical test on the sentiment waveform. As shown in <xref rid="table5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>, the correlation coefficient between sentiment and cases is 0.89, indicating a strong positive relationship. This suggests that in New York City, the sentiment of posts related to pandemic restrictions was consistently associated with COVID-19 infection status throughout the period. The correlation between the sentiment of posts related to restrictions on gatherings and cases was relatively weaker at 0.40 than for other types. There is a possibility that certain anxiety about commuting to work, going to school, and traveling may have persisted due to the spread of COVID-19, but it can be assumed that citizens exercised less caution when it came to leisure activities such as going to the movies, going on dates, and shopping.</p><p><xref rid="table6" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref> shows the feature words extracted using term frequency&#x02013;inverse document frequency (TF-IDF) for each period according to the infection status. During December 2021, when infections caused by the Omicron strain spiked, themes related to polymerase chain reaction tests and the Omicron strain were dominant, whereas from January 2022 onward, concerns about COVID-19 ceased to be the main topic. Although <xref rid="table5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref> confirms a strong relationship between sentiment and infection status, the number of posts using keywords related to COVID-19 decreased from the beginning of 2022.</p><fig position="float" id="figure2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>New COVID-19 cases and sentiment index extracted by GPT-3.5 Turbo with fine-tuning in New York City. The closer the sentiment index is to 1, the higher the degree of negativity, while the closer it is to &#x02212;1, the higher the degree of positivity.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jmir_v27i1e63824_fig2" position="float"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="table5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>The correlation coefficient between new COVID-19 cases and sentiment index extracted by GPT-3.5 Turbo with fine-tuning from December 2021 to December 2022.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="1000" cellpadding="5" cellspacing="0" border="1"><col width="30" span="1"/><col width="230" span="1"/><col width="0" span="1"/><col width="210" span="1"/><col width="0" span="1"/><col width="170" span="1"/><col width="0" span="1"/><col width="140" span="1"/><col width="0" span="1"/><col width="130" span="1"/><col width="0" span="1"/><col width="90" span="1"/><thead><tr valign="bottom"><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><italic>df</italic><sup>a</sup> (cases and index pairs)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Average log cases<sup>b</sup></td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Average index<sup>c</sup></td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><italic>r</italic><sup>d</sup> (95% CI<sup>e</sup>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> value</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr valign="top"><td colspan="12" rowspan="1">
<bold>New York City</bold>
</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">52</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">4.3</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x02013;0.1</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.89 (0.81 to 0.93)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x0003c;.001</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stay-at-home order</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">52</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">4.3</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.2</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.69 (0.41 to 0.76)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x0003c;.001</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Restrictions on gatherings</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">52</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">4.3</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x02013;0.1</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.40 (0.15 to 0.61)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x0003c;.001</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Travel restrictions</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">52</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">4.3</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x02013;0.2</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.73 (0.58 to 0.84)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x0003c;.001</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td colspan="12" rowspan="1">
<bold>Los Angeles</bold>
</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">52</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">4.3</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x02013;0.1</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.39 (0.14 to 0.60)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x0003c;.001</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stay-at-home order</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">52</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">4.3</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.2</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.41 (0.17 to 0.61)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x0003c;.001</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Restrictions on gatherings</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">52</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">4.3</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x02212;0.1</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.13 (&#x02212;0.15 to 0.38)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x0003c;.001</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Travel restrictions</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">52</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">4.3</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x02013;0.3</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.52 (0.29 to 0.69)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x0003c;.001</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td colspan="12" rowspan="1">
<bold>Chicago</bold>
</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">52</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">4.0</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x02013;0.1</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.65 (0.47 to 0.78)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x0003c;.001</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stay-at-home order</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">52</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">4.0</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.1</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.63 (0.43 to 0.77)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x0003c;.001</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Restrictions on gatherings</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">52</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">4.0</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x02013;0.1</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.42 (0.18 to 0.62)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x0003c;.001</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Travel restrictions</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">52</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">4.0</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x02013;0.3</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.48 (0.24 to 0.66)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x0003c;.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table5fn1"><p><sup>a</sup><italic>df</italic> calculated as n &#x02013; 2, where n is the number of paired observations.</p></fn><fn id="table5fn2"><p><sup>b</sup>Avg log cases: the average of the logarithmically transformed number of new COVID-19 cases that were summarized on a weekly basis.</p></fn><fn id="table5fn3"><p><sup>c</sup>Avg index: the average sentiment index derived from GPT-3.5 Turbo with fine-tuning that was summarized on a weekly basis.</p></fn><fn id="table5fn4"><p><sup>d</sup>The correlation coefficient between average log cases and average index.</p></fn><fn id="table5fn5"><p><sup>e</sup>95% CI for the correlation coefficient.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="table6"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Feature words extracted by term frequency&#x02013;inverse document frequency in New York City, Los Angeles, and Chicago.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="1000" cellpadding="5" cellspacing="0" border="1"><col width="30" span="1"/><col width="240" span="1"/><col width="0" span="1"/><col width="80" span="1"/><col width="0" span="1"/><col width="650" span="1"/><thead><tr valign="bottom"><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Period</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Trend<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feature words</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr valign="top"><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">
<bold>New York City</bold>
</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">December 2021 to January 2022</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Rise<sup>b</sup></td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x0201c;nye&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;santa&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;<italic>tests</italic>&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;<italic>cases&#x0201d;</italic>, &#x0201c;<italic>pcr&#x0201d;</italic>, &#x0201c;xmas&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;eve&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;playmates&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;<italic>omicron&#x0201d;</italic>, &#x0201c;citymd&#x0201d;</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">January 2022 to March 2022</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Fall<sup>c</sup></td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x0201c;adon&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;magazine&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;partnership&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;snow&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;playmates&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;jorge&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;cric&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;holly&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;ostine&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;har&#x0201d;</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">March 2022</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Rise</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x0201c;adon&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;magazine&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;partnership&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;mfa&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;thesis&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;easter&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;ukraine&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;ecea&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;abortion&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;ladies&#x0201d;</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">May 2022 to June 2022</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Fall</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x0201c;gelato&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;abortion&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;juneteenth&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;britney&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;Imran&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;kele&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;sonny&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;ceremony&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;conference&#x0201d;</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">June 2022 to August 2022</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Rise</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x0201c;taiwan&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;pelosi&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;gelato&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;abortion&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;gyamfua&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;teresa&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;dj&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;speaker&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;supplies&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;nancy&#x0201d;</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">August 2022 to October 2022</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Fall</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x0201c;supplies&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;hurricane&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;marcos&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;dj&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;princess&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;backpacks&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;zuccotti&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;sp&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;sept&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;depot&#x0201d;</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">October 2022 to December 2022</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Rise</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x0201c;thanksgiving&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;exile&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;election&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;pt&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;santa&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;comics&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;thankful&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;profile&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;mets&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;feet&#x0201d;</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">
<bold>Los Angeles</bold>
</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">December 2021 to January 2022</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Rise</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x0201c;shooky&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;<italic>omicron&#x0201d;</italic>, &#x0201c;mang&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;xmas&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;rain&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;nye&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;<italic>tested&#x0201d;</italic>, &#x0201c;eve&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;<italic>vaccinated&#x0201d;</italic>, &#x0201c;pickup&#x0201d;</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">January 2022 to February 2022</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Fall</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x0201c;meye&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;spotify&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;launch&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;vibration&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;return&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;colors&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;reach&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;train&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;katelyn&#x0201d;</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">February 2022 to March 2022</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Rise</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x0201c;drumz&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;ikeboy&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;corey&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;chorus&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;braves&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;platforms&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;speed&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;putin&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;pickup&#x0201d;</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">March 2022 to April 2022</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Fall</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x0201c;anaheim&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;katani&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;axie&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;mace&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;wednesdays&#x0201c;, &#x0201c;mombasa&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;syokimau&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;rd&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;gig&#x0201d;</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">April 2022 to June 2022</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Rise</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x0201c;gun&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;train&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;demand&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;mass&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;lots&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;easter&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;stand&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;anaheim&#x0201c;, &#x0201c;responders&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;dodger&#x0201d;</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">June 2022 to July 2022</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Fall</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x0201c;kbla&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;abortion&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;kele&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;tumi&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;calhope&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;inquiries&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;usc&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;alex&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;folks&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;lots&#x0201d;</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">July 2022 to November 2022</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Rise</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x0201c;halloween&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;return&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;lots&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;train&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;sinners&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;folks&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;stand&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;sharing&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;bday&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;sept&#x0201d;</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">November 2022 to December 2022</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Rise</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x0201c;thanksgiving&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;xmas&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;return&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;folks&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;rain&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;lots&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;picture&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;code&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;oregon&#x0201c;, &#x0201c;stub&#x0201d;</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">
<bold>Chicago</bold>
</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">December 2021 to January 2022</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Rise</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x0201c;christmas&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;<italic>testing&#x0201d;</italic>, &#x0201c;<italic>vaccinated&#x0201d;</italic>, &#x0201c;<italic>vaxxed&#x0201d;</italic>, &#x0201c;winter&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;merry&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;<italic>tested&#x0201d;</italic>, &#x0201c;teachers&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;<italic>tests&#x0201d;</italic>, <italic>&#x0201c;masks&#x0201d;</italic></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">January 2022 to February 2022</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Fall</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x0201c;snow&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;polio&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;valentines&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;n&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;mae&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;quite&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;<italic>vaccine&#x0201d;</italic>, &#x0201c;lens&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;strap&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;rethink&#x0201d;</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">February 2022 to March 2022</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Rise</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x0201c;ukraine&#x0201c;, &#x0201c;creature&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;ukrainian&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;women&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;session&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;uppf&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;group&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;required&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;<italic>vaccine&#x0201d;</italic>, &#x0201c;<italic>masks&#x0201d;</italic></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">March 2022 to May 2022</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Fall</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x0201c;orvieto&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;pauline&#x0201c;, &#x0201c;uppf&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;pagbalik&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;ni&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;fralaine&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;writers&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;wines&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;nevada&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;celebrate&#x0201d;</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">May 2022 to May 2022</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Rise</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x0201c;nra&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;kardashian&#x0201c;, &#x0201c;kourtney&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;send&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;lee&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;government&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;tragedy&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;travis&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;robb&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;families&#x0201d;</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">May 2022 to June 2022</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Fall</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x0201c;national&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;women&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;final&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;logical&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;bush&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;solution&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;event&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;tourists&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;crops&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;alexander&#x0201d;</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">June 2022 to July 2022</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Rise</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x0201c;women&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;abortion&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;highland&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;harris&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;tamil&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;celebrate&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;tornado&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;session&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;send&#x0201d;</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">July 2022 to August 2022</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Fall</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x0201c;bash&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;supplies&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;finkl&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;saudi&#x0201c;, &#x0201c;group&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;biden&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;bag&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;faculty&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;lee&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;jaz&#x0201d;</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">August 2022 to October 2022</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Rise</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x0201c;bark&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;tickets&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;birthday&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;dance&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;dress&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;event&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;n&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;hc&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;downtown&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;celebrate&#x0201d;</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">October 2022 to November 2022</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Fall</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x0201c;halloween&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;dailey&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;juniors&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;sign&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;visiting&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;encouraged&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;hermanos&#x0201c;, &#x0201c;fascism&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;attend&#x0201d;</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">November 2022 to December 2022</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Rise</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x0201c;christmas&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;thanksgiving&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;santa&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;winter&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;merry&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;snow&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;tickets&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;gift&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;storm&#x0201d;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table6fn1"><p><sup>a</sup>Trend denotes the current infection status of COVID-19. &#x0201c;Rise&#x0201d; signifies the period of infection expansion, and &#x0201c;Fall&#x0201d; indicates the decline or conclusion of the infection period.</p></fn><fn id="table6fn2"><p><sup>b</sup>Rise signifies the period of infection expansion.</p></fn><fn id="table6fn3"><p><sup>c</sup>Fall indicates the decline or conclusion of the infection period. Italicized texts in the Feature words column represent words relevant to COVID-19.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Los Angeles</title><p>The left axis of <xref rid="figure3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref> shows the number of cases represented by a logarithmic scale in Los Angeles County, California, and the right axis shows the average sentiment over 4 weeks extracted by GPT-3.5 Turbo fine-tuned with training data. Similar to New York City, Los Angeles experienced an increase in Omicron infections in December 2021 [<xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>], followed by subvariant BA.2 infections in spring 2022 [<xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>] and subvariant BA.5 infections in summer 2022 [<xref rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Unlike in New York City, cases caused by the Omicron subvariant XBB.1.5 were limited in Los Angeles in December 2022 [<xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. During this period, as in New York City, the state government did not order any restrictions on public movements, mainly requiring masks in public indoor settings [<xref rid="ref50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>] and recommending vaccinations for health care workers [<xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>].</p><p>Here, we examine the correlation between sentiment and cases from <xref rid="table5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>. For the total sentiment index and cases pairs, <italic>r</italic> is 0.39, which is lower than that in New York City (<italic>r</italic>=0.89). However, by setting a 2-week lag in cases in the correlation coefficient, it was confirmed that <italic>r</italic> was 0.61 (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;.001). From this, it can be confirmed that in Los Angeles, sentiment preceded infection status. Similar to New York City, there was a relatively high correlation (0.52) between posts related to travel restriction and infection status and a low correlation (0.13) between posts related to restrictions on gatherings and infection status. In addition, as shown in <xref rid="figure3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>, it is notable that although the number of cases decreased since fall 2022, sentiment did not move positively as it did in spring 2022.</p><p><xref rid="table6" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref> shows the feature words extracted for each period according to infection status. In late December 2021 when infections caused by the Omicron strain rose, words related to Omicron and vaccination became common. However, from January 2, 2022, words related to COVID-19 dropped from the top of the TF-IDF scores, following the same trend observed in New York City. This means that although subvariants such as BA.2 and BA.5 appeared after January 2022, public interest in COVID-19 had waned.</p><fig position="float" id="figure3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>New COVID-19 cases and sentiment index extracted by GPT-3.5 Turbo with fine-tuning in Los Angeles.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jmir_v27i1e63824_fig3" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Chicago</title><p>The left axis of <xref rid="figure4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref> shows the number of cases represented by a logarithmic scale in Cook County, Illinois, and the right axis shows the average sentiment over 4 weeks extracted by GPT-3.5 Turbo fine-tuned with training data. In Chicago as well, after the surge of Omicron infection at the end of 2021 [<xref rid="ref52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>], subvariant BA.2 became dominant in spring [<xref rid="ref53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>], and BA.5 replaced it in summer [<xref rid="ref54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. In Illinois, from December 2021 to 2022, vaccination and mask mandates were intermittently issued for specific situations and workers, but as in New York City and Los Angeles, restrictions on movements were also imposed.</p><p>As shown in <xref rid="table5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>, the correlation coefficient between cases and sentiment in Chicago was 0.65 throughout the period, which is lower than that in New York City (0.89) and higher than that in Los Angeles (0.39). Regarding the correlation between cases and sentiment, unlike New York City and Los Angeles, there was a relatively higher correlation (0.63) between sentiment related to stay-at-home orders and cases. In Chicago, concerns about going to school or work may have been higher than concerns about social activities and travel.</p><p><xref rid="table6" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref> shows the feature words extracted for each period according to infection status. Unlike New York City and Los Angeles, we can see that keywords related to COVID-19 were common until March 2022. In Chicago, the indoor mask mandate was lifted [<xref rid="ref55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>], and proof of vaccination in public places was repealed on February 28 [<xref rid="ref56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>], but Chicagoans may have had a more sustained interest in wearing masks and getting vaccinated compared with residents in the other 2 cities.</p><fig position="float" id="figure4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>New COVID-19 cases and sentiment index extracted by GPT-3.5 Turbo with fine-tuning in Chicago.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jmir_v27i1e63824_fig4" position="float"/></fig></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><sec><title>Principal Findings</title><p>Considering the findings presented in the Results section, here we address RQ3 and RQ4. First, we undertake RQ3: &#x0201c;To what extent will the cyclical sentiment of citizens toward restricted activities in major US cities during the &#x02018;new normal&#x02019; period weaken over time following its peak in December 2021?.&#x0201d; Our results indicate a decrease in negative sentiment starting in April 2022, as evidenced by the peak of negative sentiment being below &#x02013;0.05 in New York City (<xref rid="figure2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>) and below &#x02013;0.1 in Chicago (<xref rid="figure4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>), despite the emergence of additional variants such as Omicron BA.2 and BA.5. In contrast to New York City and Chicago, sentiment in Los Angeles remained consistently within 75% of the initial peak observed during the week of December 26, 2021, maintaining this level from August 2022 onward (<xref rid="figure3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>). This phenomenon can be attributed to the relatively modest peak value (&#x02013;0.03) for Los Angeles compared with the peak values of 0.03 in New York City and 0.04 in Chicago during the weeks of January 2 and January 9, 2022. Overall, we confirmed that the tone of the sentiment toward restricted social activities changed from negative to moderate throughout 2022, a trend observed consistently across these 3 US cities. According to the investigation about prolonged pandemic symptoms, significantly lower levels of limiting one&#x02019;s activities were reported among adults aged 18 to 39 years in the United States in June 2022 compared with other age groups [<xref rid="ref57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. This age group overlapped with the Twitter user group [<xref rid="ref58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>], partially supporting the sentiment estimation results.</p><p>Second, we address RQ4: &#x0201c;In comparing citizens&#x02019; sentiments across major metropolitan areas in the United States, namely, New York City, Los Angeles, and Chicago, between December 2021 and December 2022, what differences or similarities in sentiment were there?&#x0201d; In terms of sentiment, the correlation coefficient between New York City and Los Angeles was 0.64, between Los Angeles and Chicago was 0.32, and between Chicago and New York City was 0.60, indicating an overall positive correlation. In feature words extracted by TF-IDF, during the peak of the initial Omicron wave in New York City and Los Angeles, feature words associated with COVID-19 were common; however, they were notably absent in subsequent periods. Meanwhile, in Chicago, feature words related to COVID-19 remained prominent in Twitter&#x02019;s message space until March 2022, indicating sustained interest in COVID-19. From then on, COVID-19&#x02013;related keywords in each city were replaced by words from political contexts such as &#x0201c;Ukraine&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;abortion,&#x0201d; weather-related words such as &#x0201c;hurricane&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;rain,&#x0201d; and other words with unknown contexts. The abovementioned results are consistent with the trend of weakening sentiment throughout 2022.</p><p>Third, we consider the methodology. A novel aspect of our study is the accuracy of the sentiment estimation model, which was developed using Twitter posts extracted under the same conditions as the observed message group focused on COVID-19 awareness among people in 2021. Previous studies relied on data from before 2020, when COVID-19 emerged in the sentiment classification model. In such cases, a domain shift problem is likely to occur between the registered lexicon or training data and the observed data, which would affect the accuracy of the results. This problem remains an issue to be addressed, from conventional neural networks to LLMs, and technical solutions are being discussed [<xref rid="ref59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>,<xref rid="ref60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. We overcame these issues by training the model explicitly on data from the COVID-19 period.</p></sec><sec><title>Comparison With Prior Work</title><p>We compare our results with those of previous studies. The novelty of this study is that it showed a positive correlation over time between sentiment and cases during the &#x0201c;new normal&#x0201d; period. In a similar study, a survey in the Greater London area delved into the recovery of sentiment at the city level during the COVID-19 pandemic and found a gradual recovery in sentiment over time after reopening, similar to the findings of this study [<xref rid="ref61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. However, this study merely confined the visualization of sentiment estimation results to their association with reopening events and did not reveal a correlation with any variables related to COVID-19. In the prior study, sentiment transitioned positively with a delay after reopening events, whereas in our study, sentiment shifted positively concurrently with the issuance of reopening orders. The difference in these results is thought to stem from whether the observed messages associated with keywords related mainly to COVID-19 or to social activities restricted by the pandemic.</p><p>Next, we refer to the previous study conducted by the author [<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], which explored sentiment in New York City, Los Angeles, and Chicago from December 2019 to December 2021, using data collected under the same conditions as in this study. The sentiment waveforms correlated with infection status show the same trend, but the crucial difference is the tendency of feature words related to COVID-19 to appear. Both papers show that feature words related to COVID-19 had high TF-IDF values in New York City and Los Angeles from March 2020 to January 2022 and in Chicago from March 2020 to March 2022. In contrast, after the aforementioned period, feature words associated with COVID-19 did not surface among the top rankings in these 3 cities. In the context of COVID-19, it is plausible that Twitter&#x02019;s message space reverted to a state akin to that of February 2020 after the spring of 2022.</p></sec><sec><title>Limitations</title><p>It is important to acknowledge certain limitations of our study. First, Twitter users in the United States have tended to skew toward the 18- to 39-year age group, which constitutes 62% of the user base [<xref rid="ref58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. Moreover, there was a notable gender bias, with males accounting for 63% of the total users [<xref rid="ref62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. It is essential to recognize that these demographics may not perfectly align with the overall population distribution in the United States. Consequently, our study&#x02019;s observed data may exhibit a slight bias toward younger male demographics. Second, in this study, we estimated citizen sentiment by focusing on activities that were restricted during the COVID-19 pandemic, but these may not necessarily be messages posted in the context of the pandemic. As the goal of this study was to capture the societal atmosphere during the &#x0201c;new normal&#x0201d; period, we did not intend to limit our observations to the context of the COVID-19 pandemic. However, it is important to keep this context in mind as a premise.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>This study estimated citizens&#x02019; sentiment in major cities in the United States, spanning the period from the exponential surge in COVID-19 infections to the gradual abatement of the pandemic as it approached its conclusion. This research makes 3 primary contributions. First, it enhances the performance of the sentiment classifier by fine-tuning the LLM using data under the same conditions as the observed target. The efficacy of this improvement was validated through a comparison with previous models using <italic>F</italic><sub>1</sub>-score metrics. Second, our findings revealed a positive correlation between the estimated sentiment of citizens and actual cases of COVID-19 in New York City, Los Angeles, and Chicago. Although variations exist among these cities, a consistent trend emerged showing a gradual decline in sentiment, which corresponded to a reduction in the number of infections. Third, across these cities in 2022, references to COVID-19 gradually disappeared in the context of restricted social activities as the pandemic neared its end. This phenomenon is evidenced by the disappearance of COVID-19&#x02013;related words in feature words after the spring of 2022.</p><p>The observational data design and sentiment classifier creation method used in this study have potential applications beyond the context of the COVID-19 pandemic. They can be adapted to address various other crises that humanity encounters intermittently, including infectious diseases, natural disasters, terrorism, and warfare. In the future, this field of study is expected to evolve and be applied more broadly to society, supported by stronger collaboration between social science and computer science.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors received no financial support for this study&#x02019;s research, authorship, and publication.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="con"><p>Authors' Contributions: RS contributed to the study&#x02019;s conception, the development of the neural network model, the execution of experiments, and the writing of the manuscript. ST guided the study&#x02019;s direction and conducted a thorough review of the manuscript.</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>Conflicts of Interest: None declared.</p></fn></fn-group><app-group><supplementary-material id="app1" position="float" content-type="local-data"><label>Multimedia Appendix 1</label><p>Keywords related to citizens&#x02019; activities that were constrained by lockdowns and similar measures implemented in response to the COVID-19 pandemic.</p><media xlink:href="jmir_v27i1e63824_app1.pdf" xlink:title="PDF File (Adobe PDF File), 98 KB" id="d100e1779" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></app-group><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term id="abb1">API</term><def><p>Application Programming Interface</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="abb2">BERT</term><def><p>Bidirectional Encoder Representations from Transformers</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="abb3">LLM</term><def><p>large language model</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="abb4">MTurk</term><def><p>Mechanical Turk</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="abb5">NLP</term><def><p>natural language processing</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="abb6">RoBERTa</term><def><p>Robustly Optimized Bidirectional Encoder Representations from Transformers Pretraining Approach</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="abb7">RQ</term><def><p>research question</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="abb8">TF-IDF</term><def><p>term frequency&#x02013;inverse document frequency</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>Coronavirus disease (COVID-19) pandemic</article-title><source>World Health Organization</source><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">2024-06-30</date-in-citation><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.who.int/europe/emergencies/situations/covid-19" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.who.int/europe/emergencies/situations/covid-19</ext-link>
</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>Statement on the fifteenth meeting of the IHR (2005) emergency committee on the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title><source>World Health Organization</source><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">2024-06-30</date-in-citation><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://tinyurl.com/mr3c9854" ext-link-type="uri">https://tinyurl.com/mr3c9854</ext-link>
</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>COVID-19 map</article-title><source>Johns Hopkins Coronavirus Resource Center</source><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">2024-06-30</date-in-citation><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://coronavirus.jhu.edu/map.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://coronavirus.jhu.edu/map.html</ext-link>
</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sood</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Rawat</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Scientometric analysis of ICT-assisted intelligent control systems response to COVID-19 pandemic</article-title><source>Neural Comput Appl</source><year>2023</year><month>06</month><day>27</day><volume>35</volume><issue>26</issue><fpage>18829</fpage><lpage>49</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/S00521-023-08788-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Groves</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nonresponse rates and nonresponse bias in household surveys</article-title><source>Public Opin Q</source><year>2006</year><month>01</month><day>01</day><volume>70</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>646</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/poq/nfl033</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gina Qu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Depicting the emotion flow: super-spreaders of emotional messages on Weibo during the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title><source>Soc Media Soc</source><year>2022</year><month>03</month><day>12</day><volume>8</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>205630512210849</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/20563051221084950</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Shifting moods on Sina Weibo: the first 12&#x02009;weeks of COVID-19 in Wuhan</article-title><source>New Media Soc</source><year>2021</year><month>11</month><day>27</day><volume>26</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>346</fpage><lpage>67</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/14614448211058850</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wijaya</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of #coronavirus content moderation on misinformation and anti-Asian hate on Instagram</article-title><source>New Media Soc</source><year>2023</year><month>08</month><day>04</day><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/14614448231187529" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/14614448231187529</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Palacios</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Guetta-Jeanrenaud</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Obradovich</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global evidence of expressed sentiment alterations during the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title><source>Nat Hum Behav</source><year>2022</year><month>03</month><volume>6</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>349</fpage><lpage>58</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41562-022-01312-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">35301467</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pii">10.1038/s41562-022-01312-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35301467</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The impact of COVID-19 epidemic declaration on psychological consequences: a study on active Weibo users</article-title><source>Int J Environ Res Public Health</source><year>2020</year><month>03</month><day>19</day><volume>17</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>2032</fpage><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.mdpi.com/resolver?pii=ijerph17062032" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph17062032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">32204411</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pii">ijerph17062032</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7143846</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32204411</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lian</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Brauer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Polarization over vaccination: ideological differences in Twitter expression about COVID-19 vaccine favorability and specific hesitancy concerns</article-title><source>Soc Media Soc</source><year>2021</year><month>09</month><day>30</day><volume>7</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>205630512110484</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/20563051211048413</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ly</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kacker</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>She</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Revealing public opinion towards COVID-19 vaccines with Twitter data in the United States: spatiotemporal perspective</article-title><source>J Med Internet Res</source><year>2021</year><month>09</month><day>10</day><volume>23</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>e30854</fpage><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.jmir.org/2021/9/e30854/" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/30854</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">34346888</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pii">v23i9e30854</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8437406</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34346888</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Melton</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bednarczyk</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaban-Nejad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fine-tuned sentiment analysis of COVID-19 vaccine-related social media data: comparative study</article-title><source>J Med Internet Res</source><year>2022</year><month>10</month><day>17</day><volume>24</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>e40408</fpage><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.jmir.org/2022/10/e40408/" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/40408</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">36174192</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pii">v24i10e40408</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9578521</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36174192</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagai-Tanima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Aoyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of fear of infection and sufficient vaccine reservation information on rapid COVID-19 vaccination in Japan: evidence from a retrospective twitter analysis</article-title><source>J Med Internet Res</source><year>2022</year><month>06</month><day>09</day><volume>24</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>e37466</fpage><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.jmir.org/2022/6/e37466/" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/37466</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">35649182</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pii">v24i6e37466</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9186499</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35649182</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Derakhshan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Pham</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cutter</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Urban-rural differences in COVID-19 exposures and outcomes in the South: a preliminary analysis of South Carolina</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2021</year><volume>16</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>e0246548</fpage><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://dx.plos.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0246548" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0246548</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">33534870</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pii">PONE-D-20-31728</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7857563</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33534870</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Haruyama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimating time-series changes in social sentiment @Twitter in U.S. metropolises during the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title><source>J Comput Soc Sci</source><year>2023</year><volume>6</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>359</fpage><lpage>88</lpage><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://europepmc.org/abstract/MED/36405087" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s42001-022-00186-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">36405087</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pii">186</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9660099</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36405087</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anthes</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A C.D.C. airport surveillance program found the earliest known U.S. cases of Omicron subvariants</article-title><source>The New York Times</source><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">2024-04-29</date-in-citation><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/03/24/health/cdc-us-ba2.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.nytimes.com/2022/03/24/health/cdc-us-ba2.html</ext-link>
</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ben-David</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Blitzer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Crammer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of representations for domain adaptation</article-title><source>Adv Neural Inf Process Syst</source><year>2006</year><fpage>137</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://papers.nips.cc/paper_files/paper/2006/file/b1b0432ceafb0ce714426e9114852ac7-Paper.pdf" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7551/mitpress/7503.003.0022</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wankhade</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kulkarni</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A survey on sentiment analysis methods, applications, and challenges</article-title><source>Artif Intell Rev</source><year>2022</year><month>02</month><day>07</day><volume>55</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>5731</fpage><lpage>80</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/S10462-022-10144-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rowe</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahony</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Graells-Garrido</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Rango</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sievers</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Using Twitter to track immigration sentiment during early stages of the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title><source>Data Policy</source><year>2021</year><month>12</month><day>28</day><volume>3</volume><fpage>e36</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/dap.2021.38</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuchard</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Crooks</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Examining emergent communities and social bots within the polarized online vaccination debate in Twitter</article-title><source>Soc Media Soc</source><year>2019</year><month>09</month><day>04</day><volume>5</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>205630511986546</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2056305119865465</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Agrawal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuster</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Britt</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Liberman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cotten</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expendable to essential? Changing perceptions of gig workers on Twitter in the onset of COVID-19</article-title><source>Inf Commun Soc</source><year>2021</year><month>12</month><day>31</day><volume>25</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>634</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/1369118X.2021.2020323</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vaswani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Shazeer</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Parmar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Uszkoreit</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomez</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaiser</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Polosukhin</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Attention is all you need</article-title><source>Adv Neural Inf Process Syst</source><year>2017</year><month>06</month><day>12</day><volume>30</volume><fpage>5998</fpage><lpage>6008</lpage><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://papers.nips.cc/paper_files/paper/2017/hash/3f5ee243547dee91fbd053c1c4a845aa-Abstract.html" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Radford</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Narasimhan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Salimans</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sutskever</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improving language understanding by generative pre-training</article-title><source>OpenAI CDN</source><year>2018</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">2024-04-29</date-in-citation><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://cdn.openai.com/research-covers/language-unsupervised/language_understanding_paper.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://cdn.openai.com/research-covers/language-unsupervised/language_understanding_paper.pdf</ext-link>
</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Devlin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Toutanova</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>BERT: pre-training of deep bidirectional transformers for language understanding</article-title><source>Proceedings of the 2019 Conference of the North American Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics: Human Language Technologies</source><year>2019</year><conf-name>NAACL-HLT '19</conf-name><conf-date>June 2-7, 2019</conf-date><conf-loc>Minneapolis, MN</conf-loc><fpage>4171</fpage><lpage>86</lpage><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://aclanthology.org/N19-1423.pdf" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18653/v1/2024.naacl-short</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Theocharopoulos</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsoukala</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Georgakopoulos</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name><surname>Tasoulis</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Plagianakos</surname><given-names>VP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysing sentiment change detection of COVID-19 tweets</article-title><source>Neural Comput Appl</source><year>2023</year><month>05</month><day>31</day><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://europepmc.org/abstract/MED/37362564" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00521-023-08662-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">37362564</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pii">8662</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10230484</pub-id>--></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cresswell</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tahir</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheikh</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Dom&#x000ed;nguez Hern&#x000e1;ndez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheikh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Understanding public perceptions of COVID-19 contact tracing apps: artificial intelligence-enabled social media analysis</article-title><source>J Med Internet Res</source><year>2021</year><month>05</month><day>17</day><volume>23</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>e26618</fpage><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.jmir.org/2021/5/e26618/" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/26618</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">33939622</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pii">v23i5e26618</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8130818</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33939622</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name><name><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryder</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Subbiah</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dhariwal</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Neelakantan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Shyam</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sastry</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Askell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Agarwal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Herbert-Voss</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Krueger</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Henighan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Child</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramesh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziegler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Winter</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hesse</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sigler</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Litwin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chess</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Berner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>McCandlish</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Radford</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sutskever</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Amodei</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Language models are few-shot learners</article-title><source>arXiv</source><comment>Preprint posted online May 28, 2020</comment><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2005.14165" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>OpenAI platform</article-title><source>OpenAI</source><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">2024-06-30</date-in-citation><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://platform.openai.com/docs/models/gpt-3-5-turbo" ext-link-type="uri">https://platform.openai.com/docs/models/gpt-3-5-turbo</ext-link>
</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Corpuz</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adapting to the culture of 'new normal': an emerging response to COVID-19</article-title><source>J Public Health (Oxf)</source><year>2021</year><month>06</month><day>07</day><volume>43</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>e344</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://europepmc.org/abstract/MED/33683346" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pubmed/fdab057</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">33683346</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pii">6158063</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7989434</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33683346</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Graso</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The new normal: COVID-19 risk perceptions and support for continuing restrictions past vaccinations</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2022</year><volume>17</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>e0266602</fpage><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://dx.plos.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0266602" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0266602</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">35395026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pii">PONE-D-21-17141</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8993013</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35395026</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Callaghan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lueck</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Trujillo</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferdinand</surname><given-names>AO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rural and urban differences in COVID-19 prevention behaviors</article-title><source>J Rural Health</source><year>2021</year><month>03</month><volume>37</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>287</fpage><lpage>95</lpage><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://europepmc.org/abstract/MED/33619836" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jrh.12556</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">33619836</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8013340</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33619836</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>RyuichiSaito1 /COVID 19-Twitter-USA-restoring</article-title><source>GitHub Repository</source><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">2024-04-29</date-in-citation><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/RyuichiSaito1/covid19-twitter-usa-restoring/" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/RyuichiSaito1/covid19-twitter-usa-restoring/</ext-link>
</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>City and town population totals: 2020-2023</article-title><source>US Census Bureau</source><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">2024-06-30</date-in-citation><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.census.gov/data/tables/time-series/demo/popest/2020s-total-cities-and-towns.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.census.gov/data/tables/time-series/demo/popest/2020s-total-cities-and-towns.html</ext-link>
</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>Twitter API</article-title><source>X Developer Platform</source><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">2024-04-29</date-in-citation><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://developer.x.com/en/docs/x-api" ext-link-type="uri">https://developer.x.com/en/docs/x-api</ext-link>
</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jurafsky</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Speech and language processing</article-title><source>Stanford University</source><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">2024-06-30</date-in-citation><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://web.stanford.edu/~jurafsky/slp3/" ext-link-type="uri">https://web.stanford.edu/~jurafsky/slp3/</ext-link>
</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Phung</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rana</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Karmakar</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Shilton</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yearwood</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dimitrova</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name><name><surname>Venkatesh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Berk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Guidelines for developing and reporting machine learning predictive models in biomedical research: a multidisciplinary view</article-title><source>J Med Internet Res</source><year>2016</year><month>12</month><day>16</day><volume>18</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>e323</fpage><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.jmir.org/2016/12/e323/" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/jmir.5870</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">27986644</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pii">v18i12e323</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5238707</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27986644</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ott</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Goyal</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zettlemoyer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Stoyanov</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RoBERTa: a robustly optimized Bert pretraining approach</article-title><source>arXiv</source><comment>Preprint posted online July 26, 2019</comment><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1907.11692" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>COVID-19-data: a repository of data on coronavirus cases and deaths in the U.S</article-title><source>GitHub</source><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">2024-06-30</date-in-citation><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/nytimes/covid-19-data" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/nytimes/covid-19-data</ext-link>
</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soukhovolsky</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Kovalev</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pitt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Shulman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tarasova</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Kessel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Cyclicity of coronavirus cases: "waves" and the "weekend effect"</article-title><source>Chaos Solitons Fractals</source><year>2021</year><month>03</month><volume>144</volume><fpage>110718</fpage><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://europepmc.org/abstract/MED/33531739" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chaos.2021.110718</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">33531739</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pii">S0960-0779(21)00071-0</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7843125</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33531739</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>Omicron is spreading fast. Can New York do more to slow it down?</article-title><source>The New York Times</source><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">2024-02-11</date-in-citation><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/12/22/nyregion/omicron-nyc-spread.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.nytimes.com/2021/12/22/nyregion/omicron-nyc-spread.html</ext-link>
</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>As yet another wave of COVID looms, New Yorkers ask: should i worry?</article-title><source>The New York Times</source><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">2024-02-11</date-in-citation><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/04/07/nyregion/omicron-variant-ba2.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.nytimes.com/2022/04/07/nyregion/omicron-variant-ba2.html</ext-link>
</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>Health experts warily eye XBB.1.5, the latest Omicron subvariant</article-title><source>The New York Times</source><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">2024-02-11</date-in-citation><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/01/07/science/covid-omicron-variants-xbb.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.nytimes.com/2023/01/07/science/covid-omicron-variants-xbb.html</ext-link>
</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>Mayor de Blasio announces vaccine mandate for private-sector workers, and major expansions to nation-leading &#x0201c;key to NYC&#x0201d; program</article-title><source>The City of New York</source><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">2024-02-11</date-in-citation><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.nyc.gov/office-of-the-mayor/news/807-21/mayor-de-blasio-vaccine-mandate-private-sector-workers-major-expansions-to" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.nyc.gov/office-of-the-mayor/news/807-21/mayor-de-blasio-vaccine-mandate-private-sector-workers-major-expansions-to</ext-link>
</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>Health officials urge New Yorkers to wear masks again and visit test to treat clinics as COVID cases rise</article-title><source>CBS Broadcasting</source><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">2024-02-11</date-in-citation><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.cbsnews.com/newyork/news/health-officials-urge-new-yorkers-to-wear-masks-again-as-covid-cases-rise-test-to-treat/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cbsnews.com/newyork/news/health-officials-urge-new-yorkers-to-wear-masks-again-as-covid-cases-rise-test-to-treat/</ext-link>
</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>Coronavirus cases soaring in L.A. county</article-title><source>Los Angeles Times</source><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">2024-02-11</date-in-citation><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2021-12-23/coronavirus-cases-soaring-in-l-a-county" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2021-12-23/coronavirus-cases-soaring-in-l-a-county</ext-link>
</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>California could see coronavirus uptick with BA.2 subvariant</article-title><source>Los Angeles Times</source><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">2024-02-11</date-in-citation><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2022-03-29/spring-omicron-ba-2-wave-is-likely-but-how-big-will-it-be" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2022-03-29/spring-omicron-ba-2-wave-is-likely-but-how-big-will-it-be</ext-link>
</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>Stunning spread of BA.5 shows why this California COVID wave is so different</article-title><source>Los Angeles Times</source><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">2024-02-12</date-in-citation><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2022-07-12/omicron-ba5-coronaviru" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2022-07-12/omicron-ba5-coronaviru</ext-link>
</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref49"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>The XBB.1.5 variant is taking over on the East Coast. Will it happen in California too?</article-title><source>Los Angeles Times</source><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">2024-02-12</date-in-citation><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.latimes.com/science/story/2023-01-05/xbb-1-5-variant-is-taking-over-the-east-coast-will-it-happen-in-california" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.latimes.com/science/story/2023-01-05/xbb-1-5-variant-is-taking-over-the-east-coast-will-it-happen-in-california</ext-link>
</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref50"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>CDPH requires masking for all public indoor settings to slow the spread of COVID-19 in response to increasing case rates and hospitalization</article-title><source>California Department of Public Health</source><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">2024-02-12</date-in-citation><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.cdph.ca.gov/Programs/OPA/pages/nr21-352.aspx" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cdph.ca.gov/Programs/OPA/pages/nr21-352.aspx</ext-link>
</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref51"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>State public health officer order of March 3, 2023</article-title><source>California Department of Public Health</source><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">2024-02-12</date-in-citation><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.cdph.ca.gov/Programs/CID/DCDC/pages/covid-19/order-of-the-state-public-health-officer-health-care-worker-vaccine-requirement.aspx" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cdph.ca.gov/Programs/CID/DCDC/pages/covid-19/order-of-the-state-public-health-officer-health-care-worker-vaccine-requirement.aspx</ext-link>
</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref52"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>Omicron creates &#x02018;fifth wave&#x02019; Of COVID-19 in Chicago, with officials urging people to get tested before holidays</article-title><source>Block Club Chicago</source><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">2024-02-12</date-in-citation><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://blockclubchicago.org/2021/12/22/omicron-creates-fifth-wave-of-covid-19-in-chicago-with-officials-urging-people-to-get-tested-before-holidays/" ext-link-type="uri">https://blockclubchicago.org/2021/12/22/omicron-creates-fifth-wave-of-covid-19-in-chicago-with-officials-urging-people-to-get-tested-before-holidays/</ext-link>
</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref53"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>Sub-lineages of Omicron in Chicago</article-title><source>Chicago Department of Public Health</source><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">2024-02-12</date-in-citation><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.chicago.gov/content/dam/city/sites/covid/reports/2022/Omicron_sub-lineages_Data_Brief_May-2022.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.chicago.gov/content/dam/city/sites/covid/reports/2022/Omicron_sub-lineages_Data_Brief_May-2022.pdf</ext-link>
</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref54"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>&#x02018;The virus not done with us yet': health officials warn of reinfection as BA.5 variant spreads</article-title><source>ABC Eyewitness News</source><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">2024-02-12</date-in-citation><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://abc7chicago.com/covid-19-ba5-variant/12049925/" ext-link-type="uri">https://abc7chicago.com/covid-19-ba5-variant/12049925/</ext-link>
</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref55"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>Illinois indoor masking requirement to end Monday, February 28, 2022</article-title><source>State of Illinois Government</source><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">2024-02-12</date-in-citation><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.illinois.gov/news/press-release.24545.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.illinois.gov/news/press-release.24545.html</ext-link>
</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref56"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>Public health order no. 2021-2 - proof of vaccination in public places (fourth amended and re-issued)</article-title><source>City of Chicago Government</source><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">2024-02-12</date-in-citation><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.chicago.gov/city/en/sites/covid-19/home/health-orders.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.chicago.gov/city/en/sites/covid-19/home/health-orders.html</ext-link>
</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref57"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Slaughter</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Dalton</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Perrine</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Vahratian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Saydah</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long COVID and significant activity limitation among adults, by age - United States, June 1-13, 2022, to June 7-19, 2023</article-title><source>MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</source><year>2023</year><month>08</month><day>11</day><volume>72</volume><issue>32</issue><fpage>866</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.15585/mmwr.mm7232a3" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm7232a3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">37561665</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10415000</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37561665</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref58"><label>58</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>U.S. social network users 2023, by age group</article-title><source>Statista</source><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">2024-06-30</date-in-citation><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.statista.com/statistics/1337525/us-distribution-leading-social-media-platforms-by-age-group/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.statista.com/statistics/1337525/us-distribution-leading-social-media-platforms-by-age-group/</ext-link>
</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref59"><label>59</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ganin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ustinova</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ajakan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Germain</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Larochelle</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Laviolette</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>March</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lempitsky</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Domain-adversarial training of neural networks</article-title><source>J Mach Learn Res</source><year>2016</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.jmlr.org/papers/v17/15-239.html" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-319-58347-1_10</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref60"><label>60</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eisenschlos</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>WinoDict: probing language models for in-context word acquisition</article-title><source>Proceedings of the 17th Conference of the European Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics</source><year>2023</year><conf-name>EACL '23</conf-name><conf-date>May 2-6, 2023</conf-date><conf-loc>Dubrovnik, Croatia</conf-loc><fpage>94</fpage><lpage>102</lpage><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://aclanthology.org/2023.eacl-main.7.pdf" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18653/v1/2023.eacl-main.7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref61"><label>61</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The road to recovery: sensing public opinion towards reopening measures with social media data in post-lockdown cities</article-title><source>Cities</source><year>2023</year><month>01</month><volume>132</volume><fpage>104054</fpage><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://europepmc.org/abstract/MED/36345535" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cities.2022.104054</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">36345535</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pii">S0264-2751(22)00493-0</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9631457</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36345535</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref62"><label>62</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>X/Twitter user distribution by gender in the U.S</article-title><source>Statista</source><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">2024-06-30</date-in-citation><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.statista.com/statistics/678794/united-states-twitter-gender-distribution/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.statista.com/statistics/678794/united-states-twitter-gender-distribution/</ext-link>
</comment></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>