<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">JAMA Netw Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">JAMA Netw Open</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>JAMA Network Open</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2574-3805</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Medical Association</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40402500</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12100449</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2025.12096</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">zld250069</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="category" specific-use="electronic"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Letter</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="online-only"><subject>Online Only</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="subject-area"><subject>Equity, Diversity, and Inclusion</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Medical School Faculty Diversity and the Liaison Committee on Medical Education&#x02019;s Diversity Standards</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="headline">Faculty Diversity and the Liaison Committee on Medical Education&#x02019;s Diversity Standards</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Faculty Diversity and the Liaison Committee on Medical Education&#x02019;s Diversity Standards</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>Mytien</given-names></name><degrees>MS</degrees><xref rid="zld250069aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="zld250069aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fancher</surname><given-names>Tonya L.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><degrees>MPH</degrees><xref rid="zld250069aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chaudhry</surname><given-names>Sarwat I.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="zld250069aff4" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dardik</surname><given-names>Alan</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="zld250069aff5" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref><xref rid="zld250069aff9" ref-type="aff">
<sup>9</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Castillo-Page</surname><given-names>Laura</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="zld250069aff6" ref-type="aff">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ogedegbe</surname><given-names>Gbenga</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><degrees>MPH</degrees><xref rid="zld250069aff7" ref-type="aff">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>Paris</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="zld250069aff5" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Desai</surname><given-names>Mayur M.</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><degrees>MPH</degrees><xref rid="zld250069aff8" ref-type="aff">
<sup>8</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Venkataraman</surname><given-names>Shruthi</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="zld250069aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Campa</surname><given-names>Olivia Marie</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="zld250069aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sage</surname><given-names>Amy</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><degrees>MPP</degrees><xref rid="zld250069aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Boatright</surname><given-names>Dowin</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><degrees>MBA</degrees><degrees>MHS</degrees><xref rid="zld250069aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="zld250069aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Immunobiology, Yale School of Medicine, New Haven, Connecticut</aff><aff id="zld250069aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Emergency Medicine, New York University Grossman School of Medicine, New York</aff><aff id="zld250069aff3"><label>3</label>Division of General Internal Medicine, University of California, Davis, School of Medicine, Sacramento</aff><aff id="zld250069aff4"><label>4</label>Section of General Internal Medicine, Department of Medicine, Yale School of Medicine, New Haven, Connecticut</aff><aff id="zld250069aff5"><label>5</label>Department of Surgery, Yale School of Medicine, New Haven, Connecticut</aff><aff id="zld250069aff6"><label>6</label>National Academies of Science, Engineering, and Medicine, Washington, DC</aff><aff id="zld250069aff7"><label>7</label>Institute for Excellence in Health Equity, New York University Grossman School of Medicine, New York</aff><aff id="zld250069aff8"><label>8</label>Department of Chronic Disease Epidemiology, Yale School of Public Health, New Haven, Connecticut</aff><aff id="zld250069aff9"><label>9</label>Department of Surgery, Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai, New York, New York</aff><author-notes><title>Article Information</title><p><bold>Accepted for Publication:</bold> March 23, 2025.</p><p content-type="published-online"><bold>Published:</bold> May 22, 2025. doi:<uri content-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2025.12096</uri></p><p content-type="open-access-note"><bold>Open Access:</bold> This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link xlink:href="https://jamanetwork.com/pages/cc-by-license-permissions" ext-link-type="uri">CC-BY License</ext-link>. &#x000a9; 2025 Nguyen M et al. <italic>JAMA Network Open</italic>.</p><corresp id="zld250069cor1"><bold>Corresponding Author:</bold> Mytien Nguyen, MS, Yale School of Medicine, 333 Cedar St, New Haven, CT 06510 (<email xlink:href="mytien.nguyen@yale.edu">mytien.nguyen@yale.edu</email>).</corresp><p content-type="author-contributions"><bold>Author Contributions:</bold> Ms Nguyen and Dr Boatright had full access to all of the data in the study and take responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis.</p><p><italic>Concept and design:</italic> Fancher, Chaudhry, Castillo-Page, Boatright.</p><p><italic>Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data:</italic> Nguyen, Chaudhry, Dardik, Ogedegbe, Butler, Desai, Venkataraman, Campa, Sage, Boatright.</p><p><italic>Drafting of the manuscript:</italic> Nguyen, Butler, Campa.</p><p><italic>Critical review of the manuscript for important intellectual content:</italic> Fancher, Chaudhry, Dardik, Castillo-Page, Ogedegbe, Butler, Desai, Venkataraman, Campa, Sage, Boatright.</p><p><italic>Statistical analysis:</italic> Nguyen, Desai, Venkataraman, Campa, Boatright.</p><p><italic>Obtained funding:</italic> Boatright.</p><p><italic>Administrative, technical, or material support:</italic> Castillo-Page, Butler, Boatright.</p><p><italic>Supervision:</italic> Fancher, Chaudhry, Dardik, Butler, Sage, Boatright.</p><p content-type="COI-statement"><bold>Conflict of Interest Disclosures:</bold> None reported.</p><p content-type="funding-statement"><bold>Funding/Support:</bold> Ms Nguyen is supported by the National Institutes of Health (NIH) Medical Scientist Training Program (grant Nos. T32GM136651 and F30AI157227). Dr Boatright is supported by the NIH (grant No. R35GM153263).</p><p><bold>Role of the Funder/Sponsor:</bold> The funder had no role in the design and conduct of the study; collection, management, analysis, and interpretation of the data; preparation, review, or approval of the manuscript; and decision to submit the manuscript for publication.</p><p><bold>Disclaimer:</bold> Dr Ogedegbe is an Associate Editor of <italic>JAMA Network Open</italic> but was not involved in any of the decisions regarding review of the manuscript or its acceptance.The content is solely the responsibility of the authors and does not necessarily represent the official views of the NIH.</p><p content-type="data-sharing-statement"><bold>Data Sharing Statement:</bold> See the <xref rid="note-ZLD250069-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement</xref>.</p><p><bold>Additional Contributions:</bold> This material is based upon data provided by the Association of American Medical Colleges (AAMC). The views expressed herein are those of the authors and do not necessarily reflect the position or policy of the AAMC.</p></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2025-05-22T10:00"><day>22</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>22</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><!--PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>.--><volume>8</volume><issue>5</issue><elocation-id>e2512096</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright 2025 Nguyen M et al. <italic>JAMA Network Open</italic>.</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the CC-BY License.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf-version" xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2512096.pdf">jamanetwopen-e2512096.pdf</self-uri><self-uri content-type="silverchair" xlink:href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamanetworkopen/fullarticle/10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2025.12096"/><abstract abstract-type="teaser" specific-use="electronic"><p>This cross-sectional study evaluates US medical school faculty diversity before and after introduction of the Liaison Committee on Medical Education&#x02019;s diversity standards.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="H1-1-ZLD250069"><title>Introduction</title><p>Diversity among medical school faculty is critical to provide support, belonging, and mentorship to all students, particularly those from marginalized backgrounds.<sup><xref rid="zld250069r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="zld250069r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> In 2009, the Liaison Committee on Medical Education (LCME) introduced 2 diversity accreditation standards requiring every medical school to implement &#x0201c;policies and practices to achieve appropriate diversity among its students and faculty.&#x0201d;<sup><xref rid="zld250069r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> Implementation of these standards led to an increase in female, Black, Hispanic, and Asian medical students.<sup><xref rid="zld250069r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> However, beginning in 2025, the revised standards will not require medical schools to implement policies relating to faculty diversity. This study examines faculty diversity after introduction of the 2009 LCME diversity standards.</p></sec><sec id="H1-2-ZLD250069"><title>Methods</title><p>We used deidentified data from the Association of American Medical Colleges (AAMC) faculty roster, which includes full-time faculty across schools of medicine and affiliated hospitals from 2002 to 2019. This study follows the Strengthening the Reporting of Observational Studies in Epidemiology (<ext-link xlink:href="http://www.equator-network.org/reporting-guidelines/strobe/" ext-link-type="uri">STROBE</ext-link>) reporting guideline for cross sectional studies and met criteria to be exempt from review and need for informed consent by the New York University Grossman School of Medicine&#x02019;s institutional review board because data were deidentified. Sex, race, and ethnicity were self-reported and defined on the AAMC Faculty Roster website.<sup><xref rid="zld250069r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> Race and ethnicity included American Indian, Alaska Native, Native Hawaiian, and Pacific Islander; Asian; Black; Hispanic; and White.</p><p>We defined 3 critical periods for analysis: pre-LCME introduction (2002-2009), implementation (2009-2012), and post-LCME introduction (2012-2019). We calculated annual percentage change (APC) by gender, race, ethnicity, and their intersections, and compared pre-LCME and post-LCME periods using interrupted time series analysis. Statistical significance was defined as a 2-sided <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;.05. Statistical analyses were performed using STATA version 18 (StataCorp). Data were analyzed from September to October 2024.</p></sec><sec id="H1-3-ZLD250069"><title>Results</title><p>The total number of medical school faculty increased from 112&#x02009;247 in 2002 to 187&#x02009;838 in 2019. APC in female faculty did not change after the introduction of the 2009 LCME diversity standards (APC 0.72%; 95% CI, 0.68% to 0.76%; vs 0.76%; 95% CI, 0.73% to 0.79%; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;.06) (<xref rid="zld250069f1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>A).</p><fig position="float" id="zld250069f1" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1. </label><caption><title>Faculty Representation by Sex, Race, and Ethnicity From 2002 to 2019</title><p>Annual faculty representation during 3 critical Liaison Committee on Medical Education (LCME) periods: pre-LCME diversity standards introduction from 2002 to 2009, implementation period from 2009 to 2012, and post-LCME diversity standards introduction from 2012 to 2019. <italic>P</italic>-values within graphs indicate significance from interrupted time series comparison between pre- and post-LCME diversity standards introduction periods (2002-2009 vs 2012-2019).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2512096-g001" position="float"/></fig><p>Among racial and ethnic groups, the decline in APC for White faculty significantly decreased after implementation (&#x02212;0.92%; 95% CI, &#x02212;0.98% to &#x02212;0.86%; vs &#x02212;0.64%; 95% CI, &#x02212;0.72% to &#x02212;0.57%; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;.001) (<xref rid="zld250069f1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>B). APC for White female faculty increased after implementation (0.25%; 95% CI, 0.22% to 0.28% vs 0.17%; 95% CI, 0.14% to 0.19%; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;.001). The decline in APC for White male faculty decreased after implementation (&#x02212;1.09%; 95% CI, &#x02212;1.14% to &#x02212;1.04% vs &#x02212;0.90%; 95% CI, &#x02212;0.96% to &#x02212;0.85%; <italic>P&#x02009;</italic>&#x0003c;&#x02009;.001) (<xref rid="zld250069f2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>). APC in overall Asian faculty significantly decreased after implementation, while there was an APC decrease for Asian male faculty, and an increase for Asian female faculty (Asian: APC, 0.55%; 95% CI, 0.51 to 0.60% vs 0.50%; 95% CI, 0.49% to 0.52%; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;.01; Asian male: APC, 0.26%; 95% CI, 0.22% to 0.30% vs 0.18%; 95% CI, 0.17% to 0.19%; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;.001; Asian female: APC, 0.29%; 95% CI, 0.28% to 0.31% vs 0.32%; 95% CI, 0.31% to 0.33%; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;.01) (<xref rid="zld250069f1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>C, <xref rid="zld250069f2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="zld250069f2" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2. </label><caption><title>Faculty Representation by Intersection of Sex, Race, and Ethnicity From 2002 to 2019</title><p>Annual faculty representation by sex during 3 critical Liaison Committee on Medical Education (LCME) periods: pre-LCME diversity standards introduction from 2002 to 2009, implementation period from 2009 to 2012, and post-LCME diversity standards introduction from 2012 to 2019. <italic>P</italic>-values within graphs indicate significance from interrupted time series comparison between pre- and post-LCME diversity standards introduction periods (2002-2009 vs 2012-2019).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2512096-g002" position="float"/></fig><p>LCME standards were associated with an APC increase for Black faculty (0.00%; 95% CI, &#x02212;0.01% to 0.00%; vs 0.05%; 95% CI, 0.04% to 0.07%; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;.001) (<xref rid="zld250069f1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>D). While APC in Black male faculty was decreasing before 2009, this decline halted after the LCME diversity standards were introduced (&#x02212;0.03%; 95% CI, &#x02212;0.04% to &#x02212;0.02%; vs 0.00%; 95% CI, 0.00% to &#x02212;0.01%; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;.001). After the standards were introduced, APC in Black female faculty slightly increased (0.03%; 95% CI, 0.02% to 0.04%; vs 0.05%; 95% CI, 0.05% to &#x02212;0.06%; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;.001) (<xref rid="zld250069f2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>).</p><p>While the LCME standards were not associated with APC difference for Hispanic faculty (0.11%; 95% CI, 0.09% to 0.13% vs 0.09%; 95% CI, 0.08% to 0.10%; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;.06)., APC increased for Hispanic female (0.06%; 95% CI, 0.05% to 0.08%; vs 0.08%; 95% CI, 0.07% to 0.09%; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;.03) and decreased for Hispanic male faculty (0.04%; 95% CI, 0.03% to 0.05%; vs 0.01%; 95% CI, 0.00% to 0.02%; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;.001) (<xref rid="zld250069f2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>).</p><p>APC in American Indian, Alaska Native, Native Hawaiian, and Pacific Islander faculty significantly decreased after implementation (0.02%; 95% CI, 0.02% to 0.03%; vs &#x02212;0.01%; 95% CI, &#x02212;0.01% to 0.00%; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;.001) (<xref rid="zld250069f1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>F). Similar associations were found for both female and male faculty within this group (female: 0.01%; 95% CI, 0.007% to 0.01% vs &#x02212;0.001%; 95% CI, &#x02212;0.002% to &#x02212;0.003%; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;.001; male: 0.01%; 95% CI, 0.01% to 0.01% vs &#x02212;0.003%; 95% CI, &#x02212;0.005% to &#x02212;0.001%; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;.001) (<xref rid="zld250069f2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="H1-4-ZLD250069"><title>Discussion</title><p>Findings from this study suggest that while the 2009 LCME diversity standards were associated with gains in racial and ethnic diversity for medical students,<sup><xref rid="zld250069r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> the gains for faculty were not uniform. LCME diversity standards&#x02019; greater association with student diversity than faculty diversity may be because medical schools have more direct control over admissions policies, and potentially a more intentional focus on student diversity compared with faculty diversity, while faculty diversity may be constrained by slower hiring cycles and a more limited pool of underrepresented candidates. While representation of Black faculty increased with LCME standards introduction, the overall percentage of Black faculty remain small, and there was no gain for Black male faculty. The lack of Black male faculty in medicine limits role models for all students, particularly Black male students, making it difficult to mitigate the persistent lack of growth of Black men entering medicine. There is a persistent decline in Indigenous faculty, which highlights the need to promote Indigenous matriculants, graduates, and faculty.<sup><xref rid="zld250069r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> This study is limited by other potential factors that may influence faculty hiring, such as a rise in cluster hiring practices. However, with LCME removing faculty diversity requirements in 2025, future research is critical to assess its impact on hiring processes and faculty diversity.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="REF-ZLD250069"><title>References</title><ref id="zld250069r1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Boatright</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nguyen</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hill</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Development of a tool to measure student perceptions of equity and inclusion in medical schools</article-title>. <source>JAMA Netw Open</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<elocation-id>e240001</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.0001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38381434</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zld250069r2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Anderson</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nguyen</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marcotte</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ramos</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gruppen</surname>
<given-names>LD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boatright</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The long shadow: a historical perspective on racism in medical education</article-title>. <source>Acad Med</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>98</volume>(<issue>8S</issue>):<fpage>S28</fpage>-<lpage>S36</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/ACM.0000000000005253</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37071703</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zld250069r3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group><collab>Liaison Committee on Medical Education</collab></person-group>. Liaison Committee on Medical Education (LCME) standards on diversity. <year>2009</year>. Accessed August 19, 2024. <ext-link xlink:href="https://health.usf.edu/~/media/Files/Medicine/MD%20Program/Diversity/LCMEStandardsonDiversity1.ashx?la=en" ext-link-type="uri">https://health.usf.edu/~/media/Files/Medicine/MD%20Program/Diversity/LCMEStandardsonDiversity1.ashx?la=en</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zld250069r4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Boatright</surname>
<given-names>DH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Samuels</surname>
<given-names>EA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cramer</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Association between the Liaison Committee on Medical Education&#x02019;s Diversity Standards and changes in percentage of medical student sex, race, and ethnicity</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>320</volume>(<issue>21</issue>):<fpage>2267</fpage>-<lpage>2269</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2018.13705</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30512090</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zld250069r5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group><collab>Association of American Medical Colleges</collab></person-group>. Faculty roster: U.S. medical school faculty. Accessed December 15, 2024. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.aamc.org/data-reports/faculty-institutions/report/faculty-roster-us-medical-school-faculty" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.aamc.org/data-reports/faculty-institutions/report/faculty-roster-us-medical-school-faculty</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zld250069r6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name><surname>Brodt</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bruegl</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Miller</surname>
<given-names>MF</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The indigenous faculty forum: a longitudinal professional development program to promote the advancement of indigenous faculty in academic medicine</article-title>. <source>Hawaii J Health Soc Welf</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>78</volume>(<issue>12</issue>)(<supplement>suppl 3</supplement>):<fpage>8</fpage>-<lpage>13</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31930195</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list><notes notes-type="supplementary-material" id="note-ZLD250069-1"><supplementary-material id="note-ZLD250069-1-s" position="float" content-type="local-data"><label>Supplement.</label><caption><p>
Data Sharing Statement
</p></caption><media xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2512096-s001.pdf"/></supplementary-material></notes></back></article><!--requester-ID ggemmel-->