<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="abstract"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Eur Psychiatry</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Eur Psychiatry</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">EPA</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>European Psychiatry</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0924-9338</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1778-3585</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11862738</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1192/j.eurpsy.2024.904</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="other">EPV0118</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S0924933824009040</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Abstract</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="section"><subject>e-Poster Viewing</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Sleep disorders in patients with bipolar disorder: age and tobacco consumption correlates</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Razki</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2102" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor0762" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Najar</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2102" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ben Aissa</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2102" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Oumaya</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2103" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bouzid</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2103" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff2102"><sup>1</sup><institution>Razi Hospital</institution>, <city>LaManouba</city></aff><aff id="aff2103"><sup>2</sup>Mental Health Department, <institution>Tahar Maamouri Hospital</institution>, <city>Nabeul</city>, <country>Tunisia</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor0762"><label>*</label>Corresponding author.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="collection" iso-8601-date="2024-04"><month>4</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>67</volume><issue seq="879">Suppl 1</issue><issue-title content-type="special_issue">Abstracts of the 32nd European Congress of Psychiatry</issue-title><fpage>S436</fpage><lpage>S436</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2024</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Author(s)</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article, distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution licence (<uri xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</uri>), which permits unrestricted re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="S0924933824009040a.pdf"/><abstract><sec id="sec4580"><title>Introduction</title><p>Sleep disruptions are frequently observed in individuals with bipolar disorder and have been linked to various unfavorable consequences, such as an elevated risk of relapse and lower quality of life. Nonetheless, the impact of sociodemographic factors on the development and progression of these disruptions remains largely unexplored. Gaining insight into the relationship between sleep disruptions and sociodemographic factors is essential for designing effective interventions and enhancing clinical outcomes for individuals affected by bipolar disorder</p></sec><sec id="sec4581"><title>Objectives</title><p>The objective of this study is to examine the association&#x000a0;between sleep disorders in patients with bipolar disorder II&#x000a0;(BDII) and sociodemographic characteristics.</p></sec><sec id="sec4582"><title>Methods</title><p>This is a cross-sectional, descriptive, and analytical study that was conducted over a one-month period from October 1 to October 31, 2022, with patients attending the follow-up unit of the mental health department at Nabeul Hospital ,Tunisia.The study employed a questionnaire as a tool for data collection, and participants provided voluntary and informed consent before responding. The protection of participant confidentiality and anonymity was carefully observed during all stages of the study.</p></sec><sec id="sec4583"><title>Results</title><p>In this study, we enrolled patients who satisfied the following eligibility criteria: age range of 18 to 60 years, a confirmed diagnosis of type II bipolar disorder based on DSM V criteria, and psychiatric stability as demonstrated by no hospitalization within the preceding 6-month period.</p><p>Our study included a sample of 40 male patients diagnosed with type II bipolar disorder. The participants had a mean age of 36 &#x000b1; 13.2 years, and the majority were unmarried and living with their families or alone. Over two-thirds of the participants had attained a university level of education, while a large proportion of the patients, specifically 80%, reported being regular smokers.</p><p>The results of the study revealed that the mean global score on the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI) was 7.28 &#x000b1; 3.35, indicating an overall low quality of sleep. The majority of the participants, that is 65% (26), had poor sleep quality scores (&#x0003e; 5), while 45% (18) reported experiencing poor sleep (PSQI &#x02265; 8).</p><p>Our analyses further demonstrated that there was a significant association between tobacco consumption and PSQI scores (p=0.003). Additionally, we found that participants who were above 40 years old had a higher likelihood of experiencing sleep disturbances (p=0.0017).</p></sec><sec id="sec4584"><title>Conclusions</title><p>According to the findings of our study, it appears that patients diagnosed with type II bipolar disorder may experience impaired sleep quality, which can be influenced by age and tobacco consumption. These results underscore the need for a holistic approach to patient care that addresses both the biological and sociodemographic factors that can impact sleep in this population.</p></sec><sec id="sec4585"><title>Disclosure of Interest</title><p>None Declared</p></sec></abstract><counts><page-count count="1"/></counts></article-meta></front></article>