<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40394026</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12092764</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1332</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-025-01332-4</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Sleep regularity index as a novel indicator of sleep disturbance in stroke survivors: a secondary data analysis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schruers</surname><given-names>Katrijn B.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Weightman</surname><given-names>Matthew</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Guttesen</surname><given-names>Anna &#x000e1; V.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>Barbara</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Johansen-Berg</surname><given-names>Heidi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Fleming</surname><given-names>Melanie K.</given-names></name><address><email>melanie.fleming@ndcn.ox.ac.uk</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/0080acb59</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.8348.7</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2306 7492</institution-id><institution>Nuffield Department of Clinical Neurosciences, Wellcome Centre for Integrative Neuroimaging (WIN), FMRIB, </institution><institution>John Radcliffe Hospital, University of Oxford, </institution></institution-wrap>Oxford, OX3 9DU UK </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/02jz4aj89</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5012.6</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0481 6099</institution-id><institution>Faculty of Psychology and Neurosciences, </institution><institution>Maastricht University, </institution></institution-wrap>Maastricht, The Netherlands </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>20</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>17510</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>5</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Sleep disturbance is common but often overlooked after stroke. Regular sleep is increasingly recognised as important for overall health, yet little is known about how sleep regularity changes after stroke. This study examined differences in the Sleep Regularity Index (SRI) between stroke survivors and healthy controls using actigraphy data from an existing dataset (~ 1 week per participant). Data were analysed for 162 stroke survivors (mean age 61 &#x000b1; 14 years, 5 &#x000b1; 5 years post-stroke, 89 males) and 60 controls (mean age 57 &#x000b1; 17 years, 32 males). Stroke survivors had significantly lower SRI scores than controls (<italic>p</italic> = 0.001), indicating less regular sleep. In the stroke group, higher SRI correlated with longer total sleep time (<italic>p</italic> = 0.003) and better self-reported sleep quality (<italic>p</italic> = 0.001) but not with other sleep metrics. Lower SRI was associated with worse depressive symptoms (<italic>p</italic> = 0.006) and lower quality of life (<italic>p</italic> = 0.001) but not with disability (<italic>p</italic> = 0.886) or time since stroke (<italic>p</italic> = 0.646). These findings suggest that sleep regularity is disrupted post-stroke and may influence well-being. Future research should explore interventions to improve sleep regularity and related health outcomes in stroke survivors.</p><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1038/s41598-025-01332-4.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Actigraphy</kwd><kwd>Sleep-wake patterns</kwd><kwd>Circadian rhythm</kwd><kwd>Quality of life</kwd><kwd>Post-stroke recovery</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Neurology</kwd><kwd>Sleep disorders</kwd><kwd>Stroke</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/100010269</institution-id><institution>Wellcome Trust</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>222446/Z/21/Z</award-id></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>NIHR Oxford Health Biomedical Research Centre</institution></funding-source><award-id>NIHR203316</award-id></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/501100000627</institution-id><institution>Guarantors of Brain</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Springer Nature Limited 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par4">Stroke is a neurological condition caused by interrupted blood supply to the brain and is one of the leading causes of mortality and disability worldwide<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. Sleep-related impairments are a prevalent, yet often overlooked, complication following stroke<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. Diminished subjective (self-reported) and objective (polysomnography) sleep quality has been commonly reported in comparison with control groups<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>. This is important as disruptions in sleep are thought to exacerbate coexisting symptoms, such as cognitive deficits, fatigue, and depression<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. Moreover, these sleep disturbances may impede rehabilitation trajectories and hinder an individual&#x02019;s capacity to reintegrate into society<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par5">To investigate sleep in stroke survivors, multiple approaches can be taken. Polysomnography (PSG), the gold standard for sleep monitoring, records physiological changes that occur during sleep. However, PSG is typically conducted in sleep clinics utilising specialised equipment and trained personnel, rendering it costly and difficult to access<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. In comparison, actigraphy, which is used to infer sleep based on movement recorded from a sensor on a limb, has demonstrated good sensitivity and accuracy similar to PSG<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. High sensitivity refers to the ability of actigraphy to accurately detect periods of sleep, while its lower specificity indicates a reduced capacity to correctly identify periods of wakefulness. Despite lower specificity than PSG, actigraphy benefits from its capability to be worn continuously in the home environment over multiple days/nights, allowing for the investigation of longer-term sleep patterns<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. In addition to assessing sleep, by leveraging around-the-clock data, actigraphy can also be used to investigate circadian rhythm alterations. This is important as both sleep disturbances and circadian rhythm dysfunctions can be risk factors for, and consequences of, stroke<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>. The circadian rhythm, responsible for controlling the sleep-wake cycle and regulating physiological processes, is vital for overall health<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. Laboratory studies have demonstrated that misalignment between the timing of the sleep-wake cycle and endogenous circadian rhythmicity can impair attention, neurobehavioral performance, mood, and cognition<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. These findings highlight the potential impact of sleep regularity on various aspects of health and well-being of relevance to stroke recovery.</p><p id="Par6">In 2017, Phillips and colleagues<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup> introduced a new metric to measure sleep regularity with actigraphy, named the Sleep Regularity Index (SRI). The SRI is defined as the probability of an individual being in the same state (asleep or awake) at any two time points 24&#x000a0;h apart. Unlike other actigraphy measures, the SRI does not rely on a single main sleep period, making it suitable for individuals with multiple sleep periods throughout the day<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. Lunsford-Avery and colleagues<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup> used the SRI in older adults, finding that less regular sleep was linked to increased cardiometabolic risk, delayed sleep timing, increased daytime sleep and sleepiness, and reduced light exposure, however the SRI was independent of sleep duration. Additionally, they established a link between sleep irregularity and worse depression symptoms in older adults. Furthermore, it has been established that sleep regularity, as measured by the SRI, is more strongly associated with all-cause mortality risk than sleep duration<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. Taken together, these results underscore the importance of circadian rhythm continuity to overall health: however, the SRI has not been investigated in stroke survivors. Exploring the impact of stroke on sleep regularity and its association with other post-stroke effects could enhance our understanding and management of sleep-related issues in stroke patients. We therefore aimed to investigate the SRI in stroke survivors to better understand the differences in comparison to healthy controls, the relationship to self-reported sleep and actigraphy sleep metrics, as well as explore the potential correlations with disability, depression, and quality of life. Our primary hypothesis was that there would be a significant difference in SRI between stroke survivors and healthy controls, with a lower SRI (i.e., less regular sleep) for stroke survivors. We also hypothesised that SRI would correlate significantly with self-reported sleep and actigraphy sleep metrics (sleep fragmentation, sleep efficiency, Wake After Sleep Onset) but not with the Total Sleep Time in line with previous findings showing no association between TST and SRI in older adults<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Sample</title><p id="Par7">We utilised previously acquired datasets at the Wellcome Centre for Integrative Neuroimaging (WIN), University of Oxford. Stroke patients and healthy controls were recruited for several studies spanning from 2017 to April 2024<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. All participants included in the analysis provided informed consent at the time of their initial involvement. All five studies received ethical approval from either the National Research Ethics Service or by the University of Oxford Central University Research Ethics Committee (11/H0605/12, R40803, 22/EM/0080, R85306, 22/LO/0353). All research was performed in accordance with relevant guidelines and regulations, and was performed in accordance with the declaration of Helsinki. We only included participants living in the community, as sleep can be significantly affected by the hospital environment<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>. All studies included stroke survivors aged 18 years or older who were able and willing to provide informed consent. Participants ranged from the sub-acute to chronic phase of stroke recovery, with several studies requiring residual upper limb impairment or an expressed interest in improving sleep. Common exclusion criteria across studies included the presence of other neurological or psychiatric conditions unrelated to stroke, uncontrolled seizures, pregnancy, and current engagement in psychological therapy for insomnia. An overview of all the studies and their respective inclusion/exclusion criteria and any additional study-specific criteria (e.g., untreated or diagnosed sleep disorders prior to stroke or participation in motor tasks) are detailed in Supplementary Table S1. Moreover, the control group was recruited as part of the first included stroke study and consisted of individuals over the age of 18 who provided informed consent and had no history of stroke. Controls were age- and sex-matched to stroke participants in the original study, and recruitment aimed to capture a representative range of sleep experiences&#x02014;from individuals who reported good sleep to those with self-perceived sleep difficulties. Additionally, there are criteria for the actigraphy that should be satisfied to guarantee reliable calculation of the sleep-wake metric, these are detailed under SRI calculation.</p><p id="Par8">As SRI has not previously been investigated in this population, there are no existing studies to guide sample size estimations. Thus, a sensitivity power analysis was performed (calculation of effect size given alpha, power, and available sample size). The data available at the start of the analysis included 184 stroke patients and 70 controls. Therefore, to perform an analysis of covariance (ANCOVA) for the primary outcome to detect the difference in SRI for stroke survivors compared to controls with covariates age and sex, the smallest effect size detectable was f = 0.17 (G*Power v.3.1; alpha = 0.05, power = 80%, <italic>n</italic> = 254 analysis of covariance).</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Measures</title><sec id="Sec5"><title>Actigraphy</title><p id="Par9">Across all studies we used a Motionwatch 8 device<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>, with participants instructed to wear it for approximately one week. If able, participants were directed to press the event marker both when initiating sleep in the evening and upon waking in the morning. Participants were instructed to wear the waterproof actigraphy device continuously, including during bathing and all waking and sleeping hours throughout the recording period. They were also asked to complete a 7-night sleep diary, recording their attempted sleep and final wake times. Stroke survivors were instructed to wear the monitor on their less-affected wrist, controls and non-motor impaired participants were instructed to wear the monitor on their non-dominant wrist. In the current study, the single axis algorithm and peak detection recording mode of the MotionWatch 8 is used, as recommended for sleep recording with this device.</p><p id="Par10">Actigraphy data were automatically classified as sleep or wake for each 30&#x000a0;s interval by the MotionWare programme. The start and end of the sleep period was based on a combination of information from the sleep diary, activity, ambient light, and the utilisation of the event marker. These data were used to calculate the following sleep metrics: Total Sleep Time (TST), sleep fragmentation index, Wake After Sleep Onset (WASO), sleep efficiency and average Sleep Time per 24&#x000a0;h (a full breakdown of how these metrics were calculated can be found in the supplementary materials).</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Calculation of SRI</title><p id="Par11">The Sleep Regularity Index (SRI) used epoch data from actigraphy to calculate the percentage probability of an individual being in the same state (asleep vs. awake) at any two time-points 24&#x000a0;h apart, averaged across the study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. The practical scale of the index ranges from 0 (completely random sleep/wake patterns) to 100 (perfectly consistent sleep/wake patterns)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup> and can then be used to classify individuals as Regular (top quintile) or Irregular (bottom quintile) sleepers<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. The current computation utilizes the 30-second epochs extracted from MotionWare and is in accordance with the calculations from Lunsford Avery et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. Considering N days of recording segmented into M daily epochs, <inline-formula id="IEq1"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e394">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:{s}_{i,j}$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_1332_Article_IEq1.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> = 1 indicates the participant&#x02019;s sleep status on day <italic>i</italic> during epoch <italic>j</italic>, and <inline-formula id="IEq2"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e407">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:{s}_{i,j}$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_1332_Article_IEq1.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> = 0 indicates wakefulness. The SRI is then computed using the following Eq.&#x000a0;(<xref rid="Equ1" ref-type="disp-formula">1</xref>), where <inline-formula id="IEq3"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e416">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:\delta\:\left({s}_{i,j},{s}_{i+1,j}\right)$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_1332_Article_IEq3.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> = 1 if <inline-formula id="IEq4"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e422">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:{s}_{i,j}$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_1332_Article_IEq1.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> = <inline-formula id="IEq5"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e429">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:{s}_{i+1,j}$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_1332_Article_IEq5.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and 0 otherwise.</p><p id="Par12">
<disp-formula id="Equ1"><label>1</label><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e437">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$- 100 + \frac{{200}}{{M\left( {N - 1} \right)}}\mathop \sum \limits_{{j = 1}}^{M} \mathop \sum \limits_{{i = 1}}^{{N - 1}} \delta \left( {s_{{i,j}} ,s_{{i + 1,j}} } \right)$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_1332_Article_Equ1.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>
</p><p id="Par13">To guarantee a reliable calculation of the SRI, several criteria have been reported<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. First, to guarantee sufficient data, participants must have at least five valid wear days (i.e. 5 full rounded days). Second, previous studies report that each participant should ideally have a weekend day included in the recording. Third, participants should not have &#x0003e; 2&#x000a0;h of no recording (i.e. device off or not worn) in their duration of wearing the device<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par14">These criteria were visually inspected per participant. Where these criteria were not satisfied, the recording was ruled invalid and excluded from analysis. 36 participants (26 patients/10 controls) were excluded based on these criteria, resulting in a final sample size of 222 (162 patients/60 controls).</p><p id="Par15">Actigraphy demonstrates greater sensitivity compared to specificity, indicating proficiency in identifying periods of sleep, but relative ineffectiveness in accurately detecting wakefulness<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. The SRI is unique in that it considers both daytime and night-time activity, necessitating a resolution to this inaccuracy while maintaining the distinctive capability to detect periods of sleep during the day, e.g. naps. To address this issue and enhance the reliability of recordings for SRI calculations, specialised algorithms can be implemented; the current study used the UCSD algorithm (with a scaling factor of 0.10) and applied Webster&#x02019;s rescoring rules. To ensure transparency and accurate comparison between research studies, our procedure and refinements are detailed in supplementary materials (S2).</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Questionnaires</title><p id="Par16">Self-reported sleep in both the healthy control and stroke cohort was assessed with the Sleep Condition Indicator (SCI; range 0&#x02013;32), a valid and reliable method to diagnose DSM-5 insomnia disorder and symptoms post-stroke<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. For solely the stroke cohort, depression scores were assessed with the Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ-8; range 0&#x02013;24, higher score indicates more severe depressive symptoms)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. Post-stroke disability was assessed with the modified Rankin Scale (mRS; score range 0= &#x0201c;no symptoms at all&#x0201d; to 6=&#x0201c;death&#x0201d;)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. Finally, quality of life was assessed with short-form Stroke Impact Scale (SF-SIS; max score 100, higher score indicates better quality of life)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par17">Analyses were conducted with Python (v.3.10.12), RStudio (R v.4.3.2) and MotionWare (v.1.3.33). Plots were created with GraphPad Prism (v.10.2.3). To compare age between groups, a Welch Two Sample t-test was performed, as it accommodates unequal variances and different sample sizes. To test the relationship between pairs of categorical variables (e.g. sex and group) a chi-square test was performed. To test the primary hypothesis that stroke survivors have a lower SRI than controls, an analysis of covariance (ANCOVA) was planned, with age and sex as covariates. However, the assumption of non-interaction in an ANCOVA model was violated. Therefore, a linear regression model was used instead. Testing of assumptions and further details can be found in supplementary materials (S3). To test whether the SRI relates to standard questionnaire and actigraphy-derived sleep metrics Pearson&#x02019;s correlations were used (adjusted for age and sex) with Bonferroni correction for the multiple comparisons of the sleep metrics (&#x003b1; = 0.01; analysis details in supplementary S3). To ascertain if the strength of these correlations differs between groups, a Fisher&#x02019;s R to Z-test was performed. Interpretation of Pearson&#x02019;s correlations coefficients are reported according to the following guidelines: <italic>r</italic> &#x0003c; 0.4, weak; 0.4 &#x02264; <italic>r</italic> &#x02264; 0.7, moderate; and <italic>r</italic> &#x0003e; 0.7, strong<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>, all confidence Intervals (CIs) are reported at the 95% level and p-values were computed using a Wald t-distribution approximation.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec10"><title>Demographics and descriptive statistics SRI</title><p id="Par18">The final dataset included 162 stroke survivors (mean (&#x000b1; sd) 61 (&#x000b1; 14) years of age, 5 (&#x000b1; 5) years post-stroke, 89 males) and 60 healthy controls (57 (&#x000b1; 17) years of age, 32 males; Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). There was no significant difference in age (t(89.06) = 1.51, <italic>p</italic> = 0.135) or sex distribution (&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup> = 3.78e-03, <italic>p</italic> = 0.951) between the groups.</p><p id="Par19">
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Participant Characteristics.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Demographics</th><th align="left">Stroke survivors</th><th align="left">Healthy controls</th><th align="left">
<italic>P</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">n</td><td align="left">162</td><td align="left">60</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Sex, Female (n %)</td><td align="left">73 (45.1)</td><td align="left">28 (46.7)</td><td char="." align="char">0.951</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Age (years)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Mean (SD)</td><td align="left">61 (&#x000b1; 14)</td><td align="left">57 (&#x000b1; 17)</td><td char="." align="char">0.135</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Range</td><td align="left">20&#x02013;89</td><td align="left">19&#x02013;83</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Time since stroke (years)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Mean (SD)</td><td align="left">5 (&#x000b1; 5)</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Range (months)</td><td align="left">1&#x02013;312</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Disability (<italic>n</italic> = 54)</td><td align="left">2.28 (&#x000b1; 1.00)</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Depression (<italic>n</italic> = 116)</td><td align="left">8.80 (&#x000b1; 5.38)</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Quality of life (<italic>n</italic> = 62)</td><td align="left">26.68 (&#x000b1; 5.44)</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>F</italic> = female, <italic>M</italic> = male. Measures for the stroke group only include the modified Rankin Scale (mRS) for disability patient health questionnaire (PHQ-8) for depression and short form stroke impact scale (SF-SIS) for quality of life.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par20">The mean (&#x000b1; sd) SRI for the stroke cohort was 41.21 (&#x000b1; 12.58) and values ranged from 16.03 to 74.00. For the healthy controls, the mean (&#x000b1; sd) was 47.80 (&#x000b1; 11.74) and the values ranged from 21.72 to 72.94 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).</p><p id="Par21">
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Relationship between sleep regularity (SRI) and total sleep time (TST) for the stroke cohort (dashed line) and healthy controls (solid line). Plots that show the sleep/wake cycle according to the SRI calculation for four participants, two classified as irregular sleepers (<bold>B</bold> = stroke, <bold>C</bold> = control), with SRI values in the first quintile, and two regular sleepers (<bold>D</bold> = stroke, <bold>E</bold> = control), with SRI values in the fifth quintile. The colours reflect &#x02018;irregular&#x02019; (pink), &#x02018;normal&#x02019; (orange) and &#x02018;regular&#x02019; (teal) sleepers. The figure displays results from the current analysis, though the design is based on similar figures created by other studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_1332_Fig1_HTML" id="d33e684"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Difference in sleep regularity between stroke survivors and healthy controls</title><p id="Par22">SRI values are shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>. To test for differences between groups, a linear regression model employing Ordinary Least Squares (OLS) estimation was utilised to predict SRI based on the factors Group (0 = Control, 1 = Stroke), Age, and Sex. The linear regression model accounted for a significant but weak proportion of the variance in SRI (R<sup>2</sup> = 0.12, F(3, 218) = 10.00, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001, adj. R<sup>2</sup> = 0.11). Within this model, the effect of Group was significant and negative (&#x003b2; = -6.07, 95% CI [-9.65, -2.48], t(218) = -3.33, <italic>p</italic> = 0.001; Std. &#x003b2; = -0.48, 95% CI [-0.76, -0.20]), indicating that stroke survivors had a lower SRI, and thus less regular sleep compared to controls, as hypothesised. The effect of Age was significant and negative (&#x003b2; = -0.12, 95% CI [-0.23, -0.01], t(218) = -2.16, <italic>p</italic> = 0.032; Std. &#x003b2; = -0.14, 95% CI [-0.27, -0.01]) demonstrating that increased age is associated with less regular sleep. The effect of Sex was significant and positive (&#x003b2; = 5.07, 95% CI [1.86, 8.29], t(218) = 3.11, <italic>p</italic> = 0.002; Std. &#x003b2; = 0.20, 95% CI [0.07, 0.33]), demonstrating that, overall, women have a higher SRI (more regular sleep) compared to men. Permutation testing (i.e., randomly subsampling the stroke group to account for the unequal sample sizes) revealed similar results (supplementary S4).</p><p id="Par23">
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Violin plot showing the distribution of SRI scores in the stroke survivors and healthy controls. Higher SRI is indicative of more regular sleep. There was a significant effect of group, adjusting for age and sex (<italic>p</italic> = 0.001).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_1332_Fig2_HTML" id="d33e722"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par24">As the current research incorporates data from five distinct stroke studies, each with individualised objectives, there is an inherent sampling bias. In particular, several studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup> recruited stroke survivors based on their subjective experience of sleep issues and interest in receiving sleep treatment. We found a significant correlation between SCI and the SRI (with stroke and control combined; <italic>r</italic> = 0.25, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>), indicating the SRI is higher for participants with better self-reported sleep. We therefore repeated the linear regression with SCI as a predictor, to control for any differences between groups. The effect of Group is negative but no longer significant (&#x003b2; = -2.22, 95% CI [-6.29, 1.85], t(217) = -1.07, <italic>p</italic> = 0.284; standardized &#x003b2; = -0.18, 95% CI [-0.50, 0.15]).</p><p id="Par25">
<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>A scatterplot of the correlation between SCI and SRI for the whole dataset (including both stroke survivors and healthy controls), with better self-reported sleep associated with more regular sleep: <italic>r</italic> = 0.25, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_1332_Fig3_HTML" id="d33e760"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Investigating correlations between SRI and other sleep metrics</title><sec id="Sec13"><title>Stroke survivors</title><p id="Par26">Counter to our hypothesis, there was a weak but statistically significant correlation between SRI and Total Sleep Time (<italic>r</italic> = 0.22, <italic>p</italic> = 0.004), indicating that when stroke survivors have more regular sleep, they have longer overall nighttime sleep. There was a weak but significant correlation between SRI and Sleep Condition Indicator score (<italic>r</italic> = 0.25, <italic>p</italic> = 0.001), suggesting that better self-reported sleep after stroke is associated with more regular sleep-wake patterns. However, there were no significant correlations between SRI and Wake After Sleep Onset (<italic>r</italic> = -0.05, <italic>p</italic> = 0.56), Fragmentation Index (<italic>r</italic> = -0.13, <italic>p</italic> = 0.12) nor Sleep Efficiency (<italic>r</italic> = 0.18, <italic>p</italic> = 0.03; <italic>ns with Bonferroni correction</italic>), Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>. Interestingly, when the Average Sleep Time per 24&#x000a0;h is used, there is a significant correlation with the SRI, whereby more regular sleep is associated with shorter average sleep time per 24&#x000a0;h. Details and figures can be found in Supplementary materials (figure S8 part A).</p><p id="Par27">
<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Plotted residuals accounted for age and sex to demonstrate partial correlations for the stroke cohort between the sleep regularity index (SRI) and (<bold>A</bold>) total sleep time (TST), (<bold>B</bold>) wake after sleep onset (WASO), (<bold>C</bold>) fragmentation index, (<bold>D</bold>) sleep efficiency, (<bold>E</bold>) sleep condition indicator (SCI), &#x003b1; = 0.01 (Bonferroni corrected).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_1332_Fig4_HTML" id="d33e830"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Healthy controls</title><p id="Par28">There were no correlations between SRI and TST (<italic>r</italic> = 0.07, <italic>p</italic> = 0.616), Fragmentation Index (<italic>r</italic> = 0.04, <italic>p</italic> = 0.792), Sleep efficiency (<italic>r</italic> = -0.06, <italic>p</italic> = 0.659), wake after sleep onset (<italic>r</italic> = 0.01, <italic>p</italic> = 0.943), nor the sleep condition indicator (<italic>r</italic> = 0.28, <italic>p</italic> = 0.040; <italic>ns with Bonferroni correction</italic>) in the control group (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). Notably, when the Average Sleep Time per 24&#x000a0;h is used, there is a significant correlation with the SRI, whereby more regular sleep is associated with shorter average sleep time per 24&#x000a0;h. Details figures can be found in Supplementary materials (figure S8 part B). Comparisons of the strength of correlations between the groups revealed no statistically significant differences (supplementary S4).</p><p id="Par29">
<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Plotted residuals accounted for age and sex to demonstrate partial correlations for the healthy control cohort between the sleep regularity index (SRI) and (<bold>A</bold>) and total sleep time (TST), (<bold>B</bold>) wake after sleep onset (WASO), (<bold>C</bold>) fragmentation index, (<bold>D</bold>) sleep efficiency, (<bold>E</bold>) sleep condition indicator (SCI), &#x003b1; = 0.01 (Bonferroni correction for multiple comparisons).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_1332_Fig5_HTML" id="d33e898"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Stroke group analyses</title><p id="Par30">To test the secondary hypothesis that stroke survivors with less regular sleep would have higher (worse) depression scores, a Pearson&#x02019;s correlation (adjusted for age and sex) was performed on available data (<italic>n</italic> = 113). There was a significant correlation between the SRI and PHQ-8 (<italic>r</italic> = -0.26, <italic>p</italic> = 0.006; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>A) indicating that less regular sleep is associated with worse depression scores.</p><p id="Par31">An exploratory objective was to investigate the correlation between SRI and quality of life (SF-SIS, <italic>n</italic> = 54). There was a significant correlation (adjusted for age and sex; <italic>r</italic> = 0.40, <italic>p</italic> = 0.002), revealing that when stroke survivors have more regular sleep, their reported quality of life is higher (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>B). However, there was no significant correlation between SRI and disability (mRS) or Time Since Stroke (supplementary S4).</p><p id="Par32">
<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Plotted residuals controlled for age and sex to demonstrate partial correlations between (<bold>A</bold>) SRI and the Patient Health Questionnaire depression scale (PHQ-8) (<italic>n</italic> = 113 stroke survivors). (<bold>B</bold>) SRI and the Stroke Impact Scale (<italic>n</italic> = 54 stroke survivors).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_1332_Fig6_HTML" id="d33e951"/></fig>
</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par33">The relationship between sleep and stroke is intricate, as sleep-wake disturbances are both a risk factor and potential outcome of stroke. In the present study we utilised a pre-existing actigraphy dataset from community-dwelling stroke survivors and established a significant disparity in sleep regularity between stroke survivors and healthy controls. We also found, for the stroke group alone, that more regular sleep was linked to longer overall nighttime sleep time, better self-reported sleep quality, less severe depression scores and better quality of life.</p><p id="Par34">The group difference suggests that the stroke cohort exhibited greater irregularity in their sleep patterns. This result aligns with a growing body of literature suggesting that many aspects of sleep are negatively affected after stroke<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup> &#x02014; which could result from several interrelated factors. Neurological damage resulting from a stroke can impair regions of the brain responsible for sleep regulation, leading to disruptions in the sleep-wake cycle. Indeed, the neuroanatomical basis of sleep control is complex and involves multiple structures such as the thalamus, brainstem, hippocampus, and striatum &#x02014;regions that can be affected by stroke<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>. However, the relationship between stroke lesion characteristics and sleep disruption remains poorly understood. The impact of stroke lesions on the microstructure of sleep, including brain oscillations such as slow waves and sleep spindles, is also an area requiring further exploration, given their role in memory consolidation and neuroplasticity processes that are vital for recovery<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>. Additionally, psychological factors such as anxiety, depression, and stress, which are prevalent among stroke survivors, could also contribute to sleep irregularities<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>. These psychological factors have specifically been linked to post-stroke fatigue, a prevalent phenomenon that affects patients&#x02019; quality of life<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>. Post-stroke fatigue, as well as environmental factors and treatment schedules during hospitalisation and rehabilitation disrupt normal sleep routines, further complicating sleep regularity. Sleep irregularity has been a largely overlooked feature that may have clinical relevance. Specifically, the circadian system is crucial for maintaining overall health as it regulates numerous physiological functions, including the sleep-wake cycle<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>, which are instrumental in post-stroke recovery. Indeed, it has been shown that poor sleep can have a negative effect on rehabilitation outcomes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>. Poor sleep following a stroke has further been associated with notable cognitive and attentional impairments, along with negative health and clinical outcomes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>. However, when our analysis was repeated with subjective sleep quality (SCI) included in the model, the effect of group was no longer significant. We cannot rule out the influence of a sampling bias given that several of the included studies recruited participants with the intention of accessing a programme to try to improve their sleep problems. Therefore, we have also conducted a sensitivity analysis that can be found in supplementary materials (Fig. S5). However, given that stroke survivors typically experience worse self-reported sleep than controls<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup> this result may reflect inherent differences between these populations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>, irrespective of recruitment techniques. The finding that better self-reported sleep is associated with more regular sleep patterns in stroke survivors is of particular interest as many studies report that subjective and objective measures of sleep do not necessarily align well<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>. One possible explanation for this association is that patients may be more attuned to irregularities in their sleep patterns than to other metrics, such as sleep efficiency. For example, disruptions to regular sleep schedules may manifest in noticeable behaviours like the need for daytime naps to compensate for inadequate or inconsistent nighttime rest. This heightened awareness of irregular sleep could account for the stronger subjective reporting of poorer sleep quality when sleep patterns are less regular. Furthermore, aspects of insomnia treatment (cognitive behavioural therapy for insomnia) aim to regulate sleep and wake patterns to improve patient perceptions of sleep quality. Future research should thus test whether improvements in sleep regularity can impact sleep quality, or vice versa, after stroke.</p><p id="Par35">We also found that being of older age and male was associated with lower sleep regularity. This is consistent with prior research, with males generally having less regular sleep than females<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>. With regards to age, it has been proposed that changes in sleep with aging may result from diminished circadian control of the sleep-wake cycle. Moreover, sleep disturbances are particularly pronounced in neurodegenerative conditions such as dementia, where they become increasingly severe with disease progression. Despite the high prevalence of these disturbances, evidence-based treatment options remain limited and underexplored. Adjusting the circadian timing system has been suggested as a potential strategy to mitigate age- and disease-related declines in sleep quality and daytime functioning<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>, which warrants further investigation. The SRI values observed in our study are lower than those reported in some larger population-based studies, which may be attributable to several factors. First, our study population is generally older than those used in many SRI studies, and as stated above, older adults may tend to exhibit lower SRI scores compared to younger, healthier individuals. Second, larger datasets, such as those from population cohorts like the UK Biobank, tend to capture a broader range of values, including more extreme scores, due to increased sample size and variability. Third, the specific type of actigraphy watch, smoothing algorithm and collection modality used (PIM in our study, versus ZCM in others) may also contribute to differences in SRI scores. While this difference in device sensitivity does not affect internal comparisons within our study, it should be considered when comparing our results to findings from studies using alternative actigraphy devices.</p><p id="Par36">Within the stroke cohort only, a significant link was found between SRI and total sleep time (TST), where more regular sleep correlated with a longer actigraphy-derived total sleep time during the night. No associations were found within the healthy controls, but the strength of correlation did not differ significantly between the groups. Previous work has not found a correlation between TST and SRI in young healthy adults<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup> nor in a diverse sample of older adults<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. Suboptimal sleep duration has been linked to an elevated risk of stroke occurrence<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup>, and it remains to be seen whether sleep irregularity could also influence secondary stroke risk. We speculate that disruption to sleep after stroke could increase patients&#x02019; tendency to nap during the day, thereby diminishing sleep regularity. Furthermore, in our exploratory analysis, we observed that individuals with higher average total sleep across the 24-hour period, likely reflecting increased daytime napping, had lower sleep regularity, as indicated by a negative association between SRI and average daily sleep duration. This was evident in both the stroke and control cohorts, suggesting that greater fragmentation or redistribution of sleep across the 24-hour period may compromise the regularity of the sleep-wake cycle. These results align with the earlier observation that longer nighttime sleep was linked to higher SRI in the stroke cohort, likely due to reduced need for compensatory daytime naps for people who have longer nighttime sleep. Importantly, this metric is derived from the same actigraphy data used to calculate the SRI, making it an accessible and informative variable for future research on sleep regularity and recovery after stroke.</p><p id="Par37">Within the stroke cohort, the correlation between depression scores and SRI was significant (controlling for age and sex). This is consistent with previous studies that have revealed an association between sleep regularity and depression scores<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup>. As the relationship between sleep and depression is complex and bi-directional<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup>, it may be that irregular sleep patterns contribute to higher depression scores and/or that more severe depressive symptoms adversely affect sleep-wake patterns. In addition to depression, apathy has also been reported as a common yet understudied neuropsychiatric consequence of stroke. Characterised by diminished goal-directed behaviour, apathy can negatively impact recovery and quality of life. Often overlapping with depression but also occurring independently, apathy may be relevant in understanding post-stroke sleep-wake disturbance and would be interesting to include in future research<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par38">We did not observe a significant relationship between SRI and time since stroke. This is consistent with previous findings that sleep problems can persist over time. Studies have shown that neither self-reported sleep nor actigraphy measures of sleep disruption improve significantly during subacute rehabilitation, and that there is no clear relationship between time since stroke and sleep disturbances<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>. However, some studies do report improvements in sleep from acute to chronic timepoints<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup>. This underscores the importance of longitudinal research to better understand how sleep regularity evolves over time and in relation to stroke recovery trajectories. Similarly, we found no association between sleep regularity and level of disability after stroke. While this could indicate that functional impairment does not influence this specific aspect of sleep, it likely reflects limitations in sensitivity of this measure or cohort characteristics. These possibilities are further considered in the limitations section.</p><p id="Par39">Finally, there was a significant relationship between sleep regularity and quality of life in stroke survivors, with higher sleep regularity indicating better quality of life. This finding aligns with previous work in other patient populations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref></sup>, and is, to our knowledge, the first account reported in stroke. This is crucial, as earlier work has highlighted that sleep disorders can further reduce the quality of life in stroke patients, and diagnosing and treating sleep disturbance is vital to optimising functional outcomes and improving quality of life<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref></sup>. This finding presents an opportunity to investigate whether interventions targeting sleep regularity can enhance quality of life post-stroke.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Limitations and future research</title><p id="Par40">Limitations of the present study should be mentioned. As the data were obtained from several studies investigating post-stroke sleep, each with distinct objectives, there was a potential sampling bias. All participants are community-dwelling stroke survivors, ranging from the sub-acute to the chronic phase (mostly in the chronic phase). Future research could attempt to replicate our findings, but in a less heterogeneous group and earlier post-stroke. Furthermore, a limitation of this study is the lack of data on participants&#x02019; occupational or academic status. Social factors, including work schedules and daily responsibilities, are known to influence sleep-wake rhythms. While our sample included both retired and working individuals in both groups, we were unable to formally account for these variables, which may differentially affect sleep-wake patterns&#x02014;particularly when comparing stroke survivors, who may experience reduced social constraints post-stroke, with healthy controls. It should further be noted that the sample consists mainly of stroke survivors who range from no to moderate disability, as measured by the mRS. There are very few participants with severe functional disability in the entire dataset. A general limitation in stroke research is that stroke survivors with very severe disabilities may not meet specific study criteria and may lack the physical or cognitive ability to participate, limiting generalisability across stroke. Moreover, we did not have access to NIHSS scores to assess acute stroke severity, which may influence sleep patterns and offer a more sensitive measure than functional disability alone. While we included related metrics such as the mRS and SF-SIS to capture post-stroke disability and quality of life, future studies should incorporate formal measures of stroke severity like the NIHSS to better understand how stroke characteristics relate to sleep outcomes. Additionally, a limitation of the current study is the absence of cognitive assessments within the dataset, as this analysis was conducted using pre-existing data. While previous research suggests a potential link between sleep disturbances and cognitive impairment in acquired brain injury<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>, we were not able to explore this relationship directly. Future studies incorporating cognitive measures would be valuable in further elucidating the interplay between post-stroke sleep-wake disturbances and cognitive functioning. Finally, although we found no relationship between SRI and time since stroke, the study was cross-sectional. Future research should focus on examining changes in sleep regularity longitudinally, as this remains unexplored and the timescale by which sleep-wake problems occur post-stroke is unclear.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par41">We have demonstrated that the sleep regularity index could be a useful metric for post-stroke sleep research. When combined with other sleep metrics, SRI could potentially help address unresolved questions and provide new insights, as it uniquely accounts for sleep and wake patterns over the entire day and night. To our knowledge, this study is the first to investigate the sleep regularity index in a stroke cohort. Stroke survivors exhibited greater irregularity in their sleep patterns than controls, and more irregular sleep was associated with shorter total sleep time and worse self-reported sleep. Most notably, there was evidence connecting sleep regularity with quality of life and depression scores after stroke. Sleep regularity could be a novel target to improve post-stroke quality of life, but research is first needed to study changes in sleep regularity longitudinally, particularly to test for changes alongside recovery, and to identify potential methods for addressing sleep regularity problems.</p></sec><sec id="Sec19" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.</p><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41598_2025_1332_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><caption><p>Supplementary Material 1</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>Tom Smejka and Ellie Macey who were involved in original data collection.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>Conceptualization: K.B.S., M.K.F.; Methodology: K.B.S., M.K.F., A.&#x000e1;.V.G., M.W.; Investigation: M.W., B.R.; Data Curation: K.B.S., A.&#x000e1;.V.G., M.W., B.R.; Formal Analysis: K.B.S., A.&#x000e1;.V.G., M.W.; Writing &#x02013; Original Draft: K.B.S.; Writing &#x02013; Review &#x00026; Editing: K.B.S., A.&#x000e1;.V.G., M.W., B.R., M.K.F., H.J.B.; Supervision: M.K.F.; Funding Acquisition: M.K.F., H.J.B.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This work is supported by the Wellcome Trust and the NIHR Oxford Health Biomedical Research Centre (NIHR203316). The views expressed are those of the authors and not necessarily those of the NIHR or the Department of Health and Social Care. MKF is Funded by Guarantors of Brain and HJB is funded by the Wellcome Trust (222446/Z/21/Z). The Wellcome Centre for Integrative Neuroimaging is supported by core funding from the Wellcome Trust (203139/Z/16/Z and 203139/A/16/Z).</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The code for all processing is open access and can be found on GitHub (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/KatSchruers/RISES">https://github.com/KatSchruers/RISES</ext-link>). The data of this study are available from the corresponding author, MKF, upon reasonable request.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par42">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Cahill</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global stroke belt: geographic variation in stroke burden worldwide</article-title><source>Stroke</source><year>2015</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>3564</fpage><lpage>3570</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/STROKEAHA.115.008226</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26486867</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Kim, A. S., Cahill, E. &#x00026; Cheng, N. T. Global stroke belt: Geographic variation in stroke burden worldwide. <italic>Stroke</italic><bold>46</bold>, 3564&#x02013;3570 (2015).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26486867</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bakhshaie</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Temporal precedence of the change in obsessive-compulsive symptoms and change in depressive symptoms during exposure and response prevention for pediatric obsessive-compulsive disorders</article-title><source>Behav. Res. Ther.</source><year>2020</year><volume>133</volume><fpage>103697</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.brat.2020.103697</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32822898</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Bakhshaie, J. et al. Temporal precedence of the change in obsessive-compulsive symptoms and change in depressive symptoms during exposure and response prevention for pediatric obsessive-compulsive disorders. <italic>Behav. Res. Ther.</italic><bold>133</bold>, 103697 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32822898</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Byun</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Stroke impact symptoms are associated with sleep-related impairment</article-title><source>Heart Lung</source><year>2020</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>117</fpage><lpage>122</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.hrtlng.2019.10.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31839325</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Byun, E. et al. Stroke impact symptoms are associated with sleep-related impairment. <italic>Heart Lung</italic><bold>49</bold>, 117&#x02013;122. 10.1016/j.hrtlng.2019.10.010 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31839325</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fleming</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Self-reported and objective sleep measures in stroke survivors with incomplete motor recovery at the chronic stage</article-title><source>Neurorehabilit. Neural Repair</source><year>2021</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>851</fpage><lpage>860</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/15459683211029889</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Fleming, M. K. et al. Self-reported and objective sleep measures in stroke survivors with incomplete motor recovery at the chronic stage. <italic>Neurorehabilit. Neural Repair</italic><bold>35</bold>, 851&#x02013;860 (2021).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baglioni</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Polysomnographic characteristics of sleep in stroke: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2016</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>e0148496</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0148496</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26949966</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Baglioni, C. et al. Polysomnographic characteristics of sleep in stroke: A systematic review and meta-analysis. <italic>PLoS One</italic><bold>11</bold>, e0148496 (2016).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26949966</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ouellet</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Savard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Morin</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Book review: insomnia following traumatic brain injury: A review</article-title><source>Neurorehabilit. Neural Repair</source><year>2004</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>187</fpage><lpage>198</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1545968304271405</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Ouellet, M. C., Savard, J. &#x00026; Morin, C. M. Book review: insomnia following traumatic brain injury: A review. <italic>Neurorehabilit. Neural Repair</italic><bold>18</bold>, 187&#x02013;198 (2004).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Falck</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sleep and cognitive function in chronic stroke: a comparative cross-sectional study</article-title><source>Sleep</source><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsz040</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30805652</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Falck, R. S. et al. Sleep and cognitive function in chronic stroke: A comparative cross-sectional study. <italic>Sleep</italic>. 10.1093/sleep/zsz040 (2019).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30805652</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi-Kwon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sleep disturbances after cerebral infarction: role of depression and fatigue</article-title><source>J. Stroke Cerebrovasc. Dis.</source><year>2014</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>1949</fpage><lpage>1955</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jstrokecerebrovasdis.2014.01.029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24794949</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Suh, M., Choi-Kwon, S. &#x00026; Kim, J. S. Sleep disturbances after cerebral infarction: Role of depression and fatigue. <italic>J. Stroke Cerebrovasc. Dis.</italic><bold>23</bold>, 1949&#x02013;1955. 10.1016/j.jstrokecerebrovasdis.2014.01.029 (2014).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24794949</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fleming</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sleep disruption after brain injury is associated with worse motor outcomes and slower functional recovery</article-title><source>Neurorehabilit. Neural Repair</source><year>2020</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>661</fpage><lpage>671</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1545968320929669</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Fleming, M. K. et al. Sleep disruption after brain injury is associated with worse motor outcomes and slower functional recovery. <italic>Neurorehabilit. Neural Repair</italic><bold>34</bold>, 661&#x02013;671 (2020).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Measuring sleep: accuracy, sensitivity, and specificity of wrist actigraphy compared to polysomnography</article-title><source>Sleep</source><year>2013</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>1747</fpage><lpage>1755</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.3142</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24179309</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Marino, M. et al. Measuring sleep: Accuracy, sensitivity, and specificity of wrist actigraphy compared to polysomnography. <italic>Sleep</italic><bold>36</bold>, 1747&#x02013;1755. 10.5665/sleep.3142 (2013).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24179309</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lichstein</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Actigraphy validation with insomnia</article-title><source>Sleep</source><year>2006</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>232</fpage><lpage>239</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16494091</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Lichstein, K. L. et al. Actigraphy validation with insomnia. <italic>Sleep</italic><bold>29</bold>, 232&#x02013;239 (2006).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16494091</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sadeh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role and validity of actigraphy in sleep medicine: an update</article-title><source>Sleep Med. Rev.</source><year>2011</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>259</fpage><lpage>267</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2010.10.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21237680</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Sadeh, A. The role and validity of actigraphy in sleep medicine: an update. <italic>Sleep Med. Rev.</italic><bold>15</bold>, 259&#x02013;267 (2011).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21237680</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fekedulegn</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Actigraphy-Based assessment of sleep parameters</article-title><source>Ann. Work Expo Health</source><year>2020</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>350</fpage><lpage>367</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/annweh/wxaa007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32053169</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Fekedulegn, D. et al. Actigraphy-Based assessment of sleep parameters. <italic>Ann. Work Expo Health</italic><bold>64</bold>, 350&#x02013;367. 10.1093/annweh/wxaa007 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32053169</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gottlieb</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The bidirectional impact of sleep and circadian rhythm dysfunction in human ischaemic stroke: a systematic review</article-title><source>Sleep Med. Rev.</source><year>2019</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>54</fpage><lpage>69</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2019.03.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30954762</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Gottlieb, E. et al. The bidirectional impact of sleep and circadian rhythm dysfunction in human ischaemic stroke: A systematic review. <italic>Sleep Med. Rev.</italic><bold>45</bold>, 54&#x02013;69 (2019).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30954762</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Shiftwork-Mediated disruptions of circadian rhythms and sleep homeostasis cause serious health problems</article-title><source>Int. J. Genomics</source><year>2018</year><volume>2018</volume><fpage>8576890</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2018/8576890</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29607311</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Khan, S., Duan, P., Yao, L. &#x00026; Hou, H. Shiftwork-Mediated disruptions of circadian rhythms and sleep homeostasis cause serious health problems. <italic>Int. J. Genomics</italic><bold>2018</bold>, 8576890. 10.1155/2018/8576890 (2018).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29607311</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Czeisler</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Duration, timing and quality of sleep are each vital for health, performance and safety</article-title><source>Sleep Health J. Natl. Sleep. Found.</source><year>2015</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleh.2014.12.008</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Czeisler, C. A. Duration, timing and quality of sleep are each vital for health, performance and safety. <italic>Sleep Health J. Natl. Sleep. Found.</italic><bold>1</bold>, 5&#x02013;8 (2015).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>AJK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Irregular sleep/wake patterns are associated with poorer academic performance and delayed circadian and sleep/wake timing</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>3216</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-03171-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28607474</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Phillips, A. J. K. et al. Irregular sleep/wake patterns are associated with poorer academic performance and delayed circadian and sleep/wake timing. <italic>Sci. Rep.</italic><bold>7</bold>, 3216. 10.1038/s41598-017-03171-4 (2017).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28607474</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lunsford-Avery</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Engelhard</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Navar</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kollins</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Validation of the sleep regularity index in older adults and associations with cardiometabolic risk</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2018</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>14158</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-32402-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30242174</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Lunsford-Avery, J. R., Engelhard, M. M., Navar, A. M. &#x00026; Kollins, S. H. Validation of the sleep regularity index in older adults and associations with cardiometabolic risk. <italic>Sci. Rep.</italic><bold>8</bold>, 14158. 10.1038/s41598-018-32402-5 (2018).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30242174</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Windred</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sleep regularity is a stronger predictor of mortality risk than sleep duration: A prospective cohort study</article-title><source>Sleep</source><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsad253</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Windred, D. P. et al. Sleep regularity is a stronger predictor of mortality risk than sleep duration: A prospective cohort study. <italic>Sleep</italic>10.1093/sleep/zsad253 (2023).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Fleming, M. K. et al. Improving sleep after stroke: a randomised controlled trial of digital cognitive behavioural therapy for insomnia. <italic>J. Sleep Res.</italic> e13971 (2023).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weightman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Improving sleep and learning in rehabilitation after stroke, part 2 (INSPIRES2): study protocol for a home-based randomised control trial of digital cognitive behavioural therapy (dCBT) for insomnia</article-title><source>BMJ Open.</source><year>2023</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>e071764</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2023-071764</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37024247</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Weightman, M. et al. Improving sleep and learning in rehabilitation after stroke, part 2 (INSPIRES2): Study protocol for a home-based randomised control trial of digital cognitive behavioural therapy (dCBT) for insomnia. <italic>BMJ Open</italic><bold>13</bold>, e071764. 10.1136/bmjopen-2023-071764 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37024247</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weightman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sleep and motor learning in stroke (SMiLES): a longitudinal study investigating sleep-dependent consolidation of motor sequence learning in the context of recovery after stroke</article-title><source>BMJ Open.</source><year>2024</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>e077442</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2023-077442</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38355178</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">Weightman, M. et al. Sleep and motor learning in stroke (SMiLES): A longitudinal study investigating sleep-dependent consolidation of motor sequence learning in the context of recovery after stroke. <italic>BMJ Open</italic><bold>14</bold>, e077442 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38355178</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wesselius</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Quality and quantity of sleep and factors associated with sleep disturbance in hospitalized patients</article-title><source>JAMA Intern. Med.</source><year>2018</year><volume>178</volume><fpage>1201</fpage><lpage>1208</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamainternmed.2018.2669</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30014139</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Wesselius, H. M. et al. Quality and quantity of sleep and factors associated with sleep disturbance in hospitalized patients. <italic>JAMA Intern. Med.</italic><bold>178</bold>, 1201&#x02013;1208 (2018).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30014139</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">CamNtechLtd. <italic>MotionWare Software</italic>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.camntech.com/motionware-software/">https://www.camntech.com/motionware-software/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Klerman</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>AJK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Measuring sleep regularity: theoretical properties and practical usage of existing metrics</article-title><source>Sleep</source><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsab103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33864369</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="journal">Fischer, D., Klerman, E. B. &#x00026; Phillips, A. J. K. Measuring sleep regularity: Theoretical properties and practical usage of existing metrics. <italic>Sleep</italic>. 10.1093/sleep/zsab103 (2021).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33864369</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">de Zambotti, M. et al. State of the science and recommendations for using wearable technology in sleep and circadian research. <italic>Sleep</italic> zsad325 (2023).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR27" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McLaren</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Assessing insomnia after stroke: a diagnostic validation of the sleep condition Indicator in self-reported stroke survivors</article-title><source>BMJ Neurol. Open.</source><year>2024</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>e000768</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjno-2024-000768</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39493672</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27" publication-type="journal">McLaren, D. M. et al. Assessing insomnia after stroke: A diagnostic validation of the sleep condition Indicator in self-reported stroke survivors. <italic>BMJ Neurol. Open</italic><bold>6</bold>, e000768. 10.1136/bmjno-2024-000768 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39493672</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR28" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Espie</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The sleep condition indicator: reference values derived from a sample of 200 000 adults</article-title><source>J. Sleep Res.</source><year>2018</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>e12643</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.12643</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29193493</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28" publication-type="journal">Espie, C. A. et al. The sleep condition indicator: Reference values derived from a sample of 200 000 adults. <italic>J. Sleep Res.</italic><bold>27</bold>, e12643 (2018).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29193493</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR29" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of the usefulness of the PHQ-8 and PHQ-9 for screening for major depressive disorder: analysis of psychiatric outpatient data</article-title><source>Psychiatry Investig</source><year>2019</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>300</fpage><lpage>305</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.30773/pi.2019.02.01</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31042692</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29" publication-type="journal">Shin, C., Lee, S. H., Han, K. M., Yoon, H. K. &#x00026; Han, C. Comparison of the usefulness of the PHQ-8 and PHQ-9 for screening for major depressive disorder: Analysis of psychiatric outpatient data. <italic>Psychiatry Investig.</italic><bold>16</bold>, 300&#x02013;305. 10.30773/pi.2019.02.01 (2019).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31042692</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR30" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Banks</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Marotta</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Outcomes validity and reliability of the modified Rankin scale: implications for stroke clinical trials: a literature review and synthesis</article-title><source>Stroke</source><year>2007</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>1091</fpage><lpage>1096</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.STR.0000258355.23810.c6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17272767</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30" publication-type="journal">Banks, J. L. &#x00026; Marotta, C. A. Outcomes validity and reliability of the modified Rankin scale: Implications for stroke clinical trials: A literature review and synthesis. <italic>Stroke</italic><bold>38</bold>, 1091&#x02013;1096 (2007).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17272767</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR31" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jenkinson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitzpatrick</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Crocker</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The stroke impact scale</article-title><source>Stroke</source><year>2013</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>2532</fpage><lpage>2535</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/STROKEAHA.113.001847</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23868278</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR31" publication-type="journal">Jenkinson, C., Fitzpatrick, R., Crocker, H. &#x00026; Peters, M. The stroke impact scale. <italic>Stroke</italic><bold>44</bold>, 2532&#x02013;2535. 10.1161/STROKEAHA.113.001847 (2013).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23868278</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR32" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akoglu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>User&#x02019;s guide to correlation coefficients</article-title><source>Turk. J. Emerg. Med.</source><year>2018</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tjem.2018.08.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30191186</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32" publication-type="journal">Akoglu, H. User&#x02019;s guide to correlation coefficients. <italic>Turk. J. Emerg. Med.</italic><bold>18</bold>, 91&#x02013;93. 10.1016/j.tjem.2018.08.001 (2018).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30191186</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR33" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XP</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sleep disorders in stroke: an update on management</article-title><source>Aging Disease</source><year>2021</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>570</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14336/AD.2020.0707</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33815883</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR33" publication-type="journal">Cai, H., Wang, X. P. &#x00026; Yang, G. Y. Sleep disorders in stroke: An update on management. <italic>Aging Dis.</italic><bold>12</bold>, 570 (2021).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33815883</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR34" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frange</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Coelho</surname><given-names>FMS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The importance of sleep for successful neurorehabilitation after stroke</article-title><source>Sleep. Sci.</source><year>2023</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>e335</fpage><lpage>e343</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0043-1772805</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38196757</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR34" publication-type="journal">Frange, C., Murray, B. J. &#x00026; Coelho, F. M. S. The importance of sleep for successful neurorehabilitation after stroke. <italic>Sleep Sci.</italic><bold>16</bold>, e335&#x02013;e343 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38196757</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR35" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gottlieb</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Regional neurodegeneration correlates with sleep&#x02013;wake dysfunction after stroke</article-title><source>Sleep</source><year>2020</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>zsaa054</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsaa054</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32249910</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR35" publication-type="journal">Gottlieb, E. et al. Regional neurodegeneration correlates with sleep&#x02013;wake dysfunction after stroke. <italic>Sleep</italic><bold>43</bold>, zsaa054 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32249910</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR36" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Diekelmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Born</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The memory function of sleep</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Neurosci.</source><year>2010</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>114</fpage><lpage>126</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrn2762</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20046194</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR36" publication-type="journal">Diekelmann, S. &#x00026; Born, J. The memory function of sleep. <italic>Nat. Rev. Neurosci.</italic><bold>11</bold>, 114&#x02013;126 (2010).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20046194</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR37" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duss</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The role of sleep in recovery following ischemic stroke: a review of human and animal data</article-title><source>Neurobiol. Sleep. Circadian Rhythms</source><year>2017</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>94</fpage><lpage>105</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nbscr.2016.11.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31236498</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR37" publication-type="journal">Duss, S. B. et al. The role of sleep in recovery following ischemic stroke: A review of human and animal data. <italic>Neurobiol. Sleep. Circadian Rhythms</italic><bold>2</bold>, 94&#x02013;105 (2017).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31236498</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bassetti, C. L. In <italic>Seminars in Neurology.</italic> 19&#x02013;32 (Thieme Medical Publishers Inc., 2005).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ponchel, A. et al. Influence of medication on fatigue six months after stroke. <italic>Stroke Res. Treat.</italic><bold>2016</bold>, 2410921. 10.1155/2016/2410921 (2016).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR40" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iddagoda</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Inderjeeth</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Raymond</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Post-stroke sleep disturbances and rehabilitation outcomes: a prospective cohort study</article-title><source>Intern. Med. J.</source><year>2020</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>208</fpage><lpage>213</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/imj.14372</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31111660</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR40" publication-type="journal">Iddagoda, M. T., Inderjeeth, C. A., Chan, K. &#x00026; Raymond, W. D. Post-stroke sleep disturbances and rehabilitation outcomes: A prospective cohort study. <italic>Intern. Med. J.</italic><bold>50</bold>, 208&#x02013;213. 10.1111/imj.14372 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31111660</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR41" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gudberg</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Johansen-Berg</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sleep and Motor Learning: Implications for Physical Rehabilitation After Strokegudberg</article-title><source>Front. Neurol.</source><year>2015</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fneur.2015.00241</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26635718</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR41" publication-type="journal">Gudberg, C. &#x00026; Johansen-Berg, H. Sleep and motor learning: Implications for physical rehabilitation after Strokegudberg. <italic>Front. Neurol.</italic>10.3389/fneur.2015.00241 (2015).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26635718</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR42" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cavalcanti</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Campos</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Araujo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Actigraphic analysis of the Sleep&#x02013;Wake cycle and physical activity level in patients with stroke: implications for clinical practice</article-title><source>Chronobiol. Int.</source><year>2012</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>1267</fpage><lpage>1272</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/07420528.2012.719960</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23003002</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR42" publication-type="journal">Cavalcanti, P., Campos, T. &#x00026; Araujo, J. Actigraphic analysis of the Sleep&#x02013;Wake cycle and physical activity level in patients with stroke: Implications for clinical practice. <italic>Chronobiol. Int.</italic><bold>29</bold>, 1267&#x02013;1272. 10.3109/07420528.2012.719960 (2012).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23003002</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR43" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Unruh</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Subjective and objective sleep quality and aging in the sleep heart health study</article-title><source>J. Am. Geriatr. Soc.</source><year>2008</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>1218</fpage><lpage>1227</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1532-5415.2008.01755.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18482295</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR43" publication-type="journal">Unruh, M. L. et al. Subjective and objective sleep quality and aging in the sleep heart health study. <italic>J. Am. Geriatr. Soc.</italic><bold>56</bold>, 1218&#x02013;1227. 10.1111/j.1532-5415.2008.01755.x (2008). https://doi.org:.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18482295</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR44" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guarnieri</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Multicenter study on sleep and circadian alterations as objective markers of mild cognitive impairment and Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease reveals sex differences</article-title><source>J. Alzheimers Dis.</source><year>2020</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>1707</fpage><lpage>1719</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3233/JAD-200632</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33185597</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR44" publication-type="journal">Guarnieri, B. et al. Multicenter study on sleep and circadian alterations as objective markers of mild cognitive impairment and Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease reveals sex differences. <italic>J. Alzheimers Dis.</italic><bold>78</bold>, 1707&#x02013;1719. 10.3233/JAD-200632 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33185597</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR45" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alves Facundo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sleep regularity in athletes: comparing sex, competitive level and sport type</article-title><source>Chronobiol. Int.</source><year>2022</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>1381</fpage><lpage>1388</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07420528.2022.2108716</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35950541</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR45" publication-type="journal">Alves Facundo, L. et al. Sleep regularity in athletes: Comparing sex, competitive level and sport type. <italic>Chronobiol. Int.</italic><bold>39</bold>, 1381&#x02013;1388. 10.1080/07420528.2022.2108716 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35950541</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR46" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cajochen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000fc;nch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Knoblauch</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Blatter</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wirz-Justice</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Age&#x02010;related changes in the circadian and homeostatic regulation of human sleep</article-title><source>Chronobiol. Int.</source><year>2006</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>461</fpage><lpage>474</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07420520500545813</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16687319</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR46" publication-type="journal">Cajochen, C., M&#x000fc;nch, M., Knoblauch, V., Blatter, K. &#x00026; Wirz-Justice, A. Age&#x02010;related changes in the circadian and homeostatic regulation of human sleep. <italic>Chronobiol. Int.</italic><bold>23</bold>, 461&#x02013;474. 10.1080/07420520500545813 (2006).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16687319</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR47" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sleep duration and risk of stroke: a dose&#x02013;response meta-analysis of prospective cohort studies</article-title><source>Sleep Med.</source><year>2017</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>66</fpage><lpage>74</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2016.12.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28366344</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR47" publication-type="journal">He, Q. et al. Sleep duration and risk of stroke: A dose&#x02013;response meta-analysis of prospective cohort studies. <italic>Sleep Med.</italic><bold>32</bold>, 66&#x02013;74. 10.1016/j.sleep.2016.12.012 (2017).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28366344</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR48" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Castiglione-Fontanellaz</surname><given-names>CEG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sleep regularity in healthy adolescents: associations with sleep duration, sleep quality, and mental health</article-title><source>J. Sleep Res.</source><year>2023</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>e13865</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.13865</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36852716</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR48" publication-type="journal">Castiglione-Fontanellaz, C. E. G. et al. Sleep regularity in healthy adolescents: Associations with sleep duration, sleep quality, and mental health. <italic>J. Sleep Res.</italic><bold>32</bold>, e13865. 10.1111/jsr.13865 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36852716</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR49" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Depression in sleep disturbance: A review on a bidirectional relationship, mechanisms and treatment</article-title><source>J. Cell. Mol. Med.</source><year>2019</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>2324</fpage><lpage>2332</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jcmm.14170</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30734486</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR49" publication-type="journal">Fang, H., Tu, S., Sheng, J. &#x00026; Shao, A. Depression in sleep disturbance: A review on a bidirectional relationship, mechanisms and treatment. <italic>J. Cell. Mol. Med.</italic><bold>23</bold>, 2324&#x02013;2332. 10.1111/jcmm.14170 (2019).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30734486</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR50" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Dalen</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>van Charante</surname><given-names>EPM</given-names></name><name><surname>Nederkoorn</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>van Gool</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name><surname>Richard</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Poststroke apathy</article-title><source> Stroke</source><year>2013</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>851</fpage><lpage>860</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/STROKEAHA.112.674614</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23362076</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR50" publication-type="journal">van Dalen, J. W., van Charante, E. P. M., Nederkoorn, P. J., van Gool, W. A. &#x00026; Richard, E. Poststroke apathy. <italic>Stroke</italic><bold>44</bold>, 851&#x02013;860 10.1161/STROKEAHA.112.674614 (2013).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23362076</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR51" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bakken</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Finset</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lerdal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Subjective sleep quality in relation to objective sleep estimates: comparison, gender differences and changes between the acute phase and the six-month follow&#x02010;up after stroke</article-title><source>J. Adv. Nurs.</source><year>2014</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>639</fpage><lpage>650</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jan.12228</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23967876</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR51" publication-type="journal">Bakken, L. N., Kim, H. S., Finset, A. &#x00026; Lerdal, A. Subjective sleep quality in relation to objective sleep estimates: Comparison, gender differences and changes between the acute phase and the six-month follow&#x02010;up after stroke. <italic>J. Adv. Nurs.</italic><bold>70</bold>, 639&#x02013;650 (2014).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23967876</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR52" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trivedi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Irregular Sleep/Wake Patterns Are Associated With Reduced Quality of Life in Post-treatment Cancer Patients: A Study Across Three Cancer Cohorts</article-title><source>Front. NeuroSci.</source><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnins.2021.700923</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34630009</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR52" publication-type="journal">Trivedi, R. et al. Irregular sleep/wake patterns are associated with reduced quality of life in Post-treatment Cancer patients: A study across three Cancer cohorts. <italic>Front. Neurosci.</italic>10.3389/fnins.2021.700923 (2021).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34630009</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR53" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salah</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rekik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Frih</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association of quality of life and sleep quality in patients with ischemic stroke</article-title><source>J. Diabetes Treat.</source><year>2018</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>2574</fpage><lpage>7568</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR53" publication-type="journal">Salah, S., Rekik, M. &#x00026; Frih, Z. Association of quality of life and sleep quality in patients with ischemic stroke. <italic>J. Diabetes Treat.</italic><bold>10</bold>, 2574&#x02013;7568 (2018).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article>