<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39890852</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11785760</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">86938</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-025-86938-4</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Formulation of new drug delivery systems for insulin from natural bioactive biocompatible polymers</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Fetouh</surname><given-names>Howida A.</given-names></name><address><email>howida_fetouh@alexu.edu.eg</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Aleem</surname><given-names>Engy E. A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mohammed</surname><given-names>Najiyah H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Aldesouky</surname><given-names>Jihad M. Abd-Almajeed </given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ismail</surname><given-names>Amel M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/00mzz1w90</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.7155.6</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2260 6941</institution-id><institution>Chemistry Department, Faculty of Science, </institution><institution>Alexandria University, </institution></institution-wrap>Alexandria, Egypt </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/00mzz1w90</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.7155.6</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2260 6941</institution-id><institution>Clinical Pathology Department, Faculty of Medicine, </institution><institution>Alexandria University, </institution></institution-wrap>Alexandria, Egypt </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>31</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>3941</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>6</day><month>7</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">New insulin drug delivery systems (IDDs): insulin@chitin; insulin@chitin-grafted (g)-guar gum were prepared by using a modified sol&#x02013;gel method. Insulin vials were loaded on the safe natural inert bioactive polymers (chitin and chitin-g-GG copolymer) carriers using water green solvent. Traces amount additives were below toxicity limits. Guar gum increased the numbers of the functional groups of the polymer carrier. Insulin release monitored at 37&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.5&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C and buffer solutions of pH (1.2, 6.8 and 7.4) simulating physiological body fluids: stomach, intestine colon and blood stream. Insulin released from insulin@chitin only at pH 7.4. No release observed at pH 1.2, 6.8 due strong bonding to acetyl group of chitin. Insulin@chitin-GG system showed sustained targeting insulin-release at pH: 6.8&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;7.4&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.2. Release data obeyed pseudo second order kinetic model indicating that IDDs is heterogeneous solid surface of energetically different active sites. Each insulin molecule occupied two active sites. The slow release at pH 1.2 indicated protection against stomach juice. Release kinetic depend on physicochemical characteristics (porosity, swelling ratio as well as peptide and amino acid sequence). Both IDDs showed negative zeta potential indicating stability against aggregation. Gaur gum improved particle size distribution and insulin release.</p></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Chitin</kwd><kwd>Guar gum</kwd><kwd>Insulin</kwd><kwd>Drug delivery system</kwd><kwd>Release</kwd><kwd>Rate</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Biochemistry</kwd><kwd>Biotechnology</kwd><kwd>Drug discovery</kwd><kwd>Chemistry</kwd><kwd>Materials science</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Alexandria University</institution></funding-source></award-group><open-access><p>Open access funding provided by The Science, Technology &#x00026; Innovation Funding Authority (STDF) in cooperation with The Egyptian Knowledge Bank (EKB).</p></open-access></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Springer Nature Limited 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Chitin is a natural film forming bioactive polymer, available, biocompatible and biodegradable<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. Chitin is hypolipidemic, antimicrobial, wound healing and immunoadjuvant<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. It is abundant in crustaceans shells of seaweeds, anthoropods exoskeleton such as lobster, shrimp, insects and cephalopods such as squid and octopus fish. Chitin was named as &#x003b2;-(1&#x02009;&#x02192;&#x02009;4 glycoside)-N-acetyl-D-glucosamine), or 2-acetamido-2-deoxy-D-glucopyranose. The activity of chitin exerted by the primary alcoholic (CH<sub>2</sub>OH) and acetamide (CH<sub>3</sub>CONH) groups. Chitin chains form intra molecular hydrogen bonding (H.B). Chitin extracted as: collected shrimps scraped from loose tissue, washed and dried, demineralized in 15 wt.% HCl at room temperature (RT) for 36 h, filtered, washed thoroughly with tap- and demineralized water and dried at 80&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, grounded and sieved to 80 meshes size. Twenty gram powder was added to 5% NaOH (deproteinization), agitated for 1 h at 90&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, filtered, washed with tap water till neutrality, dried at 60&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 4 h.</p><p id="Par3">Guar gum is a plant resin linear poly-&#x003b2;-1, 4 anhydro mannose-galactose residues contains 4 OH per monomeric unit<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>; widely used in biosorbents not in DDS<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. Human insulin is a transporter dipeptide protein hormone of the molecular formula: C<sub>257</sub>H<sub>383</sub>N<sub>65</sub>O<sub>77</sub>S<sub>6</sub>. Insulin synthesized, releases and stored in the pancreas. The amino acids (aa) chains: A (21aa) and B (30 aa) residues linked by 2 disulfide bonds between cysteines units. Peptide bond formation via condensation gives the aa sequence. Blood insulin controls and regulates cellular or organs response to blood glucose level (BGL)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>. After a meal, insulin releases into blood activates cellular absorption of blood glucose (BG) for growth and energy. Insulin binding cell membranes receptors, Glucose transporter proteins released from cell interior to cell membrane carry and transport BG into the tissue.</p><p id="Par4">The IDDs tablets keeping are required for keeping of human health<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. Insulin vials such as Lantus Glargine and Levemir Detemir are long acting human insulin. Glargine is 10aa to 50 aa protein regulates uptake BGL via binding, transport into or out the cell<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. Diabetes Miletus (DM) chronic epidemic metabolic disease causes micro vascular complications such as retino-, nephron-, neuropathy and foot disorders.&#x000a0;Subcutaneous insulin injection for types I, II Diabetes Miletus (T1DM and T2DM) showed many drawbacks such as discomfort, pain and local infections<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. Acceptable insulin tablets mimic pharmacokinetics of endogenous insulin. Reported insulin carriers are pH-sensitive biodegradable biocompatible micro-particles and liposomes; layer-by-layer coat, polymer shells and nanocomposites (NCs). The obstacles of IDDs are the broad size distribution, unreproducible and uncontrolled initial burst release, excessive hypoglycemia and immunological response<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>. Examples of obstacles included: The microspheres poly (acrylic acid) @ chitosan-5-Fluoro-uracil required sodium-Na-taurocholate absorber<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. Insulin leaking from the alginate-Ca(II) ions microspheres due to the broad particle size distribution<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. &#x00392;eta cyclodextrin emulsions caused hypoglycemia<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. The poly-(anhydride, p-(COOH-ethyl-formamido)-benzoic anhydride] showed toxicity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>. Also the inefficient micro emulsion Eudragits adhered to the gastro intestinal tract (GIT)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par5">Anionic poly methyl acrylamide CH<sub>3</sub>-ester release insulin only at high pH<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. Burst release showed by encapsulated microspheres &#x02013;OH-propyl-CH<sub>3</sub>-cellulose acetate succinate. Eudragit-poly-lactic acid microspheres showed low entrapment efficiency and enzymatic degradation. Microspheres: good absorption: Tri-CH<sub>3</sub>-chitosan-Eudragit- Mg-stearate required lubricant<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>; OH-propyl-CH<sub>3</sub>-cellulose phthalate-Na-<italic>N</italic>-(8-[2-OH-benzoyl]-NH<sub>2</sub> should contain absorption enhancer<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>; Macromolecule poly ester amide limited by the enzymatic hydrolysis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par6">Chitosan (CT) increased insulin contact with duodenum and jejunum but low absorption<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>. It is a safe biocompatible biodegradable polysaccharide drug carrier, however the positive charges on its amino (NH<sub>2</sub>) group electrostatically attracted to the negative charges on insulin forming insoluble complex. In addition, CT has basic characteristics (pKa &#x02248; 6.5), so it dissolves in the acidic media. Hence CT-insulin insoluble complex tend to be soluble in the acidic juice of gastro intestinal tract<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. CT required grafting by another polymers to be insoluble. The plan of using chitin as a new carrier for insulin was based on the bond formation of insulin with the acetyl group of chitin. Chitin could be new more suitable polymer carrier for insulin than chitosan. This study aims formulation and evaluation of a new oral administration IDDs using natural inert biocompatible polymer chitin and GG carriers to overcome all the reported obstacles.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Experimental</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Materials</title><p id="Par7">Analytical grades pure chemicals purchased from certified companies of chemical products used without further purifications. Chitin A.R. (Flakes (C<sub>8</sub>H<sub>13</sub>NO<sub>5</sub>)<sub>n</sub> average molecular weight (<inline-formula id="IEq1"><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\overline{{M_{w.} }}$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_86938_Article_IEq1.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> 17&#x02013;20&#x000a0;kDa, (monomer Mw.259&#x000a0;Da), Batch NO. CH 546: Alpha Chemika Co. Powder GG (Mw. 10&#x000a0;k Da): Loba Chemie Co.-Mumbai-India. HCl, NaOH and glutaraldehyde crosslinker: EL Gomhoria Co. Ammonium persulphate (NH<sub>4</sub>S<sub>2</sub>O<sub>8</sub>) and sodium dodecyl sulphate (SDS) anionic surfactant catalyst and insulin Humalog vial solution lispro (3&#x000a0;mL (3.5&#x000a0;mg, 100 units&#x02019; mL<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>: Sigma Aldrich Co. The chemical structure of insulin carrier was represented supplementary information (SI), Fig.SI.1.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>The mechanism of formulation insulin drug delivery systems</title><p id="Par8">The insulin drug delivery systems (IDDs) were composed of compatible constituents. The type and the amount of the constituents of IDDs were shown in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Chemical constituents IDDS.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="3">Physical properties</th><th align="left">Insulin</th><th align="left">Chitin</th><th align="left">GG</th><th align="left">Glutaraldehyde</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Insulin</th><th align="left">Yellow color</th><th align="left">%Yield</th><th align="left" colspan="4">Wt.(g)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">@chitin</td><td align="left">Pale</td><td align="left">86.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">3 mL</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">0.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">@chitin-GG</td><td align="left">Dark</td><td align="left">75.2</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par9">Traces amount of NH<sub>4</sub>S<sub>2</sub>O<sub>8</sub> (0.05g) as free radical initiator and 0.03g SDS emulsifying agent below the toxicity limits were added. The IDDs were prepared in three neck Pyrex glass cell of volume capacity 100&#x000a0;mL following the sol&#x02013;gel method. The constituents&#x02019; materials were mixed and dissolved in 40&#x000a0;mL double distilled water. Alkaline pH 8 adjusted by 0.1&#x000a0;M NaOH and 0.1&#x000a0;M HCl. The reaction mixture was magnetically stirred at 150&#x000a0;rpm, 40&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 3.0&#x000a0;h under inert nitrogen (flow rate 10&#x000a0;mL min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>). Then the mixture was cooled to the room temperature. Then the mixture set to equilibrium overnight. The polymer chitin and guar gum suspend in water by the trace amount of the SDS surfactant. The contact time between insulin vial and the carrier is sufficient for efficient loading. Insulin incorporated on the carrier chitin or chitin-guar gum via integration of insulin with nanoparticle of chitin and guar gum during the formulation time. The reaction mixture was filtered under suction. The solvent was evaporated at 55&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C under reduced pressure. The nanoparticles of IDDS collected through centrifugation at 14,000&#x000a0;rpm for 20&#x000a0;min. to remove the excess solvent. The free insulin and surfactant washed away with double distilled water to remove the remaining unreacted constituents. The obtained solid products were grinded into a nanoscale powder using mortar and pestle and packed in the sealed vials<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par10">High insulin drug loading in the formulation drug delivery systems could reduce the amount of matrix drug carrier required. The loading mechanism involved adsorption or desorption processes of insulin into the pores of the polymer carriers. The drug loading and encapsulation efficiency were ensured due to good solubility of insulin in the carrier and excipient matrix that depend on the matrix composition, molecular weight, insulin-polymer interaction and the presence of functional groups (hydroxyl and acetyl group) in the drug matrix. The presence of guar gum in the carrier matrix improved the ionic interaction between insulin and matrix materials by the addition of further hydroxyl functional groups.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Characterization of the drug delivery systems</title><p id="Par11">The functional groups (FGs) were confirmed using Fourier Transformer Infrared (FTIR) spectroscopy (KBr) using Bruker TENSOR 37 spectrophotometer, Model 1430 PS calibrated (1602&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1&#x000a0;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) at the frequency range 4000&#x02013;450&#x000a0;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> at RT<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. Scanning electron microscope (SEM) micrographs using JSM-IT200 SEM. Powder X-ray diffraction (PXRD) patterns at 25&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C using Cu-K&#x003b1; radiation of wavelength (&#x003bb;) 1.54060&#x000a0;&#x000c5; accelerated at 40&#x000a0;kV using Bruker D8 advance diffractometer: Angle range&#x00026; rate were 5&#x02013;70&#x000b0;, 0.02o step, 1&#x000b0; min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> respectively<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. Differential thermal- and thermogravimetric analysis (DTA), (TGA) respectively using Shimadzu DTA/TGA-50, heating rate 10&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> using Pt. cell under nitrogen rate flow 20&#x000a0;mL min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. TGA plot (weight loss sample as a function of (temperature or time) and DTA (weight loss versus temperature difference. (<inline-formula id="IEq2"><alternatives><tex-math id="M2">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\Delta {\text{T = T}}_{{{\text{sample}}}} - {\text{T}}_{{{\text{inertrefrence}}}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_86938_Article_IEq2.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>) at zero difference heat flow against heating temperature (t&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. Mean swelling ratio&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD, n&#x02009;=&#x02009;3 in deionized water at RT due to water absorption into pores was determined using Eq.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Equ1" ref-type="disp-formula">1</xref> as: lyophilized sample was swelled in excess phosphate buffer saline (BFS), pH 7.4, 37&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.5&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, time intervals (5&#x02013;60&#x000a0;min. and 1, 8, 15&#x000a0;days; removed from BFS, reweighed after removing the excess surface H<sub>2</sub>O using blotting paper. The swelling ratio was calculated using Eq.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Equ1" ref-type="disp-formula">1</xref><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>:<disp-formula id="Equ1"><label>1</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\text{Swelling}}\;{\text{ ratio }} = \frac{{W_{s} - W_{o} }}{{W_{o} }} \times 100$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_86938_Article_Equ1.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <inline-formula id="IEq3"><alternatives><tex-math id="M4">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${W}_{o}$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_86938_Article_IEq3.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="IEq4"><alternatives><tex-math id="M5">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${W}_{s}$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_86938_Article_IEq4.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> are the weight of the dry and the swollen sample respectively.</p><p id="Par12">Mean porosity percent&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD of lyophilized sample was determined in triplicates (using Eq.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Equ2" ref-type="disp-formula">2</xref>) at 37&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.5&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C by liquid displacement method; 0.2&#x000a0;g sample was immersed in 10&#x000a0;mL distilled water <inline-formula id="IEq5"><alternatives><tex-math id="M6">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$( \text{density }\rho )$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_86938_Article_IEq5.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> 24&#x000a0;h till equilibrium; freeze dried and reweighed<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>:<disp-formula id="Equ2"><label>2</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M7">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\text{Porosity }}\% \, = \frac{{W_{2} - W_{1} }}{{\rho V_{s} }} \times 100$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_86938_Article_Equ2.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <inline-formula id="IEq6"><alternatives><tex-math id="M8">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${W}_{2}$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_86938_Article_IEq6.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="IEq7"><alternatives><tex-math id="M9">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${W}_{1}$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_86938_Article_IEq7.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> sample weights before and after immersion, <inline-formula id="IEq8"><alternatives><tex-math id="M10">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${V}_{s}$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_86938_Article_IEq8.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> volume of dry sample.</p><p id="Par13">Insulin denaturation was done by 2&#x000a0;mL Biuret reagent (0.39&#x000a0;g hydrated CuSO<sub>4</sub>&#x02009;+&#x02009;9&#x000a0;g Na&#x02013;K- tartarate) in 500&#x000a0;mL 0.2N NaOH to sample, vortex mixing, RT incubation 15&#x000a0;min. Absorbance at 550&#x000a0;nm was measured<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>. The amino acid (aa) contents were determined as follows: Different volumes standard aa glycine was pipetted into labeled test tubes. 1.0&#x000a0;mL ninhydrin reagent was added to all sample (blank and unknown), contents are mixed by vortex, placed in boiling water in waterbath for 15&#x000a0;min. 1&#x000a0;mL ninhydrin was added, mixed well and the absorbance was recorded at 570&#x000a0;nm. Calibration curves of Burette and Ninhydrin tests were used<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. Particle size (PS) of diluted sample suspension with distilled water to appropriate concentration was determined in triplicates using photon correlation spectroscopy (PCS), NanoZS/ZEN3600 Zetasizer via non-invasive backscattering technology at 173&#x000b0; detection angle at 25.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. Zeta potential was determined of diluted sample. Volume of 1.0&#x000a0;mL suspension is placed in a universal folded capillary cell contains Pt. electrodes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Kinetic of invitro insulin release</title><p id="Par14">The standard calibration curve of Insulin was constructed using known concentrations (7, 10.5, 14, 17.5, 21, 24.5, 28 and 35&#x000a0;ppm) diluted from 10&#x000a0;mg/mL insulin in 100&#x000a0;mL absolute ethanol<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. Insulin release from IDDSs was monitored by recording UV&#x02013;vis. absorbance (A) at 274&#x000a0;nm, double beam spectrophotometer UV T80. Constant length dialysis bag: (VISKING dialysis cellulose tubing 21&#x000a0;mm diameter was soaked 10&#x000a0;min. in distilled water at RT, rinsed thoroughly with distilled water to remove preservative<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>; 30&#x000a0;mg sample was dissolved in 1&#x000a0;mL buffer solutions at 37&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.5&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C; placed in 25&#x000a0;mL buffer solution in waterbath agitated at100 rpm. Released insulin was determined via withdrawing 3.0&#x000a0;mL releasing medium at different times. Total buffer volume was kept 25&#x000a0;mL. Release from insulin @chitin cannot be monitored at pH 1.2, 6.8 due strong linkage of peptide amide bond on insulin to acetyl group of chitin. Release data in duplicates from insulin@chitin-g-GG were linearly fitted to kinetic models: Zero order (Eq.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Equ3" ref-type="disp-formula">3</xref>): slow release from non-disaggregate DDs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>.<disp-formula id="Equ3"><label>3</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M11">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$Q_{t} = Q_{o + } K_{o} t$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_86938_Article_Equ3.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par15">Q<sub>0</sub> (=&#x02009;0), Q<sub>t</sub> are the initial and released concentration respectively, K<sub>0</sub> rate constant oncentration time<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>).</p><p id="Par16">Pseudo 1&#x000b0; (Eq.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Equ4" ref-type="disp-formula">4</xref>): Concentration change with time<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>.<disp-formula id="Equ4"><label>4</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M12">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\text{ln}}(q_{e} - q_{t } ) = {\text{ln}}(q_{e} ) - k_{1 } t$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_86938_Article_Equ4.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <italic>q</italic><sub><italic>e</italic></sub>, q<sub>t</sub>: equilibrium and time dependent desorption capacity respectively (mg g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), k<sub>1</sub> rate constant (min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>).</p><p id="Par17">Pseudo (2&#x000b0;), Eq.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Equ5" ref-type="disp-formula">5</xref><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>:<disp-formula id="Equ5"><label>5</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M13">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\frac{t}{{q_{t} }} = \frac{1}{{k_{2 } q_{e}^{2} }} + \frac{t}{{q_{e} }}$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_86938_Article_Equ5.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where q<sub>e</sub> and q<sub>t</sub> equilibrium and time dependent desorption capacity (pp mg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), respectively, k<sub>2</sub> rate constant (g/mg min).</p><p id="Par18">Initial desorption rate, h (ppm g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>&#x000a0;min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)&#x02009;=&#x02009;<italic>k</italic><sub><italic>2</italic></sub><italic>q</italic><sub><italic>e</italic></sub><sup><italic>2</italic></sup><italic>.</italic></p><p id="Par19">Elovich model: slow desorption chemisorbed insulin from heterogeneous surface, Eq.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Equ6" ref-type="disp-formula">6</xref><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup><disp-formula id="Equ6"><label>6</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M14">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$q_{t} = \frac{1}{\beta }\ln \left( {\alpha \beta } \right) + \frac{1}{\beta }{\text{ln}}\left( t \right)$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_86938_Article_Equ6.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>: initial desorption rate (mg g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>&#x000a0;min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), <italic>&#x003b2;:</italic> desorption constant (g mg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) at the release time (t).</p><p id="Par20">Huguchi (Eq.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Equ7" ref-type="disp-formula">7</xref>): Release from porous planar polymer; initial concentration is larger than released concentration, 1D constant diffusion without edging; particles smaller than system thickness; negligible swelling and carrier dissolution in perfect release media<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>.<disp-formula id="Equ7"><label>7</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M15">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$q_{t} = {\text{dissolution constan}} (K_{H} ) \times t^{\frac{1}{2}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_86938_Article_Equ7.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par21">Finger-Puppets-Korsmeyer-Peppas model (Eq.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Equ8" ref-type="disp-formula">8</xref>) represented drug release from a modified structural and geometrical carrier<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>:<disp-formula id="Equ8"><label>8</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M16">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$log\frac{{C_{t} }}{{C_{\infty } }} = \log k + n\log t$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_86938_Article_Equ8.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par22">(C<sub>t</sub>/C<sub>&#x0221e;</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;fraction release at time t, k: rate constant, n: diffusion exponent reflect transport mechanism, k: constant (t<sup>n</sup> unit).</p><p id="Par23">Insulin release from solution 50&#x000a0;ppm IDDs in buffer solutions was monitored using electrochemical impedance using determined using electrochemical cell at 37&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. Gamry Potentiostat-G300)-sequencer V6.12, DC105 at the frequency range 100&#x000a0;kHz-10&#x000a0;Hz. AC signal 10&#x000a0;mV at open circuit potential using carbon felt working electrode (WE: cross sectional area 0.28 cm<sup>2</sup> (cleaned by 1:1&#x000a0;V/V mixture 1.0&#x000a0;M HCl-deionized water, 1:1 (V/V) ethanol&#x02013;water solvent 5&#x000a0;min., sonicated (2&#x000a0;min. at 47&#x000a0;kHz) in DI water, air dried), activated by agitation in 1.0&#x000a0;M H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> for 24&#x000a0;h. Sulphate functional groups were adsorption site for the released insulin). Pt. wire and Ag/AgCl<sub>(s)</sub> were used as counter and reference) electrodes respectively.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Results and discussion</title><sec id="Sec8"><title>Characterization of insulin drug delivery systems</title><p id="Par24">Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> showed the different IR spectra confirmed modified chemical structure of chitin by grafted GG. Insulin@chitin-GG showed FGs chitin: CH<sub>2</sub>OH, CH<sub>3</sub>CONH), insulin: NH<sub>2</sub>, COOH. Assigned vibrational bands (Table SI.1) at characteristic wavenumber, (<inline-formula id="IEq9"><alternatives><tex-math id="M17">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\overline{\upsilon },$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_86938_Article_IEq9.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) confirmed intercalation between chitin and GG<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>FTIR spectra of IDDS.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_86938_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p id="Par25">The vibrational bands around 3444.6 due to presence of &#x02013;OH stretching and amine N&#x02013;H symmetric vibrations. The band at 1070.4 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> is due to &#x02013;C&#x02013;O groups stretching vibrations of N-acetyl group of chitin (the main adsorption center for insulin).The peaks between 1070.4&#x02013;1028 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and 530&#x02013;540 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> indicated the presence of polysaccharide rings with the characteristic C&#x02013;O groups. For insulin, O&#x02013;H stretching, &#x02013;COO&#x02013; symmetric and asymmetric stretching, and &#x02013;C&#x02013;O&#x02013;C-stretching appeared at 3239 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, 1405 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, 1592 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, and 1024 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> respectively. The C&#x02013;O stretching vibration and NH bending with contribution of CN stretching vibrations at 1639 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and 1542 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> respectively. GG exhibited the characteristic absorption bands at 3383 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and 2925 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>&#x000a0;due to O&#x02013;H stretching vibrations associated with C-H stretching vibrations. In spectrum of insulin nanocomposites, two characteristic absorption peaks of insulin are almost masked and a new peak at 1594 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> of C&#x02013;N, mainly due to C&#x02013;O stretching vibrations were observed<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. The C&#x02013;O stretching vibration and N&#x02013;H bending with contribution of C&#x02013;N stretching vibrations at 1639 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and 1542 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> respectively<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. In insulin@chitin-g-GG, two characteristic absorption peaks of insulin are almost masked, and a new peak at 1594 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> of C&#x02013;N, mainly due to C&#x02013;O stretching vibrations are observed. Acloholic CH<sub>2</sub>OH group of chitin is also involved in H.B.with GG. Successful insulin loading was accomplished in according to FTIR spectra. Chitin contains hydroxyl (OH<sup><bold>&#x02212;</bold></sup>) group of functional (CH<sub>2</sub>OH) groups at C2 of glucose monomer unit OH<sup><bold>-</bold></sup> linked to carbony group of insulin-COOH on alkaline hydrolysis.</p><p id="Par26">Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> showed SEM micrographs of insulin formulations in comparison to that of insulin and chitin.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>SEM micrographs, magnification 45,000&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_86938_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p><p id="Par27">Layered microstructure insulin due to interconnected polypeptide chains by: S&#x02013;S bond, H.B between amino (NH<sub>2</sub>)&#x02013;COOH of cysteine<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. Bright fine spherical chitin nanoparticles (NPs) regularly linked insulin chains. Chitin and insulin morpholgy were maintained in IDDS. Copolymer is smoother carrier. Insulin added uniformly distributed on the carrier polymer with no coagulation.</p><p id="Par28">The pXRD patterns of the formulated IDDs were shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>pXRD patterns of IDDs.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_86938_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p><p id="Par29">The pXRD pattern of insulin@chitin showed semi-crystallinity characterizing native chitin Insulin@chitin is semi-crystalline (N atom of chitin is strongly bidentated O atom of COOH function group of insulin. Insulin@chitin-g-GG has both crystalline and amorphous domains<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>. Grafting chitin by GG declined chitin crystallinity. Higher crystalline insulin@chitin indicated that N atom of (NH) group of chitin is strongly binding O atom of COOH insulin in bidentate chelating. Binding GG to both insulin and chitin involved H.B. and Van der Waals interaction. Many diffraction patterns were observed in pXRD of insulin@chitin indicating more crystallinity than in insulin@chitin-g-GG. The only one broad diffraction peak was due to packing of GG into chitin carrier.</p><p id="Par30">Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> showed TGA and DTA thermograms. Insulin@chitin was better thermally stable than Insulin@chitin-GG. Thermal decomposition parameters were collected in Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Thermograms of IDDs.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_86938_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Thermal decomposition data.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Insulin</th><th align="left">Steps</th><th align="left">t, &#x000b0;C range</th><th align="left">Wt. loss%</th><th align="left">%Residue</th><th align="left">DTA, peaks t, &#x000b0;C</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">@chitin</td><td char="." align="char"><p>2</p><p>2</p><p>3</p></td><td align="left"><p>36.4&#x02013;74.8</p><p>74.8&#x02013;230.4</p><p>230.4&#x02013;696.0</p></td><td align="left"><p>3.45</p><p>18.30</p><p>27.74</p></td><td char="." align="char">66.86</td><td align="left"><p>86.3&#x02013;140.8 (endo, intense)</p><p>248.4&#x02013;292.7 (exo weak)</p><p>295.5-381.1 (exo weak)</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">@chitin-GG</td><td char="." align="char"><p>1</p><p>2</p></td><td align="left"><p>36.3&#x02013;376.0</p><p>376.0&#x02013;700.1</p></td><td align="left"><p>59.78</p><p>21.53</p></td><td char="." align="char">18.59</td><td align="left"><p>276.5&#x02013;402.1 (exo, broad&#x00026; intense), </p><p>447.4&#x02013;508.2 ( exo, broad&#x00026; intense)</p></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par31">Insulin@chitin showed multistep decomposition and one endothermic peak at 86.3&#x02013;140.8&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C due to strong bound FGs of chitin and insulin. Insulin@chitin-g-GG decomposed in 2 steps, higher wt. loss% and lower residue. Two broad intense exothermic peaks due to bonded decomposed carboneous polymeric residues species<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>The validation of UV&#x02013;visible spectroscopy for in vitro kinetics of insulin release</title><p id="Par32">For quantification of insulin by absorption spectroscopy, the full wavelength scanning spectrophotometrically.The absorption maxima was found at maximum wavelength (&#x003bb;<sub>max.</sub> 274 nm).The measurement of insulin release from the drug delivery system was validated using UV spectroscopy. The following section showed the complete details about the release study.</p><p id="Par33">The validity of UV&#x02013;visible spectroscopic technique was examined by constructing calibration curves of standard solutions (7, 10.5, 14, 17.5, 21, 24.5, 28 and 35 ppm) of insulin and recording the absorption of the full curves at &#x003bb;<sub>max.</sub> 274 nm) as illustrated in experimental section "<xref rid="Sec6" ref-type="sec">Kinetic of invitro insulin release</xref>".</p><p id="Par34">Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> showed UV&#x02013;vis. spectra of the standard insulin solutions used in the construction of the calibration curve.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Full curves UV&#x02013;vis. absorbance spectra.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_86938_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p><p id="Par35">On applying the least square method on absorbance-concentration plot (standard calibration curve, Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>), a good straight line was obtained with correlation coefficient equal 0.9984 confirmed the validity of UV&#x02013;visible spectroscopy as an analytical method for analysis of insulin release.<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Standard calibration curve of insulin.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_86938_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p><p id="Par36">The molar extension coefficient (&#x003b5;) equals was calculated 0.005 from the slope of the obtained straight line. Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref> showed UV absorbance spectra of insulin released in the supernatant solution at &#x003bb;<sub>max.</sub> 274 nm for insulin release from the nanocomposite insulin-chitin-g-GG at the different aqueous buffer solutions of pH (1.2, 6.8, and 7.4 simulating the biological fluids in the stomach, colon, and blood respectively at the physiological temperature 37&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.5&#x000b0;C.<fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Variation of absorbance with time of insulin release at different pH.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_86938_Fig7_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig></p><p id="Par37">The insulin release from different DDS samples was assayed at &#x003bb;<sub>max.</sub> 274 nm. Each experiment was performed in duplicates. Insulin release from insulin @chitin microcapsule cannot be monitored spectrophotometrically except at pH 7.4 due the strong linkage of peptide amide bond of insulin to the acetyl group of chitin. The concentration of insulin released was obtained using Beers Lambert law<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par38">Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref> represented the amount of insulin release from the two formulated drug delivery systems.<fig id="Fig8"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>Released insulin concentration with the time.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_86938_Fig8_HTML" id="MO8"/></fig></p><p id="Par39">Insulin@chitin showed only insulin released at pH 7.4 give low 5 ppm concentration. Release at pH 1.2 and 6.8 cannot be followed spectrophotometrically. Insulin@chitin-g-GG showed higher release 10, 16, 18 ppm at pH 1.2, 7.4, 6.8. Encapsulated adhered insulin to permeable membrane polymer shell rapidly burst release (in 15 min.) detached in response to pH<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup> in agreement with half life time (few min.) pharmacokinetic of insulin in blood<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. Insulin@chitin-GG showed controlled release limited at 76.2%, 80.7% and 67.2% at pH 1.2, 6.8 and 7.4 indicating stability against proteolysis. The release data from insulin@chitin-g-GG were linearly fitted to different kinetic model as represented in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>.<fig id="Fig9"><label>Fig. 9</label><caption><p>The linear fitting of the release insulin concentration to pseudo 2&#x000b0; kinetic model.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_86938_Fig9_HTML" id="MO9"/></fig></p><p id="Par40">The least square linear regression analysis was applied. Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref> collected correlation coefficients values (R<sup>2</sup>).<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Values R<sup>2</sup> for linear fitting release data to kinetic models.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">pH</th><th align="left">Run</th><th align="left">0&#x000b0;</th><th align="left">Pseudo 1&#x000b0;</th><th align="left">Pseudo 2&#x000b0;</th><th align="left">Elovich</th><th align="left">Higuchi</th><th align="left">Ritger-Peppas</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">1.2</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td char="." align="char">0.7259</td><td char="." align="char">0.8845</td><td char="." align="char">0.9965</td><td char="." align="char">0.943</td><td char="." align="char">0.8452</td><td char="." align="char">0.897</td></tr><tr><td char="." align="char">2</td><td char="." align="char">0.8338</td><td char="." align="char">0.974</td><td char="." align="char">0.9994</td><td char="." align="char">0.9857</td><td char="." align="char">0.9261</td><td char="." align="char">0.9609</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">6.8</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td char="." align="char">0.3691</td><td char="." align="char">0.3611</td><td char="." align="char">0.9959</td><td char="." align="char">0.5906</td><td char="." align="char">0.4794</td><td char="." align="char">0.6197</td></tr><tr><td char="." align="char">2</td><td char="." align="char">0.3977</td><td char="." align="char">0.3821</td><td char="." align="char">0.9618</td><td char="." align="char">0.6574</td><td char="." align="char">0.5293</td><td char="." align="char">0.6915</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">7.4</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td char="." align="char">0.7466</td><td char="." align="char">0.7549</td><td char="." align="char">0.9975</td><td char="." align="char">0.8645</td><td char="." align="char">0.8098</td><td char="." align="char">0.8368</td></tr><tr><td char="." align="char">2</td><td char="." align="char">0.7721</td><td char="." align="char">0.7889</td><td char="." align="char">0.9998</td><td char="." align="char">0.9652</td><td char="." align="char">0.8815</td><td char="." align="char">0.9432</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par41">Based on the value of the correlation coefficient (R<sup>2</sup>), it was found that the best kinetic model fitted the release data was the pseudo second order model. Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref> collected the results of the linear regression analysis (R<sup>2</sup>) and the standard error (S.E) for runs 1, 2 respectively.<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Parameters of regression analysis of released insulin to 2&#x000b0; model.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="3">pH 1.2</th><th align="left" colspan="3">pH 6.8</th><th align="left" colspan="3">pH 7.4</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Regression eq.</th><th align="left">R<sup>2</sup></th><th align="left">S.E.</th><th align="left">Regression eq.</th><th align="left">R<sup>2</sup></th><th align="left">S.E</th><th align="left">Regression eq.</th><th align="left">R<sup>2</sup></th><th align="left">S.E</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">y&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.051x&#x02009;+&#x02009;0.36</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">0.22</td><td align="left">y&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.088x&#x02009;+&#x02009;0.256</td><td align="left">1.00</td><td align="left">0.32</td><td align="left">y&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.066x&#x02009;+&#x02009;0.325</td><td align="left">1.00</td><td align="left">0.46</td></tr><tr><td align="left">y&#x02009;=&#x02009;.050x&#x02009;+&#x02009;0.374</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">0.25</td><td align="left">y&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.063x&#x02009;+&#x02009;0.138</td><td align="left">0.96</td><td align="left">0.22</td><td align="left">y&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.048x&#x02009;+&#x02009;0.140</td><td align="left">1.00</td><td align="left">0.58</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par42">The pseudo 2&#x000b0; model had the highest R<sup>2</sup>: (0.9618&#x02013;0.9998) for all runs. It is the suitable fitted kinetic model for the release data of insulin. Non fitted Higuchi plot indicated desorption mechanism from polymer matrix is not under diffusion control<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. The kinetic parameters <italic>k</italic><sub>2</sub>, <italic>q</italic><sub>e</sub> collected in Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>.<table-wrap id="Tab5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>kinetic parameter of pseudo 2&#x000b0; model.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">pH</th><th align="left">Run</th><th align="left">k<sub>2</sub> (g/mg min)</th><th align="left">q<sub>e cal</sub> (ppm)</th><th align="left">h (ppm g<sup>&#x02212;&#x02009;1</sup> min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</th><th align="left"><italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">1.2</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td char="." align="char">0.0073</td><td char="." align="char">19.64</td><td char="." align="char">2.816</td><td char="." align="char">0.9965</td></tr><tr><td char="." align="char">2</td><td char="." align="char">0.0067</td><td char="." align="char">19.92</td><td char="." align="char">2.674</td><td char="." align="char">0.9994</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">6.8</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td char="." align="char">0.0305</td><td char="." align="char">11.32</td><td char="." align="char">3.908</td><td char="." align="char">0.9959</td></tr><tr><td char="." align="char">2</td><td char="." align="char">0.0290</td><td char="." align="char">15.79</td><td char="." align="char">7.237</td><td char="." align="char">0.9618</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">7.4</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td char="." align="char">0.0134</td><td char="." align="char">15.12</td><td char="." align="char">3.063</td><td char="." align="char">0.9975</td></tr><tr><td char="." align="char">2</td><td char="." align="char">0.0161</td><td char="." align="char">21.05</td><td char="." align="char">7.133</td><td char="." align="char">0.9998</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par43">The linear fitting of the release data to the pseudo 2&#x000b0; order model indicated insulin@chitin-g-GG heterogeneous solid surface has different energetic active sites<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. Insulin molecule is release from two adsorption sites. The values of the rate constant k<sub>2</sub> followed the order: pH 6.8&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;7.4&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.2 (confirmed by impedance plots, Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref><fig id="Fig10"><label>Fig. 10</label><caption><p>Impedance plots: insulin NCs at pH 1.2, 7.4 and 6.8 respectively.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_86938_Fig10_HTML" id="MO10"/></fig></p><p id="Par44">Smaller charge transfer resistance (R<sub>ct</sub> semicircle diameter) for insulin @chitin-GG at all pH indicated that low released [insulin] due to tight linkage to chitin. Few insulin molecules liberated from insulin@chitin adsorbed on WE surface by heteroatoms of FGs. DDS polarized by applied AC current, liberated insulin that adsorbed on surface of WE and increased R<sub>ct</sub><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. Release retarded at pH 1.2 and enhanced at pH 7.4. For insulin @chitin-GG, slow release at low pH indicating insulin protection against aggressive HCl in GIT: pH 1&#x02013;3 (extend transit time till passage to small intestine for absorption in blood. Chitin is muco adhesive polymer carrier retard: insulin degradation and loss in gastric acid and intestine fluid. High release rate at colon pH 6.8 due to weakness insulin-NPs connections causing release without degradation. Absorption enhancers in mosaic layer and enterocytes connected by tight junction improved release. Insulin release is pH dependent. Similar pH response, such as insulin retention within polymer matrix at acidic pH and significant release at higher pH insulin alginate microspheres<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par45">AC current polarized (by amphoteric Zwitter ionic NH<sub>2</sub> of insulin) and changed dielectric properties in IDDs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. Capacitive impedance plots confirmed: macroscopic dielectric properties, charge separation and phase transition<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>. Muco adhesive GG enhanced controlled sustained insulin release by hydrophilicity, charge density and pH response<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. Insulin release via swelling by aqueous buffer solution. Insulin relaxation gives one time constant. EIS agreed with UV&#x02013;vis. spectra: chitin carrier difficultly release insulin. Better insulin release from chitin-GG is due to swelling and porosity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>, Table <xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref>.<table-wrap id="Tab6"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Porosity and swelling percentage.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">IDDs</th><th align="left">Chitin</th><th align="left">GG</th><th align="left">Insulin @chitin</th><th align="left">Insulin @chitin-g-GG</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Porosity</td><td align="left">503&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;20</td><td align="left">723&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;37</td><td align="left">63.37&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;20</td><td align="left">47.37&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;20</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Swelling%</td><td align="left">3100</td><td align="left">2900</td><td align="left">980</td><td align="left">650</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par46">Chitin had the largest swelling percentage. GG extensively form intramolecular H.B. (4 H.B. per monomer) forming 3D network structure. High rheology limited water absorption. Although swelling insulin @chitin exceeded insulin@chitin-g-GG, however strong linkage between semi crystalline chitin and insulin retard insulin release<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. High porosity GG was attributed strong intermolecular H.B. Low porosity insulin @chitin-g-GG although better release suggested high: cross linking and loading capacity. Insulin loaded by both penetration into pores and binding multiple FGs. However, chitin-g-GG copolymer is loaded by more insulin decreased porosity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. Swelling, increase interior accessible surface for absorption aqueous physiological body fluid. Insulin @chitin-g-GG has hydrogel character behave as low viscous liquid with rapid phase transition. Grafted chitin was loaded by more insulin than chitin due to multiple FGs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>.The aa test (8&#x000a0;h immersion in phosphate buffer saline) confirmed more peptides and aa sequence in insulin@chitin-g-GG<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>, Table <xref rid="Tab7" ref-type="table">7</xref>.<table-wrap id="Tab7"><label>Table 7</label><caption><p>Peptides and aa sequence for IDDS.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left" colspan="3">Insulin@chitin</th><th align="left" colspan="3">Insulin@chitin-g-GG</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">C <sub>mg/mL</sub></td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Peptide</td><td align="left">0.39</td><td align="left">0.43</td><td align="left">0.50</td><td align="left">0.61</td><td align="left">1.46</td><td align="left">2.27</td></tr><tr><td align="left">aa</td><td align="left">0.05</td><td align="left">0.51</td><td align="left">0.9</td><td align="left">0.071</td><td align="left">0.69</td><td align="left">1.04</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par47">Insulin (biological polypeptide protein; Mw.&#x000a0;5.800&#x000a0;k Da) degradation by ninhydrin&#x000a0;(breaking peptide bonds between aa) giving aa (different NH<sub>2</sub>, COOH) position. Insulin exists in solution as monomers, dimers,&#x000a0;tetramers and hexamers by ions-, and solvent interaction. Monomers are nonpolar hydrophobic, polar, neutral, basic, and acidic<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. Insulin has primary protein structure (aa chains) has neither &#x003b1;-helix pleated sheet nor 3D conformation without association.</p><p id="Par48">Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig">11</xref> showed that IDDS have the same particle size distribution between nano-, micro scale (70&#x02013;1000&#x000a0;nm) up to 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m confirmed successful insulin loading on carrier.<fig id="Fig11"><label>Fig. 11</label><caption><p>Particle size distributions.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_86938_Fig11_HTML" id="MO11"/></fig></p><p id="Par49">P.S.D. is slightly modified at &#x000b5;m region for insulin@chtin-g-GG due to increased surface area by additional FGs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par50">Negative zeta potential originated from electrical double layer (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig12" ref-type="fig">12</xref>) confirmed stability against: coagulation, storage temperatures, and mechanical shear force<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>.<fig id="Fig12"><label>Fig. 12</label><caption><p>Zeta potentials insulin NCs.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_86938_Fig12_HTML" id="MO12"/></fig></p><p id="Par51">Chitin-g-GG is ether copolymer hydrophilic arranged in block, random or alternating configuration throughout polymeric chains network, or interpenetrating polymer blends<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>. Insulin chains firmely linked to chitin NPs. Carbonyl acetamide group NHCOCH<sub>3</sub> in chitin broken in alkaline reaction media, binding NH<sub>2</sub>-insulin. In insulin@chitin-g-GG, acloholic CH<sub>2</sub>OH of chitin form intermolecular H.B. with GG (intra-molecular) H.B<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par52">Insulin was chemical bonded and immobilized on the carrier polymers The chemical bonding between insulin and the carrier is more likely occurs via the functional groups and aided by chemical cross-linking, intermolecular hydrogen bonding, in addition to the electrostatic, hydrophobic and Van der Waals forces<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. The electrostatic interactions between the acidic amino acids in insulin protein and acetyl groups of CT<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par53">Chitin or chitin-GG are inert biodegradable permeable insulin carriers. Insulin loaded on chitin or its high functionality copolymer. Insulin-chains aa sequence bounded chitin decreased chains rigidity. Insulin@chitin has depth pores. Smoother insulin@chitin-g-GG had multiple FGs and little pores. Polymer chains chitin and GG cross linked via intermolecular H.B and Van der Waals interaction. Insulin@chitin semicrystalline with deep tunable pores. Chitin NH-, OH strongly binding insulin (O atom of COOH). Insulin chitin is more thermally stable. Insulin@chitin-g-GG showed better sustained insulin release. Chitin-g-GG is heterogeneous surface and each insulin molecule occupied 2.0 active sites. Targeting insulin-release at physiological temperature followed trend: pH 6.8&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;pH 7.4&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;pH 1.2 (lowest release rate at pH 1.2 indicated protection against acidic- or enzymatic hydrolysis in GIT, target sustained absorption in blood to regulate BGL. Physicochemical characteristics of insulin@chitin-g-GG and insulin@chitin porosity, swelling ratio, peptide &#x00026;aa sequence, zeta potential, particle size distribution and release kinetics confirmed: Insulin loaded on chitin by chemisorbed monolayer and on chitin-g-GG by chemi-, and phyi-sorption. Electrostatic bonding to multiple FGs of copolymers facilitated insulin release. Chitin was electron acceptor Lewis acid. Chitin-g-GG was Lewis and Bronsted acid. Chitin had high insulin loading capacity. However, strong irreversible chemical bonding retard release.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41598_2025_86938_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><caption><p>Supplementary Information 1.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="41598_2025_86938_MOESM2_ESM.docx"><caption><p>Supplementary Information 2.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1038/s41598-025-86938-4.</p></sec><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>All author contribute this study.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>Open access funding provided by The Science, Technology &#x00026; Innovation Funding Authority (STDF) in cooperation with The Egyptian Knowledge Bank (EKB). Funding was provided by Alexandria University.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>All data generated or analysed during this study are included in this published article.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par54">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Ethical approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par55">No ethical issue. All authors approved participation consent.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par56">Authors approved consent on publication.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mehrabani</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Karimian</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Mehramouz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahimi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kafil</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preparation of biocompatible and biodegradable silk fibroin/chitin/silver nanoparticles 3D scaffolds as a bandage for antimicrobial wound dressing</article-title><source>Int. J. Biol. Macromol.</source><year>2018</year><volume>114</volume><fpage>961</fpage><lpage>971</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2018.03.128</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29581004</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Mehrabani, M. G., Karimian, R., Mehramouz, B., Rahimi, M. &#x00026; Kafil, H. S. Preparation of biocompatible and biodegradable silk fibroin/chitin/silver nanoparticles 3D scaffolds as a bandage for antimicrobial wound dressing. <italic>Int. J. Biol. Macromol.</italic><bold>114</bold>, 961&#x02013;971 (2018).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29581004</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tolesa</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chitin and chitosan production from shrimp shells using ammonium-based ionic liquids</article-title><source>Int. J. Biol. Macromol.</source><year>2019</year><volume>130</volume><fpage>818</fpage><lpage>826</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2019.03.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30840869</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Tolesa, L. D., Gupta, B. S. &#x00026; Lee, M. J. Chitin and chitosan production from shrimp shells using ammonium-based ionic liquids. <italic>Int. J. Biol. Macromol.</italic><bold>130</bold>, 818&#x02013;826 (2019).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30840869</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bak</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intrinsic viscosity of binary gum mixtures with xanthan gum and guar gum: Effect of NaCl, sucrose, and pH</article-title><source>Int. J. Biol. Macromol.</source><year>2018</year><volume>111</volume><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2017.12.144</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29289667</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Bak, J. H. &#x00026; Yoo, B. Intrinsic viscosity of binary gum mixtures with xanthan gum and guar gum: Effect of NaCl, sucrose, and pH. <italic>Int. J. Biol. Macromol.</italic><bold>111</bold>, 77&#x02013;81 (2018).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29289667</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paix&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>MVG</given-names></name><name><surname>de Carvalho Balaban</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Application of guar gum in brine clarification and oily water treatment</article-title><source>Int. J. Biol. Macromol.</source><year>2018</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>119</fpage><lpage>126</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2017.11.166</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29191419</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Paix&#x000e3;o, M. V. G. &#x00026; de Carvalho Balaban, R. Application of guar gum in brine clarification and oily water treatment. <italic>Int. J. Biol. Macromol.</italic><bold>108</bold>, 119&#x02013;126 (2018).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29191419</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Vines</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microneedles: A versatile strategy for transdermal delivery of biological molecules</article-title><source>Int. J. Biol. Macromol.</source><year>2018</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>30</fpage><lpage>38</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2017.12.027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29223756</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Lim, D. J., Vines, J. B., Park, H. &#x00026; Lee, S. H. Microneedles: A versatile strategy for transdermal delivery of biological molecules. <italic>Int. J. Biol. Macromol.</italic><bold>110</bold>, 30&#x02013;38 (2018).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29223756</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fetouh</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ismail</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamid</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bashier</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synthesis of promising nanocomposites from an antitumer and biologically active heterocyclic compound uploaded by clay and chitosan polymers</article-title><source>Int. J. Biol. Macromol.</source><year>2019</year><volume>137</volume><fpage>1211</fpage><lpage>1220</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2019.06.187</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31254576</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Fetouh, H. A., Ismail, A. M., Hamid, H. A. &#x00026; Bashier, M. O. Synthesis of promising nanocomposites from an antitumer and biologically active heterocyclic compound uploaded by clay and chitosan polymers. <italic>Int. J. Biol. Macromol.</italic><bold>137</bold>, 1211&#x02013;1220 (2019).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31254576</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nagel</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Graewert</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Heyse</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeffries</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Svergun</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Berchtold</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The quaternary structure of insulin glargine and glulisine under formulation conditions</article-title><source>Biophys. Chem.</source><year>2019</year><volume>253</volume><fpage>106226</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bpc.2019.106226</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31376619</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Nagel, N. et al. The quaternary structure of insulin glargine and glulisine under formulation conditions. <italic>Biophys. Chem.</italic><bold>253</bold>, 106226 (2019).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31376619</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muniyappa</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gubbi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>COVID-19 pandemic, coronaviruses, and diabetes mellitus</article-title><source>Am. J. Physiol. Endocrinol. Metab.</source><year>2020</year><volume>318</volume><fpage>E736</fpage><lpage>E741</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpendo.00124.2020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32228322</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Muniyappa, R. &#x00026; Gubbi, S. COVID-19 pandemic, coronaviruses, and diabetes mellitus. <italic>Am. J. Physiol. Endocrinol. Metab.</italic><bold>318</bold>, E736&#x02013;E741 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32228322</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Homayun</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Challenges and recent progress in oral drug delivery systems for biopharmaceuticals</article-title><source>Pharmaceutics</source><year>2019</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>129</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/pharmaceutics11030129</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30893852</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Homayun, B., Lin, X. &#x00026; Choi, H. J. Challenges and recent progress in oral drug delivery systems for biopharmaceuticals. <italic>Pharmaceutics</italic><bold>11</bold>, 129 (2019).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30893852</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Messina</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Messina</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhattacharya</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Montgomery</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name><surname>Maynard</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preparation of biomolecule-polymer conjugates by grafting-from using ATRP, RAFT, or ROMP</article-title><source>Prog. Polym. Sci.</source><year>2020</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>101186</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.progpolymsci.2019.101186</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32863465</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Messina, M. S., Messina, K. M., Bhattacharya, A., Montgomery, H. R. &#x00026; Maynard, H. D. Preparation of biomolecule-polymer conjugates by grafting-from using ATRP, RAFT, or ROMP. <italic>Prog. Polym. Sci.</italic><bold>100</bold>, 101186 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32863465</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Messina</surname><given-names>KMM</given-names></name></person-group><source>Polymeric Materials to Improve the Stability and Delivery of Insulin and Glucagon</source><year>2020</year><publisher-loc>Los Angeles</publisher-loc><publisher-name>University of California</publisher-name></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="book">Messina, K. M. M. <italic>Polymeric Materials to Improve the Stability and Delivery of Insulin and Glucagon</italic> (University of California, Los Angeles, 2020).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alfatama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alginate&#x02013;C18 conjugate nanoparticles loaded in tripolyphosphate-cross-linked chitosan&#x02013;oleic acid conjugate-coated calcium alginate beads as oral insulin carrier</article-title><source>Mol. Pharm.</source><year>2018</year><volume>15</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>3369</fpage><lpage>3382</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.molpharmaceut.8b00391</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29996652</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Alfatama, M., Lim, L. Y. &#x00026; Wong, T. W. Alginate&#x02013;C18 conjugate nanoparticles loaded in tripolyphosphate-cross-linked chitosan&#x02013;oleic acid conjugate-coated calcium alginate beads as oral insulin carrier. <italic>Mol. Pharm.</italic><bold>15</bold>(8), 3369&#x02013;3382 (2018).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29996652</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Presas</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>McCartney</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Sultan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunger</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Nellen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name><name><surname>Werner</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Bazile</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Brayden</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Driscoll</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Physicochemical, pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamic analyses of amphiphilic cyclodextrin-based nanoparticles designed to enhance intestinal delivery of insulin</article-title><source>J. Control. Release</source><year>2018</year><volume>286</volume><fpage>402</fpage><lpage>414</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jconrel.2018.07.045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30075208</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Presas, E. et al. Physicochemical, pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamic analyses of amphiphilic cyclodextrin-based nanoparticles designed to enhance intestinal delivery of insulin. <italic>J. Control. Release</italic><bold>286</bold>, 402&#x02013;414 (2018).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30075208</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Salami</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Dass</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microparticles, microcapsules and microspheres: a review of recent developments and prospects for oral delivery of insulin</article-title><source>Int. J. Pharm.</source><year>2018</year><volume>537</volume><issue>1&#x02013;2</issue><fpage>223</fpage><lpage>244</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijpharm.2017.12.036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29288095</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Wong, C. Y., Al-Salami, H. &#x00026; Dass, C. R. Microparticles, microcapsules and microspheres: a review of recent developments and prospects for oral delivery of insulin. <italic>Int. J. Pharm.</italic><bold>537</bold>(1&#x02013;2), 223&#x02013;244 (2018).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29288095</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Back</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enhanced oral delivery of insulin via the colon-targeted nanocomposite system of organoclay/glycol chitosan/Eudragit&#x000ae; S100</article-title><source>J. Nanobiotechnol.</source><year>2020</year><volume>18</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12951-020-00662-x</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Lee, S. H., Back, S. Y., Song, J. G. &#x00026; Han, H. K. Enhanced oral delivery of insulin via the colon-targeted nanocomposite system of organoclay/glycol chitosan/Eudragit&#x000ae; S100. <italic>J. Nanobiotechnol.</italic><bold>18</bold>(1), 1&#x02013;10 (2020).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jamwal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ram</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ranote</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dharela</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Chauhan</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New glucose oxidase-immobilized stimuli-responsive dextran nanoparticles for insulin delivery</article-title><source>Int. J. Biol. Macromolecul.</source><year>2019</year><volume>123</volume><fpage>968</fpage><lpage>978</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2018.11.147</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Jamwal, S., Ram, B., Ranote, S., Dharela, R. &#x00026; Chauhan, G. S. New glucose oxidase-immobilized stimuli-responsive dextran nanoparticles for insulin delivery. <italic>Int. J. Biol. Macromolecul.</italic><bold>123</bold>, 968&#x02013;978 (2019).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patriota</surname><given-names>YBG</given-names></name><name><surname>Arruda</surname><given-names>IES</given-names></name><name><surname>de Jesus Oliveira</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>de Oliveira</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>EDLV</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaves</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>FDOS</given-names></name><name><surname>da Silva</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>MFDLR</given-names></name><name><surname>Soares-Sobrinho</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synthesis of Eudragit&#x000ae; L100-coated chitosan-based nanoparticles for oral enoxaparin delivery</article-title><source>Int. J. Biol. Macromol.</source><year>2021</year><volume>193</volume><fpage>450</fpage><lpage>456</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2021.10.111</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34688680</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Patriota, Y. B. G. et al. Synthesis of Eudragit&#x000ae; L100-coated chitosan-based nanoparticles for oral enoxaparin delivery. <italic>Int. J. Biol. Macromol.</italic><bold>193</bold>, 450&#x02013;456 (2021).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34688680</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Developments in encapsulation of insulin: Is oral delivery now possible?</article-title><source>J. Pharm. Biopharm. Res.</source><year>2019</year><volume>1</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>74</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.25082/JPBR.2019.02.005</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Singh, A. P., Guo, Y., Singh, A., Xie, W. &#x00026; Jiang, P. Developments in encapsulation of insulin: Is oral delivery now possible?. <italic>J. Pharm. Biopharm. Res.</italic><bold>1</bold>(2), 74&#x02013;92 (2019).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Xin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ou</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Hollett</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Poly (ester amide)-based hybrid hydrogels for efficient transdermal insulin delivery</article-title><source>J. Mater. Chem. B</source><year>2018</year><volume>6</volume><issue>42</issue><fpage>6723</fpage><lpage>6730</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C8TB01466C</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32254689</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Zhang, S. et al. Poly (ester amide)-based hybrid hydrogels for efficient transdermal insulin delivery. <italic>J. Mater. Chem. B</italic><bold>6</bold>(42), 6723&#x02013;6730 (2018).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32254689</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hovgaard</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional nanoparticles exploit the bile acid pathway to overcome multiple barriers of the intestinal epithelium for oral insulin delivery</article-title><source>Biomaterials</source><year>2018</year><volume>151</volume><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biomaterials.2017.10.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29055774</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">Fan, W. et al. Functional nanoparticles exploit the bile acid pathway to overcome multiple barriers of the intestinal epithelium for oral insulin delivery. <italic>Biomaterials</italic><bold>151</bold>, 13&#x02013;23 (2018).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29055774</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nezhad-Mokhtari</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghorbani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Roshangar</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Rad</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical gelling of hydrogels-based biological macromolecules for tissue engineering: Photo-and enzymatic-crosslinking methods</article-title><source>Int. J. Biol. Macromol.</source><year>2019</year><volume>139</volume><fpage>760</fpage><lpage>772</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2019.08.047</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31400425</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Nezhad-Mokhtari, P., Ghorbani, M., Roshangar, L. &#x00026; Rad, J. S. Chemical gelling of hydrogels-based biological macromolecules for tissue engineering: Photo-and enzymatic-crosslinking methods. <italic>Int. J. Biol. Macromol.</italic><bold>139</bold>, 760&#x02013;772 (2019).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31400425</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development of gelatin/bacterial cellulose composite sponges as potential natural wound dressings</article-title><source>Int. J. Biol. Macromol.</source><year>2019</year><volume>133</volume><fpage>148</fpage><lpage>155</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2019.04.095</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30991065</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">Ye, S. et al. Development of gelatin/bacterial cellulose composite sponges as potential natural wound dressings. <italic>Int. J. Biol. Macromol.</italic><bold>133</bold>, 148&#x02013;155 (2019).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30991065</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Subroto</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lembong</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Filianty</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Indiarto</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Primalia</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Putri</surname><given-names>MSKZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Theodora</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Junar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The analysis tech-niques of amino acid and protein in food and agricultural products</article-title><source>Int. J. Sci. Technol. Res</source><year>2020</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>36</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Subroto, E. et al. The analysis tech-niques of amino acid and protein in food and agricultural products. <italic>Int. J. Sci. Technol. Res</italic><bold>9</bold>, 29&#x02013;36 (2020).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Rub</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Asiri</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synthesis and characterization of geminis and implications of their micellar solution on ninhydrin and metal amino acid complex</article-title><source>R. Soc. Open Sci.</source><year>2020</year><volume>7</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>200775</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsos.200775</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32874661</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">Kumar, D., Rub, M. A. &#x00026; Asiri, A. M. Synthesis and characterization of geminis and implications of their micellar solution on ninhydrin and metal amino acid complex. <italic>R. Soc. Open Sci.</italic><bold>7</bold>(7), 200775 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32874661</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sallam</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Khairy</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Elnouby</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Fetouh</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sustainable electricity production from seawater using Spirulina platensis microbial fuel cell catalyzed by silver nanoparticles-activated carbon composite prepared by a new modified photolysis method</article-title><source>Biomass Bioenergy</source><year>2021</year><volume>148</volume><fpage>106038</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biombioe.2021.106038</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="journal">Sallam, E. R., Khairy, H. M., Elnouby, M. S. &#x00026; Fetouh, H. A. Sustainable electricity production from seawater using Spirulina platensis microbial fuel cell catalyzed by silver nanoparticles-activated carbon composite prepared by a new modified photolysis method. <italic>Biomass Bioenergy</italic><bold>148</bold>, 106038 (2021).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR26" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robbins</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowsher</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Chance</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Dinesen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Gingerich</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Widemeyer</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Haffner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hales</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Report of the american diabetes association&#x02019;s task force on standardization of the insulin assay</article-title><source>Diabetes</source><year>1996</year><volume>45</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>242</fpage><lpage>256</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/diab.45.2.242</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8549870</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26" publication-type="journal">Robbins, D. C. et al. Report of the american diabetes association&#x02019;s task force on standardization of the insulin assay. <italic>Diabetes</italic><bold>45</bold>(2), 242&#x02013;256 (1996).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8549870</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR27" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sudhakar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandran</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name><surname>Selvamurugan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Nazeer</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biodistribution and pharmacokinetics of thiolated chitosan nanoparticles for oral delivery of insulin in vivo</article-title><source>Int. J. Biol. Macromol.</source><year>2020</year><volume>150</volume><fpage>281</fpage><lpage>288</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2020.02.079</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32057846</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27" publication-type="journal">Sudhakar, S., Chandran, S. V., Selvamurugan, N. &#x00026; Nazeer, R. A. Biodistribution and pharmacokinetics of thiolated chitosan nanoparticles for oral delivery of insulin in vivo. <italic>Int. J. Biol. Macromol.</italic><bold>150</bold>, 281&#x02013;288 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32057846</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR28" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mallakpour</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatami</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fabrication and characterization of pH-sensitive bio-nanocomposite beads havening folic acid intercalated LDH and chitosan: Drug release and mechanism evaluation</article-title><source>Int. J. Biol. Macromol.</source><year>2019</year><volume>122</volume><fpage>157</fpage><lpage>167</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2018.10.166</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30393134</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28" publication-type="journal">Mallakpour, S. &#x00026; Hatami, M. Fabrication and characterization of pH-sensitive bio-nanocomposite beads havening folic acid intercalated LDH and chitosan: Drug release and mechanism evaluation. <italic>Int. J. Biol. Macromol.</italic><bold>122</bold>, 157&#x02013;167 (2019).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30393134</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR29" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fetouh</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hefnawy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Attia</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Facile and low-cost green synthesis of eco-friendly chitosan-silver nanocomposite as novel and promising corrosion inhibitor for mild steel in chilled water circuits</article-title><source>J. Mol. Liquids</source><year>2020</year><volume>319</volume><fpage>114355</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molliq.2020.114355</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29" publication-type="journal">Fetouh, H. A., Hefnawy, A., Attia, A. M. &#x00026; Ali, E. Facile and low-cost green synthesis of eco-friendly chitosan-silver nanocomposite as novel and promising corrosion inhibitor for mild steel in chilled water circuits. <italic>J. Mol. Liquids</italic><bold>319</bold>, 114355 (2020).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR30" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mailoud</surname><given-names>OM</given-names></name><name><surname>Elsayed</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>El Fetouh</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>ELazm</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synthesis and characterization of paramagnetic isotropic glycine manganese chloride single crystal with various dopant concentrations</article-title><source>Res. Phys.</source><year>2019</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>925</fpage><lpage>933</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30" publication-type="journal">Mailoud, O. M., Elsayed, A. H., El Fetouh, H. A. &#x00026; ELazm, A. A. Synthesis and characterization of paramagnetic isotropic glycine manganese chloride single crystal with various dopant concentrations. <italic>Res. Phys.</italic><bold>12</bold>, 925&#x02013;933 (2019).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR31" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mailoud</surname><given-names>OM</given-names></name><name><surname>Elsayed</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Abo-Elazm</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Fetouh</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synthesis and study the structure, optical, thermal and dielectric properties of promising glycine copper nitrate (GCN) single crystals</article-title><source>Res. Phys.</source><year>2018</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>512</fpage><lpage>520</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR31" publication-type="journal">Mailoud, O. M., Elsayed, A. H., Abo-Elazm, A. H. &#x00026; Fetouh, H. A. Synthesis and study the structure, optical, thermal and dielectric properties of promising glycine copper nitrate (GCN) single crystals. <italic>Res. Phys.</italic><bold>10</bold>, 512&#x02013;520 (2018).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR32" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sallam</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Fetouh</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative study for the production of sustainable electricity from marine sediment using recyclable low-cost solid wastes aluminum foil and graphite anodes</article-title><source>ChemistrySelect</source><year>2022</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>e202103972</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/slct.202103972</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32" publication-type="journal">Sallam, E. R. &#x00026; Fetouh, H. A. Comparative study for the production of sustainable electricity from marine sediment using recyclable low-cost solid wastes aluminum foil and graphite anodes. <italic>ChemistrySelect</italic><bold>7</bold>, e202103972 (2022).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR33" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taha</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaban</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fetouh</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Taha</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name><surname>Sabet</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synthesis and evaluation of nonionic surfactants based on dimethylaminoethylamine: Electrochemical investigation and theoretical modeling as inhibitors during electropolishing in-ortho-phosphoric acid</article-title><source>J. Mol. Liquids</source><year>2021</year><volume>328</volume><fpage>115421</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molliq.2021.115421</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR33" publication-type="journal">Taha, A. A. et al. Synthesis and evaluation of nonionic surfactants based on dimethylaminoethylamine: Electrochemical investigation and theoretical modeling as inhibitors during electropolishing in-ortho-phosphoric acid. <italic>J. Mol. Liquids</italic><bold>328</bold>, 115421 (2021).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR34" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tapdigov</surname><given-names>SZ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The bonding nature of the chemical interaction between trypsin and chitosan based carriers in immobilization process depend on entrapped method: A review</article-title><source>Int. J. Biol. Macromol.</source><year>2021</year><volume>183</volume><fpage>1676</fpage><lpage>1696</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2021.05.059</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34015409</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR34" publication-type="journal">Tapdigov, S. Z. The bonding nature of the chemical interaction between trypsin and chitosan based carriers in immobilization process depend on entrapped method: A review. <italic>Int. J. Biol. Macromol.</italic><bold>183</bold>, 1676&#x02013;1696 (2021).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34015409</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR35" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shinya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukamizo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interaction between chitosan and its related enzymes: A review</article-title><source>Int. J. Biol. Macromol.</source><year>2017</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>1422</fpage><lpage>1435</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2017.02.040</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28223213</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR35" publication-type="journal">Shinya, S. &#x00026; Fukamizo, T. Interaction between chitosan and its related enzymes: A review. <italic>Int. J. Biol. Macromol.</italic><bold>104</bold>, 1422&#x02013;1435 (2017).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28223213</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR36" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elbatouti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fetouh</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Extraction of eco-friendly and biodegradable surfactant for inhibition of copper corrosion during acid pickling</article-title><source>Adsorpt. Sci. Technol.</source><year>2019</year><volume>37</volume><issue>7&#x02013;8</issue><fpage>649</fpage><lpage>663</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0263617419865130</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR36" publication-type="journal">Elbatouti, M. &#x00026; Fetouh, H. A. Extraction of eco-friendly and biodegradable surfactant for inhibition of copper corrosion during acid pickling. <italic>Adsorpt. Sci. Technol.</italic><bold>37</bold>(7&#x02013;8), 649&#x02013;663 (2019).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article>