<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Microbiol Biotechnol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Microbiol Biotechnol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Microbiology and Biotechnology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1017-7825</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1738-8872</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Korean Society for Microbiology and Biotechnology</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40374542</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12099637</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4014/jmb.2501.01046</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">jmb-35-e2501046</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research article</subject><subj-group><subject>Biotechnology and Bioengineering (BB)</subject><subj-group><subject>Microbial Genetics, Physiology, and Metabolism</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Non-Catalytic Domains of Glycoside Hydrolase Family 5 from <italic toggle="yes">Paenibacillus curdlanolyticus</italic> are Important for Promoting Multifunctional Enzyme Activities and Degradation of Agricultural Residues</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fatmawati</surname><given-names>Niendy Virnanda</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Singkhala</surname><given-names>Apinya</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ketbot</surname><given-names>Prattana</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Baramee</surname><given-names>Sirilak</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Waeonukul</surname><given-names>Rattiya</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tachaapaikoon</surname><given-names>Chakrit</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Uke</surname><given-names>Ayaka</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kosugi</surname><given-names>Akihiko</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ratanakhanokchai</surname><given-names>Khanok</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Pason</surname><given-names>Patthra</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Division of Biochemical Technology, School of Bioresources and Technology, King Mongkut's University of Technology Thonburi, Bangkok 10150, <country>Thailand</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Excellent Center of Enzyme Technology and Microbial Utilization, Pilot Plant Development and Training Institute, King Mongkut's University of Technology Thonburi, Bangkok 10150, <country>Thailand</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Biological Resources and Post-harvest Division, Japan International Research Center for Agricultural Sciences, Tsukuba, Ibaraki 305-8686, <country>Japan</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">
<label>*</label>Corresponding author E-mail: <email xlink:href="patthra.pas@kmutt.ac.th">patthra.pas@kmutt.ac.th</email>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>15</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><!--PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>.--><volume>35</volume><elocation-id>e2501046</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>31</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>13</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2025 by the authors. Licensee KMB</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is an open access article distributed under the terms and conditions of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution (CC BY) license</ext-link></license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 from <italic toggle="yes">Paenibacillus curdlanolyticus</italic> strain B-6 is a modular protein consisting of a catalytic domain of glycoside hydrolase family 5 (GH5), and three non-catalytic domains (a family 11 carbohydrate-binding module (CBM11), a fibronectin type 3 (Fn3), and a family 3 carbohydrate-binding module (CBM3). In this study, the recombinants full-length <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 and the catalytic domain (<italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD) were expressed in <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> and purified. Most GH5 members exhibit endo-cellulase activity. However, the catalytic domain enzyme of strain B-6 exhibited unique properties, showing multifunctional enzyme activities of endo-cellulase, endo-xylanase, endo-mannanase, and endo-1,3-1,4-&#x003b2;-glucanase. The sequence alignment of <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD compared to other characterized GH5 enzymes suggests that the two catalytic residues and the six substrate-binding subsites of endo-cellulases were conserved with other different GH5 enzyme properties. Whereas a few conserved amino acid residues and/or short peptides located outside the active site of the GH5 endo-cellulases may be involved in broad substrate specificity of <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD enzyme on xylan, mannan and 1,3-1,4-&#x003b2;-glucan. Moreover, the non-catalytic domains (CBM11-Fn3-CBM3) linked to the GH5 catalytic domain are important for promoting the multifunctional enzyme activities of <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 on the &#x003b2;-1,4 glycosidic linkages of crystalline cellulose, highly branched polysaccharides, and &#x003b2;-1,4-1,6 and &#x003b2;-1,3-1,4 glycosidic linkages of polysaccharides, especially for the polysaccharides complex contained in agricultural residues. The full-length <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 is effective in producing oligosaccharides from agricultural residues without pretreatment. Therefore, it is interesting to use it as a source of prebiotics producer for use in various food products.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Agricultural residue</kwd><kwd>glycoside hydrolase family 5</kwd><kwd>multifunctional enzyme</kwd><kwd>non-catalytic domain</kwd><kwd>oligosaccharide</kwd><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Paenibacillus curdlanolyticus</italic></kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Agricultural residues are attractive raw materials because they are non-edible plant components, abundant, low cost and considered suitable feedstocks for producing value-added compounds. They consist of three main components: cellulose, hemicellulose and lignin. Cellulose and hemicellulose are major components of agricultural residues due to their potential as raw materials for the production of oligosaccharides [<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Cellulose is the most abundant carbon source in nature, accounting for approximately 35%&#x02013;50% of a plant&#x02019;s dry weight, where cellulolytic enzymes are important for hydrolysing cellulose [<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Hemicellulose constitutes approximately 25%&#x02013;35% of plant dry weight and represents the second most abundant renewable biomass in nature [<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Xylan and mannan are the two hemicelluloses most commonly found in agricultural residues. The main enzymes in the degradation of these two hemicelluloses are xylanolytic and mannanolytic enzymes, respectively [<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>].</p><p>Among cellulolytic and hemicellulolyic enzymes, endo-cellulases and endo-hemicellulases, which randomly hydrolyse the &#x003b2;-1,4 glycosidic linkages of cellulose and hemicelluloses to generate oligosaccharides, are the most efficient enzymes for degrading polysaccharides present in agricultural residues [<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Among these, cello-oligosaccharides, manno-oligosaccharides and xylo-oligosaccharides can be used for a variety of purposes, especially as prebiotics in food products [<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Alternatively, &#x003b2;-1,3-1,4-glucan is abundant in cereal grains, while endo-&#x003b2;-1,3-1,4-glucanases are vital for hydrolysing glucan into gluco-oligosaccharides, which can be used as prebiotics [<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].</p><p>In general, the production of oligosaccharides from polysaccharides contained in agricultural residues by enzymatic hydrolysis requires pretreatment processes to reduce the complexity of plant biomass structure. However, pretreatment, for example, chemical pretreatment, is one of the most expensive steps in sugar production from agricultural residues, which increases the cost of sugar production and water treatment processes. Furthermore, the formation of aromatic aldehydes during chemical pretreatment prevents sugar formation by inhibiting enzyme activities [<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Therefore, producing oligosaccharides from agricultural residues without chemical pretreatment using environmentally friendly enzymes is desirable.</p><p>Based on sequence homologies, 189 families of glycoside hydrolases (GHs) have been identified from a variety of microorganisms (<ext-link xlink:href="http://www.cazy.org/Glycoside-Hydrolases.html" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.cazy.org/Glycoside-Hydrolases.html</ext-link>). However, only a few of these GH families, such as a group of family 5 GHs, are representative of multifunctional enzymes [<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Multifunctional enzymes, which are single protein products comprising several glycoside hydrolase activities, tend to be less complex and less expensive to manufacture compared to combinations of several different GH enzymes in terms of enzyme purification and enzyme loading [<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Therefore, it would be interesting to study the multifunctional enzymes of the GH5 family.</p><p>The GH5 is one of the largest families of glycoside hydrolases, most of which are endo-cellulases, while other enzymes in this family are monofunctional enzymes (<italic toggle="yes">e.g.</italic> endo-mannanase, endo-xylanase, endo-&#x003b2;-1,3-1,4-glucanase, &#x003b2;-mannosidase, &#x003b2;-glucosidase, &#x003b2;-xylosidase); bifunctional enzymes (<italic toggle="yes">e.g.</italic> endo-cellulase/endo-mannanase, endo-cellulase/endo-xylanase, endo-cellulase/endo-&#x003b2;-glucanase); and multifunctional enzymes (<italic toggle="yes">e.g.</italic> endo-cellulase/endo-mannanase/endo-xylanase, endo-cellulase/endo-mannanase/endo-&#x003b2;-glucanase) (<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.cazy.org/GH5_characterized.html#pagination_FUNC" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cazy.org/GH5_characterized.html#pagination_FUNC</ext-link>). Based on the similarity of amino acid sequence and biochemical characteristics, GH5 enzymes are currently divided into 55 subfamilies.</p><p>Many GH families consist of catalytic and ancillary non-catalytic modules, such as the carbohydrate-binding modules (CBMs) and the fibronectin type-3 homology (Fn3) module [<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. CBMs are classified into many families based on amino acid sequence similarities and functions. Generally, the function of CBMs is to support the enzymatic activity of the catalytic domain by promoting close contact between the substrate and the enzyme and supporting the catalytic module for easy digestion of the substrate [<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Whereas Fn3 acts to modify the cellulose surface to increase the catalytic activity of cellulase against insoluble cellulose [<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>].</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Paenibacillus curdlanolyticus</italic> strain B-6, a cellulolytic/xylanolytic/mannanolytic bacterium, has great potential in agricultural residue degradation [<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. We found one open reading frame carrying the <italic toggle="yes">pcgh5</italic> gene encoding a modular protein, including a catalytic domain belonging to GH5, and three non-catalytic modules; a family 11 carbohydrate-binding module (CBM11), a domain of fibronectin type 3 (Fn3) and a family 3 carbohydrate-binding module (CBM3). Compared with other characterized GH5 members, the GH5 catalytic domain of strain B-6 showed a low percent identity (38.0%&#x02013;60.8%). Moreover, there are numerous non-catalytic modules associated with the GH5 catalytic domain of strain B-6. Thus, we expect to find new enzymatic properties of the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 enzyme, while the three non-catalytic modules of <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 may play some role in <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 enzymatic activity.</p><p>In this study, <italic toggle="yes">pcgh5</italic> (GH5 catalytic domain linked with three non-catalytic domains) and <italic toggle="yes">pcgh5_CD</italic> (only GH5 catalytic domain) genes from <italic toggle="yes">P. curdlanolyticus</italic> strain B-6 were expressed in <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic>, and the recombinant proteins were purified and characterized. Thereafter, the properties of <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 and the functional role of the non-catalytic domains in <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 were examined.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Chemicals</title><p>Carboxymethyl cellulose (CMC) (400&#x02013;800 cps), Avicel (PH-101), glucose, cellobiose, birchwood xylan (BWX), oat spelt xylan (OSX), locust bean gum (LBG), barley &#x003b2;-glucan, rice starch, pectin and bovine serum albumin were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich (USA). Konjac glucomannan (KGM), cello-oligosaccharides (G2&#x02013;G6), xylo-oligosaccharides (X2&#x02013;X6) and manno-oligosaccharides (M2&#x02013;M6) were purchased from Megazyme (Ireland). Mannose and xylose were purchased from Merck (KGaA, Germany). Other chemicals and reagents were of analytical grade.</p></sec><sec><title>Organisms, Media and Growth Conditions</title><p>Chromosomal DNA was obtained from <italic toggle="yes">P. curdlanolyticus</italic> B-6, growing on Berg&#x02019;s mineral salt medium at pH 7.0 [<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Plasmid pET-28a(+) (Novagen, Germany), <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> DH5&#x003b1; and <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> BL21 (DE3) (New England Biolabs, USA) were used as the vector, cloning host and expression host, respectively. Luria-Bertani (LB) medium with an antibiotic (50 &#x003bc;g/ml kanamycin) was used to cultivate <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> at 37&#x000b0;C to select <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> transformants.</p></sec><sec><title>Gene Cloning</title><p><italic toggle="yes">P. curdlanolyticus</italic> B-6 was deposited in the BIOTEC Culture Collection of the National Center for Genetic Engineering and Biotechnology (BIOTEC), Thailand, under accession number BCC no. 11175. The chromosomal DNA of <italic toggle="yes">P. curdlanolyticus</italic> B-6 was extracted using phenol and chloroform. Oligonucleotide primers were constructed from the putative GH5 enzyme found in the partial genomic DNA sequence of the B-6 strain to clone the modular protein consisting of a catalytic domain of GH5 and three non-catalytic domains (<italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5), and its truncated protein contained only the catalytic GH5 domain (<italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD). The primer containing <italic toggle="yes">Bam</italic>H1-HF and <italic toggle="yes">Not</italic>1-HF recognition sites (5'-GGGGG<bold>GGATCC</bold>GCTGAAGCTGTCGACTTAGAAAATCTG-3' was used for the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 and <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD-forward primer, while 5'-TTTTT<bold>GCGGCCGC</bold>TTATGAAGGCTCTACGCCCC-3' for <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5-reverse primer, and 5'-TTTTT<bold>GCGGCCGC</bold>TTATGAAGGCTCTACGCCCC-3' for <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD-reverse primer (<italic toggle="yes">Bam</italic>H1-HF and <italic toggle="yes">Not</italic>1-HF recognition sites are in bold) were used to amplify <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 and <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD fragments by PCR using B-6 strain genomic DNA as a template. Following the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions, PCR was carried out using Ex Taq DNA polymerases (New England Biolabs Ltd., UK). The DNA fragment was subjected to digestion using <italic toggle="yes">Bam</italic>H1-HF and <italic toggle="yes">Not</italic>1-HF (New England Biolabs, Ltd.), followed by an agarose gel run and extraction using a Qiagen, USA, Polymerase Chain Reaction (PCR) kit. After that, each resultant product was ligated between the pET28a vector&#x02019;s <italic toggle="yes">Bam</italic>H1-HF and <italic toggle="yes">Not</italic>1-HF sites to create the pET28a<italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 and pET28a<italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD plasmids. After ligating the resultant products to create recombinant plasmids, the ligated combinations were transformed into <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> DH5&#x003b1;. Positive clones were verified by using DNA sequencing and colony PCR.</p></sec><sec><title>Sequence Alignment</title><p>The protein sequence of <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD was submitted to the NCBI database, which immediately collected the high-similarity proteins for further characterization (<ext-link xlink:href="https://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Blast.cgi" ext-link-type="uri">https://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Blast.cgi</ext-link>). Moreover, these protein sequences were evaluated using the Clustal Omega multiple sequence alignment (<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.ebi.ac.uk/jdispatcher/msa/clustalo" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ebi.ac.uk/jdispatcher/msa/clustalo</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec><title>Subfamily of <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD Enzyme</title><p>The amino acid sequence of the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD enzyme was analysed to identify its subfamily classification. BLAST analysis was performed using the NCBI protein database [<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] to identify homologous sequences, prioritizing well-characterized GH5 enzymes. Multiple sequence alignment was conducted using the MUSCLE algorithm in MEGA11 software [<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], with ClustalW on the EMBL-EBI server (<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/msa/clustalw2/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/msa/clustalw2/</ext-link>) used in parallel to verify the robustness of the alignment and ensure consistent tree topology. The phylogenetic tree was constructed using the maximum likelihood method with 2,000 bootstrap replicates to enhance statistical robustness. To refine subfamily classification, additional BLAST searches were performed against the CAZy database [<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] to assess sequence identity with known GH5 subfamilies. The subfamily classification was inferred based on phylogenetic clustering with well-characterized GH5 enzymes. The resulting tree topology was examined for congruence with established GH5 subfamily relationships [<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], providing insights into the evolutionary placement of <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD enzyme within the glycoside hydrolase superfamily.</p></sec><sec><title>Three-Dimensional Structure of <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD Enzyme</title><p>Three-dimensional structure (3D structure) of <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD enzyme was performed using structural modeling analysis. Homologous proteins were first identified by searching the Protein Data Bank (PDB) database (<ext-link xlink:href="http://www.rcsb.org/pdb/home/home.do" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.rcsb.org/pdb/home/home.do</ext-link>). The crystal structure (PDB ID: 4U3A) of bifunctional endo-cellulase/endo-xylanase <italic toggle="yes">Ct</italic>Cel5E from <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium thermocellum</italic> ATCC 27405 [<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], which showed high sequence identity with the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD catalytic domain (48.43%), was selected as the reference protein. The 3D structure of the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD enzyme was built based on the 4U3A protein model by the SWISS-MODEL (<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.swissmodel.expasy.org" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.swissmodel.expasy.org</ext-link>), generating a catalytic domain model. Ligands relevant to <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD enzyme, xylotetraose (X4), mannotetraose (M4), and 1,3-1,4-&#x003b2;-glucotetraose (G4) for endo-xylanase, endo-mannanase, and endo-1,3-1,4-&#x003b2;-glucanase, respectively, which interact with the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD at subsites &#x02212;2 to +2 were obtained from PubChem (<ext-link xlink:href="https://pubchem.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/" ext-link-type="uri">https://pubchem.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/</ext-link>) and used for molecular docking analysis with PyRx software to predict binding interactions [<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Structural visualization and analysis were performed using PyMOL (<ext-link xlink:href="https://pymol.org/" ext-link-type="uri">https://pymol.org/</ext-link>), focusing on catalytic and binding sites, domain organization, and surface-exposed residues. Distance measurements between interacting residues and ligands were determined in angstroms (&#x000c5;) using PyMOL to evaluate binding interactions and substrate specificity [<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Structural modeling studies were performed to infer potential enzymes, namely, endo-xylanase, endo-mannanase, and endo-1,3-1,4-&#x003b2;-glucanase activities, based on ligands interactions with key residues within the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD subsite.</p></sec><sec><title>Expression and Purification of Recombinants <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD and <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5</title><p>The DNA fragments pET28a_<italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 and pET28a_<italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD were transformed into <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> BL21 (DE3). Subsequently, for expression, the transformants were grown in LB medium supplemented with kanamycin (50 &#x003bc;g/ml). The cultures were incubated at 200 rpm and 37&#x000b0;C until their OD<sub>600</sub> reached 0.6. Isopropyl &#x003b2;-D-1-thiogalactopyranoside was added to the cultures at a final concentration of 1 mM to promote protein production, and they were then incubated at 16&#x000b0;C for an additional 18 h. After incubations, the cells were harvested, washed, and sonicated and the cells debris were eliminated by centrifugation at 8,000 rpm for 30 min at 4&#x000b0;C. Cell extracts were purified using an affinity chromatography HisTrap HP column (GE Healthcare, Japan), which immediately estimated the purity of protein recombinants by sodium dodecyl sulphate-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (SDS-PAGE) [<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Protein Determination and Enzyme Assays of <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD and <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5</title><p>The protein concentration was ascertained using the Bradford method [<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], with bovine serum albumin as the standard. Reaction mixtures for enzyme assays consisted of the purified enzyme (1 &#x003bc;M) and 1% (w/v) of each substrate in 50 mM sodium acetate buffer (pH 6.0) at 50&#x000b0;C, which are the optimum conditions of the GH5 enzyme for hydrolysis of the substrates. The amount of reducing sugars released from each substrate (CMC, Avicel (PH-101), BWX, OSX, KGM, LBG, barley &#x003b2;-glucan, starch and pectin) was measured using the Somogyi-Nelson method [<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. The amount of enzyme that released one &#x003bc;mol of reducing sugar per minute under assay conditions was defined as one unit (U) of enzyme activity. For cellobiose, xylobiose or mannobiose, the hydrolysis product was analysed by high-performance liquid chromatography (HPLC) with a RID10A reflective index detector (Shimadzu RID-10A, Japan). The sample was separated on the BP-200 Ag carbohydrate column (Benson polymeric, USA) with a mobile phase of water (HPLC Grade, Fisher Scientific, UK) at 85&#x000b0;C and a flow rate of 0.3 ml/min.</p></sec><sec><title>Degradation Product Analysis</title><p>Enzyme activities of <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD and <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 on 1% (w/v) CMC, Avicel, BWX, OSX, KGM, LBG and barley &#x003b2;-glucan were performed using 500 &#x003bc;l of reaction mixture in sodium acetate buffer (pH 6.0) containing purified <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 enzyme (1 &#x003bc;M) at 50&#x000b0;C for 30 min. Analysis of the hydrolysis products released from the polysaccharides was performed by thin-layer chromatography (TLC) on silica gel (60 F245) plates (Merck, Germany) with a mixture of acetic acid, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>-butanol and water (1:2:1) as the solvent system. The sugar spots were detected by heating the plate at 100&#x000b0;C after spraying with a reagent consisting of 4 g of a-diphenylamine, 4 ml of aniline, 200 ml of acetone and 30 ml of 80% (v/v) phosphoric acid [<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Preparation and Saccharification of Agricultural Residues</title><p>Sugarcane bagasse was obtained from Suphanburi province, Thailand, whereas coconut meal (a by-product of coconut milk production) was obtained from a coconut milk shop at a fresh market in Nonthaburi province, Thailand). The agricultural residues were finely chopped with scissors, ground in a blender, and finally sieved through a 45-mesh screen (Endecotts Ltd., England). After washing several times with warm distilled water to remove impurities, the samples were oven-dried at 50&#x000b0;C until a constant weight and stored for later use.</p><p>The agricultural residues (1%, w/v), sugarcane bagasse and coconut meal were hydrolysed with 5 &#x003bc;M purified <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 enzyme in sodium acetate buffer (pH 6.0) at 50&#x000b0;C for 30 min, 1 h and 5 h. Analysis of the hydrolysis products released from the agricultural residues was performed by TLC.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results|discussion"><title>Results and Discussion</title><sec><title>Modular Structure of <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5</title><p>Based on the partial genome analysis of <italic toggle="yes">P. curdlanolyticus</italic> B-6, we identified the <italic toggle="yes">pcgh5</italic> gene, which consisted of 2,268 nucleotides and encoded the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 protein comprising 756 amino acid residues with a predicted molecular mass of 85,176.94 Da (<ext-link xlink:href="https://web.expasy.org/cgi-bin/compute_pi/pi_tool" ext-link-type="uri">https://web.expasy.org/cgi-bin/compute_pi/pi_tool</ext-link>). A homology search using the NCBI database (<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/</ext-link>) demonstrated that <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 was a modular protein, consisting of a family GH5 catalytic domain and three non-catalytic domains: a CBM11, an Fn3 and a CBM3 sequentially from the <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-terminus, extending from positions 62 to 311, 361 to 523, 536 to 600 and 619 to 701, respectively (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1A</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>GH5 Catalytic Domain from <italic toggle="yes">P. curdlanolyticus</italic> Strain B-6</title><p>The identified GH5 catalytic domain of strain B-6, designated as <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1B</xref>) (GenBank ID: GFN32992.1), showed low identity (38.0%&#x02013;60.8%) compared with other characterized GH5 members. According to the CAZy database (<ext-link xlink:href="http://www.cazy.org/GH5.html" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.cazy.org/GH5.html</ext-link>), GH5 is one of the largest families of glycoside hydrolases, with 34,569 members reported in the GenBank database. However, only 638 members have been characterized, which are mainly endo-cellulases (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). Analysis of the identity of the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD enzyme (GH5 catalytic domain only) to other characterized GH5 enzymes with different properties in the GH5 family whose 3D structures have been elucidated indicates that the highest sequence identity was between the bifunctional endo-cellulase/endo-xylanase from <italic toggle="yes">C. thermocellum</italic> (48.43%) [<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], endo-cellulase from <italic toggle="yes">Thermoascus aurantiacus</italic> (40.00%) [<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] and bifunctional endo-cellulase/endo-mannanase from <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus agaradhaerens</italic> (38.68%) [<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Non-Catalytic Domains of <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 Enzyme from <italic toggle="yes">P. curdlanolyticus</italic> Strain B-6</title><p>The three non-catalytic domains (CBM11, CBM3 and Fn3) within the modular <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 protein from <italic toggle="yes">P. curdlanolyticus</italic> strain B-6 were examined. BlastP analysis of CBM11 in the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 enzyme from strain B-6 with other characterized CBM11 members revealed sequence identities ranging from 25% to 47%. Among the characterized CBM11 proteins, the highest sequence similarity was observed with CBM11 from <italic toggle="yes">Acetivibrio straminisolvens</italic> (47.02%), followed by <italic toggle="yes">C. thermocellum</italic> AFN85452.1 (46.71%), <italic toggle="yes">Acetivibrio thermocellus</italic> (46.71%), <italic toggle="yes">A. thermocellus</italic> ATCC 27405 (46.47%) and <italic toggle="yes">C. thermocellum</italic> AFN85449.1 (46.2%).</p><p>BlastP analysis of the Fn3 non-catalytic domain in <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 from <italic toggle="yes">P. curdlanolyticus</italic> strain B-6 revealed sequence identities ranging from 48% to 50% with other characterized Fn3 members. The highest sequence similarities were found with the Fn3 domain from <italic toggle="yes">Paenibacillus</italic> sp. BIHB 4019 (50.00%), followed by <italic toggle="yes">Paenibacillus</italic> sp.(49.62%), <italic toggle="yes">Paenibacillus xylanivorans</italic> (49.62%), <italic toggle="yes">Paenibacillus</italic> sp. LS1 (48.85%) and <italic toggle="yes">Paenibacillus</italic> sp. FSL H8-0079 (48.85%).</p><p>According to the CAZy database (<ext-link xlink:href="http://www.cazy.org/CBM3.html" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.cazy.org/CBM3.html</ext-link>), only 22 proteins of characterized CBM3 modules have been reported. Using BlastP analysis, the CBM3 domain of <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 exhibited sequence identities between 46% and 60% compared to other characterized CBM3 members. The highest sequence similarity was observed with CBM3 from <italic toggle="yes">Paenibacillus xylaniclasticus</italic> (59.77%), followed by <italic toggle="yes">Paenibacillus xylanexedens</italic> (56.32%), <italic toggle="yes">Paenibacillus terricola</italic> (54.65%), <italic toggle="yes">Paenibacillus cellulosilyticus</italic> (53.49%) and <italic toggle="yes">Paenibacillus</italic> sp. CCS19 (51.14%).</p></sec><sec><title>Subfamily of <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD Enzyme</title><p>The phylogenetic tree of <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD enzyme with other characterized GH5 members with high sequence identity (35.09&#x02013;50.00%) was constructed by using the MUSCLE algorithm in MEGA11 software [<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], with ClustalW on the EMBL-EBI server (<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/msa/clustalw2/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/msa/clustalw2/</ext-link>) used in parallel to verify the robustness of the alignment and ensure consistent tree topology. As shown in <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD was individually separated from other GH5 members, including nine members of a bifunctional endo-cellulase/endo-xylanase from <italic toggle="yes">C. thermocellum</italic> (GenBank Accession No. 4U3A_1) (unknown subfamily), an endo-&#x003b2;-1,3-1,4-glucanase from <italic toggle="yes">Paenibacillus polymyxa</italic> (GenBank Accession No. QBY21421.1) (unknown subfamily), a bifunctional endo-cellulase/endo-mannanase from <italic toggle="yes">B. agaradhaerens</italic> (GenBank Accession No. 2WHL_1) (unknown subfamily), a multifunctional endo-cellulase/endo-mannanase/endo-&#x003b2;-1,3-1,4-glucanase from <italic toggle="yes">Caldanaerobius polysaccharolyticus</italic> (GenBank Accession No. AAD09354.1) (unknown subfamily), an endo-&#x003b2;-1,3-1,4-glucanase from <italic toggle="yes">Caldicellulosiruptor</italic> sp. F32 (GenBank Accession No. AGM71677.1) (subfamily 4), a bifunctional endo-cellulase/endo-mannanase from <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium cellulovorans</italic> (GenBank Accession No. AAD39739.1) (subfamily 4), a bifunctional endo-cellulase/endo-xylanase from <italic toggle="yes">Cellulosilyticum ruminicola</italic> (GenBank Accession No. ACZ98591.1) (subfamily 4), a bifunctional endo-cellulase/endo-xylanase from <italic toggle="yes">Xylanibacter ruminicola</italic> (GenBank Accession No. AAC36862.1)(subfamily 4), and an endo-cellulase from <italic toggle="yes">T. aurantiacus</italic> (GenBank Accession No. AAL88714.2) (subfamily 5). Although <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD is closely related to subfamilies 4 and 5, it cannot be placed in any of the known GH5 subfamilies and is therefore grouped with an unclassified enzyme. In 2012, Aspeborg <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. [<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] classified GH5 enzymes into 51 subfamilies, while in 2022, Martins <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. [<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] classified GH5 enzymes into 55 subfamilies, meaning that there are still many GH5 enzymes that need to be classified. Thus, phylogenetic analysis suggests that <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 may belong to an unidentified GH5 subfamily, which requires further studies to identify functional and evolutionary relationships within the GH5 family.</p></sec><sec><title>Catalytic Site of <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD Enzyme</title><p>The three-dimensional structures of some GH5 enzymes have been reported. To identify the conserved regions and consensus amino acids, the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD sequence was subjected to multiple sequence alignments with other characterized GH5 enzyme properties using ClustalW on the EMBL-EBI server (<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/msa/clustalw2/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/msa/clustalw2/</ext-link>). Although, GH5 members having different enzyme activities and substrate preferences, such as endo-cellulase from <italic toggle="yes">T. aurantiacus</italic> [<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], bifunctional endo-cellulase/endo-xylanase from <italic toggle="yes">C. thermocellum</italic> [<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], bifunctional endo-cellulase/endo-mannanase from <italic toggle="yes">B. agaradhaerens</italic> [<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], multifunctional endo-cellulase/endo-mannanase/endo-&#x003b2;-glucanase from <italic toggle="yes">C. polysaccharolyticus</italic> [<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] and endo-&#x003b2;-1,3-1,4-glucanase from <italic toggle="yes">P. polymyxa</italic> KF-1 [<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], two catalytic residues of endo-cellulase from <italic toggle="yes">T. aurantiacus</italic>, Glu132 (acid/base) and Glu239 (nucleophile) [<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], were conserved in all types of characterized GH5 members, including <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Substrate-Binding Subsites of <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD Enzyme</title><p>Most GH5 members exhibit endo-cellulase activity (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). As shown in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, the conserved 15 amino acid residues of the Cel5A endo-cellulase from <italic toggle="yes">T. aurantiacus</italic> [<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], which are located in the six substrate-binding subsites within the active site, Trp30 at subsite &#x02212;3; Glu132, His197, Tyr199 and Trp272 at subsite &#x02212;2; His91, Asn130, Glu132, His197, Tyr199 and Trp272 at subsite &#x02212;1; Trp169 at subsite +1; Trp169 and Tyr199 at subsite +2 and Tyr199 at subsite +3, were also conserved in almost all other GH5 enzyme properties, such as bifunctional endo-cellulase/endo-xylanase from <italic toggle="yes">C. thermocellum</italic> [<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], bifunctional endo-cellulase/endo-mannanase from <italic toggle="yes">B. agaradhaerens</italic> [<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], multifunctional endo-cellulase/endo-mannanase/endo-&#x003b2;-glucanase from <italic toggle="yes">C. polysaccharolyticus</italic> [<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] and endo-&#x003b2;-1,3-1,4-glucanase from <italic toggle="yes">P. polymyxa</italic> KF-1 [<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], as well as the GH5 catalytic domain from <italic toggle="yes">P. curdlanolyticus</italic> strain B-6.</p><p>Yuan, <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. [<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] reported that conserved amino acid residues within the substrate-binding subsites of bifunctional endo-cellulase/endo-xylanase <italic toggle="yes">Ct</italic>Cel5E from <italic toggle="yes">C. thermocellum</italic>, namely His168, Asn208, Glu209, Tyr270 and Trp347 at subsite &#x02212;1 and Trp347 at subsite &#x02212;2, were important for not only cellulase but also xylanase activity. Moreover, compared with the endo-cellulase Cel5A from <italic toggle="yes">T. aurantiacus</italic>, some amino acid residues that are located outside but close to the active site of the GH5 endo-cellulases, such as Trp103 (subsite &#x02212;2) and His169 (subsite &#x02212;1) (see binding subsites of endo-cellulase Cel5A from <italic toggle="yes">T. aurantiacus</italic> in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>), which are critical for the endo-xylanase activity of the bifunctional endo-cellulase/endo-xylanase <italic toggle="yes">Ct</italic>Cel5E from <italic toggle="yes">C. thermocellum</italic> [<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], were also found in Trp4 and His70 of the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD enzyme. However, these two residues were not found in the other GH5 enzymes that lack xylanase activity, such as multifunctional endo-cellulase/endo-mannanase/endo-&#x003b2;-glucanase from <italic toggle="yes">C. polysaccharolyticus</italic>, bifunctional endo-cellulase/endo-mannanase from <italic toggle="yes">B. agaradhaerens</italic> and endo-&#x003b2;-1,3-1,4-glucanase PpBglu5A from <italic toggle="yes">P. polymyxa</italic> KF-1 (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). On the other hand, when comparing the amino acid sequences between bifunctional endo-cellulase/endo-xylanase <italic toggle="yes">Ct</italic>Cel5E and the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD enzyme, several other conserved amino acid residues, such as Thr64 and Asp250, and short peptides, such as 123VRIPVRW129, 132HTM134, 140TID142, 145FLDRVEQ151, 154DWSLSR159, 166NSHHD170, 183RFE185, 190QIA192, 197NKS199, 246WNS248, 266TFHYYDPY273, 275FTH277, 283WGT285, 302WSD304, 308IPVY311, 322DRTSR326, 330YDF332 and 346VWD348 (the numbers correspond to <italic toggle="yes">Ct</italic>Cel5E), were found (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>), some of which are predicted to be important for the xylanase activity of the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD enzyme.</p><p>Two catalytic residues and all substrate-binding subsites from subsites &#x02013;3 to +3 within the active site of the Cel5A endo-cellulase from <italic toggle="yes">T. aurantiacus</italic> [<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] were conserved in the bifunctional endo-cellulase/endo-mannanase <italic toggle="yes">Ba</italic>Man5A from <italic toggle="yes">B. agaradhaerens</italic> [<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). On the other hand, His24, Ile118, Ala158, Gly160 and Asn183 in the bifunctional cellulase/mannanase <italic toggle="yes">Ba</italic>Man5A were conserved with His23, Ile104, Ala144, Gly146 and Asn164 in <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD, respectively, but these residues were not found in endo-cellulase Cel5A from <italic toggle="yes">T. aurantiacus</italic>, bifunctional endo-cellulase/endo-xylanase <italic toggle="yes">Ct</italic>Cel5E from <italic toggle="yes">C. thermocellum</italic> and endo-&#x003b2;-1,3-1,4-glucanase from <italic toggle="yes">P. polymyxa</italic> KF-1 (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>). Therefore, some of these amino acids are likely related to the mannanase activity of <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD.</p><p>The &#x003b2;-1,3-1,4-glucanase PpBglu5A from <italic toggle="yes">P. polymyxa</italic> KF-1 [<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] had low similarity with the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD enzyme (35.09%). However, the conserved amino acid residues in the active site of &#x003b2;-1,3-1,4-glucanase PpBglu5A enzyme were similar to those of other GH5 enzymes, including the two catalytic residues and the substrate-binding subsites, except that this enzyme lacks a tryptophan at subsite &#x02212;3 (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). In fact, this position is weaker than the other subsites [<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. There are some amino acid residues, such as Arg9 and Ile194, and short peptides outside the active site that are conserved between PpBglu5A and <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD, namely 111QII113 and 162NEPHG166 (the numbers correspond to PpBglu5A), but these peptides are not found in other GH5 enzymes. These peptides may be involved in the &#x003b2;-1,3-1,4-glucanase activity of the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD enzyme.</p><p>The results showed that due to the similarity in sugar structures (cyclic ring, &#x02013;OH group, &#x02013;H group), GH5 enzymes may be able to use amino acid residues within the substrate-binding subsites of the parent enzyme, endo-cellulase to bind to other structurally similar sugar substrates, such as the xylose-xylose linkage of xylan, the mannose-mannose, glucose-mannose and galactose-mannose linkage of mannans and the glucose-glucose linkage of &#x003b2;-glucan, together with a number of conserved amino acids and/or short peptides that are located outside but should be close to the active site of the GH5 endo-cellulases to bind and hydrolyse substrates. Moreover, these results support the evolution of GH5 endo-cellulases into endo-mannanases, endo-xylanases and endo-1,3-1,4-&#x003b2;-glucanases, using amino acid residues located within the six substrate-binding subsites of the endo-cellulase together with some mutant amino acids located near the active site to bind to other substrates (mannan, xylan, &#x003b2;-glucan) and then catalyse substrates by the two catalytic residues (Glu/Glu) of the cellulase.</p></sec><sec><title>Structure Modeling of the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD Enzyme</title><p>To confirm the substrate specificity of the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD enzyme and to obtain an in-depth understanding of the substrate-binding properties, structure modeling study on the binding of this enzyme was built by SWISS-MODEL using the crystal structure (PDB ID: 4U3A) of bifunctional endo-cellulase/endo-xylanase <italic toggle="yes">Ct</italic>Cel5E from <italic toggle="yes">C. thermocellum</italic> ATCC 27405 as the reference protein. This protein showed high sequence identity with the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD enzyme and the 3D structure and binding subsites of this enzyme has already been reported [<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. <xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5A</xref> shows the two amino acids residues (Glu110 and Glu216) at the catalytic site of the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD enzyme. Eight amino acid residues (Trp30, His69, Asn109, Glu110, Trp147, His170, Tyr172, and Trp249) within the binding subsites for endo-cellulase of the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD is shown in <xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5B</xref>. Amino acid residues on the surface of the binding subsites of the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD enzyme structure that located outside the active site of endo-cellulase, and are expected to be important for enzyme activities were detected; for endo-xylanase, such as Trp4, Thr64, His70, and Asp250 (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5C</xref>), endo-mannanase, such as His23, Ile104, Ala144, Gly146, and Asn164 (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5D</xref>), and endo-&#x003b2;-1,3-1,4-glucanase, such as Arg9 and Ile194 (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5E</xref>).</p><p><xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> shows the molecular dockings of molecular ligands into the active site of the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD enzyme within the four binding subsites between &#x02212;2 and + 2 (sequence from the reducing end) interacted with each ligand (X4, M4 or G4). For endo-xylanase, the hydrophobic stacking interaction of Xyl1 with aromatic residue of Trp4 was displayed on subsite &#x02212;2 at distance of 2.6 &#x000c5;. Whereas His70, Asp250, and Thr64 interacted with Xyl2, Xyl3 and Xyl4 at distances of 4.9, 3.4 and 2.0 &#x000c5;, respectively. For endo-mannanase, His23 and Asn164 interacted with Man1 at distances of 2.4 and 3.5 &#x000c5;, respectively. Whereas Ile104 and Ala144 interacted with Man3 at distances of 2.9 and 3.5 &#x000c5;, respectively. Moreover, Gly146 interacted with Man4 at distance of 4.1 &#x000c5;. For endo-1,3-1,4-&#x003b2;-glucanase, Arg9 interacted with Glu3 at distance of 3.5 &#x000c5;, while Ile194 interacted with Glu4 at distance of 4.7 &#x000c5;.</p></sec><sec><title>Expression and Purification of Recombinants <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD and <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5</title><p>In this work, the two genes, namely <italic toggle="yes">pcgh5</italic> (full sequence) and <italic toggle="yes">pcgh5_CD</italic> (only GH5 catalytic domain) were ligated into the pET-28a vector, yielding pET28<italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 and pET28<italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD, respectively, which were introduced into <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> DH5&#x003b1;. Recombinants full-length <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 and <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD catalytic domain were successfully expressed in <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> BL21 (DE3). Both proteins contain a fusion protein with an <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-terminal histidine tag that were purified with a HisTrap HP column. After purification, <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 and <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD showed a single band on SDS-PAGE and cellulase-zymogram with molecular masses of approximately 85 kDa and 29 kDa, respectively (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6A</xref> and <xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">6B</xref>), which was consistent with the calculated values. These purified proteins will be used for further biochemical studies.</p></sec><sec><title>Substrate Specificity of the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD Enzyme</title><p>According to the CAZy enzyme classification (<ext-link xlink:href="http://www.cazy.org/GH5.html" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.cazy.org/GH5.html</ext-link>), although most GH5 members display endo-cellulase activity, such as the endo-cellulase Cel5A from <italic toggle="yes">T. aurantiacus</italic> [<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], a few other enzymes have also been reported, <italic toggle="yes">e.g.</italic> endo-xylanase PfXyn5 from <italic toggle="yes">Penicillium funiculosum</italic> [<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], endo-mannanase AtMan5-1 from <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> [<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], endo-&#x003b2;-1,3-1,4-glucanase PpBglu5A from <italic toggle="yes">P. polymyxa</italic> KF-1 [<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>], endo-&#x003b2; (1,3)-specific endo-glucanase GH5 from the human gut bacterium <italic toggle="yes">Segatella copri</italic> [<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], &#x003b2;-glucosidase GH5BG from <italic toggle="yes">Oryza sativa</italic> [<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], &#x003b2;-xylosidase T81Xyl5_22A from <italic toggle="yes">Thermogemmatispora</italic> sp. T81 [<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], &#x003b2;-mannosidase <italic toggle="yes">Ac</italic>Man5 from the filamentous fungus <italic toggle="yes">Absidia corymbifera</italic> D1 [<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], bifunctional endo-cellulase/endo-xylanase <italic toggle="yes">Ct</italic>Cel5E from <italic toggle="yes">C. thermocellum</italic> [<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], bifunctional endo-cellulase/endo-mannanase <italic toggle="yes">Ba</italic>Man5A from <italic toggle="yes">B. agaradhaerens</italic> [<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], multifunctional endo-cellulase/endo-mannanase/endo-&#x003b2;-glucanase from <italic toggle="yes">Thermotoga maritima</italic> [<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>] and multifunctional endo-cellulase/endo-mannanase/endo-&#x003b2;-glucanase Man5A from <italic toggle="yes">C. polysaccharolyticus</italic> [<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>].</p><p>Until now, only a few multifunctional enzymes of GH5 members such as two endo-cellulase/endo-mannanase/endo-&#x003b2;-glucanase from <italic toggle="yes">T. maritima</italic> [<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>] and <italic toggle="yes">C. polysaccharolyticus</italic>has have been reported [<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. However, information on these enzymes is limited. Therefore, it would be interesting to study enzymes in the GH5 family that have multifunctional enzyme properties. To study the substrate specificity, the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD catalytic domain was examined against &#x003b2;-1,4 glycosidic linkages of polysaccharide substrates such as cellulose, xylan and mannan (KGM); &#x003b2;-1,4-1,6 glycosidic linkages of polysaccharide substrate such as mannan (LBG); &#x003b2;-1,3-1,4 glycosidic linkages of polysaccharide substrates such as barley &#x003b2;-glucan; &#x003b1;-1,4 and/or &#x003b1;-1,6 glycosidic linkages of polysaccharide substrates such as starch and pectin; &#x003b2;-1,4 glycosidic linkages of disaccharide substrates, as well as cellulose, xylan, and mannan contained in agricultural residues.</p><p>As shown in <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>, the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD catalytic domain effectively hydrolysed CMC (26.80 U mg<sup>-1</sup> protein) and Avicel (15.58 U mg<sup>-1</sup> protein). For xylan, the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD enzyme hydrolysed BWX (16.21 U mg<sup>-1</sup> protein) better than OSX (3.33 U mg<sup>-1</sup> protein). For mannan, <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD preferred to hydrolyse KGM (18.33 U mg<sup>-1</sup> protein) rather than LBG (3.33 U mg<sup>-1</sup> protein). Moreover, <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD was active on barley &#x003b2;-glucan (4.54 U mg<sup>-1</sup> protein). However, the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD enzyme could not hydrolyse disaccharides (cellobiose, xylobiose and mannobiose), starch and pectin. Interestingly, the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD enzyme, which contains only the catalytic domain, was able to hydrolyse cellulose, xylan, mannan and &#x003b2;-glucan, which are rarely found in the GH5 members (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>).</p><p>Without non-catalytic domains (CBM11-Fn3-CBM3), the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD catalytic domain had higher activity on CMC than Avicel (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). CMC is a short, single-chain derivative of cellulose that has some hydroxyl groups of its backbone replaced with carboxymethyl groups to make it more soluble [<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Consequently, CMC is highly soluble and an easy substrate for cellulases to hydrolyse, whereas Avicel is a microcrystalline cellulose with high crystallinity. Thus, <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD was more effective against CMC than Avicel. Similarly, almost all GH5 endo-cellulases preferred to hydrolyse CMC rather than Avicel [<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>].</p><p>The hydrolysis of <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD enzyme toward BWX, the low-branching xylan, was more effective than that of the high-branching xylan, OSX (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>), where BWX is composed of 94% xylose and 6% other substituents, whereas OSX is composed of 52% xylose and 48% other substituents [<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. The substrate binding site of an enzyme is often hindered by substituted side groups of the substrate. Phakeenuya <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. [<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] reported that the frequency of side chain substitution has a significant effect on the enzyme&#x02019;s activity.</p><p>The <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD enzyme preferred to hydrolyse KGM rather than LBG. KGM is a &#x003b2;-D-1,4-linked glucopyranose and &#x003b2;-D-mannopyranose heteropolymer with a molar ratio of 1.0:1.6 in a linear chain. In addition, every 9&#x02013;19th sugar unit in KGM contains an acetyl side group, which facilitate the solubility of KGM [<xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>], whereas LBG is a galactomannan, which is made up of a backbone consisting of &#x003b2;-D-1,4-linked mannopyranose with branching of 1,6-linked &#x003b1;-D-galactopyranose spaced approximately every 3.5 mannose units [<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>], which probably obstructs enzyme function. Moreover, the nature of the GH5 members are endo-cellulases (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>) that prefers to hydrolyse the &#x003b2;-1,4 glycosidic linkage between &#x003b2;-D-1,4-linked glucose-glucose molecules. Thereby, this also may be the reason for the efficient hydrolysis of the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD enzyme toward the &#x003b2;-1,4 glycosidic linkage between glucose-mannose molecules of KGM compared with galactose-mannose of LBG (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).</p><p>Barley &#x003b2;-glucan is a linear chain of the &#x003b2;-glucopyranosyl unit, of which approximately 70% is joined by &#x003b2;-1,4 glycosidic linkage and approximately 30% by &#x003b2;-1,3 glycosidic linkage [<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Unexpectedly, the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD enzyme could hydrolyse barley &#x003b2;-glucan, which is rarely found in GH5 members. Compared with other substrates, <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD may be suitable for substrates with only &#x003b2;-1,4 glycosidic linkages, resulting in low enzyme activity on this substrate. Endo-&#x003b2;-1,3-1,4-glucanase of GH5 from <italic toggle="yes">P. polymyxa</italic> KF-1 has been reported. This enzyme showed high activity on barley &#x003b2;-glucan and lichenan [<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Recently, endo-&#x003b2; (1,3)-specific endo-glucanase belonging to GH5 from the human gut bacterium <italic toggle="yes">Segatella copri</italic> has been reported [<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].</p><p>Although some GH5 members have been shown to react with &#x003b2;-1,4-linked glycosidic disaccharides, such as &#x003b2;-glucosidase from <italic toggle="yes">Oryza sativa</italic> [<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], &#x003b2;-xylosidase from <italic toggle="yes">Thermogemmatispora</italic> sp. T81 [<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], and &#x003b2;-mannosidase from the filamentous fungus <italic toggle="yes">Absidia corymbifera</italic> D1 [<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]; however, the activity of these enzymes was not detected in <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD enzyme. On the other hand, all members of GH5 were unable to hydrolyse the &#x003b1;-1,4 and/or &#x003b1;-1,6 glycosidic linkages of polysaccharide substrates, including <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD from <italic toggle="yes">P. curdlanolyticus</italic> strain B-6.</p><p>The <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD enzyme from <italic toggle="yes">P. curdlanolyticus</italic> B-6 could hydrolyse &#x003b2;-1,4 glycosidic linkages of polysaccharides and related structures (&#x003b2;-1,4-1,6 and &#x003b2;-1,3-1,4 glycosidic linkages of polysaccharides), but not for &#x003b2;-1,4 glycosidic linkages of disaccharides and &#x003b1;-1,4 and/or &#x003b1;-1,6 glycosidic linkages of polysaccharides. These results revealed that the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD enzyme exhibits multifunctional enzyme activities against various polysaccharide substrates, including cellulose, xylan, mannan and &#x003b2;-glucan. Thus, the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD enzyme exhibits unique properties of multifunctional endo-cellulase/endo-xylanase/endo-mannanase/endo-&#x003b2;-glucanase activities that have never been reported before.</p><p>Although cellulose, xylan, mannan and &#x003b2;-glucan are the main polysaccharide components in agricultural residues, the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD enzyme could not hydrolyse these polysaccharides contained in sugarcane bagasse and coconut meal (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). This may be due to the complexity of these polysaccharides in the structures of agricultural residues. Kumar <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. [<xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>] reported on the structural complexity of the agricultural residue, in which xylan is densely packed with lignin layers through ether-ester linkages and interacts with cellulose microfibrils through hydrogen bonds, protecting polysaccharide substrates from enzymatic hydrolysis.</p></sec><sec><title>Substrate Specificity of Full-Length <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 Enzyme on Polysaccharides</title><p>To study the effect of the non-catalytic domains (CBM11-Fn3-CBM3) linked to the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD catalytic domain, the activities of full-length <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 were tested against various polysaccharide substrates. Compared with the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD catalytic domain, for cellulose substrates, the enzyme activity of full-length <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 toward CMC (33.79 U mg<sup>-1</sup> protein) was slightly increased by 1.26-fold, while that of Avicel (28.04 U mg<sup>-1</sup> protein) was increased by 1.80-fold (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). For xylan substrates, the activity of the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 enzyme toward BWX (30.74 U mg<sup>-1</sup> protein) and OSX (10.09 U mg<sup>-1</sup> protein) were improved 1.90-fold and 3.03-fold, respectively. For mannan substrates, the enzyme activity on KGM (29.26 U mg<sup>-1</sup> protein) and LBG (17.37 U mg<sup>-1</sup> protein) increased by 1.60-fold and 5.22-fold, respectively. Furthermore, <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 enzyme activity on barley &#x003b2;-glucan (49.59 U mg<sup>-1</sup> protein) significantly increased the enzyme activity (10.04-fold) (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). These results indicate that the three non-catalytic domains linked to the GH5 catalytic domain of <italic toggle="yes">P. curdlanolyticus</italic> B-6 have a significant effect on improving the catalytic activity toward crystalline cellulose, highly branched polysaccharides, and &#x003b2;-1,4-1,6 and &#x003b2;-1,3-1,4 glycosidic linkages of polysaccharides. We plan to study the role of each non-catalytic domain on the function of full-length <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 in the near future.</p><p>It has been reported that CBM3s show binding affinity for cellulose, xylan and mannan [<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] and can promote the activity of the catalytic domain in glycoside hydrolase activities toward polysaccharides and complex substrates present in agricultural residue [<xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, <xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>], whereas the presence of Fn3 can modify the cellulose surface to increase cellulase activity against insoluble cellulose [<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Alternatively, the presence of CBM11 could improve the affinity of the catalytic domain for 1,3-1,4-&#x003b2;-glucan [<xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Accordingly, when these non-catalytic domains (CBM11-Fn3-CBM3) associate with the GH5 catalytic domain of <italic toggle="yes">P. curdlanolyticus</italic> strain B-6 (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1A</xref>), it may facilitate substrate recognition and orient the active site of the enzyme in the correct direction to improve the enzyme&#x02019;s activity on cellulose, xylan, mannan and &#x003b2;-glucan substrates. On the other hand, enzyme activities toward sugarcane bagasse and coconut meal were observed in full-length <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 only, not in the catalytic domain (<italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD) (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). As a result, these non-catalytic domains linked to the GH5 catalytic domain of the strain B-6 should be key factors in improving the enzyme activities toward various &#x003b2;-1,4 glycosidic linkages of polysaccharide substrates, especially hemicellulose (xylan and mannan) and cellulose contained in agricultural residues.</p><p>Previous studies demonstrated that some non-catalytic domains linked to the catalytic domains of glycoside hydrolases are involved in the specific activity of the enzymes toward insoluble and/or complex structure substrates. For example, the presence of CBM36 was found to be necessary for the endo-xylanase property of the multifunctional arabinofuranosidase/endo-xylanase/&#x003b2;-xylosidase PcAxy43B enzyme from <italic toggle="yes">P. curdlanolyticus</italic> B-6 [<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Ye <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. [<xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>] reported that when a new CBM with sequence similarity to CBM29-2 from <italic toggle="yes">Meiothermus taiwanensis</italic> WR-220 was combined with the endo-cellulase catalytic domain of Cel5A of <italic toggle="yes">T. maritima</italic>, the substrate affinity of <italic toggle="yes">Tm</italic>Cel5A increased to make a robust cellulase. Deletion of the two CBM16s from Man5A of <italic toggle="yes">Thermoanaerobacterium polysaccharolyticum</italic> resulted in a significant loss of both endo-mannanase and endo-cellulase (CMCase) activities [<xref rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Similarly, deletion of the two CBM16s from Man5B of <italic toggle="yes">C. polysaccharolyticus</italic> resulted in a significant loss of endo-mannanase activity toward LBG, guar gum and &#x003b2;-mannan [<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Alternatively, the two CBM22s of the full-length bifunctional endo-xylanase/endo-&#x003b2;-1,3-1,4-glucanase Xyn10B from <italic toggle="yes">C. stercorarium</italic> are important for &#x003b2;-1,3-1,4-glucanase activity toward barley &#x003b2;-glucan [<xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Moreover, the replacement of CBM11 in the endo-cellulase <italic toggle="yes">Ct</italic>Cel5E from <italic toggle="yes">C. thermocellum</italic> with low xylanase activity by CBM6 from <italic toggle="yes">C. stercorarium</italic> significantly increased the xylanase specificity activity of <italic toggle="yes">Ct</italic>Cel5E toward oat spelt xylan [<xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Mode of Action of the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD Enzyme on Polysaccharides</title><p>Due to the ability of <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD to hydrolyse various &#x003b2;-1,4 glycosidic linkages and the related structure of polysaccharides (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>), the product patterns of the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD enzyme on these substrates were analysed. Products released from CMC and Avicel had different patterns. The CMC products were a series of cello-oligosaccharides G6, G5, G4, G3 and G2 (<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7A</xref>). This result indicates the endo-action of the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD enzyme on the CMC substrate. On the other hand, for Avicel, cellobiose (G2) was the only product obtained (<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7B</xref>). Avicel (microcrystalline cellulose) is a highly crystalline cellulose in which the numerous cellulose chains in the Avicel structure are held tightly together by hydrogen bonds. Moreover, the substrate binding groove of the GH5 enzyme is narrow and long [<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Therefore, it did not allow the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD enzyme to attack the inner regions of the Avicel structure. However, this endo-acting enzyme attempts to produce sugar(s) from the Avicel chain ends (likely for the growth of <italic toggle="yes">P. curdlanolyticus</italic> B-6 cells), which have a loose structure, and released cellobiose as a single product. This phenomenon is observed in some endo-cellulases that hydrolyse crystalline cellulose. For example, cellobiose was the main product of Avicel hydrolysis by an endo-cellulase from <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus circulans</italic> F-2 [<xref rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>], the main product released from Avicel by the brown-rot basidiomycete <italic toggle="yes">Fomitopsis palustris</italic> endo-cellulase was cellobiose [<xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>], a processive endo-cellulase from the brown rot basidiomycete <italic toggle="yes">Gloeophyllum trabeum</italic> hydrolysed Avicel to cellobiose as the major product [<xref rid="ref50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>], and an endo-cellulase from <italic toggle="yes">Trichoderma reesei</italic> CDU-11 produced cellobiose as the main product from Avicel [<xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>].</p><p>For xylan substrates, the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD enzyme hydrolysed BWX and OSX to a series of xylo-oligosaccharides. However, the hydrolysis product patterns of BWX and OSX were clearly different. X6, X5, X4, X3 and X2 were products released from BWX, whereas the products from OSX were a series of oligosaccharides, which were not consistent with the size of standard sugars (<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7C</xref> and <xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">7D</xref>), which might be due to the effect of its substitute groups. For mannan substrates, the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD enzyme degraded KGM and released only the dimeric product, which may be mannose-mannose or mannose-glucose (<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7E</xref>). For LBG, a series of tetrameric, trimeric and dimeric mannose-mannose and/or mannose-galactose molecules were detected (<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7F</xref>). These results indicate that the hydrolysis products of the enzyme depend on the type of substrate. Phakeenuya <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. [<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] reported that the type of substrate affected the function of the enzyme. Alternatively, the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD enzyme could hydrolyse barley &#x003b2;-glucan and generated a series of gluco-oligosaccharides (<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7G</xref>).</p><p>As a result of the mode of action of the full-length <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD on polysaccharides, the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD enzyme produced various types of oligosaccharides that can be used in a variety of food products. For example, cello-oligosaccharides have prebiotic properties and can stimulate the growth of many probiotics, such as <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Bifidobacterium</italic> [<xref rid="ref52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Xylo-oligosaccharides have acceptable stability and sensory properties, which can be used as prebiotics and low-caloric food sweeteners without toxicity or adverse effects on human health [<xref rid="ref53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Manno-oligosaccharides are used as prebiotics due to their ability to promote the growth of <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacilli</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Bifidobacteria</italic>, biofilm formation and the production of beneficial short-chain fatty acids [<xref rid="ref54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>], while gluco-oligosaccharides can be used as prebiotics to improve the health of humans and animals [<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Mode of Action of Full-length <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 Enzyme on Polysaccharides</title><p>The mode of action of the full-length <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 enzyme towards all polysaccharide substrates was similar to that of the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD enzyme. However, the amounts of products produced by the full-length enzyme were higher than that of the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD enzyme for all polysaccharides tested (<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>), which may be due to the role of non-catalytic domains linked to the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD catalytic domain.</p></sec><sec><title>Hydrolysis of Untreated Agricultural Residues by Full-length <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 Enzyme</title><p>Sugarcane is grown in large quantities in tropical and subtropical countries. In 2020, approximately 1.9 billion tons of sugarcane were produced worldwide (<ext-link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org" ext-link-type="uri">https://en.wikipedia.org</ext-link> &#x0203a; wiki &#x0203a; Sugarcane). Sugarcane bagasse is the solid by-product of sugarcane juice extraction and constitutes approximately 30% of the material remaining after extraction. Sugarcane bagasse contains 51.3% cellulose, 33.5% xylan and 8.20% lignin [<xref rid="ref55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. Alternatively, coconut is an important plant in several Asian and South American countries, with an annual production of more than 58 million tons around the world, whereas coconut meal is a by-product of coconut milk production, which amounts to approximately 3,600 tons per year. Coconut meal is composed of 55.03% mannan, 8.83% cellulose and 25.59%fat [<xref rid="ref56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. Sugarcane bagasse and coconut meal occur as by-products in large quantities in Thailand. Therefore, we selected sugarcane bagasse (representative of natural xylan and cellulose) and coconut meal (representative of natural mannan and cellulose) to test the ability of the full-length <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 enzyme to hydrolyse these residues without pretreatment (only cut into small pieces).</p><p>Surprisingly, although the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD catalytic enzyme was unable to hydrolyse agriculture residues, the full-length <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 enzyme showed hydrolytic activity on sugarcane bagasse (20.58 U mg<sup>-1</sup> protein) and coconut meal (12.98 U mg<sup>-1</sup> protein) (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). The <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 enzyme released reducing sugars from sugarcane bagasse better than coconut meal, which may be due to the higher content of xylan and cellulose in sugarcane bagasse compared with that of mannan and cellulose in coconut meal. Moreover, coconut meal is high in fat (25.6%), which may interfere with the action of the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 enzyme on polysaccharide substrates. The <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 enzyme can hydrolyse polysaccharides that exist in the complex structure of agricultural residues. These results indicate the cooperative action between the GH5 catalytic domain and the three non-catalytic domains (CBM11-Fn3-CBM3) from <italic toggle="yes">P. curdlanolyticus</italic> strain B-6 to promote the enzyme activities of the catalytic domain toward naturally insoluble substrates present in agricultural residues, which has never before been reported in GH5 members. Similarly, Limsakul <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. [<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] reported that the presence of CBM36 is required for the multifunctional arabinofuranosidase/endo-xylanase/&#x003b2;-xylosidase PcAxy43B enzyme from <italic toggle="yes">P. curdlanolyticus</italic> B-6 to hydrolyse &#x003b2;-1,4 glycosidic linkages of polysaccharide (xylan) contained in corn hull. Moreover, Pasari <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. [<xref rid="ref57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>] reported on the importance of X2-CBM3 modules in agricultural residue (wheat straw) hydrolysis and provided insights into how CBM engineering can be applied to improve cellulosic enzyme binding affinity and hydrolysis potential.</p><p>TLC chromatograms demonstrated that the full-length <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 enzyme generated X2 and G2 as major products from sugarcane bagasse (<xref rid="F8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8A</xref>). This result may be due to the non-catalytic domains (CBM11-Fn3-CBM3) being important for the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD catalytic domain to deconstruct the complex structure of agricultural residues, resulting in a structural change that allows <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 xylanase to hydrolyse xylan located on the surface of sugarcane bagasse to produce X2. Thereafter, the non-catalytic domains may modify the cellulose surface by Fn3 [<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] and may disrupt the hydrogen bond network of crystalline cellulose by CBM3 [<xref rid="ref58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>], resulting in swelling and loosening of the cellulose-xylan matrix and crystalline structure. These effects result in an increase in amorphous regions and cellulose surface area and improve the accessibility of cellulase to cellulose, thus producing G2.</p><p>The full-length <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 enzyme was able to release a series of manno-oligosaccharides M6, M5, M4, M3 and M2 from coconut meal (<xref rid="F8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8B</xref>), probably due to the interaction between the endo-mannanase of the catalytic domain and CBM11, where it was reported that CBM11 enhanced the affinity of the catalytic domain to 1,3-1,4-&#x003b2;-glucan [<xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], but no cellulosic products were detected. These results indicate that the cellulose present in coconut meal is too strong for <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 to hydrolyse, which might be because the cellulose in coconut meal is coated with a high amount of fat [<xref rid="ref56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>], making the cellulose resistant to the action of endo-cellulase. The advantage of this result is that only manno-oligosaccharides from coconut meal were obtained.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusion"><title>Conclusion</title><p>This work presents a novel multifunctional endo-cellulase/endo-xylanase/endo-mannanase/endo-&#x003b2;-glucanase GH5 enzyme from <italic toggle="yes">P. curdlanolyticus</italic> B-6, and the role of its non-catalytic domains. This enzyme could hydrolyse the &#x003b2;-1,4 glycosidic linkages of polysaccharides present in agricultural residues into oligosaccharides in one step without any pretreatment. This environment-friendly enzymatic hydrolysis has received increasing attention in recent years. Therefore, <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 is a good candidate to produce oligosaccharides from agricultural residues for use as prebiotics in various food products.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>The authors acknowledge the financial support provided by King Mongkut&#x02019;s University of Technology Thonburi (KMUTT), Thailand Science Research and Innovation (TSRI), and National Science, Research and Innovation Funds (NSRF) Fiscal year 2022 Grant number (FRB650048/0164). The present work was funded by King Mongkut&#x02019;s University of Technology Thonburi under KMUTT Research Center of Excellence Project (Grant number 7601.24/4054). Niendy Virnanda Fatmawati gratefully acknowledges the support provided by KMUTT through the Petchra Pra Jom Klao Doctoral Degree Research Scholarship.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>
<bold>Conflict of Interest</bold>
</p><p>The authors have no financial conflicts of interest to declare.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Phakeenuya</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ratanakhanokchai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kosugi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tachaapaikoon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2020</year><article-title>A novel multifunctional GH9 enzyme from <italic toggle="yes">Paenibacillus curdlanolyticus</italic> B-6 exhibiting endo/exo functions of cellulase, mannanase and xylanase activities</article-title><source>Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol.</source><volume>104</volume><fpage>2079</fpage><lpage>2096</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00253-020-10388-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31980921</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lynd</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weimer</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>van Zyl</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pretorius</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Microbial cellulose utilization: fundamentals and biotechnology</article-title><source>Microbiol. Mol. Biol. Rev.</source><volume>66</volume><fpage>506</fpage><lpage>577</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/MMBR.66.3.506-577.2002</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC120791</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12209002</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Saha</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>&#x003b1;-L-Arabinofuranosidases: biochemistry, molecular biology and application in biotechnology</article-title><source>Biotechnol. Adv.</source><volume>18</volume><fpage>403</fpage><lpage>423</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0734-9750(00)00044-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14538102</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Phitsuwan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tachaapaikoon</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kosugi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kyu</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ratanakhanokchai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>Cellulolytic and xylanolytic enzyme complex from an alkalothermoanaerobacterium, <italic toggle="yes">Tepidimicrobium xylanilyticum</italic> BT14</article-title><source>J. Microbiol. Biotechnol.</source><volume>20</volume><fpage>893</fpage><lpage>903</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4014/jmb.0911.11025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20519913</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Golisch</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cordeiro</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>ASC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Briggs</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Petegem</surname><given-names>FV</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><year>2024</year><article-title>The molecular basis of cereal mixed-linkage &#x003b2;-glucan utilization by the human gut bacterium <italic toggle="yes">Segatella copri</italic></article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><volume>300</volume><elocation-id>107625</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jbc.2024.107625</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11418011</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39122003</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Teeravivattanakit</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baramee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Phitsuwan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sornyotha</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Waeonukul</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pason</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><year>2017</year><article-title>Chemical pretreatment-independent saccharifications of xylan and cellulose of rice straw by bacterial weak lignin-binding xylanolytic and cellulolytic enzymes</article-title><source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source><volume>83</volume><fpage>e01522</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.01522-17</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5666149</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28864653</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dodd</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hespen</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ohene-Adjei</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schroeder</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mackie</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>Comparative analyses of two thermophilic enzymes exhibiting both &#x003b2;-1,4 mannosidic and &#x003b2;-1,4 glucosidic cleavage activities from <italic toggle="yes">Caldanaerobius polysaccharolyticus</italic></article-title><source>J. Bacteriol.</source><volume>192</volume><fpage>4111</fpage><lpage>4121</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.00257-10</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2916432</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20562312</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Teeravivattanakit</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baramee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Phitsuwan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Waeonukul</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pason</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tachaapaikoon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><year>2016</year><article-title>Novel trifunctional xylanolytic enzyme Axy43A from <italic toggle="yes">Paenibacillus curdlanolyticus</italic> strain B-6 exhibiting endo-xylanase, &#x003b2;-D-xylosidase, and arabinoxylan arabinofuranohydrolase activities</article-title><source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source><volume>82</volume><fpage>6942</fpage><lpage>6951</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.02256-16</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5103093</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27663030</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sakka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Higashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ratanakhanokchai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sakka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>Characterization of <italic toggle="yes">Paenibacillus curdlanolyticus</italic> B-6 Xyn10D, a xylanase that contains a family 3 carbohydrate-binding module</article-title><source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source><volume>77</volume><fpage>4260</fpage><lpage>4263</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.00226-11</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3131646</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21498754</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Limsakul</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Phitsuwan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Waeonukul</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pason</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tachaapaikoon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Poomputsa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><year>2021</year><article-title>A novel multifunctional arabinofuranosidase/endoxylanase/&#x003b2;-xylosidase GH43 enzyme from <italic toggle="yes">Paenibacillus curdlanolyticus</italic> B-6 and its synergistic action to produce arabinose and xylose from cereal arabinoxylan</article-title><source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source><volume>87</volume><fpage>e01730</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.01730-21</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8612256</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34613758</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kataeva</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Seidel III</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>West</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ljungdahl</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>The fibronectin type 3-like repeat from the <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium thermocellum</italic> cellobiohydrolase CbhA promotes hydrolysis of cellulose by modifying its surface</article-title><source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source><volume>68</volume><fpage>4292</fpage><lpage>4300</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.68.9.4292-4300.2002</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC124122</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12200278</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pason</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kyu</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ratanakhanokchai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2006</year><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Paenibacillus curdlanolyticus</italic> strain B-6 xylanolytic-cellulolytic enzyme system that degrades insoluble polysaccharides</article-title><source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source><volume>72</volume><fpage>2483</fpage><lpage>2490</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.72.4.2483-2490.2006</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1448999</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16597947</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Altschul</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Madden</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sch&#x000e4;ffer</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>Gapped BLAST and PSI-BLAST: a new generation of protein database search programs</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>25</volume><fpage>3389</fpage><lpage>3402</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/25.17.3389</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC146917</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9254694</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Edgar</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>MUSCLE: multiple sequence alignment with high accuracy and high throughput</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>32</volume><fpage>1792</fpage><lpage>1797</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkh340</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC390337</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15034147</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Aspeborg</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Coutinho</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brumer III</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Henrissat</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>Evolution, substrate specificity and subfamily classification of glycoside hydrolase family 5 (GH5)</article-title><source>BMC Evol. Biol.</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>186</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2148-12-186</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3526467</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22992189</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><year>2015</year><article-title>Biochemical characterization and structural analysis of a bifunctional cellulase/xylanase from <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium thermocellum</italic></article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><volume>290</volume><fpage>5739</fpage><lpage>5748</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M114.604454</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4342484</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25575592</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Dallakyan S, Olson AJ. 2015. Small-molecule library screening by docking with PyRx, pp. 243-250. <italic toggle="yes">In</italic> Hempel JE, Williams CH, Hong CC (eds.), <italic toggle="yes">Chemical Biology: Methods and Protocols</italic> Chapter 19, Springer Protocols, Humana Press, New York.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">DeLano WL, Bromberg S. 2004. <italic toggle="yes">PyMOL User's Guide</italic>, pp. 1-66. DeLano Scientific LLC, San Francisco-CA.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Laemmli</surname><given-names>UK</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>1970</year><article-title>Cleavage of structural proteins during the assembly of the head of bacteriophage T4</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>227</volume><fpage>680</fpage><lpage>685</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/227680a0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5432063</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bradford</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>1976</year><article-title>A rapid and sensitive method for the quantitation of microgram quantities of protein utilizing the principle of protein-dye binding</article-title><source>Anal. Biochem.</source><volume>72</volume><fpage>248</fpage><lpage>254</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/abio.1976.9999</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">942051</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>1944</year><article-title>A photometric adaptation of the Somogyi method for the determination of glucose</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><volume>153</volume><fpage>375</fpage><lpage>380</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0021-9258(18)71980-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Leggio</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>The 1.62 &#x000c5; structure of <italic toggle="yes">Thermoascus aurantiacus</italic> endoglucanase: completing the structural picture of subfamilies in glycoside hydrolase family 5</article-title><source>FEBS Lett.</source><volume>523</volume><fpage>103</fpage><lpage>108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0014-5793(02)02954-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12123813</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tailford</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ducros</surname><given-names>VMA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Flint</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morland</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zechel</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Understanding how diverse &#x003b2;-mannanases recognize heterogeneous substrates</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><volume>48</volume><fpage>7009</fpage><lpage>7018</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/bi900515d</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19441796</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morais</surname><given-names>MAB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Persinoti</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Galinari</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yoshimi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><year>2022</year><article-title>Glycoside hydrolase subfamily GH5_57 features a highly redesigned catalytic interface to process complex hetero-&#x003b2;-mannans</article-title><source>Acta Crystallogr. D Struct. Biol.</source><volume>78</volume><fpage>1358</fpage><lpage>1372</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S2059798322009561</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36322419</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><year>2020</year><article-title>Degradative GH5 &#x003b2;-1,3-1,4-glucanase PpBglu5A for glucan in <italic toggle="yes">Paenibacillus polymyxa</italic> KF-1</article-title><source>Proc. Biochem.</source><volume>98</volume><fpage>183</fpage><lpage>192</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.procbio.2020.08.008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ogunyewo</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Okereke</surname><given-names>OE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yazdani</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2022</year><article-title>Characterization of a GH5 endoxylanase from <italic toggle="yes">Penicillium funiculosum</italic> and its synergism with GH16 endo-1,3(4)-glucanase in saccharification of sugarcane bagasse</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>17219</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-022-21529-1</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9568505</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36241677</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vilaplana</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brumer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aspeborg</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2014</year><article-title>Enzymatic characterization of a glycoside hydrolase family 5 subfamily 7 (GH5_7) mannanase from <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title><source>Planta</source><volume>239</volume><fpage>653</fpage><lpage>665</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00425-013-2005-y</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3928506</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24327260</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><year>2020</year><article-title>Degradative GH5 &#x003b2;-1,3-1,4-glucanase PpBglu5A for glucan in <italic toggle="yes">Paenibacillus polymyxa</italic> KF-1</article-title><source>Proc. Biochem.</source><volume>98</volume><fpage>183</fpage><lpage>192</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.procbio.2020.08.008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Opassiri</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pomthong</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Akiyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nakphaichit</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Onkoksoong</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cairns</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>A stress-induced rice (<italic toggle="yes">Oryza sativa</italic> L.) &#x003b2;-glucosidase represents a new subfamily of glycosyl hydrolase family 5 containing a fascin-like domain</article-title><source>Biochem. J.</source><volume>408</volume><fpage>241</fpage><lpage>249</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/BJ20070734</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2267349</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17705786</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tomazini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Higasi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Manzine</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stott</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sparling</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><year>2019</year><article-title>A novel thermostable GH5 &#x003b2;-xylosidase from <italic toggle="yes">Thermogemmatispora</italic> sp. T81</article-title><source>New Biotechnol.</source><volume>53</volume><fpage>57</fpage><lpage>64</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nbt.2019.07.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31299302</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y-x</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Q-j</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>S-q</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Z-q</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2015</year><article-title>Characterization of a novel glycoside hydrolase family 5 &#x003b2;-mannosidase from <italic toggle="yes">Absidia corymbifera</italic> with high transglycosylation activity</article-title><source>J. Mol. Catal. B Enzym.</source><volume>122</volume><fpage>265</fpage><lpage>274</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcatb.2015.09.018</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chhabra</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shockley</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Donald</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Regulation of endo-acting glycosyl hydrolases in the hyperthermophilic bacterium <italic toggle="yes">Thermotoga maritima</italic> grown on glucan- and mannan-based polysaccharides</article-title><source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source><volume>68</volume><fpage>545</fpage><lpage>554</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.68.2.545-554.2002</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC126696</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11823189</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Heinze T. 2005. Carboxymethyl ethers of cellulose and starch-a review, pp.13-29. <italic toggle="yes">In</italic> Heinze T, Koschella A (eds.), <italic toggle="yes">Macromolecular Symposia</italic>, Volume 223, Issue 1. WILEY&#x02010;VCH, Weinheim, Germany.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Adab</surname><given-names>FK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yaghoobi</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gharechahi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2024</year><article-title>Enhanced crystalline cellulose degradation by a novel metagenome-derived cellulase enzyme</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><volume>14</volume><fpage>8560</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-024-59256-4</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11014956</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38609443</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Azadi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tolan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eriksson</surname><given-names>KEL</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Relationships between activities of xylanases and xylan structures</article-title><source>Enzyme Microb. Technol.</source><volume>27</volume><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>94</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0141-0229(00)00190-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10862906</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nishinari</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>GO</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>1992</year><article-title>Review of the physico-chemical characteristics and properties of konjac mannan</article-title><source>Food Hydrocoll.</source><volume>6</volume><fpage>199</fpage><lpage>222</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0268-005X(09)80360-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kohajdov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Karovi&#x0010d;ov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Application of hydrocolloids as baking improvers</article-title><source>Chem. Pap.</source><volume>63</volume><fpage>26</fpage><lpage>38</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2478/s11696-008-0085-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Goudar</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Janghu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Longvah</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2020</year><article-title>Effect of processing on barley &#x003b2;-glucan content, its molecular weight and extractability</article-title><source>Int. J. Biol. Macromol.</source><volume>162</volume><fpage>1204</fpage><lpage>1216</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2020.06.208</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32592782</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Delwiche</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stroeve</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Methods for pretreatment of lignocellulosic biomass for efficient hydrolysis and biofuel production</article-title><source>Ind. Eng. Chem. Res.</source><volume>48</volume><fpage>3713</fpage><lpage>3729</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ie801542g</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ichikawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Karita</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kondo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2014</year><article-title>Cellulosomal carbohydrate-binding module from <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium josui</italic> binds to crystalline and non-crystalline cellulose, and soluble polysaccharides</article-title><source>FEBS Lett.</source><volume>588</volume><fpage>3886</fpage><lpage>3890</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.febslet.2014.08.032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25217835</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Boraston</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bolam</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Carbohydrate-binding modules: fine-tuning polysaccharide recognition</article-title><source>Biochem. J.</source><volume>382</volume><fpage>769</fpage><lpage>781</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/BJ20040892</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1133952</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15214846</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pasari</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Adlakha</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bashir</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rajacharya</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><year>2017</year><article-title>Impact of module-X2 and carbohydrate binding module-3 on the catalytic activity of associated glycoside hydrolases towards plant biomass</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>3700</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-03927-y</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5473887</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28623337</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Br&#x000e1;s</surname><given-names>NF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cerqueira</surname><given-names>NMFSA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Carbohydrate&#x02010;binding modules from family 11: understanding the binding mode of polysaccharides</article-title><source>Int. J. Quantum Chem.</source><volume>108</volume><fpage>2030</fpage><lpage>2040</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/qua.21755</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref44"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ye T-J, Huang K-F, Koa T-P, Wu S-H. 2022. Synergic action of an inserted carbohydrate-binding module in a glycoside hydrolase family 5 endoglucanase. <italic toggle="yes">Acta Cryst. D Struct. Biol.</italic>
<bold>1:</bold> 78(Pt5)633-646.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S2059798322002601</pub-id>
<!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9063844</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35503211</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cann</surname><given-names>IKO</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kocherginskaya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>King</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>White</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mackie</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>Molecular cloning, sequencing, and expression of a novel multidomain mannanase gene from <italic toggle="yes">Thermoanaerobacterium polysaccharolyticum</italic></article-title><source>J. Bacteriol.</source><volume>181</volume><fpage>1643</fpage><lpage>1651</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.181.5.1643-1651.1999</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC93557</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10049399</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Araki</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sakka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sakka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ohmiya</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Essential role of the family-22 carbohydrate-binding modules for &#x003b2;-1,3-1,4-glucanase activity of <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium stercorarium</italic> Xyn10B</article-title><source>FEBS Lett.</source><volume>561</volume><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>158</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0014-5793(04)00160-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15013768</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ichikawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Karita</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kondo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2016</year><article-title>Carbohydrate binding modules influence substrate specificity of an endoglucanase from <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium thermocellum</italic></article-title><source>Biosci. Biotechnol. Biochem.</source><volume>80</volume><fpage>188</fpage><lpage>192</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09168451.2015.1069696</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26223555</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>1995</year><article-title>Characterization and substrate specificity of an endo-&#x003b2;-1,4-D-glucanase I (Avicelase I) from an extracellular multienzyme complex of <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus circulans</italic></article-title><source>Appl. Environ. Micribiol.</source><volume>61</volume><fpage>959</fpage><lpage>965</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/aem.61.3.959-965.1995</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC167356</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7793925</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref49"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cha</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Son</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>The brown-rot basidiomycete <italic toggle="yes">Fomitopsis palustris</italic> has the endo-glucanases capable of degrading microcrystalline cellulose</article-title><source>J. Microbiol. Biotechnol.</source><volume>17</volume><fpage>800</fpage><lpage>805</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18051302</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref50"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hammel</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Processive endoglucanase active in crystalline cellulose hydrolysis by the brown rot basidiomycete <italic toggle="yes">Gloeophyllum trabeum</italic></article-title><source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source><volume>71</volume><fpage>2412</fpage><lpage>2417</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.71.5.2412-2417.2005</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1087581</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15870328</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref51"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ogawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Toyama</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fuji</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>1991</year><article-title>Microcrystalline cellulose-hydrolyzing cellulase (endo-cellulase) from <italic toggle="yes">Trichoderma reesei</italic> CDU-11</article-title><source>J. Gen. Appl. Microbiol.</source><volume>37</volume><fpage>249</fpage><lpage>259</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2323/jgam.37.249</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref52"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fujii</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Katsumata</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kikkawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Machida</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><year>2016</year><article-title>A combination of soy isoflavones and cellooligosaccharides changes equol/<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-desmethylangolensin production ratio and attenuates bone fragility in ovariectomized mice</article-title><source>Biosci. Biotechnol. Biochem.</source><volume>80</volume><fpage>1632</fpage><lpage>1635</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09168451.2016.1184559</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27191709</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref53"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fatmawati</surname><given-names>NV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ketbot</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Phitsuwan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Waeonukul</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tachaapaikoon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kosugi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><year>2021</year><article-title>Efficient biological pretreatment and bioconversion of corn cob by the sequential application of a <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus firmus</italic> K-1 cellulase-free xylanolytic enzyme and commercial cellulases</article-title><source>Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol.</source><volume>105</volume><fpage>4589</fpage><lpage>4598</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00253-021-11308-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34027563</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref54"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Suryawanshi</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kango</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2021</year><article-title>Production of mannooligosaccharides from various mannans and evaluation of their prebiotic potential</article-title><source>Food Chem.</source><volume>334</volume><elocation-id>127428</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2020.127428</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32688173</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref55"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gothwal</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alappat</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>Feasibility of dairy waste water (DWW) and distillery spent wash (DSW) effluents in increasing the yield potential of <italic toggle="yes">Pleurotus flabellatus</italic> (PF 1832) and <italic toggle="yes">Pleurotus sajor-caju</italic> (PS 1610) on bagasse</article-title><source>3 Biotech.</source><volume>2</volume><fpage>249</fpage><lpage>257</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13205-012-0053-9</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3433880</pub-id>--></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref56"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Khuwijitjaru</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Watsanit</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Adachi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>Carbohydrate content and composition of product from subcritical water treatment of coconut meal</article-title><source>J. Ind. Eng. Chem.</source><volume>18</volume><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>229</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jiec.2011.11.010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref57"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pasari</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Adlakha</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bashir</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rajacharya</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><year>2017</year><article-title>Impact of module-X2 and carbohydrate binding module-3 on the catalytic activity of associated glycoside hydrolases towards plant biomass</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>3700</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-03927-y</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5473887</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28623337</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref58"><label>58</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Irwin</surname><given-names>D-C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Processivity, substrate binding, and mechanism of cellulose hydrolysis by <italic toggle="yes">Thermobifida fusca</italic> Cel9A</article-title><source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source><volume>73</volume><fpage>3165</fpage><lpage>3172</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.02960-06</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1907127</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17369336</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>Schematic illustration of modular structures of</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) full-length <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 consisting of a GH5 catalytic domain, a family 11 carbohydrate-binding module (CBM11), a domain of fibronectin type 3 (Fn3), and a family 3 carbohydrate-binding module (CBM3) and (<bold>B</bold>) the GH5 catalytic domain (<italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD) from <italic toggle="yes">P. curdlanolyticus</italic> B-6.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jmb-35-e2501046-f1" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><title>From the Carbohydrate-Active EnZymes database (CAZy) (<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.cazy.org/GH5_characterized.html#pagination_FUNC" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cazy.org/GH5_characterized.html#pagination_FUNC</ext-link>),</title><p>the graphic shows the percentage of different enzymes in the GH5 members with different enzymatic activities. Each color is coded according to the type of substrate and the specificity of the reaction.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jmb-35-e2501046-f2" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><title>Phylogenetic tree of the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD enzyme with other characterized members of GH5 subfamily based on amino acid sequences.</title><p>The tree was constructed using MUSCLE in MEGA11 software [<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] with 2,000 bootstrap replicates. The number for each node is the bootstrap percentage. Most members exhibited unknown subfamily, such as a bifunctional endo-cellulase/endo-xylanase from <italic toggle="yes">C. thermocellum</italic> (GenBank Accession No. 4U3A_1), an endo-&#x003b2;-1,3-1,4- glucanase from <italic toggle="yes">P. polymyxa</italic> (GenBank Accession No. QBY21421.1), a bifunctional endo-cellulase/endo-mannanase from <italic toggle="yes">B. agaradhaerens</italic> (GenBank Accession No. 2WHL_1), a multifunctional endo-cellulase/endo-mannanase/endo-&#x003b2;-1,3-1,4- glucanase from <italic toggle="yes">C. polysaccharolyticus</italic> (GenBank Accession No. AAD09354.1), and subfamily 4, such as an endo-&#x003b2;-1,3-1,4- glucanase from <italic toggle="yes">Caldicellulosiruptor</italic> sp. F32 (GenBank Accession No. AGM71677.1), a bifunctional endo-cellulase/endomannanase from <italic toggle="yes">C. cellulovorans</italic> (GenBank Accession No. AAD39739.1), a bifunctional endo-cellulase/endo-xylanase from <italic toggle="yes">C. ruminicola</italic> GenBank Accession No. ACZ98591.1), a bifunctional endo-cellulase/endo-xylanase from <italic toggle="yes">X. ruminicola</italic> (GenBank Accession No. AAC36862.1), while one member, endo-cellulase from <italic toggle="yes">T. aurantiacus</italic> (GenBank Accession No. AAL88714.2), exhibited subfamily 5.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jmb-35-e2501046-f3" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><title>Amino acid sequence alignment of the catalytic domain enzyme from <italic toggle="yes">P. curdlanolyticus</italic> strain B-6 (this work) compared with other characterized GH5 enzymes with different functions such as endo-cellulase from <italic toggle="yes">T. aurantiacus</italic> (GenBank Accession No. AAL88714.2), bifunctional endo-cellulase/endo-xylanase from <italic toggle="yes">C. thermocellum</italic> (GenBank Accession No. 4U3A_1), bifunctional endo-cellulase/endo-mannanase from <italic toggle="yes">B. agaradhaerens</italic> (GenBank Accession No. 2WHL_1), multifunctional endo-cellulase/endo-mannanase/ endo-&#x003b2;-glucanase from <italic toggle="yes">C. polysaccharolyticus</italic> (GenBank Accession No. AAD09354.1), and endo-&#x003b2;-1,3-1,4- glucanase from <italic toggle="yes">P. polymyxa</italic> (GenBank Accession No. QBY21421.1).</title><p>The two catalytic residues are marked by an asterisk, while the six substrate-binding subsites of endo-cellulase are highlighted in grey. The six substrate-binding subsites are numbered &#x02212; 3, &#x02212; 2, &#x02212; 1, + 1, + 2 and + 3. Conserved residues of endo-xylanase, endo-mannanase, and endo-&#x003b2;-1,3-1,4-glucanase of GH5 members located outside the active site of endo-cellulase are highlighted in black. Blue letters represent conserved short peptides between the catalytic domain enzyme from <italic toggle="yes">P. curdlanolyticus</italic> strain B-6 and endo-xylanase, while red letters represent conserved short peptides between the catalytic domain enzyme from <italic toggle="yes">P. curdlanolyticus</italic> strain B-6 and &#x003b2;-1,3-1,4-glucanase. Alignment was constructed with the ClustalW program (<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.ebi.ac.uk/jdispatcher/msa/clustalo" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ebi.ac.uk/jdispatcher/msa/clustalo</ext-link>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jmb-35-e2501046-f4" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><title>(A) The predicted 3D structure of <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD enzyme indicating the two amino acids residues (Glu110 and Glu216) at the catalytic site. (B) Amino acid residues (Trp30, His69, Asn109, Glu110, Trp147, His170, Tyr172, and Trp249) within the binding subsites for cellulase activity. (C, D, and E) Amino acid residues on the surface of the binding subsites of the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD enzyme structure that are expected to be important for xylanase, mannanase, and &#x003b2;-1,3-1,4-glucanase activities, respectively.</title><p>The xylotetraose (X4), mannotetraose (M4), and 1,3-1,4-&#x003b2;-glucotetraose (G4) represent sugar ligands for endo-xylanase, endo-mannanase, and endo-&#x003b2;-glucanase, respectively, which interact with <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD at subsites &#x02212;2 to +2. The distances between interacting amino acid residues within these subsites and the ligands are presented by dotted lines. The 3D structure model was built based on the 4U3A reference protein model using SWISS-MODEL (<ext-link xlink:href="https://swissmodel.expasy.org/" ext-link-type="uri">https://swissmodel.expasy.org/</ext-link>). Ligands were obtained from PubChem (<ext-link xlink:href="https://pubchem.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/" ext-link-type="uri">https://pubchem.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/</ext-link>), while ligand-macromolecule interactions were analyzed with PyRx software to predict binding interactions [<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Structural visualization and analysis were performed using PyMOL (<ext-link xlink:href="https://pymol.org/" ext-link-type="uri">https://pymol.org/</ext-link>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jmb-35-e2501046-f5" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><title>SDS-PAGE and cellulase zymogram analysis of purified recombinant proteins.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) purified full-length <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 and (<bold>B</bold>) purified <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD catalytic domain. Lane M, protein marker; lane C, crude enzyme; lane P, purified fulllength <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 (85 kDa) or purified <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD catalytic domain (29 kDa); and lane Pz, zymogram analysis of purified fulllength <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 or purified <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD catalytic domain.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jmb-35-e2501046-f6" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><title>TLC analysis of hydrolysis products released from polysaccharides by purified <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD (CD) and full-length <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 (FL).</title><p>Polysaccharides tested include CMC (<bold>A</bold>), Avicel (<bold>B</bold>), BWX (<bold>C</bold>), OSX (<bold>D</bold>), KGM (<bold>E</bold>), LBG (<bold>F</bold>), and barley &#x003b2;-glucan (<bold>G</bold>). Lane M represents size markers: glucose and cellooligosaccharides (G1&#x02013;G6), xylose and xylooligosaccharides (X1&#x02013;X6), and mannose and manno-oligosaccharides (M1&#x02013;M6). Lane CD<sub>0</sub> or FL<sub>0</sub> represents the control, and lane CD<sub>30</sub> or FL<sub>30</sub> represents the reaction at 30 min. Each polysaccharide (1%, w/v) was incubated with <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD or <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 (1 &#x003bc;M) in sodium acetate buffer (pH 6.0) at 50&#x000b0;C. For inactive enzyme control, <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD or <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 was boiled for 15 min before use.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jmb-35-e2501046-f7" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F8"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><title>TLC profiles of hydrolysis products generated from agricultural residues by purified full-length <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Sugarcane bagasse. (<bold>B</bold>) Coconut meal. Lane t0 represents the control. Lane M represents size markers: glucose and cellooligosaccharides (G1&#x02013;G6), xylose and xylooligosaccharides (X1&#x02013;X6), and mannose and manno-oligosaccharides (M1&#x02013;M6). Lanes 30 min, 1 h, and 5 h represent reactions at the respective time points. Reactions were performed by incubating each substrate (1%, w/v) with 5 &#x003bc;M <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 in sodium acetate buffer (pH 6.0) at 50&#x000b0;C for 30 min, 1 h, and 5 h. For inactive enzyme control, <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 was boiled for 15 min before use.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jmb-35-e2501046-f8" position="float"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Comparison of conserved amino acid residues in the active site including the catalytic site and substrate-binding subsites of endo-cellulase from <italic toggle="yes">T. aurantiacus</italic> [<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] with other characterized GH5 enzymes with different functions from the catalytic domain (<italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD) enzyme of <italic toggle="yes">P. curdlanolyticus</italic> strain B-6 (this work), bifunctional endo-cellulase/endo-xylanase from <italic toggle="yes">C. thermocellum</italic> [<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], bifunctional endo-cellulase/ endo-mannanase from <italic toggle="yes">B. agaradhaerens</italic> [<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], multifunctional endo-cellulase/endo-mannanase/endo-&#x003b2;-glucanase from <italic toggle="yes">C. polysaccharolyticus</italic> [<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], and endo-&#x003b2;-1,3-1,4-glucanase from <italic toggle="yes">P. polymyxa</italic> KF-1 [<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>].</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<graphic xlink:href="jmb-35-e2501046-t1" position="float"/>
</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Summary of molecular dockings of X4, M4, and G4 into each amino acid residue located within the four binding subsites of <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<graphic xlink:href="jmb-35-e2501046-t2" position="float"/>
</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Substrate specificity of purified <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5_CD catalytic domain enzyme and the full-length <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic>GH5 enzyme from <italic toggle="yes">P. curdlanolyticus</italic> strain B-6 toward various substrates.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<graphic xlink:href="jmb-35-e2501046-t3" position="float"/>
</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></floats-group></article>