<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Oecologia</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Oecologia</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Oecologia</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0029-8549</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1432-1939</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer Berlin Heidelberg</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40000493</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11861133</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">5679</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00442-025-05679-3</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Death and diminishment: parasitoid flies (Diptera: Conopidae) reduce foraging efficiency before killing their bumblebee host</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1220-1315</contrib-id><name><surname>Roulston</surname><given-names>T&#x02019;ai H.</given-names></name><address><email>tai.roulston@virginia.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>Anne</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Slatosky</surname><given-names>Amber D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/0153tk833</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.27755.32</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9136 933X</institution-id><institution>Department of Environmental Sciences, </institution><institution>University of Virginia, </institution></institution-wrap>Charlottesville, VA 22908 USA </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Mountain Vista Governor&#x02019;s School, Middletown, VA 22645 USA </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/00hx57361</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.16750.35</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2097 5006</institution-id><institution>Ecology and Evolutionary Biology, </institution><institution>Princeton University, </institution></institution-wrap>Princeton, NJ 08544-2016 USA </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/04gyf1771</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.266093.8</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0668 7243</institution-id><institution>Ophthalmology Department, </institution><institution>University of California-Irvine, </institution></institution-wrap>Irvine, CA 92617 USA </aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn fn-type="com"><p>Communicated by Evan Siemann.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>25</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>25</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>207</volume><issue>2</issue><elocation-id>38</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>3</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Host&#x02013;parasitoid interactions typically result in either a dead parasitoid or a dead host. Understanding the effects of parasitoid success on a host can be estimated primarily as how much an early death curtails host reproduction. When parasitoids attack the nonreproductive caste of social insects, however, the effects are not the reduced reproduction of the host but rather the sum reduction in host contributions to its colony. In addition to the loss of host workdays due to premature death, there is potential for additional cost through reduction in foraging efficiency as the infection develops. To better understand these pre-lethal effects, we allowed conopid parasitoid flies (Conopidae) to infect workers from a colony of the bumblebee <italic>Bombus impatiens</italic> (Apidae) in the lab and then moved the colony to an outdoor location. Bumblebee foragers were monitored using RFID technology and an automated analytical balance positioned between the colony and the outside environment. We found that infected bumblebees foraged similarly to uninfected workers halfway through their fatal infections. Starting at day 6&#x02013;7, however, infected bees took fewer trips per day, which resulted in a significant reduction in resources returned to the colony over the last 3&#x000a0;days of the experiment. Both infected and uninfected bees were likely to remain out of the colony at night after their fourth day foraging, but infected bees started staying out sooner. These pre-lethal effects of a developing parasitoid add to the negative effects of a shortened lifespan on host contribution to its colony.</p></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Parasitism</kwd><kwd>Sublethal effects</kwd><kwd>Conopidae</kwd><kwd>Bombus</kwd><kwd>Behavioral immunity</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Springer-Verlag GmbH Germany, part of Springer Nature 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Parasites vary in their effects on hosts, from mild illness to sterility to death (Abbate et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2015</xref>; Cory <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2017</xref>). Since the detrimental effects of parasites on hosts can range widely, selection on hosts to resist parasites should also range widely, such that hosts do not invest in costly defenses that outstrip the damage they are likely to receive. These trade-offs in host&#x02013;parasite interactions have led to a rich literature on parasite virulence (Day et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2007</xref>; Leggett et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2013</xref>) and the concomitant responses of their hosts (Hosken <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2001</xref>; Schwenke et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2016</xref>), showing complex and often geographically varied patterns of coevolution (Anderson and May <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">1982</xref>; Thompson <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">1994</xref>; Gandon and Michalakis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2002</xref>; Lajeunesse and Forbes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2002</xref>; Laine <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2006</xref>).</p><p id="Par3">Parasitoids are a particular type of parasitic organism whose success typically ends with host death (Jervis and Ferns <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2011</xref>). Their offspring gain entry into the host by various means and feed from host tissues until the host dies. With such a dire tradeoff between success of the parasitoid and death of the host, the evolutionary possibilities should be substantially truncated, hinging primarily on two factors: successful acquisition of the host through behavioral strategies, and successful development of the parasitoid in the presence of the host&#x02019;s physiological or behavioral immune defenses (De Roode and Lef&#x000e8;vre <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2012</xref>). Despite these binary outcomes, selection on the evolution of host defense has various potential nuances (Kraaijeveld and Godfray <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">1997</xref>; Fellowes and Godfray <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2000</xref>; Schmid-Hempel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2022</xref>). If defense is costly and parasitoids are rare, low investment in defense should be selected in most circumstances (Straub et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2015</xref>). In addition, even if parasitoids are common, death by parasitoid may not be particularly costly to the host if other mortality risks are similar, such that lifespan is not greatly reduced, or if a reduction in lifespan does not substantially reduce reproduction. This could happen if a host was post-reproductive or, in the case of social insects, if the host is a nonreproductive member of a social group (Straub et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2015</xref>).</p><p id="Par4">In insects such as ants, termites, and the social bee and wasp species, reproductive individuals spend most or all of their lives within nests, surrounded by nonreproductives that guard the nest and forage for food and nest materials (Bourke <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2007</xref>). Since the fitness of nonreproductives arises through the success of their colony (Gardner and West <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2014</xref>), their behaviors should favor colony survival and growth more than their own survival. In fact, it is common for the nonreproductive castes of social insects to self-sacrifice in defense of the colony from predators or disease (Shorter and Rueppell <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2012</xref>; Cremer et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2018</xref>). An analogous form of sacrifice would be reduced self-preservation behaviors or reduced immune investment if the associated costs to colony functions (e.g., reduced foraging efficiency) were greater than the expected gains through greater longevity. Foraging is an activity with high potential for exposure to many sources of mortality, including parasitoids, and thus foragers typically live much shorter lives than the primary egg laying caste (Heinze and Schrempf <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2008</xref>). If parasitoids can kill hosts without greatly reducing their expected lifespan or their foraging efficiency, then parasitoids may not greatly reduce their hosts&#x02019; contributions to their colony. In this case, hosts would not be under strong selection pressure to alter their behavior or develop immune responses to defend themselves against this single source of risk, especially if there are costs to defense. Estimating the effects of parasitoids on host contributions to colonies, however, is challenging in natural environments.</p><p id="Par5">One of the few well-studied systems involving social insects and their susceptibility to parasitoids is bumblebees (Apidae: <italic>Bombus</italic> spp.) and conopid flies (Conopidae). Bumblebees are social insects in which queens remain in their nest after production of their first brood of workers. Workers tend the brood, defend the nest and forage for resources in the environment. Conopids are a family of obligate parasitoids that utilize other insects for hosts, especially wasps and bees (Smith and Peterson <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">1987</xref>). They are especially abundant in bumblebees, with several conopid genera utilizing different species of bumblebees on several continents and typically killing their hosts 10&#x02013;12&#x000a0;days after infection (Schmid-Hempel and Schmid-Hempel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">1996</xref>; Abdalla et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2014</xref>; Malfi and Roulston <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2014</xref>). Bumblebee infection rates have frequently been found to be over 30% of foragers in the field, with rates as high as 80% recorded (Gillespie <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2010</xref>; Davis et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2015</xref>). The effects of conopids on bumblebee colony reproduction, however, have never been directly measured, though estimates have been made based on simulating their effects through worker removals from active colonies (M&#x000fc;ller and Schmid-Hempel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">1992</xref>) and estimating their effects using a field parameterized model of bumblebee colony reproduction (Malfi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2018</xref>).</p><p id="Par6">Understanding the costs of parasitoids on bumblebee colony reproduction requires not only knowing the cost of an early death but also any pre-lethal effects that the developing infection may impose. Infected bees appear to forage up until the day of their death, even though most of their abdominal cavity is taken up by the developing fly. Thus, any effects of the fly that reduce the host&#x02019;s foraging efficiency should also be considered as impacts on potential colony reproduction. Currently, the only pre-lethal effects known are a tendency for infected bumblebees to (1) remain out of the colony at night, potentially as a behavioral immune response (M&#x000fc;ller and Schmid-Hempel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">1993</xref>); (2) bring back pollen to the colony less frequently (Schmid-Hempel and Schmid-Hempel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">1991</xref>), and (3) bring back different kinds of pollen to the colony (Schmid-Hempel and Stauffer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">1998</xref>).</p><p id="Par7">Here, we describe an experiment that examines how resource collection efficiency of infected bumblebees changes over the course of a conopid infection. We do this by allowing bumblebees to forage in an open environment following controlled lab infections by conopids and monitoring the resources returned to the colony through the use of RFID technology and the continual recording of individual bee weights as they go out to forage and return with resources.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Study site</title><p id="Par8">All field work was carried out at Blandy Experimental Farm (Virginia, United States of America, 39.06&#x000b0; N 78.06&#x000b0; W), an ecological field station of the University of Virginia. The 290 hectare property is composed of young fields with herbaceous perennials, isolated forest fragments, and a 72 hectare public garden.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Study organisms</title><p id="Par9">This study was carried out in early to mid-July, 2021 using a single commercial colony of the common eastern bumblebee, <italic>Bombus impatiens</italic> Cresson 1863, purchased from Koppert Biological Systems (Howell, Michigan). Upon their arrival, the bumblebee colony was placed in a large (15&#x000a0;m&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;11&#x000a0;m), parasitoid-free screenhouse with flowering plants so that workers could gain foraging experience. All bees that foraged in the screenhouse over a 7-day period were captured and marked individually using RFID tags (Microsensys, GmbH, Erfurt, Germany (Microsensys, GmbH, Erfurt, Germany, type: mic3<sup>&#x000ae;</sup>-TAG 16&#x000a0;k, System: iID<sup>&#x000ae;</sup>-2000-G, ISO15693, size: 1.6&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;1.9&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;0.5 mm<sup>3</sup>, Carrier Frequency: 13.56&#x000a0;MHz) and numbered tags (Betterbee<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> queen tags) following cold-induced sedation. They were then returned to the colony and the colony placed in the lab for several days prior to exposure to parasitoids. The colony contained&#x02009;~&#x02009;100 workers at deployment. Conopid flies were captured from the wild at Blandy Experimental Farm in Boyce, Virginia, a mountain meadow near Capon Bridge, West Virginia and a warm season grass meadow near Sperryville, Virginia. All flies were brought to the lab on ice and placed into a foraging arena the same day. Despite the prevalence of conopid infections in bumblebees in the region (Malfi and Roulston <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2014</xref>), female conopids can be difficult to find. In total, 9 female conopids were caught in ca. 15 person hours of searching. All but one was of the species <italic>Physocephala tibialis</italic> (Say, 1829) with one individual of <italic>P. marginata</italic> (Say, 1823).</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Lab infection protocol</title><p id="Par10">Conopids were placed together into a 1.3&#x000a0;m&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;1&#x000a0;m&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;0.7&#x000a0;m foraging arena stocked with cut flowers from fields adjacent the field station. The chamber was well lit with a 4000&#x000a0;lm LED overhead panel (Lithonia Lighting model CPANL 2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;4), a string of 120 LED lights (1200&#x000a0;lm total) and 4 additional 120&#x000a0;V flood lights (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Flowers served as feeding resources both for bees and conopid flies. Multiple female conopids (4&#x02013;5 at a time) were placed together because preliminary trials in 2020 revealed both a lack of aggression between female conopids housed in a common environment and great variation in their individual propensity to attack bees in the artificial arena. Keeping them together thus maximized the efficiency of getting multiple bumblebees attacked in a short period of time.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Foraging arena. Five bumblebees and 4&#x02013;5 female conopid flies were in the arena at once. Conopids typically perched on plants surveying the arena. After warming up, bumblebees flew in the arena visiting flowers</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="442_2025_5679_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p id="Par11">Sixty bumblebee foragers were randomly assigned to a conopid exposure treatment, either placed in a foraging environment with conopid flies or being separated from the colony and held in vials for a similar amount of time. During exposure trials, bumblebees were placed into the conopid attack arena in groups of five and monitored for attacks. Since we were unable to determine which attacks were successful, we allowed individuals to get attacked up to four times. In some cases, an individual conopid attacked the same bee in short succession as if its first attempt had been unsuccessful. No attempt was made to distinguish individual conopids, but we tracked the total number of attacks experienced by each bee. Each group of five bees was left in the foraging arena for approximately 1&#x000a0;h, when attack activity had greatly diminished. At that point, the first group was removed (even if some individuals had not been attacked) and another group was placed into the arena. All exposed and unexposed bees were returned to the colony after the attack trials. A total of six trials were carried out over 2&#x000a0;days (i.e., 30 bees were in the lab exposure group and 30 in the lab unexposed group).</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Tracking foraging efficiency in the field</title><p id="Par12">The bumblebee colony was moved to the field on July 12, 2021, the 4th day after the first groups of bees were exposed to conopids in the lab and the 3rd day after the last groups of bees were exposed. The delay in deployment was designed to allow the conopid eggs to hatch, estimated at 2&#x000a0;days (Schmid-Hempel and Schmid-Hempel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">1996</xref>), and allow the larvae to begin consuming the host. Keeping the bees in the lab during the initial days, rather than deploying them longer, reduced the likelihood of bees dying in the field of other causes prior to the conopids reaching a later developmental stage. Since we could not recognize a conopid infection prior to examining the bumblebee after it had died, we had to successfully retrieve bees at the end of the foraging period to assess their parasitoid status during the experiment.</p><p id="Par13">The colony was placed in a wooden shed in a hedgerow beside an early successional field. Upon exiting the hive box, the bees were forced to pass through an RFID reader onto an analytical balance (Sartorius Entris 64-1S), out through a second RFID reader and then outside to forage. On the surface of the analytical balance was a covered maze that slowed the passage of the bees so that the weight on the scale could stabilize (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). The maze was 3-D printed (Creality Ender 3, Shenzhen Creality 3D Technology Co., Ltd, Shenzhen, China) and covered with transparent film (0.18&#x000a0;cm thick Hygloss<sup>&#x02122;</sup> Acetate Sheets&#x02014;Hygloss Products, Inc., Wallington, NJ). It slowed bees enough for the scale to stabilize but not so much that the bees became confused and failed to cross. Scale readings were continuously fed to a computer (~&#x02009;5 readings per second) and stored with a timestamp. Following the experiment, all scale readings were read into a computer program written in R (R Development Core Team <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2021</xref>) that would detect weight shifts consistent with a bee entering or exiting the scale and determine whether the scale had stabilized based on the standard deviation of 3 consecutive scale weights between stepping on and stepping off behavior. This yielded a file of useable time-stamped scale shifts. To assess a bee foraging trip, a stable weight had to be recorded for both leaving and entering the colony. Timestamps on the RFID data were matched to the scale data to identify each bee. In addition, a motion-activated camera (Logitech C910 webcam) was placed over the scale and recorded time-stamped videos each time a bee passed. The use of the camera often allowed resolution of the weight of an individual bee even if two bees were on the scale at the same time. It also usually showed the bee&#x02019;s physical tag to further confirm its identity. A bee&#x02019;s weight was estimated as the stable weight of the bee on the scale minus the stable weight of the scale before the bee got on the scale (this allowed for weight estimates if a second bee was sitting on the scale already). Since bees do not always carry the same amount of food in their crop when they exit the colony, we always estimated the resources returned during a foraging trip as the weight of the bee when it returned minus the weight when it left.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Image (<bold>A</bold>) and schematic (<bold>B</bold>) of analytical balance showing pathway of bees from the colony to the field. Bees leave colony (d) via exit tube (e), pass through one RFID reader (a), navigate a maze (b) resting on the analytical balance, pass through a second RFID reader (a), enter a second exit tube (e), then depart into the outside environment (f). The maze allowed the balance to stabilize while the bee was on it. Small gaps (g) were necessary to ensure free movement of the scale surface. A motion-activated camera took short video clips of each bee on the maze, and the balance fed time-stamped weight data continuously to a computer</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="442_2025_5679_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p><p id="Par14">After 5&#x000a0;days of foraging, the colony was provided with pollen and an artificial nectar supply and the colony door was set so that bees could return but not exit. This was done in late afternoon because bumblebees with several days foraging experience commonly exit the colony late in the day and spend the night in the field, returning the next day. Thus, there is never a time in which all bees are naturally in the colony. Although some bees did return through the &#x02018;in-only&#x02019; door, many were deterred by the change in the doorway and had to be manually captured and returned to the colony. Bees that could not be manually captured immediately typically returned to the field and had to be pursued at the colony entrance later that day or the next day.</p><p id="Par15">All experimental bees that were recaptured at the end of the foraging time were separated from their colony and placed in an empty bumblebee colony box in the lab with 50% sugar water ad libitum. For the next 2&#x000a0;weeks, this box was checked daily and dead bees were removed and examined repeatedly for the presence of a large conopid by prying open the rear abdominal opening. At the time that a conopid kills a bumblebee, it typically occupies nearly the entire abdominal cavity and positions itself such that its paired spiracles are against the abdominal opening, making it easy to recognize advanced conopid infections. We did not do complete dissections to examine for small conopid larvae, as our interest was in the effects of later stage conopid infections at the time of foraging. Based on the number of days post-foraging that the bee died, we could distinguish between conopid infections originating from our exposure treatment and those originating in the field. Bees that died in the lab within 12&#x000a0;days of their exposure to conopids in the lab and contained a mature conopid larva were considered to have been infected during lab exposure. Bees that died in the lab with mature conopid larvae in their abdomen 14&#x02013;20&#x000a0;days after the lab exposure period (including bees that were not exposed to conopids in the lab) were considered to have been infected in the field during foraging. In those cases, conopids would have been in an early stage of development while the bee was foraging, given a 2-day latency period for conopid eggs and a total foraging duration of 5&#x000a0;days. One bee exposed in the lab but not observed to be attacked died with a mature conopid larva in its abdomen 10&#x000a0;days after its lab exposure. This was inferred to have been an unobserved lab attack because the development time for the conopid would have been too short (7&#x000a0;days) if the attack had occurred during the first day of field exposure.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Statistics</title><p id="Par16">All statistical tests were done in R (R Development Core Team <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2021</xref>). To test for differences between parasitized and unparasitized bees in the likelihood of staying out at night, we ran a Kruskal test using the total number of times (maximum possible&#x02009;=&#x02009;4) that each bee stayed out at night as the dependent variable. For the effects of parasitism on the number of foraging trips per day and the duration of each foraging trip, we built statistical models with individual bee as a repeated measure, foraging trips per day and foraging trip duration as dependent variables, and day of experiment and parasitism status (and their interaction) as factors using the package lme4 (Bates et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2015</xref>). To test the effect of parasitism on resources returned to the colony per foraging trip, we ran a similar test using proportional body weight increase between leaving and entering the colony as the dependent variable but also included whether the trip was completed after spending the night out of the colony as a factor in the model. Only trips with positive resource return (93% of trips) were included in this estimate to reduce the effect of defecation trips and colony cleaning trips on the resource return estimate. To test whether colony departure time for the first trip of the day was different between parasitized and unparasitized bees, we ran a similar model as the others using departure time of first trip as the dependent variable and also included whether the trip followed an overnight trip. In all repeated measures analyses, if the model residuals did not appear normal, we transformed the dependent variable. Since the parasite grows substantially each day in the bee gut, we expected that any effects on bee behavior would increase over time and thus the interaction in the statistical models would be most sensitive to detecting the effects of the parasite on response variables. Experiment day was considered an ordered categorical variable in the statistical models but nearly all results were qualitatively identical if day was considered a numerical value. Significance was assessed using the package car (Fox and Weisberg <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2019</xref>) through analysis of variance using type III sum of squares. If we found a significant interaction, then we examined the relationship with an interaction plot to show where the apparent effect of the growing parasite became detectible, which was just after day 2 for both trips per day and resources per trip, and just after day 1 for trip duration. We then compared the daily rates for all three variables from the day following the statistical interaction until the end of the experiment for differences between parasitized and unparasitized bees. To look at the cumulative effects of the parasite on total resources returned from the onset of the interaction until the end of the experiment, we estimated the total resources collected per bee between days 3 and 5. We did not have resource estimates for all trips taken during this time period because of a failure of the scale to stabilize in some cases. To account for this problem, we calculated a resource return rate per trip per day for each bee based on the trips that were quantified, and multiplied that estimate by the actual number of trips taken that day. We tested the significance of parasitism on total resources returned (standardized by exit body weight) with a one-way analysis of variance, with cumulative resources returned per bee as the dependent variable and parasitism status as the factor.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Results</title><p id="Par17">Of the 30 bees exposed to conopids in the lab, 21 bees were observed to be attacked 1&#x02013;4 times in the lab. The bee attacked 4 times died shortly after the last attack, but the others quickly resumed flying activity in the flight cage and appeared healthy upon reintroduction to the colony. Following 5&#x000a0;days of foraging, 34 of the 60 tagged bees were retrieved from the colony, while the others were presumed to have died in the field while foraging. Only 12 of the 30 lab-exposed bees were recovered, whereas 22 of the 30 lab unexposed bees were recovered from the field. Of the 12 lab-exposed bees that were recovered, 6 of them died of a conopid infection 10&#x02013;12&#x000a0;days after lab exposure and were considered to have been infected in the lab. No other bees exposed in the lab died of a conopid infection after foraging. Of the 22 bees that were recovered from the unexposed lab group, 5 died of conopid infections picked up in the field, 12&#x02013;18&#x000a0;days after being allowed to forage. These 5 bees were excluded from subsequent analyses comparing infected and uninfected bees given that they would have younger infections in various stages of development during field observations. Finally, the dataset was further reduced by limiting analyses only to bees that foraged for all 5&#x000a0;days of the field experiment. This was done to guarantee similarity of field conditions among foragers (weather, floral availability, etc.) on all the days in which they were being compared. This produced a core dataset for 21 bees, 6 that had been lab infected and 15 that had not been lab infected and did not acquire an infection in the field.</p><p id="Par18">A total of 718 foraging trips were recorded over the 5-day period for these 21 bees and formed the dataset for trip frequency. Of these, 402 trips were able to be fully scored for bee exit and enter weights and formed the core dataset for resource return. The primary loss of scale data was due to a failure of the scale to stabilize, which occurred when several bees crossed the scale at once or when debris bridged the gap between the exit tube and the scale balance mechanism and had to be removed.</p><p id="Par19">The total number of trips taken ranged from 29 to 49 trips per bee. Over the 5-day period, unparasitized bees took a total of 35.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.0 (mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;SE) trips compared to 30.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.16 trips for parasitized bees (<italic>F</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.577, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.224, 1-way ANOVA). Trips per bee per day varied significantly across the days of the experiment and there was a significant interaction between foraging day and parasitism status (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>A), with parasitized bees appearing to take fewer trips from days 3 to 5 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>A). An interaction plot showed the change in effect starting on day 3. Looking at foraging trips on just those last 3&#x000a0;days, parasitized bees took significantly fewer trips per day (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.009). The amount of resources bees returned to the colony, measured as a proportional increase in their body weight, also varied across foraging days and with an interaction of foraging day and parasitism status (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>B) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>B). An interaction plot showed this shift in effect starting at day 3. Although this pattern was in a similar trend to that of trips per day, parasitized bees did not carry significantly fewer resources per trip than unparasitized bees over these last 3&#x000a0;days (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.087). Combining the number of trips per day with the quantity of resources per trip, parasitized bees returned&#x02009;~&#x02009;50% fewer total resources than unparasitized bees over the last 3&#x000a0;days of the experiment (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.026, Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). The amount of food returned to the colony was not influenced by whether the bee stayed out overnight before the trip. Duration of foraging trips per bee varied over time and with an interaction between time and parasitism status (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>C). An interaction plot showed a shift in effects starting on day 2. Once again, the general pattern of mean values for trip duration was similar to other tests, with parasitized bees on average taking more time than unparasitized bees toward the end of the experiment (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>C). The trip duration per day for parasitized bees from day 2 to 5 was only marginally longer than for unparasitized bees (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.054). Bees infected by conopid flies spent more nights away from the colony than uninfected bees (median of 3.5 versus 1 for infected versus uninfected bees, Wilcoxon rank sum test with continuity correction, <italic>W</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;8, <italic>p</italic> value&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.003). Half the infected bees stayed out of the colony the first night and all stayed out by the last night. Only one of the 15 unparasitized bees stayed out of the colony the first night, but over half did so by day 4 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). Bees that spent the night outside the colony left the colony the next day for their first trip about an hour later than bees that spent the night inside the colony (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>D) but this was not influenced by parasitism status.
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Comparison of parasitized and unparasitized bees across four metrics of foraging over time</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left"><italic>F</italic></th><th align="left">Df</th><th align="left"><italic>P</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">A) Trips per day</td><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;(Intercept)</td><td char="." align="char">314.453</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td char="." align="char">2.803e-13***</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Parasitized</td><td char="." align="char">1.577</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td char="." align="char">0.224</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Day</td><td char="." align="char">4.660</td><td char="." align="char">4</td><td char="." align="char">0.002**</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Parasitized*day</td><td char="." align="char">6.911</td><td char="." align="char">4</td><td char="." align="char">8.452e-05***</td></tr><tr><td align="left">B) Resources returned</td><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;(Intercept)</td><td char="." align="char">117.039</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td char="." align="char">5.6e-13***</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Parasitized</td><td char="." align="char">0.001</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td char="." align="char">0.977</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Day</td><td char="." align="char">41.079</td><td char="." align="char">4</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;2.2e-16***</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Overnight</td><td char="." align="char">0.099</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td char="." align="char">0.754</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Parasitized*day</td><td char="." align="char">4.761</td><td char="." align="char">4</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001***</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Parasitized*overnight</td><td char="." align="char">0.605</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td char="." align="char">0.437</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C) Trip duration</td><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;(Intercept)</td><td char="." align="char">6859.846</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;2.2e-16***</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Parasitized</td><td char="." align="char">1.023</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td char="." align="char">0.325</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Day</td><td char="." align="char">12.419</td><td char="." align="char">4</td><td char="." align="char">9.831e-08***</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Parasitized*day</td><td char="." align="char">3.719</td><td char="." align="char">4</td><td char="." align="char">0.008**</td></tr><tr><td align="left">D) Time departing the colony for first trip each day</td><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">(Intercept)</td><td char="." align="char">2706.773</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;2.2e-16***</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Parasitized</td><td char="." align="char"> 0.0116</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td char="." align="char">0.916</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Day</td><td char="." align="char">5.9760</td><td char="." align="char">3</td><td char="." align="char">0.001**</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;After Overnight</td><td char="." align="char"> 15.8635</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001***</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Parasitized*day</td><td char="." align="char">4.3436</td><td char="." align="char">3</td><td char="." align="char">0.008**</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Parasitized*after Overnight</td><td char="." align="char">0.0362</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td char="." align="char">0.849</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*p&#x0003c;0.05, **p&#x0003c;0.01, ***p&#x0003c;0.001</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Change in foraging parameters per day for parasitized and unparasitized bees (mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;SD). <bold>A</bold> Number of foraging trips per day. <bold>B</bold> Amount of resources returned to the colony by individual bees on each trip. Resource return measured as the proportional increase in body weight of a returning forager compared to its weight as a departing forager. <bold>C</bold> Foraging trip duration (minutes) by bumblebee workers</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="442_2025_5679_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig><fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Cumulative resources returned over the last 3&#x000a0;days of the experiment. Resources standardized for body size as the proportional increase in return body mass over body mass during exit</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="442_2025_5679_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig><fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;5</label><caption><p>Proportion of bees staying out of the colony at night after each foraging day</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="442_2025_5679_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par20">Infected bees showed diminished foraging performance by the third day of the experiment. The primary effect was taking fewer trips per day, but there were also non-significant trends toward carrying less food per trip, and taking more time per trip. This pattern continued to the end of the experiment at foraging day 5, which represented either the 8th or 9th day since they were infected in the lab. These represented advanced infections given that the bees died of their infections 2&#x02013;3&#x000a0;days after being returned to the lab with their entire abdominal cavity occupied by the parasite. Previous work (Malfi and Roulston <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2014</xref>) found that foraging bumblebees are sometimes caught with late stage conopid infections that were within hours of killing the bee, and thus the bees often work for the colony until close to the end of their life. But here we show their escalating deduction in foraging efficiency as the parasite develops, an effect that probably extends the additional 2&#x02013;3&#x000a0;days to bee death. Prior work has shown that bumblebees parasitized with a conopid choose different host plants to visit (Schmid-Hempel and Schmid-Hempel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">1990</xref>; Schmid-Hempel and Stauffer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">1998</xref>) and are less likely to carry pollen than unparasitized bumblebees (Schmid-Hempel and Schmid-Hempel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">1991</xref>). Thus, these pre-lethal effects on bumblebee foraging magnify any colony-level effects attributable to the shorter lifespans of parasitized bumblebee workers (M&#x000fc;ller and Schmid-Hempel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">1992</xref>; Gillespie <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2010</xref>; Malfi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2018</xref>).</p><p id="Par21">Despite the significant change in parasitized bee behavior by foraging day 3 (day 6&#x02013;7 following infection), it is notable that foraging efficiency was not reduced earlier. The change in foraging efficiency is likely attributable to an increasing drain on bee physiological resources as the parasite grows. For the European conopid species <italic>Physocephala rufipes</italic>, the egg stage lasts about 2&#x000a0;days (Schmid-Hempel and Schmid-Hempel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">1996</xref>), a time in which the main impact on the host would likely be any trauma directly related to oviposition. During the first two larval stages, occurring over the next&#x02009;~&#x02009;7&#x000a0;days, the larva remains relatively small and feeds primarily on hemolymph (Abdalla et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2014</xref>). During the 3rd larval instar, however, the fly larva feeds on internal organ tissue, eventually killing the bee prior to pupating (Schmid-Hempel and Schmid-Hempel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">1996</xref>). It is not surprising that the bee becomes a poorer forager at a time in which its internal organs are being consumed by a parasitoid. It is, perhaps, more surprising that it forages as reliably as it does just prior to death.</p><p id="Par22">Our data confirm the tendency of bees infected by conopids to stay out of the colony at night as described in Europe (M&#x000fc;ller and Schmid-Hempel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">1993</xref>). In their experiments, M&#x000fc;ller &#x00026; Schmid-Hempel (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">1993</xref>) dissected foragers found in the colony at night and those returning to the colony after a night out and found that the returning ones were much more likely to be parasitized. In a lab experiment, they also showed that parasitized workers lived longer and suppressed parasitoid growth more if subjected to a constant cool lab temperature (19&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C), reflecting outdoor night temperature, than in constant warm temperatures (28&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C), reflecting the temperature of a bumblebee nest. This supports their hypothesis that overnighting behavior is an adaptive mechanism to prolong worker longevity by suppressing a parasitoid infection. In their dataset, bee age was a minor contributor to overnighting behavior. In our dataset, over half of infected bees stayed out by day 2 and over half of uninfected bees stayed out by day 4. This shows that bees initiate overnighting behavior quickly, and that there is a strong effect of experience on overnighting behavior independent of conopid infection. In our dataset, we did not dissect bees to look for immature parasites and cannot say definitively that bees staying out that did not die of conopid infections did not actually have small, failed infections. Prior work with <italic>Bombus impatiens</italic>, however, that did include dissections, found that conopid infections typically succeed in the lab with this species (Davis et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2015</xref>) and that uninfected workers as scored by dissection often spent nights in the field (unpublished data from Malfi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2018</xref>). Thus, there is likely to be at least one as yet undiscovered strong driver of overnighting behavior in addition to conopids, such as other parasites, experience, age, or colony conditions.</p><p id="Par23">While parasitizing bees in the lab proved effective, and was helpful for examining insect behavior relative to a known time of infection, it was also labor intensive for generating replication. The main challenge was collecting sufficient numbers of conopids in the field in a short period of time and having them attack bees in the lab. Despite conopid infections of bumblebees being common in the study region at the time of the study, we seldom readily find many adult female conopids in the field. Lab rearing of conopids could potentially make additional studies easier to carry out. One setback we did not expect was the relatively low return of lab infected foragers at the end of the study. Only 40% of our lab-exposed bees were captured at the end of the experiment, with the missing presumably dying in the field during foraging. In contrast, 74% of non-lab-exposed bees survived over those 5&#x000a0;days. Given that the conopid does not pupate during the time that was available, such loss could be due to trauma of the original attack or to behavioral changes in the field caused by the growing conopid. Neither of these causes is known for conopid effects on bees and could represent additional stresses on bumblebee colony productivity. If mortality due to the physical damage from a conopid attack (or from a subsequent microbial infection) is frequent in the wild, then it would likely represent an even larger effect on bumblebee colonies than the effects recorded here. We hesitate to estimate that effect from our data because we often had multiple attacks on the same bee in short succession, something that may be less likely to occur in the wild. In our trials, we noted that the bee that was attacked the most (4 times) died in the lab shortly after. Bumblebee workers are sometimes found with multiple conopid larvae in the field (Schmid-Hempel and Schmid-Hempel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">1996</xref>), so we do know that multiple attacks occur, but we do not know how they impact host health independent of the larval parasite. It is likely that this kind of estimate can only be made with additional lab studies.</p><p id="Par24">Overall, we show that measurable reductions on bumblebee productivity are evident about halfway through the period of conopid infection, which may magnify their negative impacts on colony productivity. While infected bumblebees did remain outside the colony shortly after infection, as they do in Europe (M&#x000fc;ller and Schmid-Hempel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">1993</xref>), it was not evident that doing so reduced the trajectory of the infection. Infected bees still died in the 10&#x02013;12-day period estimated for other species in this system (Schmid-Hempel and Schmid-Hempel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">1996</xref>). Prior work has shown that bumblebee species differ in their physiological defenses against conopids (Davis et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2015</xref>). The use of behavioral defenses, such as the use of nighttime cold to suppress an infection, could also vary between species of host and species of parasitoid. The potential use of lab-based infections in this study system, as demonstrated here for the first time, allows future manipulative work to examine host&#x02013;parasitoid interactions in great detail.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Mia Murray for her assistance with catching conopids and tagging bees in the lab. We thank the University of Virginia&#x02019;s Blandy Experimental Farm for access to equipment and resources.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contribution statement</title><p>THR and AML conceived, designed and carried out the experiment and drafted the manuscript; THR and ADS conceived and designed the experimental equipment; THR carried out analyses; all the authors provided editorial assistance and contributed illustrations.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>Not applicable.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>The datasets used and/or analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request and will be published in Figshare upon publication.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Code availability</title><p>All code is available upon request from the corresponding author.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p id="Par25">None of the authors has conflicts of interest with any aspect of the research carried out.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Ethical approval</title><p id="Par26">Ethics approval was not required for this study according to local legislation (U.S. National Institutes of Health Office of Laboratory Animal Welfare).</p></notes><notes id="FPar3"><title>Consent to participate</title><p id="Par27">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar4"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par28">Not applicable.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abbate</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Kada</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lion</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Beyond mortality: sterility as a neglected component of parasite virulence</article-title><source>PLoS Pathog</source><year>2015</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1005229</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26632822</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Abbate JL, Kada S, Lion S (2015) Beyond mortality: sterility as a neglected component of parasite virulence. PLoS Pathog. 10.1371/journal.ppat.1005229<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26632822</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abdalla</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name><name><surname>Sampaio</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Pedrosa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Larval development of <italic>Physocephala</italic> (Diptera, Conopidae) in the bumble bee <italic>Bombus morio</italic> (Hymenoptera, Apidae)</article-title><source>Rev Bras Entomol</source><year>2014</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>343</fpage><lpage>348</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0085-56262014000400003</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Abdalla FC, Sampaio G, Pedrosa M et al (2014) Larval development of <italic>Physocephala</italic> (Diptera, Conopidae) in the bumble bee <italic>Bombus morio</italic> (Hymenoptera, Apidae). Rev Bras Entomol 58:343&#x02013;348. 10.1590/S0085-56262014000400003</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>May</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coevolution of hosts and parasites</article-title><source>Parasitology</source><year>1982</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>411</fpage><lpage>426</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0031182000055360</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6755367</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Anderson RM, May RM (1982) Coevolution of hosts and parasites. Parasitology 85:411&#x02013;426<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6755367</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000e4;chler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bolker</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fitting linear mixed-effects models using lme4</article-title><source>J Stat Softw</source><year>2015</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>48</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18637/jss.v067.i01</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Bates D, M&#x000e4;chler M, Bolker B, Walker S (2015) Fitting linear mixed-effects models using lme4. J Stat Softw 67:1&#x02013;48. 10.18637/jss.v067.i01</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bourke</surname><given-names>AFG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Kin selection and the evolutionary theory of aging</article-title><source>Annu Rev Ecol Evol Syst</source><year>2007</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>103</fpage><lpage>128</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.ecolsys.38.091206.095528</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Bourke AFG (2007) Kin selection and the evolutionary theory of aging. Annu Rev Ecol Evol Syst 38:103&#x02013;128</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cory</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolution of host resistance to insect pathogens</article-title><source>Curr Opin Insect Sci</source><year>2017</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>54</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cois.2017.04.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28822489</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Cory JS (2017) Evolution of host resistance to insect pathogens. Curr Opin Insect Sci 21:54&#x02013;59<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28822489</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cremer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pull</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Furst</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Social immunity: emergence and evolution of colony-level disease protection</article-title><source>Annu Rev Entomol</source><year>2018</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>105</fpage><lpage>123</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-ento-020117-043110</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28945976</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Cremer S, Pull CD, Furst MA (2018) Social immunity: emergence and evolution of colony-level disease protection. Annu Rev Entomol 63:105&#x02013;123<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28945976</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Malfi</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Roulston</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Species differences in bumblebee immune response predict developmental success of a parasitoid fly</article-title><source>Oecologia</source><year>2015</year><volume>178</volume><fpage>1017</fpage><lpage>1032</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00442-015-3292-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25795253</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Davis SE, Malfi RL, Roulston TH (2015) Species differences in bumblebee immune response predict developmental success of a parasitoid fly. Oecologia 178:1017&#x02013;1032. 10.1007/s00442-015-3292-8<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25795253</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Read</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolution of parasite virulence when host responses cause disease</article-title><source>Proc R Soc b: Biol Sci</source><year>2007</year><volume>274</volume><fpage>2685</fpage><lpage>2692</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rspb.2007.0809</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Day T, Graham AL, Read AF (2007) Evolution of parasite virulence when host responses cause disease. Proc R Soc b: Biol Sci 274:2685&#x02013;2692. 10.1098/rspb.2007.0809</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Roode</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lef&#x000e8;vre</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Behavioral immunity in insects</article-title><source>Insects</source><year>2012</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>789</fpage><lpage>820</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/insects3030789</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26466629</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">De Roode JC, Lef&#x000e8;vre T (2012) Behavioral immunity in insects. Insects 3:789&#x02013;820. 10.3390/insects3030789<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26466629</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fellowes</surname><given-names>MDE</given-names></name><name><surname>Godfray</surname><given-names>HCJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The evolutionary ecology of resistance to parasitoids by <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>Heredity (Edinb)</source><year>2000</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2540.2000.00685.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10692005</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Fellowes MDE, Godfray HCJ (2000) The evolutionary ecology of resistance to parasitoids by <italic>Drosophila</italic>. Heredity (Edinb) 84:1&#x02013;8<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10692005</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Weisberg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><source>An R companion to applied regression</source><year>2019</year><edition>3</edition><publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="book">Fox J, Weisberg S (2019) An R companion to applied regression, 3rd edn. Sage, Thousand Oaks</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gandon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Michalakis</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Local adaptation, evolutionary potential and host-parasite coevolution: interactions between migration, mutation, population size and generation time</article-title><source>J Evol Biol</source><year>2002</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>451</fpage><lpage>462</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1420-9101.2002.00402.x</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Gandon S, Michalakis Y (2002) Local adaptation, evolutionary potential and host-parasite coevolution: interactions between migration, mutation, population size and generation time. J Evol Biol 15:451&#x02013;462. 10.1046/j.1420-9101.2002.00402.x</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>West</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inclusive fitness: 50 years on</article-title><source>Philos Trans R Soc b: Biol Sci</source><year>2014</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.2013.0356</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Gardner A, West SA (2014) Inclusive fitness: 50 years on. Philos Trans R Soc b: Biol Sci. 10.1098/rstb.2013.0356</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gillespie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Factors affecting parasite prevalence among wild bumblebees</article-title><source>Ecol Entomol</source><year>2010</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>737</fpage><lpage>747</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2311.2010.01234.x</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Gillespie S (2010) Factors affecting parasite prevalence among wild bumblebees. Ecol Entomol 35:737&#x02013;747. 10.1111/j.1365-2311.2010.01234.x</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heinze</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Schrempf</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aging and reproduction in social insects: a mini-review</article-title><source>Gerontology</source><year>2008</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>160</fpage><lpage>167</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000122472</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18367827</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Heinze J, Schrempf A (2008) Aging and reproduction in social insects: a mini-review. Gerontology 54:160&#x02013;167. 10.1159/000122472<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18367827</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hosken</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sex and death: microevolutionary trade-offs between reproductive and immune investment in dung flies</article-title><source>Curr Biol</source><year>2001</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>379</fpage><lpage>380</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0960-9822(01)00211-1</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Hosken DJ (2001) Sex and death: microevolutionary trade-offs between reproductive and immune investment in dung flies. Curr Biol 11:379&#x02013;380</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jervis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferns</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Towards a general perspective on life-history evolution and diversification in parasitoid wasps</article-title><source>Biol J Lin Soc</source><year>2011</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>443</fpage><lpage>461</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1095-8312.2011.01719.x</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Jervis M, Ferns P (2011) Towards a general perspective on life-history evolution and diversification in parasitoid wasps. Biol J Lin Soc 104:443&#x02013;461</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kraaijeveld</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Godfray</surname><given-names>HCJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trade-off between parasitoid resistance and larval competitive ability in <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic></article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1997</year><volume>389</volume><fpage>278</fpage><lpage>280</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/38483</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9305840</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Kraaijeveld AR, Godfray HCJ (1997) Trade-off between parasitoid resistance and larval competitive ability in <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic>. Nature 389:278&#x02013;280<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9305840</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laine</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolution of host resistance: looking for coevolutionary hotspots at small spatial scales</article-title><source>Proc R Soc b: Biol Sci</source><year>2006</year><volume>273</volume><fpage>267</fpage><lpage>273</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rspb.2005.3303</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">Laine AL (2006) Evolution of host resistance: looking for coevolutionary hotspots at small spatial scales. Proc R Soc b: Biol Sci 273:267&#x02013;273. 10.1098/rspb.2005.3303</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lajeunesse</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Forbes</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Host range and local parasite adaptation</article-title><source>Proc R Soc b: Biol Sci</source><year>2002</year><volume>269</volume><fpage>703</fpage><lpage>710</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rspb.2001.1943</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Lajeunesse MJ, Forbes MR (2002) Host range and local parasite adaptation. Proc R Soc b: Biol Sci 269:703&#x02013;710. 10.1098/rspb.2001.1943</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leggett</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Buckling</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Boots</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Generalism and the evolution of parasite virulence</article-title><source>Trends Ecol Evol</source><year>2013</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>592</fpage><lpage>596</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tree.2013.07.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23968968</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">Leggett HC, Buckling A, Long GH, Boots M (2013) Generalism and the evolution of parasite virulence. Trends Ecol Evol 28:592&#x02013;596<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23968968</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Malfi</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Roulston</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Patterns of parasite infection in bumble bees (<italic>Bombus</italic> spp.) of Northern Virginia</article-title><source>Ecol Entomol</source><year>2014</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/een.12069</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Malfi RL, Roulston TH (2014) Patterns of parasite infection in bumble bees (<italic>Bombus</italic> spp.) of Northern Virginia. Ecol Entomol 39:17&#x02013;29. 10.1111/een.12069</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Malfi</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Roulston</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The influence of conopid flies on bumble bee colony productivity under different food resource conditions</article-title><source>Ecol Monogr</source><year>2018</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>653</fpage><lpage>671</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ecm.1327</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">Malfi RL, Walter JA, Roulston TH et al (2018) The influence of conopid flies on bumble bee colony productivity under different food resource conditions. Ecol Monogr 88:653&#x02013;671. 10.1002/ecm.1327</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>M&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid-Hempel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Variation in life-history pattern in relation to worker mortality in the bumble-bee, <italic>Bombus lucorum</italic></article-title><source>Funct Ecol</source><year>1992</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>48</fpage><lpage>56</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2389770</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="journal">M&#x000fc;ller CB, Schmid-Hempel P (1992) Variation in life-history pattern in relation to worker mortality in the bumble-bee, <italic>Bombus lucorum</italic>. Funct Ecol 6:48&#x02013;56</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR26"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR26" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>M&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid-Hempel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exploitation of cold temperature as defense against parasitoids in bumblebees</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1993</year><volume>363</volume><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>67</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/363065a0</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26" publication-type="journal">M&#x000fc;ller CB, Schmid-Hempel P (1993) Exploitation of cold temperature as defense against parasitoids in bumblebees. Nature 363:65&#x02013;67</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR27"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">R Development Core Team (2021) R Software. R: a language and environment for statistical computing</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR28" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmid-Hempel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Function and mechanisms in defense strategies</article-title><source>Curr Opin Insect Sci</source><year>2022</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cois.2021.10.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34757237</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28" publication-type="journal">Schmid-Hempel P (2022) Function and mechanisms in defense strategies. Curr Opin Insect Sci 49:31&#x02013;36<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34757237</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR29"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR29" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmid-Hempel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid-Hempel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Endoparasitic larvae of conopid flies alter pollination behavior of bumblebees</article-title><source>Naturwissenschaften</source><year>1990</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>450</fpage><lpage>452</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF01135951</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29" publication-type="journal">Schmid-Hempel P, Schmid-Hempel R (1990) Endoparasitic larvae of conopid flies alter pollination behavior of bumblebees. Naturwissenschaften 77:450&#x02013;452</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR30"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR30" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmid-Hempel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid-Hempel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Endoparasitic flies, pollen-collection by bumblebees and a potential host-parasite conflict</article-title><source>Oecologia</source><year>1991</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>227</fpage><lpage>232</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00325260</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28313839</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30" publication-type="journal">Schmid-Hempel R, Schmid-Hempel P (1991) Endoparasitic flies, pollen-collection by bumblebees and a potential host-parasite conflict. Oecologia 87:227&#x02013;232<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28313839</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR31"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR31" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmid-Hempel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid-Hempel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Larval development of two parasitic flies (Conopidae) in the common host <italic>Bombus pascuorum</italic></article-title><source>Ecol Entomol</source><year>1996</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>63</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2311.1996.tb00267.x</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR31" publication-type="journal">Schmid-Hempel R, Schmid-Hempel P (1996) Larval development of two parasitic flies (Conopidae) in the common host <italic>Bombus pascuorum</italic>. Ecol Entomol 21:63&#x02013;70</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR32"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR32" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmid-Hempel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Stauffer</surname><given-names>H-P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Parasites and flower choice of bumblebees</article-title><source>Anim Behav</source><year>1998</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>819</fpage><lpage>825</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/anbe.1997.0661</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9632470</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32" publication-type="journal">Schmid-Hempel P, Stauffer H-P (1998) Parasites and flower choice of bumblebees. Anim Behav 55:819&#x02013;825<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9632470</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR33"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR33" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwenke</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lazzaro</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolfner</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reproduction-immunity trade-offs in insects</article-title><source>Annu Rev Entomol</source><year>2016</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>239</fpage><lpage>256</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-ento-010715-023924</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26667271</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR33" publication-type="journal">Schwenke RA, Lazzaro BP, Wolfner MF (2016) Reproduction-immunity trade-offs in insects. Annu Rev Entomol 61:239&#x02013;256. 10.1146/annurev-ento-010715-023924<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26667271</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR34"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR34" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shorter</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rueppell</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A review on self-destructive defense behaviors in social insects</article-title><source>Insectes Soc</source><year>2012</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00040-011-0210-x</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR34" publication-type="journal">Shorter JR, Rueppell O (2012) A review on self-destructive defense behaviors in social insects. Insectes Soc 59:1&#x02013;10</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR35"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR35" publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>KGV</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>BV</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>McAlpine</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Conopidae</article-title><source>Manual of Neararctic Diptera</source><year>1987</year><publisher-loc>Ottawa</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Biosystematic Research Centre, Research Branch Agriculture Canada</publisher-name><fpage>749</fpage><lpage>756</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR35" publication-type="book">Smith KGV, Peterson BV (1987) Conopidae. In: McAlpine JF (ed) Manual of Neararctic Diptera, vol 2. Biosystematic Research Centre, Research Branch Agriculture Canada, Ottawa, pp 749&#x02013;756</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR36"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR36" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Straub</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Pettis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Superorganism resilience: eusociality and susceptibility of ecosystem service providing insects to stressors</article-title><source>Curr Opin Insect Sci</source><year>2015</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>112</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cois.2015.10.010</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR36" publication-type="journal">Straub L, Williams GR, Pettis J et al (2015) Superorganism resilience: eusociality and susceptibility of ecosystem service providing insects to stressors. Curr Opin Insect Sci 12:109&#x02013;112. 10.1016/j.cois.2015.10.010</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR37"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR37" publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name></person-group><source>The coevolutionary process</source><year>1994</year><publisher-loc>Chicago</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Univ Chicago Press</publisher-name></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR37" publication-type="book">Thompson JN (1994) The coevolutionary process. Univ Chicago Press, Chicago</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article>