<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Vasc Bras</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Vasc Bras</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jvb</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Jornal Vascular Brasileiro</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1677-5449</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1677-7301</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Sociedade Brasileira de Angiologia e de Cirurgia Vascular (SBACV)</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40012968</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11864778</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">jvbAI20240041_EN</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="other">00701</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/1677-5449.202400412</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Innovations</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Teleproctoring of endovascular treatment of aortic diseases in times of pandemic and war</article-title><trans-title-group xml:lang="pt"><trans-title>Teleproctoria no tratamento endovascular de doen&#x000e7;as a&#x000f3;rticas em tempos de pandemia e guerra</trans-title></trans-title-group></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-4538-7678</contrib-id><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>Fabio Augusto Cypreste</given-names></name><role>conception and design</role><role>analysis and interpretation</role><role>data collection</role><role>writing the article</role><role>critical revision of the article</role><role>final approval of the article</role><role>overall responsibility</role><xref rid="aff01" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref ref-type="bio" rid="d67e45">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Campedelli</surname><given-names>Fabio Lemos</given-names></name><role>analysis and interpretation</role><role>critical revision of the article</role><role>final approval of the article</role><xref rid="aff01" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref ref-type="bio" rid="d67e56">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Amorelli</surname><given-names>Carlos Eduardo de Souza</given-names></name><role>analysis and interpretation</role><role>critical revision of the article</role><role>final approval of the article</role><xref rid="aff01" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref ref-type="bio" rid="d67e67">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pozzetti</surname><given-names>Ana Luiza Pereira da Silva</given-names></name><role>data collection</role><role>final approval of the article</role><xref rid="aff02" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref ref-type="bio" rid="d67e77">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bossa</surname><given-names>Milena Fachini dos Santos</given-names></name><role>data collection</role><role>final approval of the article</role><xref rid="aff03" ref-type="aff">3</xref><xref ref-type="bio" rid="d67e87">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jo&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>Priscila Cristina</given-names></name><role>conception and design</role><role>writing the article</role><role>final approval of the article</role><xref rid="aff04" ref-type="aff">4</xref><xref ref-type="bio" rid="d67e98">*</xref></contrib><aff id="aff01">
<label>1</label>
<institution content-type="original">Angiogyn, Goi&#x000e2;nia, GO, Brasil.</institution>
</aff><aff id="aff02">
<label>2</label>
<institution content-type="original">Universidade Estadual Paulista "J&#x000fa;lio de Mesquita Filho" &#x02013; UNESP, S&#x000e3;o Paulo, SP, Brasil.</institution>
</aff><aff id="aff03">
<label>3</label>
<institution content-type="original">Braile (International Sales Manager), S&#x000e3;o Jos&#x000e9; do Rio Preto, SP, Brasil.</institution>
</aff><aff id="aff04">
<label>4</label>
<institution content-type="original">Universidade Federal de S&#x000e3;o Paulo &#x02013; UNIFESP, S&#x000e3;o Paulo, SP, Brasil.</institution>
</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>Conflicts of interest: FACO is a proctor for Braile Biom&#x000e9;dica and received fees for supervising/guiding the implantation of the endoprostheses<bold>.</bold></p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>Ethics committee approval: Work approved by the regional ethics committee (opinion number: 5,052,995).</p></fn><corresp id="c01"><bold>Correspondence</bold>Fabio Augusto Cypreste Oliveira Av. Portugal, 1148, Bloco B, Sala 1601-03 CEP 74140-020 - Goi&#x000e2;nia (GO), Brasil Tel.: +55 (62) 4009-3003 E-mail: <email>fabioacoliveira@gmail.com</email>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>21</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>24</volume><elocation-id>e20240041</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>05</day><month>7</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>09</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright&#x000a9; 2025 The authors.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The authors.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><title>Abstract</title><p>Telemedicine encompasses various activities leveraging technology for remote health care. Surgical teleproctoring is described in the literature and has been used by some medical specialties for real-time and remote intraoperative guidance. However, there is still limited evidence on its use for the implantation of aortic endoprostheses. Technological progress and the advancement of telemedicine encourage surgical telementoring, especially in circumstances where in-person proctorship is not feasible, such as in remote areas, during pandemics and wars, and in settings lacking financial resources. In this context, we present the successful application of easily available and low-cost online teleproctoring of real-time aortic endoprosthesis implantation, addressing aortic diseases in a country experiencing social isolation due to the ongoing pandemic and war.</p></abstract><trans-abstract xml:lang="pt"><title>Resumo</title><p>A telemedicina inclui m&#x000fa;ltiplas a&#x000e7;&#x000f5;es relacionadas ao uso da tecnologia para promo&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o de sa&#x000fa;de de forma remota. A teleproctoria cir&#x000fa;rgica, j&#x000e1; descrita na literatura, vem sendo utilizada por algumas especialidades m&#x000e9;dicas para orienta&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o intraoperat&#x000f3;ria em tempo real e a dist&#x000e2;ncia. No entanto, ainda h&#x000e1; poucas evid&#x000ea;ncias para seu uso em implantes de endopr&#x000f3;teses a&#x000f3;rticas. O progresso tecnol&#x000f3;gico e o avan&#x000e7;o da telemedicina fomentam a telementoria cir&#x000fa;rgica, especialmente em circunst&#x000e2;ncias nas quais a proctoria m&#x000e9;dica presencial &#x000e9; invi&#x000e1;vel, tais como &#x000e1;reas remotas, pandemias, guerras e falta de recursos financeiros. Nesse contexto, apresentamos a aplica&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o bem-sucedida de teleproctoria em tempo real, facilmente acess&#x000ed;vel e de baixo custo, em implantes de endopr&#x000f3;teses a&#x000f3;rticas para o tratamento de doen&#x000e7;as da aorta, em um contexto de isolamento social devido &#x000e0; pandemia e a uma guerra em curso.</p></trans-abstract><kwd-group><title>Keywords: </title><kwd>telemedicine</kwd><kwd>telementoring</kwd><kwd>teleproctoring</kwd><kwd>endovascular procedures</kwd><kwd>aorta</kwd><kwd>covid-19</kwd><kwd>war</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group xml:lang="pt"><title>Palavras-chave: </title><kwd>telemedicina</kwd><kwd>telementoria</kwd><kwd>teleproctoria</kwd><kwd>procedimentos endovasculares</kwd><kwd>aorta</kwd><kwd>covid-19</kwd><kwd>guerra</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="6"/><table-count count="0"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="10"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Teleproctoring (TP) or surgical telementoring involves the exchange of guidance among surgeons through remote telecommunication technology.<sup><xref rid="B001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="B002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> This method has been adopted by various surgical medical specialties to overcome challenges related to the availability of specialized medical teams and ensure effective and safe care for patients requiring specific procedures.<sup><xref rid="B002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>-<xref rid="B004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> TP enables surgeons unfamiliar with certain medical devices and recently developed surgical techniques to receive real-time intraoperative guidance, contributing to safe and effective surgeries and fostering development in surgical education and research.<sup><xref rid="B003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>-<xref rid="B007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup></p><p>The COVID-19 pandemic and the imposition of social isolation accelerated advances in telemedicine, emerging as an essential tool for maintaining continuity of patient care and professional training.<sup><xref rid="B008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> The ability to connect surgeons in different locations, even in challenging scenarios, demonstrates the versatility and growing importance of TP in modern surgical practice.<sup><xref rid="B003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="B005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> This article reports the successful application of real-time TP to endovascular procedures conducted at distances exceeding 10,000 kilometers, connecting Brazil and Ukraine amid the COVID-19 pandemic and an ongoing war between Ukraine and Russia.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>METHODS</title><p>Endovascular procedures with TP were conducted following a protocol developed and routinely used by the specialized vascular surgery proctoring team Angiogyn (Goi&#x000e2;nia &#x02013; Goi&#x000e1;s, Brazil), in collaboration with experts in endovascular devices, international relations, and compliance from Braile Biom&#x000e9;dica&#x000ae; (S&#x000e3;o Jos&#x000e9; do Rio Preto &#x02013; S&#x000e3;o Paulo, Brazil). The study was approved by the local Ethics Committee (approval number 5.052.995).</p><p>The protocol for real-time TP of aortic endoprosthesis implantation included:</p><list list-type="order" id="L1"><list-item><p>Receipt of the patient&#x02019;s medical history and angiography images with 1mm slices.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Case analysis by the medical proctoring team, endoprosthesis specialists, and clinical engineering.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Definition of endovascular devices and surgical tactics to be used.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Teleconference among multidisciplinary teams with consensus on surgical planning (<xref rid="gf01" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>) and online training in the use of endoprostheses and endovascular devices through institutional videos and clinical discussions between teams.<fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="gf01"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Surgical planning: schematic drawing of the endoprostheses to be used based on angiography analysis: A) Endovascular repair of the thoracic aorta (TEVAR) with a Braile Biom&#x000e9;dica&#x000ae; DOMINUS&#x000ae; ENDOPROSTHESIS STENT-GRAFT and B) Covered Endovascular Reconstruction of the Aortic Bifurcation (CERAB) with a Braile Biom&#x000e9;dica&#x000ae; custom abdominal straight endoprosthesis + 2 Advanta V12&#x000ae; balloon-expandable covered stents for both common iliac arteries.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="jvb-24-e20240041-g01" position="float"/></fig>
</p></list-item><list-item><p>Testing Internet connection and telecommunication devices in the hemodynamics sector the day before the procedure.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Retesting of connections and arrangement of telecommunication devices on the day of the surgical procedure (<xref rid="gf02" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>).<fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="gf02"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Testing connections and arrangement of telecommunication devices on the day of the surgical procedure.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="jvb-24-e20240041-g02" position="float"/></fig>
</p></list-item><list-item><p>Execution of the surgical procedure.</p></list-item></list><p>Following the described protocol, endovascular procedures were conducted using real-time TP through an online platform. Bidirectional and encrypted communication between the multidisciplinary team in Brazil and Ukraine was established over a shared broadband 4G internet service, with high-resolution imaging (1280x720). Three telecommunication devices were strategically positioned with tripods, providing the Brazilian team with a comprehensive view of the fluoroscopy monitor, the Ukrainian team, and the handling of endoprostheses in both cases (<xref rid="gf03" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>). The TP team consisted of three members (a proctor and two product specialists), while the local team performing the procedure included two cardiovascular surgeons and an assistant who facilitated communication with the Brazilian team. The assisting surgeon maintained direct bidirectional communication with the Brazilian teleproctoring team through a headset. The first TP-assisted case involved a 62-year-old, white, hypertensive female who was a smoker. She presented with a penetrating aortic ulcer accompanied by an intramural hematoma and a thoracic aortic aneurysm in Zone 4. The procedure involved implantation of a DOMINUS&#x000ae; stent-graft endoprosthesis (<xref rid="gf04" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>). The second case involved a 56-year-old, white, hypertensive, diabetic male, who was also a smoker. He was diagnosed with aortic stenosis and a penetrating abdominal aortic ulcer. The procedure involved implantation of a custom-made abdominal endoprosthesis (<xref rid="gf05" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>).</p><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="gf03"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Illustration of teleproctoring setup employed.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="jvb-24-e20240041-g03" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="gf04"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Implantation of the Braile Biom&#x000e9;dica&#x000ae; DOMINUS&#x000ae; ENDOPROSTHESIS STENT-GRAFT with TP assistance to treat a thoracic aortic aneurysm.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="jvb-24-e20240041-g04" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="gf05"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Implantation of a Braile Biom&#x000e9;dica&#x000ae; custom abdominal endoprosthesis to treat a penetrating abdominal aortic ulcer.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="jvb-24-e20240041-g05" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><p>TP achieved efficacy and safety for conducting endovascular procedures. Technical success, defined as the correct deployment of planned devices without the need for repositioning and/or the use of unplanned devices, was achieved in both cases. Additionally, clinical success, defined as absence of death and clinical complications related to endovascular procedures conducted with TP within 30 days, was also achieved. The duration of the TP real-time connection was 34 minutes for the TEVAR procedure and 1 hour and 4 minutes for the CERAB procedure. Both procedures were conducted under general anesthesia with femoral access via surgical dissection, using approximately 100 ml of iodinated contrast. No adverse events occurred during either of the procedures. Both the field team and the proctoring team expressed high satisfaction with the outcomes and are confident in the potential for replication of this approach in other cases.</p><p>There were no observed difficulties with video resolution or latency between the teams in either of the cases. Postoperative control angiography at 30 days showed complete resolution of the aortic lesions that motivated treatment, with no signs of leakage, thrombosis, or migration of the endoprostheses used in either case (<xref rid="gf06" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>).</p><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="gf06"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>3D reconstructed angiography demonstrating correct positioning of the endoprostheses and complete exclusion of the penetrating abdominal aortic ulcer with no leakage.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="jvb-24-e20240041-g06" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>After the COVID-19 pandemic, significant changes and advances in education and care were observed in the field of surgical medicine. These include the growth of teleconferences, webinars, distance education, and the use of simulations and virtual reality in medical training. Advances in surgical teleproctoring, driven by telemedicine, have facilitated training of new specialists, especially in regions with a shortage of senior surgeons, providing access to procedures and surgical training in remote areas, contributing to the improvement of advanced surgical techniques, and consequently achieving better results for both the medical team and the patients. While there are various studies of the use of telemedicine in vascular surgery, specific literature on TP of vascular surgeries is still limited.<sup><xref rid="B005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="B006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="B007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="B009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup></p><p>The first report in the literature that employed TP to assist in aortic endoprosthesis implantation was published by Deaton et al. in 1999.<sup><xref rid="B006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> Using remote transmission links, the team supervised and monitored the proximal and distal release and final control angiography in the endovascular treatment of abdominal aortic aneurysms (EVAR) in 7 patients.<sup><xref rid="B006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> Since then, several studies have explored this approach, confirming its feasibility and safety.</p><p>In 2005, Di Valentino et al.<sup><xref rid="B007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> conducted a prospective study to assess the safety of TP during EVAR. The study compared three proctoring modalities: in-person monitoring for 12 patients, TP in a room adjacent to the operating room for another 12 patients, and remote TP (250 km away) for a group of 24 patients. Surprisingly, no significant differences were identified between the groups regarding proctoring time or procedure success. The authors concluded that TP for EVAR is not only feasible but also shows promising results. They encouraged the replication of this surgical proctoring model for other invasive cardiovascular procedures.</p><p>Another study, in 2017, investigated the safety of implementing a telementoring program for EVAR.<sup><xref rid="B009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> During the initial training phase, 49 patients underwent EVAR at the secondary center under telementoring. Subsequently, the same center independently performed 86 EVAR cases. The results revealed no significant difference between telementored and independent procedures, either in terms of 30-day mortality (4.1% vs. 2.3%, p=0.621) or in terms of initial technical success (93.9% vs. 97.7%, p=0.353). The study concluded that telementoring for EVAR in a remote center is effective and feasible, contributing to the successful implementation of medical competence in a distant environment.</p><p>The essential conditions for safe TP were outlined by the Society of American Gastrointestinal and Endoscopic Surgeons (SAGES) at an event called Project 6 Summit.<sup><xref rid="B010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> The criteria established for telecommunication systems for telementoring included rigorous requirements such as low latency, stability, minimum video resolution of 480 scan lines, and a minimum broadband connection of 512 kbps, along with the essential encryption of all data to ensure compliance with the Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act (HIPAA) security standard. The committee also emphasized desirable qualities for telementoring, highlighting the need to be low-cost, "plug and play," easy to use, portable, upgradable, and enabling telestration, which is the ability to draw and annotate on videos and images.</p><p>In 2021, Gerardo et al.<sup><xref rid="B004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> further advanced the specifications, stating that for surgical telementoring, image resolution should not be less than 768x492, and video transmission latency should not exceed 25ms. This implies that a broadband connection greater than 1.2mbps is imperative to ensure the effectiveness of surgical telementoring. These guidelines reiterate the importance of specific technical conditions to ensure the quality and safety of TP.</p><p>In the presented cases, TP of endovascular treatment of aortic diseases with endoprosthesis implantation was used by experienced surgical teams unfamiliar with the specific devices used. Minimum criteria for data transmission, security, and resolution were met, even using easily accessible devices not specifically dedicated to TP. Additionally, telestration was not necessary in either case, despite being available.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>CONCLUSION</title><p>Remote real-time teleproctoring, using readily available and low-cost technology, proved effective for endoprosthesis implantation to treat complex aortic diseases in a country undergoing healthcare and social isolation. The role of remote surgical teleproctoring in endovascular procedures is still evolving. However, it seems to be an irreversible path for improving global healthcare assistance and surgical training, leading to reductions in time, distance, and costs.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>How to cite:</bold> Oliveira FAC, Campedelli FL, Amorelli CES, Pozzetti ALPS, Bossa MFS, Jo&#x000e3;o PC. Teleproctoring of endovascular treatment of aortic diseases in times of pandemic and war. J Vasc Bras. 2025;24:e20240041. <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1590/1677-5449.202400412" ext-link-type="uri">https://doi.org/10.1590/1677-5449.202400412</ext-link>
</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p>Financial support: None.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>The study was carried out at Angiogyn, Goi&#x000e2;nia, GO, Brasil.</p></fn></fn-group><bio id="d67e45"><p>Vascular Surgeon and Full Member, Brazilian Society of Angiology and Vascular Surgery (SBACV); Coordinator, Vascular and Endovascular Surgery Service, Anis Rassi Heart Hospital; Preceptor, Residency Program, S&#x000e3;o Francisco de Assis and Santa Helena Hospitals, and Founding Partner of Angiogyn.</p></bio><bio id="d67e56"><p>Vascular Surgeon and Full Member, Brazilian Society of Angiology and Vascular Surgery (SBACV); Coordinator, Residency Program, S&#x000e3;o Francisco de Assis and Santa Helena Hospitals, and Founding Partner of Angiogyn.</p></bio><bio id="d67e67"><p>Vascular Surgeon and Full Member, Brazilian Society of Angiology and Vascular Surgery (SBACV); Coordinator, Vascular and Endovascular Surgery Service, S&#x000e3;o Francisco de Assis Hospital; Preceptor, Residency Program, S&#x000e3;o Francisco de Assis and Santa Helena Hospitals, and Founding Partner of Angiogyn.</p></bio><bio id="d67e77"><p>Graduated in Biomedicine with a focus on Diagnostic Imaging, Universidade Estadual Paulista "J&#x000fa;lio de Mesquita Filho" (UNESP).</p></bio><bio id="d67e87"><p>Master of Business Administration the Brazilian Association of Consulting and Advisory in Foreign Trade (ABRACOMEX).</p></bio><bio id="d67e98"><p>Master's in Health Sciences, Universidade Federal de S&#x000e3;o Paulo (UNIFESP).</p></bio><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B001"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Erridge</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yeung</surname><given-names>DKT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>HRH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Purkayastha</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Telementoring of surgeons: a systematic review</article-title><source>Surg Innov</source><year>2019</year><volume>26</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>111</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1553350618813250</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30465477</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B002"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guetter</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Telemedicine and telementoring in the surgical specialties: a narrative review</article-title><source>Am J Surg</source><year>2019</year><volume>218</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>760</fpage><lpage>766</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amjsurg.2019.07.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31350010</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B003"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>A Butt</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Augestad</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Educational value of surgical telementoring</article-title><source>J Surg Oncol</source><year>2021</year><volume>124</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>231</fpage><lpage>240</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jso.26524</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34245572</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B004"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gerardo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lele</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sundaram</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ponsky</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Surgical telementoring: feasibility, applicability, and how to</article-title><source>J Surg Oncol</source><year>2021</year><volume>124</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>241</fpage><lpage>245</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jso.26511</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34245573</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B005"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>He Herrera Montano</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Presencio Lafuente</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bre&#x000f1;osa Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ortega Mansilla</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Torre D&#x000ed;ez</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>R&#x000ed;o-Sol&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>MLD</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Systematic review of telemedicine and ehealth systems applied to vascular surgery</article-title><source>J Med Syst</source><year>2022</year><volume>46</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>104</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10916-022-01895-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36471095</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B006"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Deaton</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Balch</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kesler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bogey</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Telemedicine and endovascular aortic grafting</article-title><source>Am J Surg</source><year>1999</year><volume>177</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>75</fpage><lpage>77</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0002-9610(98)00309-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10037313</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B007"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Di Valentino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alerci</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bogen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Telementoring during endovascular treatment of abdominal aortic aneurysms: a prospective study</article-title><source>J Endovasc Ther</source><year>2005</year><volume>12</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>200</fpage><lpage>205</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1583/04-1421.1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15823067</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B008"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dedeilia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sotiropoulos</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hanrahan</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Janga</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dedeilias</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sideris</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Medical and surgical education challenges and innovations in the COVID-19 Era: a systematic review</article-title><source>In Vivo</source><year>2020</year><volume>34</volume><issue>3</issue><supplement>Suppl</supplement><fpage>1603</fpage><lpage>1611</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21873/invivo.11950</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32503818</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B009"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Porretta</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alerci</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wyttenbach</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Long-term outcomes of a telementoring program for distant teaching of endovascular aneurysm repair</article-title><source>J Endovasc Ther</source><year>2017</year><volume>24</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>852</fpage><lpage>858</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1526602817730841</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28891376</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B010"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schlachta</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ponsky</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dunkin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Project 6 summit: SAGES telementoring initiative</article-title><source>Surg Endosc</source><year>2016</year><volume>30</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>3665</fpage><lpage>3672</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00464-016-4988-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27270593</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>