<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Oral Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Oral Health</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Oral Health</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1472-6831</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12103006</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">6153</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12903-025-06153-5</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Exploring oral health related awareness, perceptions, practices and experiences among type 2 diabetes mellitus patients: a mixed method design</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-5454-6012</contrib-id><name><surname>Elsous</surname><given-names>Aymen</given-names></name><address><email>aymenelsous65@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0009-0004-7710-8332</contrib-id><name><surname>Fetaiha</surname><given-names>Aesha</given-names></name><address><email>aishafetaiha@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Radwan</surname><given-names>Mahmoud</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/03g9kfn98</institution-id><institution>Faculty of Medical Sciences, </institution><institution>Israa University, </institution></institution-wrap>Gaza Strip, Palestine </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Analysis and Decision Support Department, Unit of Planning and Institutional Performance Development, Ministry of Health, Gaza Strip, Palestine </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Medical Aids for Palestinians, Gaza Strip, Palestine </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>Aesha Fetaiha Dental Clinic, Gaza Strip, Palestine </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label>General Directorate of International Cooperation and Projects, Foreign Relations, Ministry of Health, Gaza Strip, Palestine </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>24</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>24</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>25</volume><elocation-id>781</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>27</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>9</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background/Objective</title><p id="Par1">The World Health Organization has classified diabetes mellitus as a pandemic disease, which is causing it to become a major worldwide health concern. It can have significant long-term repercussions, especially on dental health, if treatment is not received. The study aimed to explore patients with type 2 diabetes, awareness to, perceptions to and practices regarding oral health, in addition to their experiences.</p></sec><sec><title>Materials and methods</title><p id="Par2">Convergent triangulation was applied from May to November 2022. 376 patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus participated in the quantitative part and 13 patients involved in the qualitative study. The quantitative study was applied in five randomly selected primary health centers representing the five Gaza governorates using self-developed semi-structured questionnaire. The qualitative study was applied in two central primary health centers. Descriptive analysis was applied using the SPSS software and thematic analysis was approached for the qualitative study.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">64.4% of patients see themselves susceptible to oral health problems, and 67.8% perceived severity of oral complications of diabetes mellitus. Moreover, 73.2% perceived benefits from oral health practices and 56.2% perceived barriers to oral health practices. Patients' awareness regarding oral health complications from DM and oral health practices are inadequate (57.6%), as well as oral health habits (42.5%). Main themes elucidated from the qualitative study are dental care service quality, patient-dentist interaction, oral hygiene and self-care, and the patient's experiences with oral health problems.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par4">The results point to important gaps in patients' knowledge and attitudes about dental health in relation to diabetes mellitus. Even though most people are aware of their vulnerability to oral health problems and the seriousness of any potential consequences, a sizable portion continue to believe that there are obstacles in the way of good oral hygiene habits. Poor oral hygiene practices and a lack of knowledge about oral health issues point to the need for more focused interventions and improved educational programs. The significance of high-quality dental care services, productive patient-dentist relationships, and encouraging self-care behaviors are all emphasized by the qualitative findings. In order to improve patient outcomes and encourage better dental hygiene habits among diabetics, these issues must be addressed. This will ultimately reduce oral health complications and increase general well-being.</p></sec><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1186/s12903-025-06153-5.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Knowledge</kwd><kwd>Attitudes</kwd><kwd>Practices</kwd><kwd>Experiences</kwd><kwd>Diabetes Mellitus</kwd><kwd>Oral health</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; BioMed Central Ltd., part of Springer Nature 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par5">A metabolic endocrine ailment marked by hyperglycemia, diabetes mellitus (DM) is one of the chronic conditions with the fastest rate of growth in the globe [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. With its alarmingly high incidence, diabetes mellitus is becoming a global health concern that has been categorized as a pandemic disease by the World Health Organization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. From 30 million in 1985 to 135 million in 1995, the number of people with diabetes mellitus is expected to rise to 541 million by 2030 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. This growing worry is especially evident in Palestine, where the Ministry of Health (MoH) says that the prevalence of type 2 diabetes (T2DM) is underreported, despite the fact that the incidence of DM in the Gaza Strip is 149.4/100.000 population. In 2014, diabetes accounted for 8.9% of all deaths, making it the fourth leading cause of mortality, according to the Palestinian Ministry of Health [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>].</p><p id="Par6">If left untreated, diabetes mellitus (DM) can have substantial long-term effects, particularly on dental health. According to research, patients with type 2 diabetes had a 29% and 22% higher chance of developing periodontitis and bone loss, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Additionally, people with uncontrolled diabetes have a threefold increased risk of developing periodontal tissue loss [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Diabetes affects many aspects of oral health, such as the function of the salivary glands, the brain, periodontal tissues, and the oral mucosa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. People with diabetes who have uncontrolled blood glucose levels frequently have dental issues. In those with diabetes, xerostomia (dry mouth) increases the risk of dental caries, oral fungal infections (oral candidiasis), poor wound healing, taste impairment, burning mouth syndrome, and periodontal disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>].</p><p id="Par7">In light of these concerns, it is critical that individuals with diabetes comprehend their increased vulnerability to oral difficulties, such as dry mouth, periodontal diseases, and dental caries, and the significance of preventing these issues with efficient treatment techniques. DM patients should be informed about the reciprocal association between oral health and DM to prevent and cure periodontal/oral disease and manage DM. Therefore, preserving periodontal health and proper dental hygiene helps diabetics maintain appropriate glycaemic control [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. It is crucial to examine the knowledge and attitudes of patients with diabetes mellitus to determine their desire to adopt excellent oral hygiene habits. According to academic studies, promoting appropriate oral self-care habits requires increasing oral health knowledge [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. However, everyday practice does not often follow from only knowing about and having a healthy attitude toward diabetes control and oral hygiene [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>].</p><p id="Par8">In Palestine, the primary health care services are mainly delivered by the United Nations Relief and Works Agency for Palestine Refugees (UNRWA) for registered refugees and by the MoH. Evidence showed that diabetes patients attending UNRWA clinics have high levels of chronic periodontitis and DMFT index and are less aware about diabetic complications on oral health [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>].Despite the growing number of DM patients in Palestine, little is known about oral health-related knowledge, attitudes, and behaviors (KAP) for patients attending primary health centers (PHCs) of the MoH. In order to create baseline data and, consequently, strategies for oral health awareness initiatives among patients with DM, it is required to evaluate the KAP of patients with DM with reference to oral health. This study sought to determine how well-informed T2DM patients were aware about the effects of diabetes on oral health, how they perceived oral complications and problems, how they described their oral hygiene habits, and to explore patients'experience and care preferences related to oral health<bold>.</bold></p><p id="Par9">Knowledge of common oral complications in different populations helps identify risk factors early. This allows for targeted interventions to prevent or manage oral diseases more effectively. Awareness of common attitudes toward oral health can help healthcare providers encourage better preventive practices. By considering patients'experiences and preferences, healthcare providers can create treatment plans that align with patients'expectations and comfort levels. This can increase patient satisfaction and adherence to prescribed oral health practices. Moreover, it leads to the development of policies and strategies aimed at improving oral health for underserved or at-risk groups. Understanding the specific oral health challenges faced by patients allows healthcare providers to offer better care tailored to their needs. In addition, Oral health is closely linked to overall health, and studying the interconnection between attitudes, practices, and complications helps to view oral health in a broader context. It supports the idea that maintaining good oral health is an essential part of overall well-being, which can improve long-term health outcomes. By understanding these aspects, healthcare systems can adapt to meet the needs of diverse populations, ensuring that everyone has access to quality oral health care and the knowledge to maintain it.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Study design</title><p id="Par10">A convergent mixed method design was conducted from May to November 2022. Quantitative and qualitative approach were used simultaneously. In the quantitative study, a questionnaire-based cross-sectional design was applied, while face to face interview-based study was followed for the qualitative study.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Study setting</title><p id="Par11">Gaza strip is divided into five governorates named in order from north to south: North, Gaza city, Middle Zone, Khanyounis and Rafah. The MoH in Gaza operates and runs 52 PHCs distributed in five governorates. Stratified simple random sampling was approached to select one PHC from each governorate at random based. These PHCs are ordered from north to south: Beit Lahia Martyrs, Al-Remal Martyrs health center, Der-Albalh Martyrs clinic, Khanyounes Martyrs clinic and Rafah Martyrs clinic.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Sample size and sampling technique</title><p id="Par12">The study population included all diabetic mellitus patients fulfilling the below mentioned inclusion criteria and those who visited the health care center during this study period. The online Survey Monkey website, available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.surveymonkey.com/mp/sample-size-calculator/">https://www.surveymonkey.com/mp/sample-size-calculator/</ext-link>. was used to calculate sample size according to the last report of MoH (2021) which showed that 17.6% is the prevalence of T2DM, giving approximately a total of 11088 individuals above 40 years are registered within MoH PHCs. Sample calculation was done at 5% error and 95% confidence interval and revealed 372 patients should be included. The registered T2DM are distributed in the five governorates as follow: 1389, 5949, 918, 2173 and 689 individuals in the north, Gaza, middle area, Khanyounes and Rafah governorate, respectively. </p><p id="Par13">Random selection of participants following proportionate systematic sampling. The sample size included questionnaires from 376 T2DM patients. According to distribution of the 11,088 patients within the five governorates, the sample size was proportionally distributed: 48 from the north, 199 from Gaza, 31 from the middle zone, 73 and 25 from Khanyounes and Rafah, respectively. The distribution percentages are 12.5%, 53.5%, 8.25%, 19.5%, and 6.2%, in that order. Then, a list of females and males'patients was prepared from each PHC included in the study. The K<sup>th</sup> interval was 30, which means that every 30 patients, from each list, come first to the PHC one is selected if he/she met the inclusion criteria. Regarding qualitative study, the two mains central PHCs, Gaza and Khanyouns martyrs, were chosen for doing interviews.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Inclusion criteria</title><p id="Par14">Patients who were diagnosed with diabetes mellitus and undergoing treatment for the same. In addition, patients were diagnosed with diabetes mellitus for at least five years and were willing to participate in the study.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Exclusion criteria</title><p id="Par15">Patients with mental health problems, hearing impairments, patients who were unable to provide the appropriate information and those not willing to participate in the study.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Data collection procedure</title><p id="Par16">A questionnaire, specifically designed for this study consisting of four parts has been developed to assess: 1) the awareness on oral implications of DM (17 questions), 2) oral hygiene practices of diabetic patients (15 questions), and 3) perception toward oral complications based on health belief model (HBM) (19 questions); perceived susceptibility to oral complications (5 questions), perceived severity of oral complications (6 questions), perceived benefits from oral hygiene (4 questions) and perceived barriers to oral hygiene (4 questions), in addition to the corresponding socio-demographic and clinical data (supplement 1). The questionnaire was prepared first in English, after reviewing many literatures found in the PubMed, and then translated into Arabic. The steps guidelines of the AHRQ were followed to translate and validate the questionnaire [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Forward backward translation was applied, face and content validity, in addition to internal reliability and test retest were determined accordingly.</p><p id="Par17">Face validity was examined in terms of the clarity of the wording, the likelihood the target audience would be able to answer the questions, and the layout and style. Reviewers stated that the general shape of the questionnaire was organized and well arranged. Moreover, the questions were clear and easy to understand. For content validity, the content validity index -average approach (CVI/Ave) and Kappa statistics were calculated accordingly after the questionnaire being reviewed by nine referees. The item content validity index (I-CVI) and scale content validity index (S-CVI) ranged from 0.78 to 1 and 0.89 to 1, respectively. Kappa statistic (<italic>k</italic>*) for questionnaire&#x02019;s items ranged from 0.79 to 1.00. The alpha cronbach (&#x003b1;) of awareness questions, HBM and oral health practices was 0.82, 0.87 and 0.84, respectively. The test re-test reliability, measured by ICC and Pearson correlation, ranged between 0.90 to 0.99 and 0.94 to 0.99, respectively.</p><p id="Par18">Questions of awareness were measured on three points Likert scale (yes, no, don&#x02019;t know), and questions of the HBM were measured on five points Likert scale (1=strongly disagree, 2=disagree, 3=neutral, 4=agree and 5=strongly agree). Moreover, similar Likert scale was used for questions of oral hygiene practices (1=never, 2=rare, 3=sometimes, 4=often and 5=always).</p><p id="Par19">A semi-structured interview guide was developed to achieve the study objectives (13 questions with probing questions). Interview guide was presented to three health experts and dentists who have public health experience to ensure trustworthiness of questions, and to answer research questions. Moreover, interview guide was tested on two patients to make sure that questions are easy to be posed and understand. Patients were purposefully selected and we determined ten patients for the interview, but we decided to continue until saturation of information is achieved. At end, thirteen patients participated. A variety of ages and gender were represented in the sample of participants from the two centrals PHCs; Gaza and Khanyounis. We excluded patients who had not seen a dentist in the previous twelve months because our goal was to learn more about their experiences with dental professionals regarding diabetes. To ensure free bias selection of interviewees, the first thirteen individuals met the study criteria were asked to participate in the study, after the quantitative part is done, and if anyone refused, the invitation is given to next one. Interviews were conducted in a separate room within the PHCs. Audio records were transcript into papers.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Data analysis</title><p id="Par20">Data coding and analysis were done using the Statistical Package for Social Sciences software (SPSS) for Windows (version 26: IBM Corp). Prior analysis, data were checked for missing and extreme values and if a questionnaire has missing values of 5% or more, the questionnaire was discarded and not used for analysis. In descriptive analysis, means and standard deviation were used for analysis of continuous variables (age, duration of DM&#x02026;), however, frequency and percentages were used for categorical variables (gender, level of education&#x02026;), and the questionnaire items. In addition, mean percentages were presented for each item and for the whole domain (awareness, perception and practices). Perceived susceptibility to, severity of oral complications and benefits of and barriers to oral health habits are presented in graphs, and responses are presented in percentages into three categories; agree (agree and strongly agree), neutral, and disagree (disagree and strongly disagree).</p><p id="Par21">About qualitative study, thematic analysis was approached. Codes were determined through reading line by line and codes which share similar ideas were pooled under one domain presented under themes.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec11"><title>Socio-demographic and clinical characteristics of participated patients</title><p id="Par22">The mean age for participants is 57.8 &#x000b1;&#x02009;8.76 years. Females represent 55.1% of the sample. Age is divided into five categories and patients below 55 and above 65 years constitute, in each, at least one fifth of the sample size. Half of the patients participated are from Gaza city (52.9%. 199/376) and the least percentage is from Rafah in the far south (6.6%). Majority of participants had formal school education (93.6%, 352/376), whereas 6.4% (24/376) are illiterate and 18.6% (70/376) had university degree. Most participants are not working at the time of data collection (72.9%, 274/376), and live under a deep poverty line (83.5%, 314/376). The mean duration of T2DM is 10.99 &#x000b1;&#x02009;6.61 years. Almost two thirds (64.2%, 241/376) have T2DM less than 10 years. The mean HbA1c value is 8.11% &#x000b1;&#x02009;1.84, and 62% and 38% have uncontrolled and controlled T2DM, respectively. Two thirds of participants have other chronic diseases in addition to DM, mostly hypertension (43.9%, 165/376) and hypertension with heart disease (10.9%, 41/376). Half (49.5%, 186/376) have family history of oral complications resulting from T2DM and 79.8% (300/376) of patients report oral manifestations in the last 12 months, and 56.6% (213/376) visited dental clinics accordingly. Common oral manifestations reported by participants are tooth decay (58.2%, 219/376) and tooth loss (53.2%, 200/376). Almost 30% (112/376) and 18.4% (68/376) suffer from gingival bleeding and bad odor, respectively. Reasons for visiting dental clinics are due to problems with teeth, gum or mouth (57.2%, 215/376) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Socio-demographic and clinical information of participated patients (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;= 376)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left">Frequency</th><th align="left">Percent</th><th align="left">M &#x000b1;&#x02009;SD</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Age group</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">57.86 &#x000b1;&#x02009;8.76</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;50 or less</td><td align="left">84</td><td align="left">22.3</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;51&#x02013;55</td><td align="left">69</td><td align="left">18.4</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;56&#x02013;60</td><td align="left">75</td><td align="left">19.9</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;61&#x02013;65</td><td align="left">70</td><td align="left">18.6</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;More than 65</td><td align="left">78</td><td align="left">20.7</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Residency</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;North Gaza</td><td align="left">48</td><td align="left">12.8</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Gaza city</td><td align="left">199</td><td align="left">52.9</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Middle zone</td><td align="left">31</td><td align="left">8.2</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Khan Younis</td><td align="left">73</td><td align="left">19.4</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Rafah</td><td align="left">25</td><td align="left">6.6</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Are you smoker (number cigarette/days)</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">11.45 &#x000b1;&#x02009;8.28</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Yes</td><td align="left">45</td><td align="left">12.0</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;No</td><td align="left">292</td><td align="left">77.7</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Ex-smoker</td><td align="left">39</td><td align="left">10.4</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">How many shisha</td><td align="left">38</td><td align="left">10.1</td><td align="left">7.24 &#x000b1;&#x02009;3.26</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Level of education</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Illiterate</td><td align="left">24</td><td align="left">6.4</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Up to elementary school</td><td align="left">65</td><td align="left">17.3</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Up to preparatory school</td><td align="left">104</td><td align="left">27.7</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Up to secondary school</td><td align="left">113</td><td align="left">30.1</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;University and above</td><td align="left">70</td><td align="left">18.6</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Marital status</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Unmarried</td><td align="left">62</td><td align="left">16.5</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Married</td><td align="left">314</td><td align="left">83.5</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Income</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Under poverty line (&#x0003c; 1974 NIS)</td><td align="left">314</td><td align="left">83.5</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Above poverty line (&#x02265; 1974 NIS)</td><td align="left">62</td><td align="left">16.5</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Number of family member</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">1.71 &#x000b1;&#x02009;0.76</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;5 or less</td><td align="left">102</td><td align="left">27.1</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;6&#x02013;10</td><td align="left">219</td><td align="left">58.2</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;More than 10</td><td align="left">55</td><td align="left">14.6</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Working status</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Working</td><td align="left">102</td><td align="left">27.1</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Not working</td><td align="left">274</td><td align="left">72.9</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">Frequency</td><td align="left">Percent</td><td align="left">M &#x000b1;&#x02009;SD</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Having medical insurance</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Yes</td><td align="left">367</td><td align="left">97.6</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;No</td><td align="left">9</td><td align="left">2.4</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Duration DM</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">10.99 &#x000b1;&#x02009;6.61</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;10 or less</td><td align="left">241</td><td align="left">64.1</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;More than 10</td><td align="left">135</td><td align="left">35.9</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Family history of oral complications from T2DM</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Yes</td><td align="left">186</td><td align="left">49.5</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;No</td><td align="left">190</td><td align="left">50.5</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Type of treatment</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Diet restriction and physical activity</td><td align="left">18</td><td align="left">4.8</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;insulin injection</td><td align="left">48</td><td align="left">12.8</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Oral hypoglycemic agents</td><td align="left">246</td><td align="left">65.4</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Oral hypoglycemic agents and insulin injection</td><td align="left">64</td><td align="left">17.0</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Receiving education about oral care</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Yes</td><td align="left">78</td><td align="left">20.7</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;No</td><td align="left">298</td><td align="left">79.3</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Last reading of HbA1c</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">10.27 &#x000b1;&#x02009;0.86</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x02265; 7%</td><td align="left">143</td><td align="left">38</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x0003e; 7%</td><td align="left">233</td><td align="left">62</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Presence other chronic diseases</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Yes</td><td align="left">236</td><td align="left">62.8</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;No</td><td align="left">140</td><td align="left">37.2</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">If yes, specify</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Hypertension</td><td align="left">165</td><td align="left">43.9</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Hypertension, Heart disease</td><td align="left">41</td><td align="left">10.9</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Heart disease</td><td align="left">16</td><td align="left">4.3</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Arthritis</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">1.1</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Asthma</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">1.1</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Hypertension, Asthma</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Arthritis, Hypertension</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0.3</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Hypertension, cancer</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0.3</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Hypertension, Kidney disease</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0.3</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Osteoporosis</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0.3</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Suffering from oral diseases in the last year</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Yes</td><td align="left">300</td><td align="left">79.8</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;No</td><td align="left">76</td><td align="left">20.2</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Among yes reporting to have oral diseases in the last year</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">&#x02003;Tooth mobility</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x02003;Yes</td><td align="left">86</td><td align="left">22.9</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x02003;No</td><td align="left">290</td><td align="left">77.1</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">&#x02003;Tooth loss</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x02003;Yes</td><td align="left">200</td><td align="left">53.2</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x02003;No</td><td align="left">176</td><td align="left">46.8</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">&#x02003;Tooth decay</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x02003;Yes</td><td align="left">219</td><td align="left">58.2</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x02003;No</td><td align="left">157</td><td align="left">41.8</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">&#x02003;Tooth sensitivity</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x02003;Yes</td><td align="left">24</td><td align="left">6.4</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x02003;No</td><td align="left">352</td><td align="left">93.6</td><td align="left"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>M</italic> mean, <italic>SD</italic> standard deviation</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par23">Seven women and six men, ages ranging from 47 to 72, took part in the qualitative sample. Four themes were developed based on the extraction of fourteen codes: Dental care service quality, the patient-dentist interaction, oral hygiene and self-care, and the patient's experiences with oral health problems (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).
<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Codes and themes of qualitative study</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Themes</th><th align="left">Codes</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="7">Quality of dental care services</td><td align="left">Accessibility</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Availability of essential dental services</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Affordability to cost</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Lack of dental</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Lack of medical supplies</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Appointment at PHC</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Follow up of dental status</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Patient dentist relationship</td><td align="left">Communication</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Health education and information</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">Self-oral care and hygiene</td><td align="left">Awareness</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Attitudes</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Oral health practices</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Patients&#x02019; oral health experiences</td><td align="left">Dental problems</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Nutritional problem</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Patients'perception about oral complications from T2DM</title><p id="Par24">Perceived susceptibility to oral health complications.</p><p id="Par25">On a five-point Likert scale, the mean score for perceived susceptibility to oral problems is 3.22 (0.32), indicating that 64% of patients believe they are at risk for oral complications. In particular, 59.2% of people with diabetes mellitus believe that they are more likely to experience complications than others due to their condition. The assertion"I am not at risk for developing dental carries"is also disputed by nearly two thirds (61.2%) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Perceived susceptibility to oral complications</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12903_2025_6153_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p id="Par26">Perceived severity to oral health complications.</p><p id="Par27">Most patients (67.8%) believe that oral problems are severe. On a five-point Likert scale, the mean score (standard deviation) is 3.39 (0.45). Most people (79.4%) think that dental issues have a big financial impact on patients and their families. Because oral problems negatively impact patients'physical status, 67% of respondents think they are more serious than other disorders (74.4%). In exchange, 58.6% of participants said that managing oral problems is simple (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Perceived severity to oral complications</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12903_2025_6153_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p><p id="Par28">Perceived benefits from oral health practices.</p><p id="Par29">On a five-point Likert scale, the mean score for perceived benefits from oral health practices is 3.66 (0.36), indicating that 73.2% of respondents think that oral health practices provide advantages. In particular, 84.6% believe that maintaining good oral hygiene is essential even in the absence of mouth symptoms. Additionally, 80.6% believe that there is a good probability of therapy when oral symptoms are detected early. Only 56% of respondents, however, concur that maintaining good oral hygiene has little bearing on averting oral problems (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Perceived benefits from oral health practices</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12903_2025_6153_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p><p id="Par30">The majority of interviewed patients do believe that keeping the mouth, teeth, and oral cavity clean is crucial to their overall health, as well as have favorable opinions on the value of follow-up in dental offices.<disp-quote><p id="Par31">&#x0201c;&#x02026;commitment with cleaning tooth has a good effect on health &#x02026;&#x0201d; (Male, Khanyounis, 58 years)</p><p id="Par32">&#x0201c;&#x02026;in last 4 months I have a bad breath, I came to treat it, and the dentist prescribed me good mouth wash, then I felt good&#x02026;&#x0201d; (Male, Khanyounis, 63 years)</p><p id="Par33">&#x0201c;&#x02026;I went to check my teeth because I know the effect of diabetic disease on my oral health&#x02026;&#x0201d; (Female, Gaza,63 years)</p><p id="Par34">&#x0201c;&#x02026;brushing tooth daily with good nutrition is very important&#x02026;&#x0201d; (Female, Gaza, 60 years)</p><p id="Par35">&#x0201c;&#x02026;we should brush our teeth to prevent gum inflammation &#x02026;&#x0201d; (Female, Gaza, 51 years)</p></disp-quote></p><sec id="Sec13"><title>Perceived barriers to oral health practice</title><p id="Par36">The average score on a five-point Likert scale is 2.81 (0.28). Many obstacles to oral health behaviors were perceived by more than half of individuals (56,2%). The inability to pay for a dental examination is the main reason why people avoid receiving oral health care (70.8%). However, half of the participants reported feeling that their gums bleed when they clean their teeth (54%), and they are afraid to sit in a dentist chair (57.6%). Furthermore, 55.4% of respondents said they don't know enough about proper dental hygiene procedures. Low practices are a result of these variables (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Perceived barriers to oral health practices</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12903_2025_6153_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p><p id="Par37">Patients who were interviewed mentioned numerous obstacles, which can be categorized into variables linked to the institution, the doctor, and the patient. In reference to facility-related issues, interviewees expressed dissatisfaction with the inadequate dental services provided by governmental PHCs and the inability to obtain dental treatment or follow-up care when they visited a dental clinic because of a shortage of dental and occasionally medical supplies. Tooth extraction is the extent of dental services. Root canal therapy, tooth restoration, and scaling all necessary dental procedures for diabetic patients to maintain healthy gums and teeth are not available. One participant made it apparent that the lack of dental services and supplies results in poor care quality. Furthermore, basic dental and general practice supplies like gloves and sutures are not readily available, therefore occasionally dentists ask us to buy them from private pharmacies.<disp-quote><p id="Par38">&#x0201c;&#x02026;When you want to do restoration, they said it is finished and when you want to do root canal treatment, also they said has not existed, they just do tooth extraction &#x02026;&#x0201d; (Male, Gaza, 47 years).</p><p id="Par39">&#x0201c;&#x02026;They haven&#x02019;t anything to offer, bad dental care&#x02026;&#x0201d; (Female, Khanyounis, 72 years) &#x0201c;&#x02026; I'm taking two taxis to tell me it's finished, go back &#x02026;&#x0201d; (Male, Khanyounis, 58 years)</p><p id="Par40">&#x0201c;&#x02026; I don't come here too much for treatment because they have nothing to offer&#x02026;&#x0201d; (Female, Khanyounis, 72 years)</p><p id="Par41">&#x0201c;&#x02026;They told me there isn&#x02019;t gloves to treat me&#x02026;&#x0201d; (Male, Khanyounis, 58 years)</p></disp-quote></p><p id="Par42">In terms of patient-related issues, the majority of patients interviewed reported dissatisfaction with the dental care provided by the governmental PHCs and having a challenging financial situation. They claim that because dental care is not properly offered by the PHCS, they cannot afford the prices at private clinics. The majority of them require artificial teeth to replace their extracted ones. Additionally, they stated that basic dental care, such as mouthwash, is not offered in PHCs and is expensive because we require it for an extended period.<disp-quote><p id="Par43">&#x0201c;&#x02026;. Expensive (treatments) when you want to rinse your mouth for 16 shekels every time and use an expensive antibiotic&#x02026;.&#x0201d; (Female, Gaza, 63 years)</p><p id="Par44">&#x0201c;&#x02026;. I can&#x02019;t pay for dental treatment at private clinics &#x02026;.&#x0201d; (Male, Khanyounis, 58 years; Male, Khanyounis, 63 years; Female, Khanyounis, 72 years; Male, Khanyounis, 57 years)</p><p id="Par45">&#x0201c;&#x02026;Root canal treatment at private sector is expensive I can&#x02019;t pay for it, hope it found at governmental health care &#x02026;.&#x0201d; (Female, Gaza, 51 years; Female, Gaza, 60 years)</p></disp-quote></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Awareness about oral health complications related to T2DM</title><p id="Par46">According to Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>, more than half of individuals are aware of the issue and provide accurate replies regarding oral difficulties brought on by type 2 diabetes. Most people (91%) agree that"diabetic patients require to care more often than non-diabetics for their teeth and mouth"(93.6%), and they also affirm the necessity of routine dental visits. The statement"Diabetics have gum problems more often if their blood sugar is uncontrolled"is met with an incorrect response from more than one-third (36.4%) of respondents. Regarding oral signs of type 2 diabetes, the responses of the patients who took part varied. The majority of patients are unaware that T2DM may cause taste issues and an oral burning sensation (74.2% and 73.7%, respectively). Furthermore, about 60% of patients are unaware that type 2 diabetes causes mouth ulcers, foul breath, and bacterial and fungal infections in the mouth.
<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Awareness about oral health complications related to T2DM (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;= 376)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Awareness on oral health complications related to T2DM items</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Correct</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Incorrect</th></tr><tr><th align="left">n</th><th align="left">%</th><th align="left">n</th><th align="left">%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Diabetic patients require to care more often than non-diabetics for their teeth and mouth</td><td align="left">352</td><td align="left">93.6</td><td align="left">24</td><td align="left">6.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Regular dental visit is more important for diabetic patients than non-diabetics</td><td align="left">342</td><td align="left">91</td><td align="left">34</td><td align="left">9</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Diabetics have gum problems more often if their blood sugar is uncontrolled</td><td align="left">239</td><td align="left">63.6</td><td align="left">137</td><td align="left">36.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5">Oral problems associated with diabetes (prompted):</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mouth dryness</td><td align="left">304</td><td align="left">80.9</td><td align="left">72</td><td align="left">19.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Gums bleeding on brushing&#x02022;</td><td align="left">185</td><td align="left">49.2</td><td align="left">191</td><td align="left">50.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Mouth ulcers</td><td align="left">152</td><td align="left">40.4</td><td align="left">224</td><td align="left">59.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Bad odor</td><td align="left">153</td><td align="left">40.7</td><td align="left">223</td><td align="left">59.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Dental caries</td><td align="left">279</td><td align="left">74.2</td><td align="left">97</td><td align="left">25.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Oral bacterial infections</td><td align="left">142</td><td align="left">37.8</td><td align="left">234</td><td align="left">62.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Fungal mouth infections</td><td align="left">157</td><td align="left">41.8</td><td align="left">219</td><td align="left">58.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Loose teeth</td><td align="left">308</td><td align="left">81.9</td><td align="left">68</td><td align="left">18.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Taste problems</td><td align="left">97</td><td align="left">25.8</td><td align="left">279</td><td align="left">74.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Burning sensation</td><td align="left">99</td><td align="left">26.3</td><td align="left">277</td><td align="left">73.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Smoker diabetics have less serious gum disease than non-smokers. *</td><td align="left">304</td><td align="left">80.9</td><td align="left">72</td><td align="left">19.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;T2DM causes delayed wound healing at dental extraction sites</td><td align="left">282</td><td align="left">75</td><td align="left">94</td><td align="left">25</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;T2DM contributes more to developed dental abscess</td><td align="left">165</td><td align="left">43.9</td><td align="left">211</td><td align="left">56.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;as a diabetic, poor oral health condition affects badly the general health status</td><td align="left">339</td><td align="left">90.2</td><td align="left">37</td><td align="left">9.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Total</td><td align="left">57.61</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">42.39</td><td align="left"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>*</italic>a reverse question</p><p><italic>M</italic> mean, <italic>SD</italic> standard deviation</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par47">Few (2/13) respondents to the qualitative study disagreed with the link between type 2 diabetes and oral complications, indicating that DM has no effect on teeth. In exchange, the majority (11/13) concurred dental issues brought on by diabetes mellitus and how it affects not just teeth and oral cavities but also other systems.<disp-quote><p id="Par48">&#x0201c;Diabetic does not affect teeth, there is no relation between them&#x0201d; (Male, Khanyounis, 64 years).</p><p id="Par49">&#x0201c;Sure, diabetic disease affect my teeth and nerves and everything at my body&#x02026;&#x0201d; (Male, Khanyounis, 57 years)</p><p id="Par50">&#x0201c;There is direct relationship between diabetic disease and teeth problem, diabetic make bad odor for mouth&#x0201d; (Male, Khanyounis, 63 years)</p><p id="Par51">&#x0201c;High glucose affects my eyes, teeth and even my effort, it affects everything&#x02026;&#x0201d; (Female, Gaza, 51 years)</p></disp-quote></p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Oral health practices</title><p id="Par52">On a five-point Likert scale, the mean score for oral health practices is 1.71 (0.17), meaning that just 42.5% of respondents are dedicated to providing the greatest oral hygiene treatment. The majority of patients use a toothbrush and paste to clean their teeth and mouth (81% and 79.5%, respectively). On the other hand, 61.75% of people clean their teeth for at least two minutes each time, and 58.25% do so twice a day. One-third (32%) do go to the dentist twice a year for a checkup, and two-thirds (68.5%) change their toothbrush four times a year (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>).
<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Distribution of participants'responses regarding oral health practices (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;= 376)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Oral health practices items</th><th align="left">Never n(%)</th><th align="left">Rare n(%)</th><th align="left">Sometime n(%)</th><th align="left">Often n(%)</th><th align="left">Always n(%)</th><th align="left">M</th><th align="left">SD</th><th align="left">% mean</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">I brush my teeth twice a day</td><td align="left">67 (17.8)</td><td align="left">62 (16.5)</td><td align="left">84 (22.3)</td><td align="left">69 (18.4)</td><td align="left">94 (25)</td><td align="left">2.33</td><td align="left">1.34</td><td align="left">58.25</td></tr><tr><td align="left">I brush my teeth for at least two minutes each time</td><td align="left">62 (16.5)</td><td align="left">44 (11.7)</td><td align="left">77 (20.5)</td><td align="left">84 (22.3)</td><td align="left">109 (29)</td><td align="left">2.47</td><td align="left">1.35</td><td align="left">61.75</td></tr><tr><td align="left">I use toothbrush and paste to clean my teeth</td><td align="left">25 (6.6)</td><td align="left">24 (6.4)</td><td align="left">61 (16.2)</td><td align="left">37 (9.9)</td><td align="left">229 (60.9)</td><td align="left">3.18</td><td align="left">1.18</td><td align="left">79.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left">I follow the vertical technique of brushing the teeth</td><td align="left">66 (17.6)</td><td align="left">35 (9.3)</td><td align="left">101 (26.9)</td><td align="left">52 (13.8)</td><td align="left">122 (32.4)</td><td align="left">2.44</td><td align="left">1.40</td><td align="left">61.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left">I used to change toothbrush four times a year</td><td align="left">50 (13.3)</td><td align="left">40 (10.6)</td><td align="left">76 (20.3)</td><td align="left">41 (10.9)</td><td align="left">169 (44.9)</td><td align="left">2.74</td><td align="left">1.38</td><td align="left">68.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left">I use mouthwash to preserve and keep my gum healthy</td><td align="left">215 (57.2)</td><td align="left">81 (21.5)</td><td align="left">46 (12.2)</td><td align="left">15 (4)</td><td align="left">19 (5.1)</td><td align="left">1.00</td><td align="left">1.24</td><td align="left">25.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left">I remove interdental debris using dental floss or toothpick once a day</td><td align="left">167 (44.4)</td><td align="left">89 (23.7)</td><td align="left">52 (13.8)</td><td align="left">23 (6.1)</td><td align="left">45 (12)</td><td align="left">1.41</td><td align="left">1.41</td><td align="left">35.25</td></tr><tr><td align="left">I clean my tongue</td><td align="left">224 (59.6)</td><td align="left">39 (10.4)</td><td align="left">59 (15.7)</td><td align="left">16 (4.2)</td><td align="left">38 (10.1)</td><td align="left">1.05</td><td align="left">1.39</td><td align="left">26.25</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Using Silica Powder for tooth cleaning</td><td align="left">338 (89.9)</td><td align="left">18 (4.8)</td><td align="left">12 (3.1)</td><td align="left">1 (0.3)</td><td align="left">7 (1.9)</td><td align="left">0.24</td><td align="left">0.76</td><td align="left">6.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Using Miswak for tooth cleaning</td><td align="left">224 (59.6)</td><td align="left">69 (18.4)</td><td align="left">54 (14.3)</td><td align="left">14 (3.7)</td><td align="left">15 (4)</td><td align="left">0.93</td><td align="left">1.20</td><td align="left">23.25</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Using finger and paste for tooth cleaning</td><td align="left">286 (76.1)</td><td align="left">19 (5.1)</td><td align="left">43 (11.4)</td><td align="left">17 (4.5)</td><td align="left">11 (2.9)</td><td align="left">0.58</td><td align="left">1.09</td><td align="left">14.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Using rinse with salty water for tooth cleaning</td><td align="left">105 (27.9)</td><td align="left">51 (13.6)</td><td align="left">110 (29.2)</td><td align="left">63 (16.8)</td><td align="left">47 (12.5)</td><td align="left">1.86</td><td align="left">1.33</td><td align="left">46.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Using rinse with herbs for tooth cleaning</td><td align="left">236 (62.8)</td><td align="left">50 (13.3)</td><td align="left">53 (14.1)</td><td align="left">17 (4.5)</td><td align="left">20 (5.3)</td><td align="left">0.90</td><td align="left">1.25</td><td align="left">22.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Using rinse with water only for tooth cleaning</td><td align="left">15 (4)</td><td align="left">9 (2.4)</td><td align="left">79 (21)</td><td align="left">50 (13.3)</td><td align="left">223 (59.3)</td><td align="left">3.24</td><td align="left">1.06</td><td align="left">81.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left">I used to visit a dentist, for checkup, twice a year</td><td align="left">180 (47.9)</td><td align="left">94 (25)</td><td align="left">45 (12)</td><td align="left">25 (6.6)</td><td align="left">32 (8.5)</td><td align="left">1.28</td><td align="left">1.34</td><td align="left">2.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Total</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">1.71</td><td align="left">0.52</td><td align="left">42.5</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>M</italic> mean, <italic>SD</italic> standard deviation</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par53">Most interviewed patients do brush their teeth with toothpaste twice daily. Few used medical mouth wash, however based on medical advice. Others have used salty water to relief pain from gums. One patient stated that brushing teeth is based on his mood status.<disp-quote><p id="Par54">&#x0201c;&#x02026;I rinse my mouth every day 3 times and brush my teeth after meal and before bed&#x02026;&#x0201d; (Male, Khanyounis, 63 years)</p><p id="Par55">&#x0201c;&#x02026;I just clean my teeth with water&#x02026;&#x0201d; (Female, Khanyounis, 72 years)</p></disp-quote></p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Oral health problems</title><p id="Par56">According to the qualitative study, the majority of patients who were interviewed had a variety of gum and dental issues, such as loss, mobility, and dental carries. Few patients did not have oral and dental issues, and five patients lost all of their teeth. Only two patients reported having ulcers and foul breath.<disp-quote><p id="Par57">&#x0201c;&#x02026;I haven&#x02019;t any teeth at my mouth, all are falling&#x02026;&#x0201d; (Male, Khanyounis,58 years; Female, Khanyounis,72 years; Male, Khanyounis, 64 years)</p><p id="Par58">&#x0201c;&#x02026;my teeth were prosthetic, all are bad&#x02026;&#x0201d; (Male, Khanyounis, 63 years)</p><p id="Par59">&#x0201c;&#x02026;from two months ago, I went to dentist, and he said to me that your teeth are good&#x02026;&#x0201d; (Female, Gaza, 63 years)</p><p id="Par60">&#x0201c;&#x02026;most of my teeth are mobile &#x02026;&#x0201d; (Female, Khanyounis, 54 years)</p><p id="Par61">&#x0201c;&#x02026;my teeth and gum are good, and I just need a restoration&#x02026;&#x0201d; (Male, Gaza, 47 years)</p><p id="Par62">&#x0201c;&#x02026;I extracted more than one tooth after I am diagnosed with diabetic disease &#x02026;&#x0201d; (Female, Gaza, 60 years)</p></disp-quote></p><p id="Par63">The inability to chew food is a common complaint among patients with gum and dental issues. Additionally, they have been denied access to all the things they used to consume before to the onset of oral difficulties. Some of them believe that since sugar and carbohydrate products deteriorate their oral and physical health, their nutritional condition needs to be corrected and adjusted by consuming fewer of them. For two of them, diabetes has no impact on their nutritional health.<disp-quote><p id="Par64">&#x0201c;&#x02026;when you avoid eating sugar, your teeth and health will be good&#x02026;&#x0201d; (Female, Gaza, 51 years)</p><p id="Par65">&#x0201c;&#x02026;diabetic disease didn&#x02019;t affect my nutrition and my teeth&#x02026;&#x0201d; (Female, Khanyounis, 54 years)</p><p id="Par66">&#x0201c;&#x02026;I face difficulty with chewing food &#x02026;&#x0201d; (Male, Khanyounis,58 years; Female, Gaza, 50 years)</p><p id="Par67">&#x0201c;&#x02026;I feel sad when I look to my teeth, all are fallen and then I can&#x02019;t eat&#x02026;&#x0201d; (Female, Khanyouunis, 72 years)</p><p id="Par68">&#x0201c;&#x02026;my nutrition system is change, I stopped eating sugary and chocolate&#x02026;&#x0201d; (Female, Gaza, 60 years)</p></disp-quote></p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Patients&#x02019; experiences</title><p id="Par69">For patients with diabetes, patient follow-up is crucial. In fact, the majority of patients interviewed stated that they are dissatisfied with the follow-up system that the dentists give and that PHC dental clinics lack an appointment system. Furthermore, if there are dentists at their place of employment, they do not schedule follow-up appointments.<disp-quote><p id="Par70">"&#x02026;There is no follow up but only extraction (tooth), and if you need management they say (dentists) do it outside&#x02026;"(Male, Khanyounis, 58 years)</p><p id="Par71">"&#x02026;I rarely follow at PHCs, I follow mainly in private clinics&#x02026;"(Female, Khanyounis,54 years)</p><p id="Par72">&#x0201c;&#x02026;no one (doctors at PHCs) have asked me about my teeth or referred me to dentist for checkup&#x02026;&#x0201d; (Female, Gaza, 50 years)</p></disp-quote></p><p id="Par73">Many patients complained about poor time management in between appointments, long wait times, and the fact that dentists only checked their teeth briefly before referring them to private clinics for further dental care.<disp-quote><p id="Par74">&#x0201c;&#x02026;I don&#x02019;t like to take turn (in governmental dental clinic), I came just when I am so tired from dental pain&#x02026;&#x0201d; (Female, Gaza, 63 years)</p><p id="Par75">&#x0201c;&#x02026;you should go so early to get number for your turn &#x02026;.&#x0201d; (Male, Gaza, 47 years) &#x0201c;&#x02026;Dentist doesn&#x02019;t want to work or even treat us&#x02026;.&#x0201d; (Female, Gaza, 50 years)</p></disp-quote></p><p id="Par76">Respondents expressed discontent with the actions of dentists. They expressed dissatisfaction with the lack of information provided by dentists regarding how to appropriately treat oral issues. Additionally, glycemic level and medical status are not inquired about by dentists. Even the impact of diabetes treatment on dental health is not covered. Communication with dentists is satisfactory for two participants.<disp-quote><p id="Par77">&#x0201c;&#x02026;they advise me how to brush and rinse my mouth and before they work, they ask me and care about me &#x02026;&#x0201d; (Female, Gaza, 63 years)</p><p id="Par78">&#x0201c;&#x02026;they (dentists) didn&#x02019;t give me any information&#x02026;&#x0201d; (Male, Khanyounis,64; Female Khanyounis,72 years; Female, Gaza, 51 years; Male, Gaza, 47 years)</p><p id="Par79">&#x0201c;&#x02026;they (dentists) didn&#x02019;t tell us how we should care&#x02026;&#x0201d; (Male, Khanyounis, 58 years; Male, Khanyounis, 72 years; Male, Khanyounis, 64 years)</p><p id="Par80">&#x0201c;&#x02026;the care of dentist didn&#x02019;t change when he know that I am diabetic, just he answers me when I asked&#x02026;&#x0201d; (Male, Khanyounis, 63 years)</p></disp-quote></p><p id="Par81">PHCs were criticized by patients because they lack established health education programs at this time, and because dentists either don't provide any information at all or supply it enough, patients mostly rely on other sources like websites, friends, or television to learn about the effects of diabetes mellitus on oral health.<disp-quote><p id="Par82">&#x0201c;&#x02026;I get my information about diabetic disease and its effect from T.V, internet and my neighbors&#x02026;&#x0201d; (Female, Khanyounis, 54 years; Female, Gaza, 60 years)</p><p id="Par83">&#x0201c;&#x02026;they didn&#x02019;t give us health promotion program, or any information related to our status&#x02026;&#x0201d; (Male, Khanyounis, 58 years)</p><p id="Par84">&#x0201c;&#x02026;I always read about my disease from internet&#x02026;&#x0201d; (Female, Gaza, 63 years)</p><p id="Par85">&#x0201c;&#x02026;we go, and they didn&#x02019;t even talk to us, they just examine us and then say goodbye&#x02026;&#x0201d; (Female, Gaza, 50 years)</p></disp-quote></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par86">The World Health Organization has declared diabetes mellitus (DM) a pandemic due to its sharp rise in prevalence worldwide. As a result, the bidirectional association between diabetes mellitus and dental health, particularly periodontitis, concerns medical practitioners, including dentists. Good knowledge and positive attitudes are recognized to have an impact on effective oral practices [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. People with Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus require an assessment of their degree of awareness regarding the oral symptoms of the disease and its associated consequences on oral health in order to establish appropriate health care recommendations, patient education, and health care delivery to diabetic patients.</p><p id="Par87">Patients in this study expressed favorable opinions on the risks and consequences of oral health issues, as well as the advantages and disadvantages of maintaining good oral hygiene. In Ethiopia, 25.5% of participants believed that periodontal disease could lead to heart disease, and 18.8% agreed that a person with diabetes has a higher risk of developing periodontal disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. 72% of Chinese people also believed that they were at risk for diabetic complications, such as oral manifestations, and its risk factors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. The majority of Turkish patients were aware of their vulnerability to oral problems from diabetes mellitus, such as dry mouth, tooth decay, bad breath, and bleeding gums. Other problems, such as fungal infections, taste impairment, and oral ulcers, were less likely to occur, though [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Despite the severity of periodontitis itself, Abdullah and his colleagues found that patients have rated type 2 diabetes as more serious than the disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. 64% of Ethiopian patients believed that their DM was the cause of their severe oral health issues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. In exchange, fewer patients expressed satisfaction with the degree of DM oral cavity problems, such as bleeding gums and tooth movement [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Studies from Saudi Arabia and Kuwait also reported the positive opinions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. We did not study the link between smoking and periodontitis, although literature highlighted the direct effect of smoking on oral health especially periodontitis. We recommend further studies on this issue.</p><p id="Par88">Sahile et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>] found that 53% of participants thought that practicing good dental hygiene would help them avoid developing periodontitis. In a different study that involved sizable groups of diabetic patients, the patients felt that maintaining good dental hygiene led to a significant decrease in gingival bleeding and mouth inflammation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. The literature has documented numerous obstacles. Dental expenses were the main reason why people avoided or postponed dental visits, according to Poudel et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>].</p><p id="Par89">Furthermore, 71% and 70% of individuals, respectively, confirmed that they lacked insurance coverage and access to dental treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. In a similar vein, Fadel et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>] from Saudi Arabia documented differences in the frequency of dental visits and oral health practices, with the primary disadvantages being lengthy wait times and expensive treatment. In fact, dental and oral health practices were strongly predicted by self-efficacy and knowledge of the consequences of type 2 diabetes on oral health [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. Inadequate training and follow-up by dentists were also addressed, along with worry and dread [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. According to a study by Cankaya et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>] in Turkey, medical practitioners don't give enough advice about dental health care. Additionally, practitioners did not adequately explain the significance of interdental cleaning, maintaining good oral health, brushing teeth, and oral examinations. We think that in busy practices, dentists may have limited time for each patient, leading to a focus on immediate concerns rather than comprehensive education. In addition, dentists might assume that patients already understand the importance of interdental cleaning and good oral hygiene, resulting in less emphasis on these topics. Some dentists may struggle with effectively communicating complex information in a way that is easily understood by patients, and also some patients may not actively engage in conversations about their oral health, leading dentists to focus on more pressing clinical issues instead.</p><p id="Par90">We found 57.6% of participants are aware of how type 2 diabetes affects dental health. This was lower than the findings from Kuwait [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>] and Iran [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>], but it was almost identical to the findings from Egypt [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>], Tanzania [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>], and the USA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>] and Saudi Arabia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. The research also noted a lack of information about oral health [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Saudis had a low level of awareness, according to Ismail and Ali [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. In exchange, 82.7% of participants knew that diabetic people require specialized medical care, and 63.4% of individuals knew that diabetes affects dental health [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. In Saudi Arabia, diabetic patients are aware of the importance of controlling their diabetes in order to minimize oral health complications, but only a small percentage of them visit the dentist on a regular basis. Variations within the same country could be attributed to the weakness of their primary health facilities across the country and the limited lack of educational campaigns. The results of these different studies can be attributed to differences in methodology and the study population. Furthermore, many patients may not receive adequate education about the connection between diabetes and oral health during their diagnosis or ongoing treatment. Insufficient communication from healthcare providers, including dentists and diabetes educators, can lead to gaps in knowledge about oral health risks. Patients with lower health literacy may struggle to understand medical information, making it difficult to grasp the importance of oral health in diabetes management.</p><p id="Par91">Similar to data from South Asia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>] and Tanzania [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>], the majority of participants had a good attitude about oral health, although their oral health-related practices were low (42,5%). The results of this study do show that maintaining excellent dental health depends on a variety of factors, including practices linked to oral health, rather than only one's attitude. The literature found that DM patients'oral hygiene practices varied similarly. 58% of the patients in our study brushed their teeth twice a day, falling between the 24.2% and 95.3% range reported in the literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. Contrary to Cankaya and his colleagues'findings, one-third of our patients utilized toothpicks to remove interdental debris [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Despite the fact that some dentists advise against using toothpicks, many diabetic patients still using them for cleaning [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. As a source of speculation, while patients may understand the importance of oral health, they might lack specific knowledge about effective practices, such as proper brushing techniques or the importance of interdental cleaning. Some diabetes patients may experience complications, such as neuropathy or mobility issues, making it physically challenging to maintain good oral hygiene practices.</p><p id="Par92">The percentage of T2DM patients who visit the dentist on a regular basis varies greatly [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. Just 2% of T2DM patients in our study saw their dentists every six months. The socioeconomic condition of the patients that is, their degree of education and financial resources as well as aspects pertaining to the health facility may be the attributing factors for low dental clinic attendance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Patients with diabetes must see a dentist on a regular basis to prevent tooth pain and infections that could impair metabolic control, as well as to discover oral issues associated with the disease early. Patients in this study expressed dissatisfaction at the lack of an appointment system, which is in line with other reports [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>].</p><p id="Par93">We found that there are also deficiencies in the individuals who are referred to dentists by their attending physicians. A study from Tazania and Australia also found that people with diabetes mellitus are not often referred to dentists [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. The low number of referrals could mean that doctors are unaware of the strong link between diabetes mellitus and oral health, or that the health system lacks official clinical standards to assist doctors in choosing which dental specialists to recommend patients to. In another hand, high number of patients seen by physicians may influence patients to receive the right care including being seen by dentists.</p><p id="Par94">According to numerous interviewers, the lack of education programs at PHCs may be the reason why patients are not well-informed about the complications of diabetes mellitus on dental health. Patients might, however, rely on other sources, including TV shows, the internet, and friends and family, which could be false or misleading. The majority of patients who were interviewed concurred that dental evaluations and appointments should be scheduled during medical visits. According to the literature, DM patients believe that doctors, nurses, and other healthcare professionals are ineffective at informing them about the oral problems of the disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>].</p><p id="Par95">In summary, the findings highlight significant gaps in patients'awareness and perceptions regarding oral health in the context of diabetes mellitus. While a majority acknowledge their susceptibility to oral health issues and recognize the severity of potential complications, a considerable percentage still perceive barriers that hinder effective oral health practices. The inadequate awareness of oral health complications and poor oral health habits suggest a need for enhanced educational initiatives and targeted interventions. The qualitative insights emphasize the importance of dental care service quality, effective patient-dentist interactions, and the promotion of self-care practices. Addressing these factors is essential to improve patient outcomes and foster better oral health practices among individuals with diabetes, ultimately leading to a reduction in oral health complications and an enhancement of overall well-being.</p><p id="Par96">There are limitations to the study: 1) although the qualitative study had a modest number of participants, it reached saturation information and represented the two primary health center PHCs in the Gaza Strip. 2) the nature of cross-sectional studies which restrict the causal linkages between variables. The study's strength is that it's the first mixed-method design to use a qualitative approach to investigate patients'oral health experiences. Second, self-report responses are not subject to criticism because data collection was conducted through face to face interviews. Thirdly, conclusions drawn from this study could be used in other contexts. The study offered some metrics for the parameters under investigation and could be a useful tool for enhancing the oral health care of diabetics.</p><sec id="Sec19"><title>Policy implications</title><p id="Par97">
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p id="Par98">Integration of oral health into diabetes management policies: national healthcare guidelines should formally integrate oral health assessments into routine diabetes care protocols because recognizing the bidirectional relationship between diabetes and oral health, especially periodontal disease, will help promote holistic management and early intervention</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par99">Development of targeted public health education campaigns: launching culturally sensitive and accessible educational initiatives focused on raising awareness of the link between diabetes and oral health. Addressing knowledge gaps and misperceptions can empower patients to engage in preventive behaviors and seek timely dental care.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par100">Subsidized or covered dental services for patients with DM: expanding insurance coverage or provide subsidies for routine dental visits and preventive care for people with diabetes, because financial barriers were identified as a key perceived obstacle. Removing cost as a barrier can encourage regular dental check-ups and early treatment.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par101">Inter-professional collaboration and training: implementing policies that encourage collaboration between medical and dental professionals, including cross-training on diabetes and oral health, as better communication and shared knowledge among providers enhance coordinated care and improve patient guidance.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par102">Quality assurance standards for dental care providers: introducing quality assurance standards that include patient satisfaction, communication effectiveness, and diabetes-specific care protocols in dental practices. Evidences showed that improving patient-dentist interactions were emphasized as critical in the qualitative data; policies should support continuous provider education and accountability.</p></list-item></list></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec21" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="12903_2025_6153_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><caption><p>Supplementary Material 1.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors would like to thank the Director General of Human Resources Development and Research Department at the Ministry of Health, Gaza for facilitating data collection process.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>Conception and design: AE and AF, Provision of study materials: AF and AE; Literature review: AE, MR, Data analysis: AE, AF and MR, Manuscript writing: AE, AF and MR, Final approval of manuscript: AE, AF and MR. All authors have critically reviewed and approved the final draft and are responsible for the content and similarity index of the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>No funding.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The datasets used and/or analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics and consent to participate</title><p id="Par103">Ethical approval was obtained from the Helsinki Committee of the Palestinian Health Research Council (PHRC/HC/858/21). Moreover, permission was obtained from the General Directorate of Human Resources at MoH to conduct the study in its PHCs (No: 686506). Patients were asked to sign an attached consent prior filling the questionnaire. Legally Authorized Representatives of illiterate participants, literate companions from family members, provided informed consent for the study. Information regarding study'objectives was given to patients. Anonymity and confidentiality and voluntary participation were ensured. Informed consent to participate was obtained from all of the participants in the study. Similar steps were applied to qualitative study. The researcher sought permission from key informants to record interviews. Data are kept, for confidentiality, with second author's closet and will be discarded after two years. Clinical trial number: not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par104">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par105">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">GBD 2021 Diabetes Collaborators. Global, regional, and national burden of diabetes from 1990 to 2021, with projections of prevalence to 2050: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2021. The Lancet, 2023;402:203-234</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Standl, E., Khunti, K., Hansen, T. B., &#x00026; Schnell, O. The global epidemics of diabetes in the 21st century: Current situation and perspectives. European journal of preventive cardiology, 2019; 26(2_suppl), 7&#x02013;14.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Moien Abdul Basith Khan, hashim MJ, king JK, Govendra RD, Mustafa H, Kaabl JA. Epidemiology of Type 2 Diabetes &#x02013; Global Burden of Disease and Forecasted Trends. J Epidemiol Glob Health. 2020 Mar; 10(1): 107&#x02013;11.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">El Sharif N., Imam A. Current Status of Diabetes in Palestine: Epidemiology, Management, and Healthcare System. In: Laher I. (eds) Handbook of Healthcare in the Arab World. Springer, Cham, 2019. 10.1007/978-3-319-74365-3_43-2. Online ISBN 978&#x02013;3&#x02013;319&#x02013;74365&#x02013;3.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jimenez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>FB</given-names></name><name><surname>Marino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Joshipura</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Type 2 diabetes mellitus and 20-year incidence of periodontitis and tooth loss</article-title><source>Diabetes Res Clin Pract</source><year>2012</year><volume>98</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>494</fpage><lpage>500</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.diabres.2012.09.039</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23040240</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Jimenez M, Hu FB, Marino M, Li Y, Joshipura KJ. Type 2 diabetes mellitus and 20-year incidence of periodontitis and tooth loss. Diabetes Res Clin Pract. 2012;98(3):494&#x02013;500.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23040240</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Newman, G.M., Takei, H.H. and Carranza, F. Carranza&#x02019;s Clinical Periodontology. Elsevier Inc, 12th edition. 2015.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alqadi</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diabetes Mellitus and Its Influence on Oral Health: Review</article-title><source>Diabetes Metab Syndr Obes</source><year>2024</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>120</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/DMSO.S426671</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38222034</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Alqadi SF. Diabetes Mellitus and Its Influence on Oral Health: Review. Diabetes Metab Syndr Obes. 2024;17:107&#x02013;20.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38222034</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yuen</surname><given-names>VG</given-names></name><name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Withers</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Brayer</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Mustafa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>McNeill</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Glucose lowering effect of montbret in A in Zucker Diabetic Fatty rats</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biochem</source><year>2016</year><volume>411</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>373</fpage><lpage>381</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11010-015-2599-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26547551</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Yuen VG, Coleman J, Withers SG, Andersen RJ, Brayer GD, Mustafa S, McNeill JH. Glucose lowering effect of montbret in A in Zucker Diabetic Fatty rats. Mol Cell Biochem. 2016;411(1):373&#x02013;81.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26547551</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Shrivastava PK, Uppal Simran, Popli DB, Sircar K. Bidirectional relationship between oral health and diabetes mellitus: a knowledge, attitude, and practice survey. J Dent Res Rev 2022; 9:249&#x02013;56.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Glick M, Greenberg MS, Lockhart PB, Challacombe SJ. Textbook Burket's Oral Medicine 13<sup>th</sup> edition. John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Inc. June 2021.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Research in dental health education and health promotion: a review of the literature</article-title><source>Health Educ Q</source><year>1994</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>83</fpage><lpage>102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/109019819402100109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8188495</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Brown LF. Research in dental health education and health promotion: a review of the literature. Health Educ Q. 1994;21:83&#x02013;102.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8188495</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alqedra</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Aljeesh</surname><given-names>YI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Periodontal Status of Type 2 Diabetic Patients Attending UNRWA Health Centers in Gaza Governorates</article-title><source>Sci J Res Dentistry</source><year>2020</year><volume>4</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>015</fpage><lpage>022</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Alqedra E, Aljeesh YI. Periodontal Status of Type 2 Diabetic Patients Attending UNRWA Health Centers in Gaza Governorates. Sci J Res Dentistry. 2020;4(1):015&#x02013;22.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alqedra</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Aljeesh</surname><given-names>YI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DMFT Index of Type 2 Diabetic Patients Attending UNRWA Health Centers in Gaza Governorates</article-title><source>Sci J Res Dentistry</source><year>2020</year><volume>4</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>007</fpage><lpage>014</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Alqedra E, Aljeesh YI. DMFT Index of Type 2 Diabetic Patients Attending UNRWA Health Centers in Gaza Governorates. Sci J Res Dentistry. 2020;4(1):007&#x02013;14.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality (AHRQ). (2010). TEAMS STEPS: National Implementation. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://teamstepps.ahrq.gov/index.htm">http://teamstepps.ahrq.gov/index.htm</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sahile</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Mgutshini</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayehu</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oral Health Screening Status of Diabetes Patients in Selected Hospitals of Addis Ababa, Ethiopia, 2018</article-title><source>Patient Relat Outcome Meas</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>173</fpage><lpage>180</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/PROM.S269292</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33061726</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Sahile AT, Mgutshini T, Ayehu SM. Oral Health Screening Status of Diabetes Patients in Selected Hospitals of Addis Ababa, Ethiopia, 2018. Patient Relat Outcome Meas. 2020;11:173&#x02013;80.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33061726</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The relationship of health beliefs and complication prevention behaviors of Chinese individuals with Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus</article-title><source>Diabetes Res Clin Pract</source><year>2004</year><volume>66</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>77</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.diabres.2004.02.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15364164</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Tan MY. The relationship of health beliefs and complication prevention behaviors of Chinese individuals with Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus. Diabetes Res Clin Pract. 2004;66(1):71&#x02013;7.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15364164</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>&#x000c7;ankaya</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x000fc;neri</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyac&#x00131;o&#x0011f;lu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Awareness of oral complications and oral hygiene habits of subjects with diagnosed Diabetes Mellitus</article-title><source>Balkan Journal of Dental Medicine</source><year>2018</year><volume>22</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>138</fpage><lpage>145</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2478/bjdm-2018-0024</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">&#x000c7;ankaya H, G&#x000fc;neri P, Epstein JB, Boyac&#x00131;o&#x0011f;lu H. Awareness of oral complications and oral hygiene habits of subjects with diagnosed Diabetes Mellitus. Balkan Journal of Dental Medicine. 2018;22(3):138&#x02013;45.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez-Moles</surname><given-names>M&#x000c1;</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramos-Garc&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>State of Evidence on Oral Health Problems in Diabetic Patients: A Critical Review of the Literature</article-title><source>J Clin Med</source><year>2021</year><volume>10</volume><issue>22</issue><fpage>5383</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm10225383</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34830663</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Gonz&#x000e1;lez-Moles M&#x000c1;, Ramos-Garc&#x000ed;a P. State of Evidence on Oral Health Problems in Diabetic Patients: A Critical Review of the Literature. J Clin Med. 2021;10(22):5383.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34830663</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alhuwais</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Alkanderi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jospeh</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Attitudes and awareness of diabetic patients in Kuwait towards their oral health</article-title><source>Int J Oral Dent Health</source><year>2021</year><volume>7</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>133</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.23937/2469-5734/1510133</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Alhuwais M, Alkanderi A, Jospeh B. Attitudes and awareness of diabetic patients in Kuwait towards their oral health. Int J Oral Dent Health. 2021;7(3):133.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sohal</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kambole</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Owibingire</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oral Health-Related Knowledge, Attitudes, and Practices of Diabetic Patients in Tanzania</article-title><source>Int Dent J</source><year>2025</year><volume>75</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>256</fpage><lpage>262</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.identj.2024.06.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38942616</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">Sohal KS, Kambole R, Owibingire SS. Oral Health-Related Knowledge, Attitudes, and Practices of Diabetic Patients in Tanzania. Int Dent J. 2025;75(1):256&#x02013;62.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38942616</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holmer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wid&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallin Bengtsson</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wohlfart</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Steen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sj&#x000f6;berg</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improved general and oral health in diabetic patients by an okinawan-based nordic diet: A pilot study</article-title><source>Int J Mol Sci</source><year>2018</year><volume>19</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1949</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms19071949</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29970834</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Holmer H, Wid&#x000e9;n C, Wallin Bengtsson V, Coleman M, Wohlfart B, Steen S, Sj&#x000f6;berg K. Improved general and oral health in diabetic patients by an okinawan-based nordic diet: A pilot study. Int J Mol Sci. 2018;19(7):1949.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29970834</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Poudel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Arora</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>VW</given-names></name><name><surname>Flack</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>George</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oral Health Status, Knowledge and Behaviours of People with Diabetes in Sydney, Australia</article-title><source>Int J Environ Res Public Health</source><year>2021</year><volume>18</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>3464</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph18073464</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33810479</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">Poudel P, Griffiths R, Arora A, Wong VW, Flack JR, Barker G, George A. Oral Health Status, Knowledge and Behaviours of People with Diabetes in Sydney, Australia. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2021;18(7):3464.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33810479</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shimpi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Glurich</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Panny</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Acharya</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Knowledgeability, attitude, and practice behaviors of primary care providers toward managing patients&#x02019; oral health care in medical practice: Wisconsin statewide survey</article-title><source>J Am Dent Assoc</source><year>2019</year><volume>150</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>863</fpage><lpage>872</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.adaj.2019.05.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31446976</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Shimpi N, Glurich I, Panny A, Acharya A. Knowledgeability, attitude, and practice behaviors of primary care providers toward managing patients&#x02019; oral health care in medical practice: Wisconsin statewide survey. J Am Dent Assoc. 2019;150(10):863&#x02013;72.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31446976</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fadel</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name><name><surname>Sultan</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Alrasheedi</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Alsadiq</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kattuah</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Malik</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Rhbeini</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Self-perceived oral health and access to care in diabetic and non-diabetic women: A qualitative study</article-title><source>Saudi Journal of Biological Sciences</source><year>2021</year><volume>28</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>210</fpage><lpage>216</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sjbs.2020.09.050</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33424299</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">Fadel HT, Sultan RA, Alrasheedi LM, Alsadiq JG, Kattuah RT, Al-Malik MI, Rhbeini YA. Self-perceived oral health and access to care in diabetic and non-diabetic women: A qualitative study. Saudi Journal of Biological Sciences. 2021;28(1):210&#x02013;6.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33424299</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Malekmahmoodi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shamsi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Roozbahani</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A randomized controlled trial of an educational intervention to promote oral and dental health of patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus</article-title><source>BMC Public Health</source><year>2020</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>287</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-020-8395-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32131790</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="journal">Malekmahmoodi M, Shamsi M, Roozbahani N, et al. A randomized controlled trial of an educational intervention to promote oral and dental health of patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus. BMC Public Health. 2020;20:287.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32131790</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR26" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Dionne</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dental fear and anxiety as a barrier to accessing oral health care among patients with special health care needs</article-title><source>Spec Care Dentist</source><year>1998</year><volume>18</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>88</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1754-4505.1998.tb00910.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9680917</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26" publication-type="journal">Gordon SM, Dionne RA, Snyder J. Dental fear and anxiety as a barrier to accessing oral health care among patients with special health care needs. Spec Care Dentist. 1998;18(2):88&#x02013;92.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9680917</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Yonel, Zehra &#x00026; Batt, Joanna &#x00026; Jane, Rosemarie &#x00026; Cerullo, Enzo &#x00026; Gray, Laura &#x00026; Dietrich, Thomas &#x00026; Chapple, Iain. The Role of the Oral Healthcare Team in Identification of Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus: A Systematic Review. Current Oral Health Reports, 2020, 7. 10.1007/s40496-020-00250-w.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR28" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kakooei</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Afzali</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Parirokh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kakooei</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mostafavi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nekouei</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The knowledge and attitude of diabetic patients regarding oral and dental disorders in Kerman diabetes clinics</article-title><source>J Dent (Shiraz)</source><year>2020</year><volume>21</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>201</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33062813</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28" publication-type="journal">Kakooei S, Afzali S, Parirokh M, Kakooei S, Mostafavi M, Nekouei A. The knowledge and attitude of diabetic patients regarding oral and dental disorders in Kerman diabetes clinics. J Dent (Shiraz). 2020;21(3):195&#x02013;201.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33062813</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR29" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ismaeil</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diabetic patients knowledge, attitude and practice toward oral health</article-title><source>J Educ Pract</source><year>2013</year><volume>4</volume><issue>20</issue><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>25</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29" publication-type="journal">Ismaeil FM, Ali N. Diabetic patients knowledge, attitude and practice toward oral health. J Educ Pract. 2013;4(20):19&#x02013;25.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR30" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yuen</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bandyopadhyay</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Magruder</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Salinas</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>London</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oral health knowledge and behavior among adults with diabetes</article-title><source>Diabetes Res Clin Pract</source><year>2009</year><volume>86</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>239</fpage><lpage>246</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.diabres.2009.09.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19800143</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30" publication-type="journal">Yuen HK, Wolf BJ, Bandyopadhyay D, Magruder KM, Salinas CF, London SD. Oral health knowledge and behavior among adults with diabetes. Diabetes Res Clin Pract. 2009;86(3):239&#x02013;46.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19800143</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR31" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mian</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name><name><surname>Rashidi</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></name><name><surname>Alshammary</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Al Zubaidi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Al Shammary</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Siddiqui</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Amin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oral Health-related Knowledge and Assessment of Oral Health Status of Diabetic Patients Attending Dental Clinic at College of Dentistry, Hail, Kingdom of Saudi Arabia</article-title><source>Journal of Contemporary Dental Practices</source><year>2020</year><volume>21</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>78</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5005/jp-journals-10024-2729</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR31" publication-type="journal">Mian RI, Rashidi FF, Alshammary TM, Al Zubaidi S, Al Shammary F, Siddiqui AA, Amin J, Khan RS. Oral Health-related Knowledge and Assessment of Oral Health Status of Diabetic Patients Attending Dental Clinic at College of Dentistry, Hail, Kingdom of Saudi Arabia. Journal of Contemporary Dental Practices. 2020;21(1):78&#x02013;82.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR32" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Poudel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rawal</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Oral health knowledge, attitudes and practices of people living with diabetes in South Asia: a scoping review</article-title><source>Int J Environ Res Public Health</source><year>2022</year><volume>19</volume><issue>21</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph192113851</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32" publication-type="journal">Poudel P, Rawal LB, Kong A, et al. Oral health knowledge, attitudes and practices of people living with diabetes in South Asia: a scoping review. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2022;19(21):1&#x02013;21.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR33" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aky&#x000fc;z</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yarat</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bayer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ipbuker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diabetic patient&#x02019;s knowledge level on oral health and habits (questionnaire)</article-title><source>OHDMBSC</source><year>2004</year><volume>3</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>14</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR33" publication-type="journal">Aky&#x000fc;z S, Yarat A, Bayer H, Ipbuker A. Diabetic patient&#x02019;s knowledge level on oral health and habits (questionnaire). OHDMBSC. 2004;3(3):11&#x02013;4.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR34" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Habashneh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Khader</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hammad</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Almuradi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Knowledge and awareness about diabetes and periodontal health among Jordanians</article-title><source>J Diabetes Complications</source><year>2010</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>409</fpage><lpage>414</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jdiacomp.2009.06.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19628414</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR34" publication-type="journal">Habashneh R, Khader Y, Hammad MM, Almuradi M. Knowledge and awareness about diabetes and periodontal health among Jordanians. J Diabetes Complications. 2010;24:409&#x02013;14.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19628414</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR35" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kamath</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Nayak</surname><given-names>SU</given-names></name><name><surname>Pai</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Shenoy</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Knowledge and awareness of oral health among diabetic patients-a crosssectional study from Mangalore City</article-title><source>Int J Diabetes Dev Ctries</source><year>2015</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13410-015-0334-z</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR35" publication-type="journal">Kamath DG, Nayak SU, Pai KK, Shenoy R. Knowledge and awareness of oral health among diabetic patients-a crosssectional study from Mangalore City. Int J Diabetes Dev Ctries. 2015;35:71&#x02013;5.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR36" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bowyer</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Sutcliffe</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ireland</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindenmeyer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gadsby</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Graveney</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Oral health awareness in adult patients with diabetes: a questionnaire study</article-title><source>Br Dent J</source><year>2011</year><volume>23</volume><issue>211</issue><fpage>E12</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.bdj.2011.769</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR36" publication-type="journal">Bowyer V, Sutcliffe P, Ireland R, Lindenmeyer A, Gadsby R, Graveney M, et al. Oral health awareness in adult patients with diabetes: a questionnaire study. Br Dent J. 2011;23(211):E12.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR37" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kanli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanbur</surname><given-names>NO</given-names></name><name><surname>Dural</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Derman</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of oral health behaviors and socioeconomic factors on a group of Turkish adolescents</article-title><source>Quintessence Int</source><year>2008</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>e26</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18551208</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR37" publication-type="journal">Kanli A, Kanbur NO, Dural S, Derman O. Effects of oral health behaviors and socioeconomic factors on a group of Turkish adolescents. Quintessence Int. 2008;39:e26-32.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18551208</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR38" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>McGowan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Dover</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>McGowan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tadakamadla</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dental referrals for patients with diabetes: survey of barriers and enablers for medical and health professionals</article-title><source>Aust Dent J</source><year>2023</year><volume>68</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>273</fpage><lpage>281</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/adj.12978</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37676007</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR38" publication-type="journal">Davies K, McGowan K, Dover T, McGowan T, Tadakamadla SK. Dental referrals for patients with diabetes: survey of barriers and enablers for medical and health professionals. Aust Dent J. 2023;68(4):273&#x02013;81.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37676007</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR39" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valerio</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanjirath</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name><surname>Klausner</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A qualitative examination of patient awareness and understanding of type 2 diabetes and oral health care needs</article-title><source>Diabetes Res Clin Pract</source><year>2011</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>159</fpage><lpage>165</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.diabres.2011.03.034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21514966</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR39" publication-type="journal">Valerio MA, Kanjirath PP, Klausner CP, Peters MC. A qualitative examination of patient awareness and understanding of type 2 diabetes and oral health care needs. Diabetes Res Clin Pract. 2011;93:159&#x02013;65.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21514966</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article>