<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="EN" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">JACS Au</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">JACS Au</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">au</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="coden">jaaucr</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>JACS Au</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2691-3704</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Chemical Society</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11862925</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jacsau.4c00980</article-id><article-categories><subj-group><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Engineered Receptor
Capture Combined with Mass Spectrometry
Enables High-Throughput Detection and Quantitation of SARS-CoV-2
Spike Protein</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath1"><name><surname>Bate</surname><given-names>Neil</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath2"><name><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>Dan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">&#x02020;</xref><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">&#x02225;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath3"><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>Sian E.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">&#x022a5;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath4"><name><surname>Salim</surname><given-names>Farah</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">&#x02020;</xref><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">&#x02225;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath5"><name><surname>Allcock</surname><given-names>Natalie S.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">#</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath6"><name><surname>Haigh</surname><given-names>Richard</given-names></name><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">&#x022a5;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath7"><name><surname>Sale</surname><given-names>Julian E.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff8" ref-type="aff">&#x02207;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath8"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6583-870X</contrib-id><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>Donald J. L.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff7" ref-type="aff">&#x000b6;</xref><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">&#x02225;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="ath9"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4221-677X</contrib-id><name><surname>Brindle</surname><given-names>Nicholas P. J.</given-names></name><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="other">*</xref><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">&#x02020;</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">&#x02021;</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">&#x000a7;</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>&#x02020;</label>Department
of Cardiovascular Sciences, <institution>University of
Leicester</institution>, University Road, Leicester, Leicester LE1 7RH, <country>U.K.</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>&#x02021;</label>Department
of Molecular &#x00026; Cell Biology, <institution>University
of Leicester</institution>, University Road, Leicester, Leicester LE1 7RH, <country>U.K.</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>&#x000a7;</label>Leicester
Institute for Structural &#x00026; Chemical Biology, <institution>University of Leicester</institution>, University Road, Leicester, Leicester LE1 7RH, <country>U.K.</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><label>&#x02225;</label>van
Geest MS-OMICS Facility, <institution>University of Leicester</institution>, University Road, Leicester, Leicester LE1 7RH, <country>U.K.</country></aff><aff id="aff5"><label>&#x022a5;</label>Leicester
Drug Discovery &#x00026; Diagnostics, <institution>University
of Leicester</institution>, University Road, Leicester, Leicester LE1 7RH, <country>U.K.</country></aff><aff id="aff6"><label>#</label>Electron
Microscopy Facility, Core Biotechnology Services, <institution>University of Leicester</institution>, University Road, Leicester, Leicester LE1 7RH, <country>U.K.</country></aff><aff id="aff7"><label>&#x000b6;</label>Department
of Genetics, Genomics &#x00026; Cancer Sciences, <institution>University of Leicester</institution>, University Road, Leicester, Leicester LE1 7RH, <country>U.K.</country></aff><aff id="aff8"><label>&#x02207;</label><institution>MRC
Laboratory of Molecular Biology</institution>, Francis Crick Avenue, Cambridge CB2 0QH, <country>U.K.</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Email: <email>NPJB1@Le.ac.uk</email>.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>04</day><month>02</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>24</day><month>02</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>747</fpage><lpage>755</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>01</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>23</day><month>01</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2025 The Authors. Published by American Chemical Society</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Authors</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>Permits the broadest form of re-use including for commercial purposes, provided that author attribution and integrity are maintained (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p content-type="toc-graphic"><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="au4c00980_0006" id="ab-tgr1"/></p><p>Mass spectrometry (MS) is a potentially powerful approach
for the
diagnostic detection of SARS-CoV-2 and other viruses. However, MS
detection is compromised when viral antigens are present at low concentrations,
especially in complex biological media. We hypothesized that viral
receptors could be used for viral target capture to enable detection
by MS under such conditions. This was tested using the extracellular
domain of the SARS-CoV-2 receptor ACE2. To maximize recovery of the
target protein, directed protein evolution was first used to increase
the affinity of ACE2 for spike protein. This generated an evolved
ACE2 with increased binding affinity for the spike protein receptor-binding
domain (RBD). However, as with other affinity-enhanced evolved forms
of ACE2, binding was sensitive to mutations in variant RBDs. As an
alternative strategy to maximize capture, the native ACE2 extracellular
domain was engineered for increased binding by the addition of an
oligomerization scaffold to create pentameric ACE2. This bound extremely
tightly to SARS-CoV-2 RBD, with an increase in apparent affinity of
several thousand-fold over monomeric ACE2, and RBD retention of more
than 8 h. Immobilization of multimeric ACE2 enabled quantitative enrichment
of viral spike protein from saliva and increased the sensitivity of
detection by MS. These data show that capture by engineered receptors
combined with MS can be an effective, rapid method for detection and
quantitation of target protein. A similar approach could be used for
attachment proteins of other viruses or any target protein for which
there are suitable receptors.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>virus</kwd><kwd>detection</kwd><kwd>receptor capture</kwd><kwd>protein engineering</kwd><kwd>mass spectrometry</kwd><kwd>SARS-CoV2</kwd><kwd>ACE2</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Research Councils UK</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100000265</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>MC_PC_19043</award-id></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>John and Lucille van Geest Foundation</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">NA</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>NA</award-id></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>NIHR Leicester Biomedical Research Centre</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100020013</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>NA</award-id></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Research Councils UK</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100000268</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>BB/V01465X/1</award-id></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Research Councils UK</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100000265</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>U105178808</award-id></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Research Councils UK</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100000265</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>MR/X502777/1</award-id></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Research Councils UK</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100000265</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>MR/X009521/1</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>document-id-old-9</meta-name><meta-value>au4c00980</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>document-id-new-14</meta-name><meta-value>au4c00980</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>ccc-price</meta-name><meta-value/></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p id="sec1">Mass spectrometry (MS) is emerging as a fast, quantitative, and
accurate method for diagnostic detection of SARS-CoV-2 protein in
biological samples, including swabs, saliva, and serum<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>&#x02212;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref></sup> and holds great promise for use with other viruses. MS has key advantages
over other detection platforms (e.g., reverse transcription polymerase
chain reaction), as it can provide absolute quantitation and can be
readily multiplexed with other targets. A single assay could, for
example, quantify viral load simultaneously with the immunoglobulin
and complement response to infection proteins to establish a personalized
response score.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref></sup></p><p>Detection of low
abundance proteins with MS with sufficient sensitivity
against background signals of matrix components in biological and
environmental samples is challenging. For viral detection, enrichment
for virus, viral target protein, or, post digestion peptides from
viral target protein, has been shown to be successful in enabling
increased sensitivity of detection.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref>&#x02212;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref></sup> Most enrichment approaches
involve immunoaffinity capture of target protein or peptides;<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref></sup> however, generating and screening
appropriate monoclonal antibodies for target immunoaffinity enrichment
is time-consuming. Furthermore, antibody binding can be decreased
or ablated in viral variants where mutations occur in or near binding
epitopes. In the context of enrichment and diagnostic MS, this could
lead to false negative results or underestimates of concentrations
for viral variants. For this reason, antibodies targeting viral proteins
and peptides that are most prone to mutation, such as the spike protein
in SARS-CoV-2, are best avoided for immunoaffinity enrichment. However,
even antibodies targeting less mutation-prone viral proteins still
carry the risk of failing to recover variants in which mutations have
occurred in the antibody epitopes of such proteins.</p><p>We hypothesized
that a high-affinity version of a viral receptor
could be used as a trap to enrich viral attachment proteins in diagnostic
MS. This approach would circumvent the need for antibody generation
and screening, thereby speeding up the development of assays. In addition,
enrichment by binding to a trap based on the host cell receptor would
be expected to recover all variants that are capable of binding host
receptor and therefore infection-competent. In order to maximize recovery,
such a trap would benefit from having high-binding activity for the
viral attachment protein. One way to increase binding activity is
via directed protein evolution, and a range of evolved ACE2 mutants
with increased binding activity for SARS-CoV-2 spike protein have
been reported.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref>&#x02212;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref></sup> However, evolved ACE2 with mutations in the binding
site for spike protein can be sensitive to some mutations found in
variant spike proteins.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref></sup> Here, using the ACE2
ectodomain and SARS-CoV-2 spike protein as an example, we create high-binding
activity versions of a host cell receptor by directed evolution (but
retaining a nonmutated spike protein binding interface) and by oligomerizing
native ACE2 ectodomain. These were tested for binding, and the oligomeric
native receptor was found to be superior to an evolved receptor. We
then show that this engineered receptor binding approach combined
with MS can be used for target protein detection.</p><sec id="sec2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="sec2.1"><title>Materials</title><p>DNA encoding full-length human ACE2 was a
gift from Hyeryun Choe<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref></sup> (Addgene plasmid
# 1786; <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://n2t.net/addgene:1786">http://n2t.net/addgene:1786</uri>; RRID:Addgene_1786). Codon optimized DNA encoding the CD5 secretory
leader (residues 1&#x02013;24), followed by human ACE2 (residues 19&#x02013;615)
or human ACE2 (residues 19&#x02013;740), a short linker, then a FLAG
epitope tag and C-terminal Histidine6, was synthesized by GeneArt.
DNA encoding codon optimized ACE2-COMP was also synthesized by GeneArt.
This ACE2-COMP fusion protein comprised a CD5 secretory leader, human
ACE2 (residues 19&#x02013;615), a short linker followed by residues
29&#x02013;73 of rat cartilage oligomeric matrix protein, then another
linker before a FLAG epitope tag and C-terminal Histidine6. DNA-encoding
receptor binding domain (RBD) variants were synthesized by GeneArt
and have been described previously.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref></sup></p><p>Water, acetonitrile, and formic acid, all Optima LC&#x02013;MS grade,
were sourced from Fisher Chemical (Geel, Belgium). Phosphate buffered
saline (PBS) tablets were purchased from Thermo Fisher (Rockford,
IL, USA). Trypsin from bovine pancreas, 1,4-dithiothreitol (DTT),
iodoacetamide (IAA), ammonium bicarbonate (ABC), tris-buffered saline
(TBS), and acetone were obtained from Sigma-Aldrich (St. Louis, MO,
USA). The trimeric SARS-CoV-2 spike protein was purchased from BioServUK
(Rotherham, UK). Stable isotope standard peptides, GWIFGTTLDSK(*)
and SFIEDLLFNK(*) (*modified using <sup>13</sup>C<sub>6</sub><sup>15</sup>N<sub>2</sub> K), were produced by PepScan (Lelystad, The
Netherlands). For peptide preparation, a stable isotope-labeled peptide
mix was made (500 nM each of GWIFGTTLDSK(*) and SFIEDLLFNK(*)). Reagents
were made up in Protein LoBind Tubes (Eppendorf, Stevenage, UK). Nunc
MicroWell 96-Well Microplates (Fisher Scientific, Loughborough, UK)
and QuanRecovery with MaxPeak plates (Waters, Milford, MA, USA) were
sourced for protein enrichment and LC&#x02013;MS analysis, respectively.
An Eppendorf ThermoMixer C, fitted with a PCR 96 SmartBlock and a
ThermoTop, was used throughout for each incubation step (Eppendorf,
Stevenage, UK).</p><p>All other reagents were as described previously.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref></sup></p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><title>Directed Protein Evolution</title><p>Directed evolution of ACE2
was performed using the cell surface display DT40 system that we previously
described.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref></sup> Cells were transfected with
DNA encoding a fusion protein comprising a N-terminal CD5 secretory
leader sequence (residues 1&#x02013;24) followed by FLAG-epitope tag,
flanked on both sides by short linkers, and human ACE2. Stable transfectants
were obtained by selection in puromycin, DT40 cell clones with ACE2
integrated into the rearranged Ig locus were identified by PCR, and
cell surface expression of the FLAG-ACE2 fusion protein was confirmed
by anti-FLAG immunostaining as previously described.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref></sup> Cells were cultured in RPMI containing 7% (v/v) fetal bovine
serum (FBS) and 3% (v/v) chicken serum at 37 &#x000b0;C and 5% CO<sub>2</sub>.</p><p>For evolving ACE2 with enhanced affinity, approximately
40 million cells were incubated with His<sub>6</sub>-tagged SARS-CoV-2
RBD at concentrations between 2 nM and 100 pM (as indicated in <xref rid="sec3" ref-type="other">Results and Discussion</xref>) in PBS with 10% (v/v) FBS
at room temperature for 30 min. Bound RBD was detected, following
cell washing, with anti-His<sub>6</sub>-tag, and surface expressed
ACE2 with anti-FLAG, antibodies. Cells with RBD bound were selected
by fluorescence activated cell sorting with sort windows indicated
in the <xref rid="sec3" ref-type="other">Results and Discussion</xref>. DNA encoding
ACE2 was recovered from genomic DNA prepared from sorted cells and
sequenced as described previously.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref></sup></p><p>Site directed mutagenesis and expression and purification of soluble
proteins were performed as described previously.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref></sup></p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><title>Biolayer Interferometry</title><p>Biolayer interferometry using
the Octet R8 platform was performed to analyze the binding. Assays
were performed in TBS with 0.05% (v/v) Tween-20 and 1 mg/mL BSA. Monomeric
RBD was covalently immobilized onto AR2G biosensors as described by
the manufacturer. After washing, ACE2 binding was performed over the
concentration ranges indicated in <xref rid="sec3" ref-type="other">Results and Discussion</xref>, with an association time of 60 s, followed by immersion in assay
buffer to measure dissociation. Data was analyzed using Octet Analysis
software with a 1:1 binding model for monomeric interactions and a
1:2 binding model for dimeric and pentameric ACE2 binding.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><title>Electron Microscopy</title><p>Negative stain grids were prepared
by glow discharging 200 square continuous carbon copper grids (Agar
Scientific) for 30 s at 30 mA (Gloqube, Quorum Technologies). 20 &#x003bc;L
of sample was applied to clean parafilm, and the freshly glow discharged
grid was floated carbon side down on the drop for 1 min. Excess sample
was blotted from the grid using filter paper, and the grid was transferred
to a 20 &#x003bc;L drop of 2% uranyl acetate (w/v) for 30 s, followed
by blotting and transferring to a second drop of uranyl acetate for
30 s, before finally blotting with filter paper and leaving to dry.
Samples were viewed on a JEOL JEM-1400 electron microscope with an
accelerating voltage of 120 kV. Digital micrographs were collected
with an EMSIS Xarosa digital camera with Radius software.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.5"><title>Viral Capture</title><p>SARS-CoV-2 virus (variant B.1.1.369;
isolated in Leicester, May 2020) stock was propagated in Dulbecco&#x02019;s
modified Eagle medium (DMEM; Gibco) on T25 flasks of confluent Vero
E6 cells for 72 h. Tissue culture flask supernatants were harvested,
cell debris was removed by centrifugation at 500<italic>g</italic> for 10 min, and virus stocks were aliquoted and stored at &#x02212;80
&#x000b0;C; typical titers were 10<sup>6</sup> pfu/ml. All live SARS-CoV-2
virus work was performed in the Containment Level 3 (CL3) Laboratories
(University of Leicester).</p><p>ACE2-COMP immobilized to nickel beads
via the His<sub>6</sub>-tag was added to a 250 &#x003bc;L aliquot of
freshly defrosted stock SARS-CoV-2 and incubated at 37 &#x000b0;C for
20 min. Beads were harvested by centrifugation at 1700<italic>g</italic> for 5 min and washed twice with 1 mL of TBSG. The beads were resuspended
in 200 &#x003bc;L of 300 mM imidazole (in TBSG) for 2 min to elute ACE2-COMP
from beads and then collected again by centrifugation. Supernatant,
containing released COMP-ACE2 (and any bound virus), was made up to
4% (w/v) formaldehyde and stored for 24 h before removal from the
CL3 lab and analysis by electron microscopy.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.6"><title>Sample Preparation for MS without Enrichment</title><p>SARS-CoV-2
spike protein was added to saliva to create final concentrations of
100, 50, 20, 5, 1, and 0.5 nM. In duplicate, 40 &#x003bc;L of sample
was precipitated with 160 &#x003bc;L ice cold acetone and centrifuged
at 13,000 rpm for 15 min using a Labnet Prism R Refrigerated Microcentrifuge
(Labnet International, Edison, NJ USA). The supernatant was removed,
and the pellet was dried under vacuum using a Thermo Savant ISS110
SpeedVac System (Thermo Fisher, Rockford, IL, USA) before reconstitution
with 40 &#x003bc;L of ABC (50 mM). Samples were then digested with 2.8
&#x003bc;L trypsin (1 mg/mL) for 15 min at 37 &#x000b0;C. Formic acid was
added to a final 1% v/v, and samples were transferred to a QuanRecovery
96-Well plate for LC&#x02013;MS analysis.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.7"><title>Sample Preparation for MS with Enrichment</title><p>Nunc MicroWell
96-Well Microplates were prewet and incubated for 1 h with 150 &#x003bc;L
of TBS (per well). The TBS was then removed before coating each well
with 25 &#x003bc;L of ACE2-COMP or BSA control (5 &#x003bc;g/mL in TBS).
The protein was allowed to bind to the plate overnight at 4 &#x000b0;C.
After, the unbound fraction was discarded, and the plate was blocked
with the addition of 5% powdered milk (in 1xTBS) for 1 h at room temperature.
The blocking buffer was then removed, and the plate was washed with
150 &#x003bc;L of TBS.</p><p>To the ACE2-COMP-functionalized plate,
25 &#x003bc;L of SARS-CoV-2 spike protein (added into PBS or saliva)
was added at varying concentrations (1.2&#x02013;156.8 nM) before a
1 h incubation at room temperature. The unbound fraction was removed,
and the plate was washed thrice with 150 &#x003bc;L of TBS. ABC was
added to the plate (47.5 &#x003bc;L, 50 mM) along with the stable isotope-labeled
peptide mix (2.5 &#x003bc;L, 500 nM). The bound protein complex was
then subject to reduction with 5.5 &#x003bc;L DTT (15.4 mg/mL) for 30
min at 60 &#x000b0;C, then alkylation with 6.1 &#x003bc;L IAA (35.04 mg/mL)
for 30 min at room temperature and under the absence of light. Proteins
were then digested with 5 &#x003bc;L of trypsin (1 mg/mL) overnight
at 37 &#x000b0;C. Digestion was stopped with the addition of formic acid
to a final 1% v/v. Samples were then transferred to a clean QuanRecovery
96-Well plate for LC&#x02013;MS analysis. For the saturation series
experiment, spike protein was added to buffer or saliva to a final
concentration of 156.8, 78.4, 39.2, 19.6, 9.8, 4.88, 2.44, and 1.2
nM in triplicate before enrichment as above. To assess nonspecific
binding, spike protein was added to saliva to a final concentration
of 156.8 nM in triplicate and processed with the enrichment protocol,
but with plates not treated with ACE2-COMP.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.8"><title>LC&#x02013;MS Operation and Analysis</title><p>An ACQUITY UPLC
I-Class PLUS system coupled to a Xevo TQ-XS Tandem Quadrupole (LC&#x02013;MS/MS)
and an ACQUITY UPLC Peptide BEH C18 1.7 &#x003bc;m and 2.1 mm &#x000d7;
50 mm column from Waters Corporation (Milford, MA, USA) were used.
The Xevo TQ-XS instrument was equipped with a Z-spray electrospray
ionization (ESI) source set to positive mode.</p><p>Enriched peptide
eluates were analyzed as 10 &#x003bc;L injections, and chromatographic
separation was performed at a constant flow rate of 0.6 mL/min with
water/0.1% formic acid (A) and acetonitrile/0.1% formic acid (B) mobile
phases. A 3.5 min gradient was used: 95% mobile phase A initial to
0.25 min, to 55% A at 2.00 min, to 30% A at 2.20 min, to 5% A at 2.21
min until 2.68 min, and to 95% A at 2.70 min until 3.00 min. Column
temperature was set to 40 &#x000b0;C. For the ESI source parameters,
desolvation temperature (650 &#x000b0;C), capillary voltage (0.6 kV),
desolvation flow (1000 L/h), and cone flow (150 L/h) were set. Simultaneous
multiple reaction monitoring (MRM) was performed for the ACE2-COMP
peptides (EITFLK (EIT), LFNMLR (LFN), AVCHPTAWDLGK (AVC), LWAWESWR
(LWA), and SEPWTLALENVVGAK (SEP)), SARS-CoV-2 peptides (SFIEDLLFNK
(SFI), ASANLAATK (ASA), GWIFGTTLDSK (GWI), and GVYYPDK (GVY)), and
the stable isotope-labeled analogue peptides (GWIFGTTLDSK(*) (GWI*)
and SFIEDLLFNK(*) (SFI*)). MRM transitions for each of the peptides
are provided in Supporting Information, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/jacsau.4c00980/suppl_file/au4c00980_si_001.pdf">Table S1</ext-link>.</p><p>To process the LC&#x02013;MS/MS data, MRM data was
exported into
Skyline (version 23.1 (MacCoss Lab, UW, USA)). Peaks with matching
expected and found retention times were integrated. All peaks were
manually checked. Only data with both quantifier and qualifier ion
presences were used. Results were imported into RStudio (version 1.4.1106),
where the peak area for the quantifying peptide (SFI) was normalized
against the peak area of the corresponding stable isotope-labeled
peptide (SFI(*)). Normalized data were then imported into GraphPad
Prism (version 4.07) for analysis and processing.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>Results and Discussion</title><sec id="sec3.1"><title>Directed Evolution of ACE2 for Enhanced Binding to CoV-2 RBD</title><p>In order to create a form of ACE2 with increased affinity for SARS-CoV-2
RBD, we first performed directed protein evolution. This was done
using a cell surface display and mutagenesis system that we have already
described.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref></sup></p><p>The cell surface display
construct consisted of the secretory leader sequence from CD5, a FLAG-epitope
tag, and a linker region followed by full-length human ACE2, which
includes the CoV-2 RBD binding site and the ACE2 transmembrane and
intracellular domains (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref></xref>A). To evolve enhanced RBD binding, cells were incubated with
2 nM monomeric SARS-CoV-2 RBD (residues 319&#x02013;541) containing
a HA-epitope tag, and bound RBD detected with anti-HA, along with
ACE2 expression level detected using anti-FLAG. Diagonal sort windows
were used to correct binding for ACE2 expression level, and cells
displaying the highest levels of RBD binding were selected (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref></xref>B). Three rounds
of selection and expansion were performed, two at 2 nM and one at
100 pM RBD (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref></xref>B). DNA encoding evolved ACE2 was recovered from cells selected at
round 3 and sequenced. In the pool of higher-affinity ACE2 mutants
was a form in which all mutations were outside the binding interface
for the SARS-CoV-2 RBD. This evolved ACE2 has four substitutions Ala65Val,
Glu75Lys, Leu79Ile, and Thr92Lys (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref></xref>C). The position of the mutations relative
to the RBD binding site in the previously reported crystal structure
of ACE2 in complex with the CoV-2 RBD is shown in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref></xref>D. The peripheral localization
of the mutations means that the binding interface and primary binding
residues of wild-type ACE2 (Wt-ACE2) remain unchanged in this mutant
ACE2. Thus, it is possible that RBD variants capable of binding Wt
host cell ACE2 should also bind this evolved ACE2, minimizing the
risk of loss of binding of relevant RBD variants. In order to directly
test whether the mutant ACE2 binds SARS-CoV-2 RBD with increased affinity,
Wt-ACE2 and the mutant receptor (residues 19&#x02013;615), with C-terminal
epitope tags, were expressed as soluble proteins and their binding
to RBD determined by biolayer interferometry. In this mutant receptor,
we changed the Ala65Val mutation to Ala65Trp in order to maximize
improvement of affinity as others had reported Ala65Trp to have higher
affinity gain than Ala65Val.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref></sup> Consistent
with the evolution strategy, mutant ACE2 bound with an affinity higher
than that of Wt-ACE2, by more than 10-fold (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref></xref>E).</p><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Directed evolution of ACE2 ectodomain. (A) Schematic
representation
of cell surface expressed ACE2 ectodomain. Full-length ACE2 was expressed
with an amino-terminal FLAG tag and short linker region. (B) Selection
of ACE2 for increased affinity. Flow cytometry plots are shown for
cells incubated with RBD and stained for bound RBD using anti-His-phycoerythrin,
and ACE2 expression using anti-FLAG-allophycocyanin. Three rounds
of selection at the indicated RBD concentrations and diversification
were performed. The sort windows are indicated for each round of selection.
(C) Amino acid substitutions of evolved ACE2 are shown in red. (D)
Position of substitutions in ACE2 structure (PDB entry ID: 6M0J<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19">19</xref></sup>). Left panel shows part of ACE2 structure (blue)
in complex with RBD (yellow) with substitutions in evolved ACE2 shown
in red. Position of A368L is shown in orange. Right panel shows structure
of RBD binding interface of ACE2 and the position of substitutions.
Position of RBD-interacting residues in Wt-ACE2 are indicated in green.
(E) Kinetic binding constants for RBD binding by Wt-ACE2, evolved
ACE2 and evolved ACE2 with A386L, measured by biolayer interferometry
with soluble ACE2 (19&#x02013;615) and immobilized monomeric RBD. Data
are shown as means and SEM for at least two experiments.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="au4c00980_0001" id="gr1" position="float"/></fig><p>To gain insight into potential mechanisms for the
increase in affinity
of the evolved ACE2, we examined the published structure of Wt-ACE2
in complex with RBD.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19">19</xref></sup> The ACE2 substitutions
Glu75Lys and Leu75Ile are located close together, and opposite residues
Glu484 and Phe486 in the RBD (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref></xref>D). These RBD residues are located on a highly flexible
loop, which would allow Glu484 and Phe465 to come close enough to
Lys75 and Ile79, respectively, in the mutated ACE2 to facilitate new
bonding interactions. Trp65 in mutant ACE2 is located opposite Val445
and Tyr449 on another flexible loop in RBD, providing the possibility
that loop flexibility could enable a new hydrophobic interaction between
RBD and mutant ACE2. The Thr92Lys substitution occurs within the consensus
site required for N-linked glycosylation of Asn90 and would result
in loss of Asn90 glycosylation. Loss of this glycosylation has previously
been shown to increase ACE2 binding affinity for RBD.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">20</xref></sup></p><p>SARS-CoV-2 RBD interacts with two distinct sites
in ACE2, a patch
of residues in the &#x003b1;1 helix of ACE2, along with a more limited
interaction of the &#x003b1;2 helix and the loop between &#x003b2;3 and
&#x003b2;4 sheet.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">21</xref></sup> We hypothesized that the binding
affinity of the mutant receptor could be increased further by providing
additional binding options on the helix &#x003b1;1 in ACE2 or around
the &#x003b1;2 and &#x003b2;3/4 loop region. As the &#x003b1;1 helix lies
in the core binding interface and we wanted to retain this intact
without mutations, we focused on potential mutations that could be
introduced outside this region. We therefore tested the effects of
adding Ala386Leu, a mutation localized close to the &#x003b2;3/4 loop,
but like the mutations in evolved ACE2 also outside the core binding
interface, and already shown to increase binding affinity to RBD.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref></sup> Combining the mutations in the evolved ACE2
with Ala386Leu, designated Ev-ACE2-A386L, resulted in a further 2.5-fold
affinity gain, causing an overall 28-fold increase in affinity compared
with Wt-ACE2 (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref></xref>E).</p></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><title>Binding of Evolved ACE2 to SARS-COV-2 Variant RBD</title><p>We
examined the ability of Wt and Ev-ACE2-A386L to bind two SARS-CoV-2
variant RBDs, an RBD containing the Leu452Arg and Glu484Gln mutations
common to variants B.1.617.1 and B.1.617.3, and an RBD containing
Lys417Asn, Glu484Lys, and AsnN501Tyr mutations found in variant B.1.351
(<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="other">Table <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="other">1</xref></xref>).</p><table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Binding of Wt and Evolved ACE2 to
RBD Variants</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="0"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="char" char="&#x000b1;"/><col align="char" char="&#x000b1;"/><col align="char" char="&#x000b1;"/><col align="char" char="&#x000b1;"/><col align="char" char="&#x000b1;"/><col align="char" char="&#x000b1;"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th style="border:none;" align="center">&#x000a0;</th><th colspan="3" align="center" char="&#x000b1;">B.1.617.1/3 (L452R, E484Q)<hr/></th><th colspan="3" align="center" char="&#x000b1;">B.1.351
(K417N, E484 K, N501Y)<hr/></th></tr><tr><th style="border:none;" align="center">&#x000a0;</th><th style="border:none;" align="center" char="&#x000b1;">Kon (M<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>&#x000a0;s<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>)&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>4</sup></th><th style="border:none;" align="center" char="&#x000b1;">Koff (s<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>)&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>&#x02013;3</sup></th><th style="border:none;" align="center" char="&#x000b1;">KD (nM)</th><th style="border:none;" align="center" char="&#x000b1;">Kon (M<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>&#x000a0;s<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>)&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>4</sup></th><th style="border:none;" align="center" char="&#x000b1;">Koff (s<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>)&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>&#x02013;3</sup></th><th style="border:none;" align="center" char="&#x000b1;">KD (nM)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">Wt</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char="&#x000b1;">9.7&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.4</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char="&#x000b1;">9.9&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.3</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char="&#x000b1;">101&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;9.9</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char="&#x000b1;">9.8&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.0</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char="&#x000b1;">7.7&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.7</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char="&#x000b1;">79.5&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;7.6</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">EV-ACE2-A368L</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char="&#x000b1;">11.5&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.1</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char="&#x000b1;">1.0&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.1</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char="&#x000b1;">9.0&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.3</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char="&#x000b1;">9.5&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.2</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char="&#x000b1;">1.2&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.1</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char="&#x000b1;">12.5&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.1</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Kinetic binding constants for RBD binding by Wt and
mutant ACE2
were measured by biolayer interferometry with soluble ACE2 and immobilized
RBD. Data are shown as means and SEM images for at least three experiments.</p><p>Similar to the situation with binding to Wuhan-Hu-1 RBD (WH-RBD),
Ev-ACE2-A386L bound both RBD variants with higher affinity than Wt-ACE2
bound the RBD variants. Interestingly, however, the affinity gain
of Ev-ACE2-A386L is lower for the variants than it is for WH-RBD (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="other">Table <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="other">1</xref></xref>). Thus, while Wt-ACE2
bound each of the variants with higher affinity than WH-RBD, Ev-ACE2-A386L
showed lower affinity for the variants than for WH-RBD. Evolved ACE2
therefore behaves differently than Wt-ACE2, even though the mutations
in evolved ACE2 are outside the Wt binding interface. This divergence
between evolved ACE2 and Wt-ACE2 highlights the possibility that evolved
ACE2 could be compromised in its ability to capture some variants
that can bind Wt-ACE2 (and which are therefore pathologically relevant
variants).</p></sec><sec id="sec3.3"><title>Enhancing Binding by Oligomerization</title><p>As an alternative
to enhancing RBD binding by evolving ACE2, we sought to leverage avidity
effects to increase the binding ability of Wt-ACE2 by presenting the
receptor in multimeric format.</p><p>Specifically, we examined the
dimeric and pentameric forms of Wt-ACE2. Dimeric ACE2 was created
by extending the sequence beyond residue 615 to residue 740, to incorporate
the naturally occurring homodimerization motif in ACE2.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">21</xref></sup> To create pentameric ACE2, we used the coiled:coil
domain peptide from cartilage oligomeric matrix protein and fused
this to ACE2 (19&#x02013;615). This domain forms a very stable pentamer,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref22">22</xref></sup> which we and others have previously used as
a pentameric scaffold for presenting proteins.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref24">24</xref></sup> These ACE2 forms are schematically shown in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref></xref>A.</p><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>ACE2 multimerization increases binding to RBD.
(A) Schematic representation
of monomeric (ACE2&#x02013;615), dimeric (ACE2&#x02013;740), and pentameric
(ACE2-COMP) ACE2. (B) Negative stain electron microscopy of monomeric,
dimeric, and pentameric ACE2 (left to right). Scale bar, 50 nm. (C)
Kinetic binding constants for RBD binding by Wt-ACE2 dimer and pentamer
measured by biolayer interferometry with soluble ACE2 and immobilized
RBD. Data are shown as means and SEM for two experiments. (D) Kinetic
association and dissociation curves for monomeric, dimeric, and pentameric
ACE2 demonstrating decreased dissociation kinetics for dimer and pentamer,
and retention of bound RBD for more than 8 h for pentamer. (E) Negative
stain electron microscopy image of ACE2-COMP bound to SARS-CoV-2 virus.
Scale bar, 100 nm.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="au4c00980_0002" id="gr2" position="float"/></fig><p>The soluble proteins were directly visualized with
negative staining
transmission electron microscopy (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref></xref>B). Wt-ACE2 (19&#x02013;615) appeared as almost
spherical structures measuring around 9.5 nm across, whereas Wt-ACE2
(19&#x02013;740) formed clear dimeric structures (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref></xref>B). ACE2-COMP presented in
negative staining electron microscopy as doughnut-shaped structures
of approximately 18.5 nm diameter in which the globular protein monomers
are arranged around a central hole, consistent with a pentameric structure.</p><p>Relative binding of the Wt-ACE2 (19&#x02013;615), Wt-ACE2 (19&#x02013;740),
and ACE2-COMP (19&#x02013;615) to RBD was assessed using biolayer interferometry.
The dimeric Wt-ACE2 (19&#x02013;740) bound CoV-2 RBD with a KD of 1.5
nM (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref></xref>C), demonstrating
a considerable increase in binding ability compared with the monomeric
ACE2 (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref></xref>E). Others
have reported that dimerizing ACE2 increases its ability to bind RBD.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref></sup> The pentameric Wt-ACE2-COMP (19&#x02013;615)
bound CoV-2 RBD extremely tightly, with an apparent KD of less than
25 pM as determined by biolayer interferometry, representing an improvement
of several thousand-fold apparent compared with monomeric ACE2. However,
it should be noted that it is not possible to derive a true KD from
the association and dissociation curves due to the multimeric nature
of Wt-ACE2-COMP. Nevertheless, it is clear that compared to Wt-ACE2
(19&#x02013;615) or Wt-ACE2 (19&#x02013;740), this ACE2 pentamer has
very substantially increased binding to RBD (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref></xref>C,D), making it very attractive for maximizing
RBD capture. Oligomerization of binding proteins increases binding
by avidity effects and these are largely due to a decrease in the
ability of the protein to dissociate from its partner.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25">25</xref></sup> Examination of the kinetics of monomeric, dimeric,
and pentameric ACE2 interacting with monomeric CoV-2 RBD clearly shows
a moderately increased association rate of the dimer and pentamer
forms and a very substantial decrease in dissociation rates (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref></xref>C). Indeed, observation
of ACE2 dissociation from RBD over an extended period reveals that
around 90% of bound pentameric ACE2 remains attached to RBD even after
more than 8 h (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref></xref>D). These data show that pentamerization, in particular, leads to
a major increase in the binding ability of ACE2 and allows markedly
extended retention of bound RBD. Incubating ACE2-COMP with the whole
SARS-CoV-2 virus and recovering the His6-tagged pentameric receptor,
followed by negative staining electron microscopy, shows ACE2-COMP
still bound to the surface of captured virus (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref></xref>E).</p><p>The binding of pentameric ACE2
to the variant RBDs tested above
with Ev-ACE2-A386L, B.1.617.1/3, and B.1.351 variant RBD was examined
(<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref></xref>). As with
WH-RBD, the pentameric ACE2-COMP bound very tightly to the variant
RBD, with apparent KD&#x02019;s in the pM range (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref></xref>A).</p><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Binding of ACE2-COMP to RBD variants. (A) Kinetic
binding constants
for RBD binding by ACE2-COMP measured by biolayer interferometry with
soluble ACE2 and immobilized monomeric RBD. Data are shown as means
and SEM for two experiments. (B) Kinetic association and dissociation
curves for binding of ACE2-COMP to B.1.617.1/3 and B.1.351 variant
RBD, demonstrating retention of bound RBD for more than 8 h.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="au4c00980_0003" id="gr3" position="float"/></fig><p>Again, the variant RBD&#x02019;s remained bound
to ACE2-COMP for
several hours in dissociation buffer with approximately 90% of the
bound ACE2-COMP still retained after 8 h (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref></xref>B). It is possible that ACE2 could be engineered
to increase affinity still further. For example, incorporation of
heparan sulfate, which has been shown to promote spike protein binding
to ACE2,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref26">26</xref></sup> with dimeric or pentameric ACE2
could be investigated for further enhancing capture of RBD and RBD
variants. The very high-binding activity of ACE2-COMP and its retention
of RBD make this fusion protein a good candidate for the capture of
spike protein for MS detection. Furthermore, at this high level of
binding activity engineered ACE2 would be expected to capture all
spike protein variants capable of binding the cellular receptor and
therefore be relevant to infectious virus.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.4"><title>Enrichment with ACE2-COMP Increases Sensitivity of Spike Protein
Detection by MS</title><p>Prior to our enrichment strategy, we began
the development of a noncapture-based MS assay in 2021. Saliva (40
&#x003bc;L) containing SARS-CoV-2 spike protein over a range of concentrations
(0.5&#x02013;100 nM) was precipitated with ice cold acetone (160 &#x003bc;L),
followed by tryptic digestion (1 mg/mL, 37 &#x000b0;C) and resolution
of the peptides by LC&#x02013;MS. Significant issues were noted with
both interference and sensitivity. <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref></xref>A shows an interfering component in saliva
that lacked spike protein, where an intense MS signal was seen at
the expected retention time (0.6 min) of one of the spike peptides
(peptide sequence ASANLAATK; see Supporting Information, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/jacsau.4c00980/suppl_file/au4c00980_si_001.pdf">Table S1</ext-link>). Monitoring multiple peptides with
MS provides the opportunity to simply target other candidates when
there are issues with particular peptides. However, even for peptides
without interfering peaks (peptide sequence SFIEDLLFNK), sensitivity
was not sufficient to detect spike protein at 100 nM in saliva (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref></xref>B).</p><fig id="fig4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Poor sensitivity of detection
of SARS-CoV-2 spike protein without
sample enrichment. (A) Detection of a coeluting, interfering peak
for the ASANLAATK peptide (details in Supporting Information, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/jacsau.4c00980/suppl_file/au4c00980_si_001.pdf">Table S1</ext-link>) in spike protein na&#x000ef;ve saliva,
highlighting the challenges in discerning specific signals amidst
background noise, which can lead to false positives or inaccurate
quantification. (B) Absence of signal for the SFIEDLLFNK peptide (details
in Supporting Information, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/jacsau.4c00980/suppl_file/au4c00980_si_001.pdf">Table S1</ext-link>) in
saliva containing 100 nM spike protein, indicating limitations in
sensitivity and detection capability without employing capture techniques,
which can hinder reliable identification and quantification of target
analytes. LC&#x02013;MS method was longer than that used with enrichment
(6.5 min vs 3.5 min) in order to decrease the effects of the matrix
by extending the chromatographic separation.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="au4c00980_0004" id="gr4" position="float"/></fig><p>The high RBD binding ability of ACE2-COMP, together
with its retention
of bound RBD, would be expected to make this protein a good candidate
for enrichment of spike protein from samples for MS. To test this,
we examined the ability of ACE2-COMP to recover SARS-CoV-2 spike protein
for detection by LC&#x02013;MS, first in matrix na&#x000ef;ve (PBS)
samples and subsequently in saliva. We therefore developed an enrichment
assay that functionalized 96-well plates with the ACE2-COMP trap protein
(125 ng per well) before the addition of a sample containing the SARS-CoV-2
spike protein. Following incubation and washing steps, bound spike
and ACE2-COMP were subject to tryptic digestion (1 mg/mL, 37 &#x000b0;C,
overnight) after the reduction (DTT, 60 &#x000b0;C, 30 min) and alkylation
(IAA, 21 &#x000b0;C, 30 min) of the cysteine residues. A stable isotope-labeled
peptide mix (500 nM) was added before the digestion to allow for peptide
normalization of the spike tryptic peptides. Digested samples were
injected (10 &#x003bc;L) onto the LC&#x02013;MS system, where peptides
were chromatographically resolved using a binary pump, reversed phase
(C18) gradient elution with acidified water, and acetonitrile. Peptides
were detected following the observation of multiple precursor to product
ion transitions within the MS operating in the MRM mode. LC&#x02013;MS
detection required only 3 min per sample.</p><p>Recovery of the spike
protein in both matrix na&#x000ef;ve samples
and biological matrix (saliva) was successful when using the enrichment
assay detailed above, as demonstrated in <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref></xref>. ACE2-COMP-functionalized plates allowed
clear detection of spike peptides by MS, following spike protein capture
from saliva (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref></xref>A,B). Spike peptides were undetectable in control wells that lacked
ACE2-COMP. Testing recovery and quantitation of spikes over a range
of different concentrations (1.2&#x02013;156.8 nM) confirmed MS peptide
signal scales with spike concentrations up until saturation of the
binding sites was reached (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref></xref>C). Given the high-binding capacity of our ACE2-COMP,
even when immobilized at relatively low levels (125 ng per enrichment),
it would be possible to readily decrease or increase the amount of
trap used to accommodate sufficient antigen binding in different matrices
and uses.</p><fig id="fig5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>ACE2-COMP trap capture-based mass spectrometric assay for the resolution
and detection of SARS-CoV-2 spike peptides. (A) Overlayed chromatogram
of saliva with spike protein (157 nM) extracted with the trap assay
but with plates that lack ACE2-COMP capture protein. (B) Overlayed
chromatogram of saliva with spike protein (157 nM) extracted using
plates coated with the ACE2-COMP capture protein. (C) Concentration
dependence of spike protein detection in PBS and saliva (as indicated).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="au4c00980_0005" id="gr5" position="float"/></fig><p>This study aimed to develop a method for high-affinity
receptor-based
capture combined with MS for detection and quantitation of target
proteins. We used the SARS-CoV-2 spike protein as an example of an
important target protein. Directed protein evolution is a powerful
method for engineering protein functionality, including affinity.
However, mutations introduced in the evolution into the RBD binding
site on ACE2 can make such proteins sensitive to mutations in spike
protein, potentially decreasing their ability to bind variants.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref></sup> Here, we focused on ACE2 in which we evolved increased affinity
for RBD but retained the Wt binding interface, Ev-ACE2-A386L. Nevertheless,
even with this evolved ACE2, we found that despite the fact that all
mutations were peripheral to the RBD binding site, Ev-ACE-A386L displayed
differences in binding ability across the limited number of RBD variants
we tested. As an alternative to evolving ACE2, we therefore examined
Wt-ACE2 and sought to leverage avidity effects of multimerization
to increase binding to the viral spike. Pentameric ACE2, ACE2-COMP,
was found to bind very strongly to the RBD and retain the bound viral
protein over several hours. Furthermore, ACE2-COMP successfully quantitatively
enriched for viral spike protein from biological samples and increased
the sensitivity of detection of viral spike by MS. These data show
that combining capture by engineered high-binding activity receptors
with MS provides a method for rapid detection and quantitation of
target protein. This approach could be used for the detection of viral
attachment proteins other than the SARS-CoV-2 spike protein, where
host cell receptors are tractable to engineering. Furthermore, the
method could be used for any target protein for which a suitable receptor
or binding protein is known.</p></sec></sec></body><back><notes id="notes1" notes-type="si"><title>Supporting Information Available</title><p>The Supporting Information is
available free of charge at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/10.1021/jacsau.4c00980?goto=supporting-info">https://pubs.acs.org/doi/10.1021/jacsau.4c00980</ext-link>.<list id="silist" list-type="simple"><list-item><p>LC&#x02013;MS/MS MRM transitions for the SARS-CoV2, stable
isotope label, and ACE2-COMP peptides (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/jacsau.4c00980/suppl_file/au4c00980_si_001.pdf">PDF</ext-link>)</p></list-item></list></p></notes><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sifile1"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="au4c00980_si_001.pdf"><caption><p>au4c00980_si_001.pdf</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><notes notes-type="" id="notes3"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>N.P.J.B.,
J.E.S., and D.J.L.J. contributed to conceptualization; N.B. performed
evolutions, molecular biology, and protein expression; S.E.E. performed
binding experiments; D.L. and F.S. performed LC-MS; N.S.A. performed
microscopy; and R.H. performed viral culture and capture; all authors
contributed to writing. CRediT: <bold>Neil Bate</bold> investigation,
methodology, writing - review &#x00026; editing; <bold>Dan Lane</bold> formal analysis, investigation, methodology, writing - review &#x00026;
editing; <bold>Sian E Evans</bold> data curation, formal analysis,
investigation, writing - review &#x00026; editing; <bold>Farah Salim</bold> investigation, writing - review &#x00026; editing; <bold>Natalie S Allcock</bold> data curation, formal analysis, investigation, methodology, writing
- review &#x00026; editing; <bold>Richard Haigh</bold> data curation,
formal analysis, investigation, methodology, writing - review &#x00026;
editing; <bold>Julian E Sale</bold> conceptualization, writing - review
&#x00026; editing; <bold>Donald JL Jones</bold> conceptualization, funding
acquisition, supervision, writing - review &#x00026; editing; <bold>Nicholas
PJ Brindle</bold> conceptualization, data curation, formal analysis,
funding acquisition, project administration, supervision, writing
- original draft, writing - review &#x00026; editing.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement" id="notes2"><p>The authors
declare no competing financial interest.</p></notes><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>This work was funded by the Medical Research Council
(grant MC_PC_19043), N.P.J.B., D.J.L.J., and N.B. were supported by
the Medical Research Council (grant MR/X009521/1). This work was supported
through the Institute for Precision Health and Leicester Drug Discovery
(LD3) via an MRC Impact Accelerator Account award (MR/X502777/1).
R.H. was supported by the Biotechnology and Biological Sciences Research
Council (grant BB/V01465<italic>X</italic>/1). Work in the J.E.S.
group is supported by a core MRC grant to the LMB (U105178808). D.L.
is supported by the John and Lucille van Geest Foundation and the
NIHR Leicester Biomedical Research Centre (BRC). For the purpose of
open access, the author has applied a Creative Commons Attribution
license (CC BY) to any Author Accepted Manuscript version arising
from this submission.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit1"><name><surname>Kollhoff</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kipping</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Rauh</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ceglarek</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Barka</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Barka</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sinz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Development of a Rapid and Specific
MALDI-TOF Mass Spectrometric Assay for SARS-CoV-2 Detection</article-title>. <source>Clin. Proteomics</source>
<year>2023</year>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>26</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12014-023-09415-y</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37393264</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit2"><name><surname>H&#x000e4;llqvist</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Shapanis</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Heywood</surname><given-names>W. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Doykov</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>&#x0015a;piewak</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ghansah</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Keevil</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Jukes-Jones</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Foley</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Vissers</surname><given-names>J. P. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pattison</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ferries</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wardle</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Bartlett</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Calton</surname><given-names>L. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Razavi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pope</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Yip</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>L. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Nicholas</surname><given-names>B. I.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Noel</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Dalton</surname><given-names>R. N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Heales</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hopley</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pitt</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Barran</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>D. J. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Skipp</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Carling</surname><given-names>R. S.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Operation
Moonshot: Rapid Translation of a SARS-CoV-2 Targeted Peptide Immunoaffinity
Liquid Chromatography-Tandem Mass Spectrometry Test from Research
into Routine Clinical Use</article-title>. <source>Clin. Chem. Lab.
Med.</source>
<year>2023</year>, <volume>61</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>302</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>310</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1515/cclm-2022-1000</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36395058</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit3"><name><surname>Kipping</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>T&#x000e4;nzler</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sinz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<article-title>A Rapid and Reliable Liquid Chromatography/Mass
Spectrometry Method for SARS-CoV-2 Analysis from Gargle Solutions
and Saliva</article-title>. <source>Anal. Bioanal. Chem.</source>
<year>2021</year>, <volume>413</volume> (<issue>26</issue>), <fpage>6503</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6511</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00216-021-03614-y</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34427712</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit4"><name><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Allsopp</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>C. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Slingsby</surname><given-names>O. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Jukes-Jones</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Bird</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>N. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Razavi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Yip</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>T. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pope</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Khunti</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Doykov</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>H&#x000e4;llqvist</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Skipp</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Carling</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>D. J. L.</given-names></name>
<article-title>A High Throughput
Immuno-Affinity Mass Spectrometry Method for Detection and Quantitation
of SARS-CoV-2 Nucleoprotein in Human Saliva and Its Comparison with
RT-PCR, RT-LAMP, and Lateral Flow Rapid Antigen Test</article-title>. <source>Clin. Chem. Lab. Med.</source>
<year>2024</year>, <volume>62</volume>, <fpage>1206</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1515/cclm-2023-0243</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38253336</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit5"><name><surname>Suvarna</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Salkar</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Palanivel</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Bankar</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pai</surname><given-names>M. G. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Srivastava</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Khatri</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Agrawal</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Shrivastav</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Shastri</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Srivastava</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<article-title>A Multi-Omics
Longitudinal Study Reveals Alteration of the Leukocyte Activation
Pathway in COVID-19 Patients</article-title>. <source>J. Proteome Res.</source>
<year>2021</year>, <volume>20</volume> (<issue>10</issue>), <fpage>4667</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4680</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jproteome.1c00215</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34379420</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit6"><name><surname>Doykov</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Spiewak</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gilmour</surname><given-names>K. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gibbons</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pade</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>&#x000c1;ine</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Noursadeghi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Maini</surname><given-names>M. K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Manisty</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Treibel</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Captur</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Fontana</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Boyton</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Altmann</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Semper</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Heywood</surname><given-names>W. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Abbass</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; et al. <article-title>Quantitative, Multiplexed,
Targeted Proteomics for
Ascertaining Variant Specific SARS-CoV-2 Antibody Response</article-title>. <source>Cells Rep. Methods</source>
<year>2022</year>, <volume>2</volume> (<issue>9</issue>), <fpage>100279</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.crmeth.2022.100279</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit7"><name><surname>Yoshinari</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hirose</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ohya</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ohnishi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Taharaguchi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mekata</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Taniguchi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Maeda</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Orihara</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kawamura</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Arai</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Goda</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hara-Kudo</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Matrix-Assisted
Laser Desorption and Ionization Time-of-Flight Mass Spectrometry Analysis
for the Direct Detection of SARS-CoV-2 in Nasopharyngeal Swabs</article-title>. <source>Anal. Chem.</source>
<year>2022</year>, <volume>94</volume> (<issue>10</issue>), <fpage>4218</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4226</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.analchem.1c04328</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35238540</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit8"><name><surname>Renuse</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Vanderboom</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Maus</surname><given-names>A. D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kemp</surname><given-names>J. V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gurtner</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Madugundu</surname><given-names>A. K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Chavan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Madden</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mangalaparthi</surname><given-names>K. K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mun</surname><given-names>D.-G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kipp</surname><given-names>B. R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Dasari</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Grebe</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<article-title>A Mass Spectrometry-Based
Targeted Assay for Detection of SARS-CoV-2 Antigen from Clinical Specimens</article-title>. <source>eBioMedicine</source>
<year>2021</year>, <volume>69</volume>, <fpage>103465</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ebiom.2021.103465</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34229274</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit9"><name><surname>Hober</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tran-Minh</surname><given-names>K. H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Foley</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Vissers</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pattison</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ferries</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hermansson</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Betner</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Uhl&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Razavi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Yip</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pope</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>T. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>L. N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Bartlett</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Calton</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Alm</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Engstrand</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Edfors</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Rapid and Sensitive Detection of
SARS-CoV-2 Infection
Using Quantitative Peptide Enrichment LC-MS Analysis</article-title>. <source>eLife</source>
<year>2021</year>, <volume>10</volume>, <elocation-id>e70843</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.70843</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34747696</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit10"><name><surname>Van
Puyvelde</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Van Uytfanghe</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Van Oudenhove</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gabriels</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Van Royen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Matthys</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Razavi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Yip</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Drouin</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Claereboudt</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Foley</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wardle</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wyndham</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hankemeier</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Saelens</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Martens</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Stove</surname><given-names>C. P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Deforce</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Martens</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Vissers</surname><given-names>J. P. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>N. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Dhaenens</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Cov2MS: An Automated and Quantitative Matrix-Independent
Assay for Mass Spectrometric Measurement of SARS-CoV-2 Nucleocapsid
Protein</article-title>. <source>Anal. Chem.</source>
<year>2022</year>, <volume>94</volume> (<issue>50</issue>), <fpage>17379</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>17387</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.analchem.2c01610</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36490367</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit11"><name><surname>Mangalaparthi</surname><given-names>K. K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Chavan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Madugundu</surname><given-names>A. K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Renuse</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Vanderboom</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Maus</surname><given-names>A. D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kemp</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kipp</surname><given-names>B. R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Grebe</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<article-title>A SISCAPA-Based
Approach for Detection
of SARS-CoV-2 Viral Antigens from Clinical Samples</article-title>. <source>Clin. Proteomics</source>
<year>2021</year>, <volume>18</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>25</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12014-021-09331-z</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34686148</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit12"><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>K. K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Dorosky</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Abbasi</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Dye</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kranz</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Herbert</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Procko</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Engineering Human ACE2
to Optimize Binding to the Spike Protein of SARS Coronavirus 2</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<year>2020</year>, <volume>369</volume> (<issue>6508</issue>), <fpage>1261</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.abc0870</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32753553</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit13"><name><surname>Glasgow</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Glasgow</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Limonta</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Solomon</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lui</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Nix</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Rettko</surname><given-names>N. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zha</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Yamin</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kao</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>O. S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ravetch</surname><given-names>J. V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wiita</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>K. K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X. X.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hobman</surname><given-names>T. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kortemme</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Engineered
ACE2 Receptor Traps Potently Neutralize SARS-CoV-2</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source>
<year>2020</year>, <volume>117</volume>, <fpage>28046</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>28055</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.2016093117</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33093202</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit14"><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Buzko</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Higashide</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Taft</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Buta</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Bogunovic</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Spilman</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Niazi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Rabizadeh</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Soon-Shiong</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<article-title>An ACE2 Triple Decoy that Neutralizes SARS-CoV-2 Shows
Enhanced Affinity for Virus Variants</article-title>. <source>Sci. Rep.</source>
<year>2021</year>, <volume>11</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>12740</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-021-91809-9</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34140558</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit15"><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>K. K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>T. J. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Narayanan</surname><given-names>K. K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Procko</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<article-title>An Engineered Decoy
Receptor for SARS-CoV-2 Broadly Binds Protein S Sequence Variants</article-title>. <source>Sci. Adv.</source>
<year>2021</year>, <volume>7</volume> (<issue>8</issue>), <elocation-id>eabf1738</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/sciadv.abf1738</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33597251</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit16"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Vasilieva</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sui</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Berne</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Somasundaran</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Luzuriaga</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Greenough</surname><given-names>T. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Choe</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Farzan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Angiotensin-Converting
Enzyme 2 Is a Functional Receptor for the SARS Coronavirus</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<year>2003</year>, <volume>426</volume> (<issue>6965</issue>), <fpage>450</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>454</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature02145</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14647384</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit17"><name><surname>Bate</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Savva</surname><given-names>C. G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Moody</surname><given-names>P. C. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>J. K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Schwabe</surname><given-names>J. W. R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sale</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Brindle</surname><given-names>N. P. J.</given-names></name>
<article-title>In Vitro
Evolution Predicts Emerging SARS-CoV-2 Mutations with High Affinity
for ACE2 and Cross-Species Binding</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog.</source>
<year>2022</year>, <volume>18</volume> (<issue>7</issue>), <elocation-id>e1010733</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1010733</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35849637</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit18"><name><surname>Brindle</surname><given-names>N. P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sale</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Arakawa</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Buerstedde</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Nuamchit</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Steele</surname><given-names>K. H.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Directed
Evolution
of an Angiopoietin-2 Ligand Trap by Somatic Hypermutation and Cell
Surface Display</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<year>2013</year>, <volume>288</volume>, <fpage>33205</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>33212</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M113.510578</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24106271</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit19"><name><surname>Lan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Structure of the SARS-CoV-2 Spike Receptor-Binding Domain Bound to
the ACE2 Receptor</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<year>2020</year>, <volume>581</volume>, <fpage>215</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>220</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-020-2180-5</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32225176</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit20"><name><surname>Isobe</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Arai</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kuroda</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Okumura</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ono</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ushiba</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Nakakita</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Daidoji</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Nakaya</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<article-title>ACE2 N-Glycosylation
Modulates Interactions with SARS-CoV-2 Spike Protein in a Site-Specific
Manner</article-title>. <source>Commun. Biol.</source>
<year>2022</year>, <volume>5</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s42003-022-04170-6</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34987157</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit21"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Structural Basis for the Recognition of SARS-CoV-2 by Full-Length
Human ACE2</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<year>2020</year>, <volume>367</volume> (<issue>6485</issue>), <fpage>1444</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.abb2762</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32132184</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit22"><name><surname>Malashkevich</surname><given-names>V. N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kammerer</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Efimov</surname><given-names>V. P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Schulthess</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Engel</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<article-title>The Crystal Structure of a Five-Stranded Coiled Coil in COMP: A Prototype
Ion Channel?</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<year>1996</year>, <volume>274</volume>, <fpage>761</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>765</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.274.5288.761</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8864111</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit23"><name><surname>Terskikh</surname><given-names>A. V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Le Doussal</surname><given-names>J.-M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Crameri</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Fisch</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mach</surname><given-names>J.-P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kajava</surname><given-names>A. V.</given-names></name>
<article-title>&#x0201c;Peptabody&#x0201d;: A New
Type of High Avidity
Binding Protein</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source>
<year>1997</year>, <volume>94</volume> (<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>1663</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1668</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.94.5.1663</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9050835</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit24"><name><surname>Issa</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Farah</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Bate</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Giakomidi</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Brindle</surname><given-names>N. P.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Development of an Orthogonal Tie2
Ligand Resistant
to Inhibition by Ang2</article-title>. <source>Mol. Pharmaceutics</source>
<year>2018</year>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>3962</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3968</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.molpharmaceut.8b00409</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit25"><name><surname>Vauquelin</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Charlton</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Exploring Avidity:
Understanding the Potential Gains
in Functional Affinity and Target Residence Time of Bivalent and Heterobivalent
Ligands</article-title>. <source>Br. J. Pharmacol.</source>
<year>2013</year>, <volume>168</volume> (<issue>8</issue>), <fpage>1771</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1785</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/bph.12106</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23330947</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit26"><name><surname>Clausen</surname><given-names>T. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sandoval</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Spliid</surname><given-names>C. B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pihl</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Perrett</surname><given-names>H. R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Painter</surname><given-names>C. D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Narayanan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Majowicz</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kwong</surname><given-names>E. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>McVicar</surname><given-names>R. N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Thacker</surname><given-names>B. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Glass</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Torres</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Golden</surname><given-names>G. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Bartels</surname><given-names>P. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Porell</surname><given-names>R. N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Garretson</surname><given-names>A. F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Laubach</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Feldman</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hauser</surname><given-names>B. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Caradonna</surname><given-names>T. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kellman</surname><given-names>B. P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Martino</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gordts</surname><given-names>P. L. S. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Chanda</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>A. G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Godula</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Leibel</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Jose</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Corbett</surname><given-names>K. D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>A. B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Carlin</surname><given-names>A. F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Esko</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name>
<article-title>SARS-CoV-2 Infection Depends on Cellular
Heparan Sulfate and ACE2</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<year>2020</year>, <volume>183</volume> (<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>1043</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1057 e15</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2020.09.033</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32970989</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>