<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="case-report" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Radiol Case Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Radiol Case Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Radiology Case Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1930-0433</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11786798</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S1930-0433(25)00001-9</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.radcr.2025.01.003</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A rare case of myocardial bridging as a cause of complete heart block: A diagnostic challenge</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0001"><name><surname>Fathallah</surname><given-names>Ibrahim</given-names></name><email>ebrahim123qwe@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="cor0001" ref-type="corresp">&#x0204e;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0002"><name><surname>Qatza</surname><given-names>Ayham</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0003"><name><surname>Al-Talep</surname><given-names>Ahmed</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0004"><name><surname>Yousef</surname><given-names>Reham</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0005"><name><surname>Hasn</surname><given-names>Rami Asef</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">d</xref><xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">e</xref></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>a</label>Faculty of Medicine, Al-Baath University, Homs, Syria</aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>b</label>Faculty of Medicine, Hama University, Hama, Syria</aff><aff id="aff0003"><label>c</label>Faculty of Pharmacy, Damascus University, Damascus, Syria</aff><aff id="aff0004"><label>d</label>Department of Cardiology, Albasel Hospital, Tartous University, Tartous, Syria</aff><aff id="aff0005"><label>e</label>Faculty of Medicine, Tishreen University, Latakia, Syria</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor0001"><label>&#x0204e;</label>Corresponding author. <email>ebrahim123qwe@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>18</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>4</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>18</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>20</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1882</fpage><lpage>1887</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>1</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2025 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Inc. on behalf of University of Washington.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder/><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="abs0001"><p>Complete heart block (CHB) is a disruption in electrical impulses to travel from atria to ventricles and can rarely be caused by myocardial bridging (MB), where cardiac tissue compresses a coronary artery during systole. The incidence of MB ranges from 0.5 % to 16 % in coronary angiography patients. This case report presents a 30-year-old female presented with dizziness, shortness of breath, and chest pain, diagnosed with third-degree AV block. Echocardiography revealed interventricular septal thickening and mild mitral regurgitation. Coronary angiography identified myocardial bridging in the mid LAD artery causing significant systolic stenosis. After ruling out reversible causes, a dual-chamber permanent pacemaker was implanted due to persistent heart block. The patient remained stable postprocedure, with decreasing cardiac biomarkers, and was discharged symptom-free with a follow-up appointment scheduled. MB can lead to serious cardiovascular events, including myocardial infarction and CHB. Clinicians must recognize the risks associated with MB and maintain a high suspicion for CHB to ensure timely management. Further studies are needed to clarify the CHB-MB relationship and improve patient outcomes.</p></abstract><kwd-group id="keys0001"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Complete heart block</kwd><kwd>Myocardial bridging</kwd><kwd>Catheterization</kwd><kwd>Case report</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta><def-list><title>List of abbreviations</title><def-item><term id="key6a">AV</term><def><p>atrioventricular</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="key7a">beats/minute</term><def><p>beats per minute</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="key8a">CHB</term><def><p>complete heart block</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="key9a">&#x000b0;&#x000b0;C</term><def><p>degrees Celsius</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="key10a">ECG</term><def><p>electrocardiogram</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="key11a">FFR</term><def><p>fractional flow reserve</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="key12a">HCM</term><def><p>hypertrophic cardiomyopathy</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="key13a">IVSS</term><def><p>interventricular septal thickness</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="key14a">IVUS</term><def><p>intravascular ultrasonography</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="key15a">LAD</term><def><p>left anterior descending</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="key16a">LVEF</term><def><p>left ventricular ejection fraction</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="key17a">LVH</term><def><p>left ventricular hypertrophy</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="key18a">mm Hg</term><def><p>millimeters of mercury</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="key19a">MB</term><def><p>myocardial bridging</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="key20a">OCT</term><def><p>optical coherence tomography</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="key21a">PCI</term><def><p>percutaneous coronary intervention</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="key22a">2D-TTE</term><def><p>two-dimensional transthoracic echocardiogram</p></def></def-item></def-list></front><body><sec id="sec0001"><title>Introduction</title><p id="para0003">The cardiac conduction system includes specialized fibers that originate electrical impulses and transport them across the heart's chambers [<xref rid="bib0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. May have an anatomical or physiological problem in the heart's conduction system, such as a complete heart block (CHB), which is a delay or disruption in the movement of an impulse from the atria to the ventricles [<xref rid="bib0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. (CHB) can be rarely caused by a myocardial bridging (MB). MB is the constructed tunnel's systolic pressure in the coronary artery by the cardiac tissue that covers it, which entirely vanishes during diastolic [<xref rid="bib0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. MBs are primarily located in the central region of the left frontal descending coronary artery [<xref rid="bib0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. In addition, diagonal and peripheral branches may be affected in 18 % and 40 % of situations, respectively. According to coronary angiography, the predicted incidence of their finding ranges from 0.5 % to 16 % [<xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. This report presents a case of a 30-year-old female diagnosed with constrained myocardial bridging of the left anterior descending (LAD) artery, causing irreversible CHB. Following a successful dual-chamber permanent pacemaker procedure, the patient's condition stabilized.</p><sec id="sec0002"><title>Case presentation</title><p id="para0004">A 30-year-old married female presented to the cardiac clinic with dizziness, shortness of breath, and 2 days of chest pain. She characterized the pain as pressure-like, severe in intensity, nonradiating, appearing at rest and worsening with exertion, and having no alleviating factors. No disease was reported in the patient's familial history. She was pregnant for the second time without any complications in the recent pregnancies and had previously undergone 1 caesarean section. She denied smoking, drinking alcohol, or drug abuse. Vital signs on admission were as follows: blood pressure, 90/60 millimeters of mercury (mm Hg); a slow heart rate, 35 beats per minute (beats/minute); tympanic temperature, 36.5 degrees Celsius (&#x000b0;C); and oxygen saturation, 93 % on room air. On physical examination, the patient was conscious and responsive with general weakness, pallor, clear-to-auscultation lungs, and systolic murmur heard during cardiac examination because of slight mitral regurgitation. Moreover, the neurologic and abdominal examinations were normal. All laboratory investigations were normal, except for an elevated troponin T level of 24 ng/mL. The 12-lead electrocardiogram (ECG) showed third-degree atrioventricular (AV) block"CHB" (<xref rid="fig0001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). A two-dimensional transthoracic echocardiogram (2D-TTE) revealed an interventricular septal thickness (IVSS) of approximately 2 cm during systole (<xref rid="fig0002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>), mild mitral regurgitation, and a left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) of 65 % (<xref rid="fig0003" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>). To address the CHB, a temporary pacemaker wire was inserted via the femoral vein into the right ventricle. Based upon these findings, the diagnosis was an acute myocardial infarction causing reversible complete heart block, which often improves with reperfusion. The patient underwent urgent percutaneous coronary intervention (PCI) in the cardiac catheterization laboratory to determine the cause. The left coronary angiogram revealed a MB in the mid LAD artery, resulting in 90%-95% stenosis during systole, with normal caliber during diastole (<xref rid="fig0004" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>). Based on the angiographic findings, a coronary spasm provocation test was not conducted. Intravascular ultrasonography (IVUS), fractional flow reserve (FFR), and optical coherence tomography (OCT) were not conducted as they were unavailable in our setting. The patient was started on a loading dose of 300 mg aspirin, 300 mg clopidogrel, and 40 mg rosuvastatin.Following medication administration, reversible causes of CHB were ruled out. Despite 72 h of observation, there was no improvement in the heart block, leading to the implantation of a dual-chamber permanent pacemaker due to the persistent heart block and the patient's refusal for surgery. It is noteworthy that surgery does not guarantee the reversal of CHB or the return of sinus rhythm. The remainder of his ensuing hospitalization was uneventful, remaining angina-free and hemodynamically stable with decreasing cardiac biomarkers. He was discharged with a follow-up appointment scheduled in 1 week at the cardiology clinic. At the last review, he was in excellent condition without symptoms.<fig id="fig0001"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>The 12-lead electrocardiogram (ECG) demonstrated a third-degree atrioventricular block "complete heart block".</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0001">Fig 1:</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1" id="celink0001"/></fig><fig id="fig0002"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>The two-dimensional transthoracic echocardiography: Parasternal short axis view (A) and parasternal long axis view (B) echocardiogram demonstrated left ventricular hypertrophy.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0002">Fig 2:</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2" id="celink0002"/></fig><fig id="fig0003"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>The two-dimensional transthoracic echocardiography. (A): The apical 4-chamber view echocardiogram displayed mild mitral regurgitation. (B): Continuous wave doppler of the normal aortic valve without stinosis or regurgitation.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0003">Fig 3:</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr3" id="celink0003"/></fig><fig id="fig0004"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Invasive coronary angiography images: The left coronary angiogram revealed a myocardial bridge in the mid left anterior descending artery (yellow arrows), resulting in 90%-95% stenosis during systole (B), with normal caliber during diastole (A). In addition to a temporary pacemaker (red arrow).</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0004">Fig 4:</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr4" id="celink0004"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec0003"><title>Discussion</title><p id="para0005">A third-degree heart block known as CHB happens when there is no AV conduction and no P waves linked to QRS complexes. Declared alternatively, the generated supraventricular impulses do not conduct to the ventricles. Rather, a junctional or ventricular escape rhythm maintains ventricular conduction, considering it exists. The atria and ventricles are entirely distinct from one another [<xref rid="bib0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Patients with MB can present medically in one of 2 ways: by direct compression of the tunneled segment due to contraction of MB fibers or by acceleration and stimulation of atherosclerosis in the segment nearest to MB [<xref rid="bib0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. During systole, full or partial blockage of the descending anterior coronary artery can lead to significant MB. Patients with MB frequently suffer from tachycardia and other symptoms during workouts. It is considered that systolic compression was not the sole cause of ischemia because myocardial perfusion occurs mainly during diastole. Endothelial cell damage, chronic mechanical stress that predisposes the tunneled segment of a coronary artery to vasospasm, and early atherosclerosis on MB can all contribute to ischemia [<xref rid="bib0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. At rest, the patient may have chest squeezing [<xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Acute coronary syndromes, myocardial ischemia, myocardial spasm, exercise-induced dysrhythmias (such as ventricular tachycardia or AV block), transient ventricular dysfunction, syncope, or even sudden death are all possible signs of MB [<xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Previous research has shown that MB is more common in cardiac disorders related with left ventricular hypertrophy (LVH), such as aortic stenosis and hypertrophic cardiomyopathy (HCM) [<xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. In particular, HCM patients have an increased incidence than the general population, with rates up to 30 % [<xref rid="bib0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Myocardial ischemia appeared by persistently high troponin levels [<xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. This case presents a rare instance of third-degree AV block "CHB" caused by MB, with limited reports available in the literature similar to it. According to a study, patients with MB can have minor myocardial dysfunction identified by three-dimensional speckle-tracking echocardiography predicated on the amplitudes of longitudinal, circumferential, and radial strains [<xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Echocardiography is advised for all patients with AV block in order to cancel out structural heart disease [<xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. For treatment, antiplatelet therapy should be given consideration because patients with MB are more inclined to experience atherosclerosis. Beta-blockers are the primary type of conservative treatment for symptomatic patients because they reduce heart rate, increase diastolic coronary filling, and decrease myocardial contractility and coronary artery pressure. Nitroglycerin can be administered cautiously [<xref rid="bib0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. In addition, consider a temporary transvenous pacemaker for patients with unstable AV block who are not responding to medicinal treatment [<xref rid="bib0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], and permanent pacemaker implantation needs to be explored in patients with high-grade or complete heart block [<xref rid="bib0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Depending on present guidelines, dual-chamber pacing is better than single-chamber pacing [<xref rid="bib0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Herein, a dual-chamber permanent pacemaker was implanted due to persistent heart block, as the patient declined surgical intervention.</p></sec><sec id="sec0004"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="para0006">MB is an unexpected disease associated with a series of significant cardiovascular events, including myocardial infarction, arrhythmia, and sudden death. Therefore, it is crucial for clinicians to be aware of the potential risks associated with MB, and appropriate management should be implemented promptly. In addition, this paper aims to emphasise the importance of having a high suspicion of CHB in the patients diagnosed with MB because of its adverse and life-threatening consequences. Further studies and reports of similar cases can contribute to an enhanced comprehension of the CHB-MB relationship, thereby improving patient outcomes.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="sec0005"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p id="para0007">Data sharing not applicable to this article as no datasets were generated or analyzed during the current study.</p></sec><sec id="sec0006"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="para0008">Ethics clearance was not necessary since the University waives ethics approval for publication of case reports involving no patients' images, and the case report is not containing any personal information. The ethical approval is obligatory for research that involve human or animal experiments.</p></sec><sec id="sec0007"><title>CRediT authorship contribution statement</title><p id="para0009"><bold>Ibrahim Fathallah:</bold> Writing&#x02014;review and editing, Writing&#x02014;original draft, Data curation.</p><p id="para0010"><bold>Ayham Qatza:</bold> Writing&#x02014;review and editing, Writing&#x02014;original draft.</p><p id="para0011"><bold>Ahmed Al-Talep:</bold> Writing&#x02014;review and editing, Writing&#x02014;original draft.</p><p id="para0012"><bold>Reham Yousef:</bold> Writing&#x02014;review and editing, Writing&#x02014;original draft.</p><p id="para0013"><bold>Rami Asef Hasn:</bold> Writing&#x02014;review and editing, Supervisor.</p><p id="para0014"><bold>Ibrahim Fathallah:</bold> Submitted the final manuscript.</p><p id="para0015">All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="sec0008"><title>Patient consent</title><p id="para0016">Written informed consent was obtained from the patient for publication of this case report and any accompanying images. A copy of the written consent is available for review by the Editor-in-Chief of this journal on request.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebibl1"><title>References</title><ref id="bib0001"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0001"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>&#x0017b;uchowski</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x00142;aszyk</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Piskorski</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wykr&#x00119;towicz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guzik</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dependence of the atrioventricular conduction time on the conduction through the atrioventricular node and his-Purkinje system</article-title><source>J Clin Med</source><volume>12</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2023</year><fpage>1330</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm12041330</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36835864</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0002"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0002"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>A.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>DiMarco</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellenbogen</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Estes</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names><suffix>3rd</suffix></name><name><surname>Freedman</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gettes</surname><given-names>L.S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>ACC/AHA/HRS 2008 Guidelines for Device-based Therapy of Cardiac Rhythm Abnormalities: a report of the American College of Cardiology/American Heart Association Task Force on Practice Guidelines (Writing Committee to Revise the ACC/AHA/NASPE 2002 Guideline Update for Implantation of Cardiac Pacemakers and Antiarrhythmia Devices) developed in collaboration with the American Association for Thoracic Surgery and Society of Thoracic Surgeons</article-title><source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source><volume>51</volume><issue>21</issue><year>2008</year><fpage>e1</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jacc.2008.02.032</pub-id><comment>Erratum in: J Am Coll Cardiol. 2009 Apr 21;53(16):1473. Erratum in: J Am Coll Cardiol. 2009 Jan 6;53(1):147</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18498951</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0003"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0003"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akdemir</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gunduz</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Emiroglu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Uyan</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Myocardial bridging as a cause of acute myocardial infarction: a case report</article-title><source>BMC Cardiovasc Disord</source><volume>2</volume><year>2002</year><fpage>15</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2261-2-15</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12243650</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0004"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0004"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>M&#x000f6;hlenkamp</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hort</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Erbel</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Update on myocardial bridging</article-title><source>Circulation</source><volume>106</volume><issue>20</issue><year>2002</year><fpage>2616</fpage><lpage>2622</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.cir.0000038420.14867.7a</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12427660</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0005"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0005"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hongo</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tada</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yasumura</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyatake</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamagishi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Augmentation of vessel squeezing at coronary-myocardial bridge by nitroglycerin: study by quantitative coronary angiography and intravascular ultrasound</article-title><source>Am Heart J</source><volume>138</volume><issue>2 Pt 1</issue><year>1999</year><fpage>345</fpage><lpage>350</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0002-8703(99)70123-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10426850</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0006"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0006"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knabben</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chhabra</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Slane</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Third-degree atrioventricular block</part-title><source>StatPearls [Internet]</source><year>2023</year><publisher-name>StatPearls Publishing</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Treasure IslandFL</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0007"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0007"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lujinovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kulenovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kapur</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gojak</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Morphological aspects of myocardial bridges</article-title><source>Bosn J Basic Med Sci</source><volume>13</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>212</fpage><lpage>217</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17305/bjbms.2013.2304</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24289755</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0008"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0008"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dursun</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bahcivan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Durna</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ibrahimov</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Erk</surname><given-names>N.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yasar</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Treatment strategies in myocardial bridging: a case report</article-title><source>Cardiovasc Revasc Med</source><volume>7</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2006</year><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>198</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.carrev.2006.02.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16945830</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0009"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0009"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Teragawa</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujii</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueda</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Murata</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nomura</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Case of angina pectoris at rest and during effort due to coronary spasm and myocardial bridging</article-title><source>World J Cardiol</source><volume>7</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>367</fpage><lpage>372</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4330/wjc.v7.i6.367</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26131343</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0010"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0010"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Corban</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hung</surname><given-names>O.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eshtehardi</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rasoul-Arzrumly</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>McDaniel</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mekonnen</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Myocardial bridging: contemporary understanding of pathophysiology with implications for diagnostic and therapeutic strategies</article-title><source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source><volume>63</volume><issue>22</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>2346</fpage><lpage>2355</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jacc.2014.01.049</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24583304</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0011"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0011"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tarantini</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Migliore</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cademartiri</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fraccaro</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iliceto</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Left anterior descending artery myocardial bridging: a clinical approach</article-title><source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source><volume>68</volume><issue>25</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>2887</fpage><lpage>2899</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jacc.2016.09.973</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28007148</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0012"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0012"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alegria</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Herrmann</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jr</surname><given-names>Holmes DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lerman</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rihal</surname><given-names>C.S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Myocardial bridging</article-title><source>Eur Heart J</source><volume>26</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2005</year><fpage>1159</fpage><lpage>1168</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/eurheartj/ehi203</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15764618</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0013"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0013"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dupont</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mullens</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Bruyne</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanermen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Myotomy through heart-port access for myocardial bridging</article-title><source>Int J Cardiol</source><volume>124</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2008</year><fpage>e16</fpage><lpage>e18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijcard.2006.11.157</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17321617</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0014"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0014"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>A.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>G.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of left ventricular function by three-dimensional speckle-tracking echocardiography in patients with myocardial bridging of the left anterior descending coronary artery</article-title><source>J Am Soc Echocardiogr</source><volume>28</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>674</fpage><lpage>682</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.echo.2015.02.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25795472</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0015"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0015"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fontana</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pica</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reant</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdel-Gadir</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Treibel</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Banypersad</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prognostic value of late gadolinium enhancement cardiovascular magnetic resonance in cardiac amyloidosis</article-title><source>Circulation</source><volume>132</volume><issue>16</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>1570</fpage><lpage>1579</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.115.016567</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26362631</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0016"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0016"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>S.M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Myocardial bridging</article-title><source>Braz J Cardiovasc Surg</source><volume>31</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>60</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5935/1678-9741.20150082</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27074276</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0017"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0017"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bj&#x000f8;rnstad</surname><given-names>C.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gjertsen</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thorup</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gundersen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tobiasson</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Otterstad</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Temporary cardiac pacemaker treatment in five Norwegian regional hospitals</article-title><source>Scand Cardiovasc J</source><volume>46</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>137</fpage><lpage>143</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/14017431.2012.672763</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22390277</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0018"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0018"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhakta</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kron</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>A.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pascuzzi</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Groh</surname><given-names>W.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pacemaker and implantable cardioverter-defibrillator use in a US myotonic dystrophy type 1 population</article-title><source>J Cardiovasc Electrophysiol</source><volume>22</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>1369</fpage><lpage>1375</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1540-8167.2011.02200.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22035077</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0019"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0019"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sweeney</surname><given-names>M.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hellkamp</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellenbogen</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenspon</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Freedman</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>K.L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Adverse effect of ventricular pacing on heart failure and atrial fibrillation among patients with normal baseline QRS duration in a clinical trial of pacemaker therapy for sinus node dysfunction</article-title><source>Circulation</source><volume>107</volume><issue>23</issue><year>2003</year><fpage>2932</fpage><lpage>2937</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.CIR.0000072769.17295.B1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12782566</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref></ref-list><fn-group><fn id="d36e42"><p id="notep0001">Competing Interests: The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p></fn><fn id="d36e45"><p id="notep0002">Acknowledgments: We express our sincere gratitude to Dr. Ali Majd Mouhammad for his contribution to the implantation of a dual-chamber pacemaker.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>