<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="review-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Digit Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Digit Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Digit. Health</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Digital Health</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2673-253X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12098494</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fdgth.2025.1380088</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Digital Health</subject><subj-group><subject>Review</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Applying models of self-regulated learning to understand engagement with digital health interventions: a narrative review</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Claudia</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref><uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2638886/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/formal-analysis/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/investigation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/methodology/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Messer</surname><given-names>Mariel</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1214611/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/investigation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/methodology/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/supervision/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Linardon</surname><given-names>Jake</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/investigation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/methodology/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/supervision/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fuller-Tyszkiewicz</surname><given-names>Matthew</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/investigation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/methodology/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/supervision/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label><sup>1</sup></label><institution>School of Psychology, Deakin University</institution>, <addr-line>Melbourne, VIC</addr-line>, <country>Australia</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label><sup>2</sup></label><institution>Centre for Social and Early Emotional Development, Deakin University</institution>, <addr-line>Burwood, VIC</addr-line>, <country>Australia</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p><bold>Edited by:</bold> Mario Alvarez-Jimenez, The University of Melbourne, Australia</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p><bold>Reviewed by:</bold> Chien-Sing Lee, Sunway University, Malaysia</p><p>Vivienne Lewis, University of Canberra, Australia</p></fn><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label><bold>Correspondence:</bold> Claudia Liu <email>clauds.liu@deakin.edu.au</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>09</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>1380088</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>01</day><month>2</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>08</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2025 Liu, Messer, Linardon and Fuller-Tyszkiewicz.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Liu, Messer, Linardon and Fuller-Tyszkiewicz</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY)</ext-link>. The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Digital health interventions (DHIs) are often burdened by poor user engagement and high drop-out rates, diminishing their potential public health impact. Identifying user-related factors predictive of engagement has therefore drawn significant research attention in recent years. Absent from this literature&#x02014;yet implied by DHI design&#x02014;is the notion that individuals who use DHIs have well-regulated learning capabilities that facilitate engagement with unguided intervention content. In this narrative review, we make the case that learning capacity can differ markedly across individuals, and that the requirements of self-guided learning for many DHIs do not guarantee that those who sign up for these interventions have good learning capabilities at the time of uptake. Drawing upon a rich body of theoretical work on self-regulated learning (SRL) in education research, we propose a user-as-learner perspective to delineate parameters and drivers of variable engagement with DHIs. Five prominent theoretical models of SRL were wholistically evaluated according to their relevance for digital health. Three key themes were drawn and applied to extend our current understanding of engagement with DHIs: (a) common drivers of engagement in SRL, (b) the temporal nature of engagement and its drivers, and (c) individuals may differ in learning capability. Integrating new perspectives from SRL models offered useful theoretical insights that could be leveraged to enhance engagement with intervention content throughout the DHI user journey. In an attempt to consolidate these differing&#x02014;albeit complementary&#x02014;perspectives, we develop an integrated model of engagement and provide an outline of future directions for research to extend the current understanding of engagement issues in self-guided DHIs.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>digital health interventions</kwd><kwd>user engagement</kwd><kwd>self-regulated learning</kwd><kwd>narrative review</kwd><kwd>digital health</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn001">Deakin University</funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>The author(s) declare that financial support was received for the research and/or publication of this article. Open access publication fees were supported by internal funding from Deakin University. Jake Linardon holds a National Health and Medical Research Council Investigator Grant (APP1196948).</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="1"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="87"/><page-count count="13"/><word-count count="0"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>section-at-acceptance</meta-name><meta-value>Digital Mental Health</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p>Digital health interventions (DHIs) are self-guided therapeutic mental health interventions electronically administered through devices such as smartphones, tablets, and computers (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). Common forms of DHIs include app-based interventions&#x02014;where the therapeutic program is delivered using a mobile application, and web-based interventions&#x02014;that are delivered via an online web browser on a computer. With the growing reach of the internet and a global estimate of almost 6.9 billion smartphone users in 2023 (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>), there is promise for digital health to be a widely accessible and scalable component of 21st century healthcare systems alongside traditional, physically-located services such as hospitals and clinics. DHIs are viewed favorably because of their potential to overcome a number of barriers associated with face-to-face treatments including geographical constraints, shortages of trained professionals, desire for anonymity, and out-of-pocket expenses (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). Other potentially desirable features include their ability to monitor symptoms over time and to offer real-time symptom relief at pivotal life moments (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>).</p><p>Despite these potential benefits of digitalizing treatment delivery, low treatment adherence, defined as the failure to complete the full intervention (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>), is a hallmark feature of DHIs that threatens to undermine their potential contribution to healthcare delivery. A systematic review and meta-analysis investigating adherence and attrition across 70 randomized controlled trials testing smartphone-app interventions found that only 34% of users completed the full intervention (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). This pattern of findings remained consistent with observations of DHI usage in natural settings (i.e., real-world environments), as industry market data show that almost 75% of users stopped interacting with their health apps after only 10 logins (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). This is problematic because it indicates that most users are not completing the full intervention as recommended, diminishing their potential to maximize positive treatment outcomes, and limiting public health impact.</p><p>The emerging research implicates poor user engagement, defined as an individual's usage, interaction, and involvement with a DHI (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>), as a likely factor underlying low adherence with self-guided DHIs (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). With the growing evidence base linking user engagement to improved post-treatment mental health outcomes (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>), increased efforts have been directed towards understanding the factors influencing people's adherence and engagement with DHIs (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). From this research, a number of user-related (e.g., demographics and psychological) and system-related characteristics (e.g., intervention provider and features) have been proposed as potential predictors of user engagement. Particularly, studies using web-based interventions found that age, gender (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>), education level (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>), and employment status (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>) were linked to engagement behaviors. Other user-specific factors that have also been connected to engagement are mental health symptom severity (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>), motivation (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>), self-efficacy (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>), treatment expectations (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>), and desire for anonymity (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). As for system and design-related factors, intervention format (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>), method of content delivery (e.g., interactive vs. static platform) (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>), tools for self-monitoring and goal setting (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>), technology-based reminders or prompts (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>) have been suggested to impact user retention (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>).</p><p>With respect to app-based interventions, prior studies have found a similar range of predictors; identifying age (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>), education level (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>), body mass index (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>), motivation (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>), perceived usefulness of the app (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>), and self-efficacy (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>) as user characteristics related to engagement. Whereas for intervention-specific factors, in-app functions that facilitate behaviors like goal setting (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>) and self-monitoring (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>) have been suggested to enhance engagement outcomes. Moreover, the visual design and usability (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>) of the app interface, as well as the intervention type (e.g., acceptance-based therapy) were also linked to adherence rates (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). Initially these findings appeared promising, but recent empirical and meta-analytic findings revealed that the individual and combined effects of these predictors are weak and inconsistent across studies (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). As such, there is need for the field to broaden its exploration of the potential factors and processes driving people's engagement with self-guided DHIs.</p><p>Enhancing our understanding of what drives engagement with DHIs is critical for realizing their potential as a key source of therapeutic support where traditional, physically located treatment solutions are not possible or undesirable. While, in the first instance, theoretical models help to explain behavior, ultimately, they may also signal ways to enhance design of DHIs to improve behavioral goals (i.e., engagement), and may also change expectations about the therapeutic value and best approach for utilizing DHIs for treatment.</p><p>Thus, we conducted a narrative review which firstly, outlines existing theoretical positions commonly taken in digital health research, and discuss their limitations for understanding user engagement. We then propose a novel lens through which we can view and reconceptualize engagement in the digital health context using relevant&#x02014;and complementary&#x02014;theories of self-regulated learning (SRL) from education research. To achieve this, we reviewed five prominent models of SRL and distilled key themes (or lessons) relevant for advancing digital health research by discussing how these themes deviate from current theory and practice. Finally, we integrate these insights into a new theoretical model of engagement for DHIs, discuss potential implications for practice, and outline recommendations for future directions in the field.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><label>2</label><title>Limitations to existing theoretical frameworks of digital health engagement</title><p>Concurrently, there are several existing frameworks that seek to define the likely factors shaping engagement specifically with DHIs. Most prominent are the conceptual models by Ritterband (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>), Short (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>), Perski (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>) and their respective colleagues. Consistent with the empirical research, all three models have emphasized the importance of the system's design and delivery platform (e.g., intervention content, aesthetics, and available functions), along with the individual's unique set of characteristics (e.g., demographics, motivation, self-efficacy, symptom severity, beliefs, and treatment expectations). These models also hypothesize that people's environments (e.g., social, cultural, and physical) can impact how much they adhere to and use an intervention. However, a key limitation common to these models is that they have not sufficiently considered how the individual engages with the treatment content across the user journey. In other words, the inherent temporal element that characterizes engagement has not been made explicitly clear in these existing frameworks. While this may be indirectly implied since both Short et al. (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>) and Perski et al. (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>) have drawn upon theories in information technology that have considered temporality (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>), engagement in both models is still depicted as a single or &#x0201c;absolute&#x0201d; event, rather than a dynamic process with varying levels of intensities. Cognizant of this underexplored concept for the digital health context, we make the case that adopting a new theoretical lens can offer important insights that can change first, how DHIs are designed, and second, how people use self-guided mental health programs, thereby enabling more practical benefits from DHIs.</p></sec><sec id="s3"><label>3</label><title>The user-as-learner perspective: A new theoretical lens to view engagement</title><p>To flesh out a user journey focus for DHI engagement, we draw upon a <italic>user-as-learner</italic> perspective: the broad reconceptualization of the digital health user as a learner. Understanding of how people learn is central to other disciplines, such as educational psychology. The education literature has been able to characterize individual differences in learning capacity, broadly conceived as a current&#x02014;though not necessarily fixed&#x02014;state of ability to take in information. Most importantly, this rich body of research has developed empirically supported theories that explain how people engage with a learning task over time, why individuals differ in their learning capacity, and what to do to strengthen this capacity when needed (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>).</p><p>The user-as-learner perspective can also be of relevance to understanding and enhancing engagement in DHIs given the implied&#x02014;yet seldom tested&#x02014;assumption that individuals who enroll in DHIs have the requisite learning skills to take in and apply the information that DHIs impart. Additionally, the path to progress in DHI engagement requires acquisition of new information and learning of new skills (often to be deployed in relation to mental health concerns). Overwhelmingly, DHIs are self-guided by design, meaning that people are required to independently complete the intervention program without any external assistance, as opposed to &#x0201c;guided&#x0201d; interventions where user progress and engagement are supported by a human facilitator (e.g., health professionals) (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). As such, the majority of DHIs deliver therapeutic content using unguided lessons or modules in the form of video tutorials, audio recordings, and written text (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>, <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). It is therefore essential for digital health users to (a) direct their own learning of the therapeutic information, and (b) independently manage their treatment progress (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). Theoretically, this should lead to enhanced knowledge surrounding the nature of one's mental health problems and the acquisition of new behavioral, cognitive, or social skills that can be enacted to manage their symptoms. However, self-guided programs can often be overwhelming for the everyday consumer as the accountability and control of the intervention progress has shifted from the clinician to the individual&#x02014;often isolated&#x02014;user.</p><p>While there is limited research that applies the user-as-learner perspective to the digital health context, there is evidence, albeit indirect, suggesting that various outcomes of learning, namely knowledge acquisition and skill enactment (also termed treatment receipt and enactment respectively), are potentially relevant to treatment engagement. This is the extent to which users understand and apply the skills taught in DHIs (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>). Gaining insight into the processes underlying their condition and learning about the purpose behind applying intervention skills, are believed to empower individuals to actively engage in and direct their recovery process (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). Conversely, poor comprehension of the intervention material can increase the risk of users losing confidence and the motivation to adhere to their treatment plan (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>). Though largely untested and inadequately fleshed out, aspects of learning have been subsumed in a number of conceptual frameworks exploring treatment engagement in both face-to-face and DHIs (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>). For instance, in Perski and colleagues' framework (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>), knowledge acquisition and skill enactment are viewed as potential mediators of engagement and intervention effectiveness. Comparably, Ritterband et al. (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>) also proposes these outcomes of learning as facilitators of health behavior change and eventual symptom improvement. Nevertheless, not sufficiently considered is how these facets of learning may also drive engagement itself. With the emerging research suggesting that various outcomes of learning (e.g., applying intervention skills in their day-to-day lives) may be more indicative measures of effective engagement with DHIs (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>), a stronger theoretical understanding of how these concepts are related is needed.</p><sec id="s3a"><label>3.1</label><title>Learner-centric frameworks for digital health</title><p>Despite the importance of knowledge acquisition and skill enactment in psychological interventions, the digital health literature seldom mentions a guiding framework that positions the user as a learner. One potential reason for this could be the field's limited efforts to integrate findings from seemingly unrelated disciplines (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). A useful starting point for bridging this gap may involve drawing insights from a different line of research, as there exists an array of learner-centric models in the education literature that could potentially be applied to explore user engagement in the digital health context. Self-regulated learning (SRL) is a key conceptual framework in educational psychology developed to understand how individuals engage with learning tasks in a self-directed way. The term SRL refers to the self-driven process whereby learners actively control their emotions, cognitions, and behaviors, using strategies oriented towards learning and, ultimately, goal attainment (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>). An important assumption in SRL theory is learner agency; the recognition that individuals have the <italic>potential</italic> to actively control their cognitions, motivation, and behaviors throughout the process of learning. However, not everyone can or will control these to the same degree (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>). This is supported by a large empirical base suggesting that people significantly differ in their SRL profiles, even among those who self-select into programs (e.g., online university courses, massive open online courses) that require considerable independent learning skills (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>). Given their self-guided nature and focus on knowledge transfer within these self-directed learning opportunities, it is plausible that this pattern of findings may also apply to DHIs. More specifically, it may be that variability in engagement behaviors with DHIs, at least in part, reflect individual differences in SRL ability across users. This is because not all users will have the same proficiency to cope with the information imparted in a self-guided intervention program.</p><p>Interestingly, there is a growing body of research showing that aspects of SRL (e.g., self-observation, and goal-setting) have been considered in the design of commercial smartwatches and smart home systems with respect to their role in supporting increased awareness and self-management of health-related issues (<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>). Smartwatch features that enable the collection of individual health data (e.g., heart rate variability, daily step count, sleep data) indirectly supports principles of SRL, as access to this information can empower people to set personal goals, track their progress, and regulate their behaviors to improve their ongoing health. Similarly, smart home technology has drawn considerable interest in recent years for its potential to facilitate self-management behaviors in individuals with cardiovascular diseases (<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>, <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>). The emerging research shows that smart home ecosystems can support people with monitoring their symptoms, adhering to treatment regimens, and generating feedback for self-regulation. These features enable patients to play a more active role in their recovery, which has been reported to enhance treatment compliance (<xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>). This literature further highlights the likely relevance of the SRL framework to guide the exploration of potential facilitators of engagement in both web and app-based interventions.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><label>4</label><title>Review of theoretical models of self-regulated learning</title><p>There are a number of SRL models&#x02014;each differing in their points of emphasis&#x02014;that could offer new perspectives for guiding research on user engagement. However, given that this will be the first attempt at incorporating SRL into digital health, rather than limiting to one specific model, we sought to investigate the potential relevance of common SRL models in the education literature. This is a practical way forward to explore the user-as-learner perspective because the consideration of SRL models may inform a new list of possible drivers of user engagement, and subsequently, viable targets for retention strategies in future DHIs. Considering the field's limited and heavily siloed understanding of user engagement, gaining new theoretical insights may be instrumental for increasing the impact of DHIs for those who opt for online treatment modalities (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>).</p><sec id="s4a"><label>4.1</label><title>Zimmerman: Cyclical Phases Model</title><p>Zimmerman's SRL model (<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>) is one of the most prominent frameworks in the education literature (<xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>). Heavily influenced by Bandura's social cognitive theory (<xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>), Zimmerman's model describes how metacognitive and motivational processes cyclically influence SRL across three interdependent phases: (a) forethought, (b) performance, and (c) self-reflection. In the current version of the model, learners in the forethought phase analyze learning tasks using skills like goal setting and strategic planning, which is facilitated and fueled by personal motivational beliefs. During performance, learners use self-control strategies such as time management and self-instruction to maintain the cognitive engagement required to complete the learning activity. During this phase, self-regulated learners also track their progress using self-observation strategies like self-monitoring and self-recording (<xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>). In the self-reflection phase, learners appraise their recent performance and find reasons for personal successes and failures. The model posits that future task performance is shaped by a learner's self-reaction and judgments, as this can positively or negatively impact future self-efficacy and learning efforts (<xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>, <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4b"><label>4.2</label><title>Pintrich: General Framework for SRL</title><p>Pintrich's model (<xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>) of SRL is another leading conceptual framework in the education literature embedded within the socio-cognitive theory (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>). The model classifies SRL into four interactive phases: (a) forethought/planning/activation, (b) monitoring, (c) control, and (d) reaction/reflection. Each phase has four areas for regulation (cognition, motivation, behavior, context), thus giving rise to a vast number of possible SRL processes (<xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>, <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>). While the different SRL phases appear to reflect a linearly ordered sequence, it is recognized that earlier phases may not always occur before later phases. Instead, planning, monitoring, controlling, and self-reflection are viewed as ongoing dynamic processes that can simultaneously occur as a learner engages and progresses with a learning task (<xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>). The overarching theme forming the focus of Pintrich's model is the strong integration of motivational processes (e.g., goal orientations and self-efficacy) across each phase, despite its position as an independent area for regulation (<xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>, <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4c"><label>4.3</label><title>Boekaerts: Dual Processing Model</title><p>Boekaerts' (<xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>) Dual Processing Model (previously called the Model of Adaptive Learning) highlights emotion regulation as an essential aspect of SRL, as emotions can influence when, how, and why students self-regulate their learning (<xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>). The model discerns three purposes for self-regulation during learning: (a) to develop one's skills and knowledge, (b) protecting the ego from harm and threat, and (c) protecting one's devotion to the learning task (<xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>). In the model, Boekaerts explains that learners activate the growth/mastery pathway when a learning task aligns with personal goals and positive emotions are triggered. This encourages learners to commit and metacognitively sustain their engagement to the learning task without needing much extrinsic assistance because the learner is intrinsically driven to develop their competence (<xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>). Conversely, learners initiate the well-being pathway when tasks are perceived as difficult or threatening to the ego and negative emotions are triggered. When the well-being pathway is activated, students are motivated to protect the ego from harm by either avoiding or giving up the task to prevent further unpleasant emotions (<xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>, <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>). Changes in appraisal may also happen, whereby students initially activate the growth pathway but redirect themselves to the well-being pathway after experiencing negative triggers or cues for failure, likely due to previous failed attempts. However, students may also revert back to the growth pathway by implementing volitional strategies to re-focus on the learning task at hand (<xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4d"><label>4.4</label><title>Winne and Hadwin: Metacognitive Model SRL</title><p>Shaped by the Information Processing Theory (IPT), Winne and Hadwin's model offers a metacognitive conceptualization of SRL (<xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>). The authors postulate that SRL consists of four recursive and loosely sequenced phases: (a) task definition, where the learner generates their perceptions of the task; (b) goal setting and planning, where the learner forges goals and formulates a plan to achieve them; (c) enacting study tactics and strategies, where the learner executes the plan; and (d) metacognitive adapting, where the learner adjusts their strategies and future approach based on their recent task execution (<xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>). Five IPT-influenced processes (referred to using the COPES acronym) are proposed to underpin each phase: conditions, operations, products, evaluations, and standards (<xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>). <italic>Conditions</italic> are the resources accessible by the learner and constraints specific to the task or environment (e.g., instructions, time). <italic>Operations</italic> are the various SMART cognitive strategies learners use to manipulate and process information, this includes searching, monitoring, assembling, rehearsing, and translating (<xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>, <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>, <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>). <italic>Products</italic> are the outcomes (i.e., information) generated by the aforementioned SMART operations. <italic>Evaluations</italic> refer to the internal feedback generated from self-monitoring concerning the discrepancy between the products and the <italic>Standards;</italic> the set of criteria the learner considers to be the optimal outcome (<xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>, <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4e"><label>4.5</label><title>Efklides: Metacognitive Affective Self-regulated Learning (MASRL) Model</title><p>Building on the ideas proposed in earlier SRL models (e.g., Zimmerman, Pintrich, and Winne and Hadwin), Efklides' MASRL model focuses on the regulation of motivation, affect, and cognition, and explains their interrelated yet distinct roles throughout the SRL process (<xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>, <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>). The model proposes two levels of SRL functioning. First, the <italic>Person-level</italic> (i.e., macro-level) depicts the top-down processes in SRL and shows how a learner's goals and personal traits (e.g., self-concept, motivation, affect etc.) can interact with each other to impact decisions relating to engagement with a learning task (<xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>). Conversely, the <italic>Task x Person-level</italic> (i.e., micro-level) represents the bottom-up regulation of learning where the processes are less characterized by the learner's traits and more by the specific demands of the learning task. This level is more data-driven in nature, as metacognitive monitoring of task processing and performance becomes the driving force behind the learner's actions. The two levels of SRL functioning are theorized to interact and reciprocally inform each other to influence the learner's affect, motivation, and effort regulation in a specific task.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s5"><label>5</label><title>Key themes in self-regulated learning theory: Lessons for digital health research</title><p>As articulated in <xref rid="s3" ref-type="sec">Section 3</xref>, digital health interventions (DHIs) have an underlying&#x02014;and often implicit&#x02014;emphasis on knowledge acquisition and psychoeducation, even if the stated primary goal is symptom improvement. Here, we seek to give greater prominence to this underlying dimension of learning as essential to treatment engagement and positive outcomes, by connecting DHIs to key principles of learning articulated in education research. Therefore, we propose the <italic>user-as-learner</italic> perspective as a novel approach for understanding individual differences in engagement with self-guided DHIs. Learner-centric models, particularly self-regulated learning (SRL), offer a well-established conceptual framework through which we can re-appraise the self-directed learning journey of individuals engaging with DHIs.</p><p>Wholistic evaluation of five models of self-regulated learning (<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>, <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>, <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>, <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>, <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>) revealed three key themes to guide a user-as-learner perspective for DHIs: (a) common drivers of engagement in SRL, (b) the temporal nature of engagement and its drivers, and (c) individuals may differ in learning capability. In the following section, each theme will be discussed according to its potential for extending the current understanding of user engagement with DHIs. Finally, to integrate these findings into the broader literature, we propose a new model of engagement for the digital health user journey and draw out important clinical and practical implications and directions for future research to leverage key insights from SRL for DHIs.</p><sec id="s5a"><label>5.1</label><title>Theme 1: Common drivers of engagement in SRL</title><p>SRL models offer a cohesive overview of the key factors underpinning the process of engagement in the learning context (broadly conceived). We use the term &#x0201c;broadly&#x0201d; to reflect the variation in nomenclature used by different SRL researchers to describe conceptually similar constructs (e.g., self-efficacy and confidence). Through appraising the five SRL models, we deduced a list of recurring factors or skills that have been theorized to influence people's engagement with learning tasks (see <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;1</xref>). Whereas some SRL factors are common across all models (e.g., motivation), others are more unique to specific frameworks, due to the slight differences in factor emphasized by each author (<xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>, <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>). Nevertheless, there is a general consensus that higher levels across these SRL variables can facilitate and sustain effortful engagement throughout one's learning journey, and in turn, promote positive learning outcomes (<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>, <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>, <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>, <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>, <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>). Thus, we henceforth refer to these variables collectively as &#x0201c;drivers&#x0201d; of engagement. Conversely, lower levels across these drivers are viewed as potential threats to engagement and can hinder the learning process.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Broadly recurring SRL drivers across prominent models of SRL.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SRL driver</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zimmerman</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pintrich</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Boekaerts</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Winne &#x00026; Hadwin</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Efklides</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHI literature</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1">Psychological</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Motivation</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-efficacy</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Task interest</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;*</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothesized</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Task value</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;*</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothesized</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outcome expectations</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-control</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;*</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insufficiently addressed</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Positive) emotions</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothesized</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1">Behavioral</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Goal setting</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;*</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metacognition</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insufficiently addressed</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1">Social</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Social factors</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-fn1"><p>&#x02713;&#x02009;=&#x02009;explicitly addressed; &#x02713;*&#x02009;=&#x02009;indirectly addressed; X&#x02009;=&#x02009;not addressed.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>As summarized in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;1</xref>, several key SRL drivers have already been considered in digital health research, both in empirical studies looking at predictors of user engagement, and in existing theories of digital health. For instance, five of these drivers including motivation, self-efficacy, outcome (treatment) expectations, social support, and goal setting have been associated with positive engagement outcomes in a number of DHI studies (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). Moreover, drivers like task interest, (positive) emotions, and task value have been hypothesized as potential facilitators or attributes of engagement in various conceptual frameworks of DHIs (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>), albeit lack the evidence base to confirm their influence on DHI usage. Despite the potential overlap in variables explored across these disciplines, a key point of difference is how some of these drivers are conceptualized and studied with respect to their potential role in influencing engagement behaviors. This is evident in drivers like metacognition and self-control, which have seldom been addressed or sufficiently considered in digital health research, though their closest comparators are concepts such as self-monitoring, self-evaluation, and goal setting.</p><p>SRL researchers describe learners as <italic>metacognitively</italic> active when they effortfully observe, reflect, and modify their behaviors to improve learning performance and, through this process, may be expected to observe positive progress towards their goals (<xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>). Superficially, this may seem comparable to self-monitoring and goal setting as understood within the digital health literature, however there are important&#x02014;though complementary&#x02014;points of differences. In the DHI context, users are typically encouraged to learn about the antecedents and consequences of problematic behaviors in order to intervene earlier in the onset of these problematic behaviors (<xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>). The learning emphasized in this DHI context is about monitoring symptoms, whereas in SRL, the focus is on monitoring one's <italic>learning</italic>, a higher order cognitive task which may inform whether the user has appropriately understood the treatment content and can apply it effectively within their daily lives. More specifically, the SRL focus is about being or becoming metacognitively aware of one's progress in acquiring and enacting new knowledge and skills from a learning task.</p><p>Adopting the SRL perspective would allow us to apply a metacognitive lens to how key skills are utilized in DHIs, by also asking individuals to reflect on their comprehension and attempted implementation of the content received. Quizzes and self-assessment may be deployed to evaluate learning in DHIs (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>), yet SRL approaches would go a step further in offering learning strategies to enhance understanding in cases where knowledge and/or enactment gaps are evident. More specifically, digital health users would be encouraged to reflect on whether they (a) understood the intervention module they have just engaged with, (b) felt confident with putting the newly acquired skills into practice, and (c) getting them to reflect on their attempts at applying these skills. This focus on self-awareness is central to understanding one's strengths and weaknesses with learning intervention skills and could help users identify which modules require further engagement to facilitate their primary goal of symptom improvement.</p><p>Similarly, self-control is another variable mentioned in both bodies of research, although with notably different foci. In the SRL literature, self-control has been viewed as an individual's discipline to engage in and sustain goal-directed behavior (<xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>, <xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>). This is an effortful process that requires a set of self-management strategies (e.g., time-management, self-instruction, and self-consequences) to help the learner maintain concentration and interest with their learning tasks (<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>, <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>). On the other hand, self-control in DHIs is typically about minimizing harmful behaviors, often in-the-moment. For example, DHIs may focus on identifying when an urge is present and learning how to control and override temptations. Integrating SRL theory to how common drivers are understood in the digital health literature would encourage the field to explore the role of self-control in a new angle. In particular, investigating its impact on successful learning and completion of intervention content. Though seldom acknowledged from this perspective, exercising self-control (and effective time management) to learn the information received is relevant, and likely essential, for treatment engagement. This is because individuals with greater self-discipline are theoretically more inclined to use the necessary strategies that will help sustain their motivation to learn successive intervention content.</p><p>In addition to these nuances in how specific concepts are understood, the interrelations between certain constructs are more strongly articulated in one discipline than the other. For instance, motivation in digital health is often referred to as an individual's readiness to change, or intention to engage in and complete treatment (<xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>, <xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>). However, SRL models suggest that this concept is more complex, and characterize motivation as a dimension of self-regulation influenced by multiple other drivers (e.g., self-efficacy beliefs, goal-directed behaviors, and task interest) throughout the learning process (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, <xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>). Thus, adopting the user-as-learner perspective may bring more attention to the inter-relations between multiple drivers and highlight possible mediating or moderating pathways for increased engagement with DHIs (further discussed in Theme 2).</p><p>Hence, the two lessons from Theme 1 are as follows. First, there are a number of potentially relevant SRL drivers that have been insufficiently considered or directly tested in the digital health context. This, therefore, suggests the need for broadening the range of predictors that we measure in studies investigating engagement with DHIs. Second, we should also think about appraising and conceptualizing these drivers in a new light. That is, rather than limiting our understanding of these constructs to the DHI context, we should consider how they are defined in different disciplines, particularly in bodies of work with theoretical models that can more comprehensively explain the interrelations between key drivers. A greater understanding of the potential interactions and mediating pathways can suggest new opportunities for intervention to enhance user engagement and guide the prioritization of what to intervene upon.</p></sec><sec id="s5b"><label>5.2</label><title>Theme 2: The temporal nature of engagement and its drivers</title><p>The second key theme across the SRL models is the notion that learning is an evolving and dynamic process (<xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>). That is, the constructs that drive engagement are not constant, and instead can wax and wane over time. In turn, increases or decreases in these drivers can also affect levels of learner engagement. Using Boekaert's model (<xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>) as an example; a student's appraisal for a learning task can change when there is a shift in emotional experience during task performance. For instance, challenging tasks initially perceived as easy may elicit feelings of hopelessness after several failed attempts. However, the student can also re-appraise the situation using emotion regulation strategies to deescalate those negative emotions that hinder effort investment for the learning task (<xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>, <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>). Two of the five SRL models (<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>, <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>) also suggest that engagement itself may provide a feedback loop for the drivers by enhancing motivation when one feels growing competence from successful task completion, or diminishing motivation in response to difficulties or failures. In broader terms, the outcome of engagement may also have an effect on its drivers, which in turn, can reinforce more or less of this positive outcome. This indicates that there are complex interactions occurring between different SRL variables over time (<xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>), which can determine the degree to which an individual seeks to initiate successive cycles of learning (<xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>).</p><p>This theme offers three important lessons with notable implications for the digital health context. The first, is that if these drivers of engagement do fluctuate over time as SRL research suggests, then <italic>when</italic> we measure them in the user journey matters. To date, much of the empirical work in the digital health field investigating predictors of engagement have been largely limited to baseline data, particularly in studies measuring drivers like motivation and self-efficacy (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>, <xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>). This is despite the large evidence base from related disciplines showing that motivation for treatment and behavior change can vary considerably over time (<xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>). Relying on baseline predictors alone may be a critical oversight, as new users can often present with an inflated attitude during the onboarding phase. Their initial motivation, however, may diminish when faced with unexpected challenges (e.g., difficulties understanding psychoeducational content), and thus, may not reliably predict engagement patterns later in the user journey. Therefore, it is essential to recognize that those factors driving initial uptake may differ to those factors sustaining engagement and eventual symptom improvement. An important takeaway for digital health researchers is to consider measuring these drivers not only at baseline, but also <italic>during</italic> the intervention. Exploring the relative contributors of engagement at different milestones in the user journey would serve to test this possibility if certain drivers are more important at particular times, and if time of measurement impact predictive ability.</p><p>The second point of relevance for digital health research is that we need to better understand the complex relationships between the different drivers and engagement itself. As briefly discussed in Theme 1, there are potential moderating and mediating pathways that need to be considered. Ignoring how the different variables inter-relate more broadly (e.g., looking at one variable alone without the interaction of the moderator) can result in an inaccurate estimate of the true effect of each driver on engagement. To articulate the complex interplay between different variables, we describe the potential impact of self-efficacy and its proposed correlates on digital health engagement. A user's self-efficacy beliefs about their ability to learn new intervention skills can determine not only their motivation, but also their goal setting behaviors, both of which can influence one's efforts to self-regulate their engagement with the intervention task (<xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>). Furthermore, this engagement or SRL of content received (dependent on the user's initial experiences) can form a positive or negative feedback loop that sustains or diminishes their ongoing self-confidence and motivation to persist with successive treatment content. Thus, to advance our understanding of people's likelihood of engagement, it is imperative to build upon existing models of digital health, to better define these complex&#x02014;and potentially bi-directional&#x02014;relationships between different variables.</p><p>Finally, if we can understand the temporality of engagement and its drivers, as well as how they relate to each other throughout the user journey, we can identify more opportunities to intervene. Importantly, this could also highlight the need for different intervention approaches at different stages to impact specific levers and bolster treatment engagement. To put it simply, digital health developers should consider implementing targeted interventions at specific points throughout the self-guided program to enhance key drivers of engagement where necessary. Efforts to increase engagement across the user journey could support users, particularly those with lower SRL skills, to complete the recommended psychoeducational modules and facilitate symptom improvement.</p></sec><sec id="s5c"><label>5.3</label><title>Theme 3: Individuals may differ in learning capability</title><p>The third key theme emerging from these common models of SRL is the recognition that people significantly differ in their capability for SRL, but also emphasizing that this capability for SRL skills is malleable and teachable. Learners are viewed as active participants in their learning journey (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>, <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>, <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>, <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>), meaning that with effortful attention and action, SRL skills can be developed and improved over time. To ground this discussion, there is a rich evidence base in the education literature showing that people substantially differ in their SRL profiles, particularly in online learning environments (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>). Despite being cognizant of the general academic skills (e.g., time management, planning, motivation) required to successfully complete a self-guided syllabus, the consistent pattern across many online courses is low completion and high dropout rates (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>). This may, at least in part, reflect the wide range of SRL capacities of people who self-select into digital learning environments, showing that not all learners have the ability or skillset to successfully complete an online course with minimal guidance.</p><p>Consideration of these individual differences in people's SRL capacity is potentially relevant in the digital health context because not all users have the required abilities or skillset at time of commencement. Nonetheless, there is an ongoing and misguided assumption that those who sign up for DHIs will know how to effectively manage and direct their learning of the content received. As a result, there is typically no direct attempt to (a) assess people's current SRL capacity, and (b) enhance these skills where necessary. For these reasons, many DHIs are not well-equipped or designed to support users who start out with low levels of SRL. This raises serious practical implications for those relying on DHIs as their primary mode of treatment (due to geographical, financial, or time restraints), as many first-time users may find intervention tasks difficult or overwhelming without the support of a clinician. Difficulties engaging with the treatment content may in turn, diminish people's motivation to persist in their user journey and complete the full program as recommended. Using SRL as a guiding framework, we believe it may be essential for those who enroll into DHIs to (a) be aware of their current learning abilities, and (b) effortfully enhance their SRL skills to drive ongoing engagement with the intervention material. Integrating an SRL perspective into the design phase may open up new avenues to overcome issues with sustained engagement. For instance, the development of support material to teach users the necessary skills to complete their DHIs and relieve unwanted symptoms.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s6"><label>6</label><title>Proposing the self-regulated learning model of digital health intervention</title><p>These themes drawn from SRL research offer complementary elements to enhance understanding of engagement throughout the DHI user journey. Existing theoretical models of engagement (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>) in digital health have emphasized the importance of intervention design and considered a range of potential drivers of engagement and successful outcomes. This includes user-related factors such as demographic characteristics, motivation, self-efficacy, and symptom severity, as well as system-related factors like interface design, usability, visual appeal, method of delivery, and available functions. However, a common limitation across these models is that they do not consider how the individual engages with the intervention <italic>throughout</italic> the user journey, which implicitly has a temporal element. This limited emphasis on the temporal aspect of the user journey has potential to miss opportunities for developing retention strategies that can mitigate risks of dropout at specific stages. The SRL models identified in <xref rid="s3" ref-type="sec">Section 3</xref>, on the other hand, inherently tap into this temporal dimension of engagement, which encourages further thought about how to structure the learning experience, what to measure across the user journey to evaluate success or need for additional support, and to also consider what may drive engagement at different stages of the journey.</p><p>Therefore, to consolidate the theoretical perspectives from SRL models into these earlier frameworks (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>), we propose a new model (see <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). Our model aims to explicitly characterize the complex and temporal nature of engagement throughout the DHI user journey and the key drivers underpinning this process. Whereas some factors are most relevant during the design phase of the intervention, others may be drivers of initial uptake or continued use. A salient feature of our model is the notion that the SRL drivers facilitating engagement are in fact <italic>fluid</italic> and likely interact with each other over time in feedback loops that may signal positive progress, or risk of disengagement and drop-out. Likewise, engagement itself plays a role in sustaining or diminishing the ongoing level of its key drivers. This means that some factors will remain relevant as the individual continues to use the DHI, so it is vitally important that we consistently monitor how these variables evolve across the user journey, rather than simply taking a single snapshot of these at baseline (i.e., prior to commencement of an intervention). The proposed model also depicts the bidirectional relationship between engagement and symptom improvement, demonstrating that level of symptom improvement can drive further engagement, just as engagement may also lead to greater symptom improvement.</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>SRL model of DHI engagement.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fdgth-07-1380088-g001" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="s7"><label>7</label><title>Potential implications of adopting the SRL model of DHI engagement</title><p>The proposed model (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>) was designed to address the limitations of the current research on DHI engagement highlighted in <xref rid="s2" ref-type="sec">Section 2</xref>. If this revised framework can improve how the field understands and predicts people's use of DHIs over time, it carries potential implications for enhancing theoretical knowledge, optimizing DHI design, and enhancing the implementation of DHIs in practice.</p><p>With respect to potential advances in knowledge, having a comprehensive framework that integrates SRL theory to understand engagement expands the current list of potential factors that are theorized&#x02014;and, over time, may be empirically demonstrated&#x02014;to drive or hinder this process. This has direct relevance for strengthening our predictive ability of who may disengage from DHIs prematurely. In addition, the model's emphasis on the temporality of engagement can provide deeper insights into (a) critical points along the user journey where engagement is likely to drop off, and (b) the key drivers that are most influential at each stage of the user journey. The temporal element also articulates the importance of extending beyond the all-too-common practice of using baseline predictors to assess engagement and treatment outcomes in DHI studies. While some authors have previously raised the importance of considering temporality in prediction of engagement (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, <xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B87" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>), our model provides a more fully formed vision of what impacts engagement and when, which should better guide study and DHI design.</p><p>These insights not only advance the theoretical understanding of engagement but also have meaningful implications for practice and future design of DHIs. The proposed model appreciates that individuals with high SRL abilities can benefit from DHIs immediately, whilst also acknowledging that in reality, not everybody signing up to DHIs will have these requisite skills. Thus, in practice, individuals interested in using DHIs may benefit from completing a screening tool that can assess their SRL capacity to determine their suitability for self-guided treatment approaches. Screening during the onboarding phase could help experts identify individuals who may struggle with self-guided treatment content, enabling opportunities for targeted support that can enhance their SRL skills. It may be that those with lower SRL need face-to-face contact with health professionals for a brief pre-training session on how to maximize positive outcomes from self-guided interventions, or perhaps building supplementary features into DHIs to target specific SRL deficiencies (e.g., goal setting tool to help the end-user set appropriate and personalized treatment goals). Pre-screening can also lead to more optimized resource allocation across mental healthcare service providers by supporting clinicians in matching patients to the treatment modality that best aligns with not only their symptom profile but their SRL capacity. In turn, this allows the more intensive measures (e.g., in-person therapy) to be prioritized for individuals with little to no SRL abilities.</p><p>Concurrently if the proposed model is accurate in suggesting that (a) SRL is indeed a key ingredient for DHI engagement, and (b) the significance of each driver changes across the user journey, it has the potential to transform and shape how future DHIs are designed. This may involve designing DHIs in such a way to ensure that the self-guided content is structured to scaffold the user's learning of psychoeducational information or scheduling regular activities within the DHI program that encourage users to engage in SRL behaviors, such as self-reflection. For smartphone app interventions, this may involve using pushed notifications that prompt users to complete weekly self-reflection tasks in relation to their progress with learning and applying the treatment content. DHI developers may consider embedding brief assessments (e.g., quizzes) throughout the user journey to evaluate whether users understand and implement the treatment content correctly, and if not, provide touchpoints with experts or clinicians to correct mislearnings.</p></sec><sec id="s8"><label>8</label><title>Recommendations for future directions</title><p>In light of these potential implications, we have derived five actionable recommendations for future efforts in the field. The first two recommendations focus on addressing current knowledge gaps, while the third is centered around improving DHI outcomes in practice. Finally, the fourth and fifth recommendations outline potential steps for enhancing future DHI design.
<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>(i)</label><p>First, more empirical evidence is needed to show that SRL is related to engagement in DHIs. A useful starting point would be expanding the range of predictors that we currently measure to include the full range of key drivers in SRL. As detailed in Theme 1, several SRL drivers have already been considered in the digital health literature, however, there are still a number of other potentially relevant drivers (e.g., metacognition, self-control, positive emotions, task interests, and task value) that have been insufficiently acknowledged or directly tested in this context. Determining the predictive power of these drivers on user engagement may also necessitate the creation or modification of SRL measures for digital health research.</p></list-item><list-item><label>(ii)</label><p>Second, the digital health field should acknowledge the temporal nature of these drivers and its relation to user engagement, by increasing the granularity of measurements in future studies. Rather than limiting to baseline assessments, researchers should consider adding more time points of data collection throughout the user journey to better understand how and which drivers fluctuate over time, and how these changes may influence people's engagement. Given that users can often start with an inflated attitude during initial uptake, we anticipate that those temporal trends closer to the time of drop-out are more accurate predictors of user engagement than measurements captured at baseline.</p></list-item><list-item><label>(iii)</label><p>Third, professional development opportunities for health professionals are needed to ensure they are competent in supporting individuals opting for digital health options. Digital health experts should consider developing a focused, single-session training program for clinicians to improve understanding of the self-regulated learning processes required for successful DHI completion. Such a program could include guidance on identifying and addressing barriers to SRL, strategies for facilitating sustained engagement, and techniques for supporting their clients' learning of psychoeducational content and new skills throughout the user journey, ultimately maximizing treatment outcomes.</p></list-item><list-item><label>(iv)</label><p>Fourth, efforts are needed to comprehensively review and map out the current evidence base for brief interventions that can quickly and effectively bolster people's engagement with learning tasks. Where gaps exist in the literature, researchers should prioritize the development of new resources or modules that can enhance specific drivers or SRL skills (e.g., goal setting). Embedding the appropriate evidence-based resources within DHIs may be the key to supporting users in enacting important skills that help them stay engaged throughout the user journey and improve overall treatment adherence.</p></list-item><list-item><label>(v)</label><p>Finally, to confirm if SRL-specific design features (e.g., self-monitoring tools) are important for enhancing outcomes with DHIs, researchers should consider comparing a range of available DHIs that include these features, vs. those that do not, and evaluate them to see if there are differences in engagement metrics, symptom improvement and treatment outcomes.</p></list-item></list></p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s9"><label>9</label><title>Conclusion</title><p>This paper was the first to evaluate the potential relevance of SRL theory to the digital health context. From the five SRL models included in this review, three key themes were identified and applied to extend our understanding of engagement with DHIs, given their underlying emphasis on knowledge acquisition and psychoeducation. The three themes discussed were (a) how SRL models can provide a complementary lens for exploring drivers of engagement, (b) that engagement and its drivers temporally fluctuate, and (c) the need to consider individual differences for learning capacity in those who sign up to DHIs. As such, we make the case that reconceptualizing the digital health user as a <italic>learner</italic> can invite new theoretical perspectives for improving predictive and conceptual models of engagement throughout the user journey. This may inform the development and implementation of retention strategies that can better support people to engage with and complete their DHIs as recommended. Additionally, by accounting for differences in user SRL abilities, these insights can help match individuals seeking mental health support with the most appropriate treatment modality (e.g., self-guided, blended, or in-person therapy). Ultimately, this may enable more efficient resource allocation within the healthcare system and enhance treatment outcomes on a broader scale.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>I would like to thank Professor Matthew Fuller-Tyszkiewicz for his immense effort and support on drafting this manuscript.</p></ack><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="s10"><title>Author contributions</title><p>CL: Conceptualization, Formal analysis, Investigation, Methodology, Writing &#x02013; original draft, Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing. MM: Conceptualization, Investigation, Methodology, Supervision, Writing &#x02013; original draft, Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing. JL: Conceptualization, Investigation, Methodology, Supervision, Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing. MF-T: Conceptualization, Investigation, Methodology, Supervision, Writing &#x02013; original draft, Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s12"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s14"><title>Publisher's note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Linardon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuller-Tyszkiewicz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Attrition and adherence in smartphone-delivered interventions for mental health problems: a systematic and meta-analytic review</article-title>. <source>J Consult Clin Psychol</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>88</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>13</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/ccp0000459</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31697093</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Number of Smartphone Subscriptions Worldwide from 2016 to 2021, with Forecasts from 2022 to 2027: Statistica (2022)</article-title>. <comment>Available online at:</comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.statista.com/statistics/330695/number-of-smartphone-users-worldwide/#:~:text=How%20many%20people%20smartphone%20subscriptions,highest%20number%20of%20smartphone%20users" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.statista.com/statistics/330695/number-of-smartphone-users-worldwide/#:&#x0223c;:text=How%20many%20people%20smartphone%20subscriptions,highest%20number%20of%20smartphone%20users</ext-link>
<comment>(accessed February 2023)</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kazdin</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Annual research review: expanding mental health services through novel models of intervention delivery</article-title>. <source>J Child Psychol Psychiatry</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>60</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>455</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>72</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jcpp.12937</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29900543</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beatty</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Binnion</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A systematic review of predictors of, and reasons for, adherence to online psychological interventions</article-title>. <source>Int J Behav Med</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>23</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>776</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>94</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12529-016-9556-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26957109</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Localytics</collab>. <article-title>25% of Users Abandon Apps After One Use UplandSoftware: Localytics (2019)</article-title>. <comment>Available online at:</comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://uplandsoftware.com/localytics/resources/blog/25-of-users-abandon-apps-after-one-use/" ext-link-type="uri">https://uplandsoftware.com/localytics/resources/blog/25-of-users-abandon-apps-after-one-use/</ext-link>
<comment>(accessed January 2023)</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Villagonzalo</surname><given-names>K-A</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Farhall</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Foley</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kyrios</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Predicting engagement with an online psychosocial intervention for psychosis: exploring individual- and intervention-level predictors</article-title>. <source>Internet Interv</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>100266</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.invent.2019.100266</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31890619</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eysenbach</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The law of attrition</article-title>. <source>J Med Internet Res</source>. (<year>2005</year>) <volume>7</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>e11</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/jmir.7.1.e11</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15829473</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Mansourvar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sorts&#x000f8;</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Predicting dropouts from an electronic health platform for lifestyle interventions: analysis of methods and predictors</article-title>. <source>J Med Internet Res</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>21</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>e13617</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/13617</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31486409</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>DZ</given-names></name><name><surname>McGillivray</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Torok</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of engagement with digital interventions on mental health outcomes: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Front Digit Health</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>764079</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fdgth.2021.764079</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34806079</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karyotaki</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Riper</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Twisk</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoogendoorn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kleiboer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mira</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Efficacy of self-guided internet-based cognitive behavioral therapy in the treatment of depressive symptoms: a meta-analysis of individual participant data</article-title>. <source>JAMA Psychiatry</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>74</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>351</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamapsychiatry.2017.0044</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28241179</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perski</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Blandford</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>West</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Michie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Conceptualising engagement with digital behaviour change interventions: a systematic review using principles from critical interpretive synthesis</article-title>. <source>Transl Behav Med</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>7</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>254</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>67</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13142-016-0453-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27966189</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neve</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Dropout, nonusage attrition, and pretreatment predictors of nonusage attrition in a commercial web-based weight loss program</article-title>. <source>J Med Internet Res</source>. (<year>2010</year>) <volume>12</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>e1640</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/jmir.1640</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Couper</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Maddy</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Nowak</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>McClure</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Engagement and retention: measuring breadth and depth of participant use of an online intervention</article-title>. <source>J Med Internet Res</source>. (<year>2010</year>) <volume>12</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>e1430</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/jmir.1430</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bossen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Buskermolen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Veenhof</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>de Bakker</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Dekker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Adherence to a web-based physical activity intervention for patients with knee and/or hip osteoarthritis: a mixed method study</article-title>. <source>J Med Internet Res</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>15</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>e223</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/jmir.2742</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24132044</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Al-Asadi</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Pretreatment attrition and formal withdrawal during treatment and their predictors: an exploratory study of the anxiety online data</article-title>. <source>J Med Internet Res</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <volume>16</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>e152</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/jmir.2989</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24938311</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Farrer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Adherence in internet interventions for anxiety and depression: systematic review</article-title>. <source>J Med Internet Res</source>. (<year>2009</year>) <volume>11</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>e1194</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/jmir.1194</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meischke</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lozano</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Garrison</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Christakis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Engagement in &#x0201c;my child&#x02019;s asthma&#x0201d;, an interactive web-based pediatric asthma management intervention</article-title>. <source>Int J Med Inform</source>. (<year>2011</year>) <volume>80</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>765</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>74</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijmedinf.2011.08.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21958551</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Borghouts</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Eikey</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Mark</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>De Leon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Schueller</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Barriers to and facilitators of user engagement with digital mental health interventions: systematic review</article-title>. <source>J Med Internet Res</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>23</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>e24387</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/24387</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33759801</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Linardon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Messer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shatte</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenwood</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosato</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rathgen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Does the method of content delivery matter? randomized controlled comparison of an internet-based intervention for eating disorder symptoms with and without interactive functionality</article-title>. <source>Behav Ther</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>53</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>508</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.beth.2021.12.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35473653</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Glasgow</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Christiansen</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Woolley</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Faber</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Engagement in a diabetes self-management website: usage patterns and generalizability of program use</article-title>. <source>J Med Internet Res</source>. (<year>2011</year>) <volume>13</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>e9</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/jmir.1391</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21371992</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alkhaldi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Webster</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Michie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The effectiveness of prompts to promote engagement with digital interventions: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>J Med Internet Res</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>18</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>e6</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/jmir.4790</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26747176</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Linardon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Shatte</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosato</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuller-Tyszkiewicz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Efficacy of a transdiagnostic cognitive-behavioral intervention for eating disorder psychopathology delivered through a smartphone app: a randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Psychol Med</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>52</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1679</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>90</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0033291720003426</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32972467</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garnett</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Perski</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Tombor</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>West</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Michie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Predictors of engagement, response to follow up, and extent of alcohol reduction in users of a smartphone app (drink less): secondary analysis of a factorial randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>JMIR Mhealth Uhealth</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>6</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>e11175</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/11175</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30552081</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edney</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Olds</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Monroe</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fraysse</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Vandelanotte</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>User engagement and attrition in an app-based physical activity intervention: secondary analysis of a randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>J Med Internet Res</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>21</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>e14645</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/14645</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31774402</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>W-Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Machine learning analysis to identify digital behavioral phenotypes for engagement and health outcome efficacy of an mHealth intervention for obesity: randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>J Med Internet Res</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>23</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>e27218</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/27218</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34184991</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Szinay</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chadborn</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Naughton</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Influences on the uptake of and engagement with health and well-being smartphone apps: systematic review</article-title>. <source>J Med Internet Res</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>22</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>e17572</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/17572</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32348255</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bricker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Miao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Mull</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Santiago-Torres</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vock</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Can a single variable predict early dropout from digital health interventions? Comparison of predictive models from two large randomized trials</article-title>. <source>J Med Internet Res</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>25</volume>:<fpage>e43629</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/43629</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36662550</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weston</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Yardley</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Kleek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Weal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Measurements of Engagement in mobile Behavioural Interventions?</source> Digital Health 2015 conference in <publisher-loc>Florence</publisher-loc>, <publisher-loc>Italy</publisher-loc> (<year>2015</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baumel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kane</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Examining predictors of real-world user engagement with self-guided eHealth interventions: analysis of mobile apps and websites using a novel dataset</article-title>. <source>J Med Internet Res</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>20</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>e11491</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/11491</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30552077</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Linardon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuller-Tyszkiewicz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Exploration of the individual and combined effects of predictors of engagement, dropout, and change from digital interventions for recurrent binge eating</article-title>. <source>Int J Eat Disord</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>57</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1202</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/eat.24175</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38410869</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ritterband</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Thorndike</surname><given-names>FP</given-names></name><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kovatchev</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonder-Frederick</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A behavior change model for internet interventions</article-title>. <source>Ann Behav Med</source>. (<year>2009</year>) <volume>38</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>18</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>27</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12160-009-9133-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19802647</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Short</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Rebar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Plotnikoff</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Vandelanotte</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Designing engaging online behaviour change interventions: a proposed model of user engagement</article-title>. <source>Eur Health Psychol</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>17</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>32</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Toms</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>What is user engagement? A conceptual framework for defining user engagement with technology</article-title>. <source>J Am Soc Inf Sci</source>. (<year>2008</year>) <volume>59</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>938</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>55</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/asi.20801</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zimmerman</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schunk</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Handbook of Self-Regulation of Learning and Performance</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge/Taylor &#x00026; Francis Group</publisher-name> (<year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zimmerman</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schunk</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Motivation: An Essential Dimension of Self-regulated learning. Motivation and Self-Regulated Learning</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name> (<year>2012</year>). p. <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>30</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weisel</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Zarski</surname><given-names>A-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Krieger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaub</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Moser</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Efficacy and cost-effectiveness of guided and unguided internet- and mobile-based indicated transdiagnostic prevention of depression and anxiety (ICare Prevent): a three-armed randomized controlled trial in four European countries</article-title>. <source>Internet Interv</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>52</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>64</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.invent.2018.04.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30775265</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fairburn</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The impact of digital technology on psychological treatments and their dissemination</article-title>. <source>Behav Res Ther</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>88</volume>:<fpage>19</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>25</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.brat.2016.08.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28110672</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Linardon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Broadbent</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Shatte</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuller-Tyszkiewicz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The role of pre-existing knowledge and knowledge acquisition in internet-based cognitive-behavioural therapy for eating disorders</article-title>. <source>Comput Human Behav</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>134</volume>:<fpage>107332</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chb.2022.107332</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Borrelli</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The assessment, monitoring, and enhancement of treatment fidelity in public health clinical trials</article-title>. <source>J Public Health Dent</source>. (<year>2011</year>) <volume>71</volume>(<issue>s1</issue>):<fpage>S52</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>63</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1752-7325.2011.00233.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rozental</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Liljeth&#x000f6;rn</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Radvogin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Topooco</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>The role of knowledge in internet-based cognitive behavioural therapy for adolescent depression: results from a randomised controlled study</article-title>. <source>Internet Interv</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>10</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.invent.2018.10.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30519531</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Malmquist</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rozental</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Topooco</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Knowledge gain and usage of knowledge learned during internet-based CBT treatment for adolescent depression-a qualitative study</article-title>. <source>BMC Psychiatry</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>20</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12888-020-02833-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31898506</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yeager</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Benight</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>If we build it, will they come? Issues of engagement with digital health interventions for trauma recovery</article-title>. <source>mHealth</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>37</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21037/mhealth.2018.08.04</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30363749</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Piotrowska</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Tully</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenroot</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimonis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Moul</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Mothers, fathers, and parental systems: a conceptual model of parental engagement in programmes for child mental health&#x02014;connect, attend, participate, enact (CAPE)</article-title>. <source>Clin Child Fam Psychol Rev</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>146</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>61</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10567-016-0219-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27914017</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Calear</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Batterham</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohan</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Farmer</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Farrer</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Skill enactment and knowledge acquisition in digital cognitive behavioral therapy for depression and anxiety: systematic review of randomized controlled trials</article-title>. <source>J Med Internet Res</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>25</volume>:<fpage>e44673</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/44673</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37256673</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zimmerman</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Becoming a self-regulated learner: an overview</article-title>. <source>Theory Pract</source>. (<year>2002</year>) <volume>41</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>64</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>70</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1207/s15430421tip4102_2</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pintrich</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A conceptual framework for assessing motivation and self-regulated learning in college students</article-title>. <source>Educ Psychol Rev</source>. (<year>2004</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>385</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>407</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10648-004-0006-x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Broadbent</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuller-Tyszkiewicz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Profiles in self-regulated learning and their correlates for online and blended learning students</article-title>. <source>Educ Technol Res Dev</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>66</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1435</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>55</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11423-018-9595-9</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwam</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Individual differences in self-regulated learning of college students enrolled in online college courses</article-title>. <source>Am J Distance Educ</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>35</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>133</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>51</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/08923647.2020.1829255</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barnard-Brak</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Paton</surname><given-names>VO</given-names></name><name><surname>Lan</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Profiles in self-regulated learning in the online learning environment</article-title>. <source>Int Rev Res Open Distance Learn</source>. (<year>2010</year>) <volume>11</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>61</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>80</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.19173/irrodl.v11i1.769</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Baars</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Der Zee</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Houben</surname><given-names>G-J</given-names></name><name><surname>Paas</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Supporting self-regulated learning in online learning environments and MOOCs: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Int J Hum Comput Stud</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>35</volume>(<issue>4-5</issue>):<fpage>356</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>73</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10447318.2018.1543084</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cibrian</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name><name><surname>Monteiro</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhattacharya</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Beltran</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Unpacking the lived experiences of smartwatch mediated self and co-regulation with ADHD children</article-title>. <conf-name>Proceedings of the 2023 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems</conf-name> (<year>2023</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jerath</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Syam</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The future of stress management: integration of smartwatches and HRV technology</article-title>. <source>Sensors (Basel)</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>23</volume>(<issue>17</issue>):<fpage>7314</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/s23177314</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37687769</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Islam</surname><given-names>SMS</given-names></name><name><surname>Halooq</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dening</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Uddin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Laranjo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Healthcare providers&#x02019; perspectives on using smart home systems to improve self-management and care in people with heart failure: a qualitative study</article-title>. <source>Int J Med Inform</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>167</volume>:<fpage>104837</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijmedinf.2022.104837</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36126353</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Islam</surname><given-names>SMS</given-names></name><name><surname>Nourse</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Uddin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rawstorn</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Maddison</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Consensus on recommended functions of a smart home system to improve self-management behaviors in people with heart failure: a modified Delphi approach</article-title>. <source>Front Cardiovasc Med</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>896249</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fcvm.2022.896249</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35845075</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iyngkaran</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Toukhsati</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Connors</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kangaharan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ilton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Self managing heart failure in remote Australia-translating concepts into clinical practice</article-title>. <source>Curr Cardiol Rev</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>12</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>270</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>84</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/1573403(12666160703183001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27397492</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zimmerman</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Moylan</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Self-regulation: where metacognition and motivation intersect</article-title>. In: Hacker DJ, Dunlosky J, Graesser AC, editors. <source>Handbook of Metacognition in Education</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name> (<year>2009</year>). p. <fpage>311</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>28</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Panadero</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Alonso-Tapia</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>How do students self-regulate? Review of Zimmerman&#x02019;s cyclical model of self-regulated learning</article-title>. <source>An de Psicol</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <volume>30</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>450</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>62</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.6018/analesps.30.2.167221</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bandura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Social Foundations of Thought and Action: A Social Cognitive Theory</source>. <publisher-loc>Englewood Cliffs</publisher-loc>, <publisher-loc>NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name> (<year>1986</year>). p. <fpage>23</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <comment>doi: 10.1017/S0813483900008238</comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cleary</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimmerman</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A cyclical self-regulatory account of student engagement: theoretical foundations and applications</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Christenson</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Reschly</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wylie</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>, editors. <source>Handbook of Research on Student Engagement</source>. <publisher-loc>Boston</publisher-loc>, <publisher-loc>MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer US</publisher-name> (<year>2012</year>). p. <fpage>237</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>57</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Panadero</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A review of self-regulated learning: six models and four directions for research</article-title>. <source>Front Psychol</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>422</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2017.00422</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28503157</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><label>61.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pintrich</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The role of goal orientation in self-regulated learning</article-title>. In: Boekaerts M, Pintrich PR, Zeidner M, editors. <source>Handbook of Self-Regulation</source>. <publisher-loc>Burlington, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name> (<year>2000</year>). p. <fpage>451</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>502</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B62"><label>62.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schunk</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Self-regulated learning: the educational legacy of Paul R. Pintrich</article-title>. <source>Educ Psychol</source>. (<year>2005</year>) <volume>40</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>85</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>94</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1207/s15326985ep4002_3</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B63"><label>63.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Puustinen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pulkkinen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Models of self-regulated learning: a review</article-title>. <source>Scand J Educ Res</source>. (<year>2001</year>) <volume>45</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>269</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>86</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00313830120074206</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B64"><label>64.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boekaerts</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Emotions, emotion regulation, and self-regulation of learning</article-title>. In: Zimmerman BJ, Schunk DH, editors. <source>Handbook of Self-regulation of Learning and Performance. Center for the Study of Learning and Instruction, Leiden University</source>. <publisher-loc>The Netherlands, and KU Leuven</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name> (<year>2011</year>). p. <fpage>422</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>39</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B65"><label>65.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boekaerts</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cascallar</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>How far have we moved toward the integration of theory and practice in self-regulation?</article-title>
<source>Educ Psychol Rev</source>. (<year>2006</year>) <volume>18</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>199</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>210</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10648-006-9013-4</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B66"><label>66.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boekaerts</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pekrun</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Emotions and emotion regulation in academic settings</article-title>. In: Corno L, Anderman EM, editors. <source>Handbook of Educational Psychology. 3rd Edition ed</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name> (<year>2016</year>). p. <fpage>76</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>90</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B67"><label>67.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Azevedo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A theoretical review of Winne and Hadwin&#x02019;s model of self-regulated learning: new perspectives and directions</article-title>. <source>Rev Educ Res</source>. (<year>2007</year>) <volume>77</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>334</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>72</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3102/003465430303953</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B68"><label>68.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Winne</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hadwin</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Studying as self-regulated engagement in learning</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Hacker</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunlosky</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Graesser</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>, editors. <comment>(Hillsdale, NJ: Erlbaum). The Educational Psychology Series</comment>. <source>Metacognition in Educational Theory and Practice</source>. <publisher-loc>Mahwah, NJ, US</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum Associates Publishers</publisher-name> (<year>1998</year>). p. <fpage>277</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>304</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B69"><label>69.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Winne</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cognition and metacognition within self-regulated learning</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Schunk</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>, editors. <source>The Handbook of Self-Regulation of Learning and Practice</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name> (<year>2018</year>). p. <fpage>36</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>48</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B70"><label>70.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Winne</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Self-regulated learning viewed from models of information processing</article-title>. In: Zimmerman BJ, Schunk DH, editors. <source>Self-Regulated Learning and Academic Achievement: Theoretical Perspectives, 2nd ed</source>. <publisher-loc>Mahwah, NJ, US</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum Associates Publishers</publisher-name> (<year>2001</year>). p. <fpage>153</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>89</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B71"><label>71.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Efklides</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Motivation and affect in self-regulated learning: does metacognition play a role?</article-title> In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Schunck</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>, editors. <source>Handbook of Self-Regulation of Learning and Performance. 2nd Edition</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name> (<year>2018</year>). p. <fpage>64</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>82</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B72"><label>72.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Efklides</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Interactions of metacognition with motivation and affect in self-regulated learning: the MASRL model</article-title>. <source>Educ Psychol</source>. (<year>2011</year>) <volume>46</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>6</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>25</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00461520.2011.538645</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B73"><label>73.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Linardon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Messer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shatte</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Skvarc</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosato</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rathgen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Targeting dietary restraint to reduce binge eating: a randomised controlled trial of a blended internet- and smartphone app-based intervention</article-title>. <source>Psychol Med</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>53</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0033291721002786</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36762975</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B74"><label>74.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hagger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The multiple pathways by which self-control predicts behavior</article-title>. <source>Front Psychol</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>849</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2013.00849</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24302914</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B75"><label>75.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baumeister</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Vohs</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Tice</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The strength model of self-control</article-title>. <source>Curr Dir Psychol Sci</source>. (<year>2007</year>) <volume>16</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>351</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1467-8721.2007.00534.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B76"><label>76.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Postel</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>de Haan</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ter Huurne</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Palen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>de Jong</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Attrition in web-based treatment for problem drinkers</article-title>. <source>J Med Internet Res</source>. (<year>2011</year>) <volume>13</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>e1811</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/jmir.1811</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B77"><label>77.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Farrer</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Mackinnon</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Batterham</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Predictors of adherence and outcome in internet-based cognitive behavior therapy delivered in a telephone counseling setting</article-title>. <source>Cognit Ther Res</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <volume>38</volume>:<fpage>358</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>67</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10608-013-9589-1</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B78"><label>78.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zimmerman</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Motivational sources and outcomes of self-regulated learning and performance: graduate center of city university of New York</article-title>. In: Zimmerman BJ, Schunk DH, editors. <source>Handbook of Self-Regulation of Learning and Performance</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name> (<year>2011</year>). p. <fpage>63</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>78</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B79"><label>79.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wolters</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A self-regulated learning perspective on student engagement</article-title>. In: Reschly AL, Christenson SL, editors. <source>Handbook of Research on Student Engagement</source>. <publisher-loc>Cham</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer Nature</publisher-name> (<year>2012</year>). p. <fpage>635</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>51</lpage>. <comment>doi: 10.1007/978-1-4614-2018-7_30</comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B80"><label>80.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakagami</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Brekke</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The prospective relationships among intrinsic motivation, neurocognition, and psychosocial functioning in schizophrenia</article-title>. <source>Schizophr Bull</source>. (<year>2010</year>) <volume>36</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>935</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>48</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/schbul/sbq043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20462998</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B81"><label>81.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hopkins</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Spears</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoover</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Cambron</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Potter</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Trajectories of motivation and self-efficacy during a smoking quit attempt: an ecological momentary assessment study</article-title>. <source>Psychol Addict Behav</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>36</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>78</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/adb0000734</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34435832</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B82"><label>82.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morgenstern</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuerbis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Houser</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Muench</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Treloar</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Within-person associations between daily motivation and self-efficacy and drinking among problem drinkers in treatment</article-title>. <source>Psychol Addict Behav</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>30</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>630</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/adb0000204</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27560995</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B83"><label>83.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Algars</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramberg</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Moszny</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hagman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rintala</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Santtila</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Readiness and motivation for change among young women with broadly defined eating disorders</article-title>. <source>Eat Disord</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>23</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>242</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>52</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10640266.2014.1000100</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25658434</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B84"><label>84.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cahill</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Adinoff</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hosig</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Pulliam</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Motivation for treatment preceding and following a substance abuse program</article-title>. <source>Addict Behav</source>. (<year>2003</year>) <volume>28</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>67</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>79</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0306-4603(01)00217-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12507528</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B85"><label>85.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>G&#x000fc;nther</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Yau</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Elison-Davies</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>On the difficulty of predicting engagement with digital health for substance use</article-title>. In: H&#x000e4;gglund M, Blusi M, Bonacina S, Nilsson L, Madsen IC, Pelayo S, et al., editors. <source>Caring is Sharing&#x02013;Exploiting the Value in Data for Health and Innovation</source>. <publisher-name>IOS Press</publisher-name> (<year>2023</year>). p. <fpage>967</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>71</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B86"><label>86.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wiebe</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharek</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>ELearning</article-title>. In: O'Brien H, Cairns P, editors. <source>Why Engagement Matters: Cross-disciplinary perspectives of User Engagement in Digital media</source>. <publisher-loc>Cham</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer International Publishing</publisher-name> (<year>2016</year>). p. <fpage>53</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>79</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B87"><label>87.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O&#x02019;Brien</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Theoretical perspectives on user engagement</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Cairns</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>, editors. <source>Why Engagement Matters: Cross-Disciplinary Perspectives of User Engagement in Digital Media</source>. <publisher-loc>Cham</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer International Publishing</publisher-name> (<year>2016</year>). p. <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>26</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>