<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="issn">2168-8184</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cureus</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2168-8184</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cureus</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Palo Alto (CA)</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11681966</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7759/cureus.74670</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Cardiology</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Allergy/Immunology</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Hematology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Expression of Monocytes Subsets in Patients Diagnosed With Coronary Artery Atherosclerosis and Their Impact on Disease Severity</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Muacevic</surname><given-names>Alexander</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>John R</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Kamel</surname><given-names>Asmaa Khalf</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Farag</surname><given-names>Naglaa M</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Allam</surname><given-names>Emad</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Khaled</surname><given-names>Mohamed</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ismail</surname><given-names>Doaa Elzaeem</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff-1">
<label>1</label>
Department of Clinical Pathology, Minia University Faculty of Medicine, Minia, EGY </aff><aff id="aff-2">
<label>2</label>
Department of Cardiology, Minia University Faculty of Medicine, Minia, EGY </aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">
Asmaa Khalf Kamel <email>asmaa.ezzeldeen@yahoo.com</email>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>28</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic"><month>11</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><issue>11</issue><elocation-id>e74670</elocation-id><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2024, Kamel et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Kamel et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License CC-BY 4.0., which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="https://www.cureus.com/articles/308212-expression-of-monocytes-subsets-in-patients-diagnosed-with-coronary-artery-atherosclerosis-and-their-impact-on-disease-severity">This article is available from https://www.cureus.com/articles/308212-expression-of-monocytes-subsets-in-patients-diagnosed-with-coronary-artery-atherosclerosis-and-their-impact-on-disease-severity</self-uri><abstract><p>Introduction</p><p>Many studies have supported inflammation as a mediator of lipoprotein (a) (Lp(a)) induced increase in cardiovascular disease risk, as it has pro-inflammatory effects on endothelial cells and monocytes.</p><p>Aim</p><p>This study aims to correlate Lp(a) level with different monocyte subsets in coronary atherosclerotic patients with different severity.</p><p>Method</p><p>The study included 60 patients with a mean age of 53.1 &#x000b1; 10.5 diagnosed as coronary atherosclerotic patients by coronary angiography. Lp levels were measured using enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA), while blood counts and monocyte subsets were analyzed by flow cytometry, and 30 apparently healthy individuals were included as the control group.</p><p>Results</p><p>Patients showed significantly higher median monocytic %, Lp(a), and higher C-reactive protein (CRP) values than the control group. Patients were subdivided into two groups: normal Lp(a) &#x0003c; 6.2 mg/dL (n = 24) and hyperlipoproteinemia(a) (hyper Lp(a)) &#x02265; 6.2 mg/dL (n = 36). Patients with hyper Lp(a) had higher non-classical monocytes (31.5% vs. 20%). Coronary atherosclerosis severity was associated with higher Lp(a) levels as well as non-classical monocytes; patients with mild atherosclerosis showed the highest classical and intermediate subset levels. While for a non-classical subset, patients with severe atherosclerosis showed the highest median level. A significant moderate positive correlation between Lp(a) and monocyte counts, as well as monocyte-lymphocyte (M/L) index and non-classical monocytes, was found.</p><p>Conclusions</p><p>Hyper Lp(a) and increased count of non-classical monocytes are significantly increased with disease progression (triple-vessel coronary disease risk). These results suggest that the expansion of non-classical monocytes is a cardiovascular disease (CVD) risk and predictor for disease severity. Strategies targeting inflammatory monocytes may slow CVD progression.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>atherosclerosis</kwd><kwd>cd16+ monocytes</kwd><kwd>flow cytometery</kwd><kwd>lipoprotein (a)</kwd><kwd>non classical monocytes</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>According to the World Health Organization, cardiovascular disease (CVD) is a leading cause of death globally, with a mortality of 17.9 million per year [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Clinical presentations range from asymptomatic to stable angina, acute coronary syndrome, heart failure, and sudden cardiac death [<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Monocytes play a crucial role in the local inflammatory response, plaque development, and thrombus formation [<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Few studies have been conducted in humans, making monocytes attractive therapeutic targets [<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Monocyte subsets (classical monocyte (CM), intermediate monocyte (IM), and non-classical monocyte (NCM)) differentially contribute to atherosclerosis pathogenesis. Patients with CVD have a higher percentage of IM and NCM than controls [<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].</p><p>Risk-factor modification to prevent or reverse atherosclerosis progression can provide benefits at all stages of atherosclerotic disease, even as secondary prevention. Preventive therapies, including lipid-lowering, are imperfect. Reprogramming macrophages to an anti-inflammatory phenotype can promote plaque stabilization and atherosclerotic cardiovascular disease (ASCVD) regression [<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Setting a cutoff can determine whether to stent the diseased segment or not and can also help determine which patients would benefit from intervention and medical therapy [<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>].</p><p>Lipoprotein (a) (Lp(a)) levels are controlled by production rather than catabolism. Each individual inherits and expresses two copies of Lp(a), one from each parent, unless homozygous for two Lp(a) genes [<xref rid="REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Hyperlipoproteinemia(a) (hyper Lp(a)) occurs in 20% of the population and is the most common genetic lipid disorder. It is higher in calcific aortic valve disease (CAVD) and chronic kidney disease (CKD) [<xref rid="REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Because of such high CVD risk, recent lipid guidelines stress evaluating Lp(a) to stratify CVD risk [<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Large genetic epidemiologic studies have renewed interest in Lp(a) by finding strong genetic evidence of the associations of high Lp(a) with increased risk of coronary heart disease (CHD), heart failure, and mortality [<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. CAD patient prognosis, especially in those with acute myocardial ischemia, has significantly improved due to advancements in technical coronary interventions, stents, and further technical evolution [<xref rid="REF11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>].</p><p>Some studies reported that genetic lowering of Lp(a) by 10 mg/dL is associated with a 5.8% lower risk of CHD [<xref rid="REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Recent studies have reported conflicting results regarding measuring monocyte subgroups as a marker for inflammatory activation and promotion of atherogenesis [<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. The aim of this study is to investigate the association between increased plasma Lp(a) level and monocyte subsets in patients with different coronary atherosclerosis severity.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><p>The study included 60 coronary artery atherosclerosis patients diagnosed by angiography and on treatment (group I), selected from the Cardiology Clinic, Faculty of Medicine, Minia University Hospital, Minia, Egypt, and 30 apparently healthy individuals (group II) with matched age and sex as a control group. Group I was subdivided into three subgroups according to disease severity and number of affected vessels in angiography: group Ia: mild cases, who have a single vessel affected; group Ib: moderate cases, having double vessels affected; and group Ic: severe cases, having multiple vessels affected.</p><p>Patients with the following conditions were excluded from the study: Lp(a) lowering therapy, acute coronary syndrome, congestive heart failure, acute inflammatory or infectious diseases in the last three months, connective tissue disease, severe thyroid dysfunction, CKD stage IV or V, and liver disease.</p><p>The study had local Research Ethics approval of Minia University, Faculty of Medicine, Institutional Review Board "MUFMIRB" (approval no. 133:11/2021), and written consent was obtained from patients or their legal guardians.</p><p>Both patients and control groups were subjected to the following: full history-taking, thorough clinical examination, and laboratory investigations. These investigations included a complete blood count (CBC), monocyte lymphocyte index, CD14 and CD16 assay by flow cytometry, C-reactive protein (CRP), liver and renal function, and lipid profile. The level of low-density lipoprotein cholesterol (LDL-C) was calculated using Friedewald&#x02019;s formula:</p><p>LDL-C (mg/dL) = TC (mg/dL) &#x02212; HDL-C (mg/dL) &#x02212; TG (mg/dL)/5.</p><p>Lp(a) assay by enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA), using monospecific polyclonal sheep antibodies against human Lp(a). The kit was supplied by Biokit for scientific research in China. The minimum detectable limit of Lp(a) is less than 0.09 ng/mL. This assay has high sensitivity, excellent specificity, and no significant cross-reactivity or interference between Lp(a) and its analogs.</p><p>Lymphocyte-monocyte index was calculated as the ratio of absolute lymphocyte count to absolute monocyte count. Direct immunofluorescence was used to assess monocyte immunophenotyping using fluorescently labeled antibodies to CD14 and CD16 antigens. The kit was supplied by Kemet Medical. Readings were obtained using flow cytometry (BD-FACSCanto II Flow Cytometer, Becton, Dickinson and Company, Franklin Lakes, NJ) following the manufacturer&#x02019;s manuals. Gating of monocytes was performed using forward scatter parameters, and monocyte subsets were identified as classical (CD14++CD16&#x02212;), intermediate (CD14++CD16+), and non-classical (CD14+CD16++) using flow cytometry.&#x000a0;BD FACSDiva (Data-Interpolating&#x000a0;Variational&#x000a0;Analysis, Paris, France) software&#x000a0;was used for data processing.</p><p>Results were expressed as percentages of cells positive for CD14 and CD16. A case was considered positive for CD14 or CD16 expression if the percentage exceeded the cutoff of 20%. The study obtained local research ethics approval from the Minia Medical College Ethics Committee, and written consent was obtained from each patient or their legal guardians.</p><p>Qualitative data were presented as frequencies and percentages. The chi-square test was used to compare qualitative variables. Quantitative data were explored for normality by checking the distribution of data and using tests of normality (Kolmogorov-Smirnov and Shapiro-Wilk tests). All data showed normal (parametric) distribution except for lipid profile, alanine aminotransferase (ALT), aspartate aminotransferase (AST), total leucocytic counts, monocytes %, monocytes count, monocyte-lymphocyte (M/L) index, Lp(a), and monocytes subset percentages data which showed non-normal (non-parametric) distribution. Parametric data were presented as mean and standard deviation (SD) values, while non-parametric data were presented as median and range values. For parametric data, the Student&#x02019;s t-test was used for comparisons between the two groups. One-way ANOVA followed by Bonferroni&#x02019;s post-hoc test was used for comparisons between more than two groups. For non-parametric data, the Mann-Whitney U test was used for comparisons between the two groups. Kruskal-Wallis test, followed by Dunn&#x02019;s test, was used for comparisons between more than two groups. Spearman&#x02019;s correlation coefficient was used to determine the significant correlation between Lp(a), monocyte counts, M/L index, and monocyte subsets. The receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curve was constructed to determine the cutoff value for Lp(a) to differentiate between atherosclerosis and normal subjects. ROC curve analysis was performed with MedCalc&#x000ae; Statistical Software version 19.5.1 (MedCalc Software Ltd, Ostend, Belgium;&#x000a0;<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.medcalc.org" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.medcalc.org</ext-link>; 2020). Binary logistic regression analysis was used to determine significant predictors of Lp(a) categories. Model fit was tested using the chi-square test and&#x000a0;pseudo-R<sup>2</sup>&#x000a0;tests, and the model was fit to describe the relations between the dependent and independent variables. The significance level was set at p &#x02264; 0.05. Statistical analysis was performed with IBM SPSS Statistics for Windows Version 23.0 (IBM Corp., Armonk, NY).</p></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p>Table <xref rid="TAB1" ref-type="table">1</xref> presents demographic and laboratory data. Patients showed significantly higher median monocytic percentage and Lp(a) (p = 0.045, &#x0003c;0.001, &#x0003c;0.001), as well as a higher prevalence of positive CRP than the control group (p = 0.026). No significant differences were observed between patients and controls regarding gender, age, and blood picture parameters.&#x000a0;</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Comparison between the studied groups regarding demographic and laboratory data</title><p>HB: hemoglobin, PLT: platelets, WBCs: white blood cells, M/L index:&#x000a0;monocyte-lymphocyte&#x000a0;index, Lp(a):&#x000a0;lipoprotein (a), CRP: C-reactive protein</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Data</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group I (n = 60)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group II (n = 30)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mild (n = 20)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate (n = 20)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severe (n = 20)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (year)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.1 &#x000b1; 10.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 &#x000b1; 10.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.087</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.2 &#x000b1; 8&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.2 &#x000b1; 10&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.9 &#x000b1; 12.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.236</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender (male, female)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (58.3), 25 (41.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (65.7), 13(43.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.880&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (55), 9 (45)&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (70), 6 (30)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (50), 10 (50)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.410&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB (g/dL)&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.23 &#x000b1; 1.75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.43 &#x000b1; 1.41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.588</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.34 &#x000b1; 1.78&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.57 &#x000b1; 1.77&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.8 &#x000b1; 1.71&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.363</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PLT (&#x000d7; 10<sup>3</sup>/&#x000b5;L)&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">255.1 &#x000b1; 85.2&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">282.4 &#x000b1; 75.3&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.141</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">240 &#x000b1; 74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">230.4 &#x000b1; 75.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">294.9 &#x000b1; 93.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.033*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">WBCs (&#x000d7; 10<sup>3</sup>/&#x000b5;L)&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.6 (4-18)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.95 (4-10.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.292</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.05 (4-10.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1 (4-18)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.2 (4.2-11.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.076</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Monocyte count (&#x000d7;10<sup>3</sup>/&#x000b5;L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">519 (192-1972)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">465 (168-780)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.336</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">450 (250-936)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">434 (192-1440)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">777 (212-1972)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Monocytes (%)&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (3-17)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (3-10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.045*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (5-17)&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (3-13)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.5 (4-17)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007*</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lymphocytes (%)&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.55 &#x000b1; 10.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.5 &#x000b1; 6.97</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.319</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.85 &#x000b1; 5.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.05 &#x000b1; 11.93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.75 &#x000b1; 11.91</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.811</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neutrophils (%)&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.95 &#x000b1; 11.86</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.87 &#x000b1; 8.91</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.437</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.65 &#x000b1; 7.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.6 &#x000b1; 12.93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.6 &#x000b1; 14.44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.307</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">M/L index&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26 (0.1-0.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22 (0.1-0.33)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.063</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25 (0.14-0.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22 (0.1-0.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3 (0.1-0.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.100</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Classical (%)&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47 (9-74)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.5 (70-88)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.5 (44-74)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 (38-71)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.5 (9-44)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001*</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intermediate (%)&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.8 (2-37)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (2-13)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (8-20)&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (7-26)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5 (2-37)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-classical (%)&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.9 (18.3-90)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (6-25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.5 (13-40)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.5 (15-52)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61 (19-87)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001*</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lp(a)&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.75 (1.3-18)&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.65 (2.1-7.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3 (1.3-13.5)&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.55 (3.9-17)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.85 (2.5-18)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.779&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRP positive (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.026*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03*</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Patients with atherosclerosis exhibited significantly higher median values for IM and NCM subsets compared to the control group (p &#x0003c; 0.001), while CM subsets showed a significant increase in the control group compared to the atherosclerotic group (Table <xref rid="TAB1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p><p>Association between different variables and severity of atherosclerosis</p><p>Platelet and monocyte (count and percentage) showed significant increases in the severe atherosclerotic subgroup compared to mild and moderate subgroups (p = 0.033, 0.008, 0.007, respectively). Other CBC parameters showed no significant difference among atherosclerotic subgroups. There were no significant differences between the three subgroups regarding gender distribution, age, Lp(a), and CRP (Table <xref rid="TAB1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p><p>With regard to monocyte subsets, there were significant differences between groups. Pair-wise comparisons between the groups revealed that patients with mild atherosclerosis showed the highest classical and intermediate subset levels (p &#x0003c; 0.001, 0.005, respectively). While for the non-classical subset, patients with severe atherosclerosis showed the highest median level (p &#x0003c; 0.001). We previously stated that CMs were more abundant in control subjects than in patients with coronary atherosclerosis. To clarify, we found that the CM subset was higher in controls when compared to all cases combined. However, when we examined cases based on disease severity (mild, moderate, and severe), we observed that the mild subgroup had a higher proportion of CMs compared to the moderate and severe subgroups. Meaning, triple&#x02010;vessel CAD was more common in patients having a lower percentage of classical CD14++CD16&#x02212; and intermediate CD14++CD16+ monocytes and a higher percentage of non&#x02010;classical CD14+CD16++ monocytes (Table <xref rid="TAB1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p><p>Correlation between Lp(a), monocyte counts,&#x000a0;M/L index, and monocyte subsets</p><p>There was a significant moderate positive correlation between Lp(a) with monocyte counts, M/L index, and NCMs (r = 0.424, 0.376, 0.336, p &#x0003c; 0.001, &#x0003c;0.001, 0.001, respectively) (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="FIG1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="FIG2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, and Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="FIG3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Scatter diagram representing positive correlation between monocyte counts and Lp(a)</title><p>Lp(a): lipoprotein (a)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0016-00000074670-i01" position="float"/></fig><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Scatter diagram representing positive correlation between M/L index and Lp(a)</title><p>Lp(a): lipoprotein (a); M/L: monocyte lymphocyte</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0016-00000074670-i02" position="float"/></fig><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Scatter diagram representing positive correlation between non-classical monocytes and Lp(a)</title><p>Lp(a): lipoprotein(a)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0016-00000074670-i03" position="float"/></fig><p>However, there was a significant moderate negative correlation with CMs (r =-0.346, p = 0.001) (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="FIG4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>).</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Scatter diagram representing negative correlation between classical monocytes and Lp(a)</title><p>Lp(a): lipoprotein (a)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0016-00000074670-i04" position="float"/></fig><p>Meanwhile, there was no significant correlation with IMs (r = 0.145, p = 0.174).</p><p>Association between different variables and Lp(a) values less or more than 6.2 mg/dL</p><p>Patients were divided into two subgroups based on Lp(a) concentrations (greater than or less than 6.2 mg/dL). Patients with Lp(a) levels exceeding 6.2 mg/dL showed a significantly higher prevalence of positive CRP (p = 0.003), monocytes %, monocytes count, and M/L index (p = 0.001, 0.0003, 0.009, respectively), and a significantly higher median NCM (p = 0.005) compared to patients with Lp(a) levels below 6.2 mg/dL. No statistically significant differences were observed between the two groups for age, gender, IM subsets, and other blood picture parameters. In patients with Lp(a) values more than 6.2 mg/dL, triple-vessel lesions occurred in 60% of patients, which means that Lp(a) &#x0003e; 6.2 mg/dL was associated with the presence of triple-vessel coronary artery disease (CAD) (Table <xref rid="TAB2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Comparison between subjects with Lp(a) values less or more than 6.2 mg/dL</title><p>HB: hemoglobin, PLT: platelets, WBCs: white blood cells, M/L index: monocyte-lymphocyte index, Lp(a): lipoprotein (a), CRP: C-reactive protein</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;6.2 mg/dL (n = 24)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;6.2 mg/dL (n = 36)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (year) &#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.5 &#x000b1; 12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.9 &#x000b1; 11.5 &#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.186 &#x000a0;</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender (male, female)&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35(64.8), 19(35.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (47.2), 19 (52.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.098</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB (g/dL) &#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.45 &#x000b1; 1.33 &#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.07 &#x000b1; 2.02 &#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.285 &#x000a0;</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">WBCs (&#x000d7; 10<sup>3</sup>/&#x000b5;L) &#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.25 (4-10.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.15 (4-18)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.104 &#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PLT (&#x000d7; 10<sup>3</sup>/&#x000b5;L) &#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">264 &#x000b1; 79.8 &#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">263.8 &#x000b1; 87.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.972</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Monocytes (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (3-16)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (3-17)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lymphocytes (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.48 &#x000b1; 10.13 &#x000a0; &#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.94 &#x000b1; 7.46 &#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.438</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neutrophils (%) &#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.43 &#x000b1; 12.2 &#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.83 &#x000b1; 8.93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.864</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">M/L index &#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22 (0.08-0.41)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26 (0.08-0.77)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRP positive (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.4 &#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003* &#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Classical (%) &#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.5 (9-88)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55 (20-85)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.010* &#x000a0;</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intermediate (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (2-37)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.5 (5-26)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.157</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-classical (%) &#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (6-87)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.5 (9-75)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005* &#x000a0;</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Diagnostic accuracy of Lp(a)</p><p>ROC curve analysis of Lp(a) in the diagnosis of atherosclerosis is presented in Figure <xref rid="FIG5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> and showed that the cutoff value of Lp(a) for differentiating between atherosclerosis and normal subjects was 6.2 mg/dL. At this cutoff value, the sensitivity, specificity, accuracy, PPV, and NPV were 53.3%, 93.3%, 66.6%, 94.1%, and 50% (area under the curve (AUC) 0.789, 95% CI 0.69, 0.868, respectively) (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="FIG5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>).</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curve of Lp(a) for diagnosis of atherosclerosis</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0016-00000074670-i05" position="float"/></fig><p>Binary logistic regression analysis</p><p>Significant Predictors of Lp(a) Categories (&#x0003c;6.2 or &#x02265; 6.2 mg/dL)</p><p>A binary logistic regression model was constructed using Lp(a) categories (&#x0003c;6.2 or &#x02265; 6.2 mg/dL) as the dependent variable. The independent variables were gender, age, monocyte subsets, and the number of affected vessels. Model fitting was tested by several methods. First, the significant -2 log-likelihood test (-2 log-likelihood = 103.4, p = 0.013). Second,&#x000a0;pseudo-R2&#x000a0;test results were as follows: Cox and Snell = 0.179, Nagelkerke = 0.242. The values of these tests indicate a good model fit. Results of the regression model showed that the presence of multiple affected vessels was the only significant predictor of Lp(a) categories. Subjects with multiple affected vessels are 0.159 folds less prone to have Lp(a) &#x02265; 6.2 mg/dL. In other words, subjects with multiple affected vessels are 6.3 folds more prone to have Lp(a) &#x0003c;6.2 mg/dL. (Please note that 6.3 is calculated as 1/0.159 = 6.3) (Table <xref rid="TAB3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Results of binary logistic regression analysis model for predictors of Lp(a) categories</title><p>Lp(a): lipoprotein (a)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Variable
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Regression coefficient (&#x003b2;)
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Standard error (SE)
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
p-value
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Odds ratio (OR)
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
95% CI
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Gender (reference category: female)
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
0.836
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
0.499
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
0.094
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
2.306
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
0.876-6.132
</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Age
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
-0.001
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
0.024
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
0.951
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
0.999
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
0.953-1.046
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Classical monocytes
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
0.093
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
0.458
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
0.840
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
1.097
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
0.447-2.694
</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Intermediate monocytes
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
0.079
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
0.457
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
0.863
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
1.082
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
0.442-2.648
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Non-classical monocytes
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
0.124
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
0.457
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
0.786
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
1.132
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
0.462-2.772
</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Affected vessels (reference category: single)
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
-
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
-
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
-
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
-
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
-
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Double
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
-0.598
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
0.670
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
0.372
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
0.550
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
0.148-2.042
</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Multiple
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
-1.840
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
0.673
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
0.006*
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
0.159
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
0.042-0.594
</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Lp(a)&#x02019;s physiological role and its high atherogenicity mechanisms are not clear. It is stated that Lp(a) containing immune complexes interact with macrophages, leading to vessel wall inflammation [<xref rid="REF11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Atherosclerosis is a complex disease characterized by lipid accumulation within the arterial wall and inflammation [<xref rid="REF12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Innate immune cells, especially monocytes and macrophages, play a vital role in their initiation and progression through their influx into the vessel wall. A high circulating monocyte number is a high-risk factor for cardiovascular events [<xref rid="REF13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="REF14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Furthermore, increased NCMs in patients with high Lp(a) levels have been associated with an elevated risk of multi-vessel disease [<xref rid="REF12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="REF15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. This study, for the first time, demonstrates the association between Lp(a) levels greater than or equal to 6.2 mg/dL and monocyte subsets.</p><p>In this study, similar to Xiang et al. and in contrast to Matei et al., gender and age were not significantly different from control [<xref rid="REF13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="REF16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Also, another study noted that males develop atherosclerotic plaques earlier, and plaques have a greater inflamed area [<xref rid="REF17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>].</p><p>Platelets have an important role in coronary thrombosis pathogenesis and atherogenesis. Similar to Matei et al., platelets had a significant difference between mild and severe atherosclerosis (p = 0.033) [<xref rid="REF16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Studies have shown that platelet activity is different among populations, which can explain CVD by several mechanisms [<xref rid="REF18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].</p><p>CRP is an early indicator of inflammatory conditions; it mediates tissue fibrosis in several CVDs [<xref rid="REF16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. In this study, a higher prevalence of positive CRP in the patient group than in the control group was found (p = 0.026). Also, there were significant differences among mild, moderate, and severe groups (p &#x0003c; 0.0001) [<xref rid="REF16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. This is similar to another study that found increased levels of CRP strongly predict thrombotic complications of atherosclerosis and are associated with CVD risk [<xref rid="REF19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="REF20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>].</p><p>Lp(a) showed significantly higher median levels than the control group (p &#x0003c; 0.001). However, there was no significant difference in Lp(a) levels regarding the severity of atherosclerosis. This may explain the association between Lp(a) and coronary artery atherosclerosis, the high residual risk of myocardial infarction [<xref rid="REF21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="REF22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. This supports the role of Lp(a) in improving risk assessment, which may be useful for primary prevention therapy decisions [<xref rid="REF23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="REF24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. On the contrary, another study found that coronary atherosclerosis severity was correlated with the Lp(a) level [<xref rid="REF25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>].&#x000a0;</p><p>In studies by Patel et al. and Idzkowska et al. [<xref rid="REF26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="REF27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], the median monocytic % in atherosclerosis patients was significantly higher than the control group (p = 0.045). Also, monocytic count is significantly higher in the severe atherosclerotic subgroup compared with mild and moderate subgroups (p = 0.008). This agrees with a study that observed that patients with low monocyte counts have lower survival rates [<xref rid="REF15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], and a high monocyte count was independently associated with a better prognosis</p><p>In agreement with Xiang et al., who found a significant increase in intermediate and NCM subsets [<xref rid="REF13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] in the patient group compared to the control group, a recent study showed that individuals with unstable angina had a higher number of circulating IMs. However, asymptomatic subjects and patients with smaller plaques had higher quantities of CMs [<xref rid="REF28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>], supporting the association between IMs and the occurrence of major cardiovascular events and increased mortality [<xref rid="REF26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. On the other hand, Xiang et al. [<xref rid="REF13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] found no significant correlations between monocytes subsets and CA severity.</p><p>The M/L index (r = 0.376, p &#x0003c; 0.001), a new marker of systemic inflammation, is associated with CVD prognosis and independently associated with increased CVD mortality in atherosclerotic cardiovascular patients [<xref rid="REF29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Additionally, another study suggested that monocyte count and MLR may be potential, cost-effective, and clinically available indicators of CVD risk [<xref rid="REF30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>].</p><p>Here, Lp(a) had a significant moderate positive correlation with monocyte count (r = 0.424, p &#x0003c; 0.001). Similarly, the increased monocyte count in CVD is related to lipid levels, primarily to low HDL-C, which promotes monocytosis [<xref rid="REF26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. A significant moderate positive correlation between Lp(a) and NCMs (r = 0.336, p = 0.001) was found, which is similar to a study that found that relative NCMs are associated with Lp(a) concentration (r = 0.18, p = 0.03). This supported the relationship between an increased Lp(a) level and multiple vessel atherosclerosis as Lp(a) causes endothelial dysfunction and damage through different mechanisms, one of them being increased non-classical CD14+CD16++ monocytes in patients with hyper Lp(a). This is due to their &#x0201c;innate&#x0201d; control of tissues to detect Lp(a)-damaged endothelium [<xref rid="REF31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="REF32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>].</p><p>NCMs have pro-inflammatory properties through high cytokine-level production when stimulated [<xref rid="REF33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. This high level is involved in T-cell stimulation and proliferation [<xref rid="REF34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="REF35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. The established association we found between NCM increase and triple-vessel disease in Lp(a) high cases indicated that the redistribution of monocytes from classical to &#x0201c;pro-inflammatory&#x0201d; subsets may be mediated by this atherogenic lipoprotein. Understanding monocytes&#x02019; regulation, differentiation, and functioning in the presence of Lp(a) disorders may define future therapeutic interventions aimed at activating or blocking immune system components.</p><p>Limitations of the study</p><p>Patients included in the study were admitted to a single center. Other patients from different centers should be included to confirm the results. The relation between the extent of peripheral atherosclerosis and the studied parameters was not assessed. Another limitation is that other monocytic markers, such as CD64, and markers of IMs like CCR2, CXCR1, and CCR5 should be assayed. These limitations should be considered while interpreting the results.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>The findings of this study revealed an association between Lp(a) concentration and the blood content of intermediate and NCMs, regardless of gender and age. The increased level of Lp(a) and the decreased quantity of CMs were associated with the severity of coronary atherosclerosis. The expansion of CD16+ monocytes (intermediate and non-classical) in the presence of hyper Lp(a) signi&#x0fb01;cantly increased the risk of triple-vessel coronary disease.</p><p>Lp(a) was found to have no significant difference regarding the disease severity, while monocytic count and differentiated subsets were significantly affected with the disease progression. Thus, an increase in the percentage of circulating intermediate and NCM subsets can be regarded as an appropriate prognostic marker in patients with coronary artery atherosclerosis, while Lp(a) may have no prognostic value.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group content-type="conflict"><title>Disclosures</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Human subjects:</bold> Consent for treatment and open access publication was obtained or waived by all participants in this study. Minia University, Faculty of Medicine, Institutional Review Board "MUFMIRB" issued approval 133:11/2021. You are kindly informed that this letter has been issued to officially notify you that our Minia University, Faculty of Medicine, Institutional Review Board "MUFMIRB," has reviewed and approved your submitted research documents.</p><p><bold>Animal subjects:</bold> All authors have confirmed that this study did not involve animal subjects or tissue.</p><p><bold>Conflicts of interest:</bold> In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following:</p><p><bold>Payment/services info:</bold> All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work.</p><p><bold>Financial relationships:</bold> All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work.</p><p><bold>Other relationships:</bold> All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="other"><title>Author Contributions</title><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Concept and design:</bold>&#x000a0; Asmaa Khalf Kamel, Naglaa M. Farag, Mohamed Khaled, Emad Allam</p><p><bold>Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data:</bold>&#x000a0; Asmaa Khalf Kamel, Doaa Elzaeem Ismail, Naglaa M. Farag, Mohamed Khaled, Emad Allam</p><p><bold>Drafting of the manuscript:</bold>&#x000a0; Asmaa Khalf Kamel, Doaa Elzaeem Ismail, Naglaa M. Farag, Emad Allam</p><p><bold>Critical review of the manuscript for important intellectual content:</bold>&#x000a0; Asmaa Khalf Kamel, Naglaa M. Farag, Mohamed Khaled, Emad Allam</p><p><bold>Supervision:</bold>&#x000a0; Asmaa Khalf Kamel, Naglaa M. Farag, Emad Allam</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="REF1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Periodic and intermittent fasting in diabetes and cardiovascular disease</article-title><source>Curr Diab Rep</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Crupi</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Haase</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brandhorst</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Longo</surname><given-names>VD</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>83</fpage><volume>20</volume><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33301104</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Inflammation in coronary microvascular dysfunction</article-title><source>Int J Mol Sci</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Sagris</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Theofilis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Antonopoulos</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>71</fpage><volume>22</volume><year>2021</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Lipoprotein(a) and inflammation - pathophysiological links and clinical implications for cardiovascular disease</article-title><source>J Clin Lipidol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Simantiris</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Antonopoulos</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Papastamos</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Benetos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Koumallos</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tsioufis</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tousoulis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><volume>17</volume><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36333256</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Macrophages in atherosclerosis regression</article-title><source>Arterioscler Thromb Vasc Biol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><volume>40</volume><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31722535</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>The association between monocyte subsets and cardiometabolic disorders/cardiovascular disease: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Front Cardiovasc Med</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Na</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>640124</fpage><volume>8</volume><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33681309</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Physiology-guided management of serial/diffuse coronary artery disease</article-title><source>Curr Cardiol Rep</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Siddiqui</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chowdhury</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nahar</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>25</fpage><volume>21</volume><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30847746</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Lipoprotein(a): knowns, unknowns and uncertainties</article-title><source>Pharmacol Res</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Ruscica</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sirtori</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Corsini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Watts</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sahebkar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>105812</fpage><volume>173</volume><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34450317</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Lipoprotein(a): an independent, genetic, and causal factor for cardiovascular disease and acute myocardial infarction</article-title><source>Indian Heart J</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Enas</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Varkey</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dharmarajan</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pare</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bahl</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>112</lpage><volume>71</volume><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31280836</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Lipoprotein(a) and cardiovascular disease</article-title><source>Clin Chem</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Kamstrup</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>154</fpage><lpage>166</lpage><volume>67</volume><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33236085</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Lipoprotein(a) and cardiovascular diseases - revisited</article-title><source>Circ J</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sohn</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Koh</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>867</fpage><lpage>874</lpage><volume>84</volume><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32336721</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>The importance of characteristics of angina symptoms for the prediction of coronary artery disease in a cohort of stable patients in the modern era</article-title><source>Hellenic J Cardiol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Nakas</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bechlioulis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>241</fpage><lpage>246</lpage><volume>60</volume><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29890282</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Inflammation and atherosclerosis: signaling pathways and therapeutic intervention</article-title><source>Signal Transduct Target Ther</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>XF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>131</fpage><volume>7</volume><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35459215</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Lower HDL-C levels are associated with higher expressions of CD16 on monocyte subsets in coronary atherosclerosis</article-title><source>Int J Med Sci</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>2171</fpage><lpage>2179</lpage><volume>17</volume><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32922178</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Nature versus number: monocytes in cardiovascular disease</article-title><source>Int J Mol Sci</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mack</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fletcher</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Medbury</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>9119</fpage><volume>22</volume><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34502027</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Monocytes may be favorable biomarker and predictor of long-term outcome in patients with chronic heart failure: a cohort study</article-title><source>Medicine (Baltimore)</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Charach</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rogowski</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Karniel</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Charach</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Grosskopf</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Novikov</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>0</fpage><volume>98</volume><year>2019</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Utility of routine laboratory tests in the assessment of chronic venous disease progression in female patients</article-title><source>Exp Ther Med</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Matei</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Matei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Anghel</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carabenciov</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Murariu</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Olariu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>571</fpage><volume>24</volume><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35978924</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Sex as a biological variable in atherosclerosis</article-title><source>Circ Res</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Man</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Beckman</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jaffe</surname><given-names>IZ</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>1297</fpage><lpage>1319</lpage><volume>126</volume><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32324497</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Platelet function in cardiovascular disease: activation of molecules and activation by molecules</article-title><source>Cardiovasc Toxicol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Khodadi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><volume>20</volume><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31784932</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Rare SCARB1 mutations associate with high-density lipoprotein cholesterol but not with coronary artery disease</article-title><source>Eur Heart J</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Helgadottir</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sulem</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thorgeirsson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>2172</fpage><lpage>2178</lpage><volume>39</volume><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29596577</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>C-reactive protein in atherothrombosis and angiogenesis</article-title><source>Front Immunol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Badimon</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pe&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Arderiu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Padr&#x000f3;</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Slevin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vilahur</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chiva-Blanch</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>430</fpage><volume>9</volume><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29552019</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>CRP levels are significantly associated with CRP genotype and estrogen use in The Lifestyle, Biomarker and Atherosclerosis (LBA) study</article-title><source>BMC Cardiovasc Disord</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Frans&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pettersson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hurtig-Wennl&#x000f6;f</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>170</fpage><volume>22</volume><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35428187</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Lipoprotein(a) and subclinical coronary atherosclerosis in asymptomatic individuals</article-title><source>Atherosclerosis</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jeon</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>190</fpage><lpage>195</lpage><volume>349</volume><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34607706</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Association of lipoprotein(a) with atherosclerotic plaque progression</article-title><source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Kaiser</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Daghem</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tzolos</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>223</fpage><lpage>233</lpage><volume>79</volume><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35057907</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Residual cardiovascular risk at low LDL: remnants, lipoprotein(a), and inflammation</article-title><source>Clin Chem</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Hoogeveen</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ballantyne</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>143</fpage><lpage>153</lpage><volume>67</volume><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33257928</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Gender in cardiovascular medicine: chest pain and coronary artery disease</article-title><source>Eur Heart J</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bess</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Elias-Smale</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vaccarino</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Quyyumi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pepine</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bairey Merz</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>3819</fpage><lpage>3826</lpage><volume>40</volume><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31713592</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>The association of lipoprotein(a) and circulating monocyte subsets with severe coronary atherosclerosis</article-title><source>J Cardiovasc Dev Dis</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Afanasieva</surname><given-names>OI</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Filatova</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Arefieva</surname><given-names>TI</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>63</fpage><volume>8</volume><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34206012</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Monocyte subset recruitment marker profile is inversely associated with blood ApoA1 levels</article-title><source>Front Immunol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fletcher</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Medbury</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>10</fpage><volume>12</volume><year>2021</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>The role of different monocyte subsets in the pathogenesis of atherosclerosis and acute coronary syndromes</article-title><source>Scand J Immunol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Idzkowska</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eljaszewicz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Miklasz</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Musial</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tycinska</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moniuszko</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>163</fpage><lpage>173</lpage><volume>82</volume><year>2015</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25997925</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>The role of monocytes and macrophages in human atherosclerosis, plaque neoangiogenesis, and atherothrombosis</article-title><source>Mediators Inflamm</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Moroni</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ammirati</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Norata</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Magnoni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Camici</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>376</fpage><volume>4</volume><year>2019</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Monocyte/lymphocyte ratio and cardiovascular disease mortality in peritoneal dialysis patients</article-title><source>Mediators Inflamm</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>507</fpage><volume>14</volume><year>2020</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Relation of plasma lipoprotein(a) to subclinical coronary plaque volumes, three-vessel and left main coronary disease, and severe coronary stenoses in apparently healthy African Americans with a family history of early-onset coronary artery disease</article-title><source>Am J Cardiol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Kral</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kalyani</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yanek</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vaidya</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fishman</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>656</fpage><lpage>661</lpage><volume>118</volume><year>2016</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27530333</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Lipoprotein(a) and inflammation: a dangerous duet leading to endothelial loss of integrity</article-title><source>Pharmacol Res</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Pirro</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bianconi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Paciullo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mannarino</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bagaglia</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sahebkar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>178</fpage><lpage>187</lpage><volume>119</volume><year>2017</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28185944</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Pattern of human monocyte subpopulations in health and disease</article-title><source>Scand J Immunol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>O&#x0017c;a&#x00144;ska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Szymczak</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rybka</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>0</fpage><volume>92</volume><year>2020</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Gene expression profiling reveals the defining features of the classical, intermediate, and nonclassical human monocyte subsets</article-title><source>Blood</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tai</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>0</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><volume>118</volume><year>2011</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>SuperSAGE evidence for CD14++CD16+ monocytes as a third monocyte subset</article-title><source>Blood</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Zawada</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rogacev</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rotter</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Winter</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marell</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fliser</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Heine</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>0</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><volume>118</volume><year>2011</year></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>