<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sensors (Basel)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sensors (Basel)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">sensors</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Sensors (Basel, Switzerland)</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1424-8220</issn><publisher><publisher-name>MDPI</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40006247</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11859784</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/s25041019</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">sensors-25-01019</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Position Detection System for Moving-Magnet Linear Motors Based on a Magnetoresistive Sensor Array</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Jun</given-names></name><role vocab="credit" vocab-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/" vocab-term="Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/">Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing</role><xref rid="af1-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Xiang</given-names></name><role vocab="credit" vocab-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/" vocab-term="Writing &#x02013; original draft" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/">Writing &#x02013; original draft</role><xref rid="af1-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="af2-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Quyan</given-names></name><role vocab="credit" vocab-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/" vocab-term="Conceptualization" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/">Conceptualization</role><xref rid="af3-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="aff">3</xref><xref rid="c1-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xi</surname><given-names>Qing</given-names></name><role vocab="credit" vocab-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/" vocab-term="Validation" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/validation/">Validation</role><xref rid="af3-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Haiyang</given-names></name><role vocab="credit" vocab-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/" vocab-term="Investigation" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/investigation/">Investigation</role><xref rid="af1-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Sammut</surname><given-names>Nicholas</given-names></name><role>Academic Editor</role></contrib><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Calvi</surname><given-names>Marco</given-names></name><role>Academic Editor</role></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af1-sensors-25-01019"><label>1</label>College of Information Science and Technology, Nanjing Forestry University, Nanjing 210037, China; <email>wangjun@njfu.edu.cn</email> (J.W.); <email>cxiang@njfu.edu.cn</email> (X.C.); </aff><aff id="af2-sensors-25-01019"><label>2</label>Jiangsu Oubang Motor Manufacturing Co., Ltd., Dongtai 224200, China</aff><aff id="af3-sensors-25-01019"><label>3</label>Wuxi Hongyi Intelligent Technology Co., Ltd., Wuxi 214000, China; <email>xiqing722@yeah.net</email></aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1-sensors-25-01019"><label>*</label>Correspondence: <email>chenqy0102@yeah.net</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>08</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>2</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>25</volume><issue>4</issue><elocation-id>1019</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>25</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>04</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>07</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2025 by the authors.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>Licensee MDPI, Basel, Switzerland. This article is an open access article distributed under the terms and conditions of the Creative Commons Attribution (CC BY) license (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>The moving-magnet linear motor has received considerable attention in the development of logistic and factory automation in recent years. A reliable position detection system is the key to achieving the precise position and control of the motor. At present, the magnetic grid-scale and grating-scale are the most widely used traditional detection methods. However, these are not suitable for position detection with moving-magnet linear motors. They have the disadvantages of being easy to disturb, having a high cost, and exhibiting a limited measurement range. In this work, a moving-magnet linear motor position detection system based on an array of magnetoresistive sensors is used. The array is configured by arranging the magnetoresistive sensors at equal intervals along a line parallel to the trajectory of the armature. Then, the permanent magnet is fixed on the rotor and detected by sensors. When the rotor crosses the sensors in a parallel line, the changes in the magnetic field cause the magnetoresistive sensors to output two voltage signals directly proportional to the corresponding position changes. The signals are collected by the AD7606 and transmitted to the FPGA and STM32 controller for data processing, and the actual position of the rotor is calculated. This method has no length limitation and can be used for long-distance position detection. The experimental results show that the position detection system has a higher linear correlation coefficient compared with the magnetic grid ruler, in addition to a capability of &#x000b1;9 &#x003bc;m accuracy, which verifies the validity of the position detection method for the moving-magnet linear motor.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>magnetoresistive sensor array</kwd><kwd>position detection</kwd><kwd>moving magnet</kwd><kwd>linear motor</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>Jiangsu Overseas Visiting Scholar Program for University Prominent Young &#x00026; Middle-aged Teachers and Presidents</funding-source><award-id>2019070</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source>Nanjing Forestry University Postgraduate Joint Training Demonstration Base Program</funding-source><award-id>2023204</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source>Jiangsu Students&#x02019; Innovation and Entrepreneurship Training Program</funding-source><award-id>202310298111Y</award-id></award-group><funding-statement>This research was funded by the Jiangsu Overseas Visiting Scholar Program for University Prominent Young &#x00026; Middle-aged Teachers and Presidents (2019070), Nanjing Forestry University Postgraduate Joint Training Demonstration Base Program (2023204), and Jiangsu Students&#x02019; Innovation and Entrepreneurship Training Program (202310298111Y).</funding-statement></funding-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-sensors-25-01019"><title>1. Introduction</title><p>Traditional linear transmission systems often use rotary motors as their power source to convert rotary motion into linear motion through a transmission device [<xref rid="B1-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="B2-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Because of the installation of additional mechanical components, there are problems such as energy loss, noise, mechanical wear, and slow response time. Consequently, the system&#x02019;s speed and acceleration make it difficult to meet the demands of some high-precision and high-response speed applications, such as those involving industrial robots and multi-axis machining centers; therefore, linear motors have been introduced. This paper studies the displacement detection of linear motors. To overcome the above problems, some experts use linear motors as a power source [<xref rid="B3-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="B4-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. As a new type of motor structure [<xref rid="B5-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="B6-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="B7-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], a permanent-magnet synchronous linear motor has the advantages of compact structure, light weight, high precision, and high efficiency in linear transmission. It can overcome the limitations of traditional rotary motors and gradually become the primary choice for many linear transportation applications. At present, permanent-magnet synchronous linear motors are divided into two types, including the moving-coil type and the moving-magnet type [<xref rid="B8-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="B9-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="B10-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. The moving-coil linear motor&#x02019;s armature consists of a coil winding used as a rotor. The coil needs to be connected to the power supply when the rotor is in linear motion. The length of the power cable significantly limits the extent of the motor&#x02019;s linear displacement. The motor can only move within a short linear distance, and is not capable of use across a long linear distance. The moving-magnet linear motor&#x02019;s armature is composed of permanent magnets collectively utilized as a rotor or mover, and its stator consists of a sequential arrangement of many coil windings. Therefore, the rotor, in the course of its linear movement, will not be disturbed by the cable. The straight-motion length will not be limited, as long as the stator coil windings are laid along a sufficiently long path. It can achieve precise long-range servo control. With more and more applications of the moving-magnet linear motor becoming apparent, the position detection method relative to the armature has attracted more attention [<xref rid="B11-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="B12-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. In the existing research relating to position detection for a moving-magnet linear motor&#x02019;s armature [<xref rid="B13-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="B14-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], the linear-sensor methods of magnetic grids and optical gratings are the ones most commonly used [<xref rid="B15-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="B16-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="B17-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="B18-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Magnetic grids are low-cost and easy to install in most industrial applications. However, the position decoders of magnetic grids need to be installed on the rotor, and the detection distance is limited due to the electric wires connected to the power source. Additionally, the magnetic scales need to be replaced at regular intervals because of demagnetization problems [<xref rid="B19-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="B20-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="B21-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Optical gratings can achieve high measurement accuracy, but have high demands as to the conditions of the operating environment. Oil and dust affect the performance of the grating and cause measurement errors. The mechanism needs to be sealed for use in order to avoid the influence of the environment. Therefore, optical gratings are also not suitable for moving-magnet linear motor applications. In order to realize a low-cost and stable position-detection method, magnetoresistive sensors have been considered for use [<xref rid="B22-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].</p><sec id="sec1dot1-sensors-25-01019"><title>1.1. Magnetoresistance</title><p>In 1856, Kelvin [<xref rid="B23-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] discovered the phenomenon of magnetoresistance (MR) in ferromagnetic metals. Magnetoresistance is defined as the change in the electrical resistance of a material when an external magnetic field is applied. Since then, there have been growing numbers of experts and research topics focused on the magnetoresistance effect and materials and structures exhibiting magnetoresistance-based properties. Currently, the most well-established types include anisotropic magnetoresistance (AMR), giant magnetoresistance (GMR), and tunnel magnetoresistance (TMR). These effects have led to the mature development of products for both angle detection and position detection. These sensors are widely used in automotive applications, consumer electronics, and industrial equipment.</p><sec id="sec1dot1dot1-sensors-25-01019"><title>1.1.1. Anisotropic Magnetoresistance (AMR)</title><p>The change in resistance (&#x02206;R) depends on the angle (&#x003b8;) between the current and the magnetization direction of the metal [<xref rid="B24-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], primarily manifested in the influence of the rotating magnetization state in ferromagnetic materials on the direction of the current. In ferromagnetic metals, when the magnetization direction is parallel to the current direction, the resistance reaches its maximum value. When the magnetization direction is perpendicular to the current direction, the resistance reaches its minimum value (<xref rid="sensors-25-01019-f001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). The magnitude of the anisotropic magnetoresistance (AMR) in ferromagnetic metals can be calculated using Equation (1). Currently, the AMR effect has been widely applied in miniaturized and high-sensitivity magnetic field sensors. Researchers are exploring materials and structures with even higher sensitivity.<disp-formula id="FD1-sensors-25-01019"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="mm1" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mo>|</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022a5;</mml:mo></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022a5;</mml:mo></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
where <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm2" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mo>|</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the resistivity when the current is parallel to the magnetization, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm3" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022a5;</mml:mo></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the resistivity when the current is perpendicular to the magnetization.</p></sec><sec id="sec1dot1dot2-sensors-25-01019"><title>1.1.2. Giant Magnetoresistance (GMR)</title><p>In 1988, Fert and Gr&#x000fc;nberg independently discovered the giant magnetoresistance (GMR) effect in different laboratories [<xref rid="B25-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Their research demonstrated that the change in resistance in thin films composed of alternating layers of ferromagnetic materials and non-magnetic metals (such as copper) can be quite significant, reaching up to several tens of times. This effect is primarily due to the scattering of spin-polarized electrons between different magnetic layers. The high resistance values can be observed when the magnetization of two ferromagnetic layers is anti-parallel, and the low resistance state can be observed when the magnetizations are at a parallel state (<xref rid="sensors-25-01019-f002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec1dot1dot3-sensors-25-01019"><title>1.1.3. Tunneling Magnetoresistance (TMR)</title><p>In the 1970s, researchers began to explore the tunneling phenomenon associated with electrons in magnetic materials. Miyazaki and Tezuka were the first to observe that the resistance in a magnetic tunnel junction changes in response to an external magnetic field, a phenomenon that later became known as tunnel magnetoresistance (TMR) [<xref rid="B26-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. TMR uses a magnetic multilayer configuration similar to that of the GMR. The basic unit of the TMR multilayer system is the magnetic tunnel junction (MTJ), which follows the structure of ferromagnetic metal/insulator/ferromagnetic metal. The insulator layer is applied instead of the non-magnetic layer of the GMR multilayer system (<xref rid="sensors-25-01019-f003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>) [<xref rid="B27-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>].</p><p>The formula for calculating the magnetic resistance of the tunnel junction is as follows:<disp-formula id="FD2-sensors-25-01019"><label>(2)</label><mml:math id="mm4" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x00394;</mml:mo><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02032;</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02032;</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>In the equation, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm5" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm6" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> denote the conductance values when the magnetization directions of the two layers of ferromagnetic metal are in the parallel and non-parallel states, respectively, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm7" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm8" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02032;</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> denote the self-polarization rates associated with the effective transport state density of the two layers of ferromagnetic metal, respectively.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec1dot2-sensors-25-01019"><title>1.2. Giant Magnetoimpedance</title><p>Regarding the discovery of the giant magnetoimpedance (GMI) effect, it is widely recognized in the academic community that two research groups independently and nearly simultaneously identified this phenomenon. A publication by R. S. Beach and A. E. Berkowitz, along with a publication by L. V. Panina and K. Mehri, both reported the discovery of the GMI effect in amorphous wires [<xref rid="B28-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="B29-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. These researchers made a quantitative analysis of the phenomenon which is rooted in classical electrodynamics. They showed the characteristic magnetic response of the wire impedance from the experimental and theoretical field dependencies of the MI effect.</p><p>The GMI effect, which refers to the significant changes in the impedance of an amorphous wire under the excitation of alternating current, occurs as the external magnetic field applied along the wire&#x02019;s axis varies. The change rate of the impedance can reach up to 50% under a magnetic field of a few Oersted (Oe), which is an order of magnitude larger than the giant magnetoresistance (GMR) observed in metallic multilayer films such as Fe/Cu or Co/Ag at low temperatures and high magnetic-field strengths.</p><p>The most commonly used expression for the GMI effect is the magnetoimpedance ratio, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm9" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x00394;</mml:mo><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, defined as<disp-formula id="FD3-sensors-25-01019"><label>(3)</label><mml:math id="mm10" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x00394;</mml:mo><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
where <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm11" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the maximum axial DC magnetic field (usually up to a few kA/m).</p><p>The performance of the GMI effect is highly dependent on the material&#x02019;s magnetic anisotropy, soft magnetic properties, skin effect, and microstructure. Therefore, material research is the core driving force behind the advancement of GMI technology. Many experts have studied thin film materials for MI sensor applications. Gonz&#x000e1;lez, J.M. et al. [<xref rid="B30-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] employed broadband ferromagnetic resonance (FMR) measurement techniques to assess the performance and manufacturing consistency of multilayer thin-film structures for magnetoimpedance sensors. This work provides an efficient evaluation tool for quality control in magnetoimpedance sensors and analyzes the microwave resonant absorption of magnetron-sputtered Permalloy-based magnetic films suitable for magnetoimpedance sensor applications. Corr&#x000ea;a, M.A. et al. [<xref rid="B31-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] explored the influence of geometric structures on the magnetoimpedance effect by designing NiFe/Ag multilayered (ML) films and ML/SiO<sub>2</sub>/Ag/SiO<sub>2</sub>/ML structured multilayered (SD) films produced by magnetron sputtering. Aiming to optimize the magnetoimpedance (MI) performance, they compared two types of multilayered films for the different MI behaviors and explained the MI changes of sample geometry and the mechanisms observed in distinct frequency ranges. These features may be useful for technological applications of frequency-tunable MI-based magnetic-field sensors.</p><p>These two studies enhance the comprehension of the thin-film magnetoimpedance effect from the perspectives of process stability and structural design, jointly driving the practical development of high-frequency magnetic sensor technology.</p></sec><sec id="sec1dot3-sensors-25-01019"><title>1.3. Introduction to the Research Work</title><p>In this study, a moving-magnet linear motor position detection system based on an array of magnetoresistive sensors is designed. The study aims to explore the performance of magnetoresistive sensor arrays in position detection systems for moving-magnet linear motors, and to select the most suitable magnetoresistive sensors for use in displacement detection systems for moving-magnet linear motors through comparative analysis. This system not only detects the absolute position of the mover in real time with high accuracy, but also, the sensor array can be modularly spliced for detection. Additionally, the detection length can be increased at any time and any place, making it suitable for the long-distance motion detection of the mover. This study aims to develop a displacement detection system for moving-magnet linear motors. The mover of the moving-magnet linear motor consists of a permanent magnet and the stator consists of coils. Therefore, the mover does not require a power supply or cable carrier, and has the advantages of high precision, fast speed, long displacement, and high motion-control efficiency. By measuring the exact position of the mover, the stator coil voltage at the corresponding position can be controlled to control the starting, stopping, or speed of the mover. Multiple movers can be installed in one linear motor, and separate control of multiple movers can be realized, which greatly enhances the working efficiency of the actual production line. The main contributions of this paper are as follows.</p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p>According to the sensor principle and the operating mode of the linear motor&#x02019;s armature, the arrangement of sensors and the spatial relative position of the permanent magnets and sensors for detection are designed.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The output signals from each sensor may not be completely consistent, resulting in fluctuations of output voltage. By digitally processing the collected signals in the FPGA, errors can be eliminated, ensuring that the average of the two sine signals output by each sensor is the same, improving the displacement detection accuracy.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Displacement calculations are performed in the STM32, and the real-time position of the actuator is output to the host computer for display.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The final system is tested to verify the effectiveness of this method.</p></list-item></list></sec></sec><sec id="sec2-sensors-25-01019"><title>2. Composition and Detection Principle</title><sec id="sec2dot1-sensors-25-01019"><title>2.1. Introduction to the Detection System</title><p>This article describes a position detection method based on the TLE5501 (Infineon Technologies AG, Munich, Germany) magnetoresistive sensor array. The magnetoresistive sensors are arranged at equal intervals along a straight line, and the detection range of each sensor is sequentially &#x0201c;spliced&#x0201d; in the form of an array, arranged in parallel next to the guide rail on which the mover runs. The motion of the mover causes the permanent magnet to pass through the sensor, and the sensor outputs two sinusoidal voltage signals, achieving long-distance linear position detection. <xref rid="sensors-25-01019-f004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref> is the overall block diagram of the system scheme, including the TLE5501 sensor array, a differential proportional amplification circuit, an AD7606 analog-to-digital conversion module (Shenzhen Convince Technology Co., Ltd., Shenzhen, China), an FPGA and STM32 module (Nexperia Co., Ltd., Shenzhen, China), and the PC host computer.</p></sec><sec id="sec2dot2-sensors-25-01019"><title>2.2. Equivalent Magnetic Charge Model (EMC)</title><p>The equivalent magnetic charge model assumes that there is a body charge of density <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm12" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> inside the magnet and a surface charge of density <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm13" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ms</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> on the surface of the magnet.</p><p>According to the equivalent magnetic charge model, the body charge density <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm14" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> present in the permanent magnet is as follows:<disp-formula id="FD4-sensors-25-01019"><label>(4)</label><mml:math id="mm15" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02207;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>In the equation, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm16" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the vacuum permeability, and <italic toggle="yes">M</italic> is the magnetization strength.</p><p>Inside a uniformly magnetized magnet, there is <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm17" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> = 0, and hence the body charge density <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm18" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. However, at the boundaries there is still a surface charge <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm19" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> on the magnet boundaries due to the discontinuity of <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm20" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>:<disp-formula id="FD5-sensors-25-01019"><label>(5)</label><mml:math id="mm21" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>In the equation, n is the outer normal unit vector of the magnet boundary.</p><p>According to Gauss&#x02019;s law in Maxwell&#x02019;s system of equations, the scalar magnetic potential at an arbitrary point in space generated by a permanent magnet can be obtained as<disp-formula id="FD6-sensors-25-01019"><label>(6)</label><mml:math id="mm22" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mi>&#x003c0;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathsize="140%" displaystyle="true"><mml:mo>&#x0222b;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x0222b;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x0222b;</mml:mo></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mo mathvariant="italic">&#x003a9;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mi>&#x003c0;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathsize="140%" displaystyle="true"><mml:mo>&#x0222b;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x0222b;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x0222b;</mml:mo></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mo mathvariant="italic">&#x00393;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>Applying the scattering theorem, this can be rewritten as<disp-formula id="FD7-sensors-25-01019"><label>(7)</label><mml:math id="mm23" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mi>&#x003c0;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathsize="140%" displaystyle="true"><mml:mo>&#x0222b;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x0222b;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x0222b;</mml:mo></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mo mathvariant="italic">&#x003a9;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02207;</mml:mo><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>According to the relationship between the scalar magnetic potential <italic toggle="yes">&#x003c6;</italic> and the magnetic-field strength <italic toggle="yes">Hm</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Hm</italic> = <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm24" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>; the magnetic-field strength in the space around the permanent magnet can be determined:<disp-formula id="FD8-sensors-25-01019"><label>(8)</label><mml:math id="mm25" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mi>&#x003c0;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathsize="140%" displaystyle="true"><mml:mo>&#x0222b;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x0222b;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x0222b;</mml:mo></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mo mathvariant="italic">&#x003a9;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathsize="140%" displaystyle="true"><mml:mo>&#x0222b;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x0222b;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x0222b;</mml:mo></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mo mathvariant="italic">&#x00393;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>In the equation, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm26" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the vectorial diameter from the source point (inside the permanent magnet) to the field point (the solution point). <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm27" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the distance from the source point to the field point, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm28" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mo mathvariant="italic">&#x003a9;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the permanent magnet integration region, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm29" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mo mathvariant="italic">&#x00393;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the boundary of the permanent magnet.</p></sec><sec id="sec2dot3-sensors-25-01019"><title>2.3. Comparison and Introduction of Magnetic Sensors</title><p>Magnetic sensors have been used for measuring the magnitude, the direction, and the relative change of the magnetic field. There are two main categories of magnetic-field sensors: the magnetoimpedance sensor and the magnetoresistive sensor. The magnetoimpedance sensor utilizes the phenomenon known as the GMI effect, which is the large response of electrical impedance in certain materials caused by an external magnetic field. This causes an increase in the impedance of the wire with increasing frequency. The GMI sensor and integrated circuit were developed by the Aichi Steel Co., Tokai, Japan, in October 2001. Over the last two decades, many subsequent applications and studies have been developed. On the other hand, magnetoresistive sensors have been developed over time based on the magnetoresistive [<xref rid="B32-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="B33-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>] effect, and many different types of magnetoresistive sensors have now been developed, including anisotropic magnetoresistance (AMR) [<xref rid="B34-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], giant magnetoresistance (GMR), and the latest, tunneling magnetoresistance (TMR). They are summarized in the following: <list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Sensitivity and magnetic-field range: TMR sensors are extremely sensitive and accurate, capable of accurately measuring changes in weak magnetic fields. With an MR (magnetoresistive) ratio of up to 100%, the output signal sensitivity is significantly improved compared to AMR and GMR sensors, reaching improvements of 13.3 times and 3.5 times, respectively. This feature establishes TMR sensors as the preferred choice for applications that require high sensitivity and an extensive measurement range of the magnetic field. GMI sensors also exhibit a wide sensitivity range, extending from the millimeter-tesla region to the weak magnetic field of the pico-tesla.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Energy consumption: TMR sensors have low power requirements. Therefore, TMR is a very important approach for devices that require long-term operation or battery power, and especially for sensor arrays. Their low power consumption helps to extend the life of the device and reduce energy costs. AMR and GMR have relatively higher levels of power consumption due to the fact that their supply currents are larger. GMI sensors exhibit low levels of power consumption due to the pulse interval independence associated with the GMI effect.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Working temperature: TMR has good linearity and stability and shows a good linear relationship between the output signal and the input magnetic field. It also has a wide operating temperature range and can work stably under various environmental conditions. This ensures the stability and reliability of TMR sensors in harsh environments. At the same time, temperature stability also affects the performance and energy consumption of the sensor, so the temperature stability of TMR is very beneficial for power management. GMI sensors have a limited working temperature range due to the difficulty in integrating the sensing wire and the GMI effect being affected by temperature in practical applications.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Cost: The prices of AMR, TMR, and GMI sensor chips are similar, while GMR sensor chips are relatively expensive.</p></list-item></list></p><p>The comparisons of magnetic sensors are listed in <xref rid="sensors-25-01019-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p><p>Based on the above considerations, this study has chosen TMR sensors, which are associated with small size, high stability, low power consumption, and high sensitivity. The following is a description of the TMR sensor.</p><p>The TLE5501 consists of eight TMR devices. The sensor is made by micromanipulation of magnetoresistive film stack structures. This includes preparing a desired circuit pattern using processes such as photolithography, vapor deposition, and stripping, and then vapor deposition of electrode materials such as gold and copper onto the magnetoresistive film stack structure to form the desired circuit connections. The structure can be described as being equivalent to two Wheatstone bridges [<xref rid="B35-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. It is shown in <xref rid="sensors-25-01019-f005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>.</p><p>From this, we can see the following: <disp-formula id="FD9-sensors-25-01019"><label>(9)</label><mml:math id="mm30" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>Scos</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003b8;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="FD10-sensors-25-01019"><label>(10)</label><mml:math id="mm31" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>Ssin</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003b8;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
In the formula, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm32" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the supply voltage of the bridge, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm33" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">S</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the material constant. The <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm34" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b8;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the angle between the magnetization direction of the top conducting layer and bottom conducting layer, where the magnetization direction of top conducting layer follows the direction of external magnetic field. So <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm35" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b8;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the angle between the external magnetic field and the magnetization direction of the bottom conducting layer. This is shown in <xref rid="sensors-25-01019-f006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="sec2dot4-sensors-25-01019"><title>2.4. Position of the Sensor Relative to the Permanent Magnet</title><p>Since the magnetoresistive sensor is only sensitive to magnetic fields parallel to the sensor surface, magnetic fields perpendicular to the sensor surface have little effect on the sensor&#x02019;s output. The permanent magnet used in this article is a thickness-direction-magnetized permanent magnet. There are two cases regarding the spatial relationship between the sensor and the permanent magnet. The first case is illustrated in <xref rid="sensors-25-01019-f007" ref-type="fig">Figure 7</xref>.</p><p>Case 1:</p><fig position="anchor" id="sensors-25-01019-f007"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Schematic diagram of the spatial position of the sensor relative to the permanent magnet in case 1.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sensors-25-01019-g007" position="float"/></fig><p>At this time, the magnetization direction of the permanent magnet is parallel to the <italic toggle="yes">y</italic>-axis. Since the magnetoresistive sensor is only sensitive to magnetic fields parallel to the sensor surface (XY plane), the only need to be focused on is the magnetic field of the permanent magnet in the XY plane. <xref rid="sensors-25-01019-f008" ref-type="fig">Figure 8</xref> shows the Maxwell simulation of the magnetic induction intensity vector in the XY plane corresponding to case 1.</p><p><xref rid="sensors-25-01019-f009" ref-type="fig">Figure 9</xref> shows the magnetic induction vector on the line where the sensor is located in the XY plane. As can be seen in <xref rid="sensors-25-01019-f007" ref-type="fig">Figure 7</xref>, the line at position C of the magnetic induction vector coincides with the 0&#x000b0; direction of the sensor. The line with the magnetic induction vector at position B makes an angle of 45&#x000b0; with the 0&#x000b0; direction of the sensor. The line at position D of the magnetic induction vector makes an angle of &#x02212;45&#x000b0; with the 0&#x000b0; direction of the sensor. The further towards the sides one is, the closer the angle is to the +90&#x000b0; and &#x02212;90&#x000b0; angles.</p><p><xref rid="sensors-25-01019-f010" ref-type="fig">Figure 10</xref> shows the output waveform of the magnetoresistive sensor when the permanent magnet moves parallel to the magnetoresistive sensor along a straight line at a constant speed in case 1. The output waveform of the magnetoresistive sensor is shown in <xref rid="sensors-25-01019-f010" ref-type="fig">Figure 10</xref>. Obviously, when the permanent magnet crosses from one side of the sensor, the angle ranges from &#x02212;90&#x000b0; to +90&#x000b0;. The cos waveform in this figure is obviously negative, indicating that the angle in this case has a significant deviation, and the angle read by the sensor does not match the actual angle.</p><p>Case 2:</p><p><xref rid="sensors-25-01019-f011" ref-type="fig">Figure 11</xref> illustrates the spatial location relationship between the permanent magnet and the sensor in case 2. In the XY plane, the upper surface of the sensor is parallel to the lower surface of the permanent magnet.</p><p><xref rid="sensors-25-01019-f012" ref-type="fig">Figure 12</xref> shows the output waveform of the magnetoresistive sensor during the uniform velocity motion of the permanent magnet parallel to the magnetoresistive sensor along a straight line in case 2. Curve no. 2 in the figure shows that the output at point A corresponds to sin (45&#x000b0;), the output at point C corresponds to sin (0&#x000b0;), and the output at point B corresponds to cos (0&#x000b0;).</p><p>For the above two mounting methods, the first mounting method of the permanent magnet does not match the actual angular position of the permanent magnet and the sensor and the output angle of the sensor. Therefore, it is not chosen. In contrast, for the second installation method, the permanent magnet matches the actual angular position of the sensor and the output angle of the sensor, so the second one is the preferred choice.</p><p>For situations in which there is a piece of permanent magnet in the effective detection range of the TLE5501 magnetoresistive sensor, parallel to the sensor array along the straight line and with movement of a uniform speed, the sin output image of four consecutive TLE5501 sensors is shown in <xref rid="sensors-25-01019-f013" ref-type="fig">Figure 13</xref>.</p><p>This system determines the detection interval based on the positive or negative output signal of each sensor. <xref rid="sensors-25-01019-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> shows the output polarity of each sensor in different detection intervals corresponding to <xref rid="sensors-25-01019-f013" ref-type="fig">Figure 13</xref>.</p><p>From <xref rid="sensors-25-01019-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, it can be seen that when the permanent magnet is within the detection range of sensor 1, the sin output of sensor 1 is positive, while the sin output of sensor 2 is negative. The sin outputs of sensor 1 and sensor 2 have opposite polarities. The sin outputs of sensor 2 and sensor 3 have the same negative polarity, and the sin outputs of sensor 3 and sensor 4 also have the same negative polarity. Similar situations exist for other detection intervals. By analyzing the sin outputs of adjacent sensors, it can be determined which specific detection interval the permanent magnet is currently located in.</p></sec><sec id="sec2dot5-sensors-25-01019"><title>2.5. Effects of Different Y and Z Distances on Output Waveforms</title><p>The distance from the center point of the sensor to the center point of the permanent magnet along the <italic toggle="yes">y</italic>-axis in the XY-plane is defined as the Y-distance, and the distance from the upper surface of the sensor to the lower surface of the permanent magnet along the <italic toggle="yes">z</italic>-axis in the XZ-plane is defined as the Z-distance, as shown in <xref rid="sensors-25-01019-f014" ref-type="fig">Figure 14</xref>, below.</p><p>After determining the relationship between the permanent magnet and the spatial position, it is necessary to adjust the Y and Z distances to determine the optimal measurement distance. During actual measurement, the Y and Z distances cannot be too large; it must be ensured that the sensor is in a saturated state within the measurement range.</p><p>When the Z distance is 6 mm, the output waveform of the TLE5501 is measured at Y distances of 8 mm, 10 mm, 12 mm, and 14 mm, respectively. The sin outputs are shown in <xref rid="sensors-25-01019-f015" ref-type="fig">Figure 15</xref>a, and the cos outputs are shown in <xref rid="sensors-25-01019-f015" ref-type="fig">Figure 15</xref>b.</p><p>From <xref rid="sensors-25-01019-f015" ref-type="fig">Figure 15</xref>, it can be seen that when other conditions are the same, within a certain detection range, the larger the Y distance, the wider the corresponding straight line detection interval in the same angular range.</p><p>Under the condition that the Y distance is 15 mm, the TLE5501 outputs certain waveforms when the Z distances are 6 mm, 8 mm, 10 mm, and 12 mm, respectively; the sin outputs are shown in <xref rid="sensors-25-01019-f016" ref-type="fig">Figure 16</xref>a and the cos outputs are shown in <xref rid="sensors-25-01019-f016" ref-type="fig">Figure 16</xref>b:</p><p>From <xref rid="sensors-25-01019-f016" ref-type="fig">Figure 16</xref>, it can be seen that in this variation, it is not obvious that the larger the Z distance is, the wider the corresponding linear detection interval is within the same condition of angular range. This condition indicates that within a certain range, the Z distance has almost no effect on the width of the linear detection interval.</p></sec><sec id="sec2dot6-sensors-25-01019"><title>2.6. Sensor Array Program Principles</title><p>The array detection scheme is constructed by splicing multiple single-detection intervals. The displacement detection method for a single sensor interval is shown in <xref rid="sensors-25-01019-f017" ref-type="fig">Figure 17</xref>.</p><p>The two bridge outputs of the magnetoresistive sensor TLE5501 are <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm36" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm37" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, which can be converted to an angle &#x003b8; by arc tangent subdivision:<disp-formula id="FD11-sensors-25-01019"><label>(11)</label><mml:math id="mm38" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b8;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>arctan</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>The relative position <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm39" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x00394;</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> of the permanent magnet within a sensor detection interval can be calculated by finding the tangent from Equation (12) using simple trigonometric functions, as shown in <xref rid="sensors-25-01019-f017" ref-type="fig">Figure 17</xref>:<disp-formula id="FD12-sensors-25-01019"><label>(12)</label><mml:math id="mm40" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x00394;</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">tan</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b8;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
In the formula, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm41" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the vertical distance from the center point of the sensor to the center point of the permanent magnet.</p><p>If the horizontal linear position of sensor 1 is <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm42" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, the linear position <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm43" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> of the permanent magnet in a single interval in <xref rid="sensors-25-01019-f017" ref-type="fig">Figure 17</xref> is<disp-formula id="FD13-sensors-25-01019"><label>(13)</label><mml:math id="mm44" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x00394;</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>According to <xref rid="sensors-25-01019-f001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>, the single-detection interval can be expanded to array detection. Firstly, the absolute positions <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm45" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm46" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, &#x02026;, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm47" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> of the center points of each sensor are calibrated by standard length intervals and stored in ROM. After the displacement detection, when the mover is located in the detection range of sensor <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm48" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, the absolute position <italic toggle="yes">M<sub>i</sub></italic> of sensor <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm49" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is read first, and then the angular relationship between the permanent magnet and sensor <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm50" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is calculated based on the outputs <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm51" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm52" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> of sensor <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm53" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> by inverse tangent subdivision. The relative position <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm54" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x00394;</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> of the permanent magnet located in the detection range of the sensor i is calculated by Formula (14), and the linear position <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm55" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> of the permanent magnet can be obtained by adding the relative position and the absolute position:<disp-formula id="FD14-sensors-25-01019"><label>(14)</label><mml:math id="mm56" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x00394;</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>Through the integration of absolute and relative positions, the absolute position of the sensor is reliably recalculated to ensure that the errors of each sensor detection range do not accumulate and overlap with calculations for other sensor detection ranges.</p><p>The permanent magnet used as mover in the displacement detection has high remanence, high coercivity, high maximum magnetic energy product, and good material stability. References [<xref rid="B36-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="B37-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>] describe the method of calculating magnetic-field strength. The parameters of the neodymium&#x02013;iron&#x02013;boron permanent magnet (Zhejiang Sheensen Magnetics Technology Co., Ltd., Zhejiang, China) selected in this article are shown in <xref rid="sensors-25-01019-t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>.</p><p>The normal operating range of the TLE5501 is 20 to 100 (mT). This study collected data on the magnetic-field strength while the mover was in motion within a range of &#x02212;15 mm to +15 mm, specifically, for the conditions when Y = 8, 10, 12, and 14, and Z = 6, 8, 10, and 12, as shown in the <xref rid="sensors-25-01019-t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>.</p><p>According to the actual data, to ensure that the sensor operates normally, it is essential to maintain the magnetic-field strength within the range of 20 mT to 100 mT in its corresponding detection zone. Given the limited magnetic-field strength of the permanent magnet, both Y and Z should not be too large. A Y position of 10 to 12 mm and a Z position of 8 to 10 mm are considered suitable spatial positions for the sensor relative to the permanent magnet.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3-sensors-25-01019"><title>3. Signal Processing and Acquisition</title><sec id="sec3dot1-sensors-25-01019"><title>3.1. Signal Amplification Processing Circuit</title><p>The TLE5501 magnetic resistance chip outputs two kinds of differential signals. In this scheme, a dual operational amplifier chip LM358 is used to construct two differential amplification circuits. The differential signals output from the two bridges are amplified to an amplitude suitable for A/D acquisition through differential operation and amplification. The filter circuits are added to the power input and signal output in order to reduce signal interference.</p></sec><sec id="sec3dot2-sensors-25-01019"><title>3.2. AD7606 Analog-To-Digital Converter</title><p>The AD7606 analog-to-digital acquisition module is used for multi-channel synchronous A/D acquisition of amplified output signals. The AD7606 analog-to-digital conversion chip can simultaneously perform A/D acquisition on eight channels of signals, so one AD7606 chip can be combined with four TLE5501 sensors.</p></sec><sec id="sec3dot3-sensors-25-01019"><title>3.3. The FPGA and the STM32 Controller</title><p>The FPGA module is used to drive the AD7606 module; it receives the digital quantities obtained from the A/D conversion of the AD7606 module, filters out the sensor outputs of the detection interval where the actuator is currently located by logical judgment, and transmits the digital quantities of the sensor outputs as well as the numbers of the corresponding sensors to the STM32 via FSMC for the subsequent computational processing [<xref rid="B38-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="B39-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>].</p><p>The STM32 reads the absolute position of the sensor stored in ROM based on the received sensor number, performs an arc tangent operation on the received sensor output, calculates the relative displacement of the actuator in the sensor detection range, and adds the two to obtain the position of the mover of the linear motor. The calculated position of the mover of the linear motor is transmitted to the host computer control system via serial communication [<xref rid="B40-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="B41-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="B42-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec4-sensors-25-01019"><title>4. System Detection Test</title><sec id="sec4dot1-sensors-25-01019"><title>4.1. Test Subjects</title><p>To verify the feasibility of the non-contact linear motor position detection scheme based on a magnetoresistive sensor array, a linear screw module (Guangzhou CNC Equipment Co., Ltd., Guangzhou, China) was used to simulate the linear motion of the rotor. The screw slide table was installed with the mover, which was made by a 3D printer and embedded with permanent magnets. The screw module was driven and controlled by a stepper motor, with a linear positioning accuracy of 0.05 mm. A magnetic scale model MSR5000(HEIDENHAIN Corporation, Degenfeld, Germany) was selected as the position detection comparison, with an accuracy of &#x000b1;5 &#x003bc;m. The magnetic grid ruler reading head was installed on the slide table and moved simultaneously with the mover.</p><p>In this experiment, the position detection circuit board was constructed, and eight TLE5501 magnetoresistive sensors were used as a module, with 15 mm spacing for each sensor, and a total of 16 channel output signals. The sensor analogue signals were collected with two AD7606 chips, and the STM32 + FPGA dual core board was used to process the signals and upload the data to the PC to display the current position information. The sensor spacing can be adjusted according to specific requirements, but must ensure that the sensors are kept in a magnetic saturation state within the measurement distance. The physical diagram depicting this arrangement is shown as <xref rid="sensors-25-01019-f018" ref-type="fig">Figure 18</xref>.</p><p>In practical applications, the core board of FPGA with multiple IO ports can be used to collect data from various sensor chips simultaneously. Based on the required detection length, it is necessary to deploy a sufficient number of sensor chips and FPGA core boards. When the mover of the linear motor arrives at the interval, the sin and cos signals of the interval sensor are collected and processed by more than one FPGA core board and transmitted to the stm32 for accurate displacement calculation.</p></sec><sec id="sec4dot2-sensors-25-01019"><title>4.2. Sensor Signal Normalization</title><p>The outputs of each sensor may not be identical, due to the manufacturing process of the chip. Therefore, in order to achieve highly accurate position detection, the two outputs of the TLE5501 magnetoresistive sensor must be normalized. Using a magnet placed directly above the sensor and rotated one period, the trigonometric values of the outputs were obtained as shown in <xref rid="sensors-25-01019-f019" ref-type="fig">Figure 19</xref>; these are in good agreement with Equations (7) and (8).</p><p>As for the sin signal, its maximum value is <italic toggle="yes">V<sub>Amax</sub></italic> and minimum value is <italic toggle="yes">V<sub>Amin</sub></italic>; the DC bias of the bridge output <italic toggle="yes">V<sub>Aoff</sub></italic> and peak&#x02013;peak value <italic toggle="yes">V<sub>Apeak-peak</sub></italic> are given by<disp-formula id="FD15-sensors-25-01019"><label>(15)</label><mml:math id="mm57" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>max</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>min</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="FD16-sensors-25-01019"><label>(16)</label><mml:math id="mm58" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>peak</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>max</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>min</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>Similarly, the DC bias <italic toggle="yes">V<sub>Boff</sub></italic> and peak-to-peak value <italic toggle="yes">V<sub>Bpeak-peak</sub></italic> of the cos signal are<disp-formula id="FD17-sensors-25-01019"><label>(17)</label><mml:math id="mm59" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">B</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">B</mml:mi><mml:mi>max</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">B</mml:mi><mml:mi>min</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="FD18-sensors-25-01019"><label>(18)</label><mml:math id="mm60" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Bpeak</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>max</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>min</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>In the actual measurement, if the peak-to-peak value of the output of the B-bridge is selected as the reference, the output of the A-bridge is defined to be <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm61" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and the output of the B-bridge is defined to be <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm62" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> before normalization. Therefore, the output of the A-bridge is defined as <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm63" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and the output of the B-bridge is defined to be <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm64" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> after normalization, as follows:<disp-formula id="FD19-sensors-25-01019"><label>(19)</label><mml:math id="mm65" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="FD20-sensors-25-01019"><label>(20)</label><mml:math id="mm66" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>The above normalization method solves the problem of unequal DC bias and the unequal magnitudes of the two outputs of the TLE5501 magnetoresistive sensor. By performing the above operation for each sensor, the normalization of the two outputs of each sensor can be realized, which can improve the accuracy of the position detection of the magnetoresistive sensor array.</p><p>In this study, the normalization of the sensor was performed using data from a permanent magnet rotating above the sensor for one complete cycle. Subsequently, the normalized results were validated in the linear displacement detection experiments, as shown in <xref rid="sensors-25-01019-f020" ref-type="fig">Figure 20</xref> and <xref rid="sensors-25-01019-f021" ref-type="fig">Figure 21</xref>.</p><p>According to the experimental data, the normalization of the signals reduced the offset and errors.</p></sec><sec id="sec4dot3-sensors-25-01019"><title>4.3. Displacement Detection Error Test</title><p>The reciprocation error is shown in <xref rid="sensors-25-01019-f020" ref-type="fig">Figure 20</xref>.</p><p>Firstly, we evaluated the stability and repeatability of the system by monitoring for any errors or fluctuations in the position information output by the system as the linear motor was repeatedly moved to the same location. After testing, it was found that the fluctuation was basically maintained in the range of 0~3 &#x003bc;m. The source of these fluctuations is related to the circuit noise interference and changes in the temperature environment. However, the magnitude of these fluctuations does not impact the detection accuracy. The reciprocation error is shown in <xref rid="sensors-25-01019-f022" ref-type="fig">Figure 22</xref>.</p><p>During the experiment, the permanent magnet was caused to move from the starting point of the sensor array. Then, a spiral slider drove the permanent magnet linearly along the <italic toggle="yes">x</italic>-axis with a displacement of 0.1 mm per time cycle. At the same time, the PC host computer received and recorded the measured position data and compared the readings with the actual displacement length.</p><p>The discrepancy between the measured position and the magnetic encoder&#x02019;s reading was defined as the dynamic error. <xref rid="sensors-25-01019-f023" ref-type="fig">Figure 23</xref> shows a graph of the dynamic error test results. Because the spacing of each sensor was recalibrated, only the data from four measurement intervals were selected to illustrate the error range. As can be seen from the graph, the maximum error is within &#x000b1;9 &#x003bc;m, which meets the accuracy requirements of most industrial applications.</p><p>The accuracy is comparable to that of the most widely used magnetic scale. Both can meet most industrial needs. However, this study can fulfill the need for position detection of dynamic magnetic linear motors, a need which cannot be met by magnetic scales under such working conditions.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec5-sensors-25-01019"><title>5. Conclusions</title><p>This research utilized the characteristics of magnetoresistive sensors to design a mover displacement detection system for a permanent magnet linear motor with a moving-magnet configuration. This paper explains the principle and detection scheme of the magnetic sensor array used for displacement detection. By constructing a dual CPU controller detection circuit, using the Arctan subdivision algorithm, and then normalizing the sensor signal, the absolute position of the mover can be accurately obtained. The magnetoresistive sensor array has the advantages of small physical space, low cost, and easy installation, along with having no need to drag cables; this can help to realize a modular installation and allow the device to effectively detect the absolute position of the mover. This approach provides a feasible method for the position-based closed-loop servo control of moving-magnet permanent magnet linear motors [<xref rid="B43-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="B44-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,<xref rid="B45-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,<xref rid="B46-sensors-25-01019" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>].</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>All data generated or presented in this study are available, upon request, from the first author. The models and code used during this study cannot be shared, as the data also form part of an ongoing study.</p></ack><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Disclaimer/Publisher&#x02019;s Note:</bold> The statements, opinions and data contained in all publications are solely those of the individual author(s) and contributor(s) and not of MDPI and/or the editor(s). MDPI and/or the editor(s) disclaim responsibility for any injury to people or property resulting from any ideas, methods, instructions or products referred to in the content.</p></fn></fn-group><notes><title>Author Contributions</title><p>Conceptualization, J.W.; methodology, J.W.; software, X.C.; validation, X.C.; formal analysis, H.S.; investigation, Q.X.; resources, J.W.; data curation, J.W.; writing&#x02014;original draft preparation, X.C.; writing&#x02014;review and editing, J.W.; visualization, Q.C.; supervision, Q.X.; project administration, Q.C.; funding acquisition, Q.X. All authors have read and agreed to the published version of the manuscript.</p></notes><notes><title>Institutional Review Board Statement</title><p>Not applicable.</p></notes><notes><title>Informed Consent Statement</title><p>Not applicable.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>Data are contained within the article.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflicts of Interest</title><p>The company was not involved in the study design, collection, analysis, interpretation of data, the writing of this article or the decision to submit it for publication. The remaining authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></notes><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1-sensors-25-01019"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Palka</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Woronowicz</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Linear Induction Motors in Transportation Systems</article-title><source>Energies</source><year>2021</year><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>2549</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/en14092549</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2-sensors-25-01019"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The Servo Control and Experimental Investigation of the Linear Transmission System</article-title><source>International Conference on Sustainable Energy and Environment Protection (ICSEEP 2015)</source><publisher-name>Destech Publications, Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Lancaster, PA, USA</publisher-loc><year>2015</year><fpage>1002</fpage><lpage>1006</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3-sensors-25-01019"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ching</surname><given-names>T.W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Overview of Linear Motors for Transportation Applications</article-title><source>Proceedings of the IEEE International Symposium on Industrial Electronics</source><conf-loc>Cairns, QLD, Australia</conf-loc><conf-date>13&#x02013;15 June 2018</conf-date><fpage>150</fpage><lpage>154</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4-sensors-25-01019"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W.C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>Z.Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Design of Vertical Transportation System Driven by Permanent Magnet Linear Synchronous Motor Signal Acquisition</article-title><source>Proceedings of the 2012 International Conference on Industrial Control and Electronics Engineering (ICICEE)</source><conf-loc>Xi&#x02019;an, China</conf-loc><conf-date>23&#x02013;25 August 2012</conf-date><fpage>2033</fpage><lpage>2035</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5-sensors-25-01019"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Design and Electromagnetic Characteristics Study of a High Speed and High-Power Permanent Magnet Linear Synchronous Motor</article-title><source>Proceedings of the 2020 IEEE 9th International Power Electronics and Motion Control Conference (IPEMC2020-ECCE Asia)</source><conf-loc>Nanjing, China</conf-loc><conf-date>29 November&#x02013;2 December 2020</conf-date><fpage>1986</fpage><lpage>1991</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6-sensors-25-01019"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>C.-C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P.-L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C.-T.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Optimal Design of a Permanent Magnet Linear Synchronous Motor with Low Cogging Force</article-title><source>IEEE Trans. Magn.</source><year>2012</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>1039</fpage><lpage>1042</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/TMAG.2011.2172578</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7-sensors-25-01019"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Boduroglu</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gulec</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Demir</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yolacan</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aydin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>A New Asymmetric Planar V-Shaped Magnet Arrangement for A Linear PM Synchronous Motor</article-title><source>IEEE Trans. Magn.</source><year>2019</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/TMAG.2019.2897820</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8-sensors-25-01019"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yazaki</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nishimura</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ohnishi</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Imura</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fujimoto</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Moving Coil Type Wireless Linear Motor based on Magnetic Resonance Coupling</article-title><source>Proceedings of the IECON 2017&#x02014;43rd Annual Conference of the IEEE Industrial Electronics Society</source><conf-loc>Beijing, China</conf-loc><conf-date>29 October&#x02013;1 November 2017</conf-date><fpage>7288</fpage><lpage>7293</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/iecon.2017.8217276</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9-sensors-25-01019"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kou</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Analysis and Modeling of A Novel Moving-Magnet-Type Linear Synchronous Motor with Ring Structure Winding</article-title><source>Proceedings of the 2020 23rd International Conference on Electrical Machines and Systems (ICEMS)</source><conf-loc>Hamamatsu, Japan</conf-loc><conf-date>24&#x02013;27 November 2020</conf-date><fpage>1902</fpage><lpage>1906</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10-sensors-25-01019"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Modelling and Measurement of a Moving Magnet Linear Motor for Linear Compressor</article-title><source>Energies</source><year>2020</year><volume>13</volume><elocation-id>4030</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/en13154030</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11-sensors-25-01019"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Radial Position Detection of Five-Phase Bearingless PM Motor</article-title><source>Proceedings of the 2016 XXII International Conference on Electrical Machines (ICEM)</source><conf-loc>Lausanne, Switzerland</conf-loc><conf-date>4&#x02013;7 September 2016</conf-date><fpage>2602</fpage><lpage>2608</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12-sensors-25-01019"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mei</surname><given-names>T.X.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Rotor-Position Detection in Permanent-Magnet Wheel Motor to Ensure Smooth Startup From Standstill</article-title><source>IEEE Access</source><year>2019</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>54179</fpage><lpage>54191</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/ACCESS.2019.2912445</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13-sensors-25-01019"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Fiber Bragg Grating Sensor and Waveguide Grating Sensor</article-title><source>Proceedings of the Photonics North 2011</source><conf-loc>Ottawa, ON, Canada</conf-loc><conf-date>16&#x02013;18 May 2011</conf-date></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14-sensors-25-01019"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Novel Fiber Grating for Sensing Applications</article-title><source>Phys. Status Solidi A-Appl. Mater. Sci.</source><year>2019</year><volume>216</volume><fpage>1800820</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pssa.201800820</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15-sensors-25-01019"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>K.-D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S.G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>W.-H.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Unbalanced ZCP Compensation Method for Position Sensorless BLDC Motor</article-title><source>IEEE Trans. Power Electron.</source><year>2019</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>3020</fpage><lpage>3024</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/TPEL.2018.2868828</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16-sensors-25-01019"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>G.Z.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S.D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z.M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Sensorless Position Detection of the Planar Switched Reluctance Motor Using the Current Injection Method</article-title><source>Proceedings of the 2017 IEEE International Electric Machines and Drives Conference (IEMDC)</source><conf-loc>Miami, FL, USA</conf-loc><conf-date>21&#x02013;24 May 2017</conf-date></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17-sensors-25-01019"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>D.Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Improvement of Initial Rotor Position Detection for Permanent-Magnet Synchronous Motor Using Magnetic Position Sensor</article-title><source>J. Korea Acad.-Ind. Coop. Soc.</source><year>2021</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>398</fpage><lpage>404</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18-sensors-25-01019"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Anandan</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>George</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>A Wide-Range Capacitive Sensor for Linear and Angular Displacement Measurement</article-title><source>IEEE Trans. Ind. Electron.</source><year>2017</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>5728</fpage><lpage>5737</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/TIE.2017.2677308</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19-sensors-25-01019"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>A novel magnetic circuit and structure for magnetic levitation ruler</article-title><source>Meas. Control</source><year>2023</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>1545</fpage><lpage>1561</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/00202940231169528</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20-sensors-25-01019"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>J.-H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>R.-J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>C.J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Position Control of Electro-mechanical Fin Actuator using Linear Type Hall-effect Sensor BLDC Motor with Magnetic Flux Shielding Wall</article-title><source>Trans. Korean Inst. Electr. Eng.</source><year>2021</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>380</fpage><lpage>386</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5370/KIEE.2020.70.2.380</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21-sensors-25-01019"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Sensor Position Errors Estimating for Moving Sensors by Using Calibration Emitters</article-title><source>Proceedings of the 2017 2nd International Conference on Control, Automation and Artificial Intelligence (CAAI 2017)</source><conf-loc>Sanya, China</conf-loc><conf-date>25&#x02013;26 June 2017</conf-date></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22-sensors-25-01019"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>De Freitas</surname><given-names>S.C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>J.Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eames</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Freitas</surname><given-names>P.P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kazakova</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>C.W.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>Magnetoresistive Sensor Development Roadmap (Non-Recording Applications)</article-title><source>IEEE Trans. Magn.</source><year>2019</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/TMAG.2019.2896036</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23-sensors-25-01019"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>William</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>On the electro-dynamic qualities of metals: Effect of magnetization on the electric conductivity of nickel and iron</article-title><source>Proc. R. Soc. Lond.</source><year>1857</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>546</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24-sensors-25-01019"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Velev</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sabirianov</surname><given-names>R.F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jaswal</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tsymbal</surname><given-names>E.Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Ballistic Anisotropic Magnetoresistance</article-title><source>Phys. Rev. Lett.</source><year>2005</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>127203</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevLett.94.127203</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15903955</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B25-sensors-25-01019"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Baibich</surname><given-names>M.N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Broto</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fert</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Van Dau</surname><given-names>F.N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Petroff</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Etienne</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Creuzet</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Friederich</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chazelas</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Giant magnetoresistance of (001) Fe/(001) Cr magnetic superlattices</article-title><source>Phys. Rev. Lett.</source><year>1988</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>2472</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevLett.61.2472</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10039127</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B26-sensors-25-01019"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Miyazaki</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tezuka</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Giant magnetic tunneling effect in Fe/Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>/Fe junction</article-title><source>J. Magn. Magn. Mater.</source><year>1995</year><volume>139</volume><fpage>L231</fpage><lpage>L234</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0304-8853(95)90001-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B27-sensors-25-01019"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maekawa</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Theory of tunneling magnetoresistance in granular magnetic films</article-title><source>Phys. Rev. B</source><year>1996</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>R11927</fpage><lpage>R11929</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevB.53.R11927</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9982889</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B28-sensors-25-01019"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Panina</surname><given-names>L.V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mohri</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Magneto-impedance effect in amorphous wires</article-title><source>Appl. Phys. Lett.</source><year>1994</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>1189</fpage><lpage>1191</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.112104</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B29-sensors-25-01019"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Beach</surname><given-names>R.S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Berkowitz</surname><given-names>A.E.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Giant magnetic field dependent impedance of amorphous FeCoSiB wire</article-title><source>Appl. Phys. Lett.</source><year>1994</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>3652</fpage><lpage>3654</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.111170</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B30-sensors-25-01019"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a-Arribas</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shcherbinin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lepalovskij</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Collantes</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kurlyandskaya</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Broadband ferromagnetic resonance measurements in thin-film structures for magnetoimpedance sensors</article-title><source>Measurement</source><year>2018</year><volume>126</volume><fpage>215</fpage><lpage>222</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.measurement.2018.05.070</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B31-sensors-25-01019"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Correa</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bohn</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chesman</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Da Silva</surname><given-names>R.B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Viegas</surname><given-names>A.D.C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sommer</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Tailoring the magnetoimpedance effect of NiFe/Ag multilayer</article-title><source>J. Phys. D Appl. Phys.</source><year>2010</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>295004</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/0022-3727/43/29/295004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B32-sensors-25-01019"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kurlyandskaya</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barandiaran</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>V&#x000e1;zquez</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guti&#x000e9;rrez</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vas&#x02019;kovskiy</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lepalovskij</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The magnetoresistance contribution to the total magnetoimpedance of thin films: A simple model and experimental basis</article-title><source>J. Magn. Magn. Mater.</source><year>2000</year><volume>215&#x02013;216</volume><fpage>516</fpage><lpage>518</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0304-8853(00)00206-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B33-sensors-25-01019"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kondo</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Anomalous Hall Effect and Magnetoresistance of Ferromagnetic Metals</article-title><source>Prog. Theor. Phys.</source><year>1962</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>772</fpage><lpage>792</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1143/PTP.27.772</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B34-sensors-25-01019"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ritzinger</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>V&#x000fd;born&#x000fd;</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Anisotropic magnetoresistance: Materials, models and applications</article-title><source>R. Soc. Open Sci.</source><year>2023</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>230564</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsos.230564</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37859834</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B35-sensors-25-01019"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>A Method of Forming Full-Wheatstone Bridge for Linear TMR Magnetic Sensors</article-title><source>Proceedings of the 2021 5th IEEE Electron Devices Technology &#x00026; Manufacturing Conference</source><conf-loc>Chengdu, China</conf-loc><conf-date>8&#x02013;11 April 2021</conf-date></element-citation></ref><ref id="B36-sensors-25-01019"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Angular Position Sensor Based on Anisotropic Magnetoresistive and Anomalous Nernst Effect</article-title><source>Sensors</source><year>2024</year><volume>24</volume><elocation-id>1011</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/s24031011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38339727</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B37-sensors-25-01019"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Magnetic dipole model in the near-field</article-title><source>Proceedings of the 2015 IEEE International Conference on Information and Automation</source><conf-loc>Lijiang, China</conf-loc><conf-date>8&#x02013;10 August 2015</conf-date><fpage>1085</fpage><lpage>1089</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B38-sensors-25-01019"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kakarakis</surname><given-names>S.D.J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Spantideas</surname><given-names>S.T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kapsalis</surname><given-names>N.C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Capsalis</surname><given-names>C.N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Junge</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>A Software-Based Calibration Technique for Characterizing the Magnetic Signature of EUTs in Measuring Facilities</article-title><source>IEEE Trans. Electromagn. Compat.</source><year>2017</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>334</fpage><lpage>341</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/TEMC.2016.2615132</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B39-sensors-25-01019"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Motor Dynamic Loading and Comprehensive Test System Based on FPGA and MCU</article-title><source>Electronics</source><year>2022</year><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>1317</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/electronics11091317</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B40-sensors-25-01019"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X.G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C.J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Design and Implementation of LED Display Screen Controller Based on STM32 and FPGA</article-title><source>Appl. Mech. Mater.</source><year>2013</year><volume>268&#x02013;270</volume><fpage>1578</fpage><lpage>1582</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4028/www.scientific.net/AMM.268-270.1578</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B41-sensors-25-01019"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nan</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Design of Monitoring System Based on Indirect Furnace Gas Timber Drying Plant</article-title><source>Proceedings of the 2016 International Conference on Material, Energy and Environment Engineering (ICM3E 2016)</source><conf-loc>Guangzhou, China</conf-loc><conf-date>30&#x02013;31 January 2016</conf-date><fpage>343</fpage><lpage>348</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B42-sensors-25-01019"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The Host Computer Control Software Development on Test Rig of Railcar Power Wheelset</article-title><source>Proceedings of the 2012 International Conference on Financial, Management and Education Science</source><conf-loc>Beijing, China</conf-loc><conf-date>19&#x02013;20 May 2012</conf-date><fpage>272</fpage><lpage>276</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B43-sensors-25-01019"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Korpe</surname><given-names>U.U.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gokdag</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Koc</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gulbudak</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Modulated Model Predictive Control of Permanent Magnet Synchronous Motors with Im-proved Steady-State Performance</article-title><source>Proceedings of the 2021 IEEE 3rd Global Power, Energy and Communication Conference (IEEE Gpecom2021)</source><conf-loc>Antalya, Turkey</conf-loc><conf-date>5&#x02013;8 October 2021</conf-date><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>72</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B44-sensors-25-01019"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Design and Research on High Power Density Motor of Integrated Motor Drive System for Electric Vehicles</article-title><source>Energies</source><year>2022</year><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>3542</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/en15103542</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B45-sensors-25-01019"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>A Novel Variable-Proportion Desaturation PI Control for Speed Regulation in Sensor less PMSM Drive System</article-title><source>Appl. Sci.</source><year>2022</year><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>9234</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/app12189234</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B46-sensors-25-01019"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hidalgo</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>V&#x000e1;zquez</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Orosco</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hernandez</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>L&#x000f3;pez</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huerta</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pinto</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Robust Modulated Model Predictive Control for a PMSM Using Sliding Mode Cost Function</article-title><source>Proceedings of the IECON 2023&#x02014;49th Annual Conference of the IEEE Industrial Electronics Society</source><conf-loc>Singapore</conf-loc><conf-date>16&#x02013;19 October 2023</conf-date><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>6</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig position="float" id="sensors-25-01019-f001"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Schematic diagram of anisotropic magnetoresistance (AMR).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sensors-25-01019-g001" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="sensors-25-01019-f002"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Schematic diagram of giant magnetoresistance (GMR).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sensors-25-01019-g002" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="sensors-25-01019-f003"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Schematic diagram of tunneling magnetoresistance (TMR).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sensors-25-01019-g003" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="sensors-25-01019-f004"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Overall block diagram of the position detection system program.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sensors-25-01019-g004" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="sensors-25-01019-f005"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>A single sensor, the equivalent of two Wheatstone bridges.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sensors-25-01019-g005" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="sensors-25-01019-f006"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Schematic diagram of clamping resistor.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sensors-25-01019-g006" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="sensors-25-01019-f008"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Simulation of magnetic induction vector in the XY plane.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sensors-25-01019-g008" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="sensors-25-01019-f009"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p>Schematic of the magnetic induction vector of the line where the XY plane sensor is located.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sensors-25-01019-g009" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="sensors-25-01019-f010"><label>Figure 10</label><caption><p>The magnetoresistive sensor output waveform in case 1.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sensors-25-01019-g010" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="sensors-25-01019-f011"><label>Figure 11</label><caption><p>Schematic diagram of the spatial position of the sensor in relation to the permanent magnet in case 2.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sensors-25-01019-g011" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="sensors-25-01019-f012"><label>Figure 12</label><caption><p>The magnetoresistive sensor output waveform in case 2.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sensors-25-01019-g012" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="sensors-25-01019-f013"><label>Figure 13</label><caption><p>Four consecutive TLE5501 sensor sin output waveforms.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sensors-25-01019-g013" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="sensors-25-01019-f014"><label>Figure 14</label><caption><p>Schematic diagram of the definitions of the distances Y and Z.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sensors-25-01019-g014" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="sensors-25-01019-f015"><label>Figure 15</label><caption><p>Output waveforms of the TLE5501 corresponding to different Y distances: (<bold>a</bold>) Output waveforms of sin. (<bold>b</bold>) Output waveforms of cos.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sensors-25-01019-g015" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="sensors-25-01019-f016"><label>Figure 16</label><caption><p>Output waveforms of TLE5501 corresponding to different Z distances: (<bold>a</bold>) Output waveforms of sin. (<bold>b</bold>) Output waveforms of cos.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sensors-25-01019-g016" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="sensors-25-01019-f017"><label>Figure 17</label><caption><p>Schematic diagram of the TLE5501 detecting linear position.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sensors-25-01019-g017" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="sensors-25-01019-f018"><label>Figure 18</label><caption><p>Physical diagram of the test system.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sensors-25-01019-g018" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="sensors-25-01019-f019"><label>Figure 19</label><caption><p>Actual sensor output voltage waveform.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sensors-25-01019-g019" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="sensors-25-01019-f020"><label>Figure 20</label><caption><p>Comparison of sin signal normalization.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sensors-25-01019-g020" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="sensors-25-01019-f021"><label>Figure 21</label><caption><p>Comparison of cos signal normalization.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sensors-25-01019-g021" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="sensors-25-01019-f022"><label>Figure 22</label><caption><p>Repeatability detection error curve.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sensors-25-01019-g022" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="sensors-25-01019-f023"><label>Figure 23</label><caption><p>Dynamic error test result graph.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sensors-25-01019-g023" position="float"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="sensors-25-01019-t001"><object-id pub-id-type="pii">sensors-25-01019-t001_Table 1</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>The comparison of magnetic sensors.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TMR</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AMR</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GMR</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GMI</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Angle range (deg)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0~360</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;90~+90</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0~360</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0~360</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Energy consumption (mA)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.67</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.5</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Working temperature (&#x000b0;C)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;40~125</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;40~125</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;40~125</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;20~85</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cost</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Voltage sensitivity (mV/V)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">320</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">240</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Magnetic-field range (mT)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="sensors-25-01019-t002"><object-id pub-id-type="pii">sensors-25-01019-t002_Table 2</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>The output of each sensor.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sensor 1 Detection Interval</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sensor 2 Detection Interval</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sensor 3 Detection Interval</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sensor 1sin output</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sensor 2sin output</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sensor 3sin output</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sensor 4sin output</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="sensors-25-01019-t003"><object-id pub-id-type="pii">sensors-25-01019-t003_Table 3</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Parameters of NdFeB permanent magnets.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Magnet Name</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameters</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Numerical Value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="6" align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1">NdFeB permanent magnets</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Residual magnetism</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.2&#x02013;14.8 KGs</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coercive force</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;835 KA/m</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intrinsic coercive force</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;876 KA/m</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximum magnetic energy product</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">390&#x02013;422 KJ/m<sup>3</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Magnetization direction</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thickness direction</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length &#x000d7; Width &#x000d7; Height</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.3 &#x000d7; 12.7 &#x000d7; 6.35 mm<sup>3</sup></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="sensors-25-01019-t004"><object-id pub-id-type="pii">sensors-25-01019-t004_Table 4</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>The magnetic field strength at the location of the sensor when the sensor and the permanent magnet are positioned in different spatial locations.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Z = 12 (mm)</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Z = 10 (mm)</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Z = 8 (mm)</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Z = 6 (mm)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y = 14 (mm)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.8~28.5 (mT)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.8~33.4 (mT)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.1~37.2 (mT)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.8~44.2 (mT)</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y = 12 (mm)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.2~32.3 (mT)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.4~44.4 (mT)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.2~56.4 (mT)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.4~71.5 (mT)</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y = 10 (mm)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.6~41.2 (mT)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.3~54.2 (mT)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.1~80.6 (mT)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.8~96.5 (mT)</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y = 8 (mm)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.6~53.4 (mT)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.2~76.3 (mT)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.4~96.4 (mT)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.5~130.6 (mT)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></floats-group></article>