<!--

File produced by pipelineRunner package (for JATS 2 SCJATS with pipeline SCJATS)
At: 2025-05-22T15:12:31.197Z

Version        : 1.16.1
Last update    : 2024-08-27
Modified by    : dunnm

-->
<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Database (Oxford)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Database (Oxford)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">databa</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Database: The Journal of Biological Databases and Curation</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1758-0463</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>UK</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39797570</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11724190</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/database/baae122</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">baae122</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection"><subject>AcademicSubjects/SCI00960</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>DisGeNet: a disease-centric interaction database among diseases and various associated genes</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0009-0009-5372-6191</contrib-id><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Yaxuan</given-names></name><aff>
<institution content-type="department">School of Computer Science and Technology, Xidian University</institution>, 266 Xinglong Section of Xifeng Road, Xi&#x02019;an, Shaanxi 710126, <country country="CN">China</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1199-7120</contrib-id><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Xingli</given-names></name><!--xlguo@mail.xidian.edu.cn--><aff>
<institution content-type="department">School of Computer Science and Technology, Xidian University</institution>, 266 Xinglong Section of Xifeng Road, Xi&#x02019;an, Shaanxi 710126, <country country="CN">China</country></aff><xref rid="COR0001" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>Yao</given-names></name><aff>
<institution content-type="department">School of Computer Science and Technology, Xidian University</institution>, 266 Xinglong Section of Xifeng Road, Xi&#x02019;an, Shaanxi 710126, <country country="CN">China</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Liang</given-names></name><aff>
<institution content-type="department">School of Computer Science and Technology, Xidian University</institution>, 266 Xinglong Section of Xifeng Road, Xi&#x02019;an, Shaanxi 710126, <country country="CN">China</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Xiaotai</given-names></name><aff>
<institution content-type="department">School of Computer Science and Technology, Xidian University</institution>, 266 Xinglong Section of Xifeng Road, Xi&#x02019;an, Shaanxi 710126, <country country="CN">China</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>Songwei</given-names></name><aff>
<institution content-type="department">School of Computer Science and Technology, Xidian University</institution>, 266 Xinglong Section of Xifeng Road, Xi&#x02019;an, Shaanxi 710126, <country country="CN">China</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="COR0001">*Corresponding author. School of Computer Science and Technology, Xidian University, 266 Xinglong Section of Xifeng Road, Xi&#x02019;an, Shaanxi 710126, China. E-mail: <email xlink:href="xlguo@mail.xidian.edu.cn">xlguo@mail.xidian.edu.cn</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2025-01-11"><day>11</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>11</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>2025</volume><elocation-id>baae122</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>5</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>31</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="editorial-decision"><day>19</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="corrected-typeset"><day>11</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2025. Published by Oxford University Press.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="baae122.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><p>The pathogenesis of complex diseases is intricately linked to various genes and network medicine has enhanced understanding of diseases. However, most network-based approaches ignore interactions mediated by noncoding RNAs (ncRNAs) and most databases only focus on the association between genes and diseases. Based on the mentioned questions, we have developed DisGeNet, a database focuses not only on the disease-associated genes but also on the interactions among genes. Here, the associations between diseases and various genes, as well as the interactions among these genes are integrated into a disease-centric network. As a result, there are a total of 502&#x02009;688 interactions/associations involving 6697 diseases, 5780 lncRNAs (long noncoding RNAs), 16&#x02009;135 protein-coding genes, and 2610 microRNAs stored in DisGeNet. These interactions/associations can be categorized as protein&#x02013;protein, lncRNA&#x02013;disease, microRNA&#x02013;gene, microRNA&#x02013;disease, gene&#x02013;disease, and microRNA&#x02013;lncRNA. Furthermore, as users input name/ID of diseases/genes for search, the interactions/associations about the search content can be browsed as a list or viewed in a local network-view.</p><p>
<bold>Database URL</bold>: <ext-link xlink:href="https://disgenet.cn/" ext-link-type="uri">https://disgenet.cn/</ext-link></p></abstract><funding-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>National Natural Science Foundation of China</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/501100001809</institution-id></institution-wrap>
</funding-source><award-id>61672407 62372349</award-id></award-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>Natural Science Foundation Youth Project of Shaanxi Province</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source><award-id>2019JQ-495</award-id></award-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>Fundamental Research Funds for the Central Universities</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/501100012226</institution-id></institution-wrap>
</funding-source><award-id>ZYTS23197 ZYTS23208</award-id></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>National Natural Science Foundation of China</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/501100001809</institution-id></institution-wrap>
</funding-source><award-id>61672407 62372349</award-id></award-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>Natural Science Foundation Youth Project of Shaanxi Province</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source><award-id>2019JQ-495</award-id></award-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>Fundamental Research Funds for the Central Universities</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/501100012226</institution-id></institution-wrap>
</funding-source><award-id>ZYTS23197 ZYTS23208</award-id></award-group></funding-group><counts><page-count count="8"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Complex diseases typically result from the combined effects of multiple genes and various environmental factors [<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. The onset and progression of these diseases can vary significantly between individuals. For example, the rate at which a patient&#x02019;s condition progresses can differ greatly. In addition, the prevalence of certain complex diseases is influenced by factors such as gender, with autoimmune diseases showing a much greater prevalence on women [<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Therefore, studying complex diseases solely from a single-factor perspective may not provide a comprehensive understanding of their complexity. As regards to the disease-associated genes, not only protein-coding genes but also noncoding genes along with the interactions among them can give a more thorough perspective on complex diseases. In recent years, with the development of network medicine, it has offered quantitative insights into disease mechanisms, comorbidities, as well as novel diagnostic tools and treatment methods [<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>].</p><p>From the perspective of network medicine, most studies of diseases rely on a comprehensive map of protein&#x02013;protein interactions (PPIs). For example, IQSEC2 is a protein associated with neurons, and its interaction with the guanine nucleotide-binding (GTP-binding) protein ARF6 may play a crucial role in conditions such as autism and intellectual disabilities [<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. However, the onset and development of diseases are influenced by interactions among various genes. There is overwhelming evidence that ncRNAs regulate multiple biological processes, playing important roles in multiple diseases. For example, lncRNA&#x02013;microRNA regulates cell death mechanisms such as apoptosis and autophagy in cancers [<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Besides, the study in [<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] suggests that <italic toggle="yes">miR-122a</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">miR-422a</italic> may destabilize <italic toggle="yes">CYP7A1</italic> mRNA to inhibit <italic toggle="yes">CYP7A1</italic> expression which plays a critical role in regulation of bile acid synthesis in the liver. Therefore, to enhance the understanding of disease mechanisms in network medicine, interactions mediated by ncRNAs must be incorporated into the framework of network medicine.</p><p>As a disease-centric view, the various genes (such as protein-coding genes, lncRNAs, and microRNAs) play a crucial regulatory role in the occurrence and development of complex diseases. Several databases are devoted to categorize these associations, such as the associations between diseases and protein-coding genes, the associations between diseases and microRNAs, also the associations between the diseases and lncRNAs. The current version of Online Mendelian Inheritance in Man (OMIM) [<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] contains 27&#x02009;140 entries and the OMIM Morbid Map Scorecard contains 7439 molecularized phenotypes connected to 4852 genes. Additionally, LncRNADisease [<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] comprises 25&#x02009;440 ncRNA&#x02013;disease associations across 6066 lncRNAs, 10&#x02009;732 circRNAs, and 566 different diseases. Among these, there are 13&#x02009;191 experimentally supported lncRNA&#x02013;disease associations. Moreover, Human MicroRNA Disease Database (HMDD) [<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] curates 53&#x02009;530 microRNA&#x02013;disease association entries, which include 1817 human microRNA genes, 79 virus-derived microRNAs, and 2360 diseases from 37&#x02009;090 papers. However, disease is associated with various genes, yet these databases only focus on the associations between specific genes and genes, without integrating connections between multiple genes and diseases.</p><p>Taken together, in order to achieve a more comprehensive understanding of diseases, we have developed a comprehensive database called DisGeNet, which incorporates interactions mediated by ncRNAs and captures a diverse array of links among the diseases and their associated genes, visually depicting the intricate associations between diseases and genes, as well as the interactions among distinct genes in a network perspective. As shown in <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;1A</xref>, the basic information in the network, including four types of nodes and six types of links, is displayed.</p><fig position="float" id="F1" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure&#x000a0;1.</label><caption><p>The statistics of DisGeNet: (a) six types of links network, (b) four types of nodes, (c) statistics of links, and (d) the top 50 diseases associated with genes.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="baae122f1" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="s2-s1"><title>Data resources</title><p>DisGeNet curates widely recognized data sources that align with its disease-centric theme, focusing on association of genes with diseases, as well as the interactions among these related genes.</p><p>When it comes to disease data, MONDO [<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] provides a comprehensive disease ontology that integrates multiple disease-data sources, offering detailed disease classification suitable for cross-database comparison and analysis. Disease Ontology (DO) [<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] delivers standardized disease classification and disease&#x02013;gene association data. Medical Subject Headings (MeSH) [<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], maintained by the US National Library of Medicine, supports biomedical literature indexing with its controlled vocabulary. While OMIM [<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] focuses on human genes and genetic disorders, providing extensive information on genes and their associated diseases.</p><p>For protein-coding gene and lncRNA data, HUGO Gene Nomenclature Committee (HGNC) [<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] supplies standardized nomenclature for human genes, ensuring consistency and traceability. The reference gene annotation for human and mouse (GENCODE) [<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] provides accurate gene feature identification and classification in human and mouse genomes, and NCBI Gene [<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] includes data across species, covering nomenclature, reference sequences, and phenotypes. Additionally, comprehensive data on both protein-coding gene and lncRNA are provided by these databases.</p><p>With regard to microRNA data, miRBase [<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] encompasses extensive coverage, including microRNA sequences, structural predictions, genomic locations, and expression data across various species.</p><p>Furthermore, concerning lncRNA&#x02013;disease associations, Lnc2Cancer [<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] offers information on lncRNA&#x02013;circRNA associations with human cancers, supported by experimental evidence. RNADisease [<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] covers both literature-validated and predicted RNA&#x02013;disease interactions. LncRNADisease [<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] integrates comprehensive data from manual literature curation and other sources, providing a solid basis for research into lncRNA&#x02013;disease associations. For microRNA&#x02013;disease associations, HMDD [<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] provides its collection of experimentally supported microRNA&#x02013;disease associations, making it a valuable reference for researchers in the field. Regarding protein-coding gene&#x02013;disease associations, OMIM [<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] provides its expert-reviewed content, offering extensive information on gene&#x02013;disease associations with detailed descriptions of monogenic genetic disorders, including pathological mechanisms, inheritance patterns, and clinical features.</p><p>As for microRNA&#x02013;protein-coding gene interactions, miRTarBase [<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] encompasses over 360&#x02009;000 miRNA&#x02013;protein-coding gene interactions, curated through a combination of manual review and automated processes to ensure the inclusion of the latest research. Besides, STRING [<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] offers rigorously validated and scored data on PPIs, derived from multiple high-quality studies, encompassing both known and predicted interactions, including direct (physical) and indirect (functional) interactions. Lastly, ENCORI [<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] is an advanced platform for microRNA&#x02013;lncRNA interactions, providing an integrative display of RNA&#x02013;RNA and protein&#x02013;RNA interactions. It utilizes sophisticated software and pipelines to analyze high-throughput sequencing data, presenting interaction data and detailed functional annotations. A comprehensive review of the databases providing the aforementioned data types is detailed in the <xref rid="s5" ref-type="sec">Supplementary Table S1</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s2-s2"><title>Nodes in DisGeNet</title><p>As for diseases, 23&#x02009;234 entries from MONDO (as of 4 July 2024) [<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], 14&#x02009;082 entries from DO (as of 4 July 2024) [<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], 30&#x02009;724 Main Heading Terms and 323&#x02009;744 <xref rid="s5" ref-type="sec">Supplementary</xref> Concept Record Terms from MeSH (as of 4 July 2024) [<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], and 26&#x02009;820 entries from OMIM (as of 30 July 2020) [<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] are extracted with key information such as IDs, names, and synonyms. Because MeSH is primarily focused on medical subject terms found in MEDLINE/PubMed, NLM catalogs and other NLM databases, it is suitable for medical subject retrieval [<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. OMIM specializes in the molecular relationships between genetic variations and phenotypic expressions, providing detailed information on genetic diseases and associated genes [<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. There is some overlap between DO and MeSH or OMIM, and conflicts may arise in mapping. However, MONDO provides a logic-based framework for integrating multiple disease resources, allowing it to retain a broader range of disease entries [<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Therefore, MONDO is selected as the primary reference data source, and information from other sources is used to supplement it, ultimately resulting in 23&#x02009;234 disease entries with detailed information.</p><p>Concerning protein-coding genes and lncRNAs, 16&#x02009;260 entries for protein-coding genes and 5765 entries for lncRNAs in HGNC (as of 4 July 2024) [<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] are downloaded. Besides, annotation files are first downloaded from GENCODE46 [<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], from which key information such as various IDs names, gene types, and transcript IDs are extracted. Subsequently, genes with the same gene ID are merged and duplicates are removed, resulting in 20&#x02009;065 protein-coding gene entries and 19&#x02009;258 lncRNA entries. After filtering human data, 20&#x02009;688 protein-coding gene entries and 20&#x02009;188 lncRNA entries are extracted from NCBI Gene (as of 4 July 2024) [<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Finally, the data from the three sources are merged using outer joins, missing values are filled with nulls, and gene type and synonyms information are deleted, resulting in a final dataset of 21&#x02009;291 protein-coding gene entries and 32&#x02009;839 lncRNA entries.</p><p>With regard to microRNAs, there is a category of 38&#x02009;589 microRNA entries in miRBase22.1 [<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. We focus on human microRNAs; meticulous curation and filling in missing IDs with aliases are explored, leading to a final set of 2727 mature microRNA entries. Details are illustrated in <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;2A</xref>.</p><fig position="float" id="F2" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure&#x000a0;2.</label><caption><p>The data collection process of DisGeNet: (a) the collection of node information and (b) the collection of link information.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="baae122f2" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2-s3"><title>Links in DisGeNet</title><p>As for lncRNA&#x02013;disease associations, 6263 entries from Lnc2Cancer3.0 [<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], 26&#x02009;564 entries from RNADisease4.0 [<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], and 7293 entries from LncRNADisease3.0 [<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] are extracted by filtering for human data and mapping against the previously obtained lncRNA and disease datasets. Subsequently, merging using outer join, filling missing values with nulls and removing duplicate rows are performed on these associations, resulting in a standardized dataset comprising 20&#x02009;147 lncRNA&#x02013;disease associations.</p><p>Concerning microRNA&#x02013;disease associations, there is a category of 40&#x02009;607 entries in HMDD4.0 [<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. We focus on the obtained datasets of diseases and microRNAs, and the mapping results are retained with relevant information filled in. Finally, a set of 21&#x02009;706 microRNA&#x02013;disease associations in human are curated in DisGeNet.</p><p>With regard to protein-coding gene&#x02013;disease associations, 6235 entries from OMIM [<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] are downloaded as of 30 July 2020. These entries are then matched based on the previously obtained protein-coding gene and disease datasets. After data organization and removal of duplicate entries are performed, a total of 5959 protein-coding gene&#x02013;disease associations are provided in DisGeNet.</p><p>As for PPI data, 131&#x02009;289 human-related PPIs are downloaded from STRING12.0 [<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] and mapped against the obtained protein-coding gene file, with the mapping results retained and relevant information filled in, resulting in 64&#x02009;711 PPIs.</p><p>Similarly, a total of 374&#x02009;553 microRNA&#x02013;protein-coding gene interactions and 15&#x02009;612 microRNA&#x02013;lncRNA interactions are obtained by separately downloading 920&#x02009;253 interactions and 30&#x02009;847 interactions from miRTarBase9.0 [<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] and ENCORI [<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], and mapping them against the previously obtained microRNA and protein-coding gene datasets, as well as microRNA and lncRNA datasets. Details are illustrated in <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;3B</xref>.</p><fig position="float" id="F3" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure&#x000a0;3.</label><caption><p>Statistical comparison of data in DisGeNet: (a) node data and (b) link data.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="baae122f3" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2-s4"><title>Data integration</title><p>Based on the processed link data, filtering of node information with associated links and merging of duplicates with matching primary identifiers are performed (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;2A</xref>), resulting in 5780 lncRNA entries, 16&#x02009;135 protein-coding gene entries, 2610 microRNA entries, and 6697 disease entries.</p><p>After all these preprocessing, as shown in <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;1B and C</xref>, 6697 disease nodes, 5780 lncRNA nodes, 16&#x02009;135 gene nodes, and 2610 microRNA nodes are provided in DisGeNet, and the detailed information for these nodes are curated carefully in our database, which is shown in <xref rid="s5" ref-type="sec">Supplementary Table S2</xref>. Besides, the 502&#x02009;688 links encompass 20&#x02009;147 lncRNA&#x02013;disease associations, 21&#x02009;706 microRNA&#x02013;disease associations, 5959 protein-coding gene&#x02013;disease associations, 374&#x02009;553 microRNA&#x02013;protein-coding gene targeting interactions, 15&#x02009;612 microRNA&#x02013;lncRNA targeting interactions, and 64&#x02009;711 PPIs. Among them, there are 379&#x02009;189 overlapping data between gene&#x02013;gene interactions and Barab&#x000e1;si Laboratory&#x02019;s research on network medicine [<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. The information of the links in our database is described in <xref rid="s5" ref-type="sec">Supplementary Table S3</xref>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec id="s3-s1"><title>Technical implementation of DisGeNet</title><p>DisGeNet is developed with HTML and Python language using MySQL (<ext-link xlink:href="http://www.mysql.com/" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.mysql.com/</ext-link>) as the database management system. The web interface is developed based on the Bootstrap (<ext-link xlink:href="http://www.getbootstrap.com/3.3.4/" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.getbootstrap.com/3.3.4/</ext-link>) framework and JavaScript. To support the growing user base, we optimize the database querying algorithms and implement partitioning and indexing techniques to enhance query efficiency and response times. Additionally, stress testing is conducted to ensure the DisGeNet&#x02019;s stability and performance under high concurrency conditions.</p></sec><sec id="s3-s2"><title>Comparative analysis and predictions of data</title><p>As illustrated in <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>, we have conducted a comparative analysis of node and edge data statistics from DisGeNet and other databases. While the amount of data in DisGeNet may be relatively smaller compared to other databases, this is due to DisGeNet&#x02019;s rigorous selection of data on disease-associated genes and interactions among these genes, ensuring the reliability and usability of the information. This comprehensive coverage highlights DisGeNet&#x02019;s advantage in integrating data across multiple biological categories.</p><p>Additionally, data from DisGeNet is utilized to predict potential genes associated with diseases, particularly ncRNAs, allowing for a deeper understanding and analysis of disease mechanisms from a disease-centric perspective. First, the disease node is focused on, and subgraph data related to its associated genes are downloaded. Subsequently, multiple subgraph datasets for each related gene are downloaded, representing their links with other diseases/genes. By merging these subgraph datasets and performing link prediction, potential associations between the disease and genes not yet included in the DisGeNet database are validated through literatures. Using non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) as an example of a high-degree disease node, potential links between NSCLC and genes such as <italic toggle="yes">KRAS</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">LINC00963</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">MIR17HG</italic> are discovered. Among them, <italic toggle="yes">LINC00963</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">MIR17HG</italic> are lncRNAs, and the significant roles of these genes in the onset and progression of NSCLC have been substantiated by previous studies, including those by Principe et&#x000a0;al. [<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], Xie et&#x000a0;al. [<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], and Zheng et&#x000a0;al. [<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Similarly, for a disease node with a lower degree, such as kidney cancer, potential association with the lncRNA <italic toggle="yes">NEAT1</italic> is identified. Research conducted by Liu [<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] has demonstrated that <italic toggle="yes">NEAT1</italic> promotes the proliferation and migration of kidney cancer cells. These findings further confirm the reliability and usability of DisGeNet. The detailed information of these predicted links is presented in <xref rid="s5" ref-type="sec">Supplementary Table S4</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s3-s3"><title>Web interface</title><p>The &#x0201c;Search&#x0201d; page provides &#x0201c;keyword search&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;fuzzy search&#x0201d; (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;4A</xref>). In keyword search page, users can search by name/ID of gene/disease such as MONDO_ID of disease, miRBase_ID of microRNA and HGNC_ID, Ensembl_ID or NCBI GeneID of lncRNA, and protein-coding gene (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;5A</xref>). In fuzzy search, the search results will be limited to displaying only the top 20 results that are most relevant or similar. Additionally, in each search result, the parts that are similar to the search query will be highlighted, facilitating users to locate the target search content (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;5B</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F4" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure&#x000a0;4.</label><caption><p>Interface of DisGeNet: (a) search for all associations and interactions, and (b) browse all associations and interactions.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="baae122f4" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F5" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure&#x000a0;5.</label><caption><p>A general use process of DisGeNet: (a) the interface of the search module with &#x0201c;AIDS&#x0201d; input as the retrieved disease in the &#x0201c;Search&#x0201d; page (disease name used as an example), (b) fuzzy search result page of &#x0201c;AIDS&#x0201d;, (c) filtering links by node types, (d) the search results shown in a list manner, and (e) the search results shown in a graph manner.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="baae122f5" position="float"/></fig><p>With regard to the search results, the links among the genes, input disease or gene and the associated other diseases can be browsed in a manner of &#x0201c;List&#x0201d; or &#x0201c;Graph,&#x0201d; as shown in <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;4B</xref>. In the list manner, users can filter the given links by node type to obtain the specified retrieval (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;5C</xref>). Furthermore, detailed information about the links, such as node symbols, node types, experimental methods used, interaction patterns, the PubMed ID (PMID) of reference articles, and the source database is provided in the list. Users also can download the association subgraph centered on a specific disease or gene by clicking the &#x0201c;Download&#x0201d; button (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;5D</xref>). In the graph manner, statistics for nodes and links, as well as detailed information about the induced subnetwork, are visualized in a graph view. In addition, users can click on node types to hide the corresponding type of links in &#x0201c;Subnetwork Graph.&#x0201d; Finally, when users move the mouse cursor in &#x0201c;Node Statistics Bar Chart,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;Link Statistics Pie Chart,&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;Subnetwork Graph,&#x0201d; they can highlight specific data and access its detailed information (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;5E</xref>). The detailed search example of DisGeNet is illustrated in the <xref rid="s5" ref-type="sec">Supplementary Data</xref>.</p><p>On the &#x0201c;Download &#x00026; API&#x0201d; page, users can access both current and historical database data, as well as efficiently retrieve and query biological data via the API interface. The API allows users not only to access all node and edge information but also to perform parameterized queries to precisely download node and edge data related to specific diseases or genes (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;6A</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F6" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure&#x000a0;6.</label><caption><p>Other functions in DisGeNet: (a) get data via &#x0201c;Download&#x0201d; or &#x0201c;API,&#x0201d; (b) discussion and feedback in DisGeNet, (c) data statistics in DisGeNet, and (d) learn more about DisGeNet through the &#x0201c;Help&#x0201d; interface.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="baae122f6" position="float"/></fig><p>From the &#x0201c;Community&#x0201d; page, users are able to submit feedback via email, submit comments or suggestions, and participate in discussions (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;6B</xref>). The &#x0201c;Statistics&#x0201d; page, the data statistics for each type and a comparison of the data before and after updates of DisGeNet are presented in the form of charts (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;6C</xref>). For additional information and further instructions, users can refer to the &#x0201c;Help&#x0201d; page (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;6D</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Discussion and future extensions</title><p>An increasing body of evidence indicates that the association between diseases and genes, as well as the interactions among these associated genes, plays a crucial role in understanding diseases. Moreover, by including ncRNAs into the PPIs, it is possible to retrieve more complete and biologically more meaningful list of disease&#x02013;disease interactions, offering a better quantitative understanding of disease similarity and comorbidity, ultimately helping us understand disease progression in patients. Therefore, DisGeNet, a disease-centric database, integrates ncRNAs into network medicine and encompasses associations between diseases and various types of genes, as well as interactions among different genes.</p><p>To ensure the relevance and accuracy of the information, DisGeNet is updated on an annual basis. This regular update schedule allows us to promptly incorporate changes from source databases and continuously enhance the database&#x02019;s gene prediction capabilities. As research continues to advance, an increasing number of gene types associated with diseases, such as circRNA, piRNA, and eRNA, are being discovered. As more comprehensive data becomes available, we plan to integrate these gene types into our database. Therefore, DisGeNet provides a global network view to understand the mechanisms of complex diseases based on all these links among the associated genes. With accumulating disease&#x02013;gene associations and interactions among various genes, we will have a deeper and more comprehensive understanding of the disease based on all these links. To sum up, DisGeNet is just a pioneering platform in network medicine that will serve as a valuable resource for researchers studying complex diseases.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="sup1" position="float" content-type="local-data"><label>baae122_Supp</label><media xlink:href="baae122_supp.zip"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="ack1"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We would like to thank Liang Lu&#x02019;s early construction of DisGeNet. We thank all those who maintain excellent databases and publicly available data.</p></ack><sec id="s5"><title>Supplementary data</title><p>
<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary data</xref> is available at <italic toggle="yes">Database</italic> online.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s6"><title>Conflict of interest:</title><p>None declared.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Funding</title><p>This work has been supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China [61672407 and 62372349], the Fundamental Research Funds for the Central Universities [ZYTS23208 and ZYTS23197], and the Natural Science Foundation Youth Project of Shaanxi Province [2019JQ-495].</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s8"><title>Data availability</title><p>All data described in this manuscript are available at <ext-link xlink:href="https://disgenet.cn/" ext-link-type="uri">https://disgenet.cn/</ext-link>.</p></sec><ref-list id="ref1"><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Kreitmaier</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Katsoula</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zeggini</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>E</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Insights from multi-omics integration in complex disease primary tissues</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Trends Genet</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2023</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>46</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>58</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tig.2022.08.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36137835</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Pisetsky</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>DS</given-names></string-name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Pathogenesis of autoimmune disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Rev Nephrol</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2023</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>509</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>24</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41581-023-00720-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37165096</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Morselli Gysi</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barab&#x000e1;si</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>AL</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Noncoding RNAs improve the predictive power of network medicine</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2023</year>;<volume>120</volume>:<page-range>e2301342120</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.2301342120</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Mehta</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shirai</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kouyama-Suzuki</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>E</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al.</etal> &#x000a0;<article-title>IQSEC2 deficiency results in abnormal social behaviors relevant to autism by affecting functions of neural circuits in the medial prefrontal cortex</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cells</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2021</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<page-range>2724</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/cells10102724</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Entezari</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Taheriazam</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Orouei</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al.</etal> &#x000a0;<article-title>LncRNA-miRNA axis in tumor progression and therapy response: an emphasis on molecular interactions and therapeutic interventions</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biomed Pharmacother</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2022</year>;<volume>154</volume>:<page-range>113609</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopha.2022.113609</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Song</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>KH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Owsley</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>E</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al.</etal> &#x000a0;<article-title>A putative role of microRNA in regulation of cholesterol 7alpha-hydroxylase expression in human hepatocytes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Lipid Res</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2010</year>;<volume>51</volume>:<fpage>2223</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>33</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1194/jlr.M004531</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20351063</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Amberger</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bocchini</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Scott</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>AF</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al.</etal> &#x000a0;<article-title>OMIM.org: leveraging knowledge across phenotype&#x02013;gene relationships</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nucleic Acids Res</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2019</year>;<volume>47</volume>:<fpage>D1038</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>D1043</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gky1151</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30445645</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Lin</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lu</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>C</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al.</etal> &#x000a0;<article-title>LncRNADisease v3.0: an updated database of long non-coding RNA-associated diseases</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nucleic Acids Res</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2024</year>;<volume>52</volume>:<fpage>D1365</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>D1369</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkad828</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37819033</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Cui</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhong</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fan</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al.</etal> &#x000a0;<article-title>HMDD v4.0: a database for experimentally supported human microRNA-disease associations</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nucleic Acids Res</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2024</year>;<volume>52</volume>:<fpage>D1327</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>D1332</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkad717</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37650649</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Nicole</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>AV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nicolas</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Toro</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al.</etal> &#x000a0;<article-title>Mondo: unifying diseases for the world, by the world</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">medRxiv</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2022</year>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2022.04.13.22273750</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Schriml</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mitraka</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Munro</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al.</etal> &#x000a0;<article-title>Human disease ontology 2018 update: classification, content and workflow expansion</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nucleic Acids Res</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2019</year>;<volume>47</volume>:<fpage>D955</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>D962</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gky1032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30407550</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Baumann</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>
</person-group>. <article-title>How to use the medical subject headings (MeSH)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Clin Pract</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2016</year>;<volume>70</volume>:<fpage>171</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>74</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ijcp.12767</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26763799</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Seal</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Braschi</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gray</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>K</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al.</etal> &#x000a0;<article-title>Genenames.org: the HGNC resources in 2023</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nucleic Acids Res</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2023</year>;<volume>51</volume>:<fpage>D1003</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>D1009</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkac888</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36243972</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Frankish</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carbonell-Sala</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Diekhans</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al.</etal> &#x000a0;<article-title>GENCODE: reference annotation for the human and mouse genomes in 2023</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nucleic Acids Res</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2023</year>;<volume>51</volume>:<fpage>D942</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>D949</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkac1071</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36420896</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Sayers</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>EW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bolton</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>EE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brister</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al.</etal> &#x000a0;<article-title>Database resources of the national center for biotechnology information in 2023</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nucleic Acids Res</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2023</year>;<volume>51</volume>:<fpage>D29</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>D38</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkac1032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36370100</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Kozomara</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Birgaoanu</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Griffiths-Jones</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>miRBase: from microRNA sequences to function</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nucleic Acids Res</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2019</year>;<volume>47</volume>:<fpage>D155</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>D162</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gky1141</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30423142</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Gao</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shang</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guo</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al.</etal> &#x000a0;<article-title>Lnc2Cancer 3.0: an updated resource for experimentally supported lncRNA/circRNA cancer associations and web tools based on RNA-seq and scRNA-seq data</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nucleic Acids Res</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2021</year>;<volume>49</volume>:<fpage>D1251</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>D1258</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkaa1006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33219685</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Chen</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lin</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hu</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al.</etal> &#x000a0;<article-title>RNADisease v4.0: an updated resource of RNA-associated diseases, providing RNA-disease analysis, enrichment&#x000a0;and prediction</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nucleic Acids Res</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2023</year>;<volume>51</volume>:<fpage>D1397</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>D1404</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkac814</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36134718</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Huang</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>HY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lin</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>YC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cui</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>SD</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al.</etal> &#x000a0;<article-title>miRTarBase update 2022: an informative resource for experimentally validated miRNA&#x02013;target interactions</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nucleic Acids Res</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2022</year>;<volume>50</volume>:<fpage>D222</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>D230</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkab1079</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34850920</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Szklarczyk</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kirsch</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Koutrouli</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al.</etal> &#x000a0;<article-title>The STRING database in 2023: protein-protein association networks and functional enrichment analyses for any sequenced genome of interest</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nucleic Acids Res</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2023</year>;<volume>51</volume>:<fpage>D638</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>D646</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkac1000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36370105</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Li</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>H</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al.</etal> &#x000a0;<article-title>starBase v2.0: decoding miRNA-ceRNA, miRNA-ncRNA and protein-RNA interaction networks from large-scale CLIP-Seq data</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nucleic Acids Res</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2014</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>D92</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>D97</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkt1248</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24297251</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Principe</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>DR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pasquinelli</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nguyen</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>RH</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al.</etal> &#x000a0;<article-title>Loss of STK11 suppresses lipid metabolism and attenuates KRAS-induced immunogenicity in patients with non-small cell lung cancer</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cancer Res Commun</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2024</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>2282</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>94</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/2767-9764.CRC-24-0153</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39113608</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Xie</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhong</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shen</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al.</etal> &#x000a0;<article-title>LINC00963: a potential cancer diagnostic and therapeutic target</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biomed Pharmacother</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2022</year>;<volume>150</volume>:<page-range>113019</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopha.2022.113019</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Zheng</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ye</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bai</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al.</etal> &#x000a0;<article-title>Downregulation of lncRNA MIR17HG reduced tumorigenicity and Treg-mediated immune escape of non-small-cell lung cancer cells through targeting the miR-17-5p/RUNX3 axis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Biochem Mol Toxicol</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2024</year>;<volume>38</volume>:<page-range>e23715</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jbt.23715</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Liu</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>ZP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>SY</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et&#x000a0;al.</etal> &#x000a0;<article-title>BAP1-related ceRNA (NEAT1/miR-10a-5p/SERPINE1) promotes proliferation and migration of kidney cancer cells</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Oncol</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2022</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<page-range>852515</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fonc.2022.852515</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>