<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Prim Health Care Res Dev</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Prim Health Care Res Dev</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PHC</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Primary Health Care Research &#x00026; Development</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1463-4236</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1477-1128</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40325868</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12099267</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="pii">S146342362500026X</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S146342362500026X</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Measuring contraceptive self-efficacy in women: the Turkish validity and reliability study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7467-6455</contrib-id><name><surname>Dogan Gangal</surname><given-names>Aliye</given-names></name><xref rid="a1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0841-2099</contrib-id><name><surname>Senturk Erenel</surname><given-names>Ayten</given-names></name><xref rid="a2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="a1">
<label>
1
</label>Faculty of Nursing, Department of Gynaecology and Obstetrics Nursing, <institution>Gazi University</institution>, <city>Ankara</city>, <country>T&#x000fc;rkiye</country>
</aff><aff id="a2">
<label>
2
</label>Faculty of Health Science, Department of Nursing, <institution>Lokman Hekim University</institution>, <city>Ankara</city>, <country>T&#x000fc;rkiye</country>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold>Corresponding author:</bold> Aliye Dogan Gangal; Email: <email>aliyedogan@gazi.edu.tr</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2025"><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>06</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>26</volume><elocation-id>e36</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>6</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>03</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>09</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Author(s)</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article, distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution licence (<uri xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</uri>), which permits unrestricted re-use, distribution and reproduction, provided the original article is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="S146342362500026Xa.pdf"/><abstract><sec id="as1"><title>Aim:</title><p>This study aimed to evaluate the validity and reliability of the Turkish version of&#x000a0;the&#x000a0;Contraceptive Self-Efficacy in Women in Sub-Saharan Africa (CSESSA) scale.</p></sec><sec id="as2"><title>Background:</title><p>Contraceptive&#x000a0;self-efficacy is a crucial predictor of utilization of modern contraceptive methods. However, the existing tools for comprehensively assessing contraceptive self-efficacy are limited. Methods: The sample of this methodological study consisted of 510 female participants of reproductive age. The translation and cultural adaptation of the scale were performed. For validity, content validity and construct validity were tested. For reliability, test-retest reliability, Cronbach&#x02019;s alpha coefficient, and item-total score correlations were evaluated. Findings: The goodness-of-fit indices showed an overall acceptable fit with the three-factor model. Cronbach&#x02019;s alpha for the overall CSESSA scale was 0.867, and for the three subscales, it ranged from 0.77 to 0.84. The scale&#x02019;s test-retest reliability was found to be r = 0.83 (p &#x0003c; 0.001), and the item-total correlations score ranged from 0.495 to 0.646. The Turkish version of the scale is a valid and reliable tool to measure the contraceptive self-efficacy of women of reproductive age. This scale can provide a comprehensive understanding of self-efficacy by assessing various dimensions of contraceptive self-efficacy.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><title>Keywords:</title><kwd>Contraception</kwd><kwd>reliability</kwd><kwd>self-efficacy</kwd><kwd>validity</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="2"/><table-count count="3"/><ref-count count="40"/><page-count count="7"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="other" id="s1"><title>Background</title><p>Unintended pregnancies are a significant global public health issue (Bellizzi <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, <xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; United Nations, <xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). It is known that the main reason behind unintended pregnancies is inconsistent or non-use of modern contraceptive methods (Finner &#x00026; Zolna, <xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). Several factors influence the use of contraceptive methods. Some of these are economic factors associated with obtaining contraceptive methods, cultural and social factors that conflict with method use, and widespread negative beliefs. Additionally, lack of knowledge about contraception, including how to use contraceptive methods effectively and where to access them, negatively impacts method use (D&#x02019;Souza <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, <xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>; Shah <italic toggle="yes">et al.,</italic>
<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>; Yeh <italic toggle="yes">et al.,</italic>
<xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>).</p><p>Self-efficacy is important in the process of ending undesirable behaviours or promoting health-promoting behaviours (Bandura, <xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>). For this reason, the use of contraceptive methods in a consistent manner requires behavioural changes and high self-efficacy (Lopez <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, <xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Uysal <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, <xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">2023</xref>). Research has indicated that women with high contraceptive self-efficacy demonstrate greater acceptance and compliance with contraceptive methods (Hamidi <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, <xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; Shah <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., <xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>). Evaluating contraceptive self-efficacy is crucial, as it is a significant predictor of modern contraceptive method use. There are few validated tools available for a comprehensive assessment of contraceptive self-efficacy (Brafford and Beck, <xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">1991</xref>; Levinson <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., <xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">1998</xref>; Richardson <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, <xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Bhan <italic toggle="yes">et al.,</italic>
<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>). The validated tools that do exist often focus on condom use or include items adapted from other existing tools (Burke <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, <xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>; Hamidi <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, <xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; Nelson <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, <xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Furthermore, these assessments often focus on &#x02018;partner communication&#x02019;, overlooking a more comprehensive perspective. Therefore, it is clear that using a comprehensive measurement tool is essential for assessing contraceptive self-efficacy accurately. Whiting-Collins <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>) developed a measurement tool to evaluate the contraceptive self-efficacy of postpartum women and reported that it is valid and reliable in this population. It is considered that this short and easy-to-understand scale, which includes different dimensions of self-efficacy, can be used to measure the contraceptive self-efficacy of all women of reproductive age. To our knowledge, there is no measurement tool that evaluates the contraceptive self-efficacy of women with different dimensions. Therefore, examining the validity and reliability of this tool in Turkish is a guide for future studies. This study aimed to adapt the Contraceptive Self-Efficacy Among Women in Sub-Saharan Africa (CSESSA) scale into Turkish and to evaluate the validity and reliability.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title>Methods</title><p>This methodological study tested the validity and reliability of the Turkish version of CSESSA Scale. This study adhered to the &#x02018;International Test Commission Guidelines for Translating and Adapting Tests&#x02019; (International Test Commission <xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). There are different approaches to determining the sample size of validity and reliability studies (Anthoine <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, <xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). To evaluate the factor structure of the scale, it is recommended to aim for a large number of participants (Boateng <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, <xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; International Test Commission, <xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). In determining the sample size, Comrey and Lee (<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>) provided the following guidance: 100 = poor, 200 = fair, 300 = good, 500 = very good, &#x02265; 1000 = excellent. Accordingly, this study aimed to reach at least 500 women. This study was conducted with 510 women. Participants had to meet the following inclusion criteria: Reproductive age, having a sexual partner, being literate.</p><p>This study was conducted in three stages. (1) Translation and adaptation of the scale, (2) pilot study, (3) evaluation of psychometric properties (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="f1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).</p><p>
<fig position="float" id="f1"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Stages of adaptation of the scale into Turkish.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="S146342362500026X_fig1" position="float"/></fig>
</p><sec sec-type="other" id="s2-1"><title>Phase 1 Translation and adaptation</title><p>The first phase of the cross-cultural adaptation process is translation. Experts who are familiar with the terminology of the translated scale and who have experience collecting data on the subject take part in the translation phase (World Health Organization, <xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Based on this recommendation, the scale was independently translated into Turkish by two experts with PhD degrees in gynaecology and obstetrics nursing. The two translations obtained were synthesized by the researchers, and an independent linguist checked the translations and analysed the sentence structures. In the subsequent stage, back-translation was performed by two independent translators with no knowledge of the original scale. After this stage, feedback was received from Whiting-Collins regarding the back-translation of the scale. It was decided that the translation of the scale items was appropriate and no items were removed. In the next stage, expert opinions regarding the scale items were obtained from 10 experts (gynaecology and obstetrics nursing, public health nursing, measurement, and evaluation experts). Modifications were made according to their feedback and the final form for the pilot study was obtained (Borsa <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, <xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Coster &#x00026; Mancini, <xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="other" id="s2-2"><title>Phase 2 Pilot study</title><p>A pilot study was conducted to assess the validity of the scale. The scale was applied to 50 women who were similar to the target population (Borsa <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, <xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; World Health Organization, <xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). The results of the pilot study indicated that all scale items were understandable, and no revisions were required.</p></sec><sec sec-type="other" id="s2-3"><title>Phase 3 Evaluation of psychometric properties</title><p>Data were collected face-to-face from women admitted to primary health care centres in a province in T&#x000fc;rkiye between May and December 2022. The data were collected by using a descriptive information form and the Turkish version of the CSESSA Scale. The baseline characteristics of 510 participants were analysed. Two weeks later, a retest was performed with 30 participants to evaluate test-retest reliability (Alpar, <xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Confirmatory factor analysis (CFA) was performed to assess the construct validity of the scale, while test-retest reliability, item-total score correlations, and internal consistency analyses were carried out to evaluate its reliability.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="other" id="s3"><title>Data collection tools</title><sec sec-type="other" id="s3-1"><title>Descriptive information form</title><p>The researchers developed the form based on existing literature. It includes 15 items related to the participants&#x02019; demographic, obstetric, and contraceptive characteristics (Bellizzi <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, <xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Mutumba <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, <xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; Upadhyay <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, <xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="other" id="s3-2"><title>Contraceptive self-efficacy scale</title><p>The scale, developed in Kenya and Nigeria, measures the contraceptive self-efficacy of postpartum women. It consists of 11 items divided into three subscales: &#x02018;husband/partner communication&#x02019;, &#x02018;provider communication&#x02019;, and &#x02018;choosing and managing a method&#x02019;. Each item is scored on a visual analog scale from 0 (&#x02018;cannot do at all&#x02019;) to 10 (&#x02018;highly certain can do&#x02019;). Although the subscales can be scored independently, the total score is the sum of the subscale scores and ranges from 0 to 110. Higher scores indicate a higher contraceptive self-efficacy level. The original scale has Cronbach&#x02019;s alpha of 0.90. The subscales have Cronbach&#x02019;s alpha coefficients of 0.89, 0.89, and 0.88, respectively (Whiting-Collins <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, <xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="other" id="s4"><title>Data analysis</title><p>The data were analysed using SPSS (v.22) and AMOS (v.21). For categorical data, we calculated the number and percentage. For quantitative data, we calculated the mean and standard deviation. Content and construct validity indices were examined to assess the scale&#x02019;s validity. To assess content validity, the Davis technique was used, and 10 experts evaluated each item of the scale as &#x02018;very appropriate&#x02019; (4 points), &#x02018;appropriate but minor changes are needed&#x02019; (3 points), &#x02018;the item needs to be transformed into an appropriate form&#x02019; (2 points) and &#x02018;not appropriate&#x02019; (1 point). Item-Content Validity Index (I-CVI) and Scale Content Validity Index (S-CVI/Ave) were calculated (Polit and Beck, <xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). The I-CVI was calculated by dividing the sum of the items rated with three and four points by the total number of experts. S-CVI-Ave was calculated by dividing the sum of the I-CVI by the total number of items. The construct validity of the scale was tested by calculating Confirmatory Factor Analysis (CFA) goodness-of-fit indices. The following fit indices were evaluated to assess model fit: &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>/df (Chi-Square/Degree of Freedom), Comparative Fit Index (CFI), Goodness-of-Fit Index (GFI), Adjusted Goodness-of-Fit Index (AGFI), Tucker-Lewis Index (TLI), Normed Fit Index (NFI), and Root Mean Square Error of Approximation (RMSEA). The acceptable fit values for these indices are as follows: &#x003c7;&#x000b2;/df &#x0003c;5, CFI &#x02265; 0.90, GFI &#x02265; 0.90, AGFI &#x02265; 0.85, TLI &#x02265; 0.90, NFI &#x02265; 0.90, and RMSEA &#x02264; 0.08. To assess reliability, we used Cronbach&#x02019;s alpha coefficient to evaluate the internal consistency of the scale and its subscales (Polit and Beck, <xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). We also performed an item-total score analysis to examine the relationship between item scores and the total score. To determine time invariance, we carried out a test-retest and calculated the correlation coefficient (Streiner <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, <xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). In addition, Hotelling&#x02019;s T<sup>2</sup> test was used to evaluate response bias and Tukey&#x02019;s Test of Additivity was used to evaluate additivity. A p-value of less than 0.05 was considered to show a statistically significant result.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s5"><title>Results</title><p>The study sample consisted of 510 participants aged between 20 and 53 years (mean=35.25 &#x000b1; 6.58). All participants were married, and 37.1% held a university or master&#x02019;s degree. Of all participants, 69.0% were unemployed, and 53.5% had a middle perceived economic level. Additionally, 91.4% of participants had at least one child, and 15.9% had a history of unintended pregnancy. While 70.8% reported not wanting to get pregnant, 32.7% did not use any modern contraceptive methods. Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">1</xref> summarizes the baseline characteristics of the participants.</p><p>
<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Characteristics of participants (n = 510)</p></caption><alternatives><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Characteristics</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age (Mean &#x000b1;SD) (Min-Max)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">35.25 &#x000b1; 6.58 (20&#x02013;53)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">CSESSA scale (Mean &#x000b1;SD)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">9.03&#x000b1; 1.51</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Subscales of the Scale (Mean &#x000b1;SD)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Husband /partner communication</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">9.14 &#x000b1;1.87</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Provider communication</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">8.92 &#x000b1;1.91</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Choosing and managing a method</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">9.00 &#x000b1;1.86</td></tr><tr content-type="header"><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">N</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Education level</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x000a0;Primary&#x02013;Middle</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">156</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.6</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x000a0;High</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">165</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">32.4</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x000a0;Bachelor&#x02019;s or Postgraduate</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">189</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.1</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Employment</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x000a0;Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">158</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">31</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x000a0;No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">352</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">69</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Perceived economic level</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x000a0;Low</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">153</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">30</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x000a0;Middle</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">273</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">53.5</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x000a0;High</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">84</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.5</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Number of children</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x000a0;0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">49</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.6</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x000a0;1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">91</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.8</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x000a0;2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">230</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">45.1</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x000a0;3 and above</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">140</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.5</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Unintended pregnancy history</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x000a0;Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">81</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.9</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x000a0;No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">429</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">84.1</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pregnancy intention</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x000a0;In the next 3 months</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">33</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.5</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x000a0;Within 1&#x02013;2 years</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">45</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.8</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x000a0;Within 2&#x02013;5 years</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">46</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.0</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x000a0;After more than 5 years</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">25</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.9</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x000a0;I don&#x02019;t want to get pregnant</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">361</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">70.8</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Contraceptive methods</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x000a0;Modern Contraceptive Method<xref rid="t1fn1" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">343</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">67,3</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x000a0;Traditional method<xref rid="t1fn2" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">111</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.7</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x000a0;No method</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">56</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.0</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Contraceptive method decision</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x000a0;Partner decision</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">49</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.6</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x000a0;Own decision</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">148</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">29</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x000a0;Decision with partner</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">313</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">61.4</td></tr></tbody></table><graphic xlink:href="S146342362500026X_tab1" position="float"/></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t1fn1" fn-type="other"><label>*</label><p>Condom, pill, injections, spiral, subcutaneous implant, tubal ligation.</p></fn><fn id="t1fn2" fn-type="other"><label>**</label><p>Withdrawal, calendar.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p>The scale has total scores ranging from 0 to 110 points. The overall mean score, calculated by dividing the total score by the number of scale items, is 9.03 with a standard deviation (SD) of 1.51. The mean scores in sub-dimensions are also high: 9.14 (SD 1.87) for &#x02018;husband/partner communication&#x02019;, 8.92 (SD 1.91) for &#x02018;provider communication&#x02019; and 9.00 (SD 1.86) for &#x02018;choosing and managing a method&#x02019; (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p><p>The content validity was examined and revealed that all items had an I-CVI higher than 0.80 and the S-CVI Ave was 0.90. No items were removed from the scale. The CFA was performed using the three-factor structure of the original scale. CFA fit indices were found as &#x003c7;2/df = 4.09, GFI = 0.95, CFI = 0.95, AGFI = 0.913, NFI = 0.940, TLI = 0.933, and RMSEA = 0.078 (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). The results supported the construct validity of the three-factor model (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="f2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).</p><p>
<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Goodness-of-fit indices values of the scale (n = 510)</p></caption><alternatives><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fit Criteria</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Good fit</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Acceptable fit</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Values</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x003c7;2/df</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x003c7;2/df &#x0003c;3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x003c7;2/df &#x0003c;5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.097</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">GFI</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.95&#x02264; GFI&#x02264;1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.90&#x02264;GFI&#x0003c;0.95</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.950</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">CFI</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.95&#x02264; CFI &#x02264;1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.90&#x02264;CFI&#x0003c;0.95</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.954</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">NFI</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.95&#x02264; NFI &#x02264;1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.90&#x02264;NFI&#x0003c;0.95</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.940</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">TLI</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.95&#x02264; TLI &#x02264;1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.90&#x02264;TLI&#x0003c;0.95</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.933</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">AGFI</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.90&#x02264;AGFI&#x02264;1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.85&#x02264;AGFI&#x0003c;0.90</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.913</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">RMSEA</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0&#x0003c;RMSEA&#x02264;0.05</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.05&#x0003c;RMSEA&#x02264;0.08</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.078</td></tr></tbody></table><graphic xlink:href="S146342362500026X_tab2" position="float"/></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><p>Abbreviations: GFI, Goodness-of-fit index; CFI, Comparative fit index; NFI, Normed fit index; TLI, Tucker-Lewis Index; AGFI, Adjusted goodness-of-fit index; RMSEA, Root mean square error of approximation.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p>
<fig position="float" id="f2"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Confirmatory factor analysis of the Turkish version of the CSESSA scale.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="S146342362500026X_fig2" position="float"/></fig>
</p><p>Cronbach&#x02019;s alpha coefficients of the subscales were as follows: &#x02018;husband/partner communication&#x02019; subscale&#x000a0;(0.842), &#x02018;provider communication&#x02019; subscale&#x000a0;(0.770), and &#x02018;choosing and managing a method&#x02019; subscale (0.810). Cronbach&#x02019;s alpha of the total scale was found to be 0.867. The internal consistency of the total scale and subscales were adequate (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).</p><p>
<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl3"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Item total correlation and Cronbach&#x02019;s &#x003b1; coefficients of the scale</p></caption><alternatives><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Items</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Corrected item&#x02013;total correlation</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cronbach&#x02019;s &#x003b1; if item<break/>deleted</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Item1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.496</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.861</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Item 2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.591</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.854</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Item3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.599</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.854</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Item 4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.599</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.854</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Item5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.495</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.863</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Item 6</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.578</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.855</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Item 7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.568</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.856</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Item 8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.646</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.851</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Item 9</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.582</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.855</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Item 10</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.521</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.860</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Item 11</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.629</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.853</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Total Scale Cronbach&#x02019;s &#x003b1; = 0.867<break/>Subdimensions<break/>Husband /partner communication Cronbach&#x02019;s &#x003b1; = 0.842<break/>Choosing and managing a method Cronbach&#x02019;s &#x003b1; =0.810<break/>Provider communication Cronbach&#x02019;s &#x003b1; = 0.770</td></tr></tbody></table><graphic xlink:href="S146342362500026X_tab3" position="float"/></alternatives></table-wrap>
</p><p>The item-total score correlations of the scale ranged from 0.495 to 0.646. There was no significant increase in Cronbach&#x02019;s alpha values when an item was deleted (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). The test-retest correlation of the scale was found to be 0.83. The relationship between the total scale score and the subscales was investigated. A significant, positive and strong relationship was found between the total score of the scale and all its subscales (&#x02018;husband/partner communication&#x02019; p &#x0003c; 0.001, r = 0.729; &#x02018;provider communication&#x02019; p &#x0003c; 0.001, r = 0.759; &#x02018;choosing and managing a method&#x02019; p &#x0003c; 0.001, r = 0.797).</p><p>Hotelling&#x02019;s T<sup>2</sup> test was used to evaluate the response bias, and the Tukey Nonadditivity test was used to evaluate whether the scale had additivity. Hotelling&#x02019;s T<sup>2</sup> score was 92.349 (p = 0.001). Tukey&#x02019;s non-additivity test was found to be p &#x0003e; 0.05, and the scale additive.</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s6"><title>Discussion</title><p>This study evaluated the psychometric properties of the Turkish version of CSESSA scale. Currently, no measurement tools are available for women&#x02019;s contraceptive self-efficacy. The results confirm the validity and reliability of the scale. Furthermore, the results suggest that the CSESSA can be translated into other languages. This is significant, considering the limited number of validated international measures that comprehensively assess contraceptive self-efficacy.</p><p>The validity of a measurement tool means that it adequately measures its aims. In this study, independent translation and back-translation were performed, expert opinions were obtained, and a pilot test was conducted on a sample similar to the target population (International Test Commission, <xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). The results showed that the scale performed similarly to the original scale and provided cross-cultural validity (Souza <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., <xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). The content validity of the scale was examined using the Davis technique, and I-CVI and S-CVI/Ave were calculated. It is recommended that the minimum I-CVI value should be above 0.78 and the S-CVI/Ave value should be above 0.90 in the number of 6-10 experts (Polit and Beck, <xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). In this study, the I-CVI values for the items ranged from 0.80 and 1.00. The S-CVI/Ave value was determined as 0.90. Consequently, the Turkish version of the scale met the criteria for content validity (Almanasreh <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, <xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>; Esin, <xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). In this study, the CFA was performed to test the construct validity of the scale. CFA evaluates how many factors the scale has, which items are related to which factors, and whether the model fit index values are appropriate. These results indicate that the model had an acceptable fit (Boateng <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, <xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; Byrne, <xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Ya&#x0015f;l&#x00131;o&#x0011f;lu, <xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>).</p><p>Cronbach&#x02019;s alpha coefficient, item-total score analysis, and test-retest analysis were used to evaluate the reliability of the scale. Cronbach&#x02019;s alpha coefficient, which is used to evaluate the internal consistency of a scale, was found to be &#x0003e;0.70 in this study, which is considered acceptable reliability (Polit and Beck, <xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). The scale was found to be highly reliable with good internal consistency (Cronbach&#x02019;s alpha = 0.867). All subscales were found to be either reliable or highly reliable. The item-total score correlation provides the discrimination index of each item (DeVellis, <xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). In this study, item-total correlation values were higher than 0.30 and varied between 0.495 and 0.646. These results show that the items accurately discriminated between participants. (&#x000c7;okluk <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, <xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; Streiner <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, <xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). The test-retest correlation method was used to demonstrate the time invariance of the scale. This method is important because it helps to establish the reliability of the scale over time. The test-retest correlation of the scale is expected to be 0.80 (Nunnally &#x00026; Bernstein, <xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">1994</xref>; Weir, <xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>). In this study, the test-retest correlation was calculated and found to be 0.83, indicating an acceptable limit. Hotelling&#x02019;s T<sup>2</sup> test was used to assess whether the scale items were perceived as identical by the participants and whether the responses were biased. When determining self-efficacy levels, the participants may have had biased responses. Therefore, evaluation of response bias is important for scale reliability (Se&#x000e7;er, <xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; &#x000d6;zdamar, <xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). The test outcomes indicated that the mean item scores differed and there was no response bias (Hotelling&#x02019;s T2= 92.349, p = 0.001). These findings suggest that women do not exhibit bias when completing the scale. This scale comprises of three subscales. Tukey&#x02019;s additivity test was used to assess the additivity of scale items. The test results showed that the scale items could be summed to obtain a total score (p &#x0003e; 0.05) (&#x000d6;zdamar, <xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>).</p><p>The overall mean score of this scale was 9.03 (SD 1.51). In the original scale, the overall mean score was 8.72 (SD 1.72). Scores on the scale were high and skewed for both sample populations. This may be due to the high prevalence of modern contraceptives in the samples (73.3% for the Kenya sample and 67.3% for this sample) (Whiting-Collins <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, <xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). The CSESSA scale assesses women&#x02019;s self-efficacy in &#x02018;husband/partner communication&#x02019;, &#x02018;provider communication&#x02019;, and &#x02018;choosing and managing a method&#x02019;. This allows for a more comprehensive assessment of contraceptive self-efficacy. This scale is an appropriate tool for use by health professionals to evaluate contraceptive self-efficacy in women of reproductive age.</p></sec><sec sec-type="other" id="s7"><title>Study limitations</title><p>This study also has some limitations. The data of the study were collected in a single region, and convenience sampling method was used. This may have affected the generalizability of the study.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s8"><title>Conclusion</title><p>The Turkish version of the scale, a tool measuring contraceptive self-efficacy, is valid and reliable. This scale can assist health professionals in planning tailored interventions based on an individual&#x02019;s specific needs and self-efficacy levels, with the aim of preventing unintended pregnancies.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We are grateful to all the women who o participated in this research.</p></ack><sec sec-type="other" id="s9"><title>Author contributions</title><p>Conceptualization: [Aliye Dogan Gangal; Ayten Senturk Erenel]; Methodology: [Aliye Dogan Gangal; Ayten Senturk Erenel], Formal analysis and investigation: [Aliye Dogan Gangal; Ayten Senturk Erenel], Writing &#x02013; original draft preparation: [Aliye Dogan Gangal]; Writing &#x02013; review and editing: [Ayten Senturk Erenel], Resources: [Aliye Dogan Gangal]; Supervision: [Ayten Senturk Erenel]</p></sec><sec sec-type="funding-statement" id="s10"><title>Funding statement</title><p>This research did not receive any specific grant from funding agencies in the public, commercial, or not for-profit sectors.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s11"><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors report there are no competing interests to declare.</p></sec><sec sec-type="other" id="s12"><title>Ethical standards</title><p>Gazi University Ethics Committee (No: E-77082166-604.01.02-355909 &#x00026; Date: 11.05.22). The institution&#x02019;s permit Issue: E-51381736-771. The research was conducted according to the principles of the Declaration of Helsinki. Written informed consent was obtained from all women.</p></sec><ref-list id="reflist1" content-type="normal"><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="r1">
<string-name>
<surname>Almanasreh</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Moles</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</string-name> and <string-name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>TF</given-names>
</string-name>. (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>Evaluation of methods used for estimating content validity</article-title>. <source>Research in Social and Administrative Pharmacy</source>
<volume>15</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>214</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>221</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sapharm.2018.03.066</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29606610</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="r2">
<string-name>
<surname>Alpar</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</string-name>. (<year>2014</year>) <source>Applied Statistics with examples from the sports, health and education science and validity-reliability</source>. <publisher-loc>Ankara</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Detay Publishing</publisher-name>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="r3">
<string-name>
<surname>Anthoine</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Moret</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Regnault</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>S&#x000e9;bille</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</string-name> and <string-name>
<surname>Hardouin</surname>
<given-names>JB.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Sample size used to validate a scale: a review of publications on newly-developed patient reported outcomes measures</article-title>. <source>Health and Quality of Life Outcomes</source>
<volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="r4">
<string-name>
<surname>Bandura</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2005</year>) Guide for constructing self-efficacy scales. Self-efficacy beliefs of adolescents. Greenwich, CT, Information Age Publishing, 5(1), 307-337.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="r5">
<string-name>
<surname>Bellizzi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Mannava</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Nagai</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Sobel</surname>
<given-names>HL.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Reasons for discontinuation of contraception among women with a current unintended pregnancy in 36 low and middle-income countries</article-title>. <source>Contraception</source>
<volume>101</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>26</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>33</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.contraception.2019.09.006</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31655068</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="r6">
<string-name>
<surname>Bhan</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Thomas</surname>
<given-names>EE</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>McDougal</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Nanda</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Mahapatra</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Das</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2024</year>) <article-title>Validation of a family planning self-efficacy measure with married women in Bihar, India: Findings from the Bihar Integrated Family Planning Survey</article-title>. <source>Contraception</source>
<volume>X 6</volume>100113. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.conx.2024.100113</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="r7">
<string-name>
<surname>Boateng</surname>
<given-names>GO</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Neilands</surname>
<given-names>TB</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Frongillo</surname>
<given-names>EA</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Melgar-Qui&#x000f1;onez</surname>
<given-names>HR</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Young</surname>
<given-names>SL.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Best practices for developing and validating scales for health, social, and behavioral research: a primer</article-title>. <source>Frontiers in Public Health</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>149</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2018.00149</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29942800</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="r8">
<string-name>
<surname>Borsa</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Dam&#x000e1;sio</surname>
<given-names>BF</given-names>
</string-name> and <string-name>
<surname>Bandeira</surname>
<given-names>DR.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>CrossCultural adaptation and validation of psychological instruments: Some considerations</article-title>. <source>Paid&#x000e9;ia</source>
<volume>22</volume>(<issue>53</issue>), <fpage>423</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>432</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/1982-43272253201314</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="r9">
<string-name>
<surname>Brafford</surname>
<given-names>LJ</given-names>
</string-name> and <string-name>
<surname>Beck</surname>
<given-names>KH</given-names>
</string-name>. (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Development and validation of a condom self-efficacy scale for college students</article-title>. <source>Journal of American College Health</source>
<volume>39</volume>(<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>219</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>225</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07448481.1991.9936238</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1783705</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="r10">
<string-name>
<surname>Burke</surname>
<given-names>HM</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ridgeway</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Murray</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Mickler</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Thomas</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Williams</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2022</year>) <article-title>Reproductive empowerment and contraceptive self-care: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Sexual and Reproductive Health Matters</source>
<volume>29</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>2090057</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/26410397.2022.2090057</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="r11">
<string-name>
<surname>Byrne</surname>
<given-names>BM.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2016</year>) <source>Structural Equation Modeling with AMOS: Basic Concepts, Applications, and Programming</source>. <edition>3rd ed</edition>. <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="r13">
<string-name>
<surname>&#x000c7;okluk</surname>
<given-names>&#x000d6;</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>&#x0015e;ekercio&#x0011f;lu</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</string-name> and <string-name>
<surname>B&#x000fc;y&#x000fc;k&#x000f6;zt&#x000fc;rk</surname>
<given-names>&#x0015e;.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2018</year>) Multivariate statistics SPSS and LISREL applications for social sciences. Pegem Academy Publications.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="r12">
<string-name>
<surname>Comrey</surname>
<given-names>AL</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>HB.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2013</year>) <source>A First Course in Factor Analysis</source>. <publisher-name>Psychology press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="r14">
<string-name>
<surname>Coster</surname>
<given-names>WJ</given-names>
</string-name> and <string-name>
<surname>Mancini</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names>
</string-name>. (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Recommendations for translation and cross-cultural adaptation of instruments for occupational therapy research and practice</article-title>. <source>Revista de Terapia Ocupacional da Universidade de S&#x000e3;o Paulo</source>
<volume>26</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>50</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>57</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="r15">
<string-name>
<surname>D&#x02019;Souza</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Bailey</surname>
<given-names>JV</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Stephenson</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</string-name> and <string-name>
<surname>Oliver</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2022</year>) <article-title>Factors influencing contraception choice and use globally: a synthesis of systematic reviews</article-title>. <source>The European Journal of Contraception &#x00026; Reproductive Health Care</source>
<volume>27</volume>(<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>364</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>372</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13625187.2022.2096215</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36047713</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="r16">
<string-name>
<surname>DeVellis</surname>
<given-names>RF.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2012</year>) <source>Scale Development, Theory and Applications</source>. <publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE Publication Inc</publisher-name>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="r17">
<string-name>
<surname>Esin</surname>
<given-names>MN.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2014</year>) <part-title>Veri toplama y&#x000f6;ntem ve ara&#x000e7;lar&#x00131; &#x00026; Veri toplama ara&#x000e7;lar&#x00131;n&#x00131;n g&#x000fc;venirlik ve ge&#x000e7;erli&#x0011f;i</part-title>. In: <string-name>
<surname>Erdogan</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Nahcivan</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Esin</surname>
<given-names>MN</given-names>
</string-name>. (Eds) <source>Hem&#x0015f;irelikte Ara&#x0015f;t&#x00131;rma: S&#x000fc;re&#x000e7;, Uygulama ve Kritik</source>. <publisher-loc>Istanbul</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Nobel T&#x00131;p Kitabevleri</publisher-name>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="r19">
<string-name>
<surname>Finer</surname>
<given-names>LB</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Zolna</surname>
<given-names>MR.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>Declines in unintended pregnancy in the United States, 2008&#x02013;2011</article-title>. <source>New England Journal of Medicine</source>
<volume>374</volume>(<issue>9</issue>), <fpage>843</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>852</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMsa1506575</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26962904</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="r20">
<string-name>
<surname>Hamidi</surname>
<given-names>OP</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Deimling</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Lehman</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Weisman</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Chuang</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>High self-efficacy is associated with prescription contraceptive use</article-title>. <source>Womens Health Issues</source>
<volume>28</volume>(<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>509</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>513</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.whi.2018.04.006</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30131220</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="r21">
<collab>International Test Commission</collab>. (<year>2017</year>) The ITC Guidelines for Translating and Adapting Tests (2nd ed.). <uri xlink:href="https://www.intestcom.org/page/14">https://www.intestcom.org/page/14</uri>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="r42">
<string-name>
<surname>Levinson</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Wan</surname>
<given-names>CK</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Beamer</surname>
<given-names>LJ.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>The contraceptive self-efficacy scale: analysis in four samples</article-title>. <source>Journal of Youth and Adolescence</source>
<volume>27</volume>, <fpage>773</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>793</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1022865900546</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12349803</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="r22">
<string-name>
<surname>Lopez</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Grey</surname>
<given-names>TW</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Tolley</surname>
<given-names>EE</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Stockton</surname>
<given-names>LL.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>Theory-based interventions for contraception</article-title>. <source>The Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews</source>. <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>CD007249</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD007249.pub5</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27879980</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="r23">
<string-name>
<surname>Mutumba</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Wekesa</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</string-name> &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Stephenson</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Community influences on modern contraceptive use among young women in low and middle-income countries: a cross-sectional multi-country analysis</article-title>. <source>BMC Public Health</source>
<volume>18</volume>, <fpage>430</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-018-5331-y</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29609567</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="r24">
<string-name>
<surname>Nelson</surname>
<given-names>HN</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Borrero</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Lehman</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Velott</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Chuang</surname>
<given-names>CH.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Measuring oral contraceptive adherence using self-report versus pharmacy claims data</article-title>. <source>Contraception</source>
<volume>96</volume>(<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>453</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>459</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28882679</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="r25">
<string-name>
<surname>Nunnally</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Bernstein</surname>
<given-names>IH.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1994</year>) <source>The Assessment of Reliability. Psychometric theory</source> (<edition>3rd ed</edition>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>McGraw-Hill</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="r26">
<string-name>
<surname>&#x000d6;zdamar</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2016</year>) Scale and test development structural equation modeling. Nisan Publishing, Eski&#x0015f;ehir.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="r27">
<string-name>
<surname>Polit</surname>
<given-names>DF</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Beck</surname>
<given-names>CT.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2017</year>) <source>Essentials of Nursing Research: Appraising Evidence for Nursing Practice</source>, <edition>10th ed</edition>. <publisher-name>Wolters Kluwer</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="r28">
<string-name>
<surname>Richardson</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Allison</surname>
<given-names>KR</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Gesink</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Berry</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>Barriers to accessing and using contraception in highland Guatemala: the development of a family planning self-efficacy scale</article-title>. <source>Open Access Journal of Contraception</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>77</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>87</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/OAJC.S95674</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29386939</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="r30">
<string-name>
<surname>Se&#x000e7;er</surname>
<given-names>&#x00130;.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2018</year>) <source>Psychological test development and adaptation process: SPSS and LISREL applications</source>. <publisher-loc>Ankara</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>An&#x00131; Publishing</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="r29">
<string-name>
<surname>Shah</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Nisa Mir</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2021</year>) <article-title>Exploring readiness for birth control in improving women health status:factors influencing the adoption of modern contraceptives methods for family planning practices</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health</source> 18(22), <fpage>11892</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph182211892</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34831646</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="r32">
<string-name>
<surname>Souza</surname>
<given-names>ACD</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Alexandre</surname>
<given-names>NMC</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Guirardello</surname>
<given-names>EDB.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Psychometric properties in instruments evaluation of reliability and validity</article-title>. <source>Epidemiologia e Servi&#x000e7;os de Sa&#x000fa;de</source>
<volume>26</volume>, <fpage>649</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>659</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28977189</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="r33">
<string-name>
<surname>Streiner</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Norman</surname>
<given-names>GR</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Cairney</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2015</year>) <source>Health Measurement Scales: A Practical Guide to their Development and Use</source> (<edition>5th ed</edition>.). <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="r34">
<collab>United Nations</collab>. (<year>2019</year>) Family Planning and the 2030 Agenda for Sustainable Development-Data Booklet, UN Department of Economic and Social Affairs. <uri xlink:href="https://www.un.org/development/desa/pd/content/family-planning-and-2030-agenda-sustainable-development-data-booklet">https://www.un.org/development/desa/pd/content/family-planning-and-2030-agenda-sustainable-development-data-booklet</uri>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="r35">
<string-name>
<surname>Upadhyay</surname>
<given-names>UD</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Dworkin</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Weitz</surname>
<given-names>TA</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Foster</surname>
<given-names>DG.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Development and validation of a reproductive autonomy scale</article-title>. <source>Studies in Family Planning</source>
<volume>45</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>19</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>41</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1728-4465.2014.00374.x</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24615573</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="r36">
<string-name>
<surname>Uysal</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Boyce</surname>
<given-names>SC</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Undie</surname>
<given-names>CC</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Liambila</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Wendoh</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Pearson</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2023</year>) <article-title>Effects of a clinic-based reproductive empowerment intervention on proximal outcomes of contraceptive use, self-efficacy, attitudes, and awareness and use of survivor services: a cluster-controlled trial in Nairobi, Kenya</article-title>. <source>Sexual and Reproductive Health Matters</source>
<volume>31</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>2227371</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/26410397.2023.2227371</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37594312</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="r37">
<string-name>
<surname>Weir</surname>
<given-names>JP.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Quantifying test-retest reliability using the intraclass correlation coefficient and the SEM</article-title>. <source>Journal of Strength and Conditioning Research</source>
<volume>19</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>231</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>240</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1519/15184.1</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15705040</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="r38">
<string-name>
<surname>Whiting-Collins</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Grenier</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Winch</surname>
<given-names>PJ</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Tsui</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Donohue</surname>
<given-names>PK.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Measuring contraceptive self-efficacy in sub-Saharan Africa: development and validation of the CSESSA scale in Kenya and Nigeria</article-title>. <source>Contraception: X</source>
<volume>2</volume>, <fpage>100041</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.conx.2020.100041</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33145490</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="r39">
<collab>World Health Organization (WHO)</collab>. (<year>2017</year>) Process of translation and adaptation of instruments. <uri xlink:href="http://www.who.int/substance_abuse/research_tools/translation/en/">http://www.who.int/substance_abuse/research_tools/translation/en/</uri>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="r40">
<string-name>
<surname>Ya&#x0015f;l&#x00131;o&#x0011f;lu</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Factor analysis and validity in social sciences: Application of exploratory and confirmatory factor analyses</article-title>. <source>Istanbul University Journal of the School of Business</source>
<volume>46</volume>, <fpage>74</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>85</lpage>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="r41">
<string-name>
<surname>Yeh</surname>
<given-names>PT</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Kautsar</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Kennedy</surname>
<given-names>CE</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Gaffield</surname>
<given-names>ME.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2022</year>) <article-title>Values and preferences for contraception: a global systematic review</article-title>. <source>Contraception</source>
<volume>111</volume>, <fpage>3</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>21</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.contraception.2022.04.011</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35525287</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>