<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Implant Dent</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int J Implant Dent</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>International Journal of Implant Dentistry</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2198-4034</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer Berlin Heidelberg</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40392443</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12092919</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">624</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40729-025-00624-8</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Early versus conventional loading for fully guided immediate implant placement in molar sites: a randomized controlled clinical study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Botros</surname><given-names>Kirollos H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-0254-0890</contrib-id><name><surname>Adel-Khattab</surname><given-names>Doaa</given-names></name><address><email>dr.doaa.adel-khattab@dent.asu.edu.eg</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Eldabe</surname><given-names>Abdelrahman K.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Abuel Ela</surname><given-names>Hala A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/01jaj8n65</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.252487.e</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 8632 679X</institution-id><institution>Oral Medicine, Periodontology and Diagnosis, Faculty of Dentistry, </institution><institution>Assiut University, </institution></institution-wrap>Assiut, Egypt </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/00cb9w016</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.7269.a</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0621 1570</institution-id><institution>Oral Medicine, Periodontology and Diagnosis Department, Faculty of Dentistry, </institution><institution>Ain Shams University, </institution></institution-wrap>Cairo, Egypt </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/030vg1t69</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411810.d</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0621 7673</institution-id><institution>Oral Medicine, Periodontology and Diagnosis, Faculty of Dentistry, </institution><institution>Misr International University, </institution></institution-wrap>Cairo, Egypt </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>20</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>12</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>39</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>6</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Purpose</title><p id="Par1">To evaluate early versus conventional loading in immediate implants for molars. This study aims to answer the following PICO (Patient, Intervention, Comparison, and Outcome) question: In patients over 18&#x000a0;years of age, does early loading of immediately placed implants in molar areas result in a similar implant survival rate and marginal bone loss as conventional loading?</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">Twenty-seven patients (15 women and 12 men) received a total of 30 implants immediately after molar extraction. The surgical treatment protocol entailed atraumatic tooth extraction without flap elevation. Non-invasive quantitative analyses were used to assess implant stability. After an uneventful healing period, the 30 implants were restored with screw-retained monolithic zirconia prosthesis, half of which after 6&#x000a0;weeks (G1) and the other half after 3&#x000a0;months (G2).</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">Regarding the survival rate, the Kaplan&#x02013;Meier and log-rank test showed that there was no statistically significant difference between both groups (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1). Implant stability quotient at the prosthetic phase of both groups (6&#x000a0;weeks in G1 and 3&#x000a0;months in G2) revealed no statistically significant difference (G1 RFA74.4 (SD 5.54)&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;DCA 79.07 (SD 5.75))/G2 RFA 73.67 (SD 5.7), &#x02212;&#x02009;DCA78.93 (SD 4.48).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par4">Early loading of immediately placed implants in molar sites is considered a predictable treatment modality provided that ideal implant position and adequate insertion torque are achieved.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Immediate implants</kwd><kwd>Fully guided</kwd><kwd>Early loading</kwd><kwd>Molar area</kwd><kwd>Resonance frequency analysis</kwd><kwd>Damping capacity analysis</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Ain Shams University</institution></funding-source></award-group><open-access><p>Open access funding provided by The Science, Technology &#x00026; Innovation Funding Authority (STDF) in cooperation with The Egyptian Knowledge Bank (EKB).</p></open-access></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Deutsche Gesellschaft f&#x000fc;r Implantologie im Zahn&#x02010;, Mund&#x02010; und Kieferbereich e.V., Japanese Society of Oral Implantology 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec2"><title>Background</title><p id="Par14">Restorative therapy performed on implant(s) placed in a fully healed and non&#x02010;compromised alveolar process has high clinical success and survival rates [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. It was proposed that placement of an implant in a fresh extraction socket may stimulate bone tissue formation and osseointegration, and hence counteract the adaptive alterations that occur following tooth extraction. In other words, type 1 implant installation may allow the preservation of bone tissue of the socket and the surrounding jaw [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Loading concepts in implant dentistry have been widely discussed in the literature. Initially, healing phases of 3&#x000a0;months in the mandible and 6&#x000a0;months in the maxilla were recommended [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. To meet the patient&#x02019;s expectations for earlier prosthetic rehabilitation, shortened healing periods between implant installation and loading have been introduced. A variety of influencing factors, like initial implant stability, implant surface characteristics, bone quantity, bone healing, interim prosthesis design, and occlusal pattern during the healing phase, have been identified for successful osseointegration with modified loading protocols [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Developments in the implant design, especially including structured and chemically modified surfaces, have led to the accelerated osseointegration of implants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. The survival rates of different loading protocols (immediate, early, and conventional) remain a point of debate in the literature. However, the marginal bone loss and peri-implant gingival level are usually not affected by the loading regimen, indicating that different loading protocols behave similarly after successful osseointegration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>].</p><p id="Par15">Osseointegration occurs in two stages, the primary and secondary stages [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. In the primary stage, implant stability is mainly achieved from mechanical engagement with cortical bone. In contrast, in the secondary stage, implant stability is achieved through bone regeneration and remodeling [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Adequate primary stability is a prerequisite for acceptable osseointegration. It is, therefore, imperative to quantify implant stability at several time points and predict long-term prognosis based on the obtained implant stability measurements. There are several methods to measure primary stability such as ITVs (insertion torque values). Other techniques involve non-invasive quantitative analysis, such as resonance frequency analysis (RFA) and damping capacity analysis (DCA) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>].</p><p id="Par16">It should be pointed out that meta-analysis of published data indicates that while guided computer-assisted implant surgery CAIS is superior to freehand implant surgery in terms of safety and postoperative morbidity, implant success with CAIS is more or less the same [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Fully guidance means not only creation of the osteotomy bed through the surgical guide but also fixture insertion that ensures 2 benefits: ideal fixture placement according to the exact planned implant position and adequate insertion torque (primary stability) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>].</p><p id="Par17">Various surgical and prosthodontic protocols used in oral implantology are directly associated with the long&#x02010;term outcome of implant prosthesis. A systematic review highlighted the importance of evaluating outcomes in oral implantology by combining the placement and loading protocols variables as a single denominator for survival/success [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>].</p><p id="Par18">To the best of our knowledge, no prior clinical trial has compared the outcome of implants following type 1B protocol (immediate placement, early loading) vs type 1C (immediate placement, conventional loading) in molar sites with non-splinted superstructures. The null hypothesis was that there would be no difference in survival rates or marginal bone level changes in immediately placed implants between the two loading procedures, against the alternative hypothesis of a difference.</p></sec><sec id="Sec3"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec4"><title>Patient recruitment</title><p id="Par19">All patients were recruited from the outpatient clinic of Oral Medicine, Periodontology, and Oral Diagnosis Department, Faculty of Dentistry, Ain Shams University, from March 2024 to December 2024. Prior to inclusion into the study, patients were informed about the use of their data for academic purposes and written informed consent was obtained. The study was approved by the Ain Shams Institutional Ethical Committee, Faculty of Dentistry, Ain Shams University (FDASU-RecIM112221). All patients were treated in accordance with regional laws, good clinical practice, and in adherence to the Declaration of Helsinki (1996) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. In addition, the study was registered in clinical trial registration site (NCT06281535) on 24/02/2024.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Sample size calculation</title><p id="Par20">The sample size was calculated based on the primary outcome measure, the implant stability quotient (ISQ). According to a previous study reporting a standard deviation of 3.43 and mean difference of 7, calculations based on an independent-sample-t-test with a power&#x02009;=&#x02009;90% and a significance level p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.05 yielded 12 participants per group. The number was increased to 15 participants (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;30 in total) to account for any possible dropouts (Attrition Ratio 20%). The adequacy of the sample size used was determined using Ps Power and Sample Size software (version 3.1.2) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Randomization, allocation concealment, and blinding</title><p id="Par21">Computer-generated randomization lists were created with two groups consisting of an equal number of patients. Only one of the investigators, not involved in the selection and treatment of the patients, was aware of the random sequence and had access to the randomization list stored in a password-protected portable computer. The random codes were enclosed in sequentially numbered, identical, opaque, sealed envelopes. Envelopes were opened sequentially only after implant placement; therefore, treatment allocation was concealed to the investigator in charge of enrolling and treating the patients included in the trial [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>].</p><p id="Par22">The inclusion criteria were patients age range from 20&#x02013;60&#x000a0;years, molar tooth to be extracted due to periodontal diseases, peri-apical diseases, or tooth fracture. Any type of extraction socket (A, B, or C) according to Tarnow and Smith classification provided that insertion torque is above 25 Ncm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>].</p><p id="Par23">The exclusion criteria were extraction sockets that are affected by an acute infection, participants with a history or presence of severe uncontrolled systemic disease, long-term steroidal anti-inflammatory drug therapy, patients exposed to irradiation in the head and neck region with more than 70&#x000a0;Gy within the last 6&#x000a0;months, pregnant or nursing, patients with oral parafunctional (bruxism), heavy smokers (&#x0003e;&#x02009;10 cigarettes per day) or alcohol/drug abusers, poor oral hygiene, full-mouth plaque surfaces&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;10%, patients unwilling to commit to an appropriate post-therapeutic maintenance regimen [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Virtual implant planning and surgical guide fabrication</title><p id="Par24">Cone beam computer tomographies were acquired using Veraview X800 L P (JMorita Mfg. Corp., Kyoto, Japan) with standard settings for all patients (100&#x000a0;kV, 8&#x000a0;mA, 9&#x000a0;s, voxel size: 250&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m, FOV: 110&#x000a0;mm). Concurrently, digital impressions were captured using intraoral scanner Aoral scan3 (shining 3D, China). These impressions accurately represent the surface topography of the dental arches, capturing the details of the gingiva, teeth, and existing prosthetic structures. The high-resolution surface data is essential for designing restorations and planning the prosthetic outcome.</p><p id="Par25">Then, the acquired CBCT and digital impression files were imported into the Exoplan software. The software supports various file formats, such as DICOM for CBCT data and STL for digital impressions. Initial alignment was achieved by manually selecting corresponding anatomical landmarks. Common reference points include cusp tips, incisal edges, and occlusal grooves. The software&#x02019;s intelligent algorithms assist in aligning these points to create an initial match between the datasets. Once the initial alignment is established, Exoplan&#x02019;s advanced registration algorithms perform a fine-tuning process. The prosthetic-driven planning approach in Exoplan allows for the consideration of both surgical and prosthetic factors, ensuring that the implant positions align with the desired restorative outcomes.</p><p id="Par26">The finalized treatment plan, incorporating the aligned datasets, was used to design fully guided surgical guides (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). The fully guided surgical guide dictates the exact trajectory of the surgical drills and implants, translating the digital plan into precise clinical execution and ensuring that the implant placement adheres to the meticulously planned positions. These guides were fabricated using biocompatible materials and DLP 3D printer Accuafab D1s (shining 3D, China).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p><bold>a</bold>&#x02013;<bold>c</bold> Designing a fully guided surgical guide to translate the digital plan into precise clinical execution</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40729_2025_624_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Intervention (surgical procedure)</title><p id="Par27">Before the surgical procedure, Phase 1 Therapy was done to improve the oral environment for better wound healing. All patients would receive prophylactic antibiotic therapy: 1&#x000a0;g of (amoxicillin&#x02009;+&#x02009;clavulanic acid &#x000b7;1000&#x000a0;mg b.d.s) (Amoxil MUP Egypt) every 12&#x000a0;h from the day before the surgery to the sixth post-surgical day. Patients rinsed with 0.2% chlorhexidine mouthwash (Antiseptol Kahira Pharm Egypt) for 1&#x000a0;min prior to any intervention. Local anesthesia was achieved using Articaine HCL 4% (Septodont LTD, Septanest 1:100,000) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>].</p><p id="Par28">The surgical treatment protocol entailed atraumatic tooth extraction without flap elevation, thereby maintaining the periosteal blood supply. The extraction socket was debrided of any granulation tissue, and rinsing with saline solution was done. Fully guided implant placement would be performed. In other words, not only was the osteotomy made through the guide, but also fixture insertion, thus ensuring two main benefits: one is ideal fixture placement without any slippage, and the other is to guarantee a high insertion torque (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p><bold>a</bold>&#x02013;<bold>f</bold> The steps of the surgical procedure, including atraumatic extraction, fully guided fixture placement, followed by placement of a prefabricated customized healing abutment</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40729_2025_624_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p><p id="Par29">Implants were inserted in the osteotomy site with the motor set at a torque of 30 Ncm and, once the motor stopped, implants were placed manually with a ratchet (Neobiotech) until they were at the same level as the inter-septal bone. The wrench used was able to perform torque measurements within a range of 15&#x02013;80&#x000a0;Ncm, with 5% precision. In case an implant was inserted with a torque inferior to 30&#x000a0;Ncm, a larger diameter implant would be used in order to obtain the required insertion torque, or to be excluded from the research [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>].</p><p id="Par30">After having completed the implant placement procedure, screw-retained prefabricated custom healing abutments were utilized. They were milled from polymethyl methacrylate (PMMA) blanks using a 5-axis milling machine with an accuracy of repetition equal to 1 micron.</p><p id="Par31">These Customized healing abutments were designed using Dental CAD software (Exocad, Darmstadt, Germany) and had the same natural emergence profile of the tooth to be extracted. The workflow involved the combination of intraoral and CBCT scans, from which three-dimensional (3D) reconstructions of soft tissue and alveolar bone, as well as of the tooth to be extracted were obtained and exported as STL files. The files were imported to the computer-aided design (CAD) software, in which a virtual wax-up and custom abutment design was performed considering the natural emergence profile of the patient&#x02019;s tooth prior to extraction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. Sequentially numbered envelopes corresponding to the patient were opened to know when to load the implant, either early (6&#x000a0;weeks) or conventionally (3&#x000a0;months).</p><p id="Par32">Postoperative care recommendations included 1&#x000a0;g of Amoxicillin and clavulanic acid every 12&#x000a0;h (this antibiotic regimen started 1&#x000a0;day before the surgery). Analgesics, mainly ibuprofen, up to 600&#x000a0;mg every 6&#x02013;8&#x000a0;h as needed, or Paracetamol 1&#x000a0;g for patients allergic to NSAIDs. Patients were advised to rinse the mouth with 0.12% chlorhexidine gluconate twice daily for 2&#x000a0;weeks. A soft diet was recommended for 1&#x000a0;week. No prosthesis that compressed the implant would be used during the entire implant healing period [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Prosthetic procedure</title><p id="Par33">At the end of the healing period, which was normally 6&#x000a0;weeks for the first group and 3&#x000a0;months for the second group, all patients received their final rehabilitation, i.e. occlusal loading restorations. Digital impressions were taken by a blinded operator. Deviations from these periods would only occur when patients were not able to make an appointment within the scheduled week, but this was limited to 5&#x000a0;days deviation; otherwise, the patient would be excluded from the research. Prosthodontic treatment was performed according to the manual provided by the manufacturer. All patients would receive monolithic zirconia screw-retained fixed prostheses (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p><bold>a</bold>&#x02013;<bold>c</bold> Monolithic zirconia glued on a titanium base utilizing a 3D-printed model. <bold>d</bold> Non-splinted screw-retained crowns were delivered to the patient</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40729_2025_624_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Data processing and assessment</title><sec id="Sec11"><title>Implant stability measurements</title><p id="Par34">In both groups, non-invasive quantitative analysis, such as resonance frequency analysis (RFA) and damping capacity analysis (DCA) were used to assess implant stability which was checked instantly after implant placement (T0) for both groups, 6&#x000a0;weeks after surgery (T1) for the first group and 3&#x000a0;months after surgical procedure for the second group (T2). To avoid unscrewing and re-screwing the implant superstructures (healing abutments of group 2 at (T1) and permanent crowns of group 1 at (T2), the implant stability was measured only at the time of implant scanning by scan bodies on the prosthetic phase. Two devices were used: Anycheck (Neobiotech, Seoul, Korea), which is a damping capacity method device that measures the time of contact between the impacting rod and the healing abutment. It strikes the healing abutment six times over three seconds and converts the time into the implant stability test (IST) values. This device strikes the healing abutment with less force compared to the Periotest M and has a function to stop automatically when the stability is low, to protect the implant [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. At 6&#x000a0;weeks after surgery (T1) for the first group and 3&#x000a0;months after surgical procedure for the second group (T2), the custom healing abutment is unscrewed, and a stock healing abutment with a standard height of 4&#x000a0;mm is tightened to guarantee a correct and reliable iST value. Another device, Penguin RFA, uses a sensor (autoclavable multi peg) coupled with an implant fixture and measures resonance frequency values that are converted into implant stability scale values called the implant stability quotient (ISQ) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p><bold>a</bold>, <bold>b</bold> Anycheck (damping capacity analysis) and Penguin (resonance frequency analysis) were used to measure the implant stability quotient</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40729_2025_624_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Radiographic assessment</title><p id="Par35">MBL was defined as loss, in an apical direction, of alveolar bone marginally adjacent to the dental implant, in relation to the marginal bone level initially detected after the implant was surgically placed.</p><p id="Par36">Patients in both groups will receive periapical x-ray instantly after the surgical procedure (T0) and 12&#x000a0;months later. The process of periapical radiograph acquisition at the clinic is standardized, using the long cone paralleling technique. The reference points for the measurements included the implant platform (the horizontal interface between the implant and the abutment), the implant apex, and the first bone-implant contact (FBIC). The length from the implant platform to the FBIC was defined as the marginal bone level. The marginal bone level was measured in mm using the ratio of the real implant length and the length from the implant platform to the apex on the images. Measurements were taken at both mesial and distal sides of each implant, and then the mean value of these two measurements was considered. The sets of radiographs for every patient were coded, and the doctor who performed the radiological measurements was blinded (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>).<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;5</label><caption><p><bold>a</bold>, <bold>b</bold> Periapical X-ray using long cone parallel technique and a phosphor imaging plate instantly after the surgical procedure (T0) and at 12&#x000a0;months follow-up to measure marginal bone loss (MBL)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40729_2025_624_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Patient satisfaction</title><p id="Par37">At delivery of definitive crowns and 12&#x000a0;months after loading, the local blind outcome assessors provided a mirror to the patients showing the implant-supported crown on which patients were asked to express their opinions. Specifically, the patients were asked, &#x02018;Are you satisfied with the function of your implant-supported tooth?&#x02019; Possible answers were &#x02018;yes absolutely&#x02019;, &#x02018;yes partly&#x02019;, &#x02018;not sure&#x02019;,&#x02019; not really&#x02019;, and &#x02018;absolutely not&#x02019;. Then they were asked, &#x02018;Are you satisfied with the aesthetic outcome of the gums surrounding this implant?&#x02019;. Possible answers were &#x02018;yes absolutely&#x02019;, &#x02018;yes partly&#x02019;, &#x02018;not sure&#x02019;, &#x02018;not really&#x02019;, and &#x02018;absolutely not&#x02019;. Finally, patients were asked whether they would undergo the same therapy again. Possible answers were &#x02018;yes&#x02019; or &#x02018;no&#x02019;. The questions were always posed with the same wording.</p><p id="Par38">The Primary outcome was the implant stability (the degree of osseointegration) measured by two methods: Damping capacity assessment by Anycheck (Neobiotech, Seoul, Korea) and Resonance frequency analysis by Penguin from Klockner.</p><p id="Par39">The Secondary outcomes were the peri-implant marginal bone level changes and Patient Satisfaction. Implant stability and marginal bone level changes were assessed by a blinded outcome assessor. Any complications and adverse events would be recorded [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par40">The statistical analysis was performed by an independent statistician who was not involved in the patient selection and enrollment process or the surgical procedures. The chi-square test was used to compare dichotomous variables (failures and complications). An unpaired Student&#x02019;s t-test was used as a test for differences in RFA, DCA, and MBL values between the trial arms. All statistical analyses&#x000a0;were&#x000a0;carried out by using a statistical software program (SAS version 9.4; SAS Institute).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Results</title><p id="Par41">Twenty-seven patients (15 women and 12 men) received a total of 30 implants immediately after molar extraction. The implanted sites were 7 maxillary first molars, 4 maxillary second molars, 9 mandibular first molars, and 10 mandibular second molars (Figs. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>, <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref> and <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>). After an uneventful healing period, the 30 implants were restored with screw retained monolithic zirconia prosthesis, half of which after 6&#x000a0;weeks (G1) and the other half after 3&#x000a0;months (G2). Normality was checked with QQ plots, histograms, and the Shapiro&#x02013;Wilk test. The Shapiro&#x02013;Wilk test suggests that the data does not significantly deviate from normality.<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;6</label><caption><p>A bar chart shows the insertion torque of each implant in both groups</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40729_2025_624_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig><fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;7</label><caption><p>A scatterplot shows missing teeth, insertion torque, and socket type</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40729_2025_624_Fig7_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig><fig id="Fig8"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;8</label><caption><p><bold>a</bold> A bar chart illustrates socket type distribution by group. <bold>b</bold> A pie chart shows the proportion of socket types</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40729_2025_624_Fig8_HTML" id="MO8"/></fig></p><p id="Par42">A log-rank test was calculated to see if there was a difference between the two groups, Early loading (G1) and Conventional loading (G2), in terms of survival rate. For the present data, the Kaplan&#x02013;Meier and log-rank test showed that there is no statistically significant difference between both groups, p&#x02009;=&#x02009;1. Therefore, the null hypothesis is not rejected (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>).<fig id="Fig9"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;9</label><caption><p>A line graph displays the analysis of resonance frequency and damping capacity at various time intervals for both groups</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40729_2025_624_Fig9_HTML" id="MO9"/></fig></p><p id="Par43">In the test group (G1), the average RFA values increased from 70.87 (SD 7.04) at the time of implant placement (T0) to 74.4 (SD5.54) after 6&#x000a0;weeks (T1). Also, the average DCA values increased from 73.73 (SD 8.27) to 79.07 (SD 5.75). Similarly, in the control group, the average RFA and DCA values were 69.2 (SD 7.81) and 73.53 (SD 10.76), respectively, at the time of implant placement (T0). After 3&#x000a0;months (T2), both increased to 73.67 (SD 5.7) and 78.93 (SD 4.48) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Shows the values of RFA and DCA for each implant in both groups</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="3">Number</th><th align="left" rowspan="3">Group</th><th align="left" colspan="6">Implant stability quotient</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="2">T0</th><th align="left" colspan="2">T1 (G1)</th><th align="left" colspan="2">T2 (G2)</th></tr><tr><th align="left">DCA</th><th align="left">RFA</th><th align="left">DCA</th><th align="left">RFA</th><th align="left">DCA</th><th align="left">RFA</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">G1</td><td align="left">87</td><td align="left">76</td><td align="left">86</td><td align="left">81</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">G2</td><td align="left">74</td><td align="left">69</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">80</td><td align="left">75</td></tr><tr><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">G2</td><td align="left">63</td><td align="left">55</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">88</td><td align="left">83</td></tr><tr><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">G1</td><td align="left">83</td><td align="left">70</td><td align="left">86</td><td align="left">76</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">G1</td><td align="left">61</td><td align="left">57</td><td align="left">75</td><td align="left">66</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">6</td><td align="left">G1</td><td align="left">79</td><td align="left">72</td><td align="left">83</td><td align="left">78</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">7</td><td align="left">G1</td><td align="left">76</td><td align="left">66</td><td align="left">88</td><td align="left">75</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">G2</td><td align="left">71</td><td align="left">65</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">71</td><td align="left">62</td></tr><tr><td align="left">9</td><td align="left">G1</td><td align="left">64</td><td align="left">59</td><td align="left">82</td><td align="left">76</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">10</td><td align="left">G2</td><td align="left">84</td><td align="left">75</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">71</td><td align="left">67</td></tr><tr><td align="left">11</td><td align="left">G1</td><td align="left">79</td><td align="left">73</td><td align="left">74</td><td align="left">69</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">12</td><td align="left">G2</td><td align="left">82</td><td align="left">80</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">80</td><td align="left">72</td></tr><tr><td align="left">13</td><td align="left">G2</td><td align="left">72</td><td align="left">69</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">82</td><td align="left">77</td></tr><tr><td align="left">14</td><td align="left">G2</td><td align="left">55</td><td align="left">60</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">80</td><td align="left">79</td></tr><tr><td align="left">15</td><td align="left">G2</td><td align="left">78</td><td align="left">63</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">83</td><td align="left">76</td></tr><tr><td align="left">16</td><td align="left">G1</td><td align="left">77</td><td align="left">81</td><td align="left">86</td><td align="left">80</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">17</td><td align="left">G1</td><td align="left">76</td><td align="left">75</td><td align="left">76</td><td align="left">70</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">18</td><td align="left">G2</td><td align="left">83</td><td align="left">77</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">78</td><td align="left">69</td></tr><tr><td align="left">19</td><td align="left">G1</td><td align="left">81</td><td align="left">73</td><td align="left">78</td><td align="left">72</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">20</td><td align="left">G1</td><td align="left">77</td><td align="left">79</td><td align="left">69</td><td align="left">64</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">21</td><td align="left">G2</td><td align="left">87</td><td align="left">77</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">81</td><td align="left">79</td></tr><tr><td align="left">22</td><td align="left">G2</td><td align="left">85</td><td align="left">79</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">75</td><td align="left">70</td></tr><tr><td align="left">23</td><td align="left">G2</td><td align="left">60</td><td align="left">65</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">82</td><td align="left">79</td></tr><tr><td align="left">24</td><td align="left">G1</td><td align="left">60</td><td align="left">63</td><td align="left">79</td><td align="left">71</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">25</td><td align="left">G2</td><td align="left">76</td><td align="left">73</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">77</td><td align="left">72</td></tr><tr><td align="left">26</td><td align="left">G2</td><td align="left">78</td><td align="left">72</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">80</td><td align="left">77</td></tr><tr><td align="left">27</td><td align="left">G1</td><td align="left">65</td><td align="left">70</td><td align="left">74</td><td align="left">80</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">28</td><td align="left">G1</td><td align="left">73</td><td align="left">78</td><td align="left">76</td><td align="left">82</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">29</td><td align="left">G1</td><td align="left">68</td><td align="left">71</td><td align="left">74</td><td align="left">76</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">30</td><td align="left">G2</td><td align="left">55</td><td align="left">59</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">76</td><td align="left">68</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par44">When comparing the mean of both RFA and DCA measurements between the control (G2) and the test group (G1), an unpaired Student&#x02019;s t-test revealed no statistically significant differences (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.724) (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.944), respectively.</p><p id="Par45">The radiographic analysis showed stable bone conditions with a maximum bone loss of 0.34&#x000a0;mm. The early loaded implants did not show different mean values from conventionally loaded implants after 12&#x000a0;months (test 0.17&#x000a0;mm, SD 0.07; control 0.18&#x000a0;mm, SD 0.08). The difference was statistically insignificant (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.639). Applying the Albrektsson radiographic success criteria, the overall implant success rate was 100% (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Shows the mean, standard deviation, minimum and maximum of RFA, DCA and MBL</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2"/><th align="left" colspan="5">G1</th><th align="left" colspan="5">G2</th></tr><tr><th align="left">DCA (T0)</th><th align="left">RFA (T0)</th><th align="left">DCA (T1)</th><th align="left">RFA (T1)</th><th align="left">MBL (mm)</th><th align="left">DCA (T0)</th><th align="left">RFA (T0)</th><th align="left">DCA (T2)</th><th align="left">RFA (T2)</th><th align="left">MBL (mm)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Mean</td><td align="left">73.73</td><td align="left">70.87</td><td align="left">79.07</td><td align="left">74.4</td><td char="." align="char">0.17</td><td align="left">73.53</td><td align="left">69.2</td><td align="left">78.93</td><td align="left">73.67</td><td char="." align="char">0.18</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Std. deviation</td><td align="left">8.27</td><td align="left">7.04</td><td align="left">5.75</td><td align="left">5.54</td><td char="." align="char">0.07</td><td align="left">10.76</td><td align="left">7.81</td><td align="left">4.48</td><td align="left">5.7</td><td char="." align="char">0.08</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Minimum</td><td align="left">60</td><td align="left">57</td><td align="left">69</td><td align="left">64</td><td char="." align="char">0.07</td><td align="left">55</td><td align="left">55</td><td align="left">71</td><td align="left">62</td><td char="." align="char">0.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Maximum</td><td align="left">87</td><td align="left">81</td><td align="left">88</td><td align="left">82</td><td char="." align="char">0.31</td><td align="left">87</td><td align="left">80</td><td align="left">88</td><td align="left">83</td><td char="." align="char">0.34</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="Fig10"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;10</label><caption><p>A box plot describing the marginal bone level changes in both groups</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40729_2025_624_Fig10_HTML" id="MO10"/></fig></p><p id="Par46">Patient satisfaction was assessed at the time of final prosthesis delivery (6&#x000a0;weeks for group 1 and 3&#x000a0;months for group 2) and at 12&#x000a0;months after loading. Regarding the function of the prostheses at the time of delivery, 13 patients of group 2 stated they were absolutely satisfied versus 11 patients of group 1; one patient from each group declared to be partially satisfied, and one patient from group 1 declared to be uncertain about the function of his crown. At 12&#x000a0;months after loading, 11 patients of the group 2 declared to be absolutely satisfied and three were partially satisfied versus all 13 patients who were absolutely satisfied in group 1. Regarding aesthetics, at the time of loading, all patients of both groups declared to be completely satisfied. At the 12-month follow-up, 12 patients of group 2 were absolutely satisfied and two were partially satisfied versus 12 patients who were absolutely satisfied and one who was partially satisfied in group 1. There was no statistically significant difference regarding function and aesthetic satisfaction between both groups (function satisfaction at time of delivery: <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.375, function satisfaction at 12&#x000a0;months follow up: <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.336; aesthetics satisfaction at time of delivery: <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.337, aesthetics satisfaction at 12&#x000a0;months follow up: <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.583). All patients declared that they would undergo the same procedure again, both at the time of prosthesis delivery and 12&#x000a0;months after loading.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par47">The primary outcome of this randomized, two-armed clinical trial was to compare implant stability between early (6&#x000a0;weeks) and conventionally loaded (3&#x000a0;months) implants placed immediately in fresh extraction molar sockets. As the survival rate was 100% for both groups and there was no statistical difference regarding implant stability (RFA, DCA), the first null hypothesis was accepted. The second null hypothesis was also accepted because there was no statistical difference regarding marginal bone loss or patient satisfaction between the groups.</p><p id="Par48">The insertion torque (IT) of the implant into the bone significantly affects the outcome of implant therapy; thus, the capability of some equipment to quantify and assess implant stability in an accurate manner has dramatically enhanced the efficacy and quality of implant procedures. The Penguin gadget measures the implant stability quotient (ISQ) by resonance frequency analysis (RFA), while the Anycheck device uses the percussion approach. In a recent study, Okuhama et al. compared the measures of the RFA device (Osstell) with damping capacity (Anycheck) in 7 patients with 15 implants. It was the first clinical study to conduct this comparison on a weekly basis for 6&#x000a0;weeks. There was a positive correlation between all measurement points (r&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.5) except week 1, with Anycheck usually providing slightly elevated values. The authors indicate comparable performance of both devices and highlight the superiority of Anycheck by eliminating the need to remove the healing abutment for each measurement, unlike RFA systems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. A lot of authors explain the risk of frequent removal of healing abutments and its role in crestal bone resorption [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>].</p><p id="Par49">The time factor is very important for the patient when considering implant procedures. Immediate implant placement in the esthetic zone is a very common operation and is usually executed with a high survival rate, reaching 98.4% at 2&#x000a0;years follow-up [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. Regarding the molar area, immediate placement usually seeks a more experienced operator due to the morphology of the socket after extraction and the closer to vital structures (Inferior alveolar canal and maxillary sinus). Tarnow and Smith classify implant placement into molar sockets and indicate high predictability and success rate when initial implant stability is achieved within the septal bone, either completely (type A socket), partially (type B socket), or by engaging the peripheral walls of the socket (type C socket). Should primary stability be unattainable, or in the absence of the buccal plate of bone for implant stabilization, a delayed procedure must be employed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>].</p><p id="Par50">A systematic review conducted by Esposito et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>], including 11 randomized trials and comparing the 3 protocols of implant loading (immediate vs. early vs. conventional loading), revealed no statistically significant differences between the 3 regimes for any of the parameters tested. Outcome measures were prosthesis failures, implant failures, and marginal bone levels. The authors highlighted the role of the operator's experience and high implant primary stability as prerequisites for a successful immediate/early loading procedure. Bone quality and quantity, implant macro design (thread depth and pitch), and surgical technique are among the factors affecting primary stability. A recent systematic review and meta-analysis demonstrated that implants placed in fresh extraction sockets at molar sites achieved survival rates of 96.6% during a minimum follow-up period of 1&#x000a0;year. The authors emphasize the significance of atraumatic extraction, a flapless technique, and primary stability to achieve a high success rate, minimize postoperative peri-implant tissue loss, reduce operative time, expedite post-surgical healing, diminish postoperative complications, and enhance patient comfort [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>].</p><p id="Par51">In the present study, the survival rate was 100% in both groups (either early loaded or conventionally loaded) until 1-year follow-up. The obtained results are in line with a recent study with long-term follow-up (3&#x000a0;years minimum) showing 96% survival and success rate with only one implant failed from 25 implants placed immediately in the molar site. All the implants were loaded conventionally (after 6&#x000a0;months of the surgical operation). The authors justify the cause of failure to socket infection and improper occlusion in this site [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. Contrary to these results, one study showed a high failure rate (73.3% survival rate) for immediate implants in molar sites. The authors highlight the role of implant macro design ( large thread depth with sharp thread edges and a small thread pitch) and implant diameter to have a large contact area with the socket bone and to attain adequate primary stability in various socket morphologies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>].</p><p id="Par52">In a systematic review by German Gallucci, 12 different intervention protocols, depending on the time of implant placement (immediate, early, and delayed) and time of loading (immediate, early, and conventional), were compared. The study revealed no scientific validation for some interventions, including type 1B procedure (Early loading of immediately placed implants) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. In the present study, the early-loaded group showed the same outcomes as conventional loading with no statistical difference regarding survival rate (100% survival rate of both groups), implant stability at the prosthetic phase (G1 RFA 74.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.54, DCA 79.07&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.75 vs G2 RFA 73.67&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.7 and 78.93&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.48) and marginal bone loss (G1 MBL 0.17&#x000a0;mm vs G2 MBL 0.18&#x000a0;mm). Esposito et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>] in a multi-center study compared immediate, early (6&#x000a0;weeks), and delayed loading (3&#x000a0;months) of single, partial, and full arch implant-supported prostheses, whether the implants were placed immediately in fresh extraction sockets or delayed in healed ridges. The results correspond well with our research, indicating preimplant marginal bone loss of 0.19&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.44&#x000a0;mm for immediately loaded implants, 0.18&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.66&#x000a0;mm for early loaded implants, and 0.25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.28&#x000a0;mm for conventionally loaded implants. No statistically significant differences were seen in complications (P&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.000) and bone loss (P&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.806) across the three loading techniques. Also, no instances of implant failure and few complications were documented; hence, all three procedures appear to be highly effective. In the previous study, the authors rationalized the good results obtained (100% success rate) to the high insertion torque. They stipulate plus 40 Ncm insertion torque for immediate and early loading protocols; otherwise, the loading will be delayed ( after 4&#x000a0;months).In instances of medium and soft bone quality, implant sites were inadequately prepared with drills that were one or two sizes smaller than the final implant diameter [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>].</p><p id="Par53">To our knowledge, this is the first clinical study that compares early loading to conventional loading in immediately placed implants in molar sites with non-splinted prostheses. The limitations of the study are the short follow-up period, the lack of investigation of soft tissue around the implant sites, and no homogeneity between the sockets included in the study.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par54">Considering the limitations of this study, early loading of fully guided immediately placed implants in molar sites may be considered a predictable treatment modality provided that ideal implant position and adequate insertion torque are achieved.</p></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>ITVs</term><def><p id="Par5">Insertion torque values</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RFA</term><def><p id="Par6">Resonance frequency analysis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DCA</term><def><p id="Par7">Damping capacity analysis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FBIC</term><def><p id="Par8">First bone-implant contact</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CAIS</term><def><p id="Par9">Computer-assisted implant surgery</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ISQ</term><def><p id="Par10">Implant stability quotient</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DLP</term><def><p id="Par11">Digital light processing</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PMMA</term><def><p id="Par12">Polymethyl methacrylate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>STL</term><def><p id="Par13">Standard tessellation language</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>All authors have made substantial contributions to the conception and design of the study A.K.E., H.A.A., and K.H.B., conceptualized and designed the study, D.AK., and A.K.E., have been involved in data collection and data analysis. A.K.E., K.H.B., H.A.A., and D.AK., have been involved in data interpretation, and drafting of the manuscript, A.K.E., H.A.A., and D.AK., revised it critically and have given final approval of the version to be published.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>Open access funding provided by The Science, Technology &#x00026; Innovation Funding Authority (STDF) in cooperation with The Egyptian Knowledge Bank (EKB). The study was self-funded.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>Data is available upon&#x000a0;reasonable request.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar2"><title>Human ethics and consent to participate declarations</title><p id="Par55">The study was approved by the Ain Shams Institutional Ethical Committee, Faculty of Dentistry, Ain Shams University (FDASU-RecIM112221). All patients were treated in accordance with regional laws, good clinical practice and in adherence to the Declaration of Helsinki (1996). In addition, the study was registered in clinical trial registration site (NCT06281535) on 24/02/2024.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par56">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar4" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par57">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pjetursson</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><name><surname>Br&#x000e4;gger</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Egger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zwahlen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A systematic review of the survival and complication rates of fixed partial dentures (FPDs) after an observation period of at least 5 years: I. Implant-supported FPDs</article-title><source>Clin Oral Implants Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>625</fpage><lpage>642</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-0501.2004.01117.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15533124</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Pjetursson BE, Tan K, Lang NP, Br&#x000e4;gger U, Egger M, Zwahlen M. A systematic review of the survival and complication rates of fixed partial dentures (FPDs) after an observation period of at least 5 years: I. Implant-supported FPDs. Clin Oral Implants Res. 2004;15:625&#x02013;42.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15533124</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Watzek</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Haider</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Mensdorff-Pouilly</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immediate and delayed implantation for complete restoration of the jaw following extraction of all residual teeth: a retrospective study comparing different types of serial immediate implantation</article-title><source>Int J Oral Maxillofac Implants</source><year>1995</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>561</fpage><lpage>567</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7591000</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Watzek G, Haider R, Mensdorff-Pouilly N, Haas R. Immediate and delayed implantation for complete restoration of the jaw following extraction of all residual teeth: a retrospective study comparing different types of serial immediate implantation. Int J Oral Maxillofac Implants. 1995;10:561&#x02013;7.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7591000</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Denissen</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalk</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Veldhuis</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>van Waas</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anatomic consideration for preventive implantation</article-title><source>Int J Oral Maxillofac Implants</source><year>1993</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>191</fpage><lpage>196</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8359876</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Denissen HW, Kalk W, Veldhuis HA, van Waas MA. Anatomic consideration for preventive implantation. Int J Oral Maxillofac Implants. 1993;8:191&#x02013;6.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8359876</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Br&#x000e5;nemark</surname><given-names>PI</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansson</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name><name><surname>Adell</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Breine</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindstr&#x000f6;m</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Osseointegrated implants in the treatment of the edentulous jaw. Experience from a 10-year period</article-title><source>Scand J Plast Reconstr Surg Suppl.</source><year>1977</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>132</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">356184</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Br&#x000e5;nemark PI, Hansson BO, Adell R, Breine U, Lindstr&#x000f6;m J, Hall&#x000e9;n O, et al. Osseointegrated implants in the treatment of the edentulous jaw. Experience from a 10-year period. Scand J Plast Reconstr Surg Suppl. 1977;16:1&#x02013;132.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">356184</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chiapasco</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Early and immediate restoration and loading of implants in completely edentulous patients</article-title><source>Int J Oral Maxillofac Implants</source><year>2004</year><volume>19</volume><issue>Suppl</issue><fpage>76</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15635948</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Chiapasco M. Early and immediate restoration and loading of implants in completely edentulous patients. Int J Oral Maxillofac Implants. 2004;19(Suppl):76&#x02013;91.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15635948</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abrahamsson</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Berglundh</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Linder</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindhe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Early bone formation adjacent to rough and turned endosseous implant surfaces. An experimental study in the dog</article-title><source>Clin Oral Implants Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>381</fpage><lpage>392</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-0501.2004.01082.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15248872</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Abrahamsson I, Berglundh T, Linder E, Lang NP, Lindhe J. Early bone formation adjacent to rough and turned endosseous implant surfaces. An experimental study in the dog. Clin Oral Implants Res. 2004;15:381&#x02013;92.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15248872</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buser</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Broggini</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Wieland</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schenk</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Denzer</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cochran</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Enhanced bone apposition to a chemically modified SLA titanium surface</article-title><source>J Dent Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>83</volume><fpage>529</fpage><lpage>533</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/154405910408300704</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15218041</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Buser D, Broggini N, Wieland M, Schenk RK, Denzer AJ, Cochran DL, et al. Enhanced bone apposition to a chemically modified SLA titanium surface. J Dent Res. 2004;83:529&#x02013;33.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15218041</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bornstein</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Valderrama</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name><surname>Seibl</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Cochran</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bone apposition around two different sandblasted and acid-etched titanium implant surfaces: a histomorphometric study in canine mandibles</article-title><source>Clin Oral Implants Res</source><year>2008</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>233</fpage><lpage>241</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-0501.2007.01473.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18177427</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Bornstein MM, Valderrama P, Jones AA, Wilson TG, Seibl R, Cochran DL. Bone apposition around two different sandblasted and acid-etched titanium implant surfaces: a histomorphometric study in canine mandibles. Clin Oral Implants Res. 2008;19:233&#x02013;41.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18177427</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Aldhohrah</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immediate versus early or conventional loading dental implants with fixed prostheses: a systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized controlled clinical trials</article-title><source>J Prosthet Dent</source><year>2019</year><volume>122</volume><fpage>516</fpage><lpage>536</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.prosdent.2019.05.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31421892</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Chen J, Cai M, Yang J, Aldhohrah T, Wang Y. Immediate versus early or conventional loading dental implants with fixed prostheses: a systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized controlled clinical trials. J Prosthet Dent. 2019;122:516&#x02013;36.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31421892</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Esposito</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Grusovin</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Willings</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Coulthard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Worthington</surname><given-names>HV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effectiveness of immediate, early, and conventional loading of dental implants: a cochrane systematic review of randomized controlled clinical trials</article-title><source>Br Dent J</source><year>2008</year><volume>204</volume><fpage>559</fpage><lpage>559</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.bdj.2008.407</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Esposito M, Grusovin MG, Willings M, Coulthard P, Worthington HV. The effectiveness of immediate, early, and conventional loading of dental implants: a cochrane systematic review of randomized controlled clinical trials. Br Dent J. 2008;204:559&#x02013;559.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Markovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Todorovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gli&#x00161;i&#x00107;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Markovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ili&#x00107;</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Janji&#x00107;</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Immediate versus early loading of immediately placed bone-level tapered dental implants with hydrophilic surface in full arch maxillary rehabilitation: a pilot randomized clinical trial with 2-year follow-up</article-title><source>Clin Implant Dent Relat Res</source><year>2024</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>688</fpage><lpage>703</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/cid.13334</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38693759</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Markovi&#x00107; A, Todorovi&#x00107; A, Gli&#x00161;i&#x00107; M, Markovi&#x00107; J, Ili&#x00107; B, Janji&#x00107; B, et al. Immediate versus early loading of immediately placed bone-level tapered dental implants with hydrophilic surface in full arch maxillary rehabilitation: a pilot randomized clinical trial with 2-year follow-up. Clin Implant Dent Relat Res. 2024;26:688&#x02013;703.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38693759</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meredith</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of implant stability as a prognostic determinant</article-title><source>Int J Prosthodont</source><year>1998</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>491</fpage><lpage>501</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9922740</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Meredith N. Assessment of implant stability as a prognostic determinant. Int J Prosthodont. 1998;11:491&#x02013;501.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9922740</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sennerby</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Surgical determinants of clinical success of osseointegrated oral implants: a review of the literature</article-title><source>Int J Prosthodont</source><year>1998</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>408</fpage><lpage>420</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9922733</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Sennerby L, Roos J. Surgical determinants of clinical success of osseointegrated oral implants: a review of the literature. Int J Prosthodont. 1998;11:408&#x02013;20.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9922733</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogata</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaoka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogiso</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A no-contact vibration device for measuring implant stability</article-title><source>Clin Oral Implants Res</source><year>2010</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>931</fpage><lpage>936</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-0501.2010.01934.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20491836</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Hayashi M, Kobayashi C, Ogata H, Yamaoka M, Ogiso B. A no-contact vibration device for measuring implant stability. Clin Oral Implants Res. 2010;21:931&#x02013;6.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20491836</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ostman</surname><given-names>P-O</given-names></name><name><surname>Hellman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wendelhag</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Sennerby</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Resonance frequency analysis measurements of implants at placement surgery</article-title><source>Int J Prosthodont</source><year>2006</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16479765</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Ostman P-O, Hellman M, Wendelhag I, Sennerby L. Resonance frequency analysis measurements of implants at placement surgery. Int J Prosthodont. 2006;19:77&#x02013;83 (<bold>discussion 84</bold>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16479765</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sennerby</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Meredith</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Implant stability measurements using resonance frequency analysis: biological and biomechanical aspects and clinical implications</article-title><source>Periodontol</source><year>2000</year><volume>2008</volume><issue>47</issue><fpage>51</fpage><lpage>66</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Sennerby L, Meredith N. Implant stability measurements using resonance frequency analysis: biological and biomechanical aspects and clinical implications. Periodontol. 2000;2008(47):51&#x02013;66.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tahmaseb</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wismeijer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Coucke</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Derksen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Computer technology applications in surgical implant dentistry: a systematic review</article-title><source>Int J Oral Maxillofac Implants</source><year>2014</year><volume>29</volume><issue>Suppl</issue><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.11607/jomi.2014suppl.g1.2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24660188</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Tahmaseb A, Wismeijer D, Coucke W, Derksen W. Computer technology applications in surgical implant dentistry: a systematic review. Int J Oral Maxillofac Implants. 2014;29(Suppl):25&#x02013;42.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24660188</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Varga</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Antal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Major</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiscsat&#x000e1;ri</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Braunitzer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Piffk&#x000f3;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Guidance means accuracy: a randomized clinical trial on freehand versus guided dental implantation</article-title><source>Clin Oral Implants Res</source><year>2020</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>417</fpage><lpage>430</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/clr.13578</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31958166</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Varga E, Antal M, Major L, Kiscsat&#x000e1;ri R, Braunitzer G, Piffk&#x000f3; J. Guidance means accuracy: a randomized clinical trial on freehand versus guided dental implantation. Clin Oral Implants Res. 2020;31:417&#x02013;30.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31958166</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Putra</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoda</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Astuti</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The accuracy of implant placement with computer-guided surgery in partially edentulous patients and possible influencing factors: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>J Prosthodont Res</source><year>2022</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>39</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2186/jpr.JPR_D_20_00184</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33504723</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Putra RH, Yoda N, Astuti ER, Sasaki K. The accuracy of implant placement with computer-guided surgery in partially edentulous patients and possible influencing factors: a systematic review and meta-analysis. J Prosthodont Res. 2022;66:29&#x02013;39.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33504723</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gallucci</surname><given-names>GO</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Buser</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Implant placement and loading protocols in partially edentulous patients: a systematic review</article-title><source>Clin Oral Implants Res</source><year>2018</year><volume>29 suppl 166</volume><fpage>106</fpage><lpage>134</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/clr.13276</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30328194</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">Gallucci GO, Hamilton A, Zhou W, Buser D, Chen S. Implant placement and loading protocols in partially edentulous patients: a systematic review. Clin Oral Implants Res. 2018;29 suppl 166:106&#x02013;34.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30328194</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>World Medical Association</collab></person-group><article-title>WMA Declaration of Helsinki: ethical principles for medical research involving human subjects</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>1974</year><volume>353</volume><fpage>1418</fpage><lpage>1419</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">World Medical Association. WMA Declaration of Helsinki: ethical principles for medical research involving human subjects. JAMA. 1974;353:1418&#x02013;9.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Milillo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Fiandaca</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Giannoulis</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ottria</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucchese</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Silvestre</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Immediate vs non-immediate loading post-extractive implants: a comparative study of Implant Stability Quotient (ISQ)</article-title><source>ORAL Implantol</source><year>2016</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>131</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">Milillo L, Fiandaca C, Giannoulis F, Ottria L, Lucchese A, Silvestre F, et al. Immediate vs non-immediate loading post-extractive implants: a comparative study of Implant Stability Quotient (ISQ). ORAL Implantol. 2016;9:123&#x02013;31.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Samarani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Tohme</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sbricoli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immediate, early (3 weeks) and conventional loading (4 months) of single implants: preliminary data at 1 year after loading from a pragmatic multicenter randomised controlled trial</article-title><source>Artic Eur J Oral Implantol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>126</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Samarani R, Tohme H, Sbricoli L. Immediate, early (3 weeks) and conventional loading (4 months) of single implants: preliminary data at 1 year after loading from a pragmatic multicenter randomised controlled trial. Artic Eur J Oral Implantol. 2015;8:115&#x02013;26.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Tarnow</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Classification of molar extraction sites for immediate dental implant placement: technical note</article-title><source>Int J Oral Maxillofac Implants</source><year>2013</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>911</fpage><lpage>916</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.11607/jomi.2627</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23748327</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">Smith RB, Tarnow DP. Classification of molar extraction sites for immediate dental implant placement: technical note. Int J Oral Maxillofac Implants. 2013;28:911&#x02013;6.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23748327</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Man</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A prospective cohort study of immediate implant placement into posterior compromised sockets with or without primary wound closure of reactive soft tissue</article-title><source>Clin Implant Dent Relat Res</source><year>2020</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/cid.12845</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31755640</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="journal">Liu Y, Chen Y, Chu C, Qu Y, Xiang L, Man Y. A prospective cohort study of immediate implant placement into posterior compromised sockets with or without primary wound closure of reactive soft tissue. Clin Implant Dent Relat Res. 2020;22:13&#x02013;20.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31755640</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR26" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdelhay</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Walters</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibiotic prophylaxis for implant placement: a systematic review of effects on reduction of implant failure</article-title><source>Br Dent J</source><year>2020</year><volume>228</volume><fpage>943</fpage><lpage>951</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41415-020-1649-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32591710</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26" publication-type="journal">Kim A, Abdelhay N, Levin L, Walters JD, Gibson MP. Antibiotic prophylaxis for implant placement: a systematic review of effects on reduction of implant failure. Br Dent J. 2020;228:943&#x02013;51.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32591710</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Aparicio C, Rangert B, Eng M, Sennerby L. Immediate/early loading of dental implants: a Report from the Sociedad Espanola de Implantes World Congress Consensus Meeting in Barcelona, Spain, 2002.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR28" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>e Costa</surname><given-names>AJM</given-names></name><name><surname>Burgoa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rayes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>da Silva</surname><given-names>RLB</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayres</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Cortes</surname><given-names>ARG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Digital workflow for CAD-CAM custom abutments of immediate implants based on natural emergence profile of the tooth to be extracted</article-title><source>J Oral Implantol</source><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1563/aaid-joi-D-20-00214</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28" publication-type="journal">e Costa AJM, Burgoa S, Rayes A, da Silva RLB, Ayres AP, Cortes ARG. Digital workflow for CAD-CAM custom abutments of immediate implants based on natural emergence profile of the tooth to be extracted. J Oral Implantol. 2021. 10.1563/aaid-joi-D-20-00214.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR29" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shibly</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Kutkut</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Albandar</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immediate implants with immediate loading vs. conventional loading: 1-year randomized clinical trial</article-title><source>Clin Implant Dent Relat Res</source><year>2012</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>663</fpage><lpage>671</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1708-8208.2010.00310.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20977611</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29" publication-type="journal">Shibly O, Kutkut A, Patel N, Albandar JM. Immediate implants with immediate loading vs. conventional loading: 1-year randomized clinical trial. Clin Implant Dent Relat Res. 2012;14:663&#x02013;71.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20977611</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR30" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Shim</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The reliability of Anycheck device related to healing abutment diameter</article-title><source>J Adv Prosthodont</source><year>2020</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>83</fpage><lpage>88</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4047/jap.2020.12.2.83</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32377321</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30" publication-type="journal">Lee DH, Shin YH, Park JH, Shim JS, Shin SW, Lee JY. The reliability of Anycheck device related to healing abutment diameter. J Adv Prosthodont. 2020;12:83&#x02013;8.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32377321</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR31" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Okuhama</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagata</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsuruoka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Atsumi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawana</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Validation of an implant stability measurement device using the percussion response: a clinical research study</article-title><source>BMC Oral Health</source><year>2022</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>4</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12903-022-02320-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35012519</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR31" publication-type="journal">Okuhama Y, Nagata K, Kim H, Tsuruoka H, Atsumi M, Kawana H. Validation of an implant stability measurement device using the percussion response: a clinical research study. BMC Oral Health. 2022;22:4&#x02013;9.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35012519</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR32" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Esposito</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bressan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Grusovin</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x02019;Avenia</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Neumann</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sbricoli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Do repeated changes of abutments have any influence on the stability of peri-implant tissues One-year post-loading results from a multicentre randomised controlled trial</article-title><source>Eur J Oral Implantol</source><year>2017</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>57</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28327695</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32" publication-type="journal">Esposito M, Bressan E, Grusovin MG, D&#x02019;Avenia F, Neumann K, Sbricoli L, et al. Do repeated changes of abutments have any influence on the stability of peri-implant tissues One-year post-loading results from a multicentre randomised controlled trial. Eur J Oral Implantol. 2017;10:57&#x02013;72.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28327695</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR33" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bressan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Grusovin</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x02019;Avenia</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Neumann</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sbricoli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Luongo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The influence of repeated abutment changes on peri-implant tissue stability: 3-year post-loading results from a multicentre randomised controlled trial</article-title><source>Eur J Oral Implantol</source><year>2017</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>373</fpage><lpage>390</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29234745</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR33" publication-type="journal">Bressan E, Grusovin MG, D&#x02019;Avenia F, Neumann K, Sbricoli L, Luongo G, et al. The influence of repeated abutment changes on peri-implant tissue stability: 3-year post-loading results from a multicentre randomised controlled trial. Eur J Oral Implantol. 2017;10:373&#x02013;90.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29234745</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR34" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><name><surname>Pun</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>MCM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A systematic review on survival and success rates of implants placed immediately into fresh extraction sockets after at least 1 year</article-title><source>Clin Oral Implants Res</source><year>2012</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>39</fpage><lpage>66</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-0501.2011.02372.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22211305</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR34" publication-type="journal">Lang NP, Pun L, Lau KY, Li KY, Wong MCM. A systematic review on survival and success rates of implants placed immediately into fresh extraction sockets after at least 1 year. Clin Oral Implants Res. 2012;23:39&#x02013;66.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22211305</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR35" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ragucci</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Elnayef</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Criado-C&#x000e1;mara</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Del Amo</surname><given-names>FS-L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hern&#x000e1;ndez-Alfaro</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immediate implant placement in molar extraction sockets: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Int J Implant Dent</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40729-020-00235-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32770283</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR35" publication-type="journal">Ragucci GM, Elnayef B, Criado-C&#x000e1;mara E, Del Amo FS-L, Hern&#x000e1;ndez-Alfaro F. Immediate implant placement in molar extraction sockets: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Int J Implant Dent. 2020. 10.1186/s40729-020-00235-5.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32770283</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR36" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wipawin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Amornsettachai</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Panyayong</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Rokaya</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiradilok</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pujarern</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clinical outcomes of 3&#x02013;5 years follow-up of immediate implant placement in posterior teeth: a prospective study</article-title><source>BMC Oral Health</source><year>2024</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12903-024-04058-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38167114</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR36" publication-type="journal">Wipawin R, Amornsettachai P, Panyayong W, Rokaya D, Thiradilok S, Pujarern P, et al. Clinical outcomes of 3&#x02013;5 years follow-up of immediate implant placement in posterior teeth: a prospective study. BMC Oral Health. 2024;24:1&#x02013;11.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38167114</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR37" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meijer</surname><given-names>HJA</given-names></name><name><surname>Raghoebar</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immediate implant placement in molar extraction sites: a 1-year prospective case series pilot study</article-title><source>Int J Implant Dent.</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40729-019-0201-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32588142</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR37" publication-type="journal">Meijer HJA, Raghoebar GM. Immediate implant placement in molar extraction sites: a 1-year prospective case series pilot study. Int J Implant Dent. 2020. 10.1186/s40729-019-0201-7.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32588142</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR38" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pistilli</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitsias</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Esposito</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Siormpas</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sbricoli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Buti</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Immediate, early (6 weeks) and delayed loading (3 months) of single, partial and full fixed implant-supported prostheses: three-year post-loading data from a multicentre randomised controlled trial</article-title><source>Clin Trials Dent</source><year>2019</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.36130/CTD.01.2019.04</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR38" publication-type="journal">Pistilli R, Mitsias M, Esposito M, Siormpas K, Sbricoli L, Buti J, et al. Immediate, early (6 weeks) and delayed loading (3 months) of single, partial and full fixed implant-supported prostheses: three-year post-loading data from a multicentre randomised controlled trial. Clin Trials Dent. 2019;1:37&#x02013;50.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR39" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ottoni</surname><given-names>JMP</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>ZFL</given-names></name><name><surname>Mansini</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Cabral</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Correlation between placement torque and survival of single-tooth implants</article-title><source>Int J Oral Maxillofac Implants</source><year>2005</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>769</fpage><lpage>776</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16274152</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR39" publication-type="journal">Ottoni JMP, Oliveira ZFL, Mansini R, Cabral AM. Correlation between placement torque and survival of single-tooth implants. Int J Oral Maxillofac Implants. 2005;20:769&#x02013;76.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16274152</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR40" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cannizzaro</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Leone</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferri</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Viola</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Federico</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Esposito</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immediate loading of single implants inserted flapless with medium or high insertion torque: a 6-month follow-up of a split-mouth randomised controlled trial</article-title><source>Eur J Oral Implantol</source><year>2012</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>333</fpage><lpage>342</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23304687</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR40" publication-type="journal">Cannizzaro G, Leone M, Ferri V, Viola P, Federico G, Esposito M. Immediate loading of single implants inserted flapless with medium or high insertion torque: a 6-month follow-up of a split-mouth randomised controlled trial. Eur J Oral Implantol. 2012;5:333&#x02013;42.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23304687</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article>