<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="editorial"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Aging Neurosci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Aging Neurosci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Aging Neurosci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Aging Neuroscience</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1663-4365</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40013093</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11861522</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnagi.2025.1568173</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Aging Neuroscience</subject><subj-group><subject>Editorial</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Editorial: To Know or Not to Know: causes and evolution of lack of awareness of cognitive decline in neurodegenerative diseases, volume II</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cacciamani</surname><given-names>Federica</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1298478/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Nielson</surname><given-names>Kristy A.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/54475/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hanseeuw</surname><given-names>Bernard J.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/431390/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gagliardi</surname><given-names>Geoffroy P.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff7" ref-type="aff">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff8" ref-type="aff">
<sup>8</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1306091/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vannini</surname><given-names>Patrizia</given-names></name><xref rid="aff7" ref-type="aff">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff8" ref-type="aff">
<sup>8</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1232232/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>ARAMISLab, Institut du Cerveau - Paris Brain Institute - ICM, Sorbonne Universit&#x000e9;, CNRS, Inria, Inserm, AP-HP, H&#x000f4;pital de la Piti&#x000e9; Salp&#x000ea;tri&#x000e8;re</institution>, <addr-line>Paris</addr-line>, <country>France</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Qairnel SAS</institution>, <addr-line>Paris</addr-line>, <country>France</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Department of Psychology, Marquette University</institution>, <addr-line>Milwaukee, WI</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup><institution>Department of Neurology, Medical College of Wisconsin</institution>, <addr-line>Milwaukee, WI</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff5"><sup>5</sup><institution>Department of Radiology, Massachusetts General Hospital, The Gordon Center for Medical Imaging</institution>, <addr-line>Boston, MA</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff6"><sup>6</sup><institution>Department of Neurology, Cliniques Universitaires Saint-Luc, Universit&#x000e9; Catholique de Louvain</institution>, <addr-line>Brussels</addr-line>, <country>Belgium</country></aff><aff id="aff7"><sup>7</sup><institution>Brigham and Women's Hospital and Harvard Medical School</institution>, <addr-line>Boston, MA</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff8"><sup>8</sup><institution>Massachusetts General Hospital and Harvard Medical School</institution>, <addr-line>Boston, MA</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited and reviewed by: Nadine Correia Santos, University of Minho, Portugal</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Kristy A. Nielson <email>kristy.nielson@marquette.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>17</volume><elocation-id>1568173</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>04</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2025 Cacciamani, Nielson, Hanseeuw, Gagliardi and Vannini.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Cacciamani, Nielson, Hanseeuw, Gagliardi and Vannini</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><related-article related-article-type="commentary-article" id="RA1" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/research-topics/55251/to-know-or-not-to-know-causes-and-evolution-of-lack-of-awareness-of-cognitive-decline-in-neurodegenerative-diseases-volume-ii" ext-link-type="uri">Editorial on the Research Topic <article-title>To Know or Not to Know: causes and evolution of lack of awareness of cognitive decline in neurodegenerative diseases, volume II</article-title></related-article><kwd-group><kwd>anosognosia</kwd><kwd>subjective cognitive decline</kwd><kwd>Alzheimer's disease</kwd><kwd>self-awareness</kwd><kwd>denial</kwd><kwd>neuroimaging</kwd><kwd>biomarkers</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn001"><institution-wrap><institution>National Institutes of Health</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100000002</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id award-type="contract" rid="cn001">R01AG061083</award-id><award-id award-type="contract" rid="cn001">R15HD083086</award-id><award-id award-type="contract" rid="cn001">R21NS121624</award-id><award-id award-type="contract" rid="cn001">R56AG078366</award-id></award-group><funding-statement>The author(s) declare financial support was received for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article. PV was supported by the National Institute on Aging (NIA) and National Institutes of Health (NIH) R01AG061083 during the conduct of this Research Topic; KN was supported by R56AG078366, R21NS121624, and R15HD093086.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="0"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="12"/><page-count count="3"/><word-count count="2182"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>section-at-acceptance</meta-name><meta-value>Neurocognitive Aging and Behavior</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Anosognosia, or the lack of awareness of cognitive, behavioral, or functional deficits, represents a critical challenge in the clinical management of neurodegenerative diseases such as Alzheimer's disease (AD) and frontotemporal dementia. This condition not only impacts patients, caregivers, and healthcare systems (D'Souza et al., <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Turr&#x000f3;-Garriga et al., <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>) but also raises important questions about its underlying mechanisms and evolution (Hanseeuw et al., <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Starkstein, <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Vannini et al., <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Despite its critical importance, significant gaps remain in our understanding of cognitive self-awareness in neurodegenerative diseases. Building on the momentum of the first edition of To Know or Not to Know, this second volume continues to explore these pressing issues through innovative approaches and multidisciplinary perspectives. The eight articles in this volume span a diverse range of themes and methodologies, reflecting the multifaceted nature and importance of awareness research.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>The link between subjective cognitive decline, hypernosognosia, and anosognosia</title><p>Recent research, including findings from Volume I of this Research Topic (Chapman et al., <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>), suggests that subjective cognitive decline (SCD), hypernosognosia, and anosognosia may represent distinct yet interconnected states of awareness in AD. SCD refers to self-reported cognitive complaints, which may or may not be accompanied by objective cognitive decline (Jessen et al., <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). The concept has been the subject of debate within the field, wherein SCD has been demonstrated to be prone to biases and may be non-specific for neurodegenerative processes (Cacciamani et al., <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">2023</xref>). Given the heterogeneity of self-reported cognitive complaints and their possible association with factors such as mood, comorbidities, and lifestyle, SCD may benefit from refined characterization and stratification to enhance its predictive value for neurodegenerative processes. This would allow for a clearer distinction between individuals whose complaints are driven by early AD pathology vs. those influenced by non-pathological factors. For example, there may be specific subgroups where SCD is more strongly linked to underlying AD pathology. <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fnagi.2023.1067196" ext-link-type="uri">Ben-Ami et al.</ext-link> provide compelling evidence for this hypothesis. In cognitively normal middle-aged individuals with a family history of AD and the Apolipoprotein-E (APOE) &#x003b5;4 genotype, higher subjective cognitive decline (SCD) was associated with disrupted white matter integrity, notably in the uncinate fasciculus, and abnormal brain activity, specifically elevated frontal activity, during a working memory task. These findings corroborate a recent study showing that &#x003b5;4 carriers had significantly poorer self-awareness of their objective executive functioning than comparable non-carriers (Evans et al., <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>). Taken together, these findings suggest that functional neural alterations may index early AD pathology in those exhibiting altered neural mechanisms related to self-perceived cognitive decline, particularly in &#x003b5;4 carriers, even in the absence of detectable objective deficits. While SCD and anosognosia differ in clinical presentation, alterations in self-monitoring processes may point to similar mechanisms being triggered as AD pathology progresses. Indeed, even during resting-state measures, anosognosia has been linked to disrupted neural network functioning. Using resting-state fMRI, <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fnagi.2024.1415994" ext-link-type="uri">Tondelli et al.</ext-link> found anosognosia to be associated with decreased intrinsic functional connectivity in the default mode network and increased connectivity in the salience network. They suggest that this &#x0201c;imbalance&#x0201d; between self-referential networks may contribute to anosognosia, even in the absence of direct structural damage.</p><p>Hypernosognosia, on the other hand, refers to heightened self-awareness of cognitive changes (Vannini et al., <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>), marked by cognitive complaints that are not corroborated by informants or objective assessments. Studies suggested that in the early stages of AD, hypernosognosia may give way to anosognosia as the disease progresses, with awareness declining further during the prodromal phase and dementia onset. <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fnagi.2024.1394460" ext-link-type="uri">L&#x000f3;pez-Martos et al.</ext-link> provided further evidence in this Research Topic. Among cognitively normal individuals reporting complaints, hypernosognosia was associated with higher amyloid-beta levels. Conversely, in individuals without complaints, awareness followed a non-linear trajectory, increasing up to a specific amyloid-beta threshold before declining thereafter, consistent with previous findings (Gagliardi et al., <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Implications of anosognosia for caregivers</title><p>Caregiving in AD presents unique challenges, as caregivers often shoulder the dual burden of managing the patient's evolving cognitive and functional decline while coping with their own emotional and physical strain (Starkstein et al., <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). Anosognosia exacerbates these challenges by limiting the patient's ability to recognize their deficits, leading to increased caregiver stress and complicating care strategies (Turr&#x000f3;-Garriga et al., <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). In a large cohort of cohabitating spouse-patient dyads where the patient was diagnosed with dementia, <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fnagi.2023.1277336" ext-link-type="uri">Alexander et al.</ext-link> highlighted these issues showing that caregiver reports of their spouse's cognitive difficulties were greater than the spouse's own reports. Lower concordance between patient and caregiver assessments was significantly associated with reduced patient autonomy and increased levels of perceived caregiver stress. Similarly, <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fnagi.2024.1384812" ext-link-type="uri">Marks et al.</ext-link> showed participants with poorer awareness of their performance during tasks involving planning were more dependent on activities of daily living (ADL) and exhibited worse cognitive function. These findings underscore the importance of assessing awareness to anticipate caregiving needs and plan for appropriate interventions. Relatedly, <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fnagi.2024.1335878" ext-link-type="uri">Wang et al.</ext-link> found that individuals with MCI and anosognosia from the ADNI cohort developed neuropsychiatric symptoms earlier than those without anosognosia. Relevant symptoms included delusions, hallucinations, agitation, apathy, disinhibition, irritability, and aberrant motor behavior. Anosognosia may thus increase vulnerability to neuropsychiatric symptoms and highlight the need for caregiver support and services.</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Distinguishing anosognosia from denial</title><p>Anosognosia and denial, though distinct, can appear deceptively similar in clinical practice, often complicating diagnosis and care. Differentiating the two is crucial for developing appropriate therapeutic strategies, understanding patient behaviors, and ensuring that interventions are both effective and compassionate. <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fnagi.2023.1325231" ext-link-type="uri">Prigatano et al.</ext-link> explored the distinction between anosognosia and denial through case studies, defining anosognosia as a neurological inability to recognize cognitive deficits, and denial as a psychological defense mechanism. The authors proposed a scoring system to differentiate these conditions, which involves characterizing denial as (1) involving emotional responses such as anxiety, agitation, or anger when difficulties are discussed; (2) the ability to recognize when behaviors affect others, which is not consistent with anosognosia; and (3) actively resisting the acknowledgment of deficits through counterarguments or avoiding discussion.</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>The use of virtual reality to improve self-awareness in AD</title><p>Interventions to address anosognosia in AD remain limited, despite the profound impact this condition has on disease management and patient outcomes. Traditional therapeutic approaches have shown little success in improving self-awareness, underscoring the need for innovative methods. In this context, <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fnagi.2024.1376413" ext-link-type="uri">Latg&#x000e9;-Tovar et al.</ext-link> proposed virtual reality as a promising tool for both the assessment and improvement of self-awareness, including disease awareness, in AD. They propose the creation of immersive and ecological experiences based on perspective-taking. The authors reviewed the possibilities and potential limitations of this approach and highlighted the need for further research to validate its efficacy and applicability.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Conclusion and future directions</title><p>While this important second Research Topic advances our understanding of anosognosia in AD, we acknowledge that significant gaps remain. Notably, the scarcity of longitudinal data limits our ability to fully map how awareness changes in individuals over time, and how it relates to the emergence to AD pathology and other clinical symptoms. Similarly, more research is needed to refine diagnostic tools, develop effective interventions, and explore the interplay between biological, psychological, and social determinants of awareness.</p><p>We hope this Research Topic inspires further exploration into this critical area and serves as a resource for researchers and clinicians dedicated to advancing the field of aging neuroscience.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>We gratefully acknowledge all the authors and reviewers who participated in this Research Topic.</p></ack><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="s7"><title>Author contributions</title><p>FC: Conceptualization, Writing &#x02013; original draft, Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing. KN: Writing &#x02013; original draft, Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing. BH: Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing. GG: Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing. PV: Writing &#x02013; original draft, Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest. The author(s) declared that they were an editorial board member of Frontiers, at the time of submission. This had no impact on the peer review process and the final decision.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s9"><title>Publisher's note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cacciamani</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bercu</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouteloup</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grasset</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Planche</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ch&#x000ea;ne</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2023</year>). <article-title>Understanding factors associated with the trajectory of subjective cognitive complaints in groups with similar objective cognitive trajectories</article-title>. <source>Alzheimers Res. Ther</source>. <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>205</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13195-023-01348-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37993894</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Joyce</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sunderaraman</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rizer</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huey</surname><given-names>E. D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2022</year>). <article-title>Subjective cognitive decline is more accurate when metamemory is better</article-title>. <source>Front. Aging Neurosci</source>. <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>787552</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnagi.2022.787552</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35370602</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>D'Souza</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Egan</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rees</surname><given-names>C. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>The relationship between perfectionism, stress and burnout in clinical psychologists</article-title>. <source>Behav. Change</source>
<volume>28</volume>, <fpage>17</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>28</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1375/bech.28.1.17</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paitel</surname><given-names>E. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhasin</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielson</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2024</year>). <article-title>Genetic risk for Alzheimer's disease alters perceived executive dysfunction in cognitively healthy middle-aged and older adults</article-title>. <source>J. Alzheimers Dis. Rep</source>. <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>267</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>279</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3233/ADR-230166</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38405345</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gagliardi</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Houot</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cacciamani</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Habert</surname><given-names>M-. O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubois</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Epelbaum</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>The meta-memory ratio: a new cohort-independent way to measure cognitive awareness in asymptomatic individuals at risk for Alzheimer's disease</article-title>. <source>Alzheimers Res. Ther</source>. <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>57</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13195-020-00626-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32408882</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hanseeuw</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sikkes</surname><given-names>S. A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Properzi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gatchel</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salmon</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Evolution of anosognosia in Alzheimer's disease and its relationship to amyloid</article-title>. <source>Ann. Neurol</source>. <volume>87</volume>, <fpage>267</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>280</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ana.25649</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31750553</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jessen</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Amariglio</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buckley</surname><given-names>R. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Der Flier</surname><given-names>W. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Molinuevo</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>The characterisation of subjective cognitive decline</article-title>. <source>Lancet Neurol</source>. <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>271</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>278</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1474-4422(19)30368-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31958406</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Starkstein</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Anosognosia in Alzheimer's disease: diagnosis, frequency, mechanism and clinical correlates</article-title>. <source>Cortex</source>
<volume>61</volume>, <fpage>64</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>73</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cortex.2014.07.019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25481465</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Starkstein</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jorge</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizrahi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adrian</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>R. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Insight and danger in Alzheimer's disease</article-title>. <source>Eur. J. Neurol</source>. <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>455</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>460</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1468-1331.2007.01745.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17388998</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Turr&#x000f3;-Garriga</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Garre-Olmo</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Re&#x000f1;&#x000e9;-Ram&#x000ed;rez</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Calv&#x000f3;-Perxas</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gasc&#x000f3;n-Bayarri</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Conde-Sala</surname><given-names>J-. L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Consequences of anosognosia on the cost of caregivers' care in Alzheimer's disease</article-title>. <source>J. Alzheimers Dis</source>. <volume>54</volume>, <fpage>1551</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1560</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3233/JAD-160419</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27636844</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Turr&#x000f3;-Garriga</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Garre-Olmo</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vilalta-Franch</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Conde-Sala</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Gracia Blanco</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x000f3;pez-Pousa</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Burden associated with the presence of anosognosia in Alzheimer's disease</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Geriatr. Psychiatry</source>
<volume>28</volume>, <fpage>291</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>297</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/gps.3824</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22555993</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vannini</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Amariglio</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanseeuw</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>McLaren</surname><given-names>D. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chhatwal</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Memory self-awareness in the preclinical and prodromal stages of Alzheimer's disease</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychologia</source>
<volume>99</volume>, <fpage>343</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>349</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuropsychologia.2017.04.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28385579</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>