<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" id="cre270113" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Clin Exp Dent Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Clin Exp Dent Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.1002/(ISSN)2057-4347</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CRE2</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Clinical and Experimental Dental Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2057-4347</issn><publisher><publisher-name>John Wiley and Sons Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Hoboken</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40066470</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11894262</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cre2.70113</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">CRE270113</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Mothers' Knowledge, Attitude, and Behavior Concerning Their Kindergarten Children's Oral Health: A Cross&#x02010;Sectional Study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="cre270113-cr-0001" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Qahtan</surname><given-names>Dhuha K.</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6404-3016</contrib-id><xref rid="cre270113-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cre270113-aff-0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="cre270113-cr-0002" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Felemban</surname><given-names>Osama M.</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3212-5735</contrib-id><xref rid="cre270113-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><address><email>omfelemban@kau.edu.sa</email></address></contrib><contrib id="cre270113-cr-0003" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Alamoudi</surname><given-names>Rana A.</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-8220-4976</contrib-id><xref rid="cre270113-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="cre270113-cr-0004" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bamashmous</surname><given-names>Nada O.</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-6948-6833</contrib-id><xref rid="cre270113-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="cre270113-cr-0005" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>El Ashiry</surname><given-names>Eman A.</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-4010-5611</contrib-id><xref rid="cre270113-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cre270113-aff-0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="cre270113-cr-0006" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Alamoudi</surname><given-names>Najlaa M.</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-2497-2675</contrib-id><xref rid="cre270113-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="cre270113-aff-0001">
<label>
<sup>1</sup>
</label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Department of Pediatric Dentistry, Faculty of Dentistry</named-content>
<institution>King Abdulaziz University</institution>
<city>Jeddah</city>
<country country="SA">Saudi Arabia</country>
</aff><aff id="cre270113-aff-0002">
<label>
<sup>2</sup>
</label>
<institution>Private Practitioner of Pediatric Dentistry, Medical Fakeeh</institution>
<city>Jeddah</city>
<country country="SA">Saudi Arabia</country>
</aff><aff id="cre270113-aff-0003">
<label>
<sup>3</sup>
</label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Department of Pedodontics and Oral Health, Faculty of Dental Medicine for Girls</named-content>
<institution>Al Azhar University</institution>
<city>Cairo</city>
<country country="EG">Egypt</country>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="correspondenceTo">
<label>*</label>
<bold>Correspondence:</bold> Osama M. Felemban (<email>omfelemban@kau.edu.sa</email>)<break/>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>11</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>2</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue seq="77">1</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cre2.v11.1</issue-id><elocation-id>e70113</elocation-id><history>
<date date-type="rev-recd"><day>17</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></date>
<date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></date>
</history><permissions><!--&#x000a9; 2025 The Author(s). Clinical and Experimental Dental Research published by John Wiley & Sons Ltd.--><copyright-statement content-type="article-copyright">&#x000a9; 2025 The Author(s). <italic toggle="yes">Clinical and Experimental Dental Research</italic> published by John Wiley &#x00026; Sons Ltd.</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link> License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="file:CRE2-11-e70113.pdf"/><abstract><title>ABSTRACT</title><sec id="cre270113-sec-0010"><title>Objectives</title><p>To evaluate the level of oral health&#x02010;related knowledge, attitudes, and behavior among a group of mothers with kindergarten (KG) children aged 3&#x02013;5 years toward their own and their children's oral health and assess its influence on their children's oral health status.</p></sec><sec id="cre270113-sec-0020"><title>Material and Methods</title><p>This was a cross&#x02010;sectional study conducted in Jeddah, Saudi Arabia. The sample was selected randomly from public and private KGs in Jeddah. Self&#x02010;administrated questionnaires were distributed to the mothers of KG schoolchildren aged 3&#x02013;5 years, which contained translated and validated Mothers' Behavior Questionnaire about their own oral health behaviors, Mothers' Attitude Questionnaire about their children's oral health, and Mothers' Knowledge Questionnaire about their children's oral health. The oral health of the KG school children was examined to determine the decayed, missed, and filled index (dmft).</p></sec><sec id="cre270113-sec-0030"><title>Results</title><p>A total of 461 child&#x02013;mother pairs completed the study. The mean values of dmft were 5.41&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.81. The children's oral health (dental caries) and the mothers' oral health&#x02010;related knowledge, attitudes, and behavior were significantly associated with KG type (public vs. private), mothers' age, mothers' education, and family income. A multiple linear regression model indicated that younger mothers (&#x0003c;&#x02009;30&#x02013;40 years), highly educated mothers, high family income, and mothers with higher knowledge scores were significantly associated with lower dmft scores.</p></sec><sec id="cre270113-sec-0040"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Mothers whose children attended private KGs exhibited better oral health&#x02010;related attitudes, habits, and knowledge. School type, mother's age, mother's education level, and monthly income were factors that strongly impacted the behaviors, attitudes, and knowledge of the mothers. Dental caries was lower among children whose mothers were young, well&#x02010;educated, from high family income families, and had higher knowledge related to oral health. Implementing targeted educational programs for mothers, particularly those with lower educational attainment and from low&#x02010;income backgrounds, is essential for enhancing the oral health of children in kindergarten age.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd id="cre270113-kwd-0001">attitude</kwd><kwd id="cre270113-kwd-0002">dental caries</kwd><kwd id="cre270113-kwd-0003">health knowledge</kwd><kwd id="cre270113-kwd-0004">oral health</kwd><kwd id="cre270113-kwd-0005">practice</kwd><kwd id="cre270113-kwd-0006">preschool children</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="funding-0001"><funding-source>This study was supported by the Deanship of Scientific Research (DSR) at King Abdulaziz University, Jeddah, Saudi Arabia under the grant number GPIP: 1065&#x02010;165&#x02010;2024.</funding-source></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="6"/><page-count count="12"/><word-count count="8728"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>source-schema-version-number</meta-name><meta-value>2.0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>February 2025</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>details-of-publishers-convertor</meta-name><meta-value>Converter:WILEY_ML3GV2_TO_JATSPMC version:6.5.4 mode:remove_FC converted:07.04.2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><fn-group><fn id="cre270113-note-0001"><p>Dhuha K. Qahtan and Osama M. Felemban are the joint first authors.</p></fn></fn-group></notes></front><body><sec id="cre270113-sec-0050"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p>Oral health is essential for an individual's overall health and quality of life. Poor oral health can affect socio&#x02010;behavior activity, impair nutritional status, and affect the growth of children. One of the most severe oral health issues worldwide is dental caries. Increased incidence of dental caries is associated with different factors such as parents' education, socioeconomic status, and their knowledge and attitudes toward their children's oral health (Kuppuswamy et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0031" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>).</p><p>Insufficient knowledge and inadequate practice regarding oral health and hygiene of their children can result in a higher risk of dental caries in young children (Alhabdan et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0004" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; Bedaiwi et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0012" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>; Mehta et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0038" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Parents tend to be their children's role models, especially in oral hygiene practice (Nepaul and Mahomed&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0042" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). A strong association between the oral health of the mother and their children has been reported earlier (Lee et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0032" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Similarly, a direct connection between children's dental health conditions and their mothers' educational levels has been found (Kuppuswamy et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0031" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Quadri et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0047" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). Mothers with low educational levels (less than secondary school education) had poor knowledge regarding children's oral health (Moses and Arunachalam&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0039" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>), while mothers with a high level of knowledge and attitudes toward oral health had children with good dental health (Bozorgmehr et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0014" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). However, some contradicting results showed that parents' attitudes toward their children's oral health were poor, but the children were found to have good oral health (Nepaul and Mahomed&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0042" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>).</p><p>There is a relationship between the dental health status of children and their educational performance. Children with poor oral health are associated with low grades at school because severe dental pain, dental abscesses, and infections result in children missing school (Anandakrishna and Chandra&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0010" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). This is reflected in poor academic performance and lower school levels of children with poor oral health compared to those with good oral health. Poor oral health can also have financial implications and affect the child's confidence (Anandakrishna and Chandra&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0010" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Mehta et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0038" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>; Renzaho and de Silva&#x02010;Sanigorski&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0048" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). It can also adversely affect these children's quality of life and their families (Abreu et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0002" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>).</p><p>Several authors have studied mothers' knowledge and attitudes toward their children's oral health (Gerreth et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0023" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Mahmoud et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0036" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>; Nepaul and Mahomed&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0042" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Prabhu et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0046" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). The significant role of mothers' knowledge has been found in preventing dental caries and poor oral hygiene of their children in various provinces of Saudi Arabia (Al&#x02010;Zahrani et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0009" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Alhabdan et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0004" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; Alshehri&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0007" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). However, there is limited research investigating mothers' knowledge and attitude concerning their children's oral health in Jeddah, Saudi Arabia. One study conducted in Saudi Arabia evaluates the relationship between parent behavior and attitudes toward their children's oral health and oral hygiene status (Alhabdan et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0004" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). Mothers play a vital role in preventing dental caries by influencing their children's oral health behaviors through their knowledge, attitudes, and practices. Understanding these maternal factors is crucial for assessing their impact on children's oral health outcomes and developing effective preventive strategies. Therefore, the present study aimed to evaluate the level of oral health&#x02010;related knowledge, attitudes, and behavior among mothers who have children studying in Kindergarten (KG), aged 3&#x02013;5 years, toward their own oral health and their children's oral health and assess the influence of the knowledge, attitude, and behavior on the oral health status of the children.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="cre270113-sec-0060"><label>2</label><title>Methodology</title><p>This cross&#x02010;sectional study was conducted in kindergarten (KG) schools in Jeddah, Saudi Arabia. The research protocol was approved by the Research Ethics Committee at the Faculty of Dentistry, King Abdulaziz University, Saudi Arabia with a proposal number (008&#x02010;16). Local School Health and Education Directorate Authority, Ministry of Education was approached for the lists of the KG in the Jeddah district.</p><p>The target population of the study was mothers and their children aged 3&#x02013;5 years who were medically healthy, Arabic speaking (because the questionnaire was in Arabic), and attending either private or public KGs in the city of Jeddah, Saudi Arabia. It was anticipated that 406 individuals from public and private schools would be needed to get accurate findings with a confidence level of 90%&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5%, assuming a hypothesized outcome frequency of 25%. A multistage stratified random sampling technique was used to identify the participants from KG schools. For the sake of ensuring a balanced sampling of geographical location and socioeconomic status, the KGs were stratified by the district into four strata (west, east, north, and south) and further into KG management types (public/private), resulting in eight strata. Kindergarten (KG) schools were listed in each of the eight strata. One KG school was selected at random from each list using a random number generator, resulting in a total of eight KG schools. Following the random selection of the participating schools, the principals of each participating school were contacted to discuss the primary idea of the research and obtain permission to visit the school and carry out the study. Three classes, one from each grade (KG1, KG2, and KG3), were randomly selected from each KG school using the bowl technique. Every class ought to have a minimum of 20 students. If any class had fewer than 20 children, another class was chosen at random. The children in the classes and their mothers were invited to participate in the study. The class teacher facilitated the distribution of the questionnaires to the selected children, which included informed consent and permission to examine their teeth. This school visit was considered the first visit. The children took the questionnaires home for the mothers to sign and fill out. The utilization of self&#x02010;administered questionnaires facilitated the inclusion of a substantial sample size. All of the data obtained from the participants was anonymous, and only the principal investigator had access to the data.</p><p>The questionnaire consisted of four sections:
<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>1&#x02010;</label><p>Demographic data include questions regarding potential confounders such as age, gender, educational background, and familial income.</p></list-item><list-item><label>2&#x02010;</label><p>The Mothers' Behavior Questionnaire (MBQ) evaluated the mothers' behaviors related to their dental health, utilizing the Hiroshima University &#x02013; Dental Behavioral Inventory (HU&#x02010;DBI) questionnaire (Kawamura&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0029" ref-type="bibr">1988</xref>). The HU&#x02010;DBI questionnaire evaluated the opinions and behaviors of the participating women toward their oral health. It consisted of 20 items presented in a dichotomous format, where participants could respond with either &#x0201c;agree&#x0201d; or &#x0201c;disagree.&#x0201d; An adjustment was made to item number 5, where the phrase (I use a child&#x02010;sized toothbrush) was changed to (I use a recommended&#x02010;sized toothbrush). This modification was implemented to enhance accuracy and accommodate specifically mothers.</p></list-item><list-item><label>3&#x02010;</label><p>The Mothers' Attitude Questionnaire (MAQ) was utilized to evaluate the oral health&#x02010;related attitude of mothers toward the oral health of their children. This questionnaire was based on a modified version of a prior questionnaire (Len&#x0010d;ova&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0033" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). This study specifically focused on the 13 items that examine the potential impact of mothers' attitudes toward oral health on their children's dental health.</p></list-item><list-item><label>4&#x02010;</label><p>The Mothers' Knowledge Questionnaire (MKQ) evaluated the oral health&#x02010;related knowledge of mothers on their children's oral health. It utilized a modified version of a prior questionnaire (Prabhu et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0046" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>), which assessed maternal knowledge regarding children's oral health, dental care, and dietary habits. Modifications were made to this component, resulting in the usage of only 12 questions instead of the original 14. Specifically, two questions were removed, which asked whether the child under the age of five had visited a dentist and, if so, what procedures were performed. These two questions pertain to behavior rather than knowledge. Within this section of the questionnaire, the mothers who took part selected the best answer from multiple choices.</p></list-item></list>
</p><p>The questionnaire was translated into Arabic by two linguists using forward and backward translation methods. Subsequently, the two linguists and a dental public health specialist compared the original English questionnaire with the translated version and made necessary modifications. To evaluate test&#x02013;retest reliability, 20 mothers who were not part of the study were asked to complete the final Arabic version of the questionnaire twice, separated by a period of 2 weeks. The results were evaluated using Pearson's correlation coefficient (r) as a measure of reliability, yielding a value of 0.9, which was considered to be excellent. The internal consistency of the final Arabic&#x02010;translated version of the three sections of the questionnaire was assessed using Cronbach's Alpha, yielding a value of 0.86. A Cronbach's alpha of 0.70 or higher indicates sufficient internal consistency. The content validity index (CVI) was computed using an established approach (Polit et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0045" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Lynn&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0035" ref-type="bibr">1986</xref>) to determine if the items in the questionnaires accurately represented the complete theoretical construct that the questionnaire aimed to evaluate. The survey was disseminated to a group of specialists in the field of pediatric dentistry. The panel of experts was requested to evaluate each item in the questionnaire using a four&#x02010;point Likert scale, considering factors such as relevance, clarity, simplicity, and ambiguity. The content validity was determined to be 0.84. The assessment of construct validity involved the correlation of individual questions with the total score of each section of the questionnaire using Spearman's rho. The construct validity values were 0.83, 0.72, and 0.76.</p><p>The second visit took place 1 week later to collect the questionnaire and do a dental examination on the children. The dmft index was used to assess the severity of caries in the primary teeth. The participants' oral and gingival health was assessed using the Simplified Oral Hygiene Index (OHI&#x02010;S) (Greene and Vermillion&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0024" ref-type="bibr">1964</xref>). The dental examination employed the &#x0201c;Tell&#x02010;Show and Do&#x0201d; technique. Thereafter, a brief report was issued to mothers detailing their child's oral health condition and treatment requirements. A total of four examiners who were general dentists underwent calibration and training. A total of 20 pediatric dental patients were selected from pediatric dentistry clinics at the KAU Dental Hospital for assessing dental caries (dmft) according to WHO criteria. The recorded data were compared among examiners to assess inter&#x02010;rater reliability using the Intra&#x02010;Class Correlation (ICC) coefficient, which yielded a value of 0.96. One week later, the same group of patients underwent a second examination. This was done to assess the intra&#x02010;rater reliability of each examiner, which resulted in values ranging from 0.93 to 0.95.</p><p>A third visit was done in the same week where the authors met the participating mother&#x02013;child pairs to present oral health educational lectures and distribute oral health instruction pamphlets.</p><p>The data was analyzed using the Statistical Package for Social Science (SPSS), specifically IBM Statistics for Windows, Version 23.0, developed by IBM Corp in Armonk, NY. The data analysis did not include the small number of questionnaire responses that had missing data. The chi&#x02010;square test was implemented to compare the questionnaire responses of participants from public and private schools. Total scores of correct answers for each questionnaire were calculated where higher scores indicated superior knowledge, attitude, and behavior. The range for the questionnaire scores was 0&#x02013;20 for the MBQ, 0&#x02013;13 for the MAQ, and 0&#x02013;12 for the MKQ. The associations between demographic characteristics and the independent and dependent variables were assessed using an independent sample <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>&#x02010;test and one&#x02010;way ANOVA. To determine the impact of various independent variables (KG type) on the dependent variable (total dmft), while accounting for potential confounding factors (child gender, mother age, mother education level, monthly income, questionnaire scores, and OHI&#x02010;S), a multiple linear regression analysis was conducted.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="cre270113-sec-0070"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><p>Out of the 480 distributed questionnaires, 461 child&#x02013;mother pairs returned the questionnaire, and their children were dentally examined yielding a response rate of 96%. The demographic attributes of the children and mothers are presented in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-tbl-0001" ref-type="table">1</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="cre270113-tbl-0001" content-type="Table"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Demographic characteristics of the children and their mothers in the study sample.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="center" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="center" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><thead valign="bottom"><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" valign="bottom"><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Category</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">
<bold>School type</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Public</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">256 (55.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Private</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">205 (44.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">
<bold>Child age</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>3&#x02013;4 years</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">232 (50.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>5 years</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">229 (49.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">
<bold>Child gender</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Male</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">222 (48.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Female</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">239 (51.8)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">
<bold>Mother's age</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>30 or less</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">130 (28.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>31&#x02013;40</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">233 (50.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>41 or more</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98 (21.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">
<bold>Mother's education</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>High school or less</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206 (44.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Diploma/University or higher</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">255 (55.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">
<bold>Monthly Income</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Low</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">112 (24.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Medium</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">234 (50.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>High</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">115 (24.9)</td></tr></tbody></table><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd.</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap><p>The mean dmft and OHI&#x02010;S debris Index were 5.41&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.81 and 0.94&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.97, respectively. Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-tbl-0002" ref-type="table">2</xref> compares the responses of the mothers to the Mothers' Behavior Questionnaire (MBQ) between public and private KGs. Of the 20 questions, there was a statistically significant difference in 18 questions between mothers of children in public compared to mothers of children in private KGs (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001) where more positive oral health behavior was reported by mothers listed in private KGs.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="cre270113-tbl-0002" content-type="Table"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Comparison of the responses of the mothers to the Mothers' Behavior Questionnaire (MBQ) between public and private schools.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="center" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="center" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="center" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="center" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="center" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="center" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><thead valign="bottom"><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" valign="bottom"><th align="left" colspan="2" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">Items</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The correct answer</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;461)</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Public (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;256)</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Private (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;205)</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>I don't worry much about visiting the dentist</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Agree</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">230 (49.9)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">111 (43.4)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">119 (58.0)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>My gums tend to bleed when I brush my teeth</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Disagree</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">334 (72.5)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">164 (64.1)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">170 (82.9)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>3</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>I worry about the color of my teeth</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Agree</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">269 (58.4)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">176 (68.8)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93 (45.4)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>4</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>I have noticed some white sticky deposits on my teeth</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Agree</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 (8.7)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (12.1)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (4.4)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>5</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>I use a recommended&#x02010;sized toothbrush</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Agree</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">445 (96.5)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">242 (94.5)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">203 (99.0)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>6</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>I think that I cannot help having false teeth when I am old</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Disagree</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 (7.4)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (11.3)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (2.4)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>7</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>I am bothered by the color of my gums</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Disagree</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">386 (83.7)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201 (78.5)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">185 (90.2)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>8</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>I think my teeth are getting worse despite my daily brushing</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Disagree</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">291 (63.1)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">141 (55.1)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">150 (73.2)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>9</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>I brush each of my teeth carefully</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Agree</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">362 (78.5)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">191 (74.6)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">171 (83.4)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.022</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>10</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>I have never been professionally taught how to brush</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Disagree</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">179 (38.8)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92 (35.9)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87 (42.4)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.155</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>11</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>I think I can clean my teeth without using toothpaste</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Agree</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">151 (32.8)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55 (21.5)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96 (46.8)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>12</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>I often check my teeth in a mirror after brushing</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Agree</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">337 (73.1)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">174 (68.0)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">163 (79.5)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>13</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>I worry about having bad breath</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Agree</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86 (18.7)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58 (22.7)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (13.7)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.014</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>14</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>It is impossible to prevent gum disease without toothbrushing alone</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Disagree</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">153 (33.2)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70 (27.3)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83 (40.5)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>15</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>I put off going to the dentist until I have a toothache</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Disagree</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75 (16.3)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (9.8)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 (24.4)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>16</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>I have used a dye to see how clean my teeth are</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Agree</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (2.0)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (2.7)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.0)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.175</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>17</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>I use a toothbrush that has hard bristles</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Disagree</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">374 (81.1)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">184 (71.9)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">190 (92.7)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>18</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>I don't feel I've brushed well unless I brush with strong strokes</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Disagree</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">279 (60.5)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">121 (47.3)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">158 (77.1)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>19</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>I feel I sometimes take too much time to brush my teeth</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Agree</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">251 (54.4)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">106 (41.4)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">145 (70.7)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>20</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>I have had my dentist tell me that I brush very well</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Agree</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">164 (35.6)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69 (27.0)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95 (46.3)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="cre270113-tbl2-note-0001"><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Note:</italic> Chi&#x02010;square test.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd.</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap><p>Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-tbl-0003" ref-type="table">3</xref> features the differences in responses to the Mother's Attitude Questionnaire (MAQ) between public and private KG mothers. Most of the MAQ questionnaire showed a statistically significant difference between public and private KGs and mostly in favor of the mothers with children in private KGs.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="cre270113-tbl-0003" content-type="Table"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Comparison of the responses to the Mother's Attitude Questionnaire (MAQ) between public and private schools.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="center" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="center" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="center" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="center" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="center" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="center" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><thead valign="bottom"><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" valign="bottom"><th align="left" colspan="2" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">Items</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The correct answer</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;461)</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Public (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;256)</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Private (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;205)</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>We feel it is important that we check our child's teeth for decay</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Agree</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">452 (98.0)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">254 (99.2)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">198 (96.6)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.042</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>I don't know how to brush my child's teeth properly</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Disagree</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">292 (63.3)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">144 (56.3)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">148 (72.2)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>3</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>We feel it is important to check if our child has brushed his/her teeth</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Agree</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">442 (95.9)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">247 (96.5)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">195 (95.1)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.465</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>4</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>we don't have time to help brush our child's teeth daily</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Disagree</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">298 (64.6)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">151 (59.0)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">147 (71.7)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>5</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>It is the responsibility of the dentist to prevent our child from getting tooth decay</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Disagree</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">174 (37.7)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">110 (43.0)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64 (31.2)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.010</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>6</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>If our child gets tooth decay, it is by chance</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Disagree</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">304 (65.9)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">156 (60.9)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">148 (72.2)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>7</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>It would not make any difference to our child getting tooth decay if we helped him/her brush every day</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Disagree</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">135 (29.3)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63 (24.6)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72 (35.1)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.014</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>8</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>It is worthwhile to give our child sweets/biscuits to behave well</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Disagree</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">207 (44.9)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77 (30.1)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">130 (63.4)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>9</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Tooth decay is a serious problem in baby teeth</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Agree</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">352 (76.4)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">171 (66.8)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">181 (88.3)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>10</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>As parents, it is our responsibility to prevent our child from getting tooth decay</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Agree</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">449 (97.4)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">252 (98.4)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">198 (96.1)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.117</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>11</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>We can prevent tooth decay in our child by reducing sugary foods and drinks between meals</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Agree</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">445 (96.5)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">243 (94.9)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">202 (98.5)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.035</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>12</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>If we brush our child's teeth daily, we can prevent our child from getting tooth decay in the future</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Agree</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">356 (77.2)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">185 (72.3)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">171 (83.4)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>13</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>If our child uses a fluoride toothpaste, it will prevent tooth decay</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Agree</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">395 (85.7)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">203 (79.3)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">192 (93.7)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="cre270113-tbl3-note-0001"><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Note:</italic> Chi&#x02010;square test.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd.</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap><p>Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-tbl-0004" ref-type="table">4</xref> compares the Mothers' Knowledge Questionnaire (MKQ) about oral health and proper oral hygiene between mothers of public and private KGs. In general, mothers of children in private KGs demonstrated significantly superior knowledge about oral health and best oral hygiene practices compared to mothers of children in public KGs.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="cre270113-tbl-0004" content-type="Table"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Comparison of the responses to the Mothers' Knowledge Questionnaire (MKQ) between public and private schools.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="center" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="center" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="center" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="center" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="center" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="center" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><thead valign="bottom"><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" valign="bottom"><th align="left" colspan="2" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">Items</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The correct answer</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;461)</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Public (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;256)</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Private (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;205)</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>How often should you brush your child's teeth</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Twice daily</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">232 (50.3)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">110 (43.0)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">122 (59.5)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Size of brush best for your child</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Small</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">397 (86.1)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">213 (83.2)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">184 (89.8)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.043</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>3</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Quantity of paste to be used</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Pea size</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">160 (34.7)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">110 (43.0)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 (24.4)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>4</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Your position to brush your child's teeth</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Behind the child</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86 (18.7)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (10.2)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60 (29.3)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>5</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Does your child's toothpaste have fluoride</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Yes</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">335 (72.7)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">166 (64.8)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">169 (82.4)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>6</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Fluoride content of child paste</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1000 or 1450 ppm</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (7.8)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (5.1)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (11.2)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.015</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="6" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">
<bold>7</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Four of the following cause tooth decay.</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="6" align="center" valign="top" colspan="1">396 (85.9)</td><td rowspan="6" align="center" valign="top" colspan="1">200 (78.1)</td><td rowspan="6" align="center" valign="top" colspan="1">196 (95.6)</td><td rowspan="6" align="center" valign="top" colspan="1">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Chocolate</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Correct</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Cheese</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Biscuits</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Correct</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Sweets</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Correct</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Soft drink</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Correct</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>8</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Best time to give sugary snacks</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Mealtime</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87 (18.9)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (12.1)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56 (27.3)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>9</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Has the child used a sweetened baby bottle or honey&#x02010;dipped pacifier</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>No</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">384 (83.3)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">196 (76.6)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">188 (91.7)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>10</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Importance of decay in baby teeth</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Very important</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">423 (91.8)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">222 (86.7)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201 (98.0)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>11</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Child's first dental visit</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>On getting first baby tooth</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (7.8)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (7.8)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (7.8)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.998</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>12</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>If baby teeth decayed, what treatment would you prefer</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Fill it</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">355 (77.0)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">171 (66.8)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">184 (89.8)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="cre270113-tbl4-note-0001"><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Note:</italic> Chi&#x02010;square test.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd.</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap><p>Associations between demographic variables and MBQ score, MKQ score, MAQ score, and dmft are illustrated in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-tbl-0005" ref-type="table">5</xref>. Mothers whose children were in private KG had higher scores on the three questionnaires and lower mean dmft. The questionnaire scores decreased as the mothers' age increased; however, the mean dmft increased as the mothers' age increased. Mothers with higher education levels had higher questionnaire scores, but their children had lower mean dmft. The questionnaire scores increased as the income increased, but the mean dmft decreased.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="cre270113-tbl-0005" content-type="Table"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Associations between demographic variables and the MBQ score, MKQ score, MAQ score, and dmft.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="center" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="center" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="center" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="center" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="center" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><thead valign="bottom"><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" valign="bottom"><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Category</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MBQ</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MKQ</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MBQ</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">dmft</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">
<bold>School type</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Public</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.48&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.00</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.77&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.79</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.81&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.83</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.63&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.06</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Private</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.47&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.05</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.07&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.64</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.97&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.57</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.89&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.97</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> value<xref rid="cre270113-tbl5-note-0004" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">
<bold>Child age</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3&#x02013;4 years</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.72&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.34</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.27&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.97</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.82</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.12&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.83</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 years</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.90&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.40</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.43&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.69</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.42&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.81</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.72&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.78</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> value<xref rid="cre270113-tbl5-note-0004" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.576</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.361</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.317</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.181</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">
<bold>Child gender</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.85&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.19</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.45&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.69</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.36&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.74</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.03&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.39</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.77&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.52</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.26&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.96</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.29&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.88</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.77&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.14</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> value<xref rid="cre270113-tbl5-note-0004" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.806</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.254</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.652</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.099</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">
<bold>Mother's age</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 or less</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.11 a</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.94&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.87 a</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.98&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.55 a</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.73&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.41 a</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31&#x02013;40</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.46&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.15 b</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.24&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.74 b</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.11&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.83 b</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.41&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.67 b</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 or more</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.71&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.56 b</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.83&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.80 b</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.97&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.86 b</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.65&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.76 c</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> value<xref rid="cre270113-tbl5-note-0005" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>b</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">
<bold>Mother's education</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High school or less</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.99&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.98</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.64&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.83</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.60&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.77</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.72&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.70</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diploma/University or higher</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.28&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.92</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.93&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.63</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.92&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.63</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.55&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.03</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> value<xref rid="cre270113-tbl5-note-0004" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">
<bold>Monthly Income</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.81&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.59 a</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.07&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.85 a</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.03&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.79 a</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.75&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.24 a</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medium</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.56 b</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.41&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.52 b</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.46&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.56 b</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.49&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.05 b</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.17 c</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.48&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.62 c</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.56 c</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.06&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.03 c</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> value<xref rid="cre270113-tbl5-note-0005" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>b</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" valign="top" rowspan="1">
<bold>Total</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.81&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.37</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.35&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.84</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.33&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.81</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.41&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.81</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="cre270113-tbl5-note-0001"><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Note:</italic> Means sharing the same alphabetical letter are not statistically different from each other at <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 using post hoc comparisons.</p></fn><fn id="cre270113-tbl5-note-0002"><p>Means that have different alphabetical letters are statistically different from each other at <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 using post hoc comparisons.</p></fn><fn id="cre270113-tbl5-note-0003"><p>Abbreviations: MAQ, Mothers' Attitude Questionnaire; MBQ, Mothers' Behavior Questionnaire; MKQ, Mothers&#x02019; Knowledge Questionnaire.</p></fn><fn id="cre270113-tbl5-note-0004"><label>
<sup>a</sup>
</label><p>Independent sample <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>&#x02010;test.</p></fn><fn id="cre270113-tbl5-note-0005"><label>
<sup>b</sup>
</label><p>Analysis of variance test (ANOVA).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd.</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap><p>To model the influences of KG type, mother's age, mother's education, monthly income, the questionnaires scores, and OHI&#x02010;S index score on the dmft index, multiple linear regression (adjusted) was used (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-tbl-0006" ref-type="table">6</xref>). Fifty&#x02010;five percent of the variability was explained by the model (<italic toggle="yes">R</italic>
<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.551). Children of younger mothers had lower dmft scores compared to children of mothers 41 years of age or older. The dmft scores of children belonging to mothers of low income were higher by 2.53 on average (95 CI 1.12&#x02013;3.95) compared to children from high&#x02010;income families (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001). As the Mother's Knowledge Questionnaire (MKQ) score increased by one, the dmft of the children decreased by &#x02212;0.34 (95% CI &#x02212;0.56 to &#x02212;0.12), and this association was statistically significant (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.002). Also, as the OHI&#x02010;S index increased by 1, the dmft index significantly increased by 2.00 on average (95% CI 1.62&#x02013;2.39, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="cre270113-tbl-0006" content-type="Table"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Multiple linear regression (adjusted) to model the effects of questionnaire scores on caries (dmft) controlling for demographic variables (<italic toggle="yes">R</italic>
<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.551).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="center" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="center" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="center" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="center" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="center" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><thead valign="bottom"><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" valign="bottom"><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="2" valign="bottom">Independent variables</th><th rowspan="2" align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1">&#x003b2;&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SE</th><th align="center" colspan="2" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">95% CI</th><th align="center" rowspan="2" valign="bottom" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> value</th></tr><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" valign="bottom"><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower bound</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Upper bound</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">
<bold>School type</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Public</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.45</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.79</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.822</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Private</bold>
</td><td align="center" colspan="4" valign="top" rowspan="1">Reference</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">
<bold>Mother's age</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>30 or less</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.99&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.47</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2.92</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.08</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>31&#x02013;40</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.63&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.40</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2.31</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.73</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>41 or more</bold>
</td><td align="center" colspan="4" valign="top" rowspan="1">Reference</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">
<bold>Mother's education</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>High school or less</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.39</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.26</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.29</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.193</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Diploma/University or higher</bold>
</td><td align="center" colspan="4" valign="top" rowspan="1">Reference</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">
<bold>Monthly Income</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Low</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.53&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.72</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.12</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.95</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Medium</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.48</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.76</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.695</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>High</bold>
</td><td align="center" colspan="4" valign="top" rowspan="1">Reference</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" valign="top" rowspan="1">
<bold>MBQ</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.07&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.07</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.22</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.343</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" valign="top" rowspan="1">
<bold>MKQ</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.34&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.11</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.56</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.12</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" valign="top" rowspan="1">
<bold>MAQ</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.19&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.12</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.42</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.105</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" valign="top" rowspan="1">
<bold>OHI&#x02010;S index</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.20</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.62</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.39</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="cre270113-tbl6-note-0001"><p>Abbreviations: &#x003b2; beta estimate; CI, confidence interval; MAQ, Mothers' Attitude Questionnaire; MBQ, Mothers' Behavior Questionnaire; MKQ, Mothers' Knowledge Questionnaire; SE, standard error.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd.</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="cre270113-sec-0080"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p>This study highlights the significant impact of maternal knowledge, attitudes, and behaviors on the oral health of kindergarten children. Additionally, some factors play a crucial role in shaping children's oral health, alongside oral health&#x02010;related knowledge, attitudes, and behaviors.</p><p>The oral health of children can be influenced by the knowledge, attitudes, and behaviors of their parents. Most children under 5 years of age spend their time with their parents or caregivers. The &#x0201c;primary socialization&#x0201d; stage of these initial years develops the earliest routines and habits of children. The role that parents play in ensuring their child's dental health during the first 3 years of preschool is crucial (Samuel et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0051" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). The results of the current study concentrated on mothers' knowledge, attitudes, and practices regarding their own oral health as well as the dental health of their preschool&#x02010;aged children in Jeddah, Saudi Arabia. Previous research reported on comparable mother cohorts in Qatar (Alkhtib and Morawala&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0006" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>), Iran (Azimi et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0011" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>), Indonesia (Abdat and Ramayana&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0001" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>), and the western region of Saudi Arabia (Nassar et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0041" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>). In the current study, we looked at the mother's age, education level, monthly income, and KG type as variables that affected their knowledge and awareness of dental health and their effects on oral health. Previous research reported these variables (Alhabdan et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0004" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). The findings of our investigation found that the oral health of children was affected negatively by older mothers, lower educational levels, and monthly income.</p><p>Dental caries is still a plague on humanity today, despite extensive preventative methods. Globally, this disease is associated with physical, mental, financial, and social burdens, with underdeveloped and developing nations being most severely impacted (Sharna et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0053" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). The dmft is a crucial measure of oral health status that is a cumulative indication of caries experience. According to this study, the children aged 3&#x02013;5 years had a mean dmft of 5.41&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.81. This has highlighted the lack of knowledge regarding the association between various sugar intake patterns and dental caries (Cianetti et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0016" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). All of these results point to a reduced level of knowledge regarding oral health and highlight the necessity of well&#x02010;designed dental education initiatives. Early pediatric dental visits are advised by the American Academy of Pediatric Dentistry and a number of independent research. These visits should preferably occur within the age of 6 months of primary teeth eruption or before 1 year, as suggested by the American Dental Association (Liska et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0034" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). The results of current investigation were consistent with a prior study of Saudi Arabian school children, which found a mean dmft of 5.82&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.48 (Mallineni et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0037" ref-type="bibr">2023</xref>). However, our findings were not as high as those of a prior Brazilian study that showed a mean dmft of 6.25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.20 among preschoolers (Voll&#x000fa; et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0056" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>).</p><p>Mothers' level of knowledge and attitude are crucial for the prevention of oral diseases and the promotion of the oral health of their children. The majority of mothers in this survey displayed a low level of knowledge about their own as well as the dental health of their children. This result was in conflict with certain previous publications (Khaaviya et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0030" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>; Shetty et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0054" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>), but it was in line with some prior reports (Alsumait et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0008" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>; Hamasha et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0025" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). An association was shown between the mothers' knowledge level and the oral health of their children. In addition, the low oral health knowledge of mothers was reflected in the oral health status of their children in terms of dmft scores, i.e., higher scores of dmft were shown by children of mothers having lesser knowledge as compared to those having higher knowledge. This suggested that mothers would highly benefit from efficient dental health education programs. Social media campaigns or educational initiatives might be a useful strategy for raising mothers' awareness (Moses and Arunachalam&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0039" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>).</p><p>No previous studies were conducted to compare mothers' attitudes and behavior toward their own oral health between public and private schools; however, the current results are in line with studies conducted in Rawalpindi city (Sajjad et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0049" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). They found the majority of teachers in private schools had significantly higher attitudes and knowledge regarding their own oral health as compared to the teachers in public schools. Studies conducted in Lagos State, Nigeria, found that students in private schools had better oral health practices compared to public schools (Soroye and Braimoh&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0055" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). While another study conducted in Riyadh city found that there was no statistically significant difference among students in public schools versus students in private schools regarding self&#x02010;report of tooth brushing (Al Subait et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0003" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>).</p><p>In this research, there were significant variations in the total mean knowledge scores of mothers with their education level. Mothers having high school education had an average knowledge score of 5.64&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.83, whereas those who attended university had an average knowledge score of 6.93&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.63. This suggested that mothers with only an elementary or secondary education may rely more on health education programs, whereas mothers with a university degree are more likely to look for information on their own from publicly accessible sources like the internet; however, it may include errors and be skewed toward a particular viewpoint. Thus, mothers' educational level may have a significant influence on the dental health of their children. Our findings concur with those of previous research studies in the literature (Bennadi et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0013" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Mahmoud et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0036" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). The fact that mothers with greater levels of education frequently visited the dentist for dental checkups as opposed to a consultation further supports our findings. It is interesting to note that while scheduling dental checkups, highly educated mothers gave less thought to their child's willingness than less educated mothers. This could also be attributed to the autocratic and uncompromising nature of highly educated mothers in making decisions (Salama et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0050" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). On the other hand, a lower level of education is strongly associated with a diminished understanding of the importance of health and limited access to dental care. Furthermore, mothers with lower levels of education frequently spend their time in physical labor; as a result, they do not have sufficient time for dental examinations (Olak et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0043" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). The result that children of highly educated mothers had lower scores of dmft was further clarified by our study. This could be explained by the fact that parents with lower levels of education may not be as aware of the significance of preventative measures and oral hygiene as parents with greater levels of education (Nassar et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0041" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>). This could also be due to the fact that these children had a greater tendency to brush their teeth more often, get more dental checkups, eat fewer sugary drinks, and had lower rates of dental caries (Chen et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0015" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Our findings, however, conflicted with those of a previous study that discovered a significant relationship between higher maternal education and a higher frequency of caries (Ellakany et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0018" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>). One possible explanation for this might be the working status of mothers, who may not have the time to develop good dietary practices and oral hygiene habits among their children (Fernando et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0022" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). A different explanation might be that mothers in Saudi Arabia who have a high socioeconomic status and are well&#x02010;educated are accustomed to eating fast food and sugar&#x02010;laden drinks (Alshehri&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0007" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>).</p><p>According to this study, children in private kindergartens had higher dental caries rates than children in public kindergartens. This might be explained by variations in the research population's oral hygiene habits, use of dental care services, and socioeconomic status. It is shown that students from private schools have superior oral hygiene habits and use of dental care. These outcomes agree with the results of previous reports (Soroye and Braimoh&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0055" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). Furthermore, there was a statistically significant difference in the dmft scores between children in public and private kindergartens. The children's poor oral hygiene habits in public schools may possibly account for the disparity. The efficacy and consistency of oral self&#x02010;care routines, along with the frequent use of dental care services for the purpose of scaling and polishing, are strong determinants of oral hygiene status (Farsi et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0020" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). In this regard, socioeconomic status has a significant role in determining the usage of dental services; the higher the status, the more dental treatments are used. Children from high socioeconomic classes attend private preschools, and their mothers have sufficient education and knowledge and are thus more worried about their children's dental health and nutrition (Kamiab et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0028" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>).</p><p>In this study, mothers with greater monthly incomes also scored lower on dmft and showed greater knowledge about the dental health of their children. According to earlier research, children whose parents had greater income had better oral health and a lower prevalence of dental caries (Hamasha et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0025" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>; Zhang et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0057" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). These findings are consistent with our own. People from lower socioeconomic classes are less able to take care of themselves, get expert medical treatment, and live in a healthy environment because of social, financial, and material limitations. As a result, they are less resistant to oral and other illnesses. A low family income may have an impact on dietary choices and nutritional consumption (Ortiz et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0044" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Our study results differ from those of research carried out in Timor&#x02010;Leste. The prevalence of caries was shown to be lower in children belonging to low&#x02010;income families because they showed reduced consumption of sugary snacks. Conversely, children from higher socioeconomic backgrounds had a higher caries prevalence because they consumed sweetened milk and calorie&#x02010;rich snacks more often. The possible explanation could be that in comparison to parents with higher education, parents with lesser education may get paid on a daily basis, and their children's frequent visits to the dentist could result in their losing their jobs or making it harder to schedule their work hours in addition to raising their children's knowledge of oral health (Sanguida et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0052" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>).</p><p>The current investigation also demonstrated that younger mothers (&#x02264;&#x02009;30 years) had greater oral health knowledge scores than mothers in other age groups, as evidenced by their children's lower dmft scores. That might be because of the knowledge that has been disseminated through social media to aid and educate them since younger mothers tend to know more about dental health than older mothers do. The majority of younger mothers were aware of the significance of primary teeth and had the time to assist their children in brushing their teeth regularly than of older mothers. These findings corroborated the findings of the earlier study (Jain et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0027" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>), but they disagreed with findings from studies carried out in Saudi Arabia and Pakistan, which found a significant correlation between older mothers and the impact of diet on their children's oral health (AlJameel et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0005" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>; Iqbal et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0026" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>). Mothers over 40 years old may have a greater number of children in their family, so they may learn about these issues from personal experience or even from records from prior dental appointments (Fernandes et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0021" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>).</p><p>The strengths and limitations of this study should be considered when evaluating the findings. Compared to other research, the current study's response rate of 96% is very high (Fan et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0019" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>; Naidu et al.&#x000a0;<xref rid="cre270113-bib-0040" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). Given that the sample comprised children from both public and private kindergartens in Jeddah, the results have the potential to be generalized to the whole population in Jeddah. The study participants were selected at random as well as a suitable sampling technique was employed to get a nearly representative sample. Furthermore, the questionnaire was pre&#x02010;validated, and a clinical assessment was conducted to describe the oral health status. This study's methodological features included a strong study design with good external as well as internal validity, sample distribution throughout different districts, a valid and reliable questionnaire, and suitable statistical analysis. One of the study's drawbacks was that the sample did not include children who did not attend kindergarten. Such types of mothers could think differently from mothers of children attending kindergartens. Another limitation was the reliance on self&#x02010;reported data during the completion of the questionnaires. Some participants may have misinterpreted the meaning of some questions. Participants may have offered more favorable responses rather than actual responses, to enhance their image, in spite of the anonymity of the questionnaire. In this research, a greater ratio of Saudi participants was present; if a non&#x02010;Saudi sample had also been included, the results might be differed. This study's cross&#x02010;sectional design is another drawback, and further research with a longitudinal design is advised in future research to produce more convincing data. Furthermore, the comparison between mothers' knowledge with any other guardian or fathers of the children was not made. Their viewpoints may warrant guidance for a potential behavioral intervention. Additionally, it is advised that further studies be done to compare children of different ages. The results of this study can assist in filling knowledge gaps and offer an update that can direct the development of caries prevention programs and community services for mothers and children by oral healthcare professionals.</p><p>Parents should plan the first dental visit before the age of 12 months, although it is often planned only in case of dental pain. There is a need for educating mothers regarding oral health status and reinforcing attitudes regarding oral health in Saudi Arabia. More health education programs and health promotions are needed among mothers. Our findings support the implementation of awareness campaigns/health education programs targeted at preschool children to encourage good oral health attitudes and behaviors. Additional studies are required to evaluate mothers' awareness regarding oral health in different cities of Saudi Arabia.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="cre270113-sec-0090"><label>5</label><title>Conclusion</title><p>This study highlights the crucial role of maternal knowledge, attitudes, and behaviors in shaping children's oral health, with disparities observed between public and private kindergarten attendees. Lower maternal education and income levels were associated with higher dmft scores, emphasizing the need for targeted public health interventions. To address these disparities, integrating oral health education into prenatal and early childhood programs, implementing school&#x02010;based dental checkups, and providing accessible preventive dental care&#x02014;particularly for lower&#x02010;income families&#x02014;are essential. Preventive care and structured oral health programs in schools should be promoted to reach equitable and lifelong oral health habits among young children.</p></sec><sec id="cre270113-sec-0100"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>The study's conception and design were done by Prof. Najlaa M. Alamoudi, Prof. A. Eman Elashiry, Dr. Duha K. Qattan, and Dr. Nada O. Bamashmous. Data acquisition was done by Dr. Duha K. Qattan and analysis and/or interpretation of data by Dr. Osama M. Felemban. Drafting of the manuscript was done by Dr. Rana A. Alamoudi, while revising the manuscript was done by Prof. Najlaa M. Alamoudi, Dr. Ranan A. Alamoudi, Dr. Osama M. Felemban, Dr. Duha K. Qattan, and Dr. Nada O. Bamashmous. All authors approved the final draft of the manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="cre270113-sec-0120"><title>Ethics Statement</title><p>The research protocol was approved by the Research Ethics Committee at the Faculty of Dentistry, King Abdulaziz University, Saudi Arabia (Proposal Number: 008&#x02010;16).</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="cre270113-sec-0130"><title>Conflicts of Interest</title><p>The authors declare no conflicts of interest.</p></sec></body><back><ack id="cre270113-sec-0110"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>This project was funded by the Deanship of Scientific Research (DSR) at King Abdulaziz University, Jeddah, Saudi Arabia under the grant number GPIP: 1065&#x02010;165&#x02010;2024. The authors, therefore, acknowledge with thanks DSR for technical and financial support.</p></ack><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="cre270113-sec-0150"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The data that support the findings of this study are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request. The datasets generated during and/or analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request.</p></sec><ref-list content-type="cited-references" id="cre270113-bibl-0001"><title>References</title><ref id="cre270113-bib-0001"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0001">
<string-name>
<surname>Abdat</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>I.</given-names>
<surname>Ramayana</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2020</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Relationship Between Mother's Knowledge and Behaviour With Oral Health Status of Early Childhood</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Padjadjaran Journal of Dentistry</source>
<volume>32</volume>, no. <issue>3</issue>: <fpage>166</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>173</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.24198/pjd.vol32no2.24734</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0002"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0002">
<string-name>
<surname>Abreu</surname>, <given-names>M. G. L.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>F.</given-names>
<surname>Germano</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>L. S.</given-names>
<surname>Antunes</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
<surname>Azeredo Alves Antunes</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2021</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Impact of Oral Health on the Quality of Life of Preschoolers and Their Families</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Global Pediatric Health</source>
<volume>2021</volume>, no. <issue>8</issue>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2333794X21999145</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0003"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0003">
<string-name>
<surname>Al Subait</surname>, <given-names>A. A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Alousaimi</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Geeverghese</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Ali</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>El Metwally</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2016</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Oral Health Knowledge, Attitude and Behavior Among Students of Age 10&#x02013;18years Old Attending Jenadriyah Festival Riyadh; a Cross&#x02010;Sectional Study</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Saudi Journal for Dental Research</source>
<volume>7</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue>: <fpage>45</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>50</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sjdr.2015.05.001</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0004"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0004">
<string-name>
<surname>Alhabdan</surname>, <given-names>Y. A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A. G.</given-names>
<surname>Albeshr</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
<surname>Yenugadhati</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
<surname>Jradi</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2018</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Prevalence of Dental Caries and Associated Factors Among Primary School Children: A Population&#x02010;Based Cross&#x02010;Sectional Study in Riyadh, Saudi Arabia</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Environmental Health and Preventive Medicine</source>
<volume>23</volume>, no. <issue>60</issue>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12199-018-0750-z</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29291718</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0005"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0005">
<string-name>
<surname>AlJameel</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A. B.</given-names>
<surname>Mubayrik</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>E. M.</given-names>
<surname>Hadlaq</surname>
</string-name>, et al. <year>2017</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Assessing the Knowledge and Attitudes of Group of Mothers Living in Saudi Arabia With Regards to Their Children's Oral Health</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Australasian Medical Journal</source>
<volume>10</volume>, no. <issue>11</issue>: <fpage>964</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>972</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21767/amj.2017.3210</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0006"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0006">
<string-name>
<surname>Alkhtib</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Morawala</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2018</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Knowledge, Attitudes, and Practices of Mothers of Preschool Children About Oral Health in Qatar: A Cross&#x02010;Sectional Survey</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Dentistry Journal</source>
<volume>6</volume>, no. <issue>4</issue>: <elocation-id>51</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/dj6040051</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30275416</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0007"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0007">
<string-name>
<surname>Alshehri</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>
<year>2016</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Social and Behavioral Determinants of Early Childhood Caries in the Aseer Region of Saudi Arabia</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Mathews Journal of Dentistry</source>
<volume>1</volume>, no. <issue>2</issue>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0008"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0008">
<string-name>
<surname>Alsumait</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>ElSalhy</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Behzadi</surname>
</string-name>, et al. <year>2019</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Impact Evaluation of a School&#x02010;Based Oral Health Program: Kuwait National Program</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>BMC Oral Health</source>
<volume>19</volume>: <fpage>202</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12903-019-0895-1</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31477082</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0009"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0009">
<string-name>
<surname>Al&#x02010;Zahrani</surname>, <given-names>A. M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A. S.</given-names>
<surname>Al&#x02010;Mushayt</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M. F.</given-names>
<surname>Otaibi</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>A. H.</given-names>
<surname>Wyne</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2014</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Knowledge and Attitude of Saudi Mothers Towards Their Preschool Children's Oral Health</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Pakistan Journal of Medical Sciences</source>
<volume>30</volume>, no. <issue>4</issue>: <fpage>720</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>724</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12669/pjms.304.5069</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25097504</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0010"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0010">
<string-name>
<surname>Anandakrishna</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
<surname>Chandra</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2012</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Is There an Association Between Oral Health Status and School Performance? A Preliminary Study</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>International Journal of Clinical Pediatric Dentistry</source>
<volume>5</volume>, no. <issue>2</issue>: <fpage>132</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>135</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5005/jp-journals-10005-1150</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25206152</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0011"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0011">
<string-name>
<surname>Azimi</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J. B.</given-names>
<surname>Taheri</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Tennant</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
<surname>Kruger</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
<surname>Molaei</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>Z.</given-names>
<surname>Ghorbani</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2018</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Relationship Between Mothers' Knowledge and Attitude Towards the Importance of Oral Health and Dental Status of Their Young Children</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Oral Health &#x00026; Preventive Dentistry</source>
<volume>16</volume>, no. <issue>3</issue>: <fpage>265</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>270</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3290/j.ohpd.a40760</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30027166</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0012"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0012">
<string-name>
<surname>Bedaiwi</surname>, <given-names>M. A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S. S.</given-names>
<surname>Alzaidi</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>E. S.</given-names>
<surname>Alsubhi</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2017</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Knowledge and Experiences of Mothers Toward Their Children's Oral Health in Jeddah, Saudi Arabia</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>International Journal of Medical Research Professionals</source>
<volume>3</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue>: <fpage>218</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>223</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21276/ijmrp.2017.3.1.044</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0013"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0013">
<string-name>
<surname>Bennadi</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>C. V. K.</given-names>
<surname>Reddy</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Sunitha</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
<surname>Kshetrimayum</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2014</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Oral Health Status of 3&#x02013;6 Year Old Children and Their Mother's Oral Health Related Knowledge, Attitude and Practices in Mysore City, India</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Asian Journal of Medical Sciences</source>
<volume>6</volume>, no. <issue>2</issue>: <fpage>66</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>71</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0014"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0014">
<string-name>
<surname>Bozorgmehr</surname>, <given-names>E.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Hajizamani</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
<surname>Malek Mohammadi</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2013</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Oral Health Behavior of Parents as a Predictor of Oral Health Status of Their Children</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>ISRN Dentistry</source>
<volume>2013</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue>: <elocation-id>741783</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2013/741783</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23738088</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0015"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0015">
<string-name>
<surname>Chen</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Hong</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
<surname>Xiong</surname>
</string-name>, et al. <year>2020</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Are Parents' Education Levels Associated With Either Their Oral Health Knowledge or Their Children's Oral Health Behaviors? A Survey of 8446 Families in Wuhan</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>BMC Oral Health</source>
<volume>20</volume>: <fpage>203</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12903-020-01186-4</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32652985</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0016"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0016">
<string-name>
<surname>Cianetti</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
<surname>Lombardo</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
<surname>Lupatelli</surname>
</string-name>, et al. <year>2017</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Dental Caries, Parents Educational Level, Family Income and Dental Service Attendance Among Children in Italy</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>European Journal of Paediatric Dentistry</source>
<volume>18</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue>: <fpage>15</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>18</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.23804/ejpd.2017.18.01.03</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28494596</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0018"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0018">
<string-name>
<surname>Ellakany</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Madi</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S. M.</given-names>
<surname>Fouda</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Ibrahim</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>AlHumaid</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2021</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>The Effect of Parental Education and Socioeconomic Status on Dental Caries Among Saudi Children</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health</source>
<volume>18</volume>, no. <issue>22</issue>: <elocation-id>11862</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph182211862</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34831618</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0019"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0019">
<string-name>
<surname>Fan</surname>, <given-names>C. C.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>W. H.</given-names>
<surname>Wang</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
<surname>Xu</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>S. G.</given-names>
<surname>Zheng</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2019</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Risk Factors of Early Childhood Caries (ECC) Among Children in Beijing &#x02013; A Prospective Cohort Study</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>BMC Oral Health</source>
<volume>19</volume>: <fpage>34</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12903-019-0721-9</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30777062</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0020"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0020">
<string-name>
<surname>Farsi</surname>, <given-names>N. J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A. A.</given-names>
<surname>El&#x02010;Housseiny</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>D. J.</given-names>
<surname>Farsi</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>N. M.</given-names>
<surname>Farsi</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2017</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Validation of the Arabic Version of the Early Childhood Oral Health Impact Scale (ECOHIS)</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>BMC Oral Health</source>
<volume>17</volume>: <fpage>60</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12903-017-0353-x</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28245876</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0021"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0021">
<string-name>
<surname>Fernandes</surname>, <given-names>I. B.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>T. S.</given-names>
<surname>Pereira</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>D. S.</given-names>
<surname>Souza</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Ramos&#x02010;Jorge</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>L. S.</given-names>
<surname>Marques</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>M. L.</given-names>
<surname>Ramos&#x02010;Jorge</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2017</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Severity of Dental Caries and Quality of Life for Toddlers and Their Families</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Pediatric Dentistry</source>
<volume>39</volume>, no. <issue>2</issue>: <fpage>118</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>123</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0022"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0022">
<string-name>
<surname>Fernando</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S. K.</given-names>
<surname>Tadakamadla</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Bakr</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>P. A.</given-names>
<surname>Scuffham</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>N. W.</given-names>
<surname>Johnson</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2019</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Indicators of Risk for Dental Caries in Children: A Holistic Approach</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>JDR Clinical and Translational Research</source>
<volume>4</volume>, no. <issue>4</issue>: <fpage>333</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>341</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2380084419834236</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31039050</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0023"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0023">
<string-name>
<surname>Gerreth</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
<surname>Ari</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>W.</given-names>
<surname>Bednarz</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Nowicki</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Borysewicz&#x02010;Lewicka</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2020</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Dental Health Status and Oral Health Care in Nursery School&#x02010;Aged Children and Their Parents Living in Poznan (Poland)</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Medical Principles and Practice</source>
<volume>29</volume>, no. <issue>3</issue>: <fpage>211</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>218</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000503333</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31522176</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0024"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0024">
<string-name>
<surname>Greene</surname>, <given-names>J. G.</given-names>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>J. R.</given-names>
<surname>Vermillion</surname>
</string-name>. <year>1964</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>The Simplified Oral Hygiene Index</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Journal of the American Dental Association</source>
<volume>68</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue>: <fpage>7</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>13</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14076341</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0025"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0025">
<string-name>
<surname>Hamasha</surname>, <given-names>A. A. H.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S. J.</given-names>
<surname>Rasheed</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M. M.</given-names>
<surname>Aldosari</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>Z.</given-names>
<surname>Rajion</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2019</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Parents Knowledge and Awareness of Their Children's Oral Health in Riyadh, Saudi Arabia</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Open Dentistry Journal</source>
<volume>13</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue>: <fpage>236</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>241</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/1874210601913010236</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0026"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0026">
<string-name>
<surname>Iqbal</surname>, <given-names>Z.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Shafeeq</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A. U.</given-names>
<surname>Hassan</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
<surname>Ashraf</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>O.</given-names>
<surname>Bajwa</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2022</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Comparison of Dental Caries and Oral Hygiene Among Children of Working and Non&#x02010;Working Mothers</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Pakistan Journal of Medical &#x00026; Health Sciences</source>
<volume>16</volume>, no. <issue>05</issue>: <elocation-id>57</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.53350/pjmhs2216557</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0027"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0027">
<string-name>
<surname>Jain</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
<surname>Oswal</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
<surname>Chitguppi</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2014</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Knowledge, Attitude and Practices of Mothers Toward Their Children&#x02032;S Oral Health: A Questionnaire Survey Among Subpopulation in Mumbai (India)</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Journal of Dental Research and Scientific Development</source>
<volume>1</volume>, no. <issue>2</issue>: <fpage>40</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>45</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/2348-3407.135073</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0028"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0028">
<string-name>
<surname>Kamiab</surname>, <given-names>N.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
<surname>Mohammadi Kamalabadi</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Sheikh Fathollahi</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2021</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>DMFT of the First Permanent Molars, dmft and Related Factors Among All First&#x02010;Grade Primary School Students in Rafsanjan Urban Area</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Journal of Dentistry (Shiraz, Iran)</source>
<volume>22</volume>, no. <issue>2</issue>: <fpage>109</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>117</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.30476/dentjods.2020.85573.1136</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34150947</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0029"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0029">
<string-name>
<surname>Kawamura</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>
<year>1988</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>[Dental Behavioral Science. The Relationship Between Perceptions of Oral Health and Oral Status in Adults]</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Hiroshima Daigaku Shigaku Zasshi. The Journal of Hiroshima University Dental Society</source>
<volume>20</volume>, no. <issue>2</issue>: <fpage>273</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>286</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3271802</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0030"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0030">
<string-name>
<surname>Khaaviya</surname>, <given-names>N.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
<surname>Ramiya</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>V.</given-names>
<surname>Kalaivani</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2021</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Influence of Mother's Knowledge on the Oral Hygiene Habits of Their Preschool Children</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>International Journal of Community Dentistry</source>
<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>203</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>207</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/ijcd.ijcd_1_22</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0031"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0031">
<string-name>
<surname>Kuppuswamy</surname>, <given-names>V. L.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Murthy</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Sharma</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>K. M.</given-names>
<surname>Surapaneni</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Grover</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Joshi</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2014</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Oral Hygiene Status, Knowledge, Perceptions and Practices Among School Settings in Rural South India</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Oral Health and Dental Management</source>
<volume>13</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue>: <fpage>146</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>154</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24603932</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0032"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0032">
<string-name>
<surname>Lee</surname>, <given-names>S. M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>H. N.</given-names>
<surname>Kim</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J. H.</given-names>
<surname>Lee</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>J. B.</given-names>
<surname>Kim</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2019</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Association Between Maternal and Child Oral Health and Dental Caries in Korea</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Journal of Public Health</source>
<volume>27</volume>: <fpage>219</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>227</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10389-018-0936-2</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0033"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0033">
<string-name>
<surname>Len&#x0010d;ova</surname>, <given-names>E.</given-names>
</string-name>
<year>2013</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Oral Health Attitudes and Caries&#x02010;Preventive Behaviour of Czech Parents of Preschool Children</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Acta Medica Academica</source>
<volume>42</volume>, no. <issue>2</issue>: <fpage>209</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>215</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5644/ama2006-124.88</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24308400</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0034"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0034">
<string-name>
<surname>Liska</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Kelley</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
<surname>Mah</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2019</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>100% Fruit Juice and Dental Health: A Systematic Review of the Literature</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Frontiers in Public Health</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <elocation-id>190</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2019.00190</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31355175</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0035"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0035">
<string-name>
<surname>Lynn</surname>, <given-names>M. R.</given-names>
</string-name>
<year>1986</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Determination and Quantification of Content Validity</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Nursing Research</source>
<volume>35</volume>, no. <issue>6</issue>: <fpage>382</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>386</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3640358</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0036"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0036">
<string-name>
<surname>Mahmoud</surname>, <given-names>N.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Kowash</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>I.</given-names>
<surname>Hussein</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Hassan</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Al Halabi</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2017</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Oral Health Knowledge, Attitude, and Practices of Sharjah Mothers of Preschool Children, United Arab Emirates</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Journal of International Society of Preventive and Community Dentistry</source>
<volume>7</volume>, no. <issue>6</issue>: <fpage>308</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>314</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/jispcd.JISPCD_310_17</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29387613</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0037"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0037">
<string-name>
<surname>Mallineni</surname>, <given-names>S. K.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Alassaf</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
<surname>Almulhim</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Alghamdi</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2023</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Influence of Tooth Brushing and Previous Dental Visits on Dental Caries Status Among Saudi Arabian Children</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Children (Basel, Switzerland)</source>
<volume>10</volume>, no. <issue>3</issue>: <elocation-id>471</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/children10030471</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36980029</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0038"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0038">
<string-name>
<surname>Mehta</surname>, <given-names>N.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Ankola</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
<surname>Chawla</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
<surname>Rajpurohit</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2019</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Association of Maternal Oral Health&#x02010;Related Knowledge, Attitude, and Socioeconomic Status With Dental Caries Status of Preschoolchildren in Belgaum City: A Cross&#x02010;Sectional Study</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Journal of Indian Association of Public Health Dentistry</source>
<volume>17</volume>, no. <issue>3</issue>: <fpage>186</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>191</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/jiaphd.jiaphd_227_18</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0039"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0039">
<string-name>
<surname>Moses</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>S. K.</given-names>
<surname>Arunachalam</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2018</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Knowledge, Attitude, and Practice of Mothers Regarding Oral Hygiene of Primary School Children in Chennai, Tamil Nadu, India</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>International Journal of Clinical Pediatric Dentistry</source>
<volume>11</volume>, no. <issue>4</issue>: <fpage>338</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>343</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30397379</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0040"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0040">
<string-name>
<surname>Naidu</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Nunn</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
<surname>Donnelly&#x02010;Swift</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2016</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Oral Health&#x02010;Related Quality of Life and Early Childhood Caries Among Preschool Children in Trinidad</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>BMC Oral Health</source>
<volume>16</volume>: <fpage>128</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12903-016-0324-7</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27923355</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0041"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0041">
<string-name>
<surname>Nassar</surname>, <given-names>A. A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>B. A.</given-names>
<surname>Fatani</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>O. T.</given-names>
<surname>Almobarak</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S. I.</given-names>
<surname>Alotaibi</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>R. A.</given-names>
<surname>Alhazmi</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>A. A.</given-names>
<surname>Marghalani</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2022</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Knowledge, Attitude, and Behavior of Parents Regarding Early Childhood Caries Prevention of Preschool Children in Western Region of Saudi Arabia: A Cross&#x02010;Sectional Study</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Dentistry Journal</source>
<volume>10</volume>, no. <issue>12</issue>: <elocation-id>218</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/dj10120218</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36547034</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0042"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0042">
<string-name>
<surname>Nepaul</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>O.</given-names>
<surname>Mahomed</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2020</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Influence of Parent' Oral Health Knowledge and Attitudes on Oral Health Practices of Children (5&#x02013;12 Years) in a Rural School in KwaZulu&#x02010;Natal, South Africa</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Journal of International Society of Preventive and Community Dentistry</source>
<volume>10</volume>, no. <issue>5</issue>: <fpage>605</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>612</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/jispcd.JISPCD_273_20</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33282770</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0043"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0043">
<string-name>
<surname>Olak</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M. S.</given-names>
<surname>Nguyen</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>T. T.</given-names>
<surname>Nguyen</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>B. B. T.</given-names>
<surname>Nguyen</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Saag</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2018</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>The Influence of Mothers' Oral Health Behaviour and Perception Thereof on the Dental Health of Their Children</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>EPMA Journal</source>
<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>187</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>193</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13167-018-0134-x</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29896317</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0044"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0044">
<string-name>
<surname>Ortiz</surname>, <given-names>A. S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>F.</given-names>
<surname>Tomazoni</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J. K.</given-names>
<surname>Knorst</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>T. M.</given-names>
<surname>Ardenghi</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2020</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Influence of Socioeconomic Inequalities on Levels of Dental Caries in Adolescents: A Cohort Study</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>International Journal of Paediatric Dentistry</source>
<volume>30</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue>: <fpage>42</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>49</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ipd.12572</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31454454</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0045"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0045">
<string-name>
<surname>Polit</surname>, <given-names>D. F.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>C. T.</given-names>
<surname>Beck</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>S. V.</given-names>
<surname>Owen</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2007</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Is the CVI an Acceptable Indicator of Content Validity? Appraisal and Recommendations</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Research in Nursing &#x00026; Health</source>
<volume>30</volume>, no. <issue>4</issue>: <fpage>459</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>467</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/nur.20199</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17654487</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0046"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0046">
<string-name>
<surname>Prabhu</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A. P.</given-names>
<surname>Rao</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>V.</given-names>
<surname>Reddy</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S. S.</given-names>
<surname>Ahamed</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Muhammad</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Thayumanavan</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2013</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Parental Knowledge of Pre&#x02010;School Child Oral Health</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Journal of Community Health</source>
<volume>38</volume>, no. <issue>5</issue>: <fpage>880</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>884</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10900-013-9693-x</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23624797</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0047"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0047">
<string-name>
<surname>Quadri</surname>, <given-names>F. A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
<surname>Hendriyani</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Pramono</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Jafer</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2015</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Knowledge, Attitudes and Practices of Sweet Food and Beverage Consumption and Its Association With Dental Caries Among Schoolchildren in Jazan, Saudi Arabia</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Eastern Mediterranean Health Journal</source>
<volume>21</volume>, no. <issue>6</issue>: <fpage>403</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>411</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.26719/2015.21.6.403</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26369999</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0048"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0048">
<string-name>
<surname>Renzaho</surname>, <given-names>A. M. N.</given-names>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>de Silva&#x02010;Sanigorski</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2014</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>The Importance of Family Functioning, Mental Health and Social and Emotional Well&#x02010;Being on Child Oral Health</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Child: Care, Health and Development</source>
<volume>40</volume>, no. <issue>4</issue>: <fpage>543</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>552</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/cch.12053</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23551227</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0049"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0049">
<string-name>
<surname>Sajjad</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M. U.</given-names>
<surname>Rehman</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
<surname>Roshan</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2016</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Knowledge, Attitude and Practices of Primary School Teachers Regarding Oral Health in Public and Private Schools of Rawalpindi</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Pakistan Armed Forces Medical Journal</source>
<volume>66</volume>, no. <issue>3</issue>: <fpage>371</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>376</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0050"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0050">
<string-name>
<surname>Salama</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
<surname>Konsowa</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Alkalash</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2020</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Mothers' Knowledge, Attitude, and Practice Regarding Their Primary School Children's Oral Hygiene</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Menoufia Medical Journal</source>
<volume>33</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue>: <fpage>11</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>17</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/mmj.mmj_300_19</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0051"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0051">
<string-name>
<surname>Samuel</surname>, <given-names>S. R.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Acharya</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>J. C.</given-names>
<surname>Rao</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2020</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>School Interventions&#x02010;Based Prevention of Early&#x02010;Childhood Caries Among 3&#x02010;5&#x02010;year&#x02010;old Children from Very Low Socioeconomic Status: Two&#x02010;Year Randomized Trial</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Journal of Public Health Dentistry</source>
<volume>80</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue>: <fpage>51</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>60</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jphd.12348</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31710096</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0052"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0052">
<string-name>
<surname>Sanguida</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>V.</given-names>
<surname>Vinothini</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>G. S.</given-names>
<surname>Prathima</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Santhadevy</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
<surname>Premlal</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Kavitha</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2019</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Age and Reasons for First Dental Visit and Knowledge and Attitude of Parents Toward Dental Procedures for Puducherry Children Aged 0&#x02013;9 Years</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Journal of Pharmacy &#x00026; Bioallied Sciences</source>
<volume>11</volume>, no. <issue>Suppl 2</issue>: <fpage>413</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/jpbs.Jpbs_54_19</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0053"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0053">
<string-name>
<surname>Sharna</surname>, <given-names>N.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Ramakrishnan</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>V.</given-names>
<surname>Samuel</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
<surname>Ravikumar</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
<surname>Cheenglembi</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Anil</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2019</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Association Between Early Childhood Caries and Quality of Life: Early Childhood Oral Health Impact Scale and Pufa Index</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Dentistry Journal</source>
<volume>7</volume>, no. <issue>4</issue>: <elocation-id>95</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/dj7040095</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31557850</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0054"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0054">
<string-name>
<surname>Shetty</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Deoghare</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Rath</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
<surname>Sarda</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Tamrakar</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2016</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Influence of Mother's Oral Health Care Knowledge on Oral Health Status of Their Preschool Child</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Saudi Journal of Oral Sciences</source>
<volume>3</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue>: <fpage>12</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>16</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/1658-6816.174291</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0055"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0055">
<string-name>
<surname>Soroye</surname>, <given-names>M. O.</given-names>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>O. B.</given-names>
<surname>Braimoh</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2016</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>An Oral Health Status of Children in Government and Private Secondary Schools in Lagos State, Nigeria</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Nigerian Journal of Dental Research</source>
<volume>1</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue>: <fpage>34</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>40</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0056"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0056">
<string-name>
<surname>Voll&#x000fa;</surname>, <given-names>A. L.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M. E. P. R.</given-names>
<surname>da Costa</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>L. C.</given-names>
<surname>Maia</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Fonseca&#x02010;Gon&#x000e7;alves</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2018</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Evaluation of Oral Health&#x02010;Related Quality of Life to Assess Dental Treatment in Preschool Children With Early Childhood Caries: A Preliminary Study</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Journal of Clinical Pediatric Dentistry</source>
<volume>42</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue>: <fpage>37</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>44</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17796/1053-4628-42.1.7</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28937896</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cre270113-bib-0057"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cre270113-cit-0057">
<string-name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>K. Y.</given-names>
<surname>Li</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>E. C. M.</given-names>
<surname>Lo</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>M. C. M.</given-names>
<surname>Wong</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2020</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Structural Equation Model for Parental Influence on Children's Oral Health Practice and Status</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>BMC Oral Health</source>
<volume>20</volume>: <fpage>56</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12903-020-1048-2</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32066428</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>