<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="editorial"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Immunol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Immunol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Immunol.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Immunology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-3224</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12098065</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2025.1615392</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Immunology</subject><subj-group><subject>Editorial</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Editorial: Community series in intravital microscopy imaging of leukocytes, volume II</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>Connie H. Y.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/300322/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jenne</surname><given-names>Craig N.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/628802/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Kolaczkowska</surname><given-names>Elzbieta</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn001" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/399197/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
<institution>Centre for Inflammatory Diseases, Department of Medicine, School of Clinical Sciences at Monash Health, Monash Medical Centre, Monash University</institution>, <addr-line>Clayton, VIC</addr-line>, <country>Australia</country>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
<institution>Department of Microbiology, Immunology and Infectious Diseases, University of Calgary</institution>, <addr-line>Calgary, AB</addr-line>, <country>Canada</country>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
<institution>Department of Experimental Hematology, Institute of Zoology and Biomedical Research, Jagiellonian University</institution>, <addr-line>Krakow</addr-line>, <country>Poland</country>
</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited and Reviewed by: Florent Ginhoux, Singapore Immunology Network (A*STAR), Singapore</p></fn><corresp id="fn001">*Correspondence: Elzbieta Kolaczkowska, <email xlink:href="mailto:ela.kolaczkowska@uj.edu.pl">ela.kolaczkowska@uj.edu.pl</email>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>09</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><elocation-id>1615392</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2025 Wong, Jenne and Kolaczkowska</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Wong, Jenne and Kolaczkowska</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><related-article related-article-type="commentary-article" id="RA1" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/research-topics/56277/community-series-in-intravital-microscopy-imaging-of-leukocytes-volume-ii" ext-link-type="uri" journal-id="Front Immunol" journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Editorial on the Research Topic <article-title>Community series in intravital microscopy imaging of leukocytes, volume II</article-title>
</related-article><kwd-group><kwd>intravital microscopy (IVM)</kwd><kwd>leukocytes</kwd><kwd>imaging</kwd><kwd>neutrophils</kwd><kwd>myloid cells</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><funding-statement>The author(s) declare that financial support was received for the research and/or publication of this article. CW is supported by the National Heart Foundation Future Leaders Fellowship (107214). CJ is supported by the Canada Research Chairs Program-EK is supported by a grant (No. 2021/43/B/NZ6/00782) from the National Science Center, Poland (NCN).</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="0"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="19"/><page-count count="3"/><word-count count="1129"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>section-in-acceptance</meta-name><meta-value>Antigen Presenting Cell Biology</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p>The field of intravital microscopy (IVM) has come a long way since the method was established as we know it. The first humble attempts from the 19<sup>th</sup> century, with application of very basic light microscopes, allowed for initial observations of leukocytes in transparent tissues. In fact, these observations resulted in correct and clinically relevant description of a phenomenon known currently as diapedesis: &#x0201c;an emerging of colorless blood corpuscles from the interior of a vein to the outside, completely through the intact wall&#x0201d; (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>) albeit the process itself was an enigma at the time. As of late 1970s, the method was revived (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>) and gradually improved surgically and microscopically, especially upon the advent of confocal and multi-photon scopes which enabled for detection of fluorescent markers (antibodies, dyes or proteins).</p><p>The current volume of the Research Topic was proceed by volume I published in years 2019-2020 (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>) and is summarized herein (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). The first volume focused on the latest methodological advancements in the field of IVM as well as some novel findings both in terms of unstudied diseases, and leukocyte function and cellular fate. In the current volume the papers continued reporting on the latest developments in the field as well as clinically relevant discoveries accomplished with the past 5 years.</p><p>The review paper by <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2024.1372996" ext-link-type="uri">Suthya et&#x000a0;al.</ext-link> published in our Research Topic, starts by reminding us of the humble beginnings of IVM mentioned above but then updates the reader on the newest hardware, with a particular focus on imaging the brain. The types of microscopes discussed ranged from confocal microscopes through single- and multiphoton devices, leading to photoacoustic imaging (PAI). When it comes to imaging dynamic processes, spinning-disk confocal scopes, or their more contemporary alternates such as resonant-scanning confocal scopes possibly combined with multiphoton imaging, are preferred. The review also discusses the tissue penetration depth that can be achieved with each imaging technology, whilst providing the newest information on labelling tools required for IVM imaging of any organ, and emerging reporter animal models. One of the technical struggles with traditional fluorescent microscopes is the limited number of fluorescent channels, however this has been overcome with spectral scopes (i.e. the above mentioned resonant-scanning platforms) which are capable of detecting any signals in any spectrum, solve the problem. In light of this, there will be an emerging expansion of fluorophores than those existing as technically any wavelength along the spectrum can be detected by these new microscopes. However, they are not accessible to all in the field and <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2024.1372996" ext-link-type="uri">Suthya et&#x000a0;al.</ext-link> describe how application of some of the newest generations of detectable molecules i.e. quantum dots of nano-crystals/particles, can enable more flexibility even when scope technology is limited. The work-around is further emphasized by <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2022.1002919" ext-link-type="uri">Porto-Pedrosa et&#x000a0;al.</ext-link>, which is introduced in the subsequent paragraphs, underlining the key aspects of new fluorochromes, and in particular demonstrates usefulness of Brilliant Violet and other new generations of polymers.</p><p>One of the most extensively investigated leukocytes by IVM are neutrophils. Neutrophils are first responders to the inflammatory insult and can eliminate pathogens by multiple approaches, many of which are linked to their ability to release an array of mediators (some 1300 unique proteins) carried in their numerous granules (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). Pathogen elimination by neutrophils may occur either intracellularly following phagocytosis or extracellularly upon granule release (degranulation) or formation of neutrophil extracellular traps (NETs) (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2024.1458035" ext-link-type="uri">Yam et&#x000a0;al.</ext-link> focus their review on recent advancements of imaging neutrophils in the context of cancer. When it comes to methodology, the review focuses on appropriate antibodies (e.g. Gr-1 versus Ly6G) and reporter mice that recently revolutionized the IVM field. Also, the review by <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2024.1372996" ext-link-type="uri">Suthya et&#x000a0;al.</ext-link> underlines the importance of the latter model in brain studies, as staining with antibodies when neutrophils halt blood flow prevents antibody access to these cells thereby limiting labelling, and furthermore, prolonged exposure to anti-Ly6G antibodies can eventually lead to neutrophil depletion. These issues are completely solved when using <italic>Catchup<sup>IVM</sup>
</italic> mice, animals expressing genetically-encoded fluorescent reporter molecules within neutrophils. An exciting part of the <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2024.1458035" ext-link-type="uri">Yam et&#x000a0;al.</ext-link> paper highlights the use of IVM in revealing the contribution of neutrophil in cancer development/metastasis. Here, neutrophils were shown to support transformed cell development, and limit their motility (lower velocity) when inside the tumor microenvironment presumably to interact with cancer cells. Furthermore, NETs can trap circulating tumor cells in hepatic sinusoids, and modulate to the metastatic process. Previously NETs were also show to awaken dormant cancer cells (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>).</p><p>Intravital imaging of the beating heart is one of the most challenging and recent advances in IVM (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). In this Research Topic, <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2023.1257497" ext-link-type="uri">Bumroongthai et&#x000a0;al.</ext-link> used this technique in mice to investigate if therapies aimed at preventing damage to coronary microvessels which accompanies opening of occluded coronary arteries; a surgical procedure performed to patients with myocardial infarction. The group reports that they perfected culturing of mesenchymal stromal cells (MSCs) that when introduced into the mouse have the potential to limit this injury. This work involved the 3D culture of cells representing two distinct populations of bone marrow-derived MSCs. One line (CD317neg MSCs-Y201) turned out to be most effective as it limited neutrophil and platelet recruitment, especially when co-applied with heparin. These results carry an important clinical potential.</p><p>Another organ that was explored by co-authors of this Research Topic was the spleen. The study by <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2022.1002919" ext-link-type="uri">Porto-Pedrosa et&#x000a0;al.</ext-link> investigated the dynamics of immune development within this organ across postnatal period. The study reports that although the lymphoid tissue had similar structural arrangements in both newborn mice and adult individuals, they differed in the relative composition (cell number) of some of the myloid cells &#x02013; macrophages and monocytes, but not neutrophils. The important characteristic of the study was its detailed methodological approach, developing high dimensional intravital microscopy though the use of conventional confocal microscopes working as multi-channel imaging platforms.</p><p>The reviews and original papers published in volume II of our Research Topic touch upon historical aspect of IVM studies, refer to the most used techniques and present latest methodological achievements in the field of IVM. The intrinsic technical limitations or unawareness of dye applications, might limit imaging to few channels whereas the newest developments significantly improve this aspect as discussed in the papers. The Research Topic also presents information/work on the heart, spleen and brain imaging, a less frequently studied organs as opposed to well documented liver or cremaster muscle studies, revealing the expansion of potential application of IVM. Importantly, the original research papers reveal results which hold a therapeutic potential. Overall, this Research Topic shows that intravital microscopy stands strong and still carries a potential to bring new discoveries and methodological advancement in the <italic>in vivo</italic> biomedical studies.</p></body><back><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="s1"><title>Author contributions</title><p>CW: Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing. CJ: Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing. EK: Writing &#x02013; original draft, Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s3"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p><p>The author(s) declared that they were an editorial board member of Frontiers, at the time of submission. This had no impact on the peer review process and the final decision.</p></sec><sec sec-type="ai-statement" id="s4"><title>Generative AI statement</title><p>The author(s) declare that no Generative AI was used in the creation of this manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s5"><title>Publisher&#x02019;s note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cohnheim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Ueber entz&#x000fc;ndung und eiterung</article-title>. <source>Arch f&#x000fc;r Pathol Anat und Physiol und f&#x000fc;r Klin Med</source>. (<year>1867</year>) <volume>40</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>79</lpage>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02968135/METRICS</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Granger</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name><name><surname>Granger</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Brace</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Analysis of the permeability characteristics of cat intestinal capillaries</article-title>. <source>Circ Res</source>. (<year>1979</year>) <volume>44</volume>:<page-range>335&#x02013;44</page-range>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.RES.44.3.335</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Montague</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gardiner</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Imaging platelet processes and function-current and emerging approaches for imaging</article-title>. <source>Vitro vivo. Front Immunol</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<elocation-id>78</elocation-id>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2020.00078</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32082328</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Surewaard</surname><given-names>BGJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Turk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Carestia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name><name><surname>Petri</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Optimization of <italic>In vivo</italic> Imaging Provides a First Look at Mouse Model of Non-Alcoholic Fatty Liver Disease (NAFLD) Using Intravital Microscopy</article-title>. <source>Front Immunol</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<elocation-id>2988</elocation-id>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2019.02988</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31969883</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pizzagalli</surname><given-names>DU</given-names></name><name><surname>Latino</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Pulfer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Palomino-Segura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Virgilio</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Farsakoglu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Characterization of the dynamic behavior of neutrophils following influenza vaccination</article-title>. <source>Front Immunol</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<elocation-id>2621</elocation-id>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2019.02621</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31824481</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cichon</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Ortmann</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Bednarz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenartowicz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolaczkowska</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Reduced neutrophil extracellular trap (NET) formation during systemic inflammation in mice with menkes disease and wilson disease: copper requirement for NET release</article-title>. <source>Front Immunol</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<elocation-id>3021</elocation-id>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2019.03021</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32010131</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sody</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Uddin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gruneboom</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorgens</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Giebel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Gunzer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Distinct spatio-temporal dynamics of tumor-associated neutrophils in small tumor lesions</article-title>. <source>Front Immunol</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<elocation-id>1419</elocation-id>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2019.01419</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31293583</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Seyed-Razavi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ortiz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Sendra</surname><given-names>VG</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Multiphoton intravital microscopy of mandibular draining lymph nodes: A mouse model to study corneal immune responses</article-title>. <source>Front Immunol</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<elocation-id>39</elocation-id>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2020.00039</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32153558</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jamali</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Seyed-Razavi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ortiz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kenyon</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Blanco</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Intravital multiphoton microscopy of the ocular surface: alterations in conventional dendritic cell morphology and kinetics in dry eye disease</article-title>. <source>Front Immunol</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<elocation-id>742</elocation-id>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2020.00742</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32457740</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ortiz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Chao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Jamali</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Seyed-Razavi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kenyon</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of dry eye disease on the kinetics of lacrimal gland dendritic cells as visualized by intravital multi-photon microscopy</article-title>. <source>Front Immunol</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<elocation-id>1713</elocation-id>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2020.01713</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32903439</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Allan-Rahill</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamont</surname><given-names>MRE</given-names></name><name><surname>Chilian</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishimura</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Small</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Intravital microscopy of the beating murine heart to understand cardiac leukocyte dynamics</article-title>. <source>Front Immunol</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<elocation-id>92</elocation-id>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2020.00092</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32117249</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sedin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Giraud</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Steiner</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahl</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Persson</surname><given-names>AEG</given-names></name><name><surname>Melican</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>High resolution intravital imaging of the renal immune response to injury and infection in mice</article-title>. <source>Front Immunol</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<elocation-id>2744</elocation-id>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2019.02744</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31921099</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ahl</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Eriksson</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Sedin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Seignez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kreuger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Turning up the heat: local temperature control during <italic>in vivo</italic> imaging of immune cells</article-title>. <source>Front Immunol</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<elocation-id>2036</elocation-id>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2019.02036</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31507619</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>CHY</given-names></name><name><surname>Jenne</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolaczkowska</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Editorial: intravital microscopy imaging of leukocytes</article-title>. <source>Front Immunol</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<elocation-id>2137</elocation-id>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2020.02137</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33013902</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>R&#x000f8;rvig</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x000d8;stergaard</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Heegaard</surname><given-names>NHH</given-names></name><name><surname>Borregaard</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Proteome profiling of human neutrophil granule subsets, secretory vesicles, and cell membrane: correlation with transcriptome profiling of neutrophil precursors</article-title>. <source>J Leukoc Biol</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>94</volume>:<page-range>711&#x02013;21</page-range>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1189/JLB.1212619</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kolaczkowska</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kubes</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Neutrophil recruitment and function in health and inflammation</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Immunol</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<page-range>159&#x02013;75</page-range>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nri3399</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Santocki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Such</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Drab</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Burczyk</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolaczkowska</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>NETs persisting in vasculature undergo self-renewal with consequences for subsequent infection: a mouse model study</article-title>. <source>Blood</source>. (<year>2025</year>) <volume>145</volume>(<issue>18</issue>):<page-range>2070&#x02013;85</page-range>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1182/BLOOD.2024026643</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Albrengues</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Shields</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Ambrico</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Poindexter</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Neutrophil extracellular traps produced during inflammation awaken dormant cancer cells in mice</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>361</volume>:<elocation-id>eaao4227</elocation-id>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/SCIENCE.AAO4227</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30262472</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Nava</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Bribriesco</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Zinselmeyer</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Spahn</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Gelman</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Intravital 2-photon imaging of leukocyte trafficking in beating heart</article-title>. <source>J Clin Invest</source>. (<year>2012</year>) <volume>122</volume>:<page-range>2499&#x02013;508</page-range>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI62970</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>