<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40188248</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11972329</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">95951</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-025-95951-6</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Terahertz microscopy through complex media</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>Vivek</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cecconi</surname><given-names>Vittorio</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cutrona</surname><given-names>Antonio</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>Luke</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Olivieri</surname><given-names>Luana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Totero Gongora</surname><given-names>Juan S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pasquazi</surname><given-names>Alessia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Peccianti</surname><given-names>Marco</given-names></name><address><email>m.peccianti@lboro.ac.uk</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/00ayhx656</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.12082.39</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 7590</institution-id><institution>Emergent Photonics Lab (EPic), Department of Physics and Astronomy, </institution><institution>University of Sussex, </institution></institution-wrap>Brighton, BN1 9QH UK </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/04vg4w365</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.6571.5</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 8542</institution-id><institution>Emergent Photonics Research Centre, Department of Physics, School of Science, </institution><institution>Loughborough University, </institution></institution-wrap>Loughborough, LE11 3TU UK </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/04ex24z53</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.410533.0</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2179 2236</institution-id><institution>Laboratoire Kastler Brossel, </institution><institution>ENS-Universit&#x000e9; PSL, CNRS, Sorbonne Universit&#x000e9;, Coll&#x000e8;ge de France, </institution></institution-wrap>24 rue Lhomond, Paris, 75005 France </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>5</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>5</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>11706</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Manipulating broadband fields in scattering media is a modern challenge across photonics and other wave domains. Recent studies have shown that complex propagation in scattering media can be harnessed to manipulate broadband light wave packets in space-time for focusing, imaging, and computing applications. Interestingly, while many proposed methodologies operate on intensity-based assessment of scattered fields, often in the spectral domain, from a pure transmission-function perspective, scattering operates as a linear field-level combinatory process, i.e., the superposition of transformation of unit excitations. As a result, we recently demonstrated that gaining experimental access to instantaneous scattered fields, as available through time-domain spectroscopy in the terahertz (THz) spectral range, in conjunction with sparse light excitation typical of ghost imaging, provides a key advantage in enabling the functionalisation of scattering, exposing a novel modelling paradigm. In this paper, we provide experimental proof of reconstructing 1-dimensional object features through a scattering medium using a fully broadband THz time-domain approach.</p><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1038/s41598-025-95951-6.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Terahertz optics</kwd><kwd>Nonlinear optics</kwd><kwd>Imaging and sensing</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100010661</institution-id><institution>Horizon 2020 Framework Programme</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>725046</award-id><award-id>725046</award-id><award-id>851758</award-id><award-id>725046</award-id><award-id>725046</award-id><award-id>851758</award-id><award-id>725046</award-id></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100000857</institution-id><institution>Loughborough University</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>Vice-Chancellor Independent Research Fellowship - STARLIGHT</award-id></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/501100000275</institution-id><institution>Leverhulme Trust</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>Early Career Fellowship ECF-2024-537</award-id><award-id>Early Career Fellowship ECF-2022-710</award-id><award-id>Early Career Fellowship ECF-2023-315</award-id><award-id>Early Career Fellowship ECF-2020-537</award-id><award-id>RPG-2022-090</award-id></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100000266</institution-id><institution>Engineering and Physical Sciences Research Council</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>EP/X012689/1</award-id><award-id>EP/X012689/1</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Springer Nature Limited 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Inhomogeneous complex media, such as biological tissues or atmospheric turbulence, exhibit wave scattering, typically viewed as an inevitable perturbation or a nuisance. Due to the recurrence of scattering and interference, this phenomenon seemingly obliterates both the spatial and time information of any transmitted wave<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. As commonly experienced, scattering ultimately limits imaging, a challenge so fundamental that it is the sole focus of a large multi-domain research effort. However, multiple scattering is a highly complex but deterministic process; hence, information is scrambled but not completely lost. Wave propagation modelling in scattering media is an invaluable field of research and is regarded as a key objective in free-space communication and biomedical imaging<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>. Significant advancements have addressed wave control through disordered materials, resulting in scattering-assisted images using wavefront shaping techniques<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>. Within this research area, wavefront shaping methods have been explored in high-resolution imaging modalities such as optical coherence tomography<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>, fluorescence microscopy<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>, two-photon microscopy<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>, photoacoustic microscopy<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup> and improved resolution of images. These imaging modalities demonstrated that controlling the propagation of scattered light can be essentially addressed by optimising an input wavefront, a process that can be deployed via feedback optimisation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>, phase conjugation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup> or by measuring the optical transfer matrix<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par3">In its most basic embodiment, the deterministic approach towards space-time wave synthesis in scattering media is pivoted onto the idea of probing the media with spatially orthogonal illuminations and sensing their corresponding scattered wave at the output. For a sufficiently complex medium, this means that the spatiotemporal field pattern at the output can be associated with each input sampling function (or pattern) without ambiguity, as the transformation between input and output can be approximated as unique -although time-reversal would require the observation of the scattered wave in all directions, including the backscattering at the input. Via the application of the theoretical foundation presented in ref<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>, scattering can be managed as a linear combinatory process. Once a spatiotemporal output set is recorded for a series of orthogonal input illumination, we can project an arbitrary desired scattered field onto this set, determining the required input excitation. Indeed, this is not a statistically founded concept, and it is not based on any specific portion of the scattered field (i.e., ballistic or diffusing). Notably, the deterministic probing of the combinatory scattering element of a sample takes into account the surface scattering, and it is solely based on the orthogonality of the detected output pattern to reconstruct unambiguous input-output linear transformation.</p><p id="Par4">Trivially, in this vision, direct access to the instantaneous scattered fields is essential from an experimental point of view, as the superposition principle does not generally apply to photonic intensity-based scattering assessments. Additionally, in state-of-the-art, the extension of this concept to broadband illumination is challenged by the fact that the combinatory scattering element is, in general, a function of the frequency, while this aspect is marginally relevant when the superposition of scattered spatiotemporal waveforms is considered. Modern THz-time-domain spectroscopy (TDS) enables a direct route to measure the electric field oscillations in broadband pulses<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. Therefore, an intriguing question is whether working with the spatiotemporal electric field and the prospect of field-sensitive detection may shed light on reconstructing the combinatory scattering element of a sample on a broadband spectrum. In such a direction, we recently demonstrated field-level THz wave synthesis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par5">The core research literature in scattering functionalisation in photonics has presented a significant use of off-the-shelves spatial light modulators. Interestingly, spatial light modulation is somewhat challenging in the THz domain<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. The spatial modulation of THz waves has predominantly relied on indirect methods, including the use of spinning disk masks<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>, optically controlled carrier-based masking in silicon<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>, meta-material spatial light modulators<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>, spatial encoding of optical probe beams in electro-optic imaging systems<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup> as well as optical pump beams in systems using nonlinear<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup> or spintronic THz emitters<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>. Many of those wavefront modulation schemes are at the basis of single-pixel ghost imaging and other forms of imaging analysis. The use of THz spatial light modulation for achieving comprehensive wavefront control through scattering media remains at an embryonic stage. We can also observe that in this context, while typical illuminated areas in THz experimental embodiments recall similar implementations in optics, the spatial density of independent input modes in a scattering media is several orders of magnitude lower. This means that available diffraction-limited spatial light modulation cannot access a significant diversity of propagating modes in scattering samples<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>. As a possible solution implemented here, a near-field coupled knife-edge can be used to modulate the spatial properties of an input light field, exposing modes that are not coupled with input radiative fields. Here, we demonstrate the 1D imaging through scattering via a THz-TDS imager to decompose the time-domain scattered field at the output facet. The spatiotemporally resolved field-based measurements correspond to the set of spatially modulated THz wavefronts. The modulation set is simply obtained by scanning the input facet of the scattered 1D knife-edge placed in the near-field.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Results and discussion</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Spatiotemporal THz field mixing in scattering media</title><p id="Par6">We begin addressing how fields at source and detection planes are connected by a complex combinatory matrix element of a scatterer precisely for the case of broadband pulse illumination. We define the input-output field relationship via the space-time impulse response of scattering media, <inline-formula id="IEq1"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e392">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:{T}_{x}\left(x,y;{x}^{{\prime\:}},{y}^{{\prime\:}};t,{t}^{{\prime\:}}\right)$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_95951_Article_IEq1.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, as<disp-formula id="Equ1"><label>1</label><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e398">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:{E}_{d}\left({x}^{{\prime\:}},{y}^{{\prime\:}},{z}_{d};{t}^{{\prime\:}}\right)=\iiint\:{T}_{x}\left(x,y;{x}^{{\prime\:}},{y}^{{\prime\:}};t,{t}^{{\prime\:}}\right){E}_{s}\left(x,y,{z}_{s};t\right)dxdydt$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_95951_Article_Equ1.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par7">where, <inline-formula id="IEq2"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e406">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:{E}_{d}\left({E}_{s}\right)$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_95951_Article_IEq2.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is spatiotemporal field distribution at the detection/source plane in the cartesian coordinates defined by <inline-formula id="IEq3"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e412">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:({x}^{{\prime\:}},{y}^{{\prime\:}},{z}_{d})/(x,y,{z}_{s}$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_95951_Article_IEq3.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>), respectively. In frequency domain <inline-formula id="IEq4"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e418">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:\omega\:$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_95951_Article_IEq4.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, Eq.&#x000a0;(<xref rid="Equ1" ref-type="disp-formula">1</xref>) reads as follows,<disp-formula id="Equ2"><label>2</label><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e427">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:{\stackrel{\sim}{E}}_{d}\left({x}^{{\prime\:}},{y}^{{\prime\:}},{z}_{d};{\upomega\:}\right)=\iint\:{\stackrel{\sim}{T}}_{x}\left(x,y;{x}^{{\prime\:}},{y}^{{\prime\:}};{\upomega\:}\right){\stackrel{\sim}{E}}_{s}\left(x,y,{z}_{s};{\upomega\:}\right)dxdy$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_95951_Article_Equ2.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par8">where <inline-formula id="IEq5"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e435">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:{\stackrel{\sim}{E}}_{d}$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_95951_Article_IEq5.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="IEq6"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e441">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:{\stackrel{\sim}{E}}_{s}$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_95951_Article_IEq6.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> denote the time-Fourier transform of the fields at detection, source plane and <inline-formula id="IEq7"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e447">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:{\stackrel{\sim}{T}}_{x}\left(x,y;{x}^{{\prime\:}},{y}^{{\prime\:}};{\upomega\:}\right)$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_95951_Article_IEq7.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> represents coherent transfer function for a scattering sample.</p><p id="Par9">THz source providing an ultrafast broadband pulse with a duration shorter than Thouless time (the typical time scale over which light diffuses across the medium ) results in randomised field transient in both space and time after propagating through scattering media<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>. In Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, we recorded the transmitted time-resolved THz field distribution in response to Gaussian beam illumination on the scattering sample (sample details are in supplementary S1), as shown in the schematic (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a). As expected, scattering introduces a time-dependent morphology of the scattered field profile. Specifically, the THz field distribution resulted in complex spatial interference patterns in the transmission (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>b). The evolution of the spatial field on an ultrafast time scale shows the transition from the ballistic to the diffusive scattering regimes. Initial spatial THz field profiles at 8.85 ps and 9.45 ps show relatively more uniformity, indicating a ballistic propagation of THz waves associated with a low statistical occurrence of photon scattering, i.e., the THz field maintains its spatial momentum content. As time progresses, the diffused photons emerge, leading to an entirely randomization of the spatial field profiles due to several scattering occurrences inside the medium, shown by the spatial frames at 10.35 ps, 14.4 ps, 15 ps, and 18.9 ps. Also, the scattering process becomes more apparent in the temporal progression of distinct pixels that constitute the considerably broadened pulses in conjunction with the different time delays. However, the overall observed time delay in the pulses can be attributed to the thickness of the scattering sample (5.53&#x000a0;mm). As a result of the dispersive characteristics inherently present in scattering media, the temporal widening of a scattered pulse occurs concomitantly with the attenuation of its peak values. The primary cause of attenuation in the scattered pulses is attributed to the scattering of high-frequency components of the impinging pulse, as illustrated in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>c. The measured values of the mean free path (<inline-formula id="IEq8"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e475">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:{l}_{s}$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_95951_Article_IEq8.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>) for the sample are shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>d. In our experiments, we observed the variation of <inline-formula id="IEq9"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e484">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:{l}_{s}\left(\omega\:\right)$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_95951_Article_IEq9.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> ranging between 1&#x000a0;mm and 10&#x000a0;mm within the source bandwidth. Note that because the scattering media is near-field coupled with the detector, scattering can appear highly inhomogeneous in spectral properties at the output. The spatial-spectral profiles of the THz field at 0.2&#x02013;0.7 THz (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>e) exhibits the formation of broadband speckles, characterised by subwavelength spot size and disordered phase distribution. We highlight that the detection is near-field coupled with the scattering media, hence, the resolution is not bounded by the wavelength. Additionally, in our experiment, the THz source spectrum extends up to ~&#x02009;1.5 THz (supplementary figures <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref> and S4), but multiple scattering attenuates higher frequencies, limiting the effective spectrum to &#x0003c;&#x02009;1 THz (supplementary figure <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>(c)); thus, analysis is performed in the 0.2&#x02013;0.7 THz range where SNR is optimal and spatio-spectral characterisation is more reliable.</p><p id="Par10">
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Broadband speckle formation of THz fields. (<bold>a</bold>) Schematic showing the projection of a pulsed THz field at the source plane of the scattering sample and the collection of the scattered field via a time-domain THz imager. (<bold>b</bold>) Spatiotemporal THz field transmission through scattering samples exhibits temporal distortion, as shown in the pixel-wise time evolution of the pulses and random modulation in the spatial field distributions (video 1). Field amplitude is plotted 4 times the original spatial field at <inline-formula id="IEq10"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e513">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:14.40\:\text{p}\text{s}$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_95951_Article_IEq10.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="IEq11"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e519">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:15.00\:\text{p}\text{s}$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_95951_Article_IEq11.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula id="IEq12"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e525">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:18.90\:\text{p}\text{s}$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_95951_Article_IEq12.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. (<bold>c</bold>) The pixel-wise spectrum of scattered fields corresponds to the pulses shown in a. (<bold>d</bold>) Mean free path of the scattering sample within the THz source bandwidth (<bold>e</bold>) The spatial multiplexing of broadband THz fields and phases illustrates the broadband speckle synthesis within the THz source bandwidth (video 2).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_95951_Fig1_HTML" id="d33e542"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Scattering media characterisation using knife-edge wavefront shaping</title><p id="Par11">The core idea is to provide a unique scattering association to different shielding portions of the broadband THz field illumination (as per ref<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup>) with a knife-edge moving in the near-field of the scatterer. The scatterer waveform obtained by the 2D time-domain detection set is used as a base to reconstruct a 1D transmission matrix. Once the transmission matrix is known, the image of any 1D object can be deterministically retrieved. Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a illustrates a typical setting for a knife-edge (a thin conductive blade clipping a Gaussian beam) scan, where the THz near-field imager collects scattered fields from the sample partially illuminated. We can write the spatiotemporal field profile (<inline-formula id="IEq13"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e558">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:{E}_{s}$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_95951_Article_IEq13.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>) generated by the specific placement of the knife at the source plane as,<disp-formula id="Equ3"><label>3</label><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e564">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:{E}_{s}\left(x,y,{z}_{s};t\right)\propto\:\text{K}\left(x{,y}_{o},{z}_{s}\right){E}_{in}\left(x,y,{z}_{s};t\right)$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_95951_Article_Equ3.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par12">where <inline-formula id="IEq14"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e572">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:\text{K}\left(x,{y}_{o},{z}_{s}\right)$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_95951_Article_IEq14.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> represents the point-wise spatial response of the knife-edge, which is defined as a one-dimensional Heaviside step function in the transverse direction with a fixed coordinate position <inline-formula id="IEq15"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e578">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:{(y}_{o},{z}_{s})$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_95951_Article_IEq15.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq16"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e584">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:{E}_{in}$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_95951_Article_IEq16.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is the time-resolved Gaussian beam profile from the source. The knife-edge used in our setup is a thin conductive blade with micron-scale thickness at the sharp edge, placed approximately parallel to the scattering media input facet, and transversally translated, as shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>(a). Initially, we characterised the spatial beam profile for the reference THz field (included in the supplementary figure <xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">S4</xref>) to normalise the results. The key idea here is that (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a), because of the near-field coupling, the knife-edge can selectively couple with a relatively large number of modes in the scattering volume (i.e. discernible scattering outputs) not necessarily accessible through far-field illuminations.</p><p id="Par22">
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Scattering media characterisation using knife-edge wavefront shaping. (<bold>a</bold>) Schematics of the experimental setup showing a knife-edge shapes the impinging THz wavefront at the front end of the scattering medium (8% fractional mass concentration of Silicon microparticles embedded in paraffin) and corresponding scattered fields are collected using a THz time-domain imager placed within the near-field region. By combining the transmitted fields corresponding to the various knife-edge positions, the space of potential 1D spatiotemporal images could be derived and further constructed as a hyperspectral combinatory scattering matrix to characterise the scattering sample. (<bold>b</bold>) variation of pulse peak value with respect to the various transverse position of knife-edge. (<bold>c</bold>) spatial field amplitude and phase profile at 0.3 THz corresponding to knife-edge position 1 and 2 (dashed lines shown in <bold>b</bold>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_95951_Fig2_HTML" id="d33e621"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par15">Figure <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b illustrates the variation in positive and negative peak values of the pulse as a function of the transverse position of the knife-edge. The scan axis is oriented to uncover more THz field as the translation increases. In the spectral domain, the spatial field amplitude and phase distribution at 0.3 THz, corresponding to the input wavefronts generated by two different knife-edge positions (at 1.5&#x000a0;mm and 4.5&#x000a0;mm), are shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>c, highlighting the influence of the scattered field from the knife-edge positions.</p><p id="Par16">We can write fields at the source and detection plane as vectors <inline-formula id="IEq17"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e633">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:{e}_{s}\in\:{\mathbb{C}}^{S\:\times\:1}$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_95951_Article_IEq17.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq18"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e639">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:{e}_{d}\in\:{\mathbb{C}}^{D\:\times\:1}$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_95951_Article_IEq18.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, and define a scattering combinatory transfer matrix as <inline-formula id="IEq19"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e645">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:{\varvec{T}}_{ds}\in\:{\mathbb{C}}^{S\:\times\:D}$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_95951_Article_IEq19.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, for each frequency <italic>&#x003c9;</italic>. S and D represent the number of independent pixels (or segments) that sample the input and output field plane, respectively. For R number of independent spectral sampling points, <bold><italic>T</italic></bold> is a <inline-formula id="IEq20"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e658">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:{\mathbb{C}}^{S\:\times\:D\times\:R}$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_95951_Article_IEq20.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> three-dimensional matrix, defined as <inline-formula id="IEq21"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e664">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:{\varvec{T}}_{ds}\left({\omega\:}_{r}\right)$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_95951_Article_IEq21.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. For the given r-th spectral mode, the linear relationship between generic s-th source and d-th detection spatial segments reads as follows,<disp-formula id="Equ4"><label>4</label><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e670">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:{e}_{d}\left({\omega\:}_{r}\right)=\sum\:_{s}{\varvec{T}}_{ds}\left({\omega\:}_{r}\right){e}_{s}\left({\omega\:}_{r}\right)$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_95951_Article_Equ4.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par17">Further, for each i-th position of the knife-edge, we collect the corresponding <inline-formula id="IEq22"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e678">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:{e}_{d}^{\left(i\right)}\left({\omega\:}_{r}\right)$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_95951_Article_IEq22.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and column-wise stack in a measurement matrix <inline-formula id="IEq23"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e684">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:\varvec{M}\left({\omega\:}_{r}\right)\in\:{\mathbb{C}}^{D\:\times\:P}$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_95951_Article_IEq23.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and corresponding synthesised THz wavefront in decomposition matrix <inline-formula id="IEq24"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e690">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:\varvec{X}\left({\omega\:}_{r}\right)\in\:{\mathbb{C}}^{S\:\times\:P}$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_95951_Article_IEq24.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, where P is the number of wavefronts modulated by the edge of the knife. To identify the transfer matrix at frequency <inline-formula id="IEq25"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e696">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:\omega\:$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_95951_Article_IEq25.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, we set up a least square optimisation problem as,<disp-formula id="Equ5"><label>5</label><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e702">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:{\varvec{T}}_{r}^{\dagger}\left({\omega\:}_{r}\right)=\text{a}\text{r}\text{g}\text{m}\text{i}{\text{n}}_{\:{T}_{r}\in\:{\complement\:}^{S\:\times\:D}}\:\frac{1}{2}\:{\left\| {\varvec{M}\left({\omega\:}_{r}\right)}^{\dagger}-{\varvec{X}\left({\omega\:}_{r}\right)}^{\dagger}{\varvec{T}}_{r}^{\dagger}\left({\omega\:}_{r}\right) \right\|}_{2}^{2}$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_95951_Article_Equ5.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par18">where &#x02020; represents matrix conjugate transpose operation. We solve such an optimisation problem using an active-set al.gorithm<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Hyperspectral image retrieval of a hidden object behind the scattering media</title><p id="Par19">The ability to reconstruct the combinatory transfer matrix of the scatterers allows for the imaging of objects obscured by a scattering medium. Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a illustrates the implementation of our image reconstruction process, where a metallic object <inline-formula id="IEq27"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e721">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:O\left(x,y\right)$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_95951_Article_IEq27.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is positioned on the input surface of the scattering medium. This shapes the impinging THz field and results in convoluted spatiotemporal scattered field distribution at the output of the media as,<disp-formula id="Equ6"><label>6</label><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e727">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:D\left({x}^{{\prime\:}},{y}^{{\prime\:}};{t}^{{\prime\:}}\right)=\iiint\:{T}_{x}\left(x,y;{x}^{{\prime\:}},{y}^{{\prime\:}};t,{t}^{{\prime\:}}\right)O\left(x,y\right){E}_{in}\left(x,y;t\right)dxdydt$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_95951_Article_Equ6.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par20">where <inline-formula id="IEq28"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e735">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:D\left({x}^{{\prime\:}},{y}^{{\prime\:}},t\right)$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_95951_Article_IEq28.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is spatiotemporal field distribution recorded by THz near field imager. To extract the information of a hidden object behind the complex media from the measurements, we conduct a standard deconvolution of the retrieved combinatory transfer matrix, which produces the time-resolved field image <inline-formula id="IEq29"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e741">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:{E}_{retreived}\left(x,y,t\right)$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_95951_Article_IEq29.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> &#x0200b;as follows:<disp-formula id="Equ7"><label>7</label><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e747">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:{E}_{retrieved}\left(x,y;t\right)={\mathcal{F}}^{-1}\left[\stackrel{\sim}{Tr}{\left(x,y;{x}^{{\prime\:}},{y}^{{\prime\:}};\omega\:\right)}^{-1}*\stackrel{\sim}{D}\left({x}^{{\prime\:}},{y}^{{\prime\:}};\omega\:\right)\right]$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_95951_Article_Equ7.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par21">where <inline-formula id="IEq30"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e755">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:{\mathcal{F}}^{-1}$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_95951_Article_IEq30.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and * represents the inverse time-Fourier transform and spatial convolution operation, respectively, and <inline-formula id="IEq31"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e761">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:\stackrel{\sim}{D}\left({x}^{{\prime\:}},{y}^{{\prime\:}};\omega\:\right)$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_95951_Article_IEq31.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is the time-Fourier transform of the recorded signal. To perform deconvolution, the essential task involves determining the inverse of <inline-formula id="IEq32"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e767">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:\stackrel{\sim}{Tr}(x,y;{x}^{{\prime\:}},{y}^{{\prime\:}};\omega\:)$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_95951_Article_IEq32.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. We employed the Moore&#x02013;Penrose pseudo-inversion method, implemented by a truncated singular-value decomposition. Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a depicts the experimental arrangement that involves acquiring time-domain scattered fields by placing a one-dimensional image object (200 &#x003bc;m copper wire) at the anterior end of the scattering sample. Initially, we perform a Time-Fourier transform of the recorded signal to extract the spectroscopic information available for each pixel. As illustrated in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a, it is evident that the transmitted field-phase profiles of the object, subsequent to exposure to a uniform THz pulse, undergo a complete scrambling process of information within the scattering sample. The scrambled information of the object is further employed with the direct deconvolution operation as delineated by Eq.&#x000a0;(<xref rid="Equ7" ref-type="disp-formula">7</xref>) in order to conduct the image retrieval procedure. Intriguingly, the outcome of this reconstruction (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>b) is an image retrieval process across the extensive bandwidth of the THz spectrum. We can observe the remarkable matching with the measured direct field image without a scattering medium, in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>c. Intriguingly, because the wire is metallic, we can appreciate that the post-scattered field polarised along the wire direction, x. In the spectrum domain, the phase image of the wire is clearly accompanied by lateral echoes that represent the phase delay accumulated by the scattered field along x<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par220">
<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Hyperspectral image retrieval through scattering media. (<bold>a</bold>) Broadband scrambled field and phase profiles of a 1D imaging object (inset image: 200 <inline-formula id="IEq34"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e804">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:\mu\:m$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_95951_Article_IEq34.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> thick copper wire over a reference ruler with ticks spaced 100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m) hidden behind the scattering media (video 3). (<bold>b</bold>) Hyperspectral image retrieval: the data in a. are deconvoluted by the reconstructed transmission matrix of a scattering sample (video 4). (<bold>c</bold>) Hyperspectral THz images of the 1D imaging object used in a. for comparison (video 5).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_95951_Fig3_HTML" id="d33e817"/></fig>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec7"><title>Experimental settings and data post-processing</title><p id="Par23">The experimental setting is based on a full-field THz-TDS microscope as per ref<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup>, and shown in supplementary figure <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">S2</xref>. A THz field generated by a large aperture LiNbO<sub>3</sub> prism, excited with a tilted front pulse from a regenerative amplified source, is projected into the detection crystal (a thin LiNbO<sub>3</sub>) that functions as an imaging platform, as per supplementary S2. The field of view offered by THz imager is about 1.44&#x000a0;mm &#x000d7; 1.44&#x000a0;mm. The reflection of a large probe, impinging on the opposite side of the detection crystal performs a large-area electro-optic sampling, its relative delay being controlled by a delay stage placed on the optical THz pump. An imaging system project to orthogonal circular polarisation components of the probe beam onto a CMOS camera sensor, which results in a spatial resolution of 28.8&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m spatial period (obtained by binning the 600&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;600 image resolution output down to 50&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;50 to achieve appropriate signal-to-noise ratio). supplementary figure <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">S3</xref> describes the role of detection plane spatial sampling. The typical performance of the imaging setup is shown in supplementary figure <xref rid="MOESM5" ref-type="media">S5</xref>, which serves as a benchmark for our imaging system. As we compare our results with the ongoing investigation in the optical domain, it is important to stress that the temporal coherence of scatterers is a pivotal problem at optical wavelength (i.e. the medium undergoes rapid thermal changes at scales comparable to or larger than the wavelength), this is significantly mitigated by the long THz wavelength. Hence, we did not experience any drift in the scattered pattern within the typical timeframe of an experimental session.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par24">We experimentally demonstrated a deterministic approach towards imaging through complex scattering media operating with broadband THz pulses. A large area-field detection is exploited to perform an orthogonal sampling decomposition of the scattering transmission matrix. Regardless of the relatively low density of scattering element in the medium, a near-field coupled knife-edge allows the excitation of a sufficiently large number of separable scattering modes to allow complete reconstruction of a field distribution through the medium. We performed a benchmark of this concept using a 1D image. As this approach does not exploit any statistical description of the scatterer and simply applies a super-position principle, we demonstrated full operation with broadband waveforms, which translates into the ability to reconstruct the full scattered spectrum from the object, i.e. their spectral fingerprint. This specific aspect is currently the subject of further studies. We believe our microscopy approach is a gateway to new possibilities in studying complex media, specifically scattering microstructures in biological systems.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.</p><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41598_2025_95951_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><caption><p>Supplementary Material 1</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="41598_2025_95951_MOESM2_ESM.avi"><caption><p>Supplementary Material 2</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3"><media xlink:href="41598_2025_95951_MOESM3_ESM.avi"><caption><p>Supplementary Material 3</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM4"><media xlink:href="41598_2025_95951_MOESM4_ESM.avi"><caption><p>Supplementary Material 4</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM5"><media xlink:href="41598_2025_95951_MOESM5_ESM.avi"><caption><p>Supplementary Material 5</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM6"><media xlink:href="41598_2025_95951_MOESM6_ESM.avi"><caption><p>Supplementary Material 6</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>All authors were engaged in the general discussion regarding the conceptualisation. Experimental investigators: V.K. (lead), V.C. and A.C. All authors contributed to the general understanding of the results and drafting of the paper, the formal analysis and data curation. J.S.T.G., L.P., L.O. A.P. and M.P. supervised the research activities.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This project received funding from the European Research Council (ERC) under the European Union&#x02019;s Horizon 2020 Research and Innovation Programme Grant No. 725046. This project has received funding from the European Research Council (ERC) under the European Union&#x02019;s Horizon 2020 research and innovation programme grant agreement no. 851758 (TELSCOMBE). The authors acknowledge financial support from the (UK) Engineering and Physical Sciences Research Council (EPSRC), Grant Nos. EP/X012689/1 and EP/S001018/1 and Leverhulme Trust (Early Career Fellowship ECF-2020-537 and Early Career Fellowship ECF-2022-710, Early Career Fellowship ECF-2023-315, Early Career Fellowship ECF-2024-529 Project grant RPG-2022-090), and from the Loughborough University Vice-Chancellor Independent Research Fellowship (STARLIGHT).</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The data that support the findings of this study are openly available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://repository.lboro.ac.uk/">https://repository.lboro.ac.uk/</ext-link> at 10.17028/rd.lboro.28541129, reference number 28541129.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar2" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par25">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ishimaru, A. <italic>Wave Propagation and Scattering in Random Media &#x02013;&#x02009;1st Edition</italic> (Academic, 1978).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sheng, P. <italic>Introduction To Wave Scattering, Localization, and Mesoscopic Phenomena</italic> (Springer, 2006).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Recent advances in terahertz technology for biomedical applications</article-title><source>Quant. Imaging Med. Surg.</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>34555</fpage><lpage>34355</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Sun, Q. et al. Recent advances in terahertz technology for biomedical applications. <italic>Quant. Imaging Med. Surg.</italic><bold>7</bold>, 34555&#x02013;34355 (2017).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Reconfigurable beam system for non-line-of-sight free-space optical communication</article-title><source>Light Sci. Appl.</source><year>2019</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>69</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31645917</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Cao, Z. et al. Reconfigurable beam system for non-line-of-sight free-space optical communication. <italic>Light Sci. Appl.</italic><bold>8</bold>, 69 (2019).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31645917</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Deep optical imaging within complex scattering media</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Phys.</source><year>2020</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>158</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Yoon, S. et al. Deep optical imaging within complex scattering media. <italic>Nat. Rev. Phys.</italic><bold>2</bold>, 141&#x02013;158 (2020).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mosk</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Lagendijk</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lerosey</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Fink</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Controlling waves in space and time for imaging and focusing in complex media</article-title><source>Nat. Photonics</source><year>2012</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>283</fpage><lpage>292</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Mosk, A. P., Lagendijk, A., Lerosey, G. &#x00026; Fink, M. Controlling waves in space and time for imaging and focusing in complex media. <italic>Nat. Photonics</italic>. <bold>6</bold>, 283&#x02013;292 (2012).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rotter</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gigan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Light fields in complex media: mesoscopic scattering Meets wave control</article-title><source>Rev. Mod. Phys.</source><year>2017</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>015005</fpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Rotter, S. &#x00026; Gigan, S. Light fields in complex media: mesoscopic scattering Meets wave control. <italic>Rev. Mod. Phys.</italic><bold>89</bold>, 015005 (2017).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gigan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Imaging and computing with disorder</article-title><source>Nat. Phys.</source><year>2022</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>980</fpage><lpage>985</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Gigan, S. Imaging and computing with disorder. <italic>Nat. Phys.</italic><bold>18</bold>, 980&#x02013;985 (2022).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gigan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Roadmap on wavefront shaping and deep imaging in complex media</article-title><source>J. Phys. Photonics</source><year>2022</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>042501</fpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Gigan, S. et al. Roadmap on wavefront shaping and deep imaging in complex media. <italic>J. Phys. Photonics</italic>. <bold>4</bold>, 042501 (2022).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Complex wavefront shaping for optimal depth-selective focusing in optical coherence tomography</article-title><source>Opt. Express</source><year>2013</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>2890</fpage><lpage>2902</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23481747</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Jang, J. et al. Complex wavefront shaping for optimal depth-selective focusing in optical coherence tomography. <italic>Opt. Express</italic>. <bold>21</bold>, 2890&#x02013;2902 (2013).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23481747</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aizik</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gkioulekas</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fluorescent wavefront shaping using incoherent iterative phase conjugation</article-title><source>Optica</source><year>2022</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>746</fpage><lpage>754</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Aizik, D., Gkioulekas, I. &#x00026; Levin, A. Fluorescent wavefront shaping using incoherent iterative phase conjugation. <italic>Optica</italic><bold>9</bold>, 746&#x02013;754 (2022).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rueckel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mack-Bucher</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Denk</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adaptive wavefront correction in two-photon microscopy using coherence-gated wavefront sensing</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci.</source><year>2006</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>17137</fpage><lpage>17142</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17088565</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Rueckel, M., Mack-Bucher, J. A. &#x00026; Denk, W. Adaptive wavefront correction in two-photon microscopy using coherence-gated wavefront sensing. <italic>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci.</italic><bold>103</bold>, 17137&#x02013;17142 (2006).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17088565</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chaigneau</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Poland</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Girkin</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Silver</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of wavefront distortion and scattering on 2-photon microscopy in mammalian brain tissue</article-title><source>Opt. Express</source><year>2011</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>22755</fpage><lpage>22774</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22109156</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Chaigneau, E., Wright, A. J., Poland, S. P., Girkin, J. M. &#x00026; Silver, R. A. Impact of wavefront distortion and scattering on 2-photon microscopy in mammalian brain tissue. <italic>Opt. Express</italic>. <bold>19</bold>, 22755&#x02013;22774 (2011).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22109156</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Photoacoustic wavefront shaping with high signal to noise ratio for light focusing through scattering media</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2019</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>4328</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30867506</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Sun, J. et al. Photoacoustic wavefront shaping with high signal to noise ratio for light focusing through scattering media. <italic>Sci. Rep.</italic><bold>9</bold>, 4328 (2019).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30867506</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vellekoop</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mosk</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Focusing coherent light through opaque strongly scattering media</article-title><source>Opt. Lett.</source><year>2007</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>2309</fpage><lpage>2311</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17700768</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Vellekoop, I. M. &#x00026; Mosk, A. P. Focusing coherent light through opaque strongly scattering media. <italic>Opt. Lett.</italic><bold>32</bold>, 2309&#x02013;2311 (2007).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17700768</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vellekoop</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mosk</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Universal optimal transmission of light through disordered materials</article-title><source>Phys. Rev. Lett.</source><year>2008</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>120601</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18851352</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Vellekoop, I. M. &#x00026; Mosk, A. P. Universal optimal transmission of light through disordered materials. <italic>Phys. Rev. Lett.</italic><bold>101</bold>, 120601 (2008).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18851352</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yaqoob</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Psaltis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Feld</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Optical phase conjugation for turbidity suppression in biological samples</article-title><source>Nat. Photonics</source><year>2008</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>110</fpage><lpage>115</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19492016</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Yaqoob, Z., Psaltis, D., Feld, M. S. &#x00026; Yang, C. Optical phase conjugation for turbidity suppression in biological samples. <italic>Nat. Photonics</italic>. <bold>2</bold>, 110&#x02013;115 (2008).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19492016</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baek</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>de Aguiar</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><name><surname>Gigan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phase conjugation with spatially incoherent light in complex media</article-title><source>Nat. Photonics</source><year>2023</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1114</fpage><lpage>1119</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Baek, Y., de Aguiar, H. B. &#x00026; Gigan, S. Phase conjugation with spatially incoherent light in complex media. <italic>Nat. Photonics</italic>. <bold>17</bold>, 1114&#x02013;1119 (2023).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Popoff</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Measuring the transmission matrix in optics: an approach to the study and control of light propagation in disordered media</article-title><source>Phys. Rev. Lett.</source><year>2010</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>100601</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20366410</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Popoff, S. M. et al. Measuring the transmission matrix in optics: an approach to the study and control of light propagation in disordered media. <italic>Phys. Rev. Lett.</italic><bold>104</bold>, 100601 (2010).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20366410</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Bodington</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Reinig</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kubby</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High-speed scanning interferometric focusing by fast measurement of binary transmission matrix for channel demixing</article-title><source>Opt. Express</source><year>2015</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>14168</fpage><lpage>14187</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26072785</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">Tao, X., Bodington, D., Reinig, M. &#x00026; Kubby, J. High-speed scanning interferometric focusing by fast measurement of binary transmission matrix for channel demixing. <italic>Opt. Express</italic>. <bold>23</bold>, 14168&#x02013;14187 (2015).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26072785</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ultrahigh enhancement of light focusing through disordered media controlled by mega-pixel modes</article-title><source>Opt. Express</source><year>2017</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>8036</fpage><lpage>8047</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28380926</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Yu, H., Lee, K. &#x00026; Park, Y. Ultrahigh enhancement of light focusing through disordered media controlled by mega-pixel modes. <italic>Opt. Express</italic>. <bold>25</bold>, 8036&#x02013;8047 (2017).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28380926</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mariani</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Scattering media characterization with phase-only wavefront modulation</article-title><source>Opt. Express</source><year>2018</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>2369</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29401777</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">Mariani, F. et al. Scattering media characterization with phase-only wavefront modulation. <italic>Opt. Express</italic>. <bold>26</bold>, 2369 (2018).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29401777</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Deterministic terahertz wave control in scattering media</article-title><source>ACS Photonics</source><year>2022</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>2634</fpage><lpage>2642</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35996370</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Kumar, V. et al. Deterministic terahertz wave control in scattering media. <italic>ACS Photonics</italic>. <bold>9</bold>, 2634&#x02013;2642 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35996370</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cecconi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Pasquazi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Totero Gongora</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Peccianti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nonlinear field-control of terahertz waves in random media for spatiotemporal focusing</article-title><source>Open. Res. Eur.</source><year>2022</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>32</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37645307</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">Cecconi, V., Kumar, V., Pasquazi, A., Totero Gongora, J. S. &#x00026; Peccianti, M. Nonlinear field-control of terahertz waves in random media for spatiotemporal focusing. <italic>Open. Res. Eur.</italic><bold>2</bold>, 32 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37645307</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Fourier synthetic aperture-based time-resolved terahertz imaging</article-title><source>Photonics Res.</source><year>2024</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>407</fpage><lpage>416</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="journal">Kumar, V. et al. Fourier synthetic aperture-based time-resolved terahertz imaging. <italic>Photonics Res.</italic><bold>13</bold>, 407&#x02013;416 (2024).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR26" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cecconi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Terahertz spatiotemporal wave synthesis in random systems</article-title><source>ACS Photonics</source><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acsphotonics.3c01671</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38405391</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26" publication-type="journal">Cecconi, V. et al. Terahertz spatiotemporal wave synthesis in random systems. <italic>ACS Photonics</italic>. 10.1021/acsphotonics.3c01671 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38405391</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR27" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ozcan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jarrahi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High-throughput terahertz imaging: progress and challenges</article-title><source>Light Sci. Appl.</source><year>2023</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>233</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37714865</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27" publication-type="journal">Li, X., Li, J., Li, Y., Ozcan, A. &#x00026; Jarrahi, M. High-throughput terahertz imaging: progress and challenges. <italic>Light Sci. Appl.</italic><bold>12</bold>, 233 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37714865</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR28" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Terahertz pulsed spectroscopic imaging using optimized binary masks</article-title><source>Appl. Phys. Lett.</source><year>2009</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>231112</fpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28" publication-type="journal">Shen, Y. C. et al. Terahertz pulsed spectroscopic imaging using optimized binary masks. <italic>Appl. Phys. Lett.</italic><bold>95</bold>, 231112 (2009).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR29" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Spinning disk for compressive imaging</article-title><source>Opt. Lett.</source><year>2012</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>46</fpage><lpage>48</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22212786</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29" publication-type="journal">Shen, H. et al. Spinning disk for compressive imaging. <italic>Opt. Lett.</italic><bold>37</bold>, 46&#x02013;48 (2012).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22212786</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR30" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shrekenhamer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Watts</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Padilla</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Terahertz single pixel imaging with an optically controlled dynamic spatial light modulator</article-title><source>Opt. Express</source><year>2013</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>12507</fpage><lpage>12518</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23736469</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30" publication-type="journal">Shrekenhamer, D., Watts, C. M. &#x00026; Padilla, W. J. Terahertz single pixel imaging with an optically controlled dynamic spatial light modulator. <italic>Opt. Express</italic>. <bold>21</bold>, 12507&#x02013;12518 (2013).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23736469</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR31" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stantchev</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Noninvasive, near-field terahertz imaging of hidden objects using a single-pixel detector</article-title><source>Sci. Adv.</source><year>2016</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>e1600190</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27386577</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR31" publication-type="journal">Stantchev, R. I. et al. Noninvasive, near-field terahertz imaging of hidden objects using a single-pixel detector. <italic>Sci. Adv.</italic><bold>2</bold>, e1600190 (2016).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27386577</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR32" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stantchev</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Blu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Pickwell-MacPherson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Real-time terahertz imaging with a single-pixel detector</article-title><source>Nat. Commun.</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>2535</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32439984</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32" publication-type="journal">Stantchev, R. I., Yu, X., Blu, T. &#x00026; Pickwell-MacPherson, E. Real-time terahertz imaging with a single-pixel detector. <italic>Nat. Commun.</italic><bold>11</bold>, 2535 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32439984</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR33" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stantchev</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Pickwell-MacPherson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rapid imaging of pulsed terahertz radiation with spatial light modulators and neural networks</article-title><source>ACS Photonics</source><year>2021</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>3150</fpage><lpage>3155</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR33" publication-type="journal">Stantchev, R. I., Li, K. &#x00026; Pickwell-MacPherson, E. Rapid imaging of pulsed terahertz radiation with spatial light modulators and neural networks. <italic>ACS Photonics</italic>. <bold>8</bold>, 3150&#x02013;3155 (2021).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR34" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Watts</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Terahertz compressive imaging with metamaterial spatial light modulators</article-title><source>Nat. Photonics</source><year>2014</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>605</fpage><lpage>609</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR34" publication-type="journal">Watts, C. M. et al. Terahertz compressive imaging with metamaterial spatial light modulators. <italic>Nat. Photonics</italic>. <bold>8</bold>, 605&#x02013;609 (2014).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR35" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hashemi</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Cakmakyapan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jarrahi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reconfigurable metamaterials for terahertz wave manipulation</article-title><source>Rep. Prog Phys.</source><year>2017</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>094501</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28590254</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR35" publication-type="journal">Hashemi, M. R., Cakmakyapan, S. &#x00026; Jarrahi, M. Reconfigurable metamaterials for terahertz wave manipulation. <italic>Rep. Prog Phys.</italic><bold>80</bold>, 094501 (2017).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28590254</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR36" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dual-color terahertz spatial light modulator for single-pixel imaging</article-title><source>Light Sci. Appl.</source><year>2022</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>191</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35739086</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR36" publication-type="journal">Li, W. et al. Dual-color terahertz spatial light modulator for single-pixel imaging. <italic>Light Sci. Appl.</italic><bold>11</bold>, 191 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35739086</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR37" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spatial sampling of terahertz fields with sub-wavelength accuracy via probe-beam encoding</article-title><source>Light Sci. Appl.</source><year>2019</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>55</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31231521</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR37" publication-type="journal">Zhao, J., Williams, E. Y., Zhang, K., Boyd, R. W. &#x00026; X.-C. &#x00026; Spatial sampling of terahertz fields with sub-wavelength accuracy via probe-beam encoding. <italic>Light Sci. Appl.</italic><bold>8</bold>, 55 (2019).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31231521</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR38" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olivieri</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gongora</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Pasquazi</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Peccianti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Time-resolved nonlinear ghost imaging</article-title><source>ACS Photonics</source><year>2018</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>3379</fpage><lpage>3388</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR38" publication-type="journal">Olivieri, L., Gongora, T., Pasquazi, J. S., Peccianti, M. &#x00026; A. &#x00026; Time-resolved nonlinear ghost imaging. <italic>ACS Photonics</italic>. <bold>5</bold>, 3379&#x02013;3388 (2018).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR39" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Totero Gongora</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Route to intelligent imaging reconstruction via terahertz nonlinear ghost imaging</article-title><source>Micromachines</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>521</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32443881</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR39" publication-type="journal">Totero Gongora, J. S. et al. Route to intelligent imaging reconstruction via terahertz nonlinear ghost imaging. <italic>Micromachines</italic><bold>11</bold>, 521 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32443881</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR40" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olivieri</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hyperspectral terahertz microscopy via nonlinear ghost imaging</article-title><source>Optica</source><year>2020</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>186</fpage><lpage>191</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR40" publication-type="journal">Olivieri, L. et al. Hyperspectral terahertz microscopy via nonlinear ghost imaging. <italic>Optica</italic><bold>7</bold>, 186&#x02013;191 (2020).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR41" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olivieri</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Terahertz nonlinear ghost imaging via plane decomposition: toward near-field micro-volumetry</article-title><source>ACS Photonics</source><year>2023</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>1726</fpage><lpage>1734</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37363629</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR41" publication-type="journal">Olivieri, L. et al. Terahertz nonlinear ghost imaging via plane decomposition: toward near-field micro-volumetry. <italic>ACS Photonics</italic>. <bold>10</bold>, 1726&#x02013;1734 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37363629</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR42" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ghost spintronic THz-emitter-array microscope</article-title><source>Light Sci. Appl.</source><year>2020</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>99</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32549979</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR42" publication-type="journal">Chen, S. C. et al. Ghost spintronic THz-emitter-array microscope. <italic>Light Sci. Appl.</italic><bold>9</bold>, 99 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32549979</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR43" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lemoult</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lerosey</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>de Rosny</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fink</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Manipulating spatiotemporal degrees of freedom of waves in random media</article-title><source>Phys. Rev. Lett.</source><year>2009</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>173902</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19905758</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR43" publication-type="journal">Lemoult, F., Lerosey, G., de Rosny, J. &#x00026; Fink, M. Manipulating spatiotemporal degrees of freedom of waves in random media. <italic>Phys. Rev. Lett.</italic><bold>103</bold>, 173902 (2009).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19905758</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Goodman <italic>Speckle Phenomena in Optics: Theory and Applications</italic> (SPIE, 2020).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR45" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sorrentini</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zerrad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Amra</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Statistical signatures of random media and their correlation to polarization properties</article-title><source>Opt. Lett.</source><year>2009</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>2429</fpage><lpage>2431</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19684805</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR45" publication-type="journal">Sorrentini, J., Zerrad, M. &#x00026; Amra, C. Statistical signatures of random media and their correlation to polarization properties. <italic>Opt. Lett.</italic><bold>34</bold>, 2429&#x02013;2431 (2009).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19684805</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR46" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peccianti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Exact reconstruction of THz sub-&#x003bb;source features in knife-edge measurements</article-title><source>IEEE J. Sel. Top. Quantum Electron.</source><year>2013</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>8401211</fpage><lpage>8401211</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR46" publication-type="journal">Peccianti, M. et al. Exact reconstruction of THz sub-&#x003bb;source features in knife-edge measurements. <italic>IEEE J. Sel. Top. Quantum Electron.</italic><bold>19</bold>, 8401211&#x02013;8401211 (2013).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Phing, S. H. et al. Sub-wavelength Terahertz beam profiling of a THz source via an all-optical knife-edge technique. <italic>Sci. Rep.</italic><bold>5</bold>, (2015).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR48" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rontsis</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Goulart</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakatsukasa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An active-set algorithm for norm constrained quadratic problems</article-title><source>Math. Program.</source><year>2022</year><volume>193</volume><fpage>447</fpage><lpage>483</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR48" publication-type="journal">Rontsis, N., Goulart, P. J. &#x00026; Nakatsukasa, Y. An active-set algorithm for norm constrained quadratic problems. <italic>Math. Program.</italic><bold>193</bold>, 447&#x02013;483 (2022).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR49" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Novotny</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>van Hulst</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antennas for light</article-title><source>Nat. Photonics</source><year>2011</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>83</fpage><lpage>90</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR49" publication-type="journal">Novotny, L. &#x00026; van Hulst, N. Antennas for light. <italic>Nat. Photonics</italic>. <bold>5</bold>, 83&#x02013;90 (2011).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR50" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blanchard</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Real-time terahertz near-field microscope</article-title><source>Opt. Express</source><year>2011</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>8277</fpage><lpage>8284</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21643077</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR50" publication-type="journal">Blanchard, F. et al. Real-time terahertz near-field microscope. <italic>Opt. Express</italic>. <bold>19</bold>, 8277&#x02013;8284 (2011).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21643077</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR51" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Blanchard</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improving spatial resolution of real-time terahertz near-field microscope</article-title><source>J. Infrared Millim. Terahertz Waves</source><year>2011</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>1043</fpage><lpage>1051</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR51" publication-type="journal">Doi, A., Blanchard, F., Tanaka, T. &#x00026; Tanaka, K. Improving spatial resolution of real-time terahertz near-field microscope. <italic>J. Infrared Millim. Terahertz Waves</italic>. <bold>32</bold>, 1043&#x02013;1051 (2011).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article>