<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="issn">2168-8184</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cureus</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2168-8184</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cureus</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Palo Alto (CA)</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12103100</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7759/cureus.82903</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Genetics</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Pediatrics</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Identification of ARV1 Gene Mutations in Three Pediatric Cases of Developmental and Epileptic Encephalopathy</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Muacevic</surname><given-names>Alexander</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>John R</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Buhusayen</surname><given-names>Feras A. Majeed</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Alashraaf</surname><given-names>Mohamed</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jadah</surname><given-names>Raafat Hamad Seroor H</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff-1">
<label>1</label>
General Surgery, Bahrain Defence Force Hospital, Royal Medical Services, Riffa, BHR </aff><aff id="aff-2">
<label>2</label>
General Surgery, King Hamad University Hospital, Royal Medical Services, Riffa, BHR </aff><aff id="aff-3">
<label>3</label>
Pediatric Neurology, Bahrain Defence Force Hospital, Royal Medical Services, Riffa, BHR </aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">
Feras A. Majeed Buhusayen <email>fbuhusayen@gmail.com</email>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>24</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic"><month>4</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>17</volume><issue>4</issue><elocation-id>e82903</elocation-id><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2025, Buhusayen et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Buhusayen et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License CC-BY 4.0., which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="https://www.cureus.com/articles/347212-identification-of-arv1-gene-mutations-in-three-pediatric-cases-of-developmental-and-epileptic-encephalopathy">This article is available from https://www.cureus.com/articles/347212-identification-of-arv1-gene-mutations-in-three-pediatric-cases-of-developmental-and-epileptic-encephalopathy</self-uri><abstract><p>The ARV1 gene produces a protein made up of 271 amino acids that helps transport fats across membranes within the cell&#x02019;s endoplasmic reticulum (ER), a key area involved in processing lipids. This protein is related to an enzyme called ACAT2, which is important for managing cholesterol and fat levels in the body. This protein features an N-terminal zinc-binding motif located in the cytosol, followed by multiple domains that span the ER membrane, and concludes with a C-terminus that terminates in the ER lumen. ARV1 deficiency clinically manifests as autosomal recessive developmental and epileptic encephalopathy 38 (DEE38) in humans.&#x000a0;</p><p>In this report, we share three pediatric cases presenting with early-onset epileptic encephalopathy and significant developmental delay. Whole-exome sequencing (WES) identified two pathogenic ARV1 variants: p.Cys61Tyr (missense) and p.Phe144Argfs5* (frameshift), both predicted to severely disrupt protein structure and function. These findings add to what we know about how mutations in the ARV1 gene can lead to developmental and epileptic encephalopathy (DEE38), and they strengthen our understanding of the gene&#x02019;s role in brain development. The children in our report also show how widely the symptoms of ARV1-related conditions can vary from case to case. Their experiences highlight just how important early genetic testing can be, especially for young patients with unexplained seizures and developmental challenges. Our report contributes to understanding the spectrum of complex neurological conditions. By sharing these cases, we&#x02019;re adding to the growing knowledge about ARV1-related encephalopathies and reinforcing why this gene deserves a place in targeted epilepsy genetic panels.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>arv1 gene mutation</kwd><kwd>developmental and epileptic encephalopathy (dee38)</kwd><kwd>infantile seizure onset</kwd><kwd>neurodevelopmental disorder</kwd><kwd>whole-exome sequencing (wes)</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>The ARV1 gene produces a protein made up of 271 amino acids that helps transport fats across membranes within the cell's endoplasmic reticulum (ER), a key area involved in processing lipids. This protein is related to an enzyme called ACAT2, which is important for managing cholesterol and fat levels in the body [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. This protein features an N-terminal zinc-binding motif located in the cytosol, followed by multiple domains that span the ER membrane, and concludes with a C-terminus that terminates in the ER lumen [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. The ARV1 gene plays a significant role in maintaining homeostasis of cellular lipids by regulating the distribution and levels of various lipids, including cholesterol and glycosylphosphatidylinositol (GPI) anchors. It is involved in the synthesis and proper localization of these lipids, ensuring their availability for vital cellular processes. Additionally, ARV1 is connected to the ER-associated degradation (ERAD) pathway, which recognizes and breaks down misfolded proteins to provide protein quality control [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Dysfunction or mutations in the ARV1 gene can lead to severe metabolic disorders and have been linked to conditions such as congenital disorders of glycosylation and epilepsy [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Through its multifaceted roles, ARV1 contributes significantly to the proper functioning of cellular membranes and overall cell health.</p><p>To date, there have been approximately 20 reported cases of ARV1 gene mutations in the literature [<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. ARV1 deficiency clinically manifests as autosomal recessive developmental and epileptic encephalopathy 38 (DEE38) in humans [<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. In the literature, a number of variant mutations in the ARV1 gene have been identified, though they are relatively limited. Patients with ARV1 gene mutation present with several clinical manifestations including developmental milestone delay, intellectual disability, epileptic encephalopathy of infantile onset, hypotonia, ataxia, ophthalmological manifestations (visual impairment, retinal dystrophy), hearing loss, skeletal dysplasia, and dilated cardiomyopathy [<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>-<xref rid="REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. In this detailed case report, we present three distinct cases of pediatric patients diagnosed with epileptic encephalopathy and developmental delay.</p></sec><sec sec-type="cases"><title>Case presentation</title><p>Case 1</p><p>A four-month-old girl from a consanguineous marriage presented to our hospital with multiple episodes of convulsions in the form of generalized body stiffness associated with loss of consciousness, eye up-rolling, and peri-oral cyanosis lasting for two minutes, followed by post-ictal drowsiness. There was no history of fever or vomiting. Her&#x000a0;prenatal history was unremarkable, with a negative family history of seizure disorder.</p><p>Her initial vital signs were normal. Neurological assessment showed global developmental delay in the form of poor head control and inability to roll over the bed. She had poor social communication as she was not cooing/babbling and did not show any social smile. Muscle tone and power, deep tendon reflexes, and cranial nerves examination were within normal limits with no cerebellar signs. There were no dysmorphic facial features or neurocutaneous skin lesions. The rest of the physical examination was unremarkable.</p><p>Upon admission, the patient had frequent seizure episodes that were treated with multiple antiepileptic medications, including diazepam, phenobarbital, levetiracetam, vigabatrin, topiramate, lacosamide, and carbamazepine. Her&#x000a0;initial brain computed tomography (CT) scan and magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) were unremarkable (Figure <xref rid="FIG1" ref-type="fig">1A</xref>). EEG showed modified hypsarrhythmia along with right temporal electrographic seizure activity. The tandem mass spectrometry (TMS) screening showed no indication of conditions associated with amino acid, organic acid, or fatty acid disorders. Additionally, whole-exome sequencing found a homozygous variant of unknown significance in the ARV1 gene (p.Cys61Tyr).</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Brain MRI of the three reported ARV1 cases. (A) Unremarkable axial T2-weighted brain MRI. (B) T2-weighted fat-stranding brain MRI showed slightly enlarged bifrontal subarachnoid spaces (arrow). (C) Unremarkable axial FLAIR-weighted brain MRI.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0017-00000082903-i01" position="float"/></fig><p>The patient's condition was complicated by episodes of fever and subsequent development of pneumonia, sepsis, acute liver failure, and stage III hepatic encephalopathy. The lab (Table <xref rid="TAB1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) and ultrasound findings indicate a critically ill pediatric patient with multiple organ dysfunction. The complete blood count (CBC) reveals leukocytosis with white blood cells (WBC) of 19 &#x000d7; 10&#x02079;/L (reference range: 5-16 &#x000d7; 10&#x02079;/L) as well as anemia with hemoglobin (Hb) at 11 g/dL (reference range: 10-14 g/dL). The lactate dehydrogenase (LDH) levels were significantly elevated, rising from 2830 U/L to 9865 U/L (reference range: 140-280 U/L) with deranged coagulation profiles consistent with disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC). Liver function tests (LFTs) demonstrate severely elevated alanine transaminase (ALT) and aspartate transaminase (AST) levels, with total bilirubin rising from 40 umol/l&#x000a0;to 60 umol/l (reference range: 0-17 umol/l) and direct bilirubin from 31 umol/l to 47 umol/l (reference range: 0-3.4 umol/l), indicating acute liver injury and cholestasis. Electrolyte levels are mostly within normal limits. Ammonia levels have dramatically increased from 69 to 259 &#x003bc;mol/L (reference range: &#x0003c;50 &#x003bc;mol/L), indicating severe hepatic encephalopathy. Urine and blood cultures were negative. Ultrasound findings revealed signs of hepatitis and significant ascites. These findings are consistent with acute liver failure, with severe coagulopathy and hepatic encephalopathy, requiring immediate and comprehensive medical intervention. Despite extensive management of the patient with broad-spectrum antibiotics, multiple doses of vitamin K, and fresh frozen plasma, the patient&#x02019;s condition continued to deteriorate the patient eventually expired.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Laboratory results for ARV1 cases.</title><p>WBC: white blood cell; LDH:&#x000a0;lactate dehydrogenase; ALT:&#x000a0;alanine transaminase; AST:&#x000a0;aspartate transaminase</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lab Parameter</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal Range</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case 3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">WBC count (&#x000d7;10&#x02079;/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 &#x02013; 16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not mentioned</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not mentioned</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hemoglobin (g/dL)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 &#x02013; 14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not mentioned</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not mentioned</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LDH (U/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">140 &#x02013; 280</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2830 &#x02192; 9865&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not mentioned</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not mentioned</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALT / AST (U/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALT: &#x0003c;40 / AST: &#x0003c;40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severely elevated (no exact values)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not mentioned</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not mentioned</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total bilirubin (&#x000b5;mol/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 &#x02013; 17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 &#x02192; 60&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not mentioned</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not mentioned</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Direct bilirubin (&#x000b5;mol/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 &#x02013; 3.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 &#x02192; 47</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not mentioned</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not mentioned</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ammonia (&#x000b5;mol/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69 &#x02192; 259&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not mentioned</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not mentioned</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urine/blood cultures</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not mentioned</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not mentioned</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TMS screening</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urine organic acids</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not mentioned</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not mentioned</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genetic test (ARV1 gene)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homozygous VUS (p.Cys61Tyr)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homozygous pathogenic (p.Phe144Argfs*5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homozygous VUS (p.Cys61Tyr)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Case 2</p><p>A female child aged six months and 25 days presented for investigation for global developmental delay. The manifestation started at the age of three months when the mother noticed that her baby did not fixate or follow with an upward gaze, did not support her head, and was floppy without any history of abnormal movement, as well as seizure-like activity, choking, or feeding difficulties. The baby was born from a consanguineous marriage and had a four-year-old healthy brother. No family history of epilepsy or special needs child. The baby had a history of hospital admission at the age of four months due to bronchiolitis. The baby was up-to-date on her vaccinations and was on formula feeds and soft, solid food. She was born at 37 weeks with a birth weight of 3 kg without any history of perinatal complications or neonatal intensive care unit (NICU) admission.</p><p>The baby&#x02019;s developmental milestones showed the following: poor head control, does not sit with support, does not roll over from supine to prone position, can grasp/hold objects briefly, does not transfer, and can coo but does not babble.</p><p>Physical exam showed an active child, an anterior fontanelle at level, normal power and tone, normal reflexes, upward gazing, does not fix or follow, head lag on pulling, horizontal and vertical nystagmus with facial dysmorphic features in the form of macrocephaly, short neck, and low-set ears. The rest of the systemic examination was unremarkable.</p><p>The patient also developed generalized tonic-clonic seizures of both upper and lower limbs associated with drooling, upward deviation of eyes, with loss of consciousness, which lasted for forty minutes, which was managed by diazepam and phenytoin, and then kept on maintenance keppra. Brain MRI showed slightly enlarged bifrontal subarachnoid spaces with an abnormal finding noticed in the right parietal lobe (Figure <xref rid="FIG1" ref-type="fig">1B</xref>). The tandem mass spectrometry (TMS) screening showed no indication of conditions associated with amino acid, organic acid, or fatty acid disorders.</p><p>The whole-exome sequencing revealed a homozygous pathogenic variant in the ARV1 gene (p.Phe144Argfs*5). The genetic diagnosis of autosomal recessive developmental and epileptic encephalopathy-38 was confirmed. The patient remained stable in the hospital with no further attacks and seizures, was discharged home in good condition with arrangements for genetic counselling to the parents.</p><p>Case 3</p><p>A three-month-old girl, born at 35 weeks of gestation, a known case of gastroesophageal reflux disease (GERD) on anti-regurgitation (AR) formula and domperidone (1mg QID), presented to the emergency department with a history of abnormal movement that started one day before admission. These abnormal movements occurred three times the day before admission and twice on the day of admission. The episodes were described as up-rolling of the eyes with lip smacking or shivering. Episodes were followed by drowsiness and a post-ictal phase. No history of cyanosis, stiffness, convulsions, loss of consciousness, fever, cough, or shortness of breath. The baby was feeding well with no vomiting. The mother reported a history of colic and passing motion every two days with straining. The baby&#x02019;s developmental history included head lag and poor head control, not yet smiling, with a startle response present. The patient was born through cesarean delivery with a history of NICU admission due to respiratory distress syndrome (RDS). The birth weight was 2.470 Kg and the weight at admission was 3.9 (below 3rd centile). Family history was significant for epilepsy in a 19-year-old cousin.</p><p>The patient's vitals were stable. She looked well, pink, active, not in distress, and was well-hydrated with a capillary refill time of less than 2 seconds. Dysmorphic features were noticed and included a low hairline, micrognathia, hypertelorism, and a depressed nasal bridge. The rest of the systemic examination was unremarkable. Neurological exam revealed head lag, truncal hypotonia, brisk reflexes of +3 with no clonus, intact cranial nerve examination, normal anterior fontanelle, and positive Moro reflex.</p><p>Brain MRI was unremarkable (Figure <xref rid="FIG1" ref-type="fig">1C</xref>). Ophthalmology evaluation revealed normal fundoscopic examination, however, EEG showed the presence of multifocal epileptiform spike and wave discharges (Figure <xref rid="FIG2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Urine organic acid screening was performed and showed no indication of organic disease. The tandem mass spectrometry (TMS) screening showed no indication of conditions associated with amino acid, organic acid, or fatty acid disorders. In addition, whole-exome sequencing found a homozygous variant of unknown significance in the ARV1 gene (p.Cys61Tyr).</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Brain EEG showed a presence of multi-focal epileptiform spike and wave discharges.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0017-00000082903-i02" position="float"/></fig><p>The patient also developed an episode of seizure activity in the form of eye blinking with lip smacking, followed by a post-ictal phase. Seizures were controlled by levetiracetam. As a result, the patient was discharged on levetiracetam with follow-ups in the clinic for genetic study. The patient was admitted multiple times due to seizure breakthrough with presumed sepsis due to gastroenteritis or pneumonia. The latest discharge medications included diazepam, topiramate, levetiracetam, and phenytoin as antiepileptic medications, with genetic counselling for the parents.</p><p>The following table summarizes the three reported cases (Table <xref rid="TAB2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Summary of significant findings in the described cases.</title><p>EEG: electroencephalogram; CT: computed tomography; MRI: magnetic resonance imaging; TMS: transcranial magnetic stimulation.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aspect</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case 3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age of onset</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 years 11 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 months</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Consanguineous marriage</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Present</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Present</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Present</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Symptoms</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recurrent seizures, developmental delay, and dysmorphic features</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Significant global developmental delay, dysmorphic features, and seizure</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Seizure, developmental delay, and dysmorphic features</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Key diagnostics</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal EEG, brain CT/MRI normal, TMS screening negative.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal EEG, MRI with parietal abnormality, TMS screening negative.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multi-focal epileptiform discharges on EEG, brain MRI, slightly enlarged bifrontal subarachnoid spaces with abnormal findings noticed in the right parietal lobe, TMS screening negative.</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genetic findings</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARV1 mutation (p.Cys61Tyr).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARV1 mutation (p.Phe144Argfs*5), confirmed DEE-38.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARV1 mutation (p.Cys61Tyr).</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outcome</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Death</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alive</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alive</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>The ARV1 gene plays a critical role in lipid metabolism, thus maintaining cellular homeostasis [<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. ARV1 is essential for the regulation and distribution of sterols and sphingolipids within the cell, which are responsible for cell membrane integrity and function [<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Additionally, ARV1 is involved in the synthesis of glycosylphosphatidylinositol (GPI) anchors, which function as attaching proteins to cell membranes [<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Therefore, dysfunctions in ARV1 can lead to membrane disorganization, hypersensitivity to fatty acids, and endoplasmic reticulum stress. Impairment in sphingolipid metabolism has been identified to be involved in many neurodegenerative diseases, such as Niemann-Pick disease [<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. ARV1 gene mutation in humans and its association with neurological diseases was first described in 2015 by Alazami et al. after conducting whole-exome sequencing on 143 multiplex families with a diagnosis of neurogenetic disease, born from consanguineous marriage with positive family history [<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].&#x000a0;</p><p>This case series discusses three cases of infants from consanguineous marriages who exhibited recurrent breakthrough seizures, severe developmental delay, and dysmorphological features. These infants were found to possess ARV1 gene mutations through whole-exome sequencing, a known genetic cause of developmental and epileptic encephalopathy.</p><p>The first ARV1 gene variant mutation that was identified in two of our patients was p.Cys61Tyr. This variant mutation is an amino acid change from cysteine to tyrosine at position 61. This variant mutation had been identified by Salian et al. in an 11-year-old male who presented at the age of 6 months with developmental delay, profound intellectual disability, and seizure with a history of nephrocalcinosis [<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. The patient had a normal prenatal and neonatal history without any history of congenital microcephaly, feeding difficulties, or failure to thrive. Additionally, no facial dysmorphic features were observed. Ophthalmology evaluation revealed abnormal vision and strabismus. Finally, skeletal examination and survey identified kyphosis, pectus excavatum, and hip subluxation. In the present study, two patients were identified to have p.Cys61Tyr variant mutation. Both patients presented with developmental delay, dysmorphic features, and seizures.</p><p>The second ARV1 gene mutation that was identified was p.Phe144Argfs*5. This variant mutation involves a frameshift alteration starting at phenylalanine (Phe) at position 144, resulting in a change in the reading frame and the introduction of a premature stop codon five amino acids. To the best of our knowledge, this variant has not been previously documented in the literature. It has been classified as pathogenic according to the implementation of the ACMG/AMP/ClinGen SVI guidelines by CENTOGENE.</p><p>Palmer et al/ identified a variant AVR1 mutation referred to as p.(Lys59_Asn98del) in a 4-month-old female patient who presented with intractable seizure [<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. This mutation indicated that there was a loss of amino acids from lysine at position 59 to asparagine at position 98. Furthermore, this mutation was evaluated for protein expression and function by adding the mutated AVR1 gene in yeast lacking the ARV1 gene. This variant did not restore the yeast's ability to grow at high ("restrictive") temperatures, suggesting that this deletion severely impairs the function of the ARV1 protein. Davids et al. described homozygous splice-variant ARV1 gene mutations in seven patients who presented with seizure of infantile onset, profound developmental delays, substantial hypotonia, speech delay, visual impairment, and severe generalized brain atrophy [<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Using immunofluorescence microscopy and the fluorescence-activated cell sorting (FACS) analysis, the effect of these variant mutations on the expression of GPI-anchored proteins was analyzed and demonstrated reduced expression of these proteins at the surface of fibroblasts and neutrophils [<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Segel et al. concluded that the p.Gly189Arg mutation in the ARV1 gene is associated with a defect in GPI anchoring function, which consequently results in infantile epileptic encephalopathy in two brothers [<xref rid="REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Interestingly, the two brothers were reported to have cardiac involvement presented as dilated cardiomyopathy. Cardiac involvement in patients with ARV1 gene mutations was additionally documented in two recent studies [<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].</p><p>Salian et al. reported five novel mutation variants in the ARV1 gene in a cohort of seven patients with developmental delay, refractory seizures of early onset, hypotonia, with specific features on neuroimaging [<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. The variant mutations identified were as follows: p.(Ser122Glnfs7) in one patient, a compound heterozygous mutation of p.(Pro174Alafs14) and p.(Cys34Tyr) in another patient, p.(Cys61Tyr) in a different patient, c.674-1G &#x0003e; A in two patients, and p.(Pro174Alafs*14) in yet another patient [<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. They also noted that patients with ARV1 mutations exhibit a range of clinical manifestations other than the typically observed severe epileptic encephalopathy. These include variable skeletal abnormalities, genitourinary issues, nephrocalcinosis, uterine and renal congenital anomalies, and abnormal cardiac morphology [<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].</p><p>Darra et al. described two sisters from a non-consanguineous marriage who presented with dyskinetic movements, visual inattention, hypotonia, and profound developmental delay accompanied by abnormally slow EEG activity. These symptoms were associated with compound heterozygous AVR1 gene mutations, specifically <ext-link xlink:href="https://p.Se" ext-link-type="uri">p.Se</ext-link>r122Glnfs*7 and the p.Trp163* variants [<xref rid="REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. The most recent AVR1 gene mutation (p.L185del) was identified by Karabinos et al. in an adult male patient who presented with intellectual disability, developmental delay, intractable seizures, difficulties in speech and movement, and dilated cardiomyopathy [<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>In this study, we presented three cases demonstrating the significant and varied impact of ARV1 gene mutations on pediatric patients. Profound developmental delays, intractable seizures, and dysmorphic features were the presenting symptoms in all cases. Identification of the ARV1 mutation in all of the cases suggests the critical role of this gene in neurological development and function. Therefore, this case series contributes to further understanding of AVR1-associated neurological disorders and highlights the importance of genetic testing in the diagnosis and management of similar conditions. Looking forward, future researchers into ARV1 may uncover its further roles in neurodevelopment, guide the development of targeted diagnostic tools, and potentially open new plans for therapeutic interventions aimed at modifying disease progression in affected individuals.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group content-type="conflict"><title>Disclosures</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Human subjects:</bold> Consent for treatment and open access publication was obtained or waived by all participants in this study.</p><p><bold>Conflicts of interest:</bold> In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following:</p><p><bold>Payment/services info:</bold> All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work.</p><p><bold>Financial relationships:</bold> All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work.</p><p><bold>Other relationships:</bold> All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="other"><title>Author Contributions</title><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Concept and design:</bold>&#x000a0; Feras A. Majeed Buhusayen , Raafat Hamad Seroor H. Jadah</p><p><bold>Drafting of the manuscript:</bold>&#x000a0; Feras A. Majeed Buhusayen </p><p><bold>Critical review of the manuscript for important intellectual content:</bold>&#x000a0; Raafat Hamad Seroor H. Jadah, Mohamed Alashraaf</p><p><bold>Supervision:</bold>&#x000a0; Raafat Hamad Seroor H. Jadah</p><p><bold>Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data:</bold>&#x000a0; Mohamed Alashraaf</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="REF1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Deletion of murine Arv1 results in a lean phenotype with increased energy expenditure</article-title><source>Nutr Diabetes</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Lagor</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jarrett</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>0</fpage><volume>5</volume><year>2015</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Mutations in yeast ARV1 alter intracellular sterol distribution and are complemented by human ARV1</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Tinkelenberg</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alcantara</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sturley</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>40667</fpage><lpage>40670</lpage><volume>275</volume><year>2000</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11063737</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>ARV1 gene: A novel cause of autosomal recessive cerebellar ataxia with elevated alpha fetoprotein</article-title><source>Cerebellum</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Kamate</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Basavanagowda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>1239</fpage><lpage>1244</lpage><volume>23</volume><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37749428</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Neuronal deficiency of ARV1 causes an autosomal recessive epileptic encephalopathy</article-title><source>Hum Mol Genet</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jarrett</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sachdev</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>3042</fpage><lpage>3054</lpage><volume>25</volume><year>2016</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27270415</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Accelerating novel candidate gene discovery in neurogenetic disorders via whole-exome sequencing of prescreened multiplex consanguineous families</article-title><source>Cell Rep</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Alazami</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shamseldin</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>148</fpage><lpage>161</lpage><volume>10</volume><year>2015</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25558065</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Homozygous splice-variants in human ARV1 cause GPI-anchor synthesis deficiency</article-title><source>Mol Genet Metab</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Davids</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Menezes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>57</lpage><volume>130</volume><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32165008</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>A defect in GPI synthesis as a suggested mechanism for the role of ARV1 in intellectual disability and seizures</article-title><source>Neurogenetics</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Segel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aran</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gulsuner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>259</fpage><lpage>267</lpage><volume>21</volume><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32462292</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Migrating focal seizures and myoclonic status in ARV1-related encephalopathy</article-title><source>Neurol Genet</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Darra</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lo Barco</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Opri</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>0</fpage><volume>7</volume><year>2021</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Epileptic encephalopathy caused by ARV1 deficiency: Refinement of the genotype-phenotype spectrum and functional impact on GPI-anchored proteins</article-title><source>Clin Genet</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Salian</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Scala</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>607</fpage><lpage>614</lpage><volume>100</volume><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34296759</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Dilated cardiomyopathy is a part of the ARV1-associated phenotype: a case report</article-title><source>J Med Case Rep</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Karabinos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hyblova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eckertova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>98</fpage><volume>16</volume><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35227294</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>