<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="case-report" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">JACC Case Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">JACC Case Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>JACC Case Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2666-0849</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39972685</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11861944</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2666-0849(24)00470-4</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaccas.2024.102563</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">102563</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Congenital Heart Disease</subject><subj-group><subject>Clinical Case</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Rare Case of Valve-Sparing Root Reimplantation in a Patient With an Anomalous Circumflex Artery</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name><surname>Lorenz</surname><given-names>Veronica</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><email>veronica.lorenz@saintluc.uclouvain.be</email><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#x02217;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name><surname>Jahanyar</surname><given-names>Jama</given-names></name><degrees>MD, PhD</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name><surname>El Khoury</surname><given-names>Gebrine</given-names></name><degrees>MD, PhD</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4"><name><surname>De Kerchove</surname><given-names>Laurent</given-names></name><degrees>MD, PhD</degrees></contrib><aff id="aff1">Cardiovascular and Thoracic Department, University Hospital Saint-Luc, Brussels, Belgium</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x02217;</label><bold>Address for correspondence:</bold> Dr Veronica Lorenz, Department of Cardiothoracic and Vascular Surgery, Cliniques Universitaires Saint-Luc, Avenue Hippocrate 10, 1200 Bruxelles, Belgium. <email>veronica.lorenz@saintluc.uclouvain.be</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>27</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>19</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>30</volume><issue>4</issue><elocation-id>102563</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>13</day><month>5</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>2</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>12</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2025 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="abs0010"><p>We present a case of valve-sparing root reimplantation in a patient with severe aortic regurgitation, in the setting of a bicuspid aortic valve with an aberrant circumflex coronary artery arising from the right coronary artery, thus rendering standard dissection of the aortic root during a David procedure challenging and risky.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="graphical" id="abs0015"><title>Graphical Abstract</title><fig id="undfig1" position="anchor"><graphic xlink:href="ga1"/></fig></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Key Words</title><kwd>aberrant coronary artery</kwd><kwd>anomalous left circumflex</kwd><kwd>bicuspid aortic valve</kwd><kwd>valve sparing</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta><def-list><title>Abbreviations and Acronyms</title><def-item><term id="kwrd0035">ACA</term><def><p>aberrant circumflex artery</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="kwrd0045">AR</term><def><p>aortic regurgitation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="kwrd0055">BAV</term><def><p>bicuspid aortic valve</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="kwrd0065">CT</term><def><p>computed tomography</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="kwrd0075">LV</term><def><p>left ventricular</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="kwrd0085">LVEF</term><def><p>left ventricular ejection fraction</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="kwrd0095">VSRR</term><def><p>valve-sparing root replacement</p></def></def-item></def-list></front><body><sec id="sec1"><title>History of Present Illness</title><p id="p0010">The patient was a 30-year-old man, referred to our institution (University Hospital Saint-Luc, Brussels, Belgium) for a severely regurgitant bicuspid aortic valve (BAV). He was asymptomatic and had been followed up by the referring cardiologist for many years for an aortic murmur. Preoperative physical examination demonstrated normal vital signs and an early diastolic decrescendo murmur, best heard at Erb&#x02019;s point.<boxed-text id="dtbox1"><sec id="dtbox1sec1"><title>Take-Home Messages</title><p id="p0015"><list list-type="simple" id="ulist0010"><list-item id="u0010"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0020">BAVs can be associated with anomalous coronary arteries.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0015"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0025">Patients with BAVs are potential candidates for aortic valve repair, and appropriate preoperative imaging is important to demonstrate the relationship between the aortic root and the aberrant coronary artery.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0020"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0030">Mobilization of the ACA from the aortic annulus is key to performing a safe aortic valve or root procedure.</p></list-item></list></p></sec></boxed-text></p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>Past Medical History</title><p id="p0035">The patient had otherwise no significant past medical or surgical history and was in his usual state of health.</p></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>Differential Diagnosis</title><p id="p0040">The differential diagnosis of diastolic heart murmur includes early diastolic aortic regurgitation (AR), pulmonary regurgitation; mid- to late diastolic mitral stenosis, and Austin Flint murmur.</p></sec><sec id="sec4"><title>Investigations</title><p id="p0045">Transthoracic echocardiography showed a severely dilated left ventricle (end-diastolic diameter, 69&#x000a0;mm; end-systolic diameter, 47&#x000a0;mm) with mildly depressed left ventricular (LV) function (ejection fraction [EF]: 50%). Moreover, the aortic valve phenotype was a De Kerchove type A BAV<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;1</xref>), with left-right cusp fusion and a typical fused cusp prolapse with a posteriorly directed eccentric jet (regurgitant volume, 63&#x000a0;mL; EROA, 30&#x000a0;mm<sup>2</sup>) (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figures&#x000a0;2A</xref> and <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2B</xref>). The root was dilated at 42&#x000a0;mm (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figures&#x000a0;3A</xref> and <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3B</xref>, <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Video 1</xref>). The transesophageal echocardiogram indicated an anomalous path of a coronary artery (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;4</xref>), thus prompting a computed tomography (CT) angiogram. This imaging identified the presence of an aberrant circumflex artery (ACA), originating from the right coronary sinus and passing laterally along the noncoronary sinus and behind the aortic root (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;5</xref>).<fig id="fig1"><label>Figure&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Midesophageal Aortic Valve Short-Axis View</p><p>Type A bicuspid aortic valve symmetrical phenotype with a 160&#x000b0; to 180&#x000b0;commissural orientation. The commissural orientation is drawn and measured on a short-axis view and is defined as the angle measured on the nonfused cusp side between 2 lines joining each commissure to the central axis of the valve in diastole. C&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;compensation; G&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;gain; Gen&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;general; P&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;penetration; 2D&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;2-dimensional.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig><fig id="fig2"><label>Figure&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Transesophageal Echocardiography</p><p>(A) Midesophageal long-axis view and (B) transgastric view showing severe aortic regurgitation. CF&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;color flow; WF&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;frequency sound waves; other abbreviations as in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;1</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig><fig id="fig3"><label>Figure&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Aortic Root Diameter on Transesophageal Echocardiography</p><p>(A) Midesophageal long-axis view and (B) midesophageal aortic valve short-axis view with a maximum aortic root diameter of 42&#x000a0;mm. Abbreviations as in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;1</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr3"/></fig><fig id="fig4"><label>Figure&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Midesophageal Long-Axis View</p><p>The aberrant circumflex coronary artery at the level of the aortic annulus is visible (arrow). Echo&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;echocardiogram; other abbreviations as in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;1</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr4"/></fig><fig id="fig5"><label>Figure&#x000a0;5</label><caption><p>Computed Tomography of the ACA</p><p>Computed tomography showing the pathway of the ACA (A, B) originating from the right coronary sinus and passing laterally along the non-coronary sinus. (C) The origin of the ACA is alongside the ostium of the right coronary artery (red arrow). (D) 3 D reconstruction of the pathway of the aberrant circumflex artery (blue arrow). ACA&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;aberrant circumflex artery (blue arrow) arising from the right coronary ostium; LAD&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;left anterior descending coronary artery; RCA&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;right coronary artery (red arrows).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr5"/></fig></p><p id="p0050">A multidisciplinary heart team discussion determined the patient to be a suitable candidate for a valve-sparing root replacement (VSRR) despite the anomalous coronary artery.</p></sec><sec id="sec5"><title>Surgical Management</title><p id="p0055">After a full sternotomy and initiation of cardiopulmonary bypass, the aorta was cross-clamped, and antegrade intermittent warm blood cardioplegia was delivered directly into the 3 ostia (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Video 1</xref>). In fact, at the level of the proximal right coronary artery we found a short main trunk, and the circumflex artery originated at the side of the right coronary artery with a separate ostium. Valve analysis confirmed a BAV with a raphe between the left and right leaflets and a symmetrical phenotype.</p><p id="p0060">The aortic root was carefully dissected,<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> and the ACA was dissected free in its entire proximal course. It was thus mobilized off the aortic root: from its origin, in close proximity to the commissure between the right coronary cusp and the noncoronary cusp, to the posterior aspect of the noncoronary and left coronary sinus, overlying the left atrial dome, to allow for safe suture placement later (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;6</xref>). We ended the dissection at the level of roof of the left atrium, where the artery passes into the sinus oblique and takes its natural course for perfusion of the lateral wall.<fig id="fig6"><label>Figure&#x000a0;6</label><caption><p>Aberrant Circumflex Artery Mobilized</p><p>Mobilization and dissection of the aberrant circumflex artery along its entire course before the reimplantation of the valve.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr6"/></fig></p><p id="p0065">The aortic repair performed was a reimplantation technique specifically for BAVs with a 28-mm Valsalva Cardioroot prosthesis (Getinge), which has previously been described in detail.<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> The fused cusp prolapse was treated with a central plication suture of the fused cusp.</p><p id="p0070">Following completion of valve repair and reimplantation, we verified that the circumflex artery was free and did not become kinked during suture placement (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;7</xref>).<fig id="fig7"><label>Figure&#x000a0;7</label><caption><p>Aberrant Circumflex Artery Mobilized After Valve-Sparing Root Replacement</p><p>Mobilization and dissection of the aberrant circumflex artery along its entire course at the end of the reimplantation of the valve into the Valsalva graft.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr7"/></fig></p><p id="p0075">The left coronary button was then reimplanted in the anatomic position in the left neo-sinus of the graft. The right coronary button with the right and circumflex ostia was then reimplanted into the neo-right sinus (<xref rid="mmc2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Video 2</xref>).</p><p id="p0080">At the end of the procedure, intraoperative echocardiography showed a symmetrical BAV with no regurgitation and good cusp mobility with a peak gradient of 10&#x000a0;mm&#x000a0;Hg (<xref rid="mmc3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Video 3</xref>) and preserved lateral wall motion.</p><p id="p0085">The patient was extubated on day 0, had an uneventful postoperative course, and was discharged home on postoperative day&#x000a0;5.</p></sec><sec id="sec6"><title>Follow-Up</title><p id="p0090">Follow-up echocardiography at 1&#x000a0;month showed no AR with a peak transvalvular gradient of 7&#x000a0;mm&#x000a0;Hg, no lateral wall motion abnormalities, and improvement in LV function (LV ejection fraction [LVEF], 45%-50%) (<xref rid="mmc4" ref-type="supplementary-material">Video 4</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec7"><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0095">BAVs represent the most common congenital cardiac malformations,<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> often manifesting with AR, and can be associated with coronary anomalies such as higher ostial locations, a short left main trunk, or left coronary arterial dominance.<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref></p><p id="p0100">This particular coronary anomaly in itself is typically asymptomatic. Symptoms and the risk of sudden death are more prevalent when the origin of a right coronary artery arises from the left sinus with an associated intramural and/or interarterial course.</p><p id="p0105">The location of an ACA runs typically at the level of the noncoronary sinus annulus with posterior orientation and thus within the dissection plane for a VSRR, a location that renders an abnormal coronary artery at high risk for injury during aortic surgery.<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref></p><p id="p0110">In the current literature there are very few reports of concomitant BAVs and ACAs.<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> To our knowledge, this is the first case&#x000a0;of a surgical repair of this entity with VSRR and valve repair. Preoperative work-up including cardiac CT angiography helps to identify coronary anomalies and anticipate potential intraoperative risks. Abnormal coronary arteries either can be reimplanted in a more physiologic location, when performing an aortic root replacement, or can be ligated and bypassed if needed. Reimplantation into a more anatomically correct position, however, can be associated with kinking of the reimplanted artery, as reported by Urbanski et&#x000a0;al,<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref> and should therefore be approached with care. Furthermore, the ACA originates from a common ostium with the right coronary artery, and thus it cannot be reimplanted without compromising 1 of the 2 vessels.<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref> Unroofing is no option here either because there is no intramural course of the aberrant vessel.</p><p id="p0115">According to the 2020 American College of Cardiology/American Heart Association guidelines for valvular heart disease, in asymptomatic patients with severe AR and depressed LV systolic function (LVEF&#x000a0;&#x02264;55%) valvular surgery is indicated (Class 1, Level of Evidence: B); and in patients with BAV, repair can be considered if it is performed at a comprehensive valve center such as ours (Class 2, Level of Evidence: B-C). However, there are no guideline-directed recommendations for BAV and associated coronary anomalies because these occur only rarely.<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref></p><p id="p0120">Skeletonization and full mobilization of the vessel from its origin along its entire course up to the atrioventricular groove are key to reducing the risk of coronary injury related to suture placement or vessel compression related to the prosthetic graft.<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref></p><p id="p0125">Baldonado et&#x000a0;al<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> reported a 16% risk of myocardial ischemia on echocardiography after aortic valve replacement in patients with ACA. The successful management of this case highlights the notion that&#x000a0;even in the presence of an ACA with a severely regurgitant BAV, VSRR and valve repair are feasible.</p><p id="p0130">Our study received the proper ethical oversight.</p></sec><sec id="sec8"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="p0135">VSRR can be safely performed in patients with an ACA. CT angiography or coronary artery angiography is important for surgical planning, even in young patients.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="coi0010"><title>Funding Support and Author Disclosures</title><p id="p0140">The authors have reported that they have no relationships relevant to the contents of this paper to disclose.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jahanyar</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Said</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>P.I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The De Kerchove/El Khoury/Schafers&#x02019; classification:a contemporary repair-oriented categorization of bicuspid aortic valves</article-title><source>Eur J Cardiothorac Surg</source><volume>63</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2023</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ezad174</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jahanyar</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Kerchove</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>El Khoury</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bicuspid aortic valve repair: the 180&#x000b0;-reimplantation technique</article-title><source>Ann Cardiothorac Surg</source><volume>11</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>473</fpage><lpage>481</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35958541</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aphram</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamer</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mastrobuoni</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Valve sparing root replacement: reimplantation of the aortic valve</article-title><source>Ann Cardiothorac Surg</source><volume>8</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>415</fpage><lpage>417</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31240189</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez-Palomares</surname><given-names>J.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dux-Santoy</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guala</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mechanisms of aortic dilation in patients with bicuspid aortic valve: JACC state-of-the-art review</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Am Coll Cardiol</source><volume>82</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2023</year><fpage>448</fpage><lpage>464</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37495282</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>DeFaria Yeh</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coronary artery variants and bicuspid aortic valve disease: gaining insight into genetic underpinnings</article-title><source>Heart</source><volume>104</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>363</fpage><lpage>364</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28954834</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baldonado</surname><given-names>J.J.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Greason</surname><given-names>K.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Crestanello</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Surgical aortic valve replacement in the setting of anomalous circumflex coronary artery</article-title><source>Ann Thorac Surg</source><volume>113</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>563</fpage><lpage>567</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33794154</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liebrich</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tzanavaros</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheid</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Aortic valve/root procedures in patients with an anomalous left circumflex coronary artery and a bicuspid aortic valve: anatomical and technical implications</article-title><source>Interact Cardiovasc Thorac Surg</source><volume>21</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>114</fpage><lpage>116</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25820760</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doty</surname><given-names>D.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anomalous origin of the left circumflex coronary artery associated with bicuspid aortic valve</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</source><volume>122</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2001</year><fpage>842</fpage><lpage>843</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11581633</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Urbanski</surname><given-names>P.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Irimie</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Diegeler</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ascending aorta replacement in patients with coronary ostia localized above the sinotubular junction</article-title><source>Eur J Cardiothorac Surg</source><volume>59</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>758</fpage><lpage>764</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33284973</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Papakonstantinou</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leontiadis</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Katsaridis</surname><given-names>S.D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Anomalous circumflex artery: a benign variant generating a malignant potential after valve surgery</article-title><source>Coron Artery Dis</source><volume>34</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2023</year><fpage>364</fpage><lpage>371</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37139563</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="appsec1"><title>Appendix</title><p id="p0145">
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc1"><caption><title>Video 1</title><p>Preoperative Transthoracic Echocardiogram Showing Severe AR and Aortic Root Dilatation</p></caption><media xlink:href="mmc1.mp4"/></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc2"><caption><title>Video 2a</title><p>Surgical Procedure</p><p>Valve-sparing root replacement of the bicuspid valve in a Cardioroot 28-mm prosthesis (Getinge) with the skeletonization and mobilization of the aberrant circumflex artery</p></caption><media xlink:href="mmc2.mp4"/></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc3"><caption><title>Video 2b</title><p>Surgical Procedure</p><p>Valve-sparing root replacement of the bicuspid valve in a Cardioroot 28-mm prosthesis (Getinge) with the skeletonization and mobilization of the aberrant circumflex artery</p></caption><media xlink:href="mmc3.mp4"/></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc4"><caption><title>Video 2c</title><p>Surgical Procedure</p><p>Valve-sparing root replacement of the bicuspid valve in a Cardioroot 28-mm prosthesis (Getinge) with the skeletonization and mobilization of the aberrant circumflex artery</p></caption><media xlink:href="mmc4.mp4"/></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc5"><caption><title>Video 2d</title><p>Surgical Procedure</p><p>Valve-sparing root replacement of the bicuspid valve in a Cardioroot 28-mm prosthesis (Getinge) with the skeletonization and mobilization of the aberrant circumflex artery</p></caption><media xlink:href="mmc5.mp4"/></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc6"><caption><title>Video 3</title><p>Postoperative Transesophageal Echocardiogram Highlighting a Perfect Repair Result, With No AR and Mildly Depressed Left Ventricular Function</p></caption><media xlink:href="mmc6.mp4"/></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc7"><caption><title>Video 4</title><p>Follow-Up Echocardiography Demonstrating the Good Movement of the Aortic Leaflets With No AR and Good Function of the Left Ventricle</p></caption><media xlink:href="mmc7.mp4"/></supplementary-material>
</p></sec><fn-group><fn id="d36e80"><p id="ntpara0015aa">The authors attest they are in compliance with human studies committees and animal welfare regulations of the authors&#x02019; institutions and Food and Drug Administration guidelines, including patient consent where appropriate. For more information, visit the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.jacc.org/author-center" id="interref1">Author Center</ext-link>.</p></fn><fn id="appsec2"><p>Appendix</p><p id="p0150">For supplemental videos, please see the online version of this paper.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>