<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="issn">2168-8184</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cureus</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2168-8184</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cureus</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Palo Alto (CA)</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12100671</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7759/cureus.82828</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Neurology</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Radiology</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Infectious Disease</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Mild Encephalitis/Encephalopathy With a Reversible Splenial Lesion (MERS) in an Adult Following Influenza A Infection</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Muacevic</surname><given-names>Alexander</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>John R</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Malik</surname><given-names>Ahmed</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chandni</surname><given-names>Sadia Sultana</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Warsame</surname><given-names>Ramla</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Thillai</surname><given-names>Ruju Smirtha</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gollapinni</surname><given-names>Uday</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff-1">
<label>1</label>
Acute Internal Medicine, University Hospitals of North Midland, Royal Stoke University Hospital, Stoke on Trent, GBR </aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">
Ahmed Malik <email>ahmedmalik24@hotmail.com</email>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>23</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic"><month>4</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>17</volume><issue>4</issue><elocation-id>e82828</elocation-id><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2025, Malik et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Malik et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License CC-BY 4.0., which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="https://www.cureus.com/articles/357112-mild-encephalitisencephalopathy-with-a-reversible-splenial-lesion-mers-in-an-adult-following-influenza-a-infection">This article is available from https://www.cureus.com/articles/357112-mild-encephalitisencephalopathy-with-a-reversible-splenial-lesion-mers-in-an-adult-following-influenza-a-infection</self-uri><abstract><p>Mild encephalitis/encephalopathy with a reversible splenial lesion (MERS) is a rare clinical-radiological entity predominantly reported in pediatric populations, with limited cases in adults. We present a case of a 27-year-old female who developed transient neurological deficits following influenza A infection. She presented with severe headache, neck stiffness, and limb weakness with sensory deficits. Initial suspicion of meningoencephalitis prompted treatment with intravenous antibiotics and antivirals. However, an MRI revealed a hyperintense splenial lesion in the corpus callosum (SCC), supporting a diagnosis of MERS. The patient achieved full recovery without corticosteroids, reinforcing the self-limiting nature of this condition. This case highlights the diagnostic challenges, imaging findings, and management considerations of MERS, underscoring the importance of clinical awareness to avoid unnecessary interventions in adult cases.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>corpus callosum</kwd><kwd>cytokine injury</kwd><kwd>influenza a</kwd><kwd>mers</kwd><kwd>mri</kwd><kwd>neurological deficits</kwd><kwd>splenial lesion</kwd><kwd>viral encephalopathy</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Influenza is an acute viral infection primarily transmitted via respiratory droplets and contaminated surfaces. Of the four influenza subtypes (A, B, C, and D), influenza A and B are responsible for seasonal epidemics, while influenza C causes mild illness, and influenza D primarily affects cattle, with no known human infections [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. The severity of influenza varies from mild upper respiratory symptoms to life-threatening complications, including pneumonia, renal failure, and neurological manifestations such as Guillain-Barr&#x000e9; syndrome (GBS) and encephalopathy [<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Mild encephalitis/encephalopathy with a reversible splenial lesion (MERS) is a transient neurological syndrome associated with various infections, including influenza. It is characterized by MRI findings of hyperintensity in the SCC and is more commonly reported in pediatric populations [<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. This report describes an adult case of MERS secondary to influenza A, highlighting diagnostic challenges, pathophysiology, and management considerations [<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>].</p></sec><sec sec-type="cases"><title>Case presentation</title><p>A 27-year-old female was referred by a general practitioner to the emergency department with suspected meningitis. She presented with a cough-producing green sputum, rigors, severe headache, neck stiffness, progressive limb weakness, and sensory deficits. She also reported a 24-hour history of diarrhea and vomiting. Her medical history included depression, and she had received all childhood vaccinations except the meningitis vaccine. On examination, she was fully conscious with a Glasgow Coma Scale score of 15/15&#x000a0;and demonstrated reduced muscle power: 3/5 in the upper limbs and 2/5 in the lower limbs. Sensory deficits in glove-and-stocking distribution were noted, with diminished pinprick sensation and impaired temperature perception.&#x000a0;</p><p>Investigations</p><p>Laboratory findings were largely unremarkable. Renal function tests, liver function tests, vitamin B12, folate, and blood glucose levels were all within normal ranges. However, the patient had low inorganic phosphate (0.4 mmol/L) and an elevated C-reactive protein (CRP: 47.5 mg/L). The low phosphate was corrected with an intravenous infusion.</p><p>Due to the initial suspicion of meningoencephalitis, intravenous ceftriaxone and acyclovir were administered according to hospital protocol, along with supportive management including intravenous fluids. A lumbar puncture was also planned. A rapid antigen test confirmed an influenza A infection.</p><p>Although her neurological symptoms initially resolved, they recurred later that night, accompanied by photophobia and loss of vibration sensation in both great toes. Given the evolving neurological picture, an urgent MRI of the brain and spine was performed, revealing hyperintensity in the SCC&#x000a0;with diffusion restriction, consistent with MERS type 1 [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>].</p><p>The Neurology team was consulted, and the patient was reviewed by an Acute Medicine Consultant, who diagnosed influenza A infection with MERS type 1. Antibiotics and acyclovir were discontinued, and oseltamivir was initiated. The Neurology Consultant concurred with the management plan and advised that a lumbar puncture was unnecessary. Relevant blood test results are presented in Table <xref rid="TAB1" ref-type="table">1</xref> [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>], and imaging findings from the MRI of the head are shown in Figure <xref rid="FIG1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>-<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>].</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Blood test </title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Investigation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Result</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal reference range</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hb</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">126 g/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">115-165 g/L</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">WBC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4-11</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PLT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">292</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">150-450</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">B12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">261</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">200-900 pg/mL</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Influenza A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Detected</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Influenza B</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not detected</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Covid-19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not detected</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mg</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70-1.0 mmol/L</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ca</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2-2.6 mmol/L</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Albumin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35-50 g/L</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phosphate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80-1.5 mmol/L</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30-130 U/L</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Na</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">137</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">133-146 mmol/L</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">K</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5-5.3 mmol/L</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urea</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5-7.8 mmol/L</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0-48 IU/L</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AST</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0-35</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total bilirubin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0-21 umol/L</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Creatinine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53-97.2 mmol/L</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">eGFR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;90</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0-5 mg/L</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blood glucose</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4-7 mmol/L</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>MRI of the head</title><p>Brain MRI shows a small, ovoid area of increased signal intensity in the center of the splenium of the corpus callosum on axial FLAIR&#x000a0;(A) and DWI&#x000a0;(B), with corresponding diffusion restriction on the ADC&#x000a0;image (C). Repeat FLAIR (D), DWI (E), and ADC (F) imaging performed at three months demonstrate&#x000a0;complete resolution of the previously noted abnormal signals in the splenium.</p><p>FLAIR, fluid-attenuated inversion recovery; DWI, diffusion-weighted imaging; ADC, apparent diffusion coefficient</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0017-00000082828-i01" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>MERS&#x000a0;is a rare clinico-radiological syndrome characterized by transient neurological symptoms and reversible lesions in the SCC&#x000a0;seen on MRI. It is predominantly reported in pediatric populations, with limited cases documented in adults [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>].</p><p>The diagnosis of MERS is based on five criteria: 1) onset of neurological symptoms within one week of fever, 2) complete resolution of symptoms within 10 days, 3) high signal intensity in the SCC (MERS type 1), 4) diffuse involvement of the corpus callosum or white matter (MERS type 2), 5) resolution of lesions without residual changes on imaging [<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>].</p><p>Our patient fulfilled all diagnostic criteria for MERS type 1; follow-up MRI demonstrated complete resolution of the lesion. Literature suggests that repeat imaging may not be necessary if there is clear clinical improvement.</p><p>The pathophysiology of MERS is believed to involve cytokine-mediated disruption of the blood-brain barrier and transient intramyelinic edema, rather than direct viral invasion. Elevated levels of interleukins IL-6 and IL-10 have been implicated in influenza-associated encephalopathy and correlate with disease severity. The SCC&#x02019;s dense fiber composition and high metabolic demand may predispose it to transient excitotoxic injury [<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>].</p><p>Given its broad differential diagnosis, including ischemia, demyelination, posterior reversible encephalopathy syndrome (PRES), metabolic encephalopathies, and infections, early imaging and clinical correlation are crucial. Cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) analysis typically reveals no pleocytosis, distinguishing MERS from infectious encephalitis. In our case, lumbar puncture was not performed due to the patient&#x02019;s rapid neurological recovery, which represents a limitation in excluding alternative diagnoses [<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>].</p><p>Management of MERS is primarily supportive, with most cases resolving spontaneously. Although corticosteroids have been used in select cases, their benefit remains unproven [<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Our patient recovered fully without corticosteroid therapy, supporting a conservative management approach. While oseltamivir-induced neurotoxicity has been reported, it was unlikely in this case, as the patient&#x02019;s neurological symptoms predated the initiation of antiviral therapy.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>MERS&#x000a0;is a rare but important consideration in patients presenting with neurological deficits following viral infections like influenza A. This case highlights the diagnostic challenges of MERS in adults, where symptoms may mimic more common conditions such as meningoencephalitis, GBS, and myelitis. MRI remains the cornerstone of diagnosis, with the presence of a hyperintense lesion in the splenium of the corpus callosum being pathognomonic. As demonstrated in this case, MERS is self-limiting, and most patients recover without the need for corticosteroid therapy. Early recognition, appropriate imaging, and supportive management are crucial in ensuring favorable outcomes while avoiding unnecessary interventions. This case emphasizes the need for heightened awareness of MERS in adult populations, particularly in the context of post-influenza complications.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group content-type="conflict"><title>Disclosures</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Human subjects:</bold> Consent for treatment and open access publication was obtained or waived by all participants in this study.</p><p><bold>Conflicts of interest:</bold> In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following:</p><p><bold>Payment/services info:</bold> All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work.</p><p><bold>Financial relationships:</bold> All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work.</p><p><bold>Other relationships:</bold> All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="other"><title>Author Contributions</title><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Concept and design:</bold>&#x000a0; Ahmed Malik, Sadia Sultana Chandni, Ramla Warsame, Uday Gollapinni, Ruju Smirtha Thillai</p><p><bold>Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data:</bold>&#x000a0; Ahmed Malik, Sadia Sultana Chandni, Ramla Warsame, Uday Gollapinni, Ruju Smirtha Thillai</p><p><bold>Drafting of the manuscript:</bold>&#x000a0; Ahmed Malik, Sadia Sultana Chandni, Ramla Warsame, Uday Gollapinni, Ruju Smirtha Thillai</p><p><bold>Critical review of the manuscript for important intellectual content:</bold>&#x000a0; Ahmed Malik, Sadia Sultana Chandni, Ramla Warsame, Uday Gollapinni, Ruju Smirtha Thillai</p><p><bold>Supervision:</bold>&#x000a0; Ahmed Malik</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="REF1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Mild encephalitis/encephalopathy with reversible splenial lesion (MERS) in adults-a case report and literature review</article-title><source>BMC Neurol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>103</fpage><volume>17</volume><year>2017</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28545419</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Mild encephalitis/encephalopathy with a reversible splenial lesion secondary to encephalitis complicated by hyponatremia: a case report and literature review</article-title><source>Medicine (Baltimore)</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>MX</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shang</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>0</fpage><volume>98</volume><year>2019</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Classification of acquired lesions of the corpus callosum with MRI</article-title><source>Neuroradiology</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Friese</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bitzer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Freudenstein</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Voigt</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>K&#x000fc;ker</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>795</fpage><lpage>802</lpage><volume>42</volume><year>2000</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11151683</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Clinically mild encephalitis/encephalopathy with a reversible splenial lesion</article-title><source>Neurology</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Tada</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Takanashi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barkovich</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>1854</fpage><lpage>1858</lpage><volume>63</volume><year>2004</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15557501</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Influenza-associated central nervous system dysfunction: a literature review</article-title><source>Travel Med Infect Dis</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Toovey</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>114</fpage><lpage>124</lpage><volume>6</volume><year>2008</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18486065</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>