<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PeerJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PeerJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">peerj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PeerJ</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2167-8359</issn><publisher><publisher-name>PeerJ Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Diego, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12101445</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">19465</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19465</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Microbiology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Infectious Diseases</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Public Health</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Environmental Health</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Identification of bacteria on Thai banknotes and coins using MALDI-TOF mass spectrometry and their phenotypic antimicrobial susceptibility profiles</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="author-1" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Niyomdecha</surname><given-names>Nattamon</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sungvaraporn</surname><given-names>Suwitchaya</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pinmuang</surname><given-names>Arisa</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mungkornkaew</surname><given-names>Narissara</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-5" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Saita</surname><given-names>Thanchira</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-6" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rodraksa</surname><given-names>Waratchaya</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-7" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Phanitmas</surname><given-names>Achiraya</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-8" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yamasamit</surname><given-names>Nattapong</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-9" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Noisumdaeng</surname><given-names>Pirom</given-names></name><email>pirom.n@fph.tu.ac.th</email><xref rid="aff-3" ref-type="aff">3</xref><xref rid="aff-4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><aff id="aff-1"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Medical Technology, Faculty of Allied Health Sciences, Thammasat University</institution>, <city> Khlong Luang</city>, <state>Pathum Thani</state>, <country>Thailand</country></aff><aff id="aff-2"><label>2</label><institution>Microbiology Laboratory, Thammasat University Hospital, Thammasat University</institution>, <city>Khlong Luang</city>, <state>Pathum Thani</state>, <country>Thailand</country></aff><aff id="aff-3"><label>3</label><institution>Faculty of Public Health, Thammasat University</institution>, <city>Khlong Luang</city>, <state>Pathum Thani</state>, <country>Thailand</country></aff><aff id="aff-4"><label>4</label><institution>Thammasat University Research Unit in Modern Microbiology and Public Health Genomics, Thammasat University</institution>, <city>Khlong Luang</city>, <state>Pathum Thani</state>, <country>Thailand</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a-Contreras</surname><given-names>Rodolfo</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>5</month><year iso-8601-date="2025">2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>13</volume><elocation-id>e19465</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="2025-01-23"><day>23</day><month>1</month><year iso-8601-date="2025">2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="2025-04-23"><day>23</day><month>4</month><year iso-8601-date="2025">2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9;2025 Niyomdecha et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Niyomdecha et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, reproduction and adaptation in any medium and for any purpose provided that it is properly attributed. For attribution, the original author(s), title, publication source (PeerJ) and either DOI or URL of the article must be cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/19465"/><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>The existence and transmission of pathogenic and antibiotic-resistant bacteria through currency banknotes and coins poses a global public health risk. Banknotes and coins are handled by people in everyday life and have been identified as a universal medium for potentially microbial contamination.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>To ascertain existence of medically important bacteria, a total of 300 samples including 150 banknotes and 150 coins were randomly collected at onsite retail fresh meat stores, <italic toggle="yes">i.e.</italic>, pork and chicken, fish, and seafood stores, from nineteen fresh markets distributed across Bangkok, Thailand. An individual banknote or coin was entirely swabbed, and bacterial culture was carried out using tryptic soy agar (TSA), sheep blood agar (SBA) and MacConkey agar (Mac). A colony count was performed and bacterial species identification was conducted using matrix-assisted laser desorption/ionization (MALDI)-time of flight (TOF) mass spectrometry. Phenotypic antimicrobial susceptibility testing was carried out using the Kirby&#x02013;Bauer disc diffusion methods.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>The results demonstrated that the bacterial contamination rate was higher on banknotes than on coins (93.33% <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> 30.00%) in all three store types. A substantial number of colonies of &#x0003e;3,000 colony forming units (CFU) was predominantly found in banknotes (70.00%), especially from fish store (83.3%); meanwhile, &#x0003c;1,000 CFU was observed in coin sample (76.67%). MALDI-TOF mass spectrometry could identify 107 bacterial species, most of them were <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus kloosii</italic> (14.02%, 15/107), <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus saprophyticus</italic> (12.15%, 13/107), and <italic toggle="yes">Macrococcus caseolyticus</italic> (8.41%, 9/107). The prevalence based on genera were <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus</italic> (36.45%, 39/107), <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter</italic> (20.56%, 22/107), and <italic toggle="yes">Macrococcus</italic> (10.28%, 11/107). Almost all Staphylococcus isolates had low susceptibility to penicillin (21%). Notably, <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus&#x000a0;arlettae</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus haemolyticus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">M. caseolyticus</italic> were multidrug-resistant (MDR). It is notable that none of the staphylococci and macrococci isolates exhibited inducible clindamycin resistance (D-test negative). <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas putida</italic> isolates were carbapenem-resistant, and <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> isolates were MDR with showing carbapenem resistance.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Our data demonstrated a high prevalence of medically important bacteria presented on Thai currency, which may pose a potential risk to human health and food safety. Food vendors and consumers should be educated about the possible cross-contamination of bacteria between the environment, food item, and currency.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>Bacteria</kwd><kwd>MALDI-TOF mass spectrometry</kwd><kwd>Currency</kwd><kwd>Markets</kwd><kwd>Antimicrobial susceptibility test</kwd><kwd>Thai</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="fund-1"><funding-source>The Thailand Science Research and Innovation (TSRI) Fundamental Fund, fiscal year 2024</funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by the Thailand Science Research and Innovation (TSRI) Fundamental Fund, fiscal year 2024. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Cashless payment technology is a feature that currency transactions in the digital world provide for individuals; nevertheless, this advanced technology is still unable to apply to all users or be implemented in all places. Consequently, transactions utilizing banknotes and coins remain significant and unavoidable. Accumulated data reported over the last 20&#x000a0;years globally on the microbial status and survival of pathogen on currency notes indicated that this could represent a potential cause of disease transmission, especially respiratory and gastrointestinal infections (<xref rid="ref-80" ref-type="bibr">Schaarschmidt, 1884</xref>; <xref rid="ref-2" ref-type="bibr">Agersew, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="ref-71" ref-type="bibr">Ofoedu et al., 2021</xref>). The frequent handling of money by individuals with bacteria-contaminated hands, as well as its contact with contaminated surfaces or food, poses a significant risk. Money, as a universal medium of exchange, has the potential to act as a carrier for the transmission of infectious pathogens to humans and animals. Additionally, it may facilitate the horizontal transfer of antimicrobial resistance genes between commensal and pathogenic bacteria, as documented in prior studies (<xref rid="ref-70" ref-type="bibr">Nemeghaire et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="ref-23" ref-type="bibr">Chanchaithong, Perreten &#x00026; Schwendener, 2019</xref>).</p><p>Previous reports indicated that banknotes and coins were frequently contaminated with bacteria, particularly from human skin microbiota such as coagulase-negative staphylococci (CoNS), gut microbiota enterococci, and environmental <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus</italic> spp. (<xref rid="ref-71" ref-type="bibr">Ofoedu et al., 2021</xref>; <xref rid="ref-66" ref-type="bibr">Meister et al., 2023</xref>). Additionally, various other pathogenic bacteria, such as <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">S.&#x000a0;aureus</italic>), <italic toggle="yes">Streptococcus</italic> spp., <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">E.&#x000a0;coli</italic>), <italic toggle="yes">Proteus</italic> spp., <italic toggle="yes">Klebsiella</italic> spp., <italic toggle="yes">Enterobacter</italic> spp., <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas</italic> spp., <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter</italic> spp., <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> spp., and multiple-drug resistance bacteria, are frequently identified (<xref rid="ref-66" ref-type="bibr">Meister et al., 2023</xref>). Certain bacteria have been documented to flourish on the skin (<xref rid="ref-61" ref-type="bibr">Mackintosh &#x00026; Hoffman, 1984</xref>), and on inanimate surfaces for a long time (<xref rid="ref-52" ref-type="bibr">Kramer, Schwebke &#x00026; Kampf, 2006</xref>). Nonetheless, several parameters such as humidity, temperature, pH, salinity, surface material, UV radiation, the presence of organic matter, and ventilation, along with pathogen-specific factors like the initial quantity of infectious agents, can significantly influence the persistence of infectious microbes (<xref rid="ref-57" ref-type="bibr">Leung, 2021</xref>).</p><p>Thailand is located in a tropical region with high temperatures and humidity, which effectively encourages the growth of germs. Thailand is experiencing rapid aging, positioning itself as the second most aged society in ASEAN, following Singapore. At present, twenty percent of the Thai population is aged 60&#x000a0;years or older. By 2030, approximately one-third of the Thai population is projected to be over 60&#x000a0;years old (<xref rid="ref-91" ref-type="bibr">UNFPA Country Office in Thailand, 2021</xref>). These factors might raise the risk of bacterial colonization, transmission, and infection in elderly individuals who are susceptible. Consequently, it is imperative to prioritize the evaluation of bacterial contamination on currency to reduce public health hazards, particularly for vulnerable populations that lack access to advanced cashless technologies. Unfortunately, research is scarce on this significant field in Thailand. This study aimed to identify bacterial strains contaminating Thai currency using the MALDI-TOF assay and to determine the antimicrobial resistance profiles of the medically important bacteria detected. This has the potential to offer important information regarding public health surveillance, which could encourage individuals to be aware of and maintain their hygiene.</p></sec><sec><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Study sites and sample collection</title><p>This cross-sectional study was conducted from June to July 2024, which any kinds of Thai banknotes and coins were randomly collected from retail fresh meat stores at the markets in Bangkok, Thailand. Excellent fresh food markets certified by the Department of Internal Trade (DIT), Ministry of Commerce, Thailand, located in Bangkok were selected as the study sites.</p><p>Based on previous investigations, many studies from several countries including Thailand have reported the very high prevalence of bacterial contamination ranging from 69% to 100% of tested currencies with varying degrees of sample sizes randomly collected (70&#x02013;343 banknotes and coins) (<xref rid="ref-76" ref-type="bibr">Phunpae et al., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="ref-71" ref-type="bibr">Ofoedu et al., 2021</xref>; <xref rid="ref-97" ref-type="bibr">Yar, 2020</xref>; <xref rid="ref-31" ref-type="bibr">Ejaz, Javeed &#x00026; Zubair, 2018</xref>; <xref rid="ref-36" ref-type="bibr">Gabriel, Coffey &#x00026; O&#x02019;Mahony, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr">Alemu, 2014</xref>). In addition, most of the tested currencies were contaminated by pathogenic or potentially pathogenic bacteria. Therefore, we hypothesized that most of actively used banknotes and coins in the circulation system might be contaminated by bacteria. Our study set the sample sizes with at least 35 samples based on each type of fresh stores (pork and chicken, seafood, and fish stores) located in nineteen markets, identified as excellent fresh food markets, across Bangkok. Therefore, a presumptive sample sizes of 105 banknotes and 105 coins should be collected. However, to precise statistically descriptive analysis, our study collected a total of 300 samples, including 150 banknotes and 150 coins, with a similar proportion from each store type as described in <xref rid="table-1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. The samples were collected by the purchasing process from three categories of retail stores: pork and chicken stores, fish stores, and seafood stores. The samples received from each store were kept in a sterile plastic bag under cold storage condition before further processing.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="table-1"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19465/table-1</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Details of markets and data distribution in sample collection.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-13-19465-g005" position="float"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<bold>Market details</bold>
<xref rid="table-1fn1" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<bold>Pork/Chicken</bold>
</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<bold>Seafood</bold>
</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<bold>Fish</bold>
</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<bold>Total</bold>
</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Label</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>District</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>B</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>C</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>B</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>C</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>B</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>C</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>B</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>C</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<bold>(I) Phra&#x000a0;Nakhon Zone</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sai Mai</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bang Sue</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bang Khen</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bang Khen</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Khan Na Yao</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min Buri</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lak Si</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">H</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chatuchak</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Suan Luang</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">J</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prawet</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">K</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Din Daeng</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pathum Wan</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<bold>(II) Thonburi Zone</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bangkok Noi</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Khlong San</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">O</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Taling Chan</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Suan Luang</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thung Khru</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thawi Watthana</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thawi Watthana</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Total</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">150</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">150</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-1fn"><p>
<bold>Notes.</bold>
</p></fn><fn id="table-1fn1"><label>a</label><p>Samples were collected from each market once, except for market O, which was sampled twice.</p></fn><fn id="table-1fn2" fn-type="other"><p>
<def-list id="dl1"><term-head>Abbreviations</term-head><def-item><term> B</term><def><p>banknote</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> C</term><def><p>coin</p></def></def-item></def-list>
</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Sample processing</title><p>Each banknote or coin was entirely swabbed, and the swab was then resuspended with 1 ml of tryptic soy broth (TSB) and incubated for 30 min at 37 &#x000b0;C (<xref rid="ref-76" ref-type="bibr">Phunpae et al., 2018</xref>). One-hundred microliters (&#x000b5;l) TSB culture was directly inoculated to tryptic soy agar (TSA) without making a dilution for colony count, and a full loop of culture was utilized to isolate the bacterial colonies in the sample using a cross-streak technique on sheep blood agar (SBA) and MacConkey agar (Mac). All culture plates were incubated overnight at 37 &#x000b0;C. The leftover TSB culture was kept at 4 &#x000b0;C. A colony count on TSA was reported as CFU/ml or too many to count (TMTC). The positive culture on SBA/Mac was recorded and calculated as the prevalence percentage (%). The suspected medically important bacterial colonies were chosen for subculturing as pure isolation on SBA/Mac, and the basic characteristics was determined by gram-staining to differentiate between gram-positive and gram-negative bacteria and by testing the presumptive tests of catalase/oxidase (<xref rid="ref-55" ref-type="bibr">Lee, 2021</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Colony identification using MALDI-TOF mass spectrometry</title><p>A fresh pure colony was spotted on a MALDI-TOF target Microflex (Bruker Daltonik, Wissembourg, France) using a sterile wooden toothpick. An expanded direct transfer (&#x0201c;on-target&#x0201d; extraction) method was used for the gram-positive colony. The spotted colony as a film was treated with one &#x000b5;l of 70% formic acid (Sigma Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA) in HPLC grade water (Sigma Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA) and left to air dry at room temperature. Following the drying, 1&#x02013;2 &#x000b5;l of a saturated solution of &#x003b1;-Cyano-4-hydroxycinnamic acid (HCCA) matrix solution in 50% acetonitrile and 2.5% trifluoroacetic acid was applied and allowed to dry at room temperature for 5 min before loading sample targets into the matrix-assisted laser desorption/ionization (MALDI)-time of flight (TOF) mass spectrometry (MALDI-TOF MS) instrument for analysis. On the other hand, a direct transfer method was applied for the gram-negative colony. The same protocol was done as described for the gram-positive colony except for not treating with formic acid solution (<xref rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr">Calderaro &#x00026; Chezzi, 2024</xref>).</p><p>Sample mass spectra were acquired and analyzed by the Biotyper software to compare the protein profile of the bacteria with a library database (<xref rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr">Calderaro &#x00026; Chezzi, 2024</xref>). An analyzed score &#x0003c;1.70 was considered unreliable and no identification of bacteria, while a score &#x02265;1.70 was accepted for identification. A score &#x0003e;1.99 represents a precise identification of genus and species, whereas a score &#x02265;1.70&#x02212;1.99 confirms identification of genus only, without species specification (<xref rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr">Calderaro &#x00026; Chezzi, 2024</xref>; <xref rid="ref-26" ref-type="bibr">Czeszewska-Rosiak et al., 2025</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Antimicrobial susceptibility test</title><p>An antimicrobial susceptibility assay was performed using the Kirby-Bauer disc diffusion method. Inhibition zones were measured and interpreted using the Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute (CLSI) guidelines (33rd edition) (<xref rid="ref-44" ref-type="bibr">Institute CLSI, 2023</xref>). The following antibiotics (Oxoid) were used: penicillin 10 &#x000b5;g (P), ampicillin 10 &#x000b5;g (AMP), ampicillin/clavulanic acid 20/10 &#x000b5;g (AMC), amikacin 30 &#x000b5;g (AK), clindamycin two &#x000b5;g (DA), erythromycin 15 &#x000b5;g (E), cefoxitin 30 &#x000b5;g (FOX), sulfamethoxazole/trimethoprim 23.75/1.25 &#x000b5;g (SXT), tetracyclin 30 &#x000b5;g (TE), fusidic acid 10 &#x000b5;g (FD), gentamicin 10 &#x000b5;g (CN), gentamicin 120 &#x000b5;g (CN), vancomycin 30 &#x000b5;g (VA), ceftazidime 30 &#x000b5;g (CAZ), cefotaxime 30 &#x000b5;g (CTX), meropenem 10 &#x000b5;g (MEM), imipenem 10 &#x000b5;g (IMP), ciprofloxacin five &#x000b5;g (CIP), and levofloxacin five &#x000b5;g (LEV). The clinical resistance breakpoints established for <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus</italic> spp. were applied to <italic toggle="yes">Macrococcus</italic> spp., as proposed by <xref rid="ref-25" ref-type="bibr">Cotting et al. (2017)</xref>. Inducible clindamycin resistance was detected using a double disk diffusion test by CLSI guidelines. The antimicrobial susceptibility results for each group of tested microorganisms were calculated as a percentage of susceptibility (only S result) and presented as antimicrobial resistance profiles.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Descriptive statistical analysis was carried out to calculate the frequency or percentage of data.</p></sec><sec><title>Biosafety approval</title><p>The biosafety issue was approved by the Institutional Biosafety Committee (TU-IBC), Thammasat University with the certificate of approval number 015/2567.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Sample collection and bacteria identification by MALDI-TOF mass spectrometry</title><p>Nineteen excellent fresh food markets (labelled A-S in <xref rid="fig-1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>) located in different locations across two zone areas of Thonburi (green zone) and Phra Nakhon (yellow zone) of Bangkok province were chosen as study sites. A total of 300 samples, including 150 banknotes and 150 coins, were collected with a similar proportion from each store type as described in <xref rid="table-1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p><fig position="float" id="fig-1"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19465/fig-1</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Map of the study sites encompassing nineteen excellent fresh food markets (labeled A-S) located in different locations across two zone areas of Thonburi (green zone) and PhraNakhon (yellow zone) of Bangkok, Thailand.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-13-19465-g001" position="float"/></fig><p>As shown in <xref rid="fig-2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>, the bacteria contamination rates were detected on banknotes higher than on coins (93.33% <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> 30.00%) in all store types. All positive samples were contaminated with multiple colony types. The highest bacterial contamination rate on banknotes was observed in fish stores (100%, 30/30), whereas the highest contamination rate on coins was found in pork and chicken stores (45.76%, 27/59) (<xref rid="supp-1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S1</xref>). Additionally, the colony count was evaluated for banknote and coin samples as illustrated in <xref rid="fig-3" ref-type="fig">Figs. 3A</xref> and <xref rid="fig-3" ref-type="fig">3B</xref>. Seventy percent of the banknote samples exhibited a substantial number of colonies, ranging from over 3,000 CFU to TMTC, whereas 76.67% of the coin samples displayed colony counts below 1000 CFU. Notably, the highest percentage of &#x0003e;3000-TMTC CFU colony count was observed on banknotes at fish stores (83.33%) and on coins at pork and poultry stores (13.56%) (<xref rid="supp-2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S2</xref>). In addition, the number of contaminated bacteria detected across different location sites for both banknote and coin was comparable by showing minimum detection at ranged of 0&#x02013;60 CFU and maximum detection of &#x0003e;3,000 CFU or TMTC (<xref rid="supp-2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table&#x000a0;S2</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig-2"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19465/fig-2</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Percentage of bacterial detection on Thai banknotes and coins from retail fresh meat stores, <italic toggle="yes">i.e.,</italic> pork and chicken, fish, and seafood stores.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-13-19465-g002" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="fig-3"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19465/fig-3</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Enumeration of bacterial colonies grown in tryptic soy agar (TSA).</title><p>A colony count was evaluated and reported as CFU/ml or too many to count (TMTC) for banknotes (A) and coins (B).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-13-19465-g003" position="float"/></fig><p>One-hundred and twenty-five colonies grown on SBA/Mac were randomly selected from any kind and any source of samples. They were isolated and identified using the MALDI-TOF MS, and the analyzed score of each isolate was reported in <xref rid="supp-3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S3</xref>. About 85.60% (107/125) of isolates could be reported due to some of them showing the problems of no peak signal presence or unidentified peptide peak based on the database. Colony isolation from fish stores could be identified in the highest proportion (90.91%, 20/22) when compared to pork and chicken stores (89.66%, 52/58), and seafood stores (77.78%, 35/45). Data from MALDI-TOF MS indicated that the majority were uncommon bacterial strains identified as shown in <xref rid="table-2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. Of the detected strains, 58.69% (27/46) were gram-negative. The top three predominant strains were <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus kloosii</italic> (14.02%, 15/107), <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus saprophyticus</italic> (12.15%, 13/107), and <italic toggle="yes">Macrococcus caseolyticus</italic> (8.41%, 9/107). <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus kloosii</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Macrococcus caseolyticus</italic> were the most prevalence in pork and chicken stores; meanwhile, <italic toggle="yes">S. saprophyticus</italic> was mostly detected in seafood stores. Nevertheless, the prevalence data analyzed based on genus, <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus</italic> (36.45%, 39/107), <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter</italic> (20.56%, 22/107), and <italic toggle="yes">Macrococcus</italic> (10.28%, 11/107) were identified as the three most predominant genera.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="table-2"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19465/table-2</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Description of bacteria identified by MALDI-TOF mass spectrometry, sources of isolation, and infection system.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-13-19465-g006" position="float"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Microorganisms</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gram</th><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">No. of isolation</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total (%)<break/>(<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;107)</th><th align="center" colspan="8" rowspan="1">Infection systems</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pork/Chicken<break/>(<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;52)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Seafood<break/>(<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;35)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fish<break/>(<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;20)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">RT</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">SST</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">UT</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">CNS</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">BL</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GI</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Others</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">No report</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GNC/GNCB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (2.80)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="ref-42" ref-type="bibr">Howard et al. (2012)</xref>, <xref rid="ref-89" ref-type="bibr">Towner (2009)</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter bereziniae</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GNCB/GNB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (3.74)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr">Dahal, Paul &#x00026; Gupta (2023)</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter defluvii</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GNCB/GNB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.93)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter gandensis</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GNCB/GNB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.93)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter indicus</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GNCB/GNB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.93)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr">Dahal, Paul &#x00026; Gupta (2023)</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter junii</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GNCB/GNB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.93)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-1" ref-type="bibr">Abo-Zed, Yassin &#x00026; Phan (2020)</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter lactucae</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GNCB/GNB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.93)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-82" ref-type="bibr">Sheck et&#x000a0;al. (2023)</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter pittii</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GNCB/GNB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.93)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr">Bello-L&#x000f3;pez et&#x000a0;al. (2024)</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter radioresistens</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GNCB/GNB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.93)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-95" ref-type="bibr">Wang et&#x000a0;al. (2019)</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter seifertii</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GNCB/GNB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.93)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-82" ref-type="bibr">Sheck et al. (2023)</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter ursingii</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GNCB/GNB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (5.61)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr">Dahal, Paul &#x00026; Gupta (2023)</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter variabilis</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GNCB/GNB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.93)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Aerococcus viridans</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GPC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (2.80)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-67" ref-type="bibr">Mohan et al. (2017)</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas veronii</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GNB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.93)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-45" ref-type="bibr">Janda &#x00026; Abbott (2010)</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Bacillus pumilus</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GPB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.93)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="ref-87" ref-type="bibr">Tena et&#x000a0;al. (2007)</xref>, <xref rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr">Bentur, Dalzell &#x00026; Riordan (2007)</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Corynebacterium casei</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GPB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.93)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr">Bernard (2012)</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Cronobacter sp.</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GNB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.93)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-74" ref-type="bibr">Patrick et&#x000a0;al. (2014)</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Delftia tsuruhatensis</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GNB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (1.87)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-78" ref-type="bibr">Ranc et&#x000a0;al. (2018)</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Empedobacter falsenii</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GNB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.93)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-72" ref-type="bibr">Olowo-Okere et&#x000a0;al. (2022)</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Enterobacter kobei</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GNB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.93)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="ref-41" ref-type="bibr">Hoffmann et&#x000a0;al. (2005)</xref>, <xref rid="ref-47" ref-type="bibr">Ji et al. (2021)</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Enterobacter roggenkampii</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GNB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.93)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-47" ref-type="bibr">Ji et al. (2021)</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus casseliflavus</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GPC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.93)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-98" ref-type="bibr">Yoshino (2023)</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GNB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.93)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-68" ref-type="bibr">Mueller &#x00026; Tainter (2023)</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Lysinibacillus fusiformis</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GPB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.93)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-86" ref-type="bibr">Sulaiman et&#x000a0;al. (2018)</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Macrococcus canis</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GPC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (1.87)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr">Jost et al. (2021)</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Macrococcus caseolyticus</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GPC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (8.41)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-99" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al. (2022)</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Mammaliicoccus sciuri</italic>
<xref rid="table-2fn1" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>&#x02020;</sup>
</xref>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GPC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (1.87)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="ref-17" ref-type="bibr">Boonchuay et&#x000a0;al. (2023)</xref>, <xref rid="ref-28" ref-type="bibr">Daki&#x00107; et&#x000a0;al. (2005)</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Mixta calida</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GNB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.93)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-43" ref-type="bibr">Huzefa et&#x000a0;al. (2022)</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Moraxella osloensis</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GNCB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (1.87)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-5" ref-type="bibr">Alkhatib et&#x000a0;al. (2017)</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Ochrombactrum amthropi</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GNB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.93)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-46" ref-type="bibr">Jeyaraman et&#x000a0;al. (2022)</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Pantoea eucrina</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GNB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.93)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Pantoea piersonii</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GNB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.93)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Pluralibacter gergoviae</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GNB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (1.87)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-35" ref-type="bibr">Furlan &#x00026; Stehling (2023)</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Priestia megaterium</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GPB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.93)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="ref-84" ref-type="bibr">Shwed et&#x000a0;al. (2021)</xref>, <xref rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr">Bocchi et al. (2020)</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas putida</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GNB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (1.87)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-11" ref-type="bibr">Baykal et&#x000a0;al. (2022)</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Rothia amarae</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GPC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (1.87)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-34" ref-type="bibr">Fatahi-Bafghi (2021)</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Rothia endophytica</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GPC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (1.87)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-34" ref-type="bibr">Fatahi-Bafghi (2021)</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus arlettae</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GPC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.93)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-29" ref-type="bibr">Dinakaran et&#x000a0;al. (2012)</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GPC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.93)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-88" ref-type="bibr">Tong et&#x000a0;al. (2015)</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus epidermidis</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GPC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (2.80)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-73" ref-type="bibr">Otto (2009)</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus haemolyticus</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GPC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.93)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-33" ref-type="bibr">Eltwisy et&#x000a0;al. (2022)</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus hominis</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GPC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (2.80)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-92" ref-type="bibr">Vasconcellos et&#x000a0;al. (2022)</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus kloosii</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GPC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (14.02)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr">Blondeau et&#x000a0;al. (2021)</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus saprophyticus</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GPC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (12.15)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-54" ref-type="bibr">Lawal et&#x000a0;al. (2021)</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus xylosus</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GPC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (1.87)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-30" ref-type="bibr">Dordet-Frisoni et&#x000a0;al. (2007)</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Stenotrophomonas maltophilia</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GNB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (2.80)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-20" ref-type="bibr">Brooke (2012)</xref>
</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-2fn"><p>
<bold>Notes.</bold>
</p></fn><fn id="table-2fn1"><label>&#x02020;</label><p>It was previously known as <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus sciuri</italic>.</p></fn><fn id="table-2fn2" fn-type="other"><p>
<def-list id="dl2"><term-head>Abbreviations</term-head><def-item><term> N</term><def><p>number of isolates</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> RT</term><def><p>respiratory tract</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> SST</term><def><p>skin and soft tissues or wound</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> UT</term><def><p>urinary tract</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> CNS</term><def><p>central nervous system</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> BL</term><def><p>blood</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> GI</term><def><p>gastrointestinal tract</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> GNC</term><def><p>gram-negative cocci</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> GNCB</term><def><p>gram-negative coccobacilli</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> GNB</term><def><p>gram-negative bacilli</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> GPC</term><def><p>gram-positive cocci</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> GPB</term><def><p>gram-positive bacilli</p></def></def-item></def-list>
</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Considering the majority of uncommon bacterial strains were detected, their category as human pathogens and their pathogenesis was examined, as illustrated in <xref rid="table-2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. The literature review identified eight classifications of infection systems for each microorganism: respiratory tract (RT), skin and soft tissues (SST) or wound, urinary tract (UT), central nervous system (CNS), blood (BL), gastrointestinal tract (GI), other systems, and no report. Among them, the majority of detected bacteria (78.26%, 36/46) were classified as human pathogens, with a significant proportion (69.44%, 25/36) responsible for multiple tract infections. Nonetheless, bloodstream infection was the most prevalent (<xref rid="fig-4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> and <xref rid="supp-4" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S4</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig-4"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19465/fig-4</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Percentages of detected bacteria classified as human pathogens for causing infections in several systems.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-13-19465-g004" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Antimicrobial susceptibility</title><p>As shown in <xref rid="table-3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>, fifty bacterial isolates were randomly selected from groups of bacteria that can be tested by standard antimicrobial drugs, which have interpretation criteria based on CLSI guidelines. Almost all <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus</italic> isolates had low susceptibility to penicillin (21%), with the exception of <italic toggle="yes">S. epidermidis</italic>, which demonstrated no resistance for all drugs tested. Isolates of <italic toggle="yes">S. arlettae</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">S. haemolyticus</italic> were multidrug-resistant (MDR), defined as the bacterial isolate acquired non-susceptibility to at least one agent in three or more antimicrobial categories (<xref rid="ref-62" ref-type="bibr">Magiorakos et al., 2012</xref>), and methicillin-resistant. Macrococci, a close relative of the <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus</italic> genus, were highly resistant to erythromycin and clindamycin. <italic toggle="yes">M. caseolyticus</italic> exhibited intermediate susceptibility to fusidic acid and low susceptibility to tetracyclin. Thus, some <italic toggle="yes">M. caseolyticus</italic> isolates were multidrug resistance. It is notable that none of the staphylococci and macrococci isolates exhibited inducible clindamycin resistance (D-test negative). A single isolate of <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> was susceptible to all drugs that were tested.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="table-3"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19465/table-3</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Antimicrobial resistance profiles of identified gram positive bacteria (A) and gram negative bacteria (B) in the study.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-13-19465-g007" position="float"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Microorganisms (N)</bold>
</th><th align="center" colspan="19" rowspan="1">
<bold>% Drug Susceptibility</bold>
<xref rid="table-3fn1" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>P</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>DA</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>E</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>FOX</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>SXT</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>TE</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>FD</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>AMC</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>VA</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>h-CN</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>LEV</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>AMP</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>CAZ</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>CTX</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>CN</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>IMP</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>MEM</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>AK</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>CIP</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="20" rowspan="1">
<bold>(A) Gram positive bacteria</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus</italic>
</bold>
<bold> (19)</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74<xref rid="table-3fn" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">89<xref rid="table-3fn" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">S.&#x000a0;kloosii</italic> (4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">S.&#x000a0;hominis</italic> (3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">S.&#x000a0;xylosus</italic> (2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">S.&#x000a0;saprophyticus</italic> (5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">S.&#x000a0;epidermidis</italic> (2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">S.&#x000a0;arlettae</italic> (1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">S.&#x000a0;haemolyticus</italic> (1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">S.&#x000a0;aureus</italic> (1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic toggle="yes">Macrococcus</italic>
</bold>
<bold> (6)</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67<xref rid="table-3fn" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83<xref rid="table-3fn" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">M.&#x000a0;canis</italic> (2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">M.&#x000a0;caseolyticus</italic> (4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75<xref rid="table-3fn" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus casseliflavus</italic> (1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="20" rowspan="1">
<bold>(B) Gram negative bacteria</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Stenotrophomonas maltophilia</italic> (1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Enterobacter roggenkampii</italic> (1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Enterobacter kobei</italic> (1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> (1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas putida</italic> (2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter</italic>
</bold>
<bold> (16)</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">88<xref rid="table-3fn" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">94</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">88<xref rid="table-3fn" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">A.&#x000a0;baumannii</italic> (2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">A.&#x000a0;bereziniae</italic> (3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67<xref rid="table-3fn" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">A.&#x000a0;defluvii</italic> (1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">A.&#x000a0;gandensis</italic> (1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">A.&#x000a0;indicus</italic> (1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">A.&#x000a0;junii</italic> (1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">A.&#x000a0;pittii</italic> (1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">A.&#x000a0;radioresistens</italic> (1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">A.&#x000a0;seifertii</italic> (1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">A.&#x000a0;ursingii</italic> (3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">A.&#x000a0;variabilis</italic> (1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-3fn"><p>
<bold>Notes.</bold>
</p></fn><fn id="table-3fn1"><label>a</label><p>The data was calculated from only susceptible result. Level of drug susceptibility was classified into three levels: Low susceptibility (&#x02264; 50%) was indicated in bold number; Intermediate susceptibility (51&#x02013;89%) was indicated with asterisk sign (*); and High susceptibility (&#x02265; 90%).</p></fn><fn id="table-3fn2" fn-type="other"><p>
<def-list id="dl3"><term-head>Abbreviations</term-head><def-item><term> N</term><def><p>number of isolates</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> P</term><def><p>penicillin 10&#x000a0;&#x003bc; g</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> AMP</term><def><p>ampicillin 10 &#x003bc; g</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> AMC</term><def><p>ampicillin/clavulanic acid 20/10 &#x003bc; g</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> AK</term><def><p>amikacin 30 &#x003bc; g</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> DA</term><def><p>clindamycin 2&#x000a0;&#x003bc; g</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> E</term><def><p>erythromycin 15&#x000a0;&#x003bc; g</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> FOX</term><def><p>cefoxitin 30&#x000a0;&#x003bc; g</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> SXT</term><def><p>sulfamethoxazole/trimethoprim 23.75/1.25 &#x003bc; g</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> TE</term><def><p>Tetracyclin 30 &#x003bc; g</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> FD</term><def><p>Fusidic acid 10 &#x003bc; g</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> CN</term><def><p>gentamicin 10 &#x003bc; g</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> h-CN</term><def><p>gentamicin 120 &#x003bc; g</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> VA</term><def><p>vancomycin 30 &#x003bc; g</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> CAZ</term><def><p>ceftazidime 30 &#x003bc; g</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> CTX</term><def><p>cefotaxime 30 &#x003bc; g</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> MEM</term><def><p>meropenem 10 &#x003bc; g</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> IMP</term><def><p>imipenem 10 &#x003bc; g</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> CIP</term><def><p>ciprofloxacin 5 &#x003bc; g</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> LEV</term><def><p>levofloxacin 5&#x000a0;&#x003bc; g</p></def></def-item></def-list>
</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>For gram-negative bacteria, most of them were resistant to ampicillin, ampicillin/clavulanic acid, and ceftazidime. Notably, <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">P. putida</italic> isolates were carbapenem-resistant, and <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolates were MDR and carbapenem-resistant. Ceftazidime resistance was observed in particular <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter</italic> non-<italic toggle="yes">baumannii</italic> species, such as <italic toggle="yes">A. bereziniae</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">A. defluvii</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">A. gandensis</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">A. seifertii</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">A. ursingii</italic>. Ciprofloxacin resistance was also discovered in <italic toggle="yes">A. gandensis</italic> (<xref rid="table-3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> and <xref rid="supp-5" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S5</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Despite the digital world enabling cashless transactions, the utilization of currency remains essential for some individuals, locations, and circumstances. A significant quantity of germs has been found on banknotes, some of which are infectious to humans (<xref rid="ref-76" ref-type="bibr">Phunpae et al., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="ref-40" ref-type="bibr">Gosa, 2015</xref>). The currency circulation could be a vehicle for transmitting pathogenic bacteria to other compromised or healthy individuals. Neglecting personal hygiene and allowing hand contact or physical transfer between bacteria-shedding sources and currency results in cash contamination. Sources of bacterial contamination in this study may occur <italic toggle="yes">via</italic> the release of infectious bacteria through mucus, feces, and aerosol droplets during coughing or sneezing by infected individuals, or from other contaminated environmental surfaces or fresh meats in each store. Paper notes from meat shops were likely to be contaminated with blood, which is a good medium for facilitating substantial microbial proliferation (<xref rid="ref-97" ref-type="bibr">Yar, 2020</xref>). Contaminated banknotes and coins act as a universal carrier for the spread of pathogens, posing a threat to public health.</p><p>Our finding aligned with prior studies (<xref rid="ref-76" ref-type="bibr">Phunpae et al., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="ref-49" ref-type="bibr">Kalita et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="ref-37" ref-type="bibr">Glenn et al., 2015</xref>) indicating that the positive culture results from banknotes were observed at a higher rate and quantity compared to coins. It is noteworthy that several bacterial strains were identified in the majority of positive culture samples, as indicated by previous research (<xref rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr">Basavarajappa, Rao &#x00026; Suresh, 2005</xref>). The difference in material type and size between Thai banknotes and Thai coins corroborated the findings. Nearly all Thai banknotes are composed of cotton-linen paper; however, the 20-baht banknote was changed to polymer material in 2009 to enhance durability for practical use. In contrast, Thai coins are composed of various metals based on their denomination, including copper, nickel, and aluminum (<xref rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr">Bank of Thailand, 2024</xref>). The predominant metal in all Thai coins is copper, comprising between 75% and 92% (<xref rid="ref-76" ref-type="bibr">Phunpae et al., 2018</xref>). The porous structure of cotton-linen fibers in banknotes could promote bacterial colonization more effectively than polymers and metals (<xref rid="ref-94" ref-type="bibr">Vriesekoop et al., 2016</xref>). This may be attributed to a variety of physicochemical parameters in polymers (<xref rid="ref-77" ref-type="bibr">Prasai, Yami &#x00026; Joshi, 2010</xref>) copper metal exhibits broad antibacterial properties that can suppress bacterial growth (<xref rid="ref-79" ref-type="bibr">Salah, Parkin &#x00026; Allan, 2021</xref>).</p><p>Using the advanced MALDI-TOF MS technology to identify colonies grown on SBA/Mac agar facilitated this study to discover uncommon bacteria and newly emerging opportunistic pathogens that traditional biochemical assays, mostly utilized in prior research, could not identify. Our study identified a total of 107 bacterial isolates covering 46 species in 24 genera. Most isolates were identified as medically important and opportunistic pathogens, and the variation of bacterial species presented in currencies is comparable to previous studies (<xref rid="ref-76" ref-type="bibr">Phunpae et al., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="ref-71" ref-type="bibr">Ofoedu et al., 2021</xref>; <xref rid="ref-97" ref-type="bibr">Yar, 2020</xref>; <xref rid="ref-31" ref-type="bibr">Ejaz, Javeed &#x00026; Zubair, 2018</xref>; <xref rid="ref-36" ref-type="bibr">Gabriel, Coffey &#x00026; O&#x02019;Mahony, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr">Alemu, 2014</xref>). Despite the rarity of these uncommon bacteria infecting immunocompromised hosts, our comprehensively reviewed demonstrated that opportunistic and nosocomial infections have been recently documented.</p><p>Genus <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus</italic> was the most contaminated bacteria on cash samples that this study could identify. The eight species included one coagulase-positive <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> and seven coagulase-negative staphylococci (CoNS), with a distinction in frequency. Staphylococci are common skin and mucous membrane colonizers in humans, poultry, and other warm-blooded animals (<xref rid="ref-56" ref-type="bibr">Lee &#x00026; Yang, 2021</xref>). Despite coagulase-negative staphylococci (CoNS) being less prevalent in human pathogenesis compared to <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic>, its potential to cause infections in humans and animals under appropriate conditions has drawn greater scientific interest over the past decade (<xref rid="ref-93" ref-type="bibr">Von Eiff, Peters &#x00026; Heilmann, 2002</xref>). Numerous species of coagulase-negative staphylococci, including <italic toggle="yes">S. gallinarum</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">S. arlettae</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">S. chromogenes</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">S. xylosus</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">S. epidermidis</italic>, have been frequently isolated from the nares and skin of chickens. Our investigation was able to identify <italic toggle="yes">S. arlettae</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">S. xylosus</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">S. epidermidis</italic> from pork and chicken stores. Recent studies have demonstrated that CoNS can also produce staphylococcal enterotoxins (SEs) and could be a potential cause of food poisoning. Numerous virulence genes linked to pathogenesis, such as <italic toggle="yes">ica</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">nuc</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">ssp</italic>, which are typically present in the genomes of pathogenic staphylococci, are also identified in specific CoNS, including <italic toggle="yes">S. haemolyticus</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">S. saprophyticus</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">S. arlettae</italic> (<xref rid="ref-83" ref-type="bibr">Shimizu et al., 1992</xref>; <xref rid="ref-53" ref-type="bibr">Lavecchia et&#x000a0;al., 2019</xref>).</p><p>Furthermore, the potential role of CoNS in the transmission of antimicrobial resistance by serving as a reservoir for antimicrobial resistance genes has been increasingly documented (<xref rid="ref-70" ref-type="bibr">Nemeghaire et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="ref-6" ref-type="bibr">Archer &#x00026; Niemeyer, 1994</xref>). Staphylococci that were nearly entirely isolated, with the exception of <italic toggle="yes">S. epidermidis</italic>, demonstrated a high level of penicillin resistance. From the late 1960s to the present, over 80% of staphylococcal isolates acquired in both community and hospital settings were resistant to penicillin, a resistance that was mediated by the <italic toggle="yes">blaZ</italic> gene, which encodes <italic toggle="yes">&#x003b2;</italic>-lactamase/penicillinase (<xref rid="ref-59" ref-type="bibr">Lowy, 2003</xref>). Only <italic toggle="yes">S. haemolyticus</italic> exhibited a methicillin-resistant (MR) strain, while <italic toggle="yes">S. haemolyticus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">S. arlettae</italic> were multidrug-resistant strains (resistant to three or more antibiotic classes). This study was in line with the previous study, which could isolate MDR-<italic toggle="yes">S. heamolyticus</italic> from ready-to-eat (RTE) foods served in bars and restaurants (<xref rid="ref-22" ref-type="bibr">Chajecka-Wierzchowska et al., 2023</xref>). Despite the legal prohibitions, antimicrobial agents are still in use for prophylaxis or metaphylaxis in aquaculture and livestock production (<xref rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr">Collignon &#x00026; McEwen, 2019</xref>; <xref rid="ref-75" ref-type="bibr">Pepi &#x00026; Focardi, 2021</xref>). In recent years, there has been a significant increase in the number of reports on the occurrence of antibiotic-resistant CoNS in food (<xref rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr">Aslanta&#x0015f; &#x00026; Y&#x00131;ld&#x00131;r&#x00131;m, 2021</xref>; <xref rid="ref-85" ref-type="bibr">Silva et al., 2022</xref>). This strongly implies that the food chain production may represent a pathway for the transmission of antimicrobial resistance genes. Antimicrobial resistance genes in staphylococci are typically located on plasmids, transposons, or other mobile genetic elements (MGEs), facilitating horizontal gene transfer (<xref rid="ref-32" ref-type="bibr">El-Adawy et al., 2022</xref>).</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter</italic> was the second most prevalent bacterium on currency samples; twelve species of <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> and eleven <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter</italic> non-<italic toggle="yes">baumannii</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">Anb</italic>) were detected<italic toggle="yes">. Anb</italic> species are becoming more significant as opportunistic nosocomial pathogens for humans (<xref rid="ref-82" ref-type="bibr">Sheck et al., 2023</xref>; <xref rid="ref-96" ref-type="bibr">Wong et al., 2017</xref>). The identified strains of <italic toggle="yes">A. lactucae</italic> (formerly referred to as <italic toggle="yes">A. dijkshoorniae</italic>), <italic toggle="yes">A. pittii</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">A. seifertii</italic> belong to the <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter calcoaceticus-baumannii</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">Acb</italic>) complex (<xref rid="ref-82" ref-type="bibr">Sheck et al., 2023</xref>). While the phenotypes of the species within the <italic toggle="yes">Acb</italic> complex are nearly identical, they exhibit substantial differences in terms of their ecology, pathogenesis, epidemiology, and susceptibility to antibiotics (<xref rid="ref-69" ref-type="bibr">Nemec et al., 2011</xref>). Moreover, the isolated isolates of <italic toggle="yes">A. bereziniae</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">A. junii</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">A.&#x000a0;ursingii</italic> have been frequently reported in human infections (<xref rid="ref-82" ref-type="bibr">Sheck et al., 2023</xref>).</p><p>The presence of extensive antibiotic resistance phenotype in <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic> isolated from cash samples in this study, as well as from commercial food samples in prior research (<xref rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr">Al Atrouni, 2016</xref>; <xref rid="ref-60" ref-type="bibr">Lupo, Haenni &#x00026; Madec, 2018</xref>), indicated that environmental sources may contribute to the transmission of antibiotic-resistant bacteria to humans. <italic toggle="yes">A.&#x000a0;baumannii</italic> exhibited intrinsic resistance to numerous antibiotics and possessed a notable capacity to acquire resistance to all existing therapeutic agents, including carbapenems. This has established it among the ESKAPE pathogens (<italic toggle="yes">E. faecium</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">K. pneumoniae</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Enterobacter</italic> spp.) (<xref rid="ref-18" ref-type="bibr">Boucher et&#x000a0;al., 2009</xref>) and contributed to the critical position on the WHO&#x02019;s global priority list of antibiotic-resistant bacteria (<xref rid="ref-19" ref-type="bibr">Breijyeh, Jubeh &#x00026; Karaman, 2020</xref>). Nonetheless, most of the isolated <italic toggle="yes">Anb</italic> demonstrated susceptibility to the majority of the tested antibiotics, with the exception of certain species that exhibited resistance to ceftazidime. This aligns with earlier research that identified ceftazidime resistance in <italic toggle="yes">Anb</italic> isolates at a rate of 12.6% (<xref rid="ref-50" ref-type="bibr">Kittinger et al., 2017</xref>). Moreover, nearly all other gram-negative bacteria exhibited resistance to penicillins and third-generation cephalosporins. Resistance of <italic toggle="yes">Enterobacteriaceae</italic> to third-generation cephalosporins exceeds 10%, whereas resistance to carbapenems ranges from 2% to 7%. This is a result of the rapid dissemination of strains that produce extended-spectrum &#x003b2;-lactamases (ESBLs) (<xref rid="ref-8" ref-type="bibr">Baba et al., 2009</xref>).</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Macrococcus</italic> was another type of isolate that was prevalent in this investigation. The genus <italic toggle="yes">Macrococcus</italic> is closely related to the genus <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus</italic> (<xref rid="ref-8" ref-type="bibr">Baba et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="ref-65" ref-type="bibr">Mazhar et al., 2019</xref>). It demonstrated significant homology in phenotypic and biological traits, sharing characteristics with these oxidase-positive and novobiocin-resistant staphylococci (<xref rid="ref-64" ref-type="bibr">Ma&#x00161;la&#x00148;ov&#x000e1; et al., 2018</xref>). Members of <italic toggle="yes">Macrococcus</italic> are currently classified into twelve species (<xref rid="ref-64" ref-type="bibr">Ma&#x00161;la&#x00148;ov&#x000e1; et al., 2018</xref>), which are commonly isolated from animal skin (ponies, horses, cows, llamas, and dogs), as well as from dairy or meat products (<xref rid="ref-51" ref-type="bibr">Kloos et al., 1998</xref>; <xref rid="ref-63" ref-type="bibr">Mannerov&#x000e1; et al., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="ref-38" ref-type="bibr">Gobeli Brawand et al., 2017</xref>). Despite the almost all macrococci have yet to be documented in human clinical specimens, recent studies indicated high mortality rates in animals infected with Macrococci (<xref rid="ref-25" ref-type="bibr">Cotting et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="ref-38" ref-type="bibr">Gobeli Brawand et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="ref-58" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2018</xref>), suggesting a potential risk for human infections. <italic toggle="yes">Macrococcus caseolyticus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">M. canis</italic> were two isolated species in the present study. <italic toggle="yes">M. caseolyticus</italic> was the most prevalent species that was previously classified as <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus caseolyticus</italic> due to the high degree of similarity (<xref rid="ref-25" ref-type="bibr">Cotting et al., 2017</xref>). Recently, <italic toggle="yes">M. canis</italic> was described for the first time as isolated from a human skin infection (<xref rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr">Jost et al., 2021</xref>).</p><p>It is crucial to note that the adaptive acquisition of methicillin resistance genes in Macrococci genomes, such as <italic toggle="yes">mecABCD</italic> has been observed over the past decades (<xref rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr">Jost et al., 2021</xref>; <xref rid="ref-81" ref-type="bibr">Schwendener, Cotting &#x00026; Perreten, 2017</xref>; <xref rid="ref-39" ref-type="bibr">G&#x000f3;mez-Sanz et al., 2015</xref>). In contrast to classical <italic toggle="yes">mecA</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">mecC</italic>, which are predominantly associated with <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic>, the methicillin-resistant genes found in Macrococci are primarily associated with <italic toggle="yes">mecB</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">mecD</italic> (<xref rid="ref-99" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2022</xref>; <xref rid="ref-90" ref-type="bibr">Tsubakishita et&#x000a0;al., 2010</xref>). The <italic toggle="yes">mecB</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">mecD</italic> genes, being homologs of <italic toggle="yes">mecA</italic>, raise significant safety concerns because of the potential for these mobile elements to transfer to other commensal or pathogenic bacteria, such as <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> (<xref rid="ref-23" ref-type="bibr">Chanchaithong, Perreten &#x00026; Schwendener, 2019</xref>; <xref rid="ref-39" ref-type="bibr">G&#x000f3;mez-Sanz et al., 2015</xref>). Despite the fact that this investigation was unable to identify methicillin-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Macrococcus</italic> spp. in Thai currency samples, the isolation of a potential multidrug-resistant strain may have been the result of the acquisition of MDR mobile genetic elements (<xref rid="ref-99" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2022</xref>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Despite the advanced features of E-commerce technology, the use of currency as a universal medium for daily transactions remains indispensable. This study demonstrated that Thai currency, particularly Thai banknotes, was significantly contaminated with numerous highly pathogenic and newly emerging opportunistic microorganisms. It is crucial to note that the majority of these bacteria were resistant to antibiotic therapeutic medications, which raises concerns about the public health risks associated with the potential transmission of pathogens through contaminated cash. Furthermore, certain bacteria have significant drug-resistant genes within their genome, posing a risk of transferring these mobile genetic elements to other commensal or pathogenic bacteria. Consequently, our study indicates that increased focus is necessary on the surveillance and monitoring of bacterial contamination on currency, while also promoting the use of digital wallets to reduce exposure to contaminated materials, alongside enhancing education on maintaining proper personal hygiene practices.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="supplemental-information"><title>Supplemental Information</title><supplementary-material id="supp-1" position="float" content-type="local-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19465/supp-1</object-id><label>Supplemental Information 1</label><caption><title>Detail of sample collection and percentage of bacterial detection on Thai banknotes and coins from retail fresh meat stores</title></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-13-19465-s001.xlsx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="supp-2" position="float" content-type="local-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19465/supp-2</object-id><label>Supplemental Information 2</label><caption><title>Enumeration of bacterial colonies grown in tryptic soy agar (TSA) from banknotes and coins</title></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-13-19465-s002.xlsx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="supp-3" position="float" content-type="local-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19465/supp-3</object-id><label>Supplemental Information 3</label><caption><title>Bacteria were isolated and identified using the MALDI-TOF MS, and the analyzed score of each isolate was reported</title></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-13-19465-s003.xlsx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="supp-4" position="float" content-type="local-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19465/supp-4</object-id><label>Supplemental Information 4</label><caption><title>Description of bacteria previously reported for causing infection in various systems</title></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-13-19465-s004.xlsx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="supp-5" position="float" content-type="local-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19465/supp-5</object-id><label>Supplemental Information 5</label><caption><title>Results of antimicrobial susceptibility tests by using the Kirby-Bauer disc diffusion methods</title></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-13-19465-s005.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="additional-information"><title>Additional Information and Declarations</title><fn-group content-type="competing-interests"><title>Competing Interests</title><fn id="conflict-1" fn-type="COI-statement"><p>The authors declare there are no competing interests.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="author-contributions"><title>Author Contributions</title><fn id="contribution-1" fn-type="con"><p><xref rid="author-1" ref-type="contrib">Nattamon Niyomdecha</xref> conceived and designed the experiments, performed the experiments, analyzed the data, prepared figures and/or tables, authored or reviewed drafts of the article, and approved the final draft.</p></fn><fn id="contribution-2" fn-type="con"><p><xref rid="author-2" ref-type="contrib">Suwitchaya Sungvaraporn</xref> performed the experiments, analyzed the data, prepared figures and/or tables, authored or reviewed drafts of the article, and approved the final draft.</p></fn><fn id="contribution-3" fn-type="con"><p><xref rid="author-3" ref-type="contrib">Arisa Pinmuang</xref> performed the experiments, analyzed the data, prepared figures and/or tables, authored or reviewed drafts of the article, and approved the final draft.</p></fn><fn id="contribution-4" fn-type="con"><p><xref rid="author-4" ref-type="contrib">Narissara Mungkornkaew</xref> performed the experiments, analyzed the data, prepared figures and/or tables, and approved the final draft.</p></fn><fn id="contribution-5" fn-type="con"><p><xref rid="author-5" ref-type="contrib">Thanchira Saita</xref> performed the experiments, analyzed the data, prepared figures and/or tables, and approved the final draft.</p></fn><fn id="contribution-6" fn-type="con"><p><xref rid="author-6" ref-type="contrib">Waratchaya Rodraksa</xref> performed the experiments, analyzed the data, prepared figures and/or tables, and approved the final draft.</p></fn><fn id="contribution-7" fn-type="con"><p><xref rid="author-7" ref-type="contrib">Achiraya Phanitmas</xref> performed the experiments, analyzed the data, prepared figures and/or tables, and approved the final draft.</p></fn><fn id="contribution-8" fn-type="con"><p><xref rid="author-8" ref-type="contrib">Nattapong Yamasamit</xref> performed the experiments, analyzed the data, prepared figures and/or tables, authored or reviewed drafts of the article, and approved the final draft.</p></fn><fn id="contribution-9" fn-type="con"><p><xref rid="author-9" ref-type="contrib">Pirom Noisumdaeng</xref> conceived and designed the experiments, performed the experiments, analyzed the data, prepared figures and/or tables, authored or reviewed drafts of the article, project administration and Funding acquisition, and approved the final draft.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="other"><title>Data Availability</title><fn id="addinfo-1"><p>The following information was supplied regarding data availability:</p><p>The raw data are available in the <xref rid="supplemental-information" ref-type="sec">Supplementary Files</xref>.</p></fn></fn-group></sec><ref-list content-type="authoryear"><title>References</title><ref id="ref-1"><label>Abo-Zed, Yassin &#x00026; Phan (2020)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Abo-Zed</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yassin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Phan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter junii</italic> as a rare pathogen of urinary tract infection</article-title><source>Urology Case Reports</source><volume>32</volume><elocation-id>101209</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eucr.2020.101209</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32322533</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-2"><label>Agersew (2014)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Agersew</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Microbial contamination of currency notes and coins in circulation: a potential public health hazard</article-title><source>Biomedicine and Biotechnology</source><volume>2</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>46</fpage><lpage>53</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-3"><label>Al&#x000a0;Atrouni et&#x000a0;al. (2016)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Al&#x000a0;Atrouni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Joly-Guillou</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hamze</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kempf</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Reservoirs of non-baumannii Acinetobacter species</article-title><source>Frontiers in Microbiology</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>49</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2016.00049</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26870013</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-4"><label>Alemu (2014)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Alemu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Microbial contamination of currency notes and coins in circulation: a potential public health hazard</article-title><source>Biomedicine and Biotechnology</source><volume>2</volume><fpage>46</fpage><lpage>53</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-5"><label>Alkhatib et&#x000a0;al. (2017)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Alkhatib</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Younis</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alobaidi</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shaath</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>An unusual osteomyelitis caused by <italic toggle="yes">Moraxella osloensis</italic>: a case report</article-title><source>International Journal of Surgery Case Reports</source><volume>41</volume><fpage>146</fpage><lpage>149</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijscr.2017.10.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29078156</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-6"><label>Archer &#x00026; Niemeyer (1994)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Archer</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Niemeyer</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="1994">1994</year><article-title>Origin and evolution of DNA associated with resistance to methicillin in staphylococci</article-title><source>Trends in Microbiology</source><volume>2</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>343</fpage><lpage>347</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0966-842x(94)90608-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7850198</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-7"><label>Aslanta&#x0015f; &#x00026; Y&#x00131;ld&#x00131;r&#x00131;m (2021)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Aslanta&#x0015f;</surname><given-names>&#x000d6;</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Y&#x00131;ld&#x00131;r&#x00131;m</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year><article-title>Isolation of methicillin resistant (MR) Staphylococci from chicken meat samples</article-title><source>Harran University Journal of the Faculty of Veterinary Medicine</source><volume>10</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>126</fpage><lpage>131</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.31196/huvfd.958632</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-8"><label>Baba et&#x000a0;al. (2009)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Baba</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kuwahara-Arai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Uchiyama</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Takeuchi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hiramatsu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Complete genome sequence of <italic toggle="yes">Macrococcus caseolyticus</italic> strain JCSCS5402, (corrected) reflecting the ancestral genome of the human-pathogenic staphylococci</article-title><source>Journal of Bacteriology</source><volume>191</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1180</fpage><lpage>1190</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.01058-08</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19074389</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-9"><label>Bank&#x000a0;of Thailand (2024)</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>Bank&#x000a0;of Thailand</collab>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2024">2024</year><article-title>About BoT</article-title><uri xlink:href="https://www.bot.or.th/en/about-us.html">https://www.bot.or.th/en/about-us.html</uri><date-in-citation content-type="access-date" iso-8601-date="2024-10-14">14 October 2024</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-10"><label>Basavarajappa, Rao &#x00026; Suresh (2005)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Basavarajappa</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Suresh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>Study of bacterial, fungal, and parasitic contamination of currency notes in circulation</article-title><source>Indian Journal of Pathology &#x00026; Microbiology</source><volume>48</volume><fpage>278</fpage><lpage>279</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16758695</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-11"><label>Baykal et&#x000a0;al. (2022)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Baykal</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>&#x000c7;elik</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>&#x000dc;lger</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vezir</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>G&#x000fc;ng&#x000f6;r</surname><given-names>M&#x000d6;</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year><article-title>Clinical features, risk factors, and antimicrobial resistance of <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas putida</italic> isolates</article-title><source>Medicine</source><volume>101</volume><issue>48</issue><elocation-id>e32145</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000032145</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36482647</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-12"><label>Bello-L&#x000f3;pez et&#x000a0;al. (2024)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bello-L&#x000f3;pez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Escobedo-Mu&#x000f1;oz</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guerrero</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cruz-C&#x000f3;rdova</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Garza-Gonz&#x000e1;lez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hern&#x000e1;ndez-Castro</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zarain</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morf&#x000ed;n-Otero</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Volkow</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xicohtencatl-Cortes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cevallos</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2024">2024</year><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter pittii</italic>: the emergence of a hospital-acquired pathogen analyzed from the genomic perspective</article-title><source>Frontiers in Microbiology</source><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>1412775</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2024.1412775</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38989032</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-13"><label>Bentur, Dalzell &#x00026; Riordan (2007)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bentur</surname><given-names>HN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dalzell</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Riordan</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Central venous catheter infection with <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus pumilus</italic> in an immunocompetent child: a case report</article-title><source>Annals of Clinical Microbiology and Antimicrobials</source><volume>6</volume><fpage>12</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1476-0711-6-12</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17967173</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-14"><label>Bernard (2012)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bernard</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>The genus corynebacterium and other medically relevant coryneform-like bacteria</article-title><source>Journal of Clinical Microbiology</source><volume>50</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>3152</fpage><lpage>3158</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.00796-12</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22837327</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-15"><label>Blondeau et&#x000a0;al. (2021)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Blondeau</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Deneer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kanthan</surname></name>
<name><surname>Sanche</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Blondeau</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year><article-title>Isolation of <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus kloosii</italic> from an ankle wound of an elderly female patient in rural Saskatchewan, Canada: a case report</article-title><source>Annals of Clinical Case Reports</source><volume>6</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>2073</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-16"><label>Bocchi et&#x000a0;al. (2020)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bocchi</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cianni</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Perna</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vitiello</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Greco</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maccauro</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Perisano</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><article-title>A rare case of <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus megater</italic> ium soft tissues infection</article-title><source>Acta Bio-Medica: Atenei Parmensis</source><volume>91</volume><issue>14-S</issue><elocation-id>e2020013</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.23750/abm.v91i14-S.10849</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-17"><label>Boonchuay et&#x000a0;al. (2023)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Boonchuay</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sontigun</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wongtawan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fungwithaya</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2023">2023</year><article-title>Association of multilocus sequencing types and antimicrobial resistance profiles of methicillin-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Mammaliicoccus sciuri</italic> in animals in Southern Thailand</article-title><source>Veterinary World</source><volume>16</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>291</fpage><lpage>295</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14202/vetworld.2023.291-295</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37041994</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-18"><label>Boucher et&#x000a0;al. (2009)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Boucher</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Talbot</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Scheld</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Spellberg</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bartlett</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Bad bugs, no drugs: no ESKAPE! An update from the Infectious Diseases Society of America</article-title><source>Clinical Infectious Diseases</source><volume>48</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/595011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19035777</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-19"><label>Breijyeh, Jubeh &#x00026; Karaman (2020)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Breijyeh</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jubeh</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Karaman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><article-title>Resistance of gram-negative bacteria to current antibacterial agents and approaches to resolve it</article-title><source>Molecules (Basel, Switzerland)</source><volume>25</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1340</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules25061340</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32187986</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-20"><label>Brooke (2012)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brooke</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Stenotrophomonas maltophilia: an emerging global opportunistic pathogen</article-title><source>Clinical Microbiology Reviews</source><volume>25</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>2</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/CMR.00019-11</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22232370</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-21"><label>Calderaro &#x00026; Chezzi (2024)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Calderaro</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chezzi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2024">2024</year><article-title>MALDI-TOF MS: a reliable tool in the real life of the clinical microbiology laboratory</article-title><source>Microorganisms</source><volume>12</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>322</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/microorganisms12020322</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38399726</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-22"><label>Chaj&#x00119;cka-Wierzchowska et&#x000a0;al. (2023)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chaj&#x00119;cka-Wierzchowska</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gajewska</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zadernowska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Randazzo</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Caggia</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2023">2023</year><article-title>A comprehensive study on antibiotic resistance among coagulase-negative Staphylococci (CoNS) Strains isolated from ready-to-eat food served in bars and restaurants</article-title><source>Foods (Basel, Switzerland)</source><volume>12</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>514</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/foods12030514</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36766043</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-23"><label>Chanchaithong, Perreten &#x00026; Schwendener (2019)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chanchaithong</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Perreten</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schwendener</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>Macrococcus canis contains recombinogenic methicillin resistance elements and the mecB plasmid found in <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title><source>The Journal of Antimicrobial Chemotherapy</source><volume>74</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>2531</fpage><lpage>2536</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jac/dkz260</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31243455</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-24"><label>Collignon &#x00026; McEwen (2019)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Collignon</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McEwen</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>One health-its importance in helping to better control antimicrobial resistance</article-title><source>Tropical Medicine and Infectious Disease</source><volume>4</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>22</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/tropicalmed4010022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30700019</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-25"><label>Cotting et&#x000a0;al. (2017)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cotting</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Strauss</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rodriguez-Campos</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rostaher</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roosje</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Favrot</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Perreten</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Macrococcus canis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">M. caseolyticus</italic> in dogs: occurrence, genetic diversity and antibiotic resistance</article-title><source>Veterinary Dermatology</source><volume>28</volume><issue>6</issue><elocation-id>559&#x02013;e133</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/vde.12474</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28748533</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-26"><label>Czeszewska-Rosiak et&#x000a0;al. (2025)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Czeszewska-Rosiak</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Adamczyk</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ludwiczak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fija&#x00142;kowski</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fija&#x00142;kowski</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Twaruzek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Z&#x00142;och</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gabry&#x0015b;</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mi&#x0015b;ta</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tretyn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pomastowski</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2025">2025</year><article-title>Analysis of the efficacy of MALDI-TOF MS technology in identifying microorganisms in cancer patients and oncology hospital environment</article-title><source>Heliyon</source><volume>11</volume><issue>2</issue><elocation-id>e42015</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2025.e42015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39906802</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-27"><label>Dahal, Paul &#x00026; Gupta (2023)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dahal</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2023">2023</year><article-title>The multifaceted genus Acinetobacter: from infection to bioremediation</article-title><source>Journal of Applied Microbiology</source><volume>134</volume><issue>8</issue><elocation-id>lxad145</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jambio/lxad145</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37442632</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-28"><label>Daki&#x00107; et&#x000a0;al. (2005)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Daki&#x00107;</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vukovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Savi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shittu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jezek</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hauschild</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stepanovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>Isolation and molecular characterization of <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus sciuri</italic> in the hospital environment</article-title><source>Journal of Clinical Microbiology</source><volume>43</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>2782</fpage><lpage>2785</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.43.6.2782-2785.2005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15956397</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-29"><label>Dinakaran et&#x000a0;al. (2012)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dinakaran</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shankar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jayashree</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rathinavel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gunasekaran</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rajendhran</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Genome sequence of <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus arlettae</italic> strain CVD059, isolated from the blood of a cardiovascular disease patient</article-title><source>Journal of Bacteriology</source><volume>194</volume><issue>23</issue><fpage>6615</fpage><lpage>6616</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.01732-12</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23144377</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-30"><label>Dordet-Frisoni et&#x000a0;al. (2007)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dordet-Frisoni</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dorchies</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>De Araujo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Talon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Leroy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Genomic diversity in <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus xylosus</italic></article-title><source>Applied and Environmental Microbiology</source><volume>73</volume><issue>22</issue><fpage>7199</fpage><lpage>7209</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.01629-07</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17890333</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-31"><label>Ejaz, Javeed &#x00026; Zubair (2018)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ejaz</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Javeed</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zubair</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Bacterial contamination of Pakistani currency notes from hospital and community sources</article-title><source>Pakistan Journal of Medical Sciences</source><volume>34</volume><fpage>1225</fpage><lpage>1230</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30344581</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-32"><label>El-Adawy et&#x000a0;al. (2016)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>El-Adawy</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hotzel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Monecke</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hartung</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ehricht</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Neubauer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hafez</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Characterization of methicillin-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> isolated from healthy turkeys and broilers using DNA microarrays</article-title><source>Frontiers in Microbiology</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>2019</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2016.02019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28066346</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-33"><label>Eltwisy et&#x000a0;al. (2022)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Eltwisy</surname><given-names>HO</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Twisy</surname><given-names>HO</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hafez</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sayed</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>El-Mokhtar</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year><article-title>Clinical infections, antibiotic resistance, and pathogenesis of <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus haemolyticus</italic></article-title><source>Microorganisms</source><volume>10</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1130</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/microorganisms10061130</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35744647</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-34"><label>Fatahi-Bafghi (2021)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fatahi-Bafghi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year><article-title>Characterization of the Rothia spp. and their role in human clinical infections</article-title><source>Infection, Genetics and Evolution</source><volume>93</volume><elocation-id>104877</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.meegid.2021.104877</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-35"><label>Furlan &#x00026; Stehling (2023)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Furlan</surname><given-names>JPR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stehling</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2023">2023</year><article-title>Genomic insights into <italic toggle="yes">Pluralibacter gergoviae</italic> sheds light on emergence of a multidrug-resistant species circulating between clinical and environmental settings</article-title><source>Pathogens (Basel, Switzerland)</source><volume>12</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1335</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/pathogens12111335</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38003800</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-36"><label>Gabriel, Coffey &#x00026; O&#x02019;Mahony (2013)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gabriel</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Coffey</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>O&#x02019;Mahony</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Investigation into the prevalence, persistence and antibiotic resistance profiles of staphylococci isolated from euro currency</article-title><source>Journal of Applied Microbiology</source><volume>115</volume><fpage>565</fpage><lpage>571</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jam.12247</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23679680</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-37"><label>Glenn et&#x000a0;al. (2015)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Glenn</surname><given-names>LSS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Christelle</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Audrey</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Regalado</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Anna</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mary</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Teresita</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Bacteriological and parasitological assessment of currencies obtained in selected markets of Metro Manila</article-title><source>Asian Pacific Journal of Tropical Disease</source><volume>5</volume><fpage>468</fpage><lpage>470</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2222-1808(15)60817-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-38"><label>Gobeli&#x000a0;Brawand et&#x000a0;al. (2017)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gobeli&#x000a0;Brawand</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cotting</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>G&#x000f3;mez-Sanz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Collaud</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thomann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brodard</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rodriguez-Campos</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Strauss</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Perreten</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Macrococcus canis</italic> sp. nov. a skin bacterium associated with infections in dogs</article-title><source>International Journal of Systematic and Evolutionary Microbiology</source><volume>67</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>621</fpage><lpage>626</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/ijsem.0.001673</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27902286</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-39"><label>G&#x000f3;mez-Sanz et&#x000a0;al. (2015)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>G&#x000f3;mez-Sanz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schwendener</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thomann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gobeli&#x000a0;Brawand</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Perreten</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>First Staphylococcal cassette chromosome mec containing a mecB-carrying gene complex independent of transposon Tn6045 in a <italic toggle="yes">Macrococcus canis</italic> isolate from a canine infection</article-title><source>Antimicrobial Agents and Chemotherapy</source><volume>59</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>4577</fpage><lpage>4583</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.05064-14</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25987634</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-40"><label>Gosa (2015)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gosa</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Health risk associated with handling of paper currencies</article-title><source>International Journal of Food and Nutritional Science</source><volume>2</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15436/2377-0619.15.014</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-41"><label>Hoffmann et&#x000a0;al. (2005)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schmoldt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tr&#x000fc;lzsch</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stumpf</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bengsch</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Blankenstein</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Heesemann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roggenkamp</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year><article-title>Nosocomial urosepsis caused by <italic toggle="yes">Enterobacter kobei</italic> with aberrant phenotype</article-title><source>Diagnostic Microbiology and Infectious Disease</source><volume>53</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>143</fpage><lpage>147</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.diagmicrobio.2005.06.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16168611</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-42"><label>Howard et&#x000a0;al. (2012)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>O&#x02019;Donoghue</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Feeney</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sleator</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>: an emerging opportunistic pathogen</article-title><source>Virulence</source><volume>3</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>243</fpage><lpage>250</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4161/viru.19700</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22546906</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-43"><label>Huzefa et&#x000a0;al. (2022)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Huzefa</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vinayak</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nakeya</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Josue</surname><given-names>V-G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Samiullah</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Subramanya</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Adnan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gaurang</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year><article-title>Indolent course of <italic toggle="yes">mixta calida</italic> bacteremia mimicking decompensated heart failure</article-title><source>Chest</source><volume>162</volume><fpage>A160</fpage><lpage>A161</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chest.2022.08.115</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-44"><label>Institute&#x000a0;CLSI (2023)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>Institute&#x000a0;CLSI</collab>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2023">2023</year><source>Performance standards for antimicrobial susceptibility testing: 33rd edition</source><publisher-name>Clinical Laboratory Standards Institute</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Wayne</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-45"><label>Janda &#x00026; Abbott (2010)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Janda</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Abbott</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>The genus Aeromonas: taxonomy, pathogenicity, and infection</article-title><source>Clinical Microbiology Reviews</source><volume>23</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/CMR.00039-09</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20065325</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-46"><label>Jeyaraman et&#x000a0;al. (2022)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jeyaraman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Muthu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sarangan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jeyaraman</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Packkyarathinam</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Ochrobactrum anthropi</italic>&#x02014;an emerging opportunistic pathogen in musculoskeletal disorders&#x02014;a case report and review of literature</article-title><source>Journal of Orthopaedic Case Reports</source><volume>12</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.13107/jocr.2022.v12.i03.2730</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-47"><label>Ji et&#x000a0;al. (2021)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year><article-title>Development of a one-step multiplex PCR assay for differential detection of four species (<italic toggle="yes">Enterobacter cloacae</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Enterobacter hormaechei</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Enterobacter roggenkampii</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Enterobacter kobei</italic>) belonging to <italic toggle="yes">Enterobacter cloacae</italic> complex with clinical significance</article-title><source>Frontiers in Cellular and Infection Microbiology</source><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>677089</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fcimb.2021.677089</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34095000</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-48"><label>Jost et&#x000a0;al. (2021)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jost</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schwendener</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liassine</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Perreten</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year><article-title>Methicillin-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Macrococcus canis</italic> in a human wound</article-title><source>Infection, Genetics and Evolution</source><volume>96</volume><elocation-id>105125</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.meegid.2021.105125</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-49"><label>Kalita et&#x000a0;al. (2013)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kalita</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Palusi&#x00144;ska-Szysz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Turska-Szewczuk</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wdowiak-Wr&#x000f3;bel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Urbanik-Sypniewska</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Isolation of cultivable microorganisms from Polish notes and coins</article-title><source>Polish Journal of Microbiology</source><volume>62</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>281</fpage><lpage>286</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.33073/pjm-2013-036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24459833</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-50"><label>Kittinger et&#x000a0;al. (2017)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kittinger</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kirschner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lipp</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baumert</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mascher</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Farnleitner</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zarfel</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Antibiotic resistance of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter</italic> spp. isolates from the river Danube: susceptibility stays high</article-title><source>International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health</source><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>52</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph15010052</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29301193</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-51"><label>Kloos et&#x000a0;al. (1998)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kloos</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ballard</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>George</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Webster</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hubner</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ludwig</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schleifer</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fiedler</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schubert</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year><article-title>Delimiting the genus Staphylococcus through description of <italic toggle="yes">Macrococcus caseolyticus</italic> gen. nov., comb. nov. and <italic toggle="yes">Macrococcus equipercicus</italic> sp. nov., and <italic toggle="yes">Macrococcus bovicus</italic> sp. no. and <italic toggle="yes">Macrococcus carouselicus</italic> sp. nov</article-title><source>International Journal of Systematic Bacteriology</source><volume>48</volume><issue>Pt 3</issue><fpage>859</fpage><lpage>877</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/00207713-48-3-859</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9734040</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-52"><label>Kramer, Schwebke &#x00026; Kampf (2006)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schwebke</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kampf</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>How long do nosocomial pathogens persist on inanimate surfaces? A systematic review</article-title><source>BMC Infectious Diseases</source><volume>6</volume><fpage>130</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2334-6-130</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16914034</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-53"><label>Lavecchia et&#x000a0;al. (2019)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lavecchia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chiara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>De Virgilio</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Manzari</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Monno</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>De Carlo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pazzani</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Horner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pesole</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Placido</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus arlettae</italic> genomics: novel insights on candidate antibiotic resistance and virulence genes in an emerging opportunistic pathogen</article-title><source>Microorganisms</source><volume>7</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>580</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/microorganisms7110580</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31752379</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-54"><label>Lawal et&#x000a0;al. (2021)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lawal</surname><given-names>OU</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barata</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fraqueza</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Worning</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bartels</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goncalves</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Paix&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goncalves</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Toscano</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Empel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Urba&#x0015b;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Domi&#x000ec;nguez</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Westh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>De Lencastre</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Miragaia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus saprophyticus</italic> from clinical and environmental origins have distinct biofilm composition</article-title><source>Frontiers in Microbiology</source><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>663768</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2021.663768</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34163443</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-55"><label>Lee (2021)</label><element-citation publication-type="report"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year><source>MB352 general microbiology laboratory</source><institution>LibreText&#x02122;</institution><uri xlink:href="https://bio.libretexts.org/Courses/North_Carolina_State_University/MB352_General_Microbiology_Laboratory_2021_(Lee)/07%3A_Microbial_Metabolism/7.02%3A_Introduction_to_Biochemical_Tests_Part_II#:&#x000a0;:text=Oxidase%20positive%20bacteria%20change%20the,reagent%20from%20colorless%20to%20black">https://bio.libretexts.org/Courses/North_Carolina_State_University/MB352_General_Microbiology_Laboratory_2021_(Lee)/07%3A_Microbial_Metabolism/7.02%3A_Introduction_to_Biochemical_Tests_Part_II#:&#x000a0;:text=Oxidase%20positive%20bacteria%20change%20the,reagent%20from%20colorless%20to%20black</uri><date-in-citation content-type="access-date" iso-8601-date="2024-03-18">18 March 2024</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-56"><label>Lee &#x00026; Yang (2021)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year><article-title>Profiles of coagulase-positive and -negative staphylococci in retail pork: prevalence, antimicrobial resistance, enterotoxigenicity, and virulence factors</article-title><source>Animal Bioscience</source><volume>34</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>734</fpage><lpage>742</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5713/ajas.20.0660</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33705626</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-57"><label>Leung (2021)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>NHL</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year><article-title>Transmissibility and transmission of respiratory viruses</article-title><source>Nature Reviews Microbiology</source><volume>19</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>528</fpage><lpage>545</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41579-021-00535-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33753932</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-58"><label>Li et&#x000a0;al. (2018)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Emergence of pathogenic and multiple-antibiotic-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Macrococcus caseolyticus</italic> in commercial broiler chickens</article-title><source>Transboundary and Emerging Diseases</source><volume>65</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1605</fpage><lpage>1614</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tbed.12912</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29799666</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-59"><label>Lowy (2003)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lowy</surname><given-names>FD</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year><article-title>Antimicrobial resistance: the example of <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title><source>The Journal of Clinical Investigation</source><volume>111</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1265</fpage><lpage>1273</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI18535</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12727914</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-60"><label>Lupo, Haenni &#x00026; Madec (2018)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lupo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Haenni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Madec</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Antimicrobial resistance in Acinetobacter spp. and Pseudomonas spp</article-title><source>Microbiology Spectrum</source><volume>6</volume><issue>3</issue><elocation-id>ARBA-0007-2017</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/microbiolspec.ARBA-0007-2017</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-61"><label>Mackintosh &#x00026; Hoffman (1984)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mackintosh</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="1984">1984</year><article-title>An extended model for transfer of micro-organisms <italic toggle="yes">via</italic> the hands: differences between organisms and the effect of alcohol disinfection</article-title><source>The Journal of Hygiene</source><volume>92</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>345</fpage><lpage>355</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/s0022172400064561</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6429238</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-62"><label>Magiorakos et&#x000a0;al. (2012)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Magiorakos</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Srinivasan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carey</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carmeli</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Falagas</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Giske</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Harbarth</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hindler</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kahlmeter</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Olsson-Liljequist</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Paterson</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stelling</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Struelens</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vatopoulos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Monnet</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Multidrug-resistant, extensively drug-resistant and pandrug-resistant bacteria: an international expert proposal for interim standard definitions for acquired resistance</article-title><source>Clinical Microbiology and Infection</source><volume>18</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>268</fpage><lpage>281</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-0691.2011.03570.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21793988</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-63"><label>Mannerov&#x000e1; et&#x000a0;al. (2003)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mannerov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pant&#x0016f;&#x0010d;ek</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Do&#x00161;ka&#x00159;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>&#x00160;vec</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Snauwaert</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vancanneyt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Swings</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sedl&#x000e1;&#x0010d;ek</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Macrococcus brunensis</italic> sp. nov., <italic toggle="yes">Macrococcus hajekii</italic> sp. nov. and <italic toggle="yes">Macrococcus lamae</italic> sp. nov., from the skin of llamas</article-title><source>International Journal of Systematic and Evolutionary Microbiology</source><volume>53</volume><issue>Pt 5</issue><fpage>1647</fpage><lpage>1654</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/ijs.0.02683-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13130064</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-64"><label>Ma&#x00161;la&#x00148;ov&#x000e1; et&#x000a0;al. (2018)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ma&#x00161;la&#x00148;ov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wertheimer</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sedl&#x000e1;&#x0010d;ek</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>&#x00160;vec</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Indr&#x000e1;kov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kova&#x00159;ovic</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schumann</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Spr&#x000f6;er</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kr&#x000e1;lov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>&#x00160;edo</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kri&#x00161;tofov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vrbovsk&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>F&#x000fc;zik</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Petr&#x000e1;&#x00161;</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zdr&#x000e1;hal</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ru&#x0017e;i&#x0010d;kov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Do&#x00161;ka&#x00159;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pantu&#x0010d;ek</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Description and comparative Ggenomics of <italic toggle="yes">Macrococcus caseolyticus</italic> subsp. hominis subsp. nov., <italic toggle="yes">Macrococcus goetzii</italic> sp. nov., <italic toggle="yes">Macrococcus epidermidis</italic> sp. nov., and <italic toggle="yes">Macrococcus bohemicus</italic> sp. nov., Novel Macrococci from human clinical material with virulence potential and suspected uptake of foreign DNA by natural transformation</article-title><source>Frontiers in Microbiology</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>1178</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2018.01178</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29951040</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-65"><label>Mazhar et&#x000a0;al. (2019)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mazhar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Altermann</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McAuliffe</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>Draft genome sequences of the type strains of six Macrococcus species</article-title><source>Microbiology Resource Announcements</source><volume>8</volume><issue>19</issue><elocation-id>e00344&#x02013;19</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/MRA.00344-19</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31072882</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-66"><label>Meister et&#x000a0;al. (2023)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Meister</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kirchhoff</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Br&#x000fc;ggemann</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Todt</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Steinmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Steinmann</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2023">2023</year><article-title>Stability of pathogens on banknotes and coins: a narrative review</article-title><source>Journal of Medical Virology</source><volume>95</volume><issue>12</issue><elocation-id>e29312</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jmv.29312</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38100621</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-67"><label>Mohan et&#x000a0;al. (2017)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mohan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zaman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Anand</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Taneja</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Aerococcus viridans: a rare pathogen causing urinary tract infection</article-title><source>Journal of Clinical and Diagnostic Research</source><volume>11</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>DR01</fpage><lpage>DR03</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7860/JCDR/2017/23997.9229</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28273968</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-68"><label>Mueller &#x00026; Tainter (2023)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tainter</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2023">2023</year><article-title>Escherichia coli infection. [Updated 2023 Jul 13]</article-title><source>StatPearls</source><publisher-name>StatPearls Publishing</publisher-name><date-in-citation content-type="access-date" iso-8601-date="2024-01-00">2024 Jan</date-in-citation><publisher-loc>Treasure Island (FL)</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-69"><label>Nemec et&#x000a0;al. (2011)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nemec</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Krizova</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maixnerova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Van der Reijden</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Deschaght</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Passet</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vaneechoutte</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brisse</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dijkshoorn</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year><article-title>Genotypic and phenotypic characterization of the <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter calcoaceticus</italic>-<italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> complex with the proposal of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter pittii</italic> sp. nov. (formerly Acinetobacter genomic species 3) and <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter nosocomialis</italic> sp. nov. (formerly Acinetobacter genomic species 13TU)</article-title><source>Research in Microbiology</source><volume>162</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>393</fpage><lpage>404</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.resmic.2011.02.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21320596</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-70"><label>Nemeghaire et&#x000a0;al. (2014)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nemeghaire</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Argud&#x000ed;n</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fe&#x000df;ler</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hauschild</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Butaye</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>The ecological importance of the <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus sciuri</italic> species group as a reservoir for resistance and virulence genes</article-title><source>Veterinary Microbiology</source><volume>171</volume><issue>3&#x02013;4</issue><fpage>342</fpage><lpage>356</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetmic.2014.02.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24629775</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-71"><label>Ofoedu et&#x000a0;al. (2021)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ofoedu</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Iwouno</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Agunwah</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Obodoechi</surname><given-names>PZ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Okpala</surname><given-names>COR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Korzeniowska</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year><article-title>Bacterial contamination of Nigerian currency notes: a comparative analysis of different denominations recovered from local food vendors</article-title><source>PeerJ</source><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>e10795</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.10795</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33552745</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-72"><label>Olowo-Okere et&#x000a0;al. (2022)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Olowo-Okere</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>YKE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Olayinka</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mohammed</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nabti</surname><given-names>LZ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lupande-Mwenebitu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rolain</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Diene</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year><article-title>Genomic features of an isolate of <italic toggle="yes">Empedobacter falsenii</italic> harbouring a novel variant of metallo-<italic toggle="yes">&#x003b2;</italic>-lactamase, blaEBR-4 gene</article-title><source>Infection, Genetics and Evolution</source><volume>98</volume><elocation-id>105234</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.meegid.2022.105234</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-73"><label>Otto (2009)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Otto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Staphylococcus epidermidis-the &#x02018;accidental&#x02019; pathogen</article-title><source>Nature Reviews Microbiology</source><volume>7</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>555</fpage><lpage>567</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro2182</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19609257</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-74"><label>Patrick et&#x000a0;al. (2014)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Patrick</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mahon</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rounds</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cronquist</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wymore</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Booth</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lathrop</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bowen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Incidence of <italic toggle="yes">Cronobacter</italic> spp. infections, United States, 2003&#x02013;2009</article-title><source>Emerging Infectious Diseases</source><volume>20</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1520</fpage><lpage>1523</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3201/eid2009.140545</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25148394</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-75"><label>Pepi &#x00026; Focardi (2021)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pepi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Focardi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year><article-title>Antibiotic-resistant bacteria in aquaculture and climate change: a challenge for health in the mediterranean area</article-title><source>International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health</source><volume>18</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>5723</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph18115723</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34073520</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-76"><label>Phunpae et&#x000a0;al. (2018)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Phunpae</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sriruan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Udpuan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Buamongkol</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pawichai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ruangpayuk</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chairungwut</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Bacterial contamination and their tolerance in banknotes and coins surrounding the area of Chiang Mai University Hospital in Chiang Mai Province</article-title><source>Journal of Associated Medical Sciences</source><volume>51</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>179</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14456/jams.2018.23</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-77"><label>Prasai, Yami &#x00026; Joshi (2010)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Prasai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yami</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Microbial load on paper/polymer currency and coins</article-title><source>Nepal Journal of Science and Technology</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>105</fpage><lpage>109</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3126/njst.v9i0.3173</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-78"><label>Ranc et&#x000a0;al. (2018)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ranc</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dubourg</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fournier</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Raoult</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fenollar</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Delftia tsuruhatensis, an emergent opportunistic healthcare-associated pathogen</article-title><source>Emerging Infectious Diseases</source><volume>24</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>594</fpage><lpage>596</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3201/eid2403.160939</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29460754</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-79"><label>Salah, Parkin &#x00026; Allan (2021)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Salah</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Parkin</surname><given-names>IP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Allan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year><article-title>Copper as an antimicrobial agent: recent advances</article-title><source>RSC Advances</source><volume>11</volume><issue>30</issue><fpage>18179</fpage><lpage>18186</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/d1ra02149d</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35480904</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-80"><label>Schaarschmidt (1884)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schaarschmidt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="1884">1884</year><article-title>Upon the occurrence of bacteria and minute alg&#x000e6;on the surface of paper money</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>30</volume><fpage>360</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/030360a0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-81"><label>Schwendener, Cotting &#x00026; Perreten (2017)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schwendener</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cotting</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Perreten</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Novel methicillin resistance gene mecD in clinical <italic toggle="yes">Macrococcus caseolyticus</italic> strains from bovine and canine sources</article-title><source>Scientific Reports</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>43797</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep43797</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28272476</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-82"><label>Sheck et&#x000a0;al. (2023)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sheck</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Romanov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shapovalova</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shaidullina</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Martinovich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ivanchik</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mikotina</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Skleenova</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oloviannikov</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Azizov</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vityazeva</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lavrinenko</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kozlov</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Edelstein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2023">2023</year><article-title>Acinetobacter non-baumannii species: occurrence in infections in hospitalized patients, identification, and antibiotic Resistance</article-title><source>Antibiotics (Basel, Switzerland)</source><volume>12</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1301</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/antibiotics12081301</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37627721</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-83"><label>Shimizu et&#x000a0;al. (1992)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ozaki</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kawano</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Saitoh</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="1992">1992</year><article-title>Distribution of Staphylococcus species on animal skin</article-title><source>The Journal of Veterinary Medical Science</source><volume>54</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>355</fpage><lpage>357</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1292/jvms.54.355</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1606265</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-84"><label>Shwed et&#x000a0;al. (2021)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shwed</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Crosthwait</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weedmark</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hoover</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dussault</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year><article-title>Complete genome sequences of <italic toggle="yes">Priestia megaterium</italic> type and clinical strains feature complex plasmid arrays</article-title><source>Microbiology Resource Announcements</source><volume>10</volume><issue>27</issue><elocation-id>e0040321</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/MRA.00403-21</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34236233</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-85"><label>Silva et&#x000a0;al. (2022)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cani&#x000e7;a</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vieira-Pinto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Saraiva</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Capelo</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Igrejas</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Poeta</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year><article-title>Multidrug-resistant methicillin-resistant coagulase-negative Staphylococci in healthy poultry slaughtered for human consumption</article-title><source>Antibiotics</source><volume>11</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>365</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/antibiotics11030365</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35326828</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-86"><label>Sulaiman et&#x000a0;al. (2018)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sulaiman</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Miranda</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kerdahi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Identification of <italic toggle="yes">Lysinibacillus fusiformis</italic> isolated from cosmetic samples using MALDI-TOF MS and 16S rRNA sequencing methods</article-title><source>Journal of AOAC International</source><volume>101</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1757</fpage><lpage>1762</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5740/jaoacint.18-0092</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29895347</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-87"><label>Tena et&#x000a0;al. (2007)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tena</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Martinez-Torres</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Perez-Pomata</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>S&#x000e1;ez-Nieto</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rubio</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bisquert</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year><article-title>Cutaneous infection due to <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus pumilus</italic>: report of 3 cases</article-title><source>Clinical Infectious Diseases</source><volume>44</volume><issue>4</issue><elocation-id>e40&#x02013;e42</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/511077</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17243047</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-88"><label>Tong et&#x000a0;al. (2015)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eichenberger</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Holland</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fowler&#x000a0;Jr</surname><given-names>VG</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> infections: epidemiology, pathophysiology, clinical manifestations, and management</article-title><source>Clinical Microbiology Reviews</source><volume>28</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>603</fpage><lpage>661</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/CMR.00134-14</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26016486</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-89"><label>Towner (2009)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Towner</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Acinetobacter: an old friend, but a new enemy</article-title><source>Journal of Hospital Infection</source><volume>73</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>355</fpage><lpage>363</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhin.2009.03.032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19700220</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-90"><label>Tsubakishita et&#x000a0;al. (2010)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tsubakishita</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kuwahara-Arai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baba</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hiramatsu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>Staphylococcal cassette chromosome mec-like element in <italic toggle="yes">Macrococcus caseolyticus</italic></article-title><source>Antimicrobial Agents and Chemotherapy</source><volume>54</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1469</fpage><lpage>1475</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.00575-09</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20086147</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-91"><label>UNFPA Country Office&#x000a0;in Thailand (2021)</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>UNFPA Country Office&#x000a0;in Thailand</collab>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year><article-title>Comprehensive policy framework a life-cycle approach to ageing in Thailand</article-title><uri xlink:href="https://thailand.un.org/sites/default/files/2021-11/framework_on_ageing.pdf">https://thailand.un.org/sites/default/files/2021-11/framework_on_ageing.pdf</uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-92"><label>Vasconcellos et&#x000a0;al. (2022)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vasconcellos</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weng</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sutjita</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus hominis</italic> infective endocarditis presenting with embolic splenic and renal infarcts and spinal discitis</article-title><source>Case Reports in Infectious Diseases</source><volume>2022</volume><elocation-id>7183049</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2022/7183049</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35607353</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-93"><label>Von Eiff, Peters &#x00026; Heilmann (2002)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Von Eiff</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Heilmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year><article-title>Pathogenesis of infections due to coagulase-negative staphylococci</article-title><source>Lancet Infectious Diseases</source><volume>2</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>677</fpage><lpage>685</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s1473-3099(02)00438-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12409048</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-94"><label>Vriesekoop et&#x000a0;al. (2016)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vriesekoop</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oldaker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Besnard</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Leversha</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith-Arnold</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Worrall</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rufray</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Scannell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Dirty money: a matter of bacterial survival, adherence, and toxicity</article-title><source>Microorganisms</source><volume>4</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>42</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/microorganisms4040042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27886085</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-95"><label>Wang et&#x000a0;al. (2019)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hartman</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Westblade</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter radioresistens</italic> infection with bacteremia and pneumonia</article-title><source>IDCases</source><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>e00495</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.idcr.2019.e00495</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30906692</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-96"><label>Wong et&#x000a0;al. (2017)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bonomo</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pantapalangkoor</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Luna</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Spellberg</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Clinical and pathophysiological overview of Acinetobacter infections: a century of challenges</article-title><source>Clinical Microbiology Reviews</source><volume>30</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>409</fpage><lpage>447</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/CMR.00058-16</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27974412</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-97"><label>Yar (2020)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yar</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><article-title>Bacterial contaminants and antibiogram of Ghana paper currency notes in circulation and their associated health risks in asante-mampong, Ghana</article-title><source>International Journal of Microbiology</source><volume>2020</volume><elocation-id>8833757</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2020/8833757</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33101415</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-98"><label>Yoshino (2023)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yoshino</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2023">2023</year><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus casseliflavus</italic> infection: a review of clinical features and treatment</article-title><source>Infection and Drug Resistance</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>363</fpage><lpage>368</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/IDR.S398739</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36714353</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-99"><label>Zhang et&#x000a0;al. (2022)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Min</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year><article-title>Characteristics of population structure, antimicrobial resistance, virulence factors, and morphology of methicillin-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Macrococcus caseolyticus</italic> in global clades</article-title><source>BMC Microbiology</source><volume>22</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>266</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12866-022-02679-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36335318</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>