<!--

File produced by pipelineRunner package (for JATS 2 SCJATS with pipeline SCJATS)
At: 2025-05-21T06:07:11.564Z

Version        : 1.16.1
Last update    : 2024-08-27
Modified by    : dunnm

-->
<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Genome Biol Evol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Genome Biol Evol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">gbe</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Genome Biology and Evolution</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1759-6653</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>UK</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40333419</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12092913</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gbe/evaf083</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">evaf083</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection"><subject>AcademicSubjects/SCI01130</subject><subject>AcademicSubjects/SCI01140</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Genomics of Experimental Adaptive Radiation in the Cryptic Coloration of Feather Lice</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2493-089X</contrib-id><name><surname>Baldwin-Brown</surname><given-names>James G</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>School of Biological Sciences, University of Utah</institution>, <addr-line>Salt Lake City, UT 84112, USA</addr-line></aff><xref rid="evaf083-cor1" ref-type="corresp"/><xref rid="FN01" ref-type="author-notes"/><!--jgbaldwinbrown@gmail.com--></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5097-6026</contrib-id><name><surname>Villa</surname><given-names>Scott M</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>School of Biological Sciences, University of Utah</institution>, <addr-line>Salt Lake City, UT 84112, USA</addr-line></aff><xref rid="evaf083-cor2" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Waight</surname><given-names>Emiko</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>School of Biological Sciences, University of Utah</institution>, <addr-line>Salt Lake City, UT 84112, USA</addr-line></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>Kevin P</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Illinois Natural History Survey, Prairie Research Institute, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</institution>, <addr-line>Champaign, IL 61820, USA</addr-line></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bush</surname><given-names>Sarah E</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>School of Biological Sciences, University of Utah</institution>, <addr-line>Salt Lake City, UT 84112, USA</addr-line></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Clayton</surname><given-names>Dale H</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>School of Biological Sciences, University of Utah</institution>, <addr-line>Salt Lake City, UT 84112, USA</addr-line></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>Michael D</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>School of Biological Sciences, University of Utah</institution>, <addr-line>Salt Lake City, UT 84112, USA</addr-line></aff><xref rid="evaf083-cor1" ref-type="corresp"/><xref rid="FN01" ref-type="author-notes"/><!--mike.shapiro@utah.edu--></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name><role>Associate Editor</role></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="evaf083-cor2">Present address: Davidson College, Davidson, NC 28035, USA</corresp><corresp id="evaf083-cor1">Corresponding authors: E-mails: <email>jgbaldwinbrown@gmail.com</email>; <email>mike.shapiro@utah.edu</email></corresp><fn id="FN01" fn-type="COI-statement"><p>Conflict of Interest: The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2025-05-07"><day>07</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>07</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>17</volume><issue>5</issue><elocation-id>evaf083</elocation-id><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="corrected-typeset"><day>21</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2025. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of Society for Molecular Biology and Evolution.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="evaf083.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><p>A major challenge faced by living organisms is adaptation to novel environments. This process is poorly understood because monitoring genetic changes in natural populations is difficult. One way to simplify the task is to focus on organisms that can be studied in captivity under conditions that remain largely natural. Feather lice (Insecta, Phthiraptera, Ischnocera) are host-specific parasites of birds that live, feed, and breed solely on feathers. Birds defend themselves against lice, which damage feathers, by killing them with their beaks during bouts of preening. In response, feather lice have evolved background-matching cryptic coloration to help them avoid preening. We experimentally manipulated the color backgrounds of host-specific pigeon lice (<italic toggle="yes">Columbicola columbae</italic>) by confining them to different colored breeds of rock pigeon (<italic toggle="yes">Columba livia</italic>) over a period of 4 years (ca. 60 louse generations). Over the course of the experiment, we sampled lice from pigeons every 6 months for genomic resequencing and then calculated allele frequency differences and trajectories to identify putative genomic sites under selection. We documented many loci that changed in response to selection for color. Most loci putatively under selection were unshared among replicate populations of lice, indicating that independent adaptation of distinct lineages to the same novel environment resulted in similar phenotypes driven by different genotypes.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>genomics</kwd><kwd>pigeon louse</kwd><kwd>experimental evolution</kwd><kwd>adaptive radiation</kwd><kwd>body color</kwd><kwd>allele frequency trajectory</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>National Science Foundation</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/100000001</institution-id></institution-wrap>
</funding-source><award-id>DEB-0107947</award-id><award-id>DEB-1342600</award-id><award-id>DEB-1926738</award-id><award-id>DEB-1342604</award-id><award-id>DEB-1926919</award-id><award-id>DEB-1925487</award-id><award-id>DEB-2328118</award-id></award-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>National Institutes of Health</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/100000002</institution-id></institution-wrap>
</funding-source><award-id>R35GM131787</award-id><award-id>R01GM141422</award-id><award-id>1S10OD021644-01A1</award-id></award-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>University of Utah</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/100007747</institution-id></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group></funding-group><counts><page-count count="15"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><boxed-text id="evaf083-box1" position="float"><caption><title>Significance</title></caption><p>Adaptive radiations are a fundamental feature of evolution, yet the genetic architecture and repeatability of rapid diversification remains poorly understood. We found that rapid experimental evolution of parasitic louse pigmentation, an adaptive trait that protects against preening by pigeon hosts, entailed changes throughout the genome, and experimental replicates showed almost no overlap in the loci associated with pigment variation. This study demonstrates that complex genetic changes are associated with variation in a trait that is often relatively simple, and shows that repeated evolution of similar phenotypes may not be mirrored by parallel genetic changes, even among very closely related populations.</p></boxed-text><sec sec-type="intro" id="evaf083-s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Adaptive radiation occurs when members of a single lineage evolve different adaptive forms in response to divergent natural selection. Despite its fundamental importance to biodiversity, most of what we know about adaptive radiation is from historical inferences. Iconic examples include organisms that live on islands, such as Darwin's finches, Caribbean <italic toggle="yes">Anolis</italic> lizards, and Hawaiian silversword plants (<xref rid="evaf083-B50" ref-type="bibr">Schluter 2000</xref>). Islands are younger than mainland ecosystems, making it easier to reconstruct the history of colonization and speciation events for island radiations.</p><p>Some host-parasite interactions also provide tractable systems for the study of adaptive radiation because hosts are effectively living &#x0201c;islands&#x0201d; for host-specific parasites (<xref rid="evaf083-B901" ref-type="bibr">Kuris et al. 1980</xref>). Parasitic feather lice feed on the downy regions of bird feathers, which reduces host survival and mating success (<xref rid="evaf083-B12" ref-type="bibr">Clayton et al. 2016</xref>). Birds combat feather lice by removing them with their beaks during regular bouts of preening. Lice, in turn, have adaptations to avoid preening such as background-matching cryptic coloration: light colored species of birds host lighter species of lice, while dark colored species of birds host darker species of lice (<xref rid="evaf083-F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>; <xref rid="evaf083-B9" ref-type="bibr">Bush et al. 2010</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="evaf083-F1" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>Examples of cryptic coloration among feather lice in the genus columbicola. The Australian pied imperialpigeon, Ducula bicolor (a), is parasitized by C. wolffhuegeli (b); the rock pigeon, Columba livia (c), is parasitized by C. columbae (d); and the chestnut-quilled rock pigeon, Petrophassa rufipennis (e), is parasitized by C. masoni (f). Photos by: (a) JJ Harrison, Wikimedia Commons, CC BY-SA 4.0; (b) SEB; (c) <ext-link xlink:href="https://pxfuel.com/en/free-photo-qffys" ext-link-type="uri">pxfuel.com/en/free-photo-qffys</ext-link>; (d and f) SMV and J. Altuna; (e) Nimzee, <ext-link xlink:href="https://inaturalist.ala.org.au/photos/123753242" ext-link-type="uri">https://inaturalist.ala.org.au/photos/123753242</ext-link>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="evaf083f1" position="float"/></fig><p>Feather lice are permanent parasites that complete their entire life cycle on feathers (<xref rid="evaf083-B12" ref-type="bibr">Clayton et al. 2016</xref>). A previous study (<xref rid="evaf083-B10" ref-type="bibr">Bush et al. 2019</xref>) experimentally triggered diversification in the coloration of host-specific parasites that were confined to different colored host &#x0201c;islands.&#x0201d; The study employed an unusually tractable host-parasite system consisting of rock pigeons (<italic toggle="yes">Columba livia</italic>) and their feather lice (<italic toggle="yes">Columbicola columbae</italic>). Because the pigeon represents the entire habitat for its feather lice, populations of lice on captive birds live under conditions that are essentially natural. This fact, coupled with their short generation time (about 3.5 weeks from egg to adult, <xref rid="evaf083-B36" ref-type="bibr">Martin 1934</xref>), makes feather lice good candidates for experimental evolutionary studies of adaptive radiation. Feather lice experimentally transferred to different-colored rock pigeons experienced rapid and sustained divergence with populations of lice on white pigeons becoming lighter and populations of lice on black pigeons becoming darker over the course of the 48-month study (<xref rid="evaf083-F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). Thus, the study identified the pattern and tempo of change in color among louse populations subjected to different host-imposed selective regimes.</p><fig position="float" id="evaf083-F2" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><p>Experimental evolution of lice on hosts of varying color shows adaptation toward the host's color. a) Feather lice (Columbicola columbae) were transferred to 3 different rock pigeon color morphs: white (left), black (right), and gray (wild-type controls, middle). b) Half of the pigeons could preen normally, while the other half were fitted with poultry &#x0201c;bits&#x0201d; to impair their preening ability. (C&#x02013;D) Evolution of feather lice on different colored rock pigeons over a 4-year period (ca. 60 louse generations). The <italic toggle="yes">y</italic>-axis shows changes in the mean (&#x000b1;SE) luminosity (brightness) of lice on white and black rock pigeons, relative to lice on gray rock pigeon controls (set to zero). Different lower-case letters indicate statistically significant differences. c) On birds with normal preening, the relative luminosity of lice on white pigeons increased rapidly (LMM, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.0001); the relative luminosity of lice on black pigeons decreased, but more slowly (LMM, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.001). d) Relative luminosity did not change significantly over time on white or black pigeons with impaired preening (LMM, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x02265; 0.34 in both cases). (Panels B&#x02013;D redrawn from <xref rid="evaf083-B10" ref-type="bibr">Bush et al. 2019</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="evaf083f2" position="float"/></fig><p>A key goal in studies of adaptive evolution is to understand the number and location of genetic factors contributing to changes in adaptive phenotypic traits, such as color. Therefore, in addition to quantifying phenotypic change over time, we sampled lice from each of 4 replicate lineages for each color selection regime for genomic analyses. Lice vary in color from light to dark, consistent with differences in melanin content observed in other insects. The melanin production pathway is well described in insects, especially in <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic> spp. (<xref rid="evaf083-B55" ref-type="bibr">True 2003</xref>). Thus, the many studies of melanin color and patterning diversity in insects provide numerous a priori candidate genes for adaptive color shifts in lice. Changes in some of these genes can produce large color shifts alone or in combination with a modest number of other genes (<xref rid="evaf083-B64" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al. 2017</xref>). Here, we use an &#x0201c;evolve and resequence&#x0201d; approach in which we sequenced samples of lice from selected and nonselected lineages of lice over the course of a 48-month experiment. The evolve and resequence approach has been used to identify loci underlying diversity in viruses, microbes, and metazoans (e.g. <xref rid="evaf083-B61" ref-type="bibr">Wichman et al. 2000</xref>; <xref rid="evaf083-B59" ref-type="bibr">Van Laere et al. 2003</xref>; <xref rid="evaf083-B1" ref-type="bibr">Andersson and Hughes 2009</xref>; <xref rid="evaf083-B3" ref-type="bibr">Barrick et al. 2009</xref>; <xref rid="evaf083-B8" ref-type="bibr">Burke et al. 2010</xref>; <xref rid="evaf083-B24" ref-type="bibr">Johansson et al. 2010</xref>; <xref rid="evaf083-B43" ref-type="bibr">Paterson et al. 2010</xref>; <xref rid="evaf083-B48" ref-type="bibr">Rubin et al. 2010</xref>; <xref rid="evaf083-B58" ref-type="bibr">Turner et al. 2011</xref>).</p><p>The goal of the current study is to identify the tempo and mode of genomic change in populations of lice evolving cryptic coloration. Lice vary in color from light to dark, consistent with differences in melanin content observed in other insects. We investigate patterns of genome wide allele frequency changes in color selection lines of pigeon lice and evaluate whether putative targets of selection occur in regions that harbor melanin pathway genes. Prior studies provide some evidence that, when adaptation to a new optimal body color is repeated, the same genes are involved each time (<xref rid="evaf083-B7" ref-type="bibr">Biland&#x0017e;ija et al. 2012</xref>; <xref rid="evaf083-B49" ref-type="bibr">San Jose and Roulin 2018</xref>). In the current study, we test whether the same or different genomic regions are involved in replicate color selection lines and find that largely different sets of loci change in parallel experimental manipulations.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="evaf083-s2"><title>Results and Discussion</title><sec id="evaf083-s2.1"><title>Genomic Sequencing and Variant Calling</title><p>To study the genomic basis of adaptive diversification, pigeon lice were experimentally evolved on different color backgrounds by maintaining selection lines on pigeon breeds that differed in color (black, white, and ancestral gray). We investigated allelic variation among the experimentally evolved lice by whole-genome sequencing. We generated 4 replicate populations for each host treatment, then froze and sequenced a pool of individuals from each population at 6-month intervals. The only exception to this was the 36-month time point, at which lice were sequenced individually rather than pooled. We generated a total of 13.8 Tb of whole genome sequencing data. We sequenced 321 pools of lice, to an average of 84.9X genomic coverage, and 2151 individual lice to an average of 18.3X genomic coverage. We then aligned these reads to the <italic toggle="yes">C. columbae</italic> reference genome version 0.1 (<xref rid="evaf083-B2" ref-type="bibr">Baldwin-Brown et al. 2021</xref>). Of these reads, 11.6 Tb mapped successfully, producing 4.57 million polymorphic sites. The average sequenced population contained 38.0 individuals, with a standard deviation of 15.8. The full list of sample sizes is in <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">supplementary table S6, Supplementary Material</xref> online.</p><p>We used <italic toggle="yes">popvae</italic> (<xref rid="evaf083-B4" ref-type="bibr">Battey et al. 2021</xref>) to identify structure in the evolved populations based on individuals sequenced at the 36-month time point. Using a whole-genome assay of population structure, we found that individuals were most closely related to other individuals from the same population; i.e. lice among the 4 pigeons in a single aviary were each other's closest relatives (<xref rid="evaf083-F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>). Moreover, populations tended to cluster with the 5 other populations from the same replicate. This result is consistent with the design of the experiment, in which lice transferred to birds in each replicate set of 6 aviaries were drawn from the initial ancestral population 6 weeks after the previous replicate. A common problem with experimental evolution studies is that accidental migration between populations can confound the inference of selection because similarities driven by accidental gene flow produce the same signal of allele frequency similarity as the experimental treatments. In our study, physical isolation of lice between aviaries (see Materials and Methods), as well as the results from <italic toggle="yes">popvae</italic>, show that accidental migration seldom, if ever, occurred.</p><fig position="float" id="evaf083-F3" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><p>Population structure of experimental populations. Analysis with popvae shows that lice within a population&#x02014;i.e. lice on birds inhabiting the same aviary (same replicate, host color, and preening regime)&#x02014;are generally more genetically similar to one another, and that populations in the same replicate (<xref rid="evaf083-T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) are more closely related to one another, than they are to lice from the same treatment in other replicates. The lice here were all drawn from populations at the 36-month time point and individually sequenced.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="evaf083f3" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="evaf083-s2.2"><title>Many Genomic Regions Drive Adaptation</title><p>A previous study showed that color change in lice on pigeons of different plumage colors is rapid and substantial (<xref rid="evaf083-B10" ref-type="bibr">Bush et al. 2019</xref>). Nevertheless, the genomic signatures of color change in our experimental populations of lice are highly complex and do not include regions that harbor known melanin pathway genes. We searched for loci under selection by comparing allele frequencies between populations using p<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>ST</sub> (<xref rid="evaf083-B31" ref-type="bibr">Kronenberg 2015</xref>; <xref rid="evaf083-B16" ref-type="bibr">Domyan et al. 2016</xref>; <xref rid="evaf083-B20" ref-type="bibr">Garrison et al. 2021</xref>). We compared allele frequencies at 36 months among lice on normally preening white and black pigeons to the equivalent lice on normally preening gray pigeons (controls). We made this comparison in 2 ways. First, we took all lice on normally preening white or black pigeons and compared them to all lice on normally preening gray pigeons (i.e. lice from a given treatment were pooled across all 4 replicates). Second, we compared lice from normally preening white or black pigeons to lice on normally preening gray pigeons within each replicate. We included this replicate-by-replicate comparison not primarily to better account for background effects like laboratory selection and shared ancestry, but to detect putative selected loci that occurred in a subset of populations. In principle, lice on gray (control) pigeons as well as lice on white and black pigeons should be subject to the same &#x0201c;laboratory&#x0201d; conditions, but only lice on white and black pigeons with normal preening should experience selection for cryptic coloration. We found 126 total significantly differentiated loci in louse populations on preening pigeons and 227 in louse populations on preening-impaired pigeons. We controlled our contrasts to only identify selection associated with preening by ignoring all 23 putatively selected loci that were also identified as putatively selected in a matching comparison of lice on preening-impaired birds. In total, we found 103 putative selected sites across our populations (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">supplementary fig. S4, Supplementary Material</xref> online), 71 of which came from lice on white pigeons and 32 from lice on black pigeons (<xref rid="evaf083-F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>). Of the 71 sites from lice on white pigeons, 20 sites were shared with 2 of the 4 replicates, while only 3 sites from lice on black pigeons were shared by 2 replicates (<xref rid="evaf083-F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>). No sites were shared by 3 or 4 replicates in either the black or white treatments.</p><fig position="float" id="evaf083-F4" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 4.</label><caption><p>GWAS analyses identified different genomic regions under putative selection in different treatments and replicates. We used pFST at month 36 of the experiment to identify regions of the genome under selection. (a&#x02013;b) We contrasted an experimental population&#x02014;lice on a) white pigeons or b) black pigeons&#x02014;with lice from gray controls. The top 0.1% of sites (upper dotted line) are shown in red and are above the higher dotted line. FDR-corrected &#x02212;log(<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>) values are plotted, with the FDR-corrected significance threshold of <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.05 near the bottom of each plot (lower dotted line). We calculated pFST in each of the 4 replicates individually (R1&#x02013;R4), and in a combination of all replicates (all pFST). In addition, we used the Cochran-Mantel-Haenszel (CMH) test to identify sites with replicated allele frequency change across replicate populations of the same treatment. Purple bars represent regions where the normally-preening louse population is above the 0.01% statistical threshold, while the impaired-preening louse population on the same color birds is not above 0.01%.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="evaf083f4" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="evaf083-s2.3"><title>Different Loci are Selected in Different Replicates of the Same Treatment</title><p>A major question in evolutionary biology (and experimental evolution studies) is, how repeatable is evolutionary change? That is, if we could turn back the clock and let a population evolve in the same environment a second time, would the same alleles change to adapt to that environment? We tested this idea by comparing the putative selected loci in different replicates of the same selection treatment. This comparison tested whether the same loci were selected repeatedly as an adaptive response to identical selective regimes. Putatively selected sites in many pairs of replicates did overlap between 2 replicates more than expected by chance (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">supplementary table S2, Supplementary Material</xref> online); however, none of the putatively selected loci were shared by 3 or 4 replicates (<xref rid="evaf083-F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>). In fact, most of the putative selected sites are unique to just one replicate in a treatment.</p><fig position="float" id="evaf083-F5" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 5.</label><caption><p>Most selected sites are private to each treatment and replicate. This plot shows the average number of putative selected sites that are private (<italic toggle="yes">x</italic>-axis = 1) versus shared between replicates (<italic toggle="yes">x</italic>-axis &#x02265; 2). While a few putative selected sites were found in 2 replicates, none were shared by 3 or 4 replicates.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="evaf083f5" position="float"/></fig><p>A tempting explanation for the overall low overlap between putative selected sites across the different replicates is the balance of selection and genetic drift. Classical population genetic theory argues that selection dominates over drift when selection is strong (<italic toggle="yes">s</italic> &#x0003e; 1/<italic toggle="yes">Ne</italic>, where <italic toggle="yes">s</italic> is the selection coefficient and <italic toggle="yes">Ne</italic> is effective population size), but drift dominates when selection is weak (<italic toggle="yes">s</italic> &#x0003c; 1/<italic toggle="yes">Ne</italic>). If we imagine that all loci contribute to a trait equally, we should expect selection to be detectable when <italic toggle="yes">s</italic>/<italic toggle="yes">L</italic> &#x0003e; 1/<italic toggle="yes">Ne</italic>, where <italic toggle="yes">L</italic> is the number of loci contributing to the trait under selection. In this experiment, where sites are largely not replicated, <italic toggle="yes">Ne</italic> is relatively small, while <italic toggle="yes">L</italic> appears to be large. This is the case in other artificial selection experiments performed on complex traits, such as size, that involve macroscopic plants or animals that are difficult to maintain in large numbers (<xref rid="evaf083-B58" ref-type="bibr">Turner et al. 2011</xref>, <xref rid="evaf083-B41" ref-type="bibr">Orozco-Terwengel et al. 2012</xref>, <xref rid="evaf083-B57" ref-type="bibr">Turner and Miller 2012</xref>, <xref rid="evaf083-B39" ref-type="bibr">Mueller et al. 2018</xref>). Because prior studies have found color to be a relatively complex trait (<xref rid="evaf083-B55" ref-type="bibr">True 2003</xref>; but see other <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic> color mutants such as <italic toggle="yes">ebony</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">yellow</italic>, <xref rid="evaf083-B63" ref-type="bibr">Wittkopp et al. 2002</xref>), we expected to have a high L, and therefore a low rate of overlap, in color evolution. We find no difference between the color selection regimes either in terms of number of selected sites or the chance that selected sites overlap with each other between replicates (<xref rid="evaf083-F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>, <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">supplementary table S3, Supplementary Material</xref> online). This result, combined with the large number of loci identified as selected, suggests that the genetic control of color in feather lice is complex. Since most sites that change in allele frequency in response to selection are not shared among replicates, this suggests that chance factors, such as differences in allelic representation in the starting populations for each replicate, also influence the outcome of evolution in our experiment.</p><p>Another explanation for the large number of unshared putative selected sites could be a low <italic toggle="yes">s</italic> or a low <italic toggle="yes">Ne</italic>. Although we cannot directly measure the selection coefficient for color in these experiments, phenotypic evidence from the time course of phenotypic change suggests that selection was strong (<xref rid="evaf083-B10" ref-type="bibr">Bush et al. 2019</xref>). We do, however, have direct measurements of <italic toggle="yes">Ne</italic> both by counting lice removed from birds by CO<sub>2</sub> and by population genetics. These data indicate effective population sizes that range from dozens to hundreds (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">supplementary fig. S1, Supplementary Material</xref> online). The small <italic toggle="yes">Ne</italic> of some of our populations increases the potential role of genetic drift in the evolutionary outcome of the experiment.</p></sec><sec id="evaf083-s2.4"><title>Allele Frequency Trajectories Show Consistent, Ongoing Selection</title><p>We tracked allele frequencies across the experiment at all polymorphic loci. At each of our putative selected loci, we identified the most significant polymorphic site by p<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>ST</sub> and plotted its allele frequency over time (<xref rid="evaf083-F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>). We polarized these sites to measure the frequency of whichever allele is more common in experimental than control populations at 36 months. There is a clear upward trend in allele frequency in these selected alleles over time. This result both supports the inference that these sites are under selection and helps us to characterize the selection that is occurring. While some sites rapidly rise to fixation, most sites change allele frequency gradually over the course of the experiment, with most fixations occurring only toward the end of the experiment (<xref rid="evaf083-F7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>). This is consistent with our phenotypic results, which showed dramatic changes in color early in the experiment followed by continued modest changes later in the experiment. Note that the allele frequencies at these selected sites are biased to be high at 36 months because they were chosen due to their high allele frequency differences between selected and control populations. This causes the frequencies to regress to the mean (<xref rid="evaf083-B19" ref-type="bibr">Galton 1886</xref>) outside of the 36-month time point. We expect allele frequencies at other time points to be unbiased.</p><fig position="float" id="evaf083-F6" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 6.</label><caption><p>Selected alleles increased in frequency over time. We identified the most significant SNPs by pFST in each of our putatively selected loci (65 loci for white, 26 for black), then plotted allele frequencies over time. a) Allele frequency change in lice from populations exposed to preening-mediated selection (normally preening birds). The heavier red line is the average of all plotted allele frequencies. b) Allele frequency change at the same sites, but in lice not exposed to preening-mediated selection (impaired preening birds); these populations showed no change in allele frequencies over time. c) Allele frequency change at randomly chosen sites in louse populations on normally preening birds; these sites have more rare minor alleles than A or B, in keeping with a neutral site frequency spectrum outside of selected regions. d) Slopes of lines of best fit for the same trajectories in A&#x02013;C, with the midline representing the median, the box representing the interquartile range, and the whiskers representing 1.5 times the interquartile range. Different lower-case letters indicate statistically significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01, Tukey's HSD test).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="evaf083f6" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="evaf083-F7" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 7.</label><caption><p>Populations of lice experiencing selection by preening have higher rates of allelic fixation (solid lines) than populations of lice on impaired preening birds (dotted lines). Lines depict cumulative fixations in the polymorphic loci shown in <xref rid="evaf083-F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref> (65 loci for lice on white pigeons, 26 for lice on black pigeons). An allele was assumed to be fixed if its frequency reached 100% and remained at 100% for the remainder of the experiment. Fixations at the putatively selected sites in unselected populations of lice on impaired preening birds were exceedingly rare.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="evaf083f7" position="float"/></fig><p>Interestingly, the continued change in allele frequency among louse populations in our study suggests that selection was ongoing and additional adaptation would occur if the experiment were allowed to continue. Further, over macro-evolutionary time, lice in the genus <italic toggle="yes">Columbicola</italic> have adapted to different species of pigeons that vary dramatically in color. For example, the louse species <italic toggle="yes">C. wolffhuegeli</italic> parasitizes the pied-imperial pigeon (<italic toggle="yes">Ducula bicolor</italic>), a species with mostly white plumage. If we extrapolate the rate of phenotypic divergence between white-evolved and gray-evolved lice in our experiment (a difference of about 18 lumens over 4 years), it would take only 14 years to reach the level of phenotypic divergence between <italic toggle="yes">C. columbae</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">C. wolffhuegeli</italic> (65 lumens), which are species of lice that diverged millions of years ago (<xref rid="evaf083-B25" ref-type="bibr">Johnson et al. 2007</xref>, <xref rid="evaf083-B53" ref-type="bibr">Smith et al. 2011</xref>). Though this extrapolation is admittedly simplistic, it implies the potential for very rapid adaptation of feather lice to new hosts.</p></sec><sec id="evaf083-s2.5"><title>Differentiated Sites in Unselected Lines do not Show Evidence of Selection</title><p>To test for the possibility that the selection we detected was due to factors other than preening-mediated selection, we examined the putatively selected sites in louse populations on pigeons with impaired preening. Specifically, we plotted the frequencies of alleles in these same polymorphic sites from populations of lice on preening-impaired pigeons versus normally preening pigeons. We also plotted the frequency of alleles in randomly chosen polymorphic sites from populations of lice on normally preening pigeons. The differences between slopes in these trajectories (<xref rid="evaf083-F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>) are informative. First, the mean slope of selected sites of lice on normally preening populations is significantly higher than the near-zero slope of these same sites in the population of lice on preening-impaired pigeons (Tukey's HSD test; black <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 5.0 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup>, white <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 6.0 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;7</sup>), confirming that these sites are indeed under selection in the experimental populations. Second, the mean slope of the putative selected sites is significantly higher than the near-zero slope of randomly chosen sites from the same population (Tukey's HSD test; black <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0046, white <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 2.8 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup>). These results demonstrate that nonrandom allele frequency change is localized to the regions identified as selected.</p></sec><sec id="evaf083-s2.6"><title>Differentiated Sites Have High Starting Minor Allele Frequencies</title><p>Site frequency spectra inform us about the types of sites that are likely to respond to selection and likely to be detected as differentiated. The expectation for the site frequency spectrum under neutrality is a large proportion of low-frequency alleles (<xref rid="evaf083-B29" ref-type="bibr">Kimura 1983</xref>). Recent selective sweeps tend to remove polymorphism from the population while raising the allele frequency of the polymorphisms linked to the selected site, thus skewing the site frequency spectrum toward common alleles. The initial site frequency spectra of unselected sites contains a high proportion of low-frequency alleles, as expected in neutral evolution (<xref rid="evaf083-B29" ref-type="bibr">Kimura 1983</xref>) (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">supplementary table S4, Supplementary Material</xref> online). In contrast, the selected sites in our analyses have site frequency spectra highly skewed toward common variants in louse populations on both preening and preening-impaired pigeons.</p><p>Population genetic theory predicts that selection should dominate drift more easily in common variants because they contribute more to the heritability of the trait under selection (<xref rid="evaf083-B51" ref-type="bibr">Scoville et al. 2011</xref>). Thus, common variants are more likely to respond to selection in the first place. Theory also predicts that common variants change allele frequency more rapidly (<xref rid="evaf083-B65" ref-type="bibr">Zhao et al. 2013</xref>), suggesting that power to detect allele frequency change is highest in common variants. Overall, these theoretical expectations present 2 possibilities for why the allele frequencies at selected sites are skewed toward common alleles. It may be that common alleles are overrepresented at our selected sites because selection removed rare alleles, or it may be that common alleles are overrepresented because common alleles are more likely to respond strongly to selection in the first place. These 2 explanations are not mutually exclusive and are difficult to distinguish here.</p></sec><sec id="evaf083-s2.7"><title>Selection is Removing Trait-affecting Variation From the Population</title><p>A central question in evolutionary biology is whether adaptation removes useful variation from the population. That is, if a population is selected to change some trait, does it lose the variation needed to change that trait again in the future? To better understand this possibility, we characterized the loss of variance at selected sites. We scored variants as fixed or lost in a population if they reached and remained at an allele frequency of 100% or 0%, respectively (<xref rid="evaf083-F7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>). Allele fixation and loss can be caused by either genetic drift or selection; we found evidence for both. Our putative selected sites were more likely to fix in louse populations on normally preening pigeons than on preening-impaired pigeons. This difference in fixation probability reinforces the hypothesis that the genetic variants associated with the selected phenotype(s) were responding to preening-driven selection. Past experimental evolution studies in insects show that, when selection toward a phenotype is reversed, adaptation in the opposite direction occurs as quickly as initial adaptation, implying that the genetic variation needed to adapt was not lost in these populations, even in experimental evolution that ran for hundreds of generations (<xref rid="evaf083-B47" ref-type="bibr">Rose et al. 2004</xref>). In contrast, we found that approximately 10% of putative selected sites were fixed or lost by the end of our experiment. If this experiment continued, we would expect much of the original variation driving these populations to be lost, making reverse adaptation at these sites much slower than initial adaptation due to a loss of standing variation.</p></sec><sec id="evaf083-s2.8"><title>Many More Undetected Sites are Likely Under Selection</title><p>Our method for identifying selected loci focused on just one time point and identified only sites that were significantly differentiated from a control population. An alternative approach is to test for outlier allele frequency trajectories within each population. Selected alleles are expected to change frequency much more quickly than neutral alleles, so allele frequency trajectories with sharp slopes are likely to be the selected ones (cf. <xref rid="evaf083-B34" ref-type="bibr">Li and Barton 2023</xref>). This approach (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">supplementary figs. S2</xref> and <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3, Supplementary Material</xref> online) yields a very different set of selected sites. Although the evidence for selection in these sites is strong (the top 0.1% of 10-kb sliding window averaged allele frequency slopes), there are several reasons to be more skeptical that these sites are under selection.</p><p>Unlike p<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>ST</sub>, which takes sequencing coverage into account and assigns lower confidence to allele frequency differences at sites with low coverage, our slope calculation does not correct for sequencing coverage. Because of this, many slope outliers are at chromosome edges, where sequencing coverage is poor and allele frequency estimates are less accurate.</p><p>To account for this problem, we also estimated allele frequency slopes using a binomial GLM (see Materials and Methods). We do not believe this approach reliably identified loci under selection, as it found many more outliers than our other methods did. After combining all significant loci within 500&#x02005;bp of each other into a single putative locus, and before removing loci identified in the unbitted treatments, the p<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>ST</sub> approach found, on average, 22.3 putative selected loci per population. The binomial GLM method, on the other hand, found 1,910 putative selected loci per population (about 100X more). Because these putative selected loci are widespread throughout the genome and are much more numerous than those detected by other methods, we did not pursue the sites identified by the binomial GLM approach here. We suspect the high coverage in our resequencing data led to some locations appearing significant even with very small estimated slopes. That said, the binomial GLM approach did reduce slope outliers at the edges of chromosome. For this reason, we believe any outliers at the chromosome edges should be regarded with skepticism. Also, unlike with p<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>ST</sub>, it is hard to differentiate a slope outlier due to experimental preening conditions from a slope-outlier that is due to selection for a trait other than the one of interest. This limitation exists because we did not contrast the slope of alleles in louse populations on preening pigeons to slopes of louse populations on nonpreening pigeons. In summary, while some of the slope-outliers are likely examples of real selection, it is hard to distinguish these from false positives.</p></sec><sec id="evaf083-s2.9"><title>Genes in Differentiated Regions</title><p>To better understand the genes and cellular functions that may be involved in selection for color, and to see if adaptation for color in lice resembles color adaptation in other taxa, we characterized the genes in the regions under selection using the gene ontology (GO) tool <italic toggle="yes">goatools</italic> (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Data table D1, Supplementary Material</xref> online) (<xref rid="evaf083-B30" ref-type="bibr">Klopfenstein et al. 2018</xref>). We found 12 significantly enriched GO terms in our putatively selected sites (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">supplementary table S5, Supplementary Material</xref> online). Selected loci in dark-adapted lice were enriched for 2 cation transporter activity GO terms (cation-transporting ATPase complex, sodium:potassium-exchanging ATPase complex). Because such transporters are involved in many cell functions, they could plausibly be mechanistically connected to color, especially relating to pigment transport and deposition in the body. Melanin is known to have a high affinity for metal cations (<xref rid="evaf083-B45" ref-type="bibr">Potts and Au 1976</xref>; <xref rid="evaf083-B32" ref-type="bibr">Larsson and Tj&#x000e4;lve 1978</xref>) and cation transport is implicated in the development and function of melanosomes in vertebrates (<xref rid="evaf083-B5" ref-type="bibr">Bellono and Oancea 2014</xref>; <xref rid="evaf083-B62" ref-type="bibr">Wiriyasermkul et al. 2020</xref>). Still, the connection between cation transport and pigment variation in our louse populations is speculative.</p><p>While white-adapted lice showed enrichment for several GO categories, most were connected to nervous system function and olfaction. Our selection regimes did not specifically target olfaction traits, but melanin and the neurotransmitter components associated with olfaction use some of the same precursor molecules (<xref rid="evaf083-B21" ref-type="bibr">Gelis et al. 2016</xref>; <xref rid="evaf083-B44" ref-type="bibr">Pavan and Dalpiaz 2017</xref>). One might imagine these neurotransmitter precursors are under selection in our populations not because of their role in olfaction, but because they also affect color. However, we see no evidence for genes directly related to these molecules in our enrichment set. There are connections between nervous system function and pigment deposition, notably the role of pigment dispersing factor in the regulation of circadian rhythm (<xref rid="evaf083-B42" ref-type="bibr">Park and Hall 1998</xref>; <xref rid="evaf083-B37" ref-type="bibr">Matsushima et al. 2004</xref>). The product of one gene in a significantly differentiated genomic region in lice adapted to white birds, <italic toggle="yes">Pdx</italic>, was shown to have protein-protein interactions with pigment dispersing factor in the <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic> protein interaction map (DpiM; <xref rid="evaf083-B22" ref-type="bibr">Guruharsha et al 2011</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="evaf083-s2.10"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Adaptation of parasites to novel hosts, either due to a host-switching event or evolution of a host population, is an opportunity for adaptive radiation. We sequenced the genomes of pigeon lice subjected to artificial host switches to characterize the genetic underpinnings of an experimental adaptive radiation. Our results indicate that one trait under selection, louse body color, appears to be genetically complex with numerous contributing loci. We also found that the same loci were rarely involved in replicate lineages of lice exposed to very similar conditions. We used allele frequency trajectories at selected sites to show that adaptation is rapid and selection persisted for the duration of the 48-month experiment (ca. 60 louse generations). We also found that selection causes the loss of some genetic variation, which may make phenotypic reversion more difficult and may reduce the fitness of these lice if they were to encounter gray hosts in the future.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="evaf083-s3"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="evaf083-s3.1"><title>Animal Housing and Husbandry Design</title><p>We used lice from the experimental evolution study of <xref rid="evaf083-B10" ref-type="bibr">Bush et al. (2019)</xref>, the design of which is briefly summarized here. Prior to the start of the study, any resident &#x0201c;background&#x0201d; lice were eradicated by housing 96 captive pigeons under low humidity conditions (&#x0003c;25% relative ambient humidity) for &#x02265; 10 weeks. This method kills lice and their eggs, while avoiding residues from insecticides (<xref rid="evaf083-B23" ref-type="bibr">Harbison et al. 2008</xref>). Next, hundreds of lice were collected from wild caught feral pigeons. Random subsets of 25 lice were transferred to each of 96 captive pigeons housed in 24 aviaries (4 birds per aviary; aviary dimensions: 1.8&#x02005;m &#x000d7; 1.5&#x02005;m &#x000d7; 1.0&#x02005;m). When lice were transferred to birds in the experiment, the relative humidity was increased to 35% to 60%, providing sufficient humidity for feather lice to survive and reproduce on the birds (<xref rid="evaf083-B40" ref-type="bibr">Nelson and Murray 1971</xref>).</p><p>The captive pigeons consisted of 32 white birds, 32 black birds, and 32 &#x0201c;gray&#x0201d; birds (ancestral &#x0201c;blue-bar&#x0201d; phenotype, controls) (<xref rid="evaf083-F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2a</xref>). Preening, which is a pigeon's major defense against ectoparasites (<xref rid="evaf083-B13" ref-type="bibr">Clayton et al. 2005</xref>), was impaired using harmless poultry &#x0201c;bits,&#x0201d; which are C-shaped pieces of plastic inserted between the upper and lower mandibles of a bird's beak (<xref rid="evaf083-F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2b</xref>). Bits have no apparent side effects, and they do not impair the ability of birds to feed (<xref rid="evaf083-B14" ref-type="bibr">Clayton and Tompkins 1995</xref>). Preening was impaired in half of the birds, chosen at random, with all birds in the same aviary assigned to the same preening treatment.</p><p>Each aviary housed 2 male and 2 female birds of a given color and preening treatment (<xref rid="evaf083-T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The inclusion of 4 birds per aviary kept birds socially active and helped to ensure that birds did not preen their lice to extinction, which can occur on isolated birds that double their preening rates out of apparent boredom (<xref rid="evaf083-B60" ref-type="bibr">Waller et al. 2024</xref>). The <italic toggle="yes">Columbicola columbae</italic> lice used in our experiment are so specialized for life on feathers that they seldom, if ever, venture onto the host's skin, or away from the host's body. <italic toggle="yes">C. columbae</italic> requires direct contact between feathers to move between birds (<xref rid="evaf083-B14" ref-type="bibr">Clayton and Tompkins 1995</xref>). Since contact was common among birds in each aviary, the lice in each aviary were considered members of a single population. Lice were not able to move between birds in different aviaries. <italic toggle="yes">C. columbae</italic> are also known to move between birds by phoretic hitchhiking on hippoboscid flies (<xref rid="evaf083-B23" ref-type="bibr">Harbison et al. 2008</xref>); however, such flies were not present on any of the birds in our experiment.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="evaf083-T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Distribution of birds among 24 aviaries in the experimental evolution study (<xref rid="evaf083-B10" ref-type="bibr">Bush et al. 2019</xref>)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</th><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">White pigeons</th><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Gray pigeons</th><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Black pigeons</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aviaries</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Birds per aviary</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total birds</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aviaries</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Birds per aviary</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total birds</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aviaries</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Birds per aviary</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total birds</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal preening</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Impaired preening</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn1"><p>Each aviary held 2 male and 2 female pigeons of the indicated color and preening treatment. Thus, there are 4 replicates in this experiment; each replicate consists of 6 populations of lice that include 1 population of lice from each color and preening treatment.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>In summary, this experimental design included 4 replicates, each with 6 aviaries containing infested hosts of 3 colors and 2 preening treatments (<xref rid="evaf083-T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The 24 birds in each replicate were randomly seeded with lice from an infested captive population at the same time (as described above); however, the start dates of the 6 different replicates were staggered by approximately 6 weeks to allow time for the time-consuming activities associated with phenotypic and genomic sampling, described next.</p></sec><sec id="evaf083-s3.2"><title>Phenotyping and Genomic Sampling</title><p>At 6-month intervals throughout the 48-month experiment, we removed random samples of lice from each population (<xref rid="evaf083-B10" ref-type="bibr">Bush et al. 2019</xref>). Lice were removed by exposing birds&#x02019; feathers to CO<sub>2</sub>, which anesthetizes the lice. After exposure to CO<sub>2</sub> the feathers of each bird were ruffled over a gridded sheet of paper on a tray to collect the anesthetized lice. The total number of lice removed from the 4 birds in an aviary was used to estimate louse population size. Up to 50 lice per population were chosen randomly from the grid, digitally photographed for phenotyping, then preserved at &#x02212;80 &#x000b0;C for genomic DNA extraction and sequencing. The remaining lice from the population were placed back on the birds. When fewer than 100 lice were recovered across the 4 birds in an aviary, only half of the louse population was chosen (randomly) for photographing and preservation. Thus, the number of preserved lice from each population ranged between a low of 5 and a high of 50.</p><p>For downstream analyses, we calculated the harmonic mean of census count for all time points for a population as a proxy for the effective population size (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">supplementary fig. S1, Supplementary Material</xref> online). We used the harmonic mean to approximate the effective population size because it accounts for the effect of bottlenecks in the population size over time (<xref rid="evaf083-B27" ref-type="bibr">Karlin 1968</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="evaf083-s3.3"><title>Isolation of DNA</title><p>For collection timepoints at months 6, 12, 18, 24, 30, 42, and 48, we pooled samples from each louse population for DNA extraction, library preparation, and sequencing (3 colors, 2 preening conditions, and 4 replicates at 6 timepoints for a total of 144 sample pools). We also sampled and pooled 50 lice from infested wild caught feral pigeons each time a replicate was started (i.e. a time-matched sample of the ancestral population for each of the 4 replicates). Thus, we had a grand total of 148 pooled samples. We chose one time point, 36 months, for more intensive genomic analyses. This time point was chosen for 2 reasons: (1) phenotypic divergence had clearly occurred by that time, and (2) one of the populations (replicate 4 on white birds) began to decline in size at this time point. We sequenced lice individually at this time point to have the option to test for individual haplotypes that might be associated with regions under selection.</p><p>DNA from both pooled and individual samples was isolated by grinding with the TissueLyser LT (Qiagen) followed by DNA extraction with the Qiagen DNEasy Extraction Kit (Qiagen). Several modifications were made to the manufacturer's protocol to extract DNA most effectively from the tough, chitinous lice. First, we ground the lice using seven 1-min TissueLyser cycles at the maximum frequency, then visually inspected the samples to confirm breakage of the cuticle. Second, we incubated tissue in lysis solution for between 6 h and overnight. Third, for individually sequenced lice, we eluted DNA in 50&#x02005;&#x003bc;L of elution buffer EB warmed to 65 &#x000b0;C, then eluted again in a second 50-&#x003bc;L aliquot to maximize yield.</p></sec><sec id="evaf083-s3.4"><title>Genomic DNA Sequencing</title><p>Libraries were constructed using high molecular weight DNA (1 to 20&#x02005;ng) with the Nextera DNA Flex Library Prep kit (Illumina, Inc., San Diego, cat#20025520) and an average insert size of 450&#x02005;bp. PCR-amplified libraries were quantified on an Agilent Technologies 2200 TapeStation using a D1000 ScreenTape assay (cat# 5067-5582 and 5067-5583); the molarity of adapter-modified molecules was defined by quantitative PCR using the Kapa Biosystems Kapa Library Quant Kit (cat#KK4824). Libraries were normalized and pooled in preparation for Illumina sequencing with an Illumina Novaseq 6000 by the University of Utah High-Throughput Genomics Shared Resource. All sequencing runs produced 150-bp paired-end reads.</p></sec><sec id="evaf083-s3.5"><title>Variant Calling</title><p>We used <italic toggle="yes">BWA</italic> (<xref rid="evaf083-B33" ref-type="bibr">Li and Durbin 2009</xref>) for alignment of our data to the <italic toggle="yes">Columbicola columbae</italic> draft genome assembly (<xref rid="evaf083-B2" ref-type="bibr">Baldwin-Brown et al. 2021</xref>) and <italic toggle="yes">Sentieon</italic> (<xref rid="evaf083-B28" ref-type="bibr">Kendig et al. 2019</xref>; Sentieon, Inc., San Jose, CA), a commercial software package with a faster reimplementation of the polymorphism calling algorithm used by <italic toggle="yes">GATK</italic> (<xref rid="evaf083-B38" ref-type="bibr">McKenna et al. 2010</xref>), for variant calling. Using BWA and <italic toggle="yes">Sentieon</italic>, we generated gVCF files for each of the 148 pooled samples and each of the sequenced individuals from the 36-month timepoint. The gVCF files from individuals were then aggregated using a custom script to build VCF files for each population. This script is available as part of the <italic toggle="yes">VCFStats</italic> package (<ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/jgbaldwinbrown/vcfstats" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/jgbaldwinbrown/vcfstats</ext-link>).</p><p>For most analyses, we combined variant data from all the individuals within each 36-month sample to simulate pooled data and allow direct comparisons with the pooled data from other time points. To use the individual sequencing data in these grand analyses, we wrote a custom program that calculated allele counts from the VCFs representing the individual samples, using the genotype at each SNP for each individual to produce allele counts analogous to those available from pooled sequencing in all other populations. This script is also available as part of <italic toggle="yes">VCFStats</italic>. Briefly, for each population, this script counts the 2 alleles at each locus for each individual, then generates a new VCF file with one column for each population. For example, in a 3-individual population with genotypes at a single locus of GA, GG, and GA, the column representing the allele counts in the final VCF file would have a count of 4 Gs and 2 As. These re-formatted data were then combined into an experiment-wide VCF that also included the pooled populations.</p><p>For analysis of allele frequencies with <italic toggle="yes">PoolSeq</italic> (<xref rid="evaf083-B54" ref-type="bibr">Taus et al. 2017</xref>) and our custom code, we converted VCF files into synchronized files using the custom script <italic toggle="yes">vcf2sync.py</italic>, also included in <italic toggle="yes">VCFStats</italic>. This conversion takes allele counts directly from a VCF file, identifies the reference and highest-frequency alternative allele for each locus, and generates a sync file containing allele counts for all biallelic SNPs.</p></sec><sec id="evaf083-s3.6"><title>Population Structure</title><p>We used <italic toggle="yes">popvae</italic> to identify population structure across the experiment. A full description of this software is available in <xref rid="evaf083-B4" ref-type="bibr">Battey et al. (2021)</xref>; it is summarized here. Typical dimension reduction analysis for the purpose of clustering individuals into related populations are principal component analysis (PCA), UMAP, or t-SNE. PCA is the most venerable of these approaches and has the advantage of simplicity, but when the relationship between individuals is complex, often 2 principal components are not enough to distinguish subpopulations accurately, making plotting difficult and causing the variance explained to be split between many PCs. On the other hand, UMAP and t-SNE retain more of the variance in the data in their first 2 dimensions, but they do not preserve global geometry, making the distances between points in the dimension-reduced space meaningful, but not the points&#x02019; positions. The <italic toggle="yes">popvae</italic> software attempts to solve these problems by producing a reduced-dimension space where the positions of points in space are still meaningful, and as much of the variance in the dataset as possible is maintained. The <italic toggle="yes">popvae</italic> program works through a variational autoencoder, which is a type of neural net-based machine learning in which there are 2 neural nets&#x02014;one that reduces the data down to a small-dimensional space known as the latent space, and another that uses the latent space to reconstruct the original data. The <italic toggle="yes">popvae</italic> software uses the positions of data points in latent space as its dimension-reduced, plottable data that accurately represents the relationship between data points.</p><p>We applied <italic toggle="yes">popvae</italic> to a VCF file containing SNPs from our dataset with a minor allele frequency &#x02265;10% and a coverage &#x0003e;10X in at least 1 sample. To avoid the problem of correlation between sites due to linkage, we wrote a custom script (<italic toggle="yes">space_vcf</italic> in <italic toggle="yes">vcfstats</italic>) that retains only SNPs spaced greater than a minimum distance (here, 10&#x02005;kb) from each other.</p></sec><sec id="evaf083-s3.7"><title>Linkage Disequilibrium</title><p>We calculated reduction in linkage disequilibrium (LD) a priori based on the number of generations from the start of the experiment according to the classical equation:</p><p>where <italic toggle="yes">D</italic> is linkage disequilibrium, <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> is the number of generations, and <italic toggle="yes">c</italic> is the recombination rate (<xref rid="evaf083-B52" ref-type="bibr">Slatkin 2008</xref>). Because most phenotypic change occurred early in the experiment, we expect the LD subsequent to major allele frequency change to have decayed approximately as many generations as the experiment ran. We further calculated the distance at which decay reduced LD to a given fraction of its initial value as:</p><disp-formula id="UM0001">
<mml:math id="mml-disp1" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:math>
</disp-formula><p>where <italic toggle="yes">d</italic> is the distance producing the given recombination rate and <italic toggle="yes">C</italic> is the chromosome size (assuming 1 recombination event per chromosome, per generation).</p></sec><sec id="evaf083-s3.8"><title>Tests for Selection</title><p>We performed 2 tests for selection, both by testing for allele frequency differences between populations. We first used the Cochran-Mantel-Haenszel test (<xref rid="evaf083-B15" ref-type="bibr">Cochran 1954</xref>; <xref rid="evaf083-B35" ref-type="bibr">Mantel and Haenszel 1959</xref>) to compare different selection treatments at the 36-month timepoint. We also used the p<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>ST</sub> test (<xref rid="evaf083-B31" ref-type="bibr">Kronenberg 2015</xref>; <xref rid="evaf083-B16" ref-type="bibr">Domyan et al. 2016</xref>; <xref rid="evaf083-B20" ref-type="bibr">Garrison et al. 2021</xref>) to compare these same treatments, and to compare allele frequencies within a single replicate (<ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/vcflib" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/vcflib</ext-link>). A full description of p<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>ST</sub> is available in <xref rid="evaf083-B31" ref-type="bibr">Kronenberg (2015)</xref>; it is summarized here and discussed in greater detail in the <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">supplementary Supplementary Material</xref>s. Traditional <italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>ST</sub> statistics can produce false positive signals of differentiation at loci with low sequencing coverage due to inaccurate measurement of allele frequency. p<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>ST</sub> accounts for this problem using a maximum likelihood approach such that only highly differentiated sites with good coverage are identified as significantly divergent between populations. In more detail, p<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>ST</sub> identifies differentiated sites through a likelihood ratio contrasting the likelihood that allele frequency of the target population (AFT) is drawn from the same distribution as the background population (AFB) against the likelihood that AFT is drawn from a different distribution than AFB. The allelic counts in this model come from the counts of sequencing reads representing the 2 alleles at the locus of interest. Crucially, the 2 contrasted likelihoods are determined taking into account the likelihood of genotyping errors, thus avoiding the problem faced by traditional <italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>ST</sub> statistics <inline-formula><mml:math id="mml-inline1" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p><p>We generated 10-kb sliding window <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-values from the <italic toggle="yes">CMH</italic> and p<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>ST</sub> tests using the Fisher method (<xref rid="evaf083-B18" ref-type="bibr">Fisher 1928</xref>). We chose this window size conservatively because recombination should yield haplotypes that are, on average, approximately 377&#x02005;kb long after 48 generations (the 36-month time point is approximately 45 generations in this experiment) (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">supplementary table S1, Supplementary Material</xref> online, and see &#x0201c;Linkage Disequilibrium&#x0201d; in Materials and Methods). All sliding window analyses were performed with a step size of 50&#x02005;kb. All <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-values were corrected by Benjamini-Hochberg FDR (<xref rid="evaf083-B6" ref-type="bibr">Benjamini and Hochberg 1995</xref>). We identified genome-wide effective population size (<italic toggle="yes">N<sub>e</sub></italic>) using the method &#x0201c;P.planII&#x0201d; in <italic toggle="yes">PoolSeq</italic>'s <italic toggle="yes">estimateNe</italic> function (<xref rid="evaf083-B54" ref-type="bibr">Taus et al. 2017</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="evaf083-s3.9"><title>Other Statistics</title><p>We compared allele frequency slopes between populations of lice in different treatments with Tukey's Honest Significant Difference test (<xref rid="evaf083-B56" ref-type="bibr">Tukey 1949</xref>). We used Fisher's Exact test (<xref rid="evaf083-B17" ref-type="bibr">Fisher 1922</xref>) to compare the rate of pairwise overlaps of putatively selected genomic regions for louse populations among the 4 replicates. For example, the 4 values in the contingency table in a comparison of 2 treatments were: (i) total significant sites in treatment 1; (ii) total pairwise overlapped significant sites between any 2 replicates in treatment 1; (iii) total significant sites in treatment 2; (iv) total pairwise overlapped significant sites between any 2 replicates in treatment 2.</p></sec><sec id="evaf083-s3.10"><title>Tests of Overlap</title><p>We used a permutation approach to identify overlap between genomic regions identified as significant by p<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>ST</sub> in different replicates of the experiment. We permuted the position, but not size, of each significant region in each dataset, then counted the proportion of permuted sets with more overlap than that of the empirical data. This was our <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value for overlap. We used 2,000 permutations for each comparison. The custom tool for permuting these intervals, <italic toggle="yes">Permuvals</italic>, is available at <ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/jgbaldwinbrown/permuvals" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/jgbaldwinbrown/permuvals</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="evaf083-s3.11"><title>Allele Frequency Trajectory Calculations</title><p>We used the custom tool <italic toggle="yes">tsplot</italic> (<ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/jgbaldwinbrown/tsplot" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/jgbaldwinbrown/tsplot</ext-link>) to calculate and plot allele frequency trajectories over the course of the experiment. We used this same tool to calculate lines of best fit and slopes for all trajectories using the formula allele frequency &#x0223c; time. We calculated slopes twice&#x02014;once with a simple line of best fit on allele frequencies, and once with a binomial generalized linear model (GLM) that avoids accidental false positives in low-coverage genome regions. In its default mode, the <italic toggle="yes">tsplot</italic> tool uses the <italic toggle="yes">regression</italic> package (<ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/sajari/regression" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/sajari/regression</ext-link>) for fitting lines of best fit according to the formula &#x0201c;frequency &#x0223c; generation&#x0201d; and then does all other calculations, including identifying the selected allele for polarizing plots, collecting alleles from matching sequencing runs for time series generation, identifying the time interval of greatest allele frequency change, and instantaneous slope calculation.</p><p>In its alternate mode, <italic toggle="yes">tsplot</italic> acts the same except for the method of fitting allele frequency slopes. In this mode, <italic toggle="yes">tsplot</italic> fits a binomial GLM using the <italic toggle="yes">glm</italic> function in R (<xref rid="evaf083-B46" ref-type="bibr">R Core Team 2025</xref>). Here, the tracked allele is coded as a set of &#x0201c;1&#x0201d; values and the alternative allele is coded as a set of &#x0201c;0&#x0201d; values, one for each read indicating the allele. Then, the model is fit according to the formula &#x0201c;allele &#x0223c; generation&#x0201d; and the &#x0201c;logit&#x0201d; link function. Finally, we take the coefficient associated with the &#x0201c;generation&#x0201d; predictor variable as the allele frequency slope and the <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value associated with the effect of generation on allele frequency as our final indicator of a slope larger than expected by chance. Altogether, this method and the simple line of best fit should produce similar allele frequency slope estimates. However, unlike the simple line of best fit, the <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value associated with the binomial GLM should scale with the amount of evidence (coverage) at the locus.</p></sec><sec id="evaf083-s3.12"><title>GO Enrichment</title><p>We used the default settings of <italic toggle="yes">goatools</italic> (<xref rid="evaf083-B30" ref-type="bibr">Klopfenstein et al. 2018</xref>) to identify enrichment in gene functional categories under peaks of differentiation between populations of lice on birds of different color and preening treatments. GO term associations with genes were drawn directly from the <italic toggle="yes">Columbicola columbae</italic> genome annotation (<xref rid="evaf083-B2" ref-type="bibr">Baldwin-Brown et al. 2021</xref>). All GO terms originate from InterProScan (<xref rid="evaf083-B26" ref-type="bibr">Jones et al. 2014</xref>), and were derived by running InterProScan on the transcripts identified by MAKER (<xref rid="evaf083-B11" ref-type="bibr">Cantarel et al. 2008</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="evaf083-s3.13"><title>Functional Characterization of Polymorphisms</title><p>We used <italic toggle="yes">snpdat</italic> (<xref rid="evaf083-B902" ref-type="bibr">Doran and Creevey 2013</xref>) to characterize SNPs as synonymous, nonsynonymous, or untranslated. We used the genome annotation and the filtered polymorphisms described above to identify the set of putative selected, nonsynonymous SNPs.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="sup1" position="float" content-type="local-data"><label>evaf083_Supplementary_Data</label><media xlink:href="evaf083_supplementary_data.zip"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="ack1"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Andr&#x000e9; Watson for his help maintaining the louse populations, collecting lice, and physical measurement of lice; and Anna Vickrey for assistance in optimizing DNA extractions.</p></ack><sec id="evaf083-s4"><title>Supplementary Material</title><p>
<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary material</xref> is available at <italic toggle="yes">Genome Biology and Evolution</italic> online.</p></sec><sec id="evaf083-s5"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was supported by the National Science Foundation (DEB-0107947 to DHC; DEB-1342600 to DHC, SEB and MDS; DEB-1926738 to DHC and SEB; and DEB-1342604, DEB-1926919, DEB-1925487, DEB-2328118 to KPJ); and the National Institutes of Health (R35GM131787 to MDS). We also thank Nitin Phadnis for his advice and acknowledge the National Institutes of Health grant R01GM141422. The support and resources from the Center for High Performance Computing at the University of Utah are gratefully acknowledged. The computational resources used were partially funded by the National Institutes of Health Shared Instrumentation Grant 1S10OD021644-01A1.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="evaf083-s7"><title>Data Availability</title><p>Sequence data are available through NCBI SRA (BioProject PRJNA1038774). All analysis scripts are available through GitHub at <ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/jgbaldwinbrown/jgbutils" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/jgbaldwinbrown/jgbutils</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="evaf083-s8"><title>Ethics Statement</title><p>All procedures involving vertebrates were approved by the University of Utah Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee, protocol #14-06010.</p></sec><ref-list id="ref1"><title>Literature Cited</title><ref id="evaf083-B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Andersson</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>DI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hughes</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>D</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Gene amplification and adaptive evolution in bacteria</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Genet</source>. <year>2009</year>:<volume>43</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>167</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>195</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-genet-102108-134805</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19686082</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Baldwin-Brown</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Villa</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vickrey</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>AI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Johnson</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>KP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bush</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>SE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Clayton</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>DH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shapiro</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>MD</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The assembled and annotated genome of the pigeon louse <italic toggle="yes">Columbicola columbae</italic>, a model ectoparasite</article-title>. <source>G3</source>. <year>2021</year>:<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>jkab009</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/g3journal/jkab009</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33604673</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Barrick</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yu</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>DS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yoon</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>SH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jeong</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Oh</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>TK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schneider</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lenski</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>RE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JF</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Genome evolution and adaptation in a long-term experiment with <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2009</year>:<volume>461</volume>:<fpage>1243</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1247</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature08480</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19838166</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Battey</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Coffing</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>GC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kern</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>AD</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Visualizing population structure with variational autoencoders</article-title>. <source>G3</source>. <year>2021</year>:<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>jkaa036</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/g3journal/jkaa036</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33561250</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Bellono</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>NW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Oancea</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>EV</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Ion transport in pigmentation</article-title>. <source>Arch Biochem Biophys</source>. <year>2014</year>:<volume>563</volume>:<fpage>35</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>41</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.abb.2014.06.020</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25034214</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Benjamini</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hochberg</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Controlling the false discovery date: a practical and powerful approach to multiple testing</article-title>. <source>J R Stat Soc Ser B Methodol</source>. <year>1995</year>:<volume>57</volume>:<fpage>289</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>300</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.2517-6161.1995.tb02031.x</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Biland&#x0017e;ija</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>&#x00106;etkovi&#x00107;</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jeffery</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>WR</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Evolution of albinism in cave planthoppers by a convergent defect in the first step of melanin biosynthesis</article-title>. <source>Evol Dev</source>. <year>2012</year>:<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>196</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>203</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1525-142X.2012.00535.x</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23017027</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Burke</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>MK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dunham</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shahrestani</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thornton</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>KR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rose</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Long</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>AD</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Genome-wide analysis of a long-term evolution experiment with <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic></article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2010</year>:<volume>467</volume>:<fpage>587</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>590</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature09352</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20844486</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Bush</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>SE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reed</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Clayton</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>DH</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Evolution of cryptic coloration in ectoparasites</article-title>. <source>Am Nat</source>. <year>2010</year>:<volume>176</volume>:<fpage>529</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>535</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/656269</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20722554</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Bush</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>SE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Villa</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Altuna</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Johnson</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>KP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shapiro</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>MD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Clayton</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>DH</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Host defense triggers rapid adaptive radiation in experimentally evolving parasites</article-title>. <source>Evol Lett</source>. <year>2019</year>:<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>120</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>128</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/evl3.104</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31007943</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Cantarel</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>BL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Korf</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Robb</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>SMC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Parra</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ross</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moore</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Holt</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>S&#x000e1;nchez Alvarado</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yandell</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>MAKER: an easy-to-use annotation pipeline designed for emerging model organism genomes</article-title>. <source>Genome Res</source>. <year>2008</year>:<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>188</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>196</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.6743907</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18025269</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Clayton</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>DH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bush</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>SE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>KP</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <source>Coevolution of life on hosts: integrating ecology and history</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL, USA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>; <year>2016</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Clayton</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>DH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moyer</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>BR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bush</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>SE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jones</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>TG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gardiner</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>DW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rhodes</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>BB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Goller</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>F</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Adaptive significance of avian beak morphology for ectoparasite control</article-title>. <source>Proc Roy Soc B Biol Sci</source>. <year>2005</year>:<volume>272</volume>:<fpage>811</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>817</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rspb.2004.3036</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Clayton</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>DH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tompkins</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>DM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Comparative effects of mites and lice on the reproductive success of rock doves (<italic toggle="yes">Columba livia</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Parasitology</source>. <year>1995</year>:<volume>110</volume>:<fpage>195</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>206</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0031182000063964</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7885738</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Cochran</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>WG</given-names></string-name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Some methods for strengthening the common &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup> tests</article-title>. <source>Biometrics</source>. <year>1954</year>:<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>417</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>451</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/3001616</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Domyan</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>ET</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kronenberg</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Infante</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>CR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vickrey</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>AI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stringham</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bruders</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guernsey</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>MW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Park</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Payne</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Beckstead</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>RB</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Molecular shifts in limb identity underlie development of feathered feet in two domestic avian species. Bronner, ME, editor</article-title>. <source>eLife</source>. <year>2016</year>:<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>e12115</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12115</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26977633</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B902"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>Doran AG, Creevey CJ</collab>
</person-group>. <article-title>Snpdat: easy and rapid annotation of results from de novo snp discovery projects for model and non-model organisms</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinformatics.</source> &#x000a0;<year>2013</year>:<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>45</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-14-45</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23390980</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Fisher</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>
</person-group>. <article-title>On the interpretation of &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup> from contingency tables, and the calculation of P</article-title>. <source>J R Stat Soc</source>. <year>1922</year>;<volume>85</volume>:<fpage>87</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2340521</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Fisher</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>
</person-group>. <source>Statistical methods for research workers</source>. <publisher-loc>Edinburgh, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oliver and Boyd</publisher-name>; <year>1928</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Galton</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Regression towards mediocrity in hereditary stature</article-title>. <source>J Anthropol Inst Great Br Irel</source>. <year>1886</year>:<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>246</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>263</lpage>. doi: doi<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2841583</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Garrison</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kronenberg</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>ZN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dawson</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>ET</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pedersen</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>BS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Prins</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>P.</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<year>2021</year>. Vcflib and tools for processing the VCF variant call format. BioRxiv .445151. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2021.05.21.445151</pub-id>, <year>23 May 2021</year>, preprint: not peer reviewed.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Gelis</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jovancevic</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Veitinger</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mandal</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Arndt</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>H-D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Neuhaus</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>EM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hatt</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>H</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Functional characterization of the odorant receptor 51E2 in human melanocytes</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> &#x000a0;<year>2016</year>:<volume>291</volume>(<issue>34</issue>):<fpage>17772</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>17786</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M116.734517</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27226631</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Guruharsha</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>KG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rual</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhai</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mintseris</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vaidya</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vaidya</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Beekman</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wong</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rhee</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>DY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cenaj</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>A protein Complex network of <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila melanogaster</italic></article-title>. <source>Cell</source>. <year>2011</year>:<volume>147</volume>:<fpage>690</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>703</lpage>. doi: doi<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2011.08.047</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22036573</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Harbison</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>CW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bush</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>SE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Malenke</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Clayton</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>DH</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Comparative transmission dynamics of competing parasite species</article-title>. <source>Ecology</source>. <year>2008</year>:<volume>89</volume>:<fpage>3186</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3194</lpage>. doi: doi<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1890/07-1745.1</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31766819</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Johansson</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pettersson</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Siegel</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>PB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carlborg</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>O</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Genome-wide effects of long-term divergent selection</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source>. <year>2010</year>:<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>e1001188</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1001188</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21079680</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Johnson</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>KP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reed</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>DL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hammond Parker</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Clayton</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>DH</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Phylogenetic analysis of nuclear and mitochondrial genes supports species groups for <italic toggle="yes">Columbicola</italic> (Insecta: <italic toggle="yes">phthiraptera</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Mol Phylo Evo</source>. <year>2007</year>:<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>506</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>518</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ympev.2007.07.005</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Jones</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Binns</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chang</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>H-Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fraser</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McAnulla</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McWilliam</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Maslen</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mitchell</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nuka</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>InterProScan 5: genome-scale protein function classification</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>. <year>2014</year>:<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>1236</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1240</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu031</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24451626</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Karlin</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Rates of approach to homozygosity for finite stochastic models with variable population size</article-title>. <source>Am Nat.</source> &#x000a0;<year>1968</year>:<volume>102</volume>:<fpage>443</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>455</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/282557</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Kendig</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>KI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baheti</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bockol</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Drucker</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>TM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hart</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>SN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Heldenbrand</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hernaez</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hudson</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kalmbach</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>MT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Klee</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>EW</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Sentieon DNASeq variant calling workflow demonstrates strong computational performance and accuracy</article-title>. <source>Front Genet</source>. <year>2019</year>:<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>736</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fgene.2019.00736</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31481971</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Kimura</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>
</person-group>. <source>The neutral theory of molecular evolution</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>; <year>1983</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Klopfenstein</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>DV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pedersen</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>BS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ram&#x000ed;rez</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Warwick Vesztrocy</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Naldi</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mungall</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yunes</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Botvinnik</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weigel</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>GOATOOLS: a python library for gene ontology analyses</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep</source>. <year>2018</year>:<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>10872</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-28948-z</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30022098</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Kronenberg</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>ZN</given-names></string-name>
</person-group>. <source>Genotype-phenotype association using high throughput sequencing data. PhD thesis</source>. <publisher-loc>Salt Lake City, UT, USA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Department of Human Genetics, University of Utah</publisher-name>; <year>2015</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B901"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>Kuris AM, Blaustein AR, Alio JJ</collab>
</person-group>. <article-title>Hosts as Islands</article-title>. <source>Am Nat.</source> &#x000a0;<year>1980</year>:<volume>116</volume>:<fpage>570</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>586</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/283647</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Larsson</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tj&#x000e4;lve</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>H</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Studies on the melanin-affinity of metal ions</article-title>. <source>Acta Physiol Scand.</source> &#x000a0;<year>1978</year>:<volume>104</volume>:<fpage>479</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>484</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1748-1716.1978.tb06303.x</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">726939</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Li</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Durbin</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Fast and accurate short read alignment with burrows&#x02013;wheeler transform</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>. <year>2009</year>:<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>1754</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1760</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp324</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19451168</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Li</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barton</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JP</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Estimating linkage disequilibrium and selection from allele frequency trajectories</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source>. <year>2023</year>:<volume>223</volume>:<fpage>iyac189</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/genetics/iyac189</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36610715</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Mantel</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Haenszel</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>W</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Statistical aspects of the analysis of data from retrospective studies of disease</article-title>. <source>JNCI J Natl Cancer Inst</source>. <year>1959</year>:<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>719</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>748</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jnci/22.4.719</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13655060</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Martin</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Life history and habits of the pigeon louse (<italic toggle="yes">Columbicola columbae</italic> [linnaeus])</article-title>. <source>Canad Entomol</source>. <year>1934</year>:<volume>66</volume>:<fpage>6</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>16</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4039/Ent666-1</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Matsushima</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sato</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chuman</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Takeda</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yokotani</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nose</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tominaga</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shimohigashi</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shimohigashi</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>cDNA cloning of the housefly pigment-dispersing factor (PDF) precursor protein and its peptide comparison among the insect circadian neuropeptides</article-title>. <source>J Pept Sci</source>. <year>2004</year>:<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>82</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>91</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/psc.511</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14994986</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>McKenna</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hanna</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Banks</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sivachenko</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cibulskis</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kernytsky</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Garimella</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Altshuler</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gabriel</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Daly</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>The genome analysis toolkit: a MapReduce framework for analyzing next-generation DNA sequencing data</article-title>. <source>Genome Res</source>. <year>2010</year>:<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>1297</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1303</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.107524.110</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20644199</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Mueller</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>LD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Phillips</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barter</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>TT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Greenspan</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>ZS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rose</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Genome-wide mapping of gene&#x02013;phenotype relationships in experimentally evolved populations</article-title>. <source>Mol Bio Evol</source>. <year>2018</year>:<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>2085</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2095</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msy113</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29860403</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Nelson</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>BC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Murray</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>MD</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The distribution of <italic toggle="yes">Mallophaga</italic> on the domestic pigeon (<italic toggle="yes">Columba livia</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Int J Parasit</source>. <year>1971</year>:<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>21</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>29</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0020-7519(71)90042-7</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Orozco-Terwengel</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kapun</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nolte</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kofler</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Flatt</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schl&#x000f6;tterer</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>C</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Adaptation of Drosophila to a novel laboratory environment reveals temporally heterogeneous trajectories of selected alleles</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol</source>. <year>2012</year>:<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>4931</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4941</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-294X.2012.05673.x</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22726122</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Park</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hall</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Isolation and chronobiological analysis of a neuropeptide pigment-dispersing factor gene in <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila melanogaster</italic></article-title>. <source>J Biol Rhythms</source>. <year>1998</year>:<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>219</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>228</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/074873098129000066</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9615286</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Paterson</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vogwill</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Buckling</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Benmayor</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Spiers</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thomson</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>NR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Quail</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smith</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Walker</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Libberton</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Antagonistic coevolution accelerates molecular evolution</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2010</year>:<volume>464</volume>:<fpage>275</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>278</lpage>. doi: doi<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature08798</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20182425</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Pavan</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dalpiaz</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Odorants could elicit repair processes in melanized neuronal and skin cells</article-title>. <source>Neural Regen Res.</source> &#x000a0;<year>2017</year>:<volume>12</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1401</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1404</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/1673-5374.215246</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29089976</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Potts</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Au</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>PC</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The affinity of melanin for inorganic ions</article-title>. <source>Exp Eye Res.</source> &#x000a0;<year>1976</year>:<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>487</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>491</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0014-4835(76)90186-X</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1278259</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>R Core Team</collab>
</person-group>. <source>R: a language and environment for statistical computing</source>. <publisher-loc>Vienna, Austria</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>R Foundation for Statistical Computing</publisher-name>; <year>2025</year>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.R-project.org/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.R-project.org/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<string-name>
<surname>Rose</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Passananti</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>HB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Matos</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>, editors. <source>Methuselah Flies: A Case Study in the Evolution of Aging</source>. <publisher-loc>Singapore</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>World Scientific</publisher-name>; <year>2004</year>. p. <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>495</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Rubin</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>C-J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zody</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eriksson</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Meadows</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JRS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sherwood</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Webster</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>MT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jiang</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ingman</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sharpe</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ka</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Whole-genome resequencing reveals loci under selection during chicken domestication</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2010</year>:<volume>464</volume>:<fpage>587</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>591</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature08832</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20220755</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>San-Jose</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roulin</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Toward understanding the repeated occurrence of associations between melanin-based coloration and multiple phenotypes</article-title>. <source>Am Nat.</source> &#x000a0;<year>2018</year>:<volume>192</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>111</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>130</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/698010</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30016163</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B50"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Schluter</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>
</person-group>. <source>The ecology of adaptive radiation</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>; <year>2000</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Scoville</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>AG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>YW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Willis</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kelly</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JK</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Explaining the heritability of an ecologically significant trait in terms of individual quantitative trait loci</article-title>. <source>Biol Lett</source>. <year>2011</year>:<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>896</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>898</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsbl.2011.0409</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21653565</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Slatkin</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Linkage disequilibrium&#x02014;understanding the evolutionary past and mapping the medical future</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Genet</source>. <year>2008</year>:<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>477</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>485</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrg2361</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18427557</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Smith</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>VS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ford</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Johnson</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>KP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Johnson</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>PCD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yoshizawa</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Light</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Multiple lineages of lice pass through the K-pg boundary</article-title>. <source>Biol Lett</source>. <year>2011</year>:<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>782</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>785</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsbl.2011.0105</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21471047</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Taus</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Futschik</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schl&#x000f6;tterer</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>C</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Quantifying selection with pool-seq time series data</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>. <year>2017</year>:<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>3023</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3034</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msx225</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28961717</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>True</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Insect melanism: the molecules matter</article-title>. <source>Trends Ecol Evol</source>. <year>2003</year>:<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>640</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>647</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tree.2003.09.006</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Tukey</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Comparing individual means in the analysis of variance</article-title>. <source>Biometrics</source>. <year>1949</year>:<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>99</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>114</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/3001913</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18151955</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Turner</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>TL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Miller</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>PM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Investigating natural variation in Drosophila courtship song by the evolve and resequence approach</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source>. <year>2012</year>:<volume>191</volume>:<fpage>633</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>642</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.112.139337</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22466043</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Turner</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>TL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stewart</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>AD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fields</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>AT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rice</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>WR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tarone</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Population-based resequencing of experimentally evolved populations reveals the genetic basis of body size variation in <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila melanogaster</italic></article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source>. <year>2011</year>:<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>e1001336</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1001336</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21437274</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Van Laere</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A-S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nguyen</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Braunschweig</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nezer</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Collette</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moreau</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Archibald</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Haley</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>CS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Buys</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tally</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>A regulatory mutation in IGF2 causes a major QTL effect on muscle growth in the pig</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2003</year>:<volume>425</volume>:<fpage>832</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>836</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature02064</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14574411</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Waller</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Warr</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>HM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Goodman</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>GB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bush</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>SE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Clayton</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>DH</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Influence of grooming on permanent arthropod associates of birds: cattle egrets, lice, and mites</article-title>. <source>J Parasitol</source>. <year>2024</year>:<volume>110</volume>:<fpage>143</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>149</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1645/23-85</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38561014</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Wichman</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>HA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Scott</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yarber</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>CD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bull</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Experimental evolution recapitulates natural evolution</article-title>. <source>Phil Trans Roy Soc Lond Ser B Biol Sci</source>. <year>2000</year>:<volume>355</volume>:<fpage>1677</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1684</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.2000.0731</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11127915</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Wiriyasermkul</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moriyama</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nagamori</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Membrane transport proteins in melanosomes: regulation of ions for pigmentation</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta (BBA) Biomembr</source>. <year>2020</year>:<volume>1862</volume>:<fpage>183318</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbamem.2020.183318</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Wittkopp</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>True</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carroll</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>SB</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Reciprocal functions of the <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic> yellow and ebony proteins in the development and evolution of pigment patterns</article-title>. <source>Development</source>. <year>2002</year>:<volume>129</volume>:<fpage>1849</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1858</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.129.8.1849</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11934851</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B64"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Zhang</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martin</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Perry</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>MW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>van der Burg</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>KRL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Matsuoka</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Monteiro</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reed</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>RD</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Genetic basis of melanin pigmentation in butterfly wings</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source>. <year>2017</year>:<volume>205</volume>:<fpage>1537</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1550</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.116.196451</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28193726</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evaf083-B65"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Zhao</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lascoux</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Overall</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>ADJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Waxman</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>D</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The characteristic trajectory of a fixing allele: a consequence of fictitious selection that arises from conditioning</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source>. <year>2013</year>:<volume>195</volume>:<fpage>993</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1006</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.113.156059</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24002647</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>