<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="issn">2168-8184</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cureus</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2168-8184</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cureus</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Palo Alto (CA)</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11681925</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7759/cureus.76400</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Family/General Practice</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Obstetrics/Gynecology</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Oral Medicine</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Knowledge of the Benefits and Risks of Oral Contraceptive Use Among Women of Reproductive Age in Western Saudi Arabia: A Descriptive Cross-Sectional Study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Muacevic</surname><given-names>Alexander</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>John R</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Salem</surname><given-names>Anwar</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shafi</surname><given-names>Nusaybah</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Alsaadi</surname><given-names>Shajn S</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Klantan</surname><given-names>Fatimah</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Alhajjaji</surname><given-names>Danah S</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Allihyani</surname><given-names>Rojinah</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Daghestani</surname><given-names>Mazen</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff-1">
<label>1</label>
College of Medicine, Umm Al-Qura University, Makkah, SAU </aff><aff id="aff-2">
<label>2</label>
Obstetrics and Gynaecology, Umm Al-Qura University, Makkah, SAU </aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">
Shajn S. Alsaadi <email>shajn.alsaadi@gmail.com</email>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>26</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic"><month>12</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><issue>12</issue><elocation-id>e76400</elocation-id><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2024, Salem et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Salem et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License CC-BY 4.0., which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="https://www.cureus.com/articles/273546-knowledge-of-the-benefits-and-risks-of-oral-contraceptive-use-among-women-of-reproductive-age-in-western-saudi-arabia-a-descriptive-cross-sectional-study">This article is available from https://www.cureus.com/articles/273546-knowledge-of-the-benefits-and-risks-of-oral-contraceptive-use-among-women-of-reproductive-age-in-western-saudi-arabia-a-descriptive-cross-sectional-study</self-uri><abstract><p>Introduction: For women of reproductive age, oral contraceptives (OCs) are a well-liked and practical way to control pregnancy. OCs are also used to treat acne, irregular uterine bleeding, and premenstrual syndrome. However, there are false beliefs regarding their benefits and risks. The primary health benefits of OCs are the reduction of acne, the risk of colon, ovarian, and endometrial cancer,&#x000a0;and the risk of osteoporosis. Other benefits include the reduction of the risk of endometriosis, fibroid tumors, menorrhagia, dysmenorrhea, benign breast illness, and ovarian cysts. The objective of this study was to assess the level of awareness among women of reproductive age in western Saudi Arabia regarding the benefits and risks of OCs.</p><p>Method: A descriptive cross-sectional study was used to gather data from women aged 15-49 in western Saudi Arabia. The study used an online questionnaire designed using Google Forms (Google LLC, Mountain View, California, United States) that was distributed electronically via social media apps in Arabic language. Data was collected in Excel sheets (Microsoft Corporation, Redmond, Washington, United States) and analyzed using IBM SPSS Statistics for Windows, Version 21.0 (Released 2012; IBM Corp., Armonk, New York, United States). After determining our study population, we calculated the sample size using OpenEpi version 3.0.</p><p>Results: A total of 588 Saudi women participated in the study and revealed that only 13.6% had an excellent understanding of OCs. The primary sources of information about oral contraceptives were friends and relatives (n=268, 45.6%), followed closely by physicians (n=255, 43.5%). Other sources included reading reliable materials, social media, and personal experience.</p><p>The sources of information were strongly linked to the participants' knowledge levels. Among those who sourced their information from reading reliable sources, 25.1% (n=42) exhibited good overall knowledge, while 22% (n=27) of those who relied on social media, 16% (n=41) of those who were informed by their physician, and only 3.2% (n=1) of those without any information source demonstrated a similar level of understanding.</p><p>Conclusions: The study highlights a lack of knowledge among reproductive-age women in western Saudi Arabia about the benefits and risks of OCs. It underscores the need for targeted educational initiatives to enhance awareness and understanding. By improving knowledge, healthcare providers can empower women to make informed decisions about their reproductive health. Ongoing research and advocacy are essential to ensure access to accurate information and support, ultimately aiming for better reproductive health outcomes in the region.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>associated</kwd><kwd>awareness</kwd><kwd>oral contraception</kwd><kwd>risks and benefits</kwd><kwd>western region of saudi arabia</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Oral contraceptives (OCs) are used worldwide to prevent pregnancy in women of reproductive age and to treat premenstrual syndrome, abnormal uterine bleeding, and severe acne [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. In a study conducted in Riyadh, Saudi Arabia, which included 432 women, 249 (57.6%) were contraceptive users, with the most common method being OCs (55.6%) [<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. OCs are one of the most popular and most effective reversible forms of birth control [<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Combined estrogen-progesterone pills and progestin-only pills are two types of OCs and are made of synthetic ovarian hormones [<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Rapid changes in the sociodemographic pattern of the Saudi Arabian population, particularly those affecting women&#x02019;s employment and education, are playing a significant role in altering fertility beliefs, increasing the tendency to space out births, and thus in the use of contraceptives [<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. However, despite the widespread use of OCs, there are many misconceptions about both the benefits and risks.</p><p>Many studies describe the benefits of OCs. In addition to preventing pregnancy, regulating menstruation, and reducing the risk of endometrial, ovarian, and colon cancer, they can be used to treat dysmenorrhea, endometriosis, acne, menorrhagia, hyperandrogenism, polycystic ovary syndrome, functional ovarian cysts, premenstrual syndrome, myomas, and pelvic inflammatory disease. OCs are also beneficial in treating rheumatoid arthritis, multiple sclerosis, and certain conditions experienced in perimenopause [<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>-<xref rid="REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Possible side effects of using hormonal contraceptives include depression, breast cancer, and breakthrough bleeding [<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>-<xref rid="REF11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>].</p><p>There have been numerous studies on OCs in Saudi Arabia to evaluate women&#x02019;s attitudes and practices regarding their use. However, there are limited studies dedicated to assessing Saudi women&#x02019;s knowledge of the benefits and risks associated with OCs. Therefore, the aim of this study was to evaluate the knowledge of women of reproductive age living in western Saudi Arabia regarding the benefits and risks of using OCs.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><p>This was a cross-sectional study carried out at the Umm Al-Qura University College of Medicine,&#x000a0;Makkah, Saudi Arabia, from November 2023 to January 2024. The study was approved by the Institutional Research Board at Umm Al-Qura University (approval number: HAPO-02-K-012-2023-10-1793). The target population for this study consisted of women residing in the western region of Saudi Arabia aged 15-49 years who were residents of the western region during the study period.</p><p>After determining our study population, we calculated the sample size using OpenEpi version 3.0 (<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.openepi.com" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.openepi.com</ext-link>). The study successfully included 588 women who met the aforementioned criteria. All participants voluntarily agreed to take part in the study, ensuring that the data collected reflected genuine insights from individuals who were willing to contribute.</p><p>Study tool and data collection</p><p>An online self-administered questionnaire, designed in Arabic to accommodate the linguistic preferences of the target population, was utilized. The questionnaire was validated and adapted from a published study [<xref rid="REF12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] with some questions rephrased to align with the cultural context of our environment. The English translation is given in the Appendices. Moreover, a pre-test was conducted by distributing the survey to 20 participants, and then the survey was distributed through various social media applications, ensuring broad accessibility and reach to eligible participants. The use of social media platforms for distribution allowed for efficient and wide-reaching engagement with potential participants who fit these criteria.</p><p>The structured questionnaire comprised four distinct sections to capture a comprehensive range of data: (i) Demographic information: This section collected essential background data about the participants, including age, educational background, and other relevant demographic variables; (ii) Level of knowledge concerning the benefits and side effects of oral contraceptives: Here, participants were assessed on their understanding of the advantages and potential adverse effects associated with the use of oral contraceptives; (iii) Background information concerning the use of oral contraceptives: This section gathered information about the participants' personal experiences and history with oral contraceptives, including duration of use and reasons for choosing or not choosing these methods; (iv) Usage patterns and preferences: This final segment aimed to elucidate patterns of OC use, including frequency, types of OCs used, and personal preferences or trends.</p><p>This comprehensive approach aimed to provide a detailed understanding of contraceptive knowledge and practices within the specified demographic, offering valuable insights for public health initiatives and educational programs.</p><p>Data analysis</p><p>The data were collected, reviewed, and then analyzed using the IBM SPSS Statistics for Windows, Version 21.0 (Released 2012; IBM Corp., Armonk, New York, United States). All statistical methods used were two-tailed with an alpha level of 0.05. The p value was considered significant if it was less than .05. Regarding knowledge and awareness, each correct answer was given a score of 1. The overall level of awareness about the benefits and risks of OCs was determined by summing up the scores for correct answers. Knowledge was categorized as poor if a participant&#x02019;s score was less than 60% of the overall score and as good if a participant&#x02019;s score was 60% or more of the overall score. Descriptive analysis was conducted using frequency distribution and percentage for the study variables, including the participants&#x02019; personal data, education, and use of OCs. In addition, scores regarding knowledge and awareness of the benefits and risks of OCs were tabulated, and overall knowledge level and source of information were detailed in graphs. Cross-tabulation to show the distribution of the participants&#x02019; level of overall knowledge based on their data was carried out using a Pearson chi-square test for significance and an exact probability test if there were small frequency distributions.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p>A total of 588 women participated in the survey, with an average age of 33.1 years. The majority were married (65.1%) and had university-level education (70.6%). About 48.8% had used or were using OCs. Key findings included that only 13.6% of the participants had good overall knowledge about OCs, and the most recognized benefits were contraception and menstrual regulation, while risks such as weight gain, nausea, and increased risk of blood clots were the most commonly known. Table <xref rid="TAB1" ref-type="table">1</xref> presents a summary of the participants&#x02019; demographic information, including age, marital status, educational level, and their current or past use of OCs.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Personal characteristics of the participants (N = 588)</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Personal data</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age group in years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15&#x02013;19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20&#x02013;29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">219</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.2%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30&#x02013;39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">124</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.1%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40&#x02013;49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">232</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.5%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Are you married?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">383</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.1%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">205</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.9%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Educational level</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Below university</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">121</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.6%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">University graduate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">415</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.6%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Above university</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.8%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Do you use/have you ever used oral contraceptives?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">287</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.8%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">301</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.2%</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Table <xref rid="TAB2" ref-type="table">2</xref> summarizes the participants&#x02019; knowledge regarding both the risks and benefits of OC use. While most were aware of the risk of weight gain, other potential side effects and benefits were less recognized, indicating gaps in knowledge.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Participants&#x02019; knowledge of the benefits and risks associated with oral contraceptives (N=588)</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Knowledge items</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The expected side effects of oral contraceptives</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increased weight</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">443</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.3%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increased risk of ectopic pregnancy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">114</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.4%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increased risk of ovarian cancer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">129</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.9%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increased risk of cervical cancer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">121</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.6%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increased risk of breast cancer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.0%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nausea</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">305</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.9%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elevated blood pressure</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">242</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.2%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increased risk of pelvic inflammatory disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.2%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The expected benefits of oral contraceptives</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Contraception</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">541</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.0%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reduced risk of ovarian cancer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regulating the menstrual cycle</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">369</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.8%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reduced acne</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.4%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reduced anemia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.8%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reduced risk of cervical cancer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.3%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reduced blood pressure</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reduced depression</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.1%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reduced risk of breast cancer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking for those taking oral contraceptives may lead to</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increased risk of blood clots</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">384</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.3%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elevated blood pressure</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">237</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.3%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increased risk of stroke</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">141</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.0%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increased menstrual blood density</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">120</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.4%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increased risk of brain cancer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.8%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increased risk of uterine cancer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">111</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.9%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">There is no risk associated with smoking while taking oral contraceptives</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.0%</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Figure <xref rid="FIG1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> illustrates the distribution of participants based on their overall knowledge of OCs. Only 13.6% had good knowledge, while the remaining 86.4% had poor knowledge, emphasizing the need for better education on this topic.</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Participants&#x02019; overall knowledge about the benefits of oral contraceptives</title><p>Data presented as n (%)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0016-00000076400-i01" position="float"/></fig><p>Figure <xref rid="FIG2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> displays the different sources from which participants gained information about OCs, with the majority relying on friends and relatives, followed by physicians. Reliable sources and social media were less frequently used.</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Participants&#x02019; sources of information about oral contraceptives</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0016-00000076400-i02" position="float"/></fig><p>Table <xref rid="TAB3" ref-type="table">3</xref> explores various demographic and personal factors that are linked to participants&#x02019; overall knowledge of OCs. The table divides the participants into two categories: those with &#x0201c;Good&#x0201d; knowledge and those with &#x0201c;Poor&#x0201d; knowledge. It analyzes how different factors, such as age, marital status, educational level, and the use of OCs, influence the level of knowledge.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Factors associated with the participants&#x02019; overall knowledge about oral contraceptives</title><p>P: Pearson X2 test; ^: exact probability test; * P &#x0003c; 0.05 (significant)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Factors</td><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Overall knowledge level</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">P value</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Poor (n=508)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Good (n=80)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age in years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="5" colspan="1">.476</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15&#x02013;19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.9%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.1%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20&#x02013;29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">185</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.5%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.5%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30&#x02013;39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">108</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.1%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.9%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40&#x02013;49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">205</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.6%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Are you married?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">.433</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">334</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.8%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">174</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.9%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.1%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Educational level</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">.735</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Below university</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">107</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.6%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">University graduate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">357</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.0%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Above university</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.6%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.4%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Do you use/have you ever used oral contraceptives?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">.330</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">252</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.8%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.2%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">256</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.0%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sources of information about oral contraceptives</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="8" colspan="1">.001*^</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.8%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physician request</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">215</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.0%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Friends and relatives</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">227</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.3%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Previous experience</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">87</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.9%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.1%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reading reliable sources</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">125</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.9%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.1%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Social media</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">96</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.0%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0%</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>The results show no statistically significant relationship between age, marital status, education, or OC use and overall knowledge levels. However, sources of information show a strong statistical significance (p = 0.001), indicating that those who received their information from reliable sources were more likely to have good knowledge. Specifically, 25.1% of participants who consulted reliable sources had good knowledge, compared to only 3.2% of those who had no source of information. Other notable sources, like social media and physician consultations, also influenced knowledge levels but to a lesser extent.</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>OCs are among the most widely used forms of reversible contraception globally, offering both contraceptive and non-contraceptive health benefits. A variety of contraceptive options exist, including combined oral contraceptives (COCs), progestin-only pills (POPs), long-acting reversible contraceptives (LARCs), and barrier methods. Despite this range of options, many women remain unaware of the full spectrum of health benefits each method provides and lack knowledge about which option might best suit their needs [<xref rid="REF13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. According to a study done in the central region of Saudi Arabia, 66.1% of women know little or have incorrect information about OCs [<xref rid="REF12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. This is in contrast to a study carried out in India, which indicated women have high knowledge (99.2%) and a positive attitude (63.7%) about OCs [<xref rid="REF14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>].</p><p>The findings of this study revealed that only 13.6% of participants had a good overall knowledge of OCs. This mirrors the results of previous research, indicating a common trend of limited awareness about OCs beyond their contraceptive use [<xref rid="REF12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Notably, while the majority (92%) recognized pregnancy prevention as a primary benefit, awareness of other benefits, like menstrual cycle regulation (62.8%) or acne reduction (13.4%), was significantly lower. In terms of the least expected benefits, 4.1% mentioned a reduction in the rate of depression, 3.9% mentioned a decreased risk of breast cancer, and 2.0% mentioned a reduction in blood pressure. A study by Kaunitz has addressed the gap between the perceived and actual benefits of oral contraceptives (OCs) [<xref rid="REF15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. It emphasizes that while oral contraceptives are widely recognized for their contraceptive purposes, their non-contraceptive health benefits, such as the treatment of acne, regulation of the menstrual cycle, reduction of menstrual disorders, and lowering the risk of certain cancers, are often underappreciated or overlooked by both patients and healthcare providers. The study highlights the need for better education and awareness around these non-contraceptive benefits to align perception with reality [<xref rid="REF15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. This aligns with our findings, where many participants were unaware of or undervalued the non-contraceptive benefits of OCs.</p><p>Additionally, awareness of side effects was mixed. Most participants were familiar with common side effects like weight gain (75.3%) and nausea (51.9%), but fewer knew about more serious risks such as the potential for ectopic pregnancy or an increased risk of ovarian cancer. The mixed awareness of oral contraceptive side effects observed in this study mirrors findings from other regions. Bryden and Fletcher reported that while university-aged women were familiar with common side effects like weight gain, knowledge of serious risks was lacking [<xref rid="REF16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Similarly, Bardaweel et al. found that although most women in Jordan were aware of common issues like hormonal disturbances, knowledge of serious risks, such as cancer, was limited [<xref rid="REF17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. This consistency across different populations highlights the universal need for comprehensive education on both common and serious side effects, suggesting that more tailored educational strategies could address these gaps effectively.</p><p>Moreover, low-dose COCs offer several benefits, including a reduced incidence of adverse effects, compared to higher doses. These benefits may include a lower risk of thromboembolic events, improved tolerability, and fewer side effects such as weight gain and mood changes. Research indicates that low-dose COCs are effective for contraception while minimizing complications. Studies comparing low-dose and high-dose COCs highlight the safety and effectiveness of lower doses, making them an attractive option for many patients [<xref rid="REF18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].</p><p>In the current study, the participants were also asked about how smoking might affect women who take OCs. A large percentage of the participants, 65.3%, stated that it may lead to an increased risk of blood clots, 40.3% stated that it might lead to high blood pressure, and 24.0% stated that it might lead to an increased risk of stroke, increased menstrual blood density, and an increased risk of brain and uterine cancer. Surprisingly, 17% of the participants stated that smoking has no effect on women who take OCs. These results are similar to the results of a study conducted in Canada, with the percentage of participants who stated smoking has no effect on women who take OCs being 4% [<xref rid="REF16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>].</p><p>In contrast to earlier studies, such as one conducted in Riyadh, which found a positive correlation between education level and knowledge of OCs [<xref rid="REF19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], the current study did not find a significant relationship between educational attainment and overall knowledge of OCs. Instead, the key factor influencing knowledge levels in our study was the source of information. Women who obtained information from reliable sources such as healthcare providers or academic materials had significantly better knowledge than those relying on informal sources like friends, relatives, or social media. These findings differ from the 2012 Riyadh study [<xref rid="REF19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], which showed that knowledge about OCs was positively correlated with longer usage and higher education levels.</p><p>Similarly, an Australian study from the same year also found that higher educational attainment was associated with a greater understanding of OCs [<xref rid="REF20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. This discrepancy with the current study can be attributed to the reliance on information sources in the present study. Cultural and regional factors may contribute to this; the western Saudi Arabian region may have limited access to integrated health education programs seen in other regions. Additionally, the rise of social media as a dominant source of health information has introduced a mix of accurate and misleading content, influencing awareness even among educated individuals. These findings underscore the need for targeted public health campaigns and education efforts to address these gaps effectively.</p><p>The sources of information our study participants relied on most to gain knowledge were friends and relatives, followed by physicians, reading reliable sources, social media, previous experience, and studying. This is in line with another Saudi Arabian survey wherein 33% of participants indicated their family was their primary source of information about OCs [<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].</p><p>In summary, this study highlights critical gaps in knowledge about OCs among women in Western Saudi Arabia, particularly regarding non-contraceptive benefits and serious side effects. These findings underscore the urgent need for targeted educational interventions by healthcare providers and public health campaigns to improve awareness. Clinicians should prioritize offering comprehensive education during consultations, focusing on both the risks and benefits of OCs. Concurrently, public health campaigns must address misinformation and emphasize non-contraceptive benefits, especially for populations that rely heavily on informal information sources. By providing accurate information through credible channels, these efforts could bridge the knowledge gap and enable more informed decision-making about OC use.</p><p>The implications of these findings extend beyond addressing immediate knowledge deficits. From a clinical perspective, healthcare providers must adopt a more proactive role, emphasizing the importance of engaging patients with tailored educational efforts. This study challenges the conventional assumption that higher educational attainment directly correlates with better health knowledge, highlighting instead the critical role of reliable information sources. By shifting focus to the accessibility and accuracy of health information, clinicians can reshape educational practices in ways that align with patients&#x02019; needs and cultural contexts. On a policy level, the findings advocate for integrating targeted reproductive health education into public health initiatives. Policymakers could develop culturally tailored awareness campaigns utilizing accessible platforms, such as digital tools and community outreach, to reduce reliance on informal and often unreliable sources. This approach ensures that accurate and trustworthy information reaches diverse demographics, fostering better health literacy.</p><p>For future research, the study calls for investigations into the long-term effectiveness of diverse educational strategies, including school-based programs, mobile health applications, and community workshops. Research should also explore methods to enhance the reach of credible information, addressing disparities in health knowledge across different regions and demographic groups. Ultimately, these findings hold the potential to shift current understanding and practice by emphasizing the pivotal role of reliable information sources over educational attainment. By aligning clinical, policy, and research efforts with the insights from this study, healthcare systems can foster informed contraceptive use, leading to improved reproductive health outcomes for women in the region.</p><p>Our study had some limitations, including the reliance on self-reported data and the restriction of the sample to women with internet access. Future studies could expand the scope by including in-person interviews to capture a more representative sample of women across Saudi Arabia. However, sharing the questionnaire through various social media platforms significantly expedited the data collection process, enabling the collection of a substantial number of responses in a shorter period. This approach also broadened the reach of the survey, attracting a diverse demographic, which enriched the quality of the data collected.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>This study emphasized the critical gaps in knowledge among women of reproductive age in western Saudi Arabia regarding the benefits and risks associated with OC use. Most participants lacked awareness of the broader implications of OC use. While contraception and menstrual cycle regulation were well-recognized benefits, other health advantages such as reduction of the risk of certain cancers were significantly underappreciated. Similarly, common side effects like weight gain and nausea were better understood compared to more serious risks, such as an increased likelihood of blood clots or certain types of cancer. A significant association was seen between the sources of information and participants&#x02019; knowledge levels. Reliance on informal channels like friends, relatives, or social media resulted in misinformation or inadequate understanding. Additionally, the study identified a notable gap in understanding the impact of behaviors such as smoking while using OCs, with misconceptions potentially affecting health outcomes.</p><p>To address these gaps, targeted educational initiatives are essential to empower women with accurate, reliable, and comprehensive information, enabling them to make informed decisions about their reproductive health. By bridging the knowledge gap, healthcare providers can promote safer and more effective contraceptive use, ultimately improving reproductive health outcomes in the region. Continued research and advocacy remain crucial to refining public health strategies and ensuring widespread access to trustworthy resources and support systems</p></sec></body><back><fn-group content-type="conflict"><title>Disclosures</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Human subjects:</bold> Consent for treatment and open access publication was obtained or waived by all participants in this study. &#x0200f;Institutional Research Board at Umm Al-Qura University issued approval HAPO-02-K-012-2023-10-1793.</p><p><bold>Animal subjects:</bold> All authors have confirmed that this study did not involve animal subjects or tissue.</p><p><bold>Conflicts of interest:</bold> In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following:</p><p><bold>Payment/services info:</bold> All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work.</p><p><bold>Financial relationships:</bold> All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work.</p><p><bold>Other relationships:</bold> All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="other"><title>Author Contributions</title><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Concept and design:</bold>&#x000a0; Anwar Salem, Nusaybah Shafi, Shajn S. Alsaadi, Fatimah Klantan, Danah S. Alhajjaji, Rojinah Allihyani, Mazen Daghestani</p><p><bold>Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data:</bold>&#x000a0; Anwar Salem, Nusaybah Shafi, Shajn S. Alsaadi, Fatimah Klantan, Danah S. Alhajjaji, Rojinah Allihyani, Mazen Daghestani</p><p><bold>Drafting of the manuscript:</bold>&#x000a0; Anwar Salem, Nusaybah Shafi, Shajn S. Alsaadi, Fatimah Klantan, Danah S. Alhajjaji, Rojinah Allihyani, Mazen Daghestani</p><p><bold>Critical review of the manuscript for important intellectual content:</bold>&#x000a0; Anwar Salem, Nusaybah Shafi, Shajn S. Alsaadi, Fatimah Klantan, Danah S. Alhajjaji, Rojinah Allihyani, Mazen Daghestani</p></fn></fn-group><app-group><app><title>Appendices</title><p>Questionnaire (Translated to English from the original Arabic)</p><p>Age?</p><p>&#x000b7;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; 15-19 years old</p><p>&#x000b7;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; 20-29 years old</p><p>&#x000b7;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; 30-39 years old</p><p>&#x000b7;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; 40-49 years old</p><p>Are you from the western region of Saudi Arabia?</p><p>&#x000b7;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; Yes</p><p>&#x000b7;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; No</p><p>Are you married?</p><p>&#x000b7;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; Yes</p><p>&#x000b7;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; No</p><p>Educational status?</p><p>&#x000b7;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; Below bachelor&#x02019;s degree (middle school, high school etc.)</p><p>&#x000b7;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; In university (bachelor&#x02019;s degree)</p><p>&#x000b7;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; Above bachelor&#x02019;s degree (doctorate, masters etc.)</p><p>Are you using oral contraceptives or have used them before?</p><p>&#x000b7;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; Yes</p><p>&#x000b7;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; No</p><p>Where did you get your information on oral contraceptives? (Please choose all the correct answers)</p><p>&#x000b7;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; Used them before (past experience)</p><p>&#x000b7;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; Asking a doctor</p><p>&#x000b7;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; Reading about them from trusted resources</p><p>&#x000b7;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; Social media</p><p>&#x000b7;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; Friends and family (community)</p><p>&#x000b7;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; Other (please mention)</p><p>Which are possible side effects of the pill? (Please circle all that apply)</p><p>&#x000b7;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; Increased blood pressure</p><p>&#x000b7;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; Increased risk of ovarian cancer</p><p>&#x000b7;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; Increased risk of ectopic pregnancy</p><p>&#x000b7;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; Increased pelvic inflammatory disease</p><p>&#x000b7;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; Increased risk of cervical cancer</p><p>&#x000b7;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; Increased risk of breast cancer</p><p>&#x000b7;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; Nausea</p><p>&#x000b7;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; Weight gain</p><p>Which of the following are possible health benefits of the pill?</p><p>&#x000b7;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; Decreased anemia</p><p>&#x000b7;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; Decreased risk of cervical cancer</p><p>&#x000b7;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; Decreased risk of breast cancer</p><p>&#x000b7;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; Decreased blood pressure</p><p>&#x000b7;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; Decreased risk of ovarian cysts</p><p>&#x000b7;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; Decreased depression</p><p>&#x000b7;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; Clears up acne</p><p>&#x000b7;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; Regulates menstrual cycle</p><p>&#x000b7;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; Not getting pregnant</p><p>Smoking while on the pill can lead to ?</p><p>&#x000b7;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; Increased risk of blood clots</p><p>&#x000b7;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; Increased menstrual bleeding</p><p>&#x000b7;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; Increased blood pressure</p><p>&#x000b7;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; Increased risk of stroke</p><p>&#x000b7;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; Increased risk of brain cancer</p><p>&#x000b7;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; Increased risk of cancer of the uterus</p><p>&#x000b7;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; No dangers</p><p>&#x000b7;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; Other risks not listed (Please mention them)</p></app></app-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="REF1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Quality of life and mental health in adolescent users of oral contraceptives. Results from the nationwide, representative German Health Interview and Examination Survey for Children and Adolescents (KiGGS)</article-title><source>Qual Life Res</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Lewandowski</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Duttge</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>2209</fpage><lpage>2218</lpage><volume>29</volume><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32144614</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Awareness of contraceptives and their use among Saudi women attending primary care centers in King Abdulaziz Medical City, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia</article-title><source>Cureus</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Ashoor</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alrashid</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alruhaimi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alanazi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alzahrani</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alshammari</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alotaibi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>0</fpage><volume>15</volume><year>2023</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Women&#x02019;s contraceptive preference-use mismatch</article-title><source>J Womens Health (Larchmt)</source><person-group>
<name><surname>He</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dalton</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zochowski</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>692</fpage><lpage>701</lpage><volume>26</volume><year>2017</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27710196</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Knowledge, attitude, and use of oral contraceptive pills among Saudi women seen at the primary care clinics of Security Forces Hospital, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia</article-title><source>J Med Sci Clin Res</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Alotaibi</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shiddo</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ghoraba</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>974</fpage><lpage>981</lpage><volume>6</volume><year>2018</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Awareness and use of contraceptives among Saudi women attending primary care centers in Al-Qassim, Saudi Arabia</article-title><source>Int J Health Sci (Qassim)</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Al Sheeha</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><volume>4</volume><year>2010</year><uri xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3068803/">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3068803/</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21475521</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Assessing hormonal contraceptive dispensing and counseling provided by community pharmacists in the United Arab Emirates: a simulated patient study</article-title><source>Pharm Pract (Granada)</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Mobark</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Al-Tabakha</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hasan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>1465</fpage><volume>17</volume><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31275503</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Unforeseen uses of oral contraceptive pills: exploratory study in Jordanian community pharmacies</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Barakat</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Al-Qudah</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Akour</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Al-Qudah</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dallal Bashi</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>0</fpage><volume>15</volume><year>2020</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Combined oral contraceptives: health benefits beyond contraception</article-title><source>Panminerva Med</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Caserta</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ralli</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Matteucci</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bordi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mallozzi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moscarini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>233</fpage><lpage>244</lpage><volume>56</volume><year>2014</year><uri xlink:href="https://www.minervamedica.it/en/journals/panminerva-medica/article.php?cod=R41Y2014N03A0233">https://www.minervamedica.it/en/journals/panminerva-medica/article.php?cod=R41Y2014N03A0233</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25056245</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Association of hormonal contraception with depression</article-title><source>JAMA Psychiatry</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Skovlund</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>M&#x000f8;rch</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kessing</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lidegaard</surname><given-names>&#x000d8;</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>1154</fpage><lpage>1162</lpage><volume>73</volume><year>2016</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27680324</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Contemporary hormonal contraception and the risk of breast cancer</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><person-group>
<name><surname>M&#x000f8;rch</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Skovlund</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hannaford</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Iversen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fielding</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lidegaard</surname><given-names>&#x000d8;</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>2228</fpage><lpage>2239</lpage><volume>377</volume><year>2017</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29211679</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>The risk of breakthrough bleeding justifies the use of combined hormonal contraception over progesterone-only pills while breastfeeding</article-title><source>Breastfeed Med</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Segev</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Samson</surname><given-names>AO</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Katz-Samson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Srebnik</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>84</fpage><lpage>85</lpage><volume>18</volume><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36720088</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Attitudes, awareness, and compliance of progesterone-only contraceptive pills among women in the Central Region, Saudi Arabia</article-title><source>Int J Med Developing Countries</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Alhabardi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Almutiri</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alkhaliwi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Almutairi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alazzam</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>1636</fpage><lpage>1644</lpage><volume>4</volume><year>2020</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Family planning practices among women seeking induced abortion: an institution-based cross-sectional study from Eastern India</article-title><source>J Family Med Prim Care</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Mohapatra</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Panda</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Misra</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>6339</fpage><lpage>6344</lpage><volume>11</volume><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36618191</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>A study on knowledge, attitude and practice of contraception among college students in Sikkim, India</article-title><source>J Turk Ger Gynecol Assoc</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Renjhen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pattanshetty</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sagir</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Samarasinghe</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>78</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><volume>11</volume><year>2010</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24591903</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Oral contraceptive health benefits: perception versus reality</article-title><source>Contraception</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Kaunitz</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><volume>59</volume><year>1999</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Knowledge of the risks and benefits associated with oral contraception in a university-aged sample of users and non-users</article-title><source>Contraception</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Bryden</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fletcher</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>223</fpage><lpage>227</lpage><volume>63</volume><year>2001</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11376650</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Current knowledge, attitude, and patterns of oral contraceptives utilization among women in Jordan</article-title><source>BMC Womens Health</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Bardaweel</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Akour</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kilani</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>117</fpage><volume>15</volume><year>2015</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26654875</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Choosing a combined oral contraceptive pill</article-title><source>Aust Prescr</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Black</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>6</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><volume>38</volume><year>2015</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26648603</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Knowledge on adherence and safety of the oral contraceptive pill in Saudi women</article-title><source>Saudi Med J</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Al-Shaikh</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mayet</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alshaikh</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hamad</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mahmoud</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aljadhey</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>665</fpage><lpage>671</lpage><volume>33</volume><year>2012</year><uri xlink:href="https://smj.org.sa/content/33/6/665">https://smj.org.sa/content/33/6/665</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22729123</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Women's knowledge, beliefs, and information needs in relation to the risks and benefits associated with use of the oral contraceptive pill</article-title><source>J Womens Health (Larchmt)</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Philipson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wakefield</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kasparian</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>635</fpage><lpage>642</lpage><volume>20</volume><year>2011</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21410331</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>