<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PeerJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PeerJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PeerJ</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PeerJ</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2167-8359</issn><publisher><publisher-name>PeerJ Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Diego, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12101447</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">19483</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19483</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Diabetes and Endocrinology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Orthopedics</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Pediatrics</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Metabolic Sciences</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Data Mining and Machine Learning</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Exploring the effect of the triglyceride-glucose index on bone metabolism in prepubertal children, a retrospective study: insights from traditional methods and machine-learning-based bone remodeling prediction</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="author-1" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Shunshun</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Aolei</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Botian</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-4" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6710-7425</contrib-id><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Yangyang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><email>209204@wzhealth.com</email></contrib><aff id="aff-1">
<label>1</label><institution>Pediatric Endocrinology, Genetics and Metabolism, The Second Affiliated Hospital of Wenzhou Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Wenzhou</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff-2">
<label>2</label><institution>Reproductive Medicine Center, Obstetrics and Gynecology, The Second Affiliated Hospital of Wenzhou Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Wenzhou</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Menini</surname><given-names>Stefano</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>5</month><year iso-8601-date="2025">2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>13</volume><elocation-id>e19483</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="2025-01-21"><day>21</day><month>1</month><year iso-8601-date="2025">2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="2025-04-26"><day>26</day><month>4</month><year iso-8601-date="2025">2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2025 Cao et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Cao et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, reproduction and adaptation in any medium and for any purpose provided that it is properly attributed. For attribution, the original author(s), title, publication source (PeerJ) and either DOI or URL of the article must be cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/19483"/><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Childhood obesity poses a significant risk to bone health, but the impact of insulin resistance (IR) on bone metabolism in prepubertal children, as assessed by the triglyceride-glucose (TyG) index, remains underexplored. Bone turnover markers (BTMs) provide a non-invasive method for evaluating bone remodeling, but their relationship to obesity-related metabolic changes requires further study.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>In this retrospective study of 332 prepubertal children (163 boys and 169 girls), we used multivariate linear regression and five machine learning (ML) algorithms to explore the association between the TyG index and BTMs, including &#x003b2;-C-terminal telopeptide of type 1 collagen (&#x003b2;-CTx), total procollagen type 1 N-terminal propeptide (T-P1NP), and N-terminal mid-fragment of osteocalcin (N-MID). The categorical boosting (CatBoost) models selected based on optimal performance metrics were interpreted using SHapley Additive exPlanation (SHAP) analysis to identify key features affecting prediction.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>The TyG index was negatively correlated with &#x003b2;-CTx, T-P1NP, and N-MID levels (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05), with a dose-response effect. The CatBoost model showed higher predictive accuracy and robustness, with the area under the receiver operating characteristic curve (AUROC) values of 0.782 (95% CI [0.68&#x02013;0.885]), 0.789 (95% CI [0.691&#x02013;0.874]), and 0.727 (95% CI [0.619&#x02013;0.827]) for &#x003b2;-CTx, T-P1NP, and N-MID predictions, respectively. The SHAP analysis highlighted body mass index (BMI) and HbA1c as the key predictors.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>The TyG index is a reliable predictor of bone metabolic disorders in prepubertal obese children, and the interpretable CatBoost model provides a cost-effective tool for early intervention. This study has important implications for prevention strategies for disorders of bone metabolism in prepubertal obese children to reduce the risk of skeletal fragility in adulthood or old age.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>Triglyceride glucose index</kwd><kwd>Bone turnover markers</kwd><kwd>Machine learning</kwd><kwd>Bone metabolism</kwd><kwd>Prepubertal children</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="fund-1"><funding-source>Wenzhou Basic Scientific Research Project of China</funding-source><award-id>Y2023304</award-id></award-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by the Wenzhou Basic Scientific Research Project of China (No. Y2023304). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>The prevalence of childhood obesity has increased dramatically in all regions of the world over the past 2&#x02013;3 years, with as many as one-third of children in Europe and the United States being overweight and obese (<xref rid="ref-11" ref-type="bibr">Chung, Krenek &#x00026; Magge, 2023</xref>). Globally, obesity incurs an annual cost of nearly $2 trillion, with direct and indirect losses projected to reach $4 trillion by 2035, representing approximately 3% of the global gross domestic product (<xref rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr">Dicken &#x00026; Batterham, 2024</xref>). The TyG index assesses the body&#x02019;s insulin sensitivity by combining triglyceride and fasting blood glucose levels (<xref rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr">Dang et al., 2024</xref>). The triglyceride-glucose (TyG) index is a novel biomarker of insulin resistance (IR), an important risk factor for various metabolic diseases (<xref rid="ref-40" ref-type="bibr">Sun et al., 2025</xref>). <xref rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr">Aslan &#x000c7;in et al. (2020)</xref> demonstrated that the TyG index is a superior biomarker for assessing IR and the risk of metabolic syndrome compared to the homeostasis model assessment of IR (HOMA-IR). Children&#x02019;s body size, puberty, nutrition, and metabolism are different from those of adults and reflect unique states, making it important to explore the relationship between the TyG index, obesity, and disease in children (<xref rid="ref-1" ref-type="bibr">Abdollahian et al., 2023</xref>; <xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr">Badakhshan et al., 2023</xref>). Childhood obesity can lead to serious consequences affecting various organs and systems, such as the early onset of puberty, non-alcoholic fatty liver disease, diabetes mellitus (DM), and IR (<xref rid="ref-32" ref-type="bibr">Quarta et al., 2023</xref>; <xref rid="ref-2" ref-type="bibr">Ani&#x0015b;ko, Siatkowski &#x00026; W&#x000f3;jcik, 2024</xref>; <xref rid="ref-39" ref-type="bibr">Sohouli et al., 2024</xref>). However, its impact on the skeletal system remains particularly controversial (<xref rid="ref-28" ref-type="bibr">L&#x000f3;pez-Peralta et al., 2022</xref>).</p><p><xref rid="ref-6" ref-type="bibr">Bilinski, Paradowski &#x00026; Sypniewska (2020)</xref> reviewed bone health and hyperglycemia in the pediatric population, stating that bone health in children can be assessed in different ways such as bone mineral density (BMD), bone strength, bone microarchitecture, and bone turnover, and that impaired regulation of glucose metabolism in children and adolescents, and IR can adversely affect bone health. <xref rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr">Dole et al. (2024)</xref> demonstrated that obesity increases the risk of skeletal fragility, a vulnerability that stems from poor bone quality and may be caused by defects in the material properties of the bone matrix and that TGF-&#x003b2; signaling plays a key role in mediating the effects of obesity on the bone. <xref rid="ref-20" ref-type="bibr">Fuglsang-Nielsen et al. (2022)</xref> showed that abdominal obesity and type 2 DM (T2DM) decreased bone turnover, increased BMD, and increased fracture risk in participants. <xref rid="ref-26" ref-type="bibr">Lappe et al. (2015)</xref> concluded that a 10% increase in peak bone mass during childhood is associated with a 50% reduction in the risk of osteoporotic fractures in advanced age. Furthermore, they found that for each 1 standard deviation decrease in peak bone mass in childhood, the relative risk of fractures in later life increases by 2.6-fold. Bone mass accumulates rapidly during childhood and adolescence, reaching its peak around the age of twenty. Metabolic bone diseases, abnormal weight fluctuations, and the effects of certain medications can disrupt this accumulation process, potentially increasing the risk of osteoporosis and bone fragility in adulthood (<xref rid="ref-46" ref-type="bibr">Thom et al., 2023</xref>). Consequently, osteoporosis prevention efforts should ideally begin in childhood. <xref rid="ref-42" ref-type="bibr">Tahani et al. (2021)</xref> demonstrated that obese children exhibit higher bone mineral content (BMC) and BMD compared to their normal-weight peers. <xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr">Liang et al. (2022)</xref> demonstrated that obese children have a higher risk of supracondylar humeral fractures compared to children of healthy weight and found a correlation between obesity, BMD, and fracture risk.</p><p><xref rid="ref-35" ref-type="bibr">Rinonapoli et al. (2021)</xref> reviewed evidence indicating that obesity is associated with an increase in BMD, likely due to mechanical loading effects and elevated estrogen levels. However, despite the increase in BMD, individuals with obesity have a higher risk of fractures, suggesting that BMD values alone are insufficient to accurately assess fracture risk. Dual-energy X-ray absorptiometry (DXA) and quantitative computed tomography (QCT) are commonly used methods for measuring BMD and BMC. However, their clinical application for long-term monitoring of bone health in children is limited due to potential radiation risks and the high cost of these examinations (<xref rid="ref-49" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2023</xref>). Bone turnover markers (BTMs) are biochemical indicators of bone metabolism that can be detected earlier in the bloodstream than changes in BMD, reflecting the bone remodeling rate and metabolism state (<xref rid="ref-47" ref-type="bibr">Vasikaran et al., 2024</xref>). However, clinical data remain insufficient regarding the use of BTMs to monitor the effects of childhood obesity on bone metabolism and bone remodeling.</p><p>The current studies have focused on the association between TyG index and stroke and cardiovascular disease in adults, whereas the relationship between TyG index and bone remodeling and metabolism in prepubertal children is unclear (<xref rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2024</xref>). Therefore, the purpose of our study was twofold: (1) to investigate the association between TyG index and BTMs (&#x003b2;-C-terminal telopeptide of type 1 collagen (&#x003b2;-CTx), total procollagen type 1 N-terminal propeptide (T-P1NP), and N-terminal mid-fragment of osteocalcin (N-MID)); and (2) the TyG index was combined with other variables to construct an interpretable machine learning (ML) model to predict bone metabolism in prepubertal children for monitoring bone health.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Data selection and study design</title><p>A total of 356 prepubertal children who visited the Department of Pediatric Endocrinology at the Second Affiliated Hospital of Wenzhou Medical University between June 2021 and October 2023 were retrospectively analyzed. Of these, 332 participants met the inclusion criteria, comprising 163 boys and 169 girls, aged 7&#x02013;11 years. To avoid the influence of puberty on the results of the study, we chose children in the Tanner stage 1 as the study participants (<xref rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr">Eckert-Lind et al., 2020</xref>). This is because the rapid skeletal development of children during puberty is accompanied by an increased secretion of growth hormones and sex hormones (<italic toggle="yes">e.g</italic>., testosterone and estrogen), which play key roles in bone formation, remodeling, and metabolism. Written informed consent was obtained from both participants and their guardians. This study adhered to the principles of the Declaration of Helsinki and was approved by the Medical Ethics Committee of the Second Affiliated Hospital of Wenzhou Medical University (Approval No. 2024-K-031-02).</p><p>Inclusion criteria were as follows: (1) written informed consent was obtained from both participants and guardians, (2) participants cooperated with medical history taking, anthropometric measurements, and fasting blood sample collection, and (3) Tanner stage 1 children aged 7&#x02013;11 years. Exclusion criteria included: (1) missing key data, (2) presence of metabolic bone disease, (3) chromosomal or genetic abnormalities affecting endocrine or bone metabolism, (4) history of bone fracture within the past year, (5) use of medications influencing bone metabolism, (6) Tanner stages 2&#x02013;5, and (7) chronic systemic diseases.</p></sec><sec><title>Grouping and variable definitions</title><p>According to the standardized growth charts from the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, adjusted for age and gender, we defined a healthy weight as a body mass index (BMI) between the 5th and 84th percentiles, overweight as a BMI between the 85th and 94th percentiles, and obesity as a BMI at or above the 95th percentile, as described by <xref rid="ref-31" ref-type="bibr">Peinado Fabregat, Saynina &#x00026; Sanders (2023)</xref>. We categorized the participants into three groups: 135 in the healthy weight group (64 boys and 71 girls), 86 in the overweight group (41 boys and 45 girls), and 111 in the obese group (58 boys and 53 girls).</p><p>Since there was no clear cut-off value for BTMs, we classified &#x003b2;-CTx (threshold: 488.345 pg/ml), T-P1NP (threshold: 374.000 ng/ml), and N-MID (threshold: 29.280 ng/ml) according to the median level of BTMs in the participants to suggest enhanced or inhibited bone metabolism and remodeling, respectively. The TyG index is calculated using the formula: ln[fasting triglycerides (mg/dL) &#x000d7; fasting glucose (mg/dL)/2] (<xref rid="ref-45" ref-type="bibr">Tao et al., 2022</xref>). Similar to the TyG index, the TyG-BMI index is a novel biomarker for IR, calculated by multiplying the TyG index by BMI (<xref rid="ref-23" ref-type="bibr">Huang et al., 2023</xref>). <xref rid="ref-44" ref-type="bibr">Tang et al. (2022)</xref> demonstrated that systemic immune inflammation (SII) is a reliable and stable hematological indicator of the body&#x02019;s systemic immune and inflammatory status, calculated using the formula: platelet count &#x000d7; neutrophil count/lymphocyte count. The HOMA-IR was calculated using the formula: HOMA-IR = Fasting Insulin (&#x003bc;U/mL) &#x000d7; Fasting Glucose (mmol/L)/22.5 (<xref rid="ref-43" ref-type="bibr">Tahapary et al., 2022</xref>). Spexin, a recently identified adipokine belonging to the galanin/kisspeptin/spexin peptide family, plays a significant role in the pathophysiology of obesity-induced IR and T2DM (<xref rid="ref-18" ref-type="bibr">Fang et al., 2022</xref>). Fibroblast growth factor 23 (FGF23) is an osteogenic hormone produced and secreted by the skeletal system. Alongside parathyroid hormone (PTH), 1,25-dihydroxyvitamin D (1,25(OH)<sub>2</sub>D), and calcitonin, FGF23 plays a critical role in regulating phosphate and calcium homeostasis across the bone, kidneys, and gastrointestinal tract to support optimal bone mineralization (<xref rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr">Cipriani et al., 2022</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Missing value handles</title><p>In medical research, there are often missing values in medical data, which can result in wasted sample size if only complete variables are considered for analysis, and statistical analyses that ignore missing values have the potential to introduce bias in parameter estimation (<xref rid="ref-8" ref-type="bibr">Cao &#x00026; Hu, 2024</xref>). Imputation of missing values plays a vital role in maintaining the integrity of the data and improving the validity of the study results. In this study, we used the R package &#x0201c;mice&#x0201d; to multiply impute variables with less than 15% missing data (<xref rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr">Blazek et al., 2021</xref>). Variables with more than 15% missing data were excluded from the analysis.</p></sec><sec><title>Feature engineering and modeling strategies</title><p>Based on previous studies (<xref rid="ref-36" ref-type="bibr">Schini et al., 2023</xref>; <xref rid="ref-47" ref-type="bibr">Vasikaran et al., 2024</xref>) and expert opinions from pediatric and orthopedic specialists at the Second Affiliated Hospital of Wenzhou Medical University, we selected demographics, laboratory parameters, and anthropometric measurements as the initial model features for this study, comprising a total of 26 variables (<xref rid="supp-9" ref-type="supplementary-material">Data S1</xref>). We screened the model variables through correlation analysis and near-zero variance tests to mitigate multicollinearity and overfitting. Based on the results of the correlation analysis (correlation coefficient threshold &#x0003e; 0.85) and the comparison of the explanatory power of the variables on the target variables, we removed four redundant variables: waist circumference, TyG-BMI index, insulin, and triglycerides, and ended up with a dataset containing 22 features and three target variables (&#x003b2;-CTx, T-P1NP, and N-MID). The dataset includes one categorical feature and 21 continuous features. To more robustly evaluate the performance of the model in unknown data, we randomly split the original predictive BTMs dataset into a training set and a test set based on 80:20. We used a five-fold cross-validation and grid search to determine the optimal combination of hyperparameters for the model, trained the model using the training set data, and evaluated the model&#x02019;s performance in predicting BTMs in the test set data (<xref rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2023</xref>). The data were normalized using Scikit-Learn&#x02019;s StandardScaler, and categorical variables were transformed into numerical form through one-hot encoding (<xref rid="ref-38" ref-type="bibr">Singh et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="ref-37" ref-type="bibr">2023</xref>). Different ML algorithms have different applicability due to their ability to handle category variables, data nonlinearities, and computational efficacy. We employed five ML algorithms&#x02014;support vector machine (SVM), Random Forest (RF), extreme gradient boosting (XGBoost), light gradient boosting machine (LGBM), and categorical boosting (CatBoost)&#x02014;to investigate the relationship between TyG indexes and BTMs, including &#x003b2;-CTx, T-P1NP, and N-MID. After evaluating seven performance metrics for each ML model, the model that best captured the relationship between the TyG index and BTMs was selected and interpreted using SHapley Additive exPlanation (SHAP) analysis.</p></sec><sec><title>SHAP-based model interpretability approach</title><p>With the extensive application of ML and artificial intelligence in healthcare, model interpretability has emerged as a critical topic in both research and practical applications. The high complexity of these models, along with the nonlinearity of their features, often complicates the understanding of their internal decision logic and influencing factors. SHAP-based interpretation methods offer a novel approach for visualizing and quantifying model behavior, enhancing the transparency and usability of complex predictive models in healthcare settings (<xref rid="ref-17" ref-type="bibr">Fan et al., 2023</xref>). The SHAP value quantifies the importance of each feature by calculating its marginal contribution across various feature combinations, ensuring fair consideration of each feature&#x02019;s role in different permutations (<xref rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2021</xref>). This approach enhances our understanding of how individual features influence model decisions. In the healthcare domain, SHAP values facilitate insights into how specific features impact a given patient&#x02019;s diagnostic outcome, thereby supporting personalized diagnosis and treatment.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>The study sample size was determined using the pmsampsize R package (<xref rid="ref-34" ref-type="bibr">Riley et al., 2020</xref>). Based on data distribution, normally distributed data were represented as mean &#x000b1; standard deviation (SD), while non-normally distributed data were expressed as median and interquartile range (25%, 75%). The Kruskal-Wallis H test was used for comparisons across three groups, with categorical variables presented as frequencies (percentages) and analyzed using the Pearson chi-square test for group comparisons. Multivariate linear regression assessed the correlation between the TyG index and BTMs. The performance of the ML model was evaluated using metrics including the area under the receiver operating characteristic curve (AUROC), accuracy, precision, recall, F1 score, brier score, and the area under the P&#x02013;R curve (AP). Statistical significance was defined as a two-sided <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value &#x0003c; 0.05. Data analysis was performed using R software version 4.3.1, with the following packages: tidyverse, dplyr, tsummary, ggplot2, tableone, glmnet, car, MASS, psych, rms, ggExtra, mice, pmsampsize, and ggpubr. ML analyses were conducted in Python version 3.11.5, utilizing the scikit-learn library (version 1.2.2).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Baseline characteristics of the study population</title><p><xref rid="fig-1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref> shows the process for inclusion and exclusion of participants, as well as the flow of the study design, which resulted in the inclusion of 332 prepubertal children as the study sample. <xref rid="table-1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> summarizes the baseline characteristics of participants grouped according to BMI. Gender, age, and 1,25(OH)<sub>2</sub>D levels were not statistically different when compared between the healthy weight, overweight, and obese groups, respectively (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003e; 0.05). In the obese group, height, high-density lipoprotein (HDL), Spexin, &#x003b2;-CTx, T-P1NP, and N-MID levels were lower than in the healthy weight and overweight groups, while the rest of the variables were higher than in the healthy weight and overweight groups, and the difference was statistically significant <italic toggle="yes">(P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05).</p><fig position="float" id="fig-1"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19483/fig-1</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Flowchart of participant inclusion, exclusion criteria screening, and study design.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-13-19483-g001" position="float"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="table-1"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19483/table-1</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Baseline characteristics of participants grouped by BMI.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-13-19483-g006" position="float"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" content-type="text"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristics</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy weight group<break/>(<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 135)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overweight group<break/>(<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 86)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Obese group<break/>(<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 111)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.700</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Boys</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64 (47.41%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 (47.67%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58 (52.25%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Girls</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71 (52.59%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 (52.33%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53 (47.75%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.00 (8.00, 10.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.00 (8.00, 10.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.00 (8.00, 10.00)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.300</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weight (kg)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.40 (32.10, 39.55)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.20 (35.98, 47.28)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.30 (40.65, 52.55)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Height (cm)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">145.50 (141.00, 149.05)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">142.65 (136.33, 150.08)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">140.30 (135.00, 146.75)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.69 (15.67, 18.07)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.25 (19.25, 21.23)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.26 (21.56, 25.46)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">WC (cm)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.70 (58.80, 66.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.15 (66.40, 74.28)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.40 (72.75, 83.10)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total BMD (g/cm<sup>2</sup>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82 (0.78, 0.87)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83 (0.78, 0.92)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86 (0.82, 0.90)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TBLH BMD (g/cm<sup>2</sup>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71 (0.66, 0.75)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73 (0.68, 0.76)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81 (0.76, 0.87)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TBLH BMD Z -score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.32 (0.95, 1.69)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.61 (1.23, 1.90)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00 (1.62, 2.37)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lumbar spine BMD (g/cm<sup>2</sup>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71 (0.66, 0.76)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74 (0.68, 0.79)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79 (0.71, 0.86)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total fat percentage (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.70 (23.05, 30.10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.90 (30.33, 37.40)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.40 (35.10, 41.75)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SII</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">321.43 (226.44, 391.19)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">383.60 (290.79, 487.39)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">403.13 (329.94, 512.09)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HS- CRP (mg/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91 (0.56, 1.15)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.33 (1.00, 1.69)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.95 (1.55, 2.37)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HDL (mmol/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.69 (1.35, 2.05)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18 (1.01, 1.39)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78 (0.63, 1.03)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LDL (mmol/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.58 (1.08, 2.08)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.52 (2.04, 2.97)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.11 (2.62, 3.91)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TC (mmol/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.25 (2.68, 3.84)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.95 (3.40, 4.32)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.59 (4.08, 5.03)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FBG (mmol/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.82 (4.53, 5.10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.45 (5.11, 5.57)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.56 (5.50, 5.74)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TyG index</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.36 (8.18, 8.51)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.82 (8.67, 8.94)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.29 (9.10, 9.49)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HOMA-IR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.26 (1.87, 2.61)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.70 (3.09, 4.18)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.75 (5.01, 6.47)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HbA1c (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.61 (4.32, 5.01)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.21 (4.95, 5.38)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.59 (5.13, 6.05)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spexin (ng/ml)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55 (0.46, 0.63)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47 (0.37, 0.56)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34 (0.25, 0.43)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FGF23 (ng/ml)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.50 (43.41, 52.90)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.53 (41.35, 54.77)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.60 (41.88, 63.94)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.017</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b2;- CTx (pg/ml)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">524.19 (482.02, 566.15)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">488.91 (449.63, 543.20)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">429.37 (379.67, 487.86)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T-P1NP (ng/ml)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">410.73 (340.09, 504.30)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">402.17 (297.74, 468.59)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">312.24 (233.62, 398.21)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N-MID (ng/ml)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.73 (26.52, 40.63)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.47 (22.76, 32.91)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.68 (19.72, 32.52)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,25(OH)<sub>2</sub>D (ng/ml)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.00 (53.18, 71.63)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.27 (52.98, 66.83)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.44 (51.70, 66.07)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.300</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-1fn"><p>
<bold>Note:</bold>
</p></fn><fn id="table-1fn1" fn-type="other"><p>BMI, body mass index; WC, waist circumference; TBLH, total body less head; BMD, bone mineral density; SII, systemic immune inflammation; HS- CRP, hypersensitive C-reactive protein; HDL, high-density lipoprotein; LDL, low-density lipoprotein; TC, total cholesterol; FBG, fasting blood glucose; TyG, triglyceride glucose; HOMA, homeostasis model assessment; FGF23, fibroblast growth factor 23; &#x003b2;-CTx, &#x003b2;-C-terminal telopeptide of type 1 collagen; T-P1NP, total procollagen type 1 N-terminal propeptide; N-MID, N-terminal mid-fragment of osteocalcin; 1,25(OH)<sub>2</sub>D, 1,25-dihydroxyvitamin D.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Dose-response effects of TyG index and BTMs</title><p><xref rid="table-2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> summarizes the results of the multivariate linear regression analysis of the relationship between the TyG index and BTMs. Initially, the unadjusted model showed that the TyG index was associated with the response variables &#x003b2;-CTx (&#x003b2; = &#x02212;75.98, 95% CI [&#x02212;90.85 to &#x02212;61.10], <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001), T-P1NP (&#x003b2; = &#x02212;91.99, 95% CI [&#x02212;115.24 to &#x02212;68.73], <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001), and N-MID (&#x003b2; = &#x02212;6.62, 95% CI [&#x02212;8.54 to &#x02212;4.70], <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001), respectively, and was negatively correlated. In model 2, this association remained statistically significant even after adjusting for gender and age factors, &#x003b2;-CTx (&#x003b2; = &#x02212;76.00, 95% CI [&#x02212;90.90 to &#x02212;61.11], <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001), T-P1NP (&#x003b2; = &#x02212;92.03, 95% CI [&#x02212;115.23 to &#x02212;68.83], <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001), N-MID (&#x003b2; = &#x02212;6.61, 95% CI [&#x02212;8.52 to &#x02212;4.70], <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001). In Model 3, after adjusting for more covariates, for each unit increase in the TyG index, &#x003b2;-CTx decreased by 54.66 pg/ml (&#x003b2; = &#x02212;54.66, 95% CI [&#x02212;75.91 to &#x02212;33.42], <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001), T-P1NP decreased by 72.38 ng/ml (&#x003b2; = &#x02212;72.38, 95% CI [&#x02212;105.60 to &#x02212;39.17], <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001), and N-MID decreased by 4.21 ng/ml (&#x003b2; = &#x02212;4.21, 95% CI [&#x02212;6.97 to &#x02212;1.46], <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.003), and the correlation remained significant. In Model 3, we observed that individuals in the highest quartile of the TyG index exhibited reductions in &#x003b2;-CTx, T-P1NP, and N-MID levels compared to those in the lowest quartile of the TyG index. Specifically, &#x003b2;-CTx decreased by 62.18 pg/mL (&#x003b2; = &#x02212;62.18, 95% CI [&#x02212;89.22 to &#x02212;35.14], <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001), T-P1NP decreased by 90.35 ng/mL (&#x003b2; = &#x02212;90.35, 95% CI [&#x02212;132.47 to &#x02212;48.23], <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001), and N-MID decreased by 5.07 ng/mL (&#x003b2; = &#x02212;5.07, 95% CI [&#x02212;8.56 to &#x02212;1.58], <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.005). In model 3, there was a significant dose-response effect of the TyG index with &#x003b2;-CTx, T-P1NP, and N-MID when the TyG index was &#x02265;8.74, &#x02265;8.44, and &#x02265;8.74, respectively (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05). Normality, independence, homoscedasticity, and linearity assumptions of the multivariate linear regression equations were evaluated using Q-Q plots, the Durbin-Watson test, the non-constant variance score test, and the variance inflation factor (VIF), respectively. Results indicate that all model assumptions are met, supporting the model&#x02019;s robustness.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="table-2"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19483/table-2</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Multivariate linear regression analysis of the relationship between the TyG index and serum BTMs.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-13-19483-g007" position="float"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" content-type="text"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Exposure</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Model 1</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Model 2</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Model 3</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b2; (95%CI) <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b2; (95%CI) <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b2; (95%CI) <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Response variable: &#x003b2;-CTx</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TyG index (continuous)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;75.98 [&#x02212;90.85 to &#x02212;61.10] &#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;76.00 [&#x02212;90.90 to &#x02212;61.11] &#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;54.66 [&#x02212;75.91 to &#x02212;33.42] &#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TyG index (quartile)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q1 (&#x02265;7.79, &#x0003c;8.44)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q2 (&#x02265;8.44, &#x0003c;8.74)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;12.20 [&#x02212;31.46 to 7.06] 0.215</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;11.43 [&#x02212;30.77 to 7.90] 0.247</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;8.22 [&#x02212;27.76 to 11.32] 0.410</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q3 (&#x02265;8.74, &#x0003c;9.10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;54.97 [&#x02212;74.12 to &#x02212;35.83] &#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;55.06 [&#x02212;74.23 to &#x02212;35.89] &#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;38.48 [&#x02212;62.04 to &#x02212;14.91] 0.002</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q4 (&#x02265;9.10, &#x0003c;9.66)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;86.79 [&#x02212;106.11 to &#x02212;67.46] &#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;88.77 [&#x02212;106.10 to &#x02212;67.44] &#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;62.18 [&#x02212;89.22 to &#x02212;35.14] &#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P for trend</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Response variable: T-P1NP</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TyG index (continuous)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;91.99 [&#x02212;115.24 to &#x02212;68.73] &#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;92.03 [&#x02212;115.23 to &#x02212;68.83] &#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;72.38 [&#x02212;105.60 to &#x02212;39.17] &#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TyG index (quartile)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q1 (&#x02265;7.79, &#x0003c;8.44)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q2 (&#x02265;8.44, &#x0003c;8.74)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;36.93 [&#x02212;67.03 to &#x02212;6.84] 0.017</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;34.79 [&#x02212;64.90 to &#x02212;4.68] 0.024</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;33.38 [&#x02212;63.82 to &#x02212;2.93] 0.032</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q3 (&#x02265;8.74, &#x0003c;9.10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;63.80 [&#x02212;93.71 to &#x02212;33.88] &#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;62.81 [&#x02212;92.66 to &#x02212;32.96] &#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;47.59 [&#x02212;84.31 to &#x02212;10.88] 0.012</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q4 (&#x02265;9.10, &#x0003c;9.66)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;114.43 [&#x02212;144.62 to &#x02212;84.23] &#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;114.58 [&#x02212;144.68 to &#x02212;84.47] &#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;90.35 [&#x02212;132.47 to &#x02212;48.23] &#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P for trend</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Response variable: N-MID</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TyG index (continuous)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;6.62 [&#x02212;8.54 to &#x02212;4.70] &#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;6.61 [&#x02212;8.52 to &#x02212;4.70] &#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;4.21 [&#x02212;6.97 to &#x02212;1.46] 0.003</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TyG index (quartile)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q1 (&#x02265;7.79, &#x0003c;8.44)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q2 (&#x02265;8.44, &#x0003c;8.74)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.73 [&#x02212;4.21 to 0.75] 0.172</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.88 [&#x02212;4.36 to 0.59] 0.137</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.36 [&#x02212;3.88 to 1.16] 0.291</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q3 (&#x02265;8.74, &#x0003c;9.10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;5.89 [&#x02212;8.35 to &#x02212;3.43] &#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;5.88 [&#x02212;8.33 to &#x02212;3.42] &#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;3.95 [&#x02212;6.99 to &#x02212;0.91] 0.011</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q4 (&#x02265;9.10, &#x0003c;9.66)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;7.66 [&#x02212;10.15 to &#x02212;5.18] &#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;7.66 [&#x02212;10.14 to &#x02212;5.19] &#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;5.07 [&#x02212;8.56 to &#x02212;1.58] 0.005</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P for trend</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-2fn"><p>
<bold>Note:</bold>
</p></fn><fn id="table-2fn1" fn-type="other"><p>CI, confidence intervals; Model 1, no covariate adjustment; Model 2, Adjusted for gender and age; Model 3, adjusted for gender, age, weight, SII, and LDL.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Comparison of ML model performance metrics</title><p><xref rid="table-3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> summarizes fifteen ML models&#x02019; performance metrics for predicting BTMs. We trained fifteen ML models predicting &#x003b2;-CTx, T-P1NP, and N-MID based on the training set data and tested each model on the test set data for performance evaluation metrics including AUROC, accuracy, precision, recall, F1-score, Brier score, and AP, and 1,000 times resampling using Bootstrap to improve the robustness of the model predictions. Based on the confusion matrix and ROC curves, the CatBoost model has higher accuracy and robustness in predicting &#x003b2;-CTx, T-P1NP, and N-MID compared to other models (<xref rid="fig-2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>, <xref rid="supp-5" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figs. S1</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="supp-8" ref-type="supplementary-material">S4</xref>). The AUROC (95% CI) for predicting &#x003b2;- CTx, T-P1NP and N-MID were 0.782 [0.683&#x02013;0.885], 0.789 [0.691&#x02013;0.874], and 0.727 [0.619&#x02013;0.827], respectively.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="table-3"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19483/table-3</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Evaluation of performance metrics of five ML models for predicting BTMs (&#x003b2;-CTx/T-P1NP/N-MID).</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-13-19483-g008" position="float"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" content-type="text"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristics</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">SVM</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">RF</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">XGBoost</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">LGBM</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">CatBoost</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUROC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.716/0.683/0.668</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.716/0.764/0.695</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.721/0.688/0.711</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.707/0.675/0.715</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.782/0.789/0.727</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.612&#x02013;0.822]/<break/>[0.576&#x02013;0.792]/<break/>[0.550&#x02013;0.780]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.610&#x02013;0.817]/<break/>[0.668&#x02013;0.858]/<break/>[0.585&#x02013;0.796]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.618&#x02013;0.820]/<break/>[0.574&#x02013;0.798]/<break/>[0.607&#x02013;0.814]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.600&#x02013;0.803]/<break/>[0.558&#x02013;0.782]/<break/>[0.604&#x02013;0.817]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.683&#x02013;0.885]/<break/>[0.691&#x02013;0.874]/<break/>[0.619&#x02013;0.827]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Accuracy (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.07/94.03/82.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.06/88.06/92.54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.07/91.04/94.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.55/89.55/89.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.54/92.54/94.03</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Precision (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.74/90.00/63.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.00/80.95/86.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.19/81.82/84.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.08/77.42/72.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.87/88.37/90.24</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recall (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100/100/100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100/100/100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100/100/100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100/100/100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100/100/100</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F1 score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.808/0.947/0.778</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.857/0.895/0.928</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.865/0.900/0.913</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.896/0.873/0.837</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.912/0.938/0.949</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brier score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.218/0.232/0.234</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.215/0.200/0.223</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.218/0.224/0.232</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.217/0.227/0.233</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.220/0.228/0.231</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.713/0.743/0.695</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.674/0.832/0.699</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.704/0.638/0.720</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.697/0.620/0.769</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.741/0.767/0.676</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-3fn"><p>
<bold>Note:</bold>
</p></fn><fn id="table-3fn1" fn-type="other"><p>SVM, support vector machine; RF, random forest; XGBoost, extreme gradient boosting; LGBM, light gradient boosting machine; CatBoost, category boosting; AUROC, area under the receiver operating characteristic curve; AP, area under the P&#x02013;R curve.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="fig-2"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19483/fig-2</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>The CatBoost model predicting BTMs (&#x003b2;-CTx/T-P1NP/N-MID).</title><p>(A, D, G) The confusion matrices of CatBoost models predicting &#x003b2;-CTx, T-P1NP, and N-MID, respectively. (B, E, H) The ROC curves of CatBoost models predicting &#x003b2;-CTx, T-P1NP, and N-MID, respectively. (C, F, I) The P-R curves of CatBoost models predicting &#x003b2;-CTx, T-P1NP, and N-MID, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-13-19483-g002" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec><title>SHAP features importance and modeling decisions</title><p>The SHAP global summary plot shows the positive and negative impact of all features in the CatBoost model on predicting &#x003b2;-CTx, T-P1NP, and N-MID, sorted by the importance of each feature&#x02019;s contribution to the model output. The model SHAP values suggested a negative correlation between TyG index and BMI for the prediction of BTMs (&#x003b2;-CTx, T-P1NP, N-MID) (<xref rid="fig-3" ref-type="fig">Figs. 3A</xref>, <xref rid="fig-4" ref-type="fig">4A</xref>, and <xref rid="fig-5" ref-type="fig">5A</xref>). The SHAP summary plot suggests that the most important features for predicting &#x003b2;-CTx, T-P1NP, and N-MID in the CatBoost model are BMI, BMI, and HbA1c, respectively (<xref rid="fig-3" ref-type="fig">Figs. 3B</xref>, <xref rid="fig-4" ref-type="fig">4B</xref>, and <xref rid="fig-5" ref-type="fig">5B</xref>). The SHAP individual decision plot reveals the individual prediction of BTMs (&#x003b2;-CTx, T-P1NP, N-MID) for each feature in the CatBoost model (<xref rid="fig-3" ref-type="fig">Figs. 3C</xref>, <xref rid="fig-4" ref-type="fig">4C</xref>, and <xref rid="fig-5" ref-type="fig">5C</xref>). In the decision plot, the gray vertical line represents the base value of the CatBoost model&#x02019;s prediction of BTMs, the red curve indicates a positive prediction of BTMs, and the blue curve indicates a negative prediction of BTMs. The decision curves reflect the specific contribution of each feature to the CatBoost model&#x02019;s BTMs prediction and label the SHAP value of each feature.</p><fig position="float" id="fig-3"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19483/fig-3</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>The CatBoost model predicts the SHAP interpretation of &#x003b2;-CTx (top 15 features).</title><p>(A) The SHAP global summary plot. (B) The SHAP features importance. (C) The SHAP individual decision plot. (D) The SHAP top 50 individual decision plot.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-13-19483-g003" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="fig-4"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19483/fig-4</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>The CatBoost model predicts the SHAP interpretation of T-P1NP (top 15 features).</title><p>(A) The SHAP global summary plot. (B) The SHAP features importance. (C) The SHAP individual decision plot. (D) The SHAP top 50 individual decision plot.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-13-19483-g004" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="fig-5"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19483/fig-5</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>The CatBoost model predicts the SHAP interpretation of N-MID (top 15 features).</title><p>(A) The SHAP global summary plot. (B) The SHAP features importance. (C) The SHAP individual decision plot. (D) The SHAP top 50 individual decision plot.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-13-19483-g005" position="float"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Our study explored the relationship between the TyG index and bone metabolism and remodeling in prepubertal children, revealing some important findings: (1) The TyG index was negatively correlated with &#x003b2;-CTx, T-P1NP, and N-MID, and this relationship remained significant when adjusting for more confounding factors. This demonstrates that IR inhibits bone metabolism and bone remodeling in prepubertal children. (2) Significant dose-response effects of the TyG index with &#x003b2;-CTx, T-P1NP, and N-MID were observed when the TyG index was &#x02265;8.74, &#x02265;8.44, and &#x02265;8.74, respectively. This suggests that there exists a threshold for IR to inhibit bone metabolism and bone remodeling in prepubertal children, with significant dose-response effects on bone remodeling and bone metabolism only when TyG index &#x02265;8.74, &#x02265;8.44, and &#x02265;8.74, respectively. (3) The TyG index can be used as an important independent predictor for constructing the CatBoost model to predict the state of bone metabolism and bone remodeling in prepubertal children, which is important for clinical monitoring of bone health.</p><p>This is the first study on prepubertal children to employ an interpretable ML framework in a retrospective cohort study to investigate the association between the TyG index and BTMs (&#x003b2;-CTx, T-P1NP, and N-MID). The SHAP-based CatBoost model combines powerful predictive performance and interpretation capabilities for bone metabolism monitoring scenarios in prepubertal children that require high-accuracy prediction and model transparency. This combination enhances the usability and credibility of the model and provides strong support for clinical decision-making. In contrast to the increased BMD in children with high BMI found by <xref rid="ref-42" ref-type="bibr">Tahani et al. (2021)</xref>, the present study suggests that IR may lead to negative regulation of bone metabolism from the perspective of bone metabolism markers, providing a new perspective to explain the high fracture risk in children with high BMI. Although similar reports of using ML to predict bone health in prepubertal children using BTMs have not been found, we still compared them with ML models that predict osteoporosis in adults. <xref rid="ref-5" ref-type="bibr">Baik et al. (2024)</xref> constructed an ML diagnostic model for predicting osteoporosis in adults using BTM and demographic variables, and their best model was LGBM with an internally validated AUC of 0.706, whereas the CatBoost model AUCs of 0.782, 0.789, and 0.727 suggested better predictive performance and robustness, respectively.</p><p>The CatBoost model as our optimal model for predicting BTMs may be related to its many advantages. The CatBoost model has a variety of regularization means (<italic toggle="yes">e.g</italic>., using Ordered Boosting) that can effectively prevent data overfitting, especially when the data size is small (<xref rid="ref-22" ref-type="bibr">Hu et al., 2024</xref>). For medical data, where the sample size for training and validating the model is often small, the generalization ability of the model is crucial for the generalization of the findings, and the CatBoost model also has the advantage of being efficient, robust, and dealing with categorical features. In addition, the CatBoost model provides a variety of model interpretability tools (<italic toggle="yes">e.g</italic>., SHAP) that can help users understand the basis of the model&#x02019;s decisions, which is particularly important in the field of medical diagnosis, where clinicians need to understand the reasons for the model&#x02019;s judgments (<xref rid="ref-19" ref-type="bibr">Fieggen et al., 2022</xref>).</p><p><xref rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al. (2024)</xref> suggested that based on the available evidence, the sensitivity and specificity of TyG for the diagnosis of IR were 96.5% and 85.0%, respectively, and that TyG could be used as a reliable and easily evaluated alternative measure of IR. Studies have shown that T2DM increases BMD yet also raises fracture risk, likely due to factors such as abnormal bone metabolism, reduced bone turnover, lower bone mass, and altered bone microarchitecture (<xref rid="ref-41" ref-type="bibr">Sun et al., 2023</xref>). These findings suggest that BMD alone is insufficient as an indicator for assessing osteoporosis risk. <xref rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr">Gkastaris et al. (2020)</xref> demonstrated that the positive impact of increased mechanical loading on BMD associated with obesity may depend on the site of weight-bearing. Conversely, low-grade systemic inflammation and elevated bone marrow adipogenesis resulting from obesity may exert negative effects on bone health (<xref rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr">Gkastaris et al., 2020</xref>). These findings align with our study, which demonstrated that BMI was positively correlated with the SII, lumbar BMD, and total body less head (TBLH) BMD Z-scores while being negatively correlated with serum levels of &#x003b2;-CTx, T-P1NP, and N-MID. Furthermore, the SHAP summary plot revealed that elevated TyG index and BMI values were negatively associated with the predictive values of &#x003b2;-CTx, T-P1NP, and N-MID. <xref rid="ref-33" ref-type="bibr">Rand et al. (2023)</xref> showed that baseline bone-specific alkaline phosphatase, &#x003b2;-CTx, osteocalcin, and T-P1NP levels in healthy children and adolescents were positively correlated with subsequent changes in total BMD/BMC. The foundation of skeletal fragility in old age is partially established during childhood and adolescence, and the accumulation of bone mass during this period contributes largely to peak bone mass. Combined with our findings, we hypothesize that childhood obesity may be associated with the risk of skeletal fragility in adulthood or old age.</p><p>1,25(OH)<sub>2</sub>D and phosphorus are essential components for maintaining various biological functions in humans, playing critical roles in energy metabolism and bone mineralization (<xref rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr">Jin, Bertholf &#x00026; Yi, 2023</xref>). Phosphorus deficiency can lead to musculoskeletal disorders, whereas phosphorus excess may cause ectopic calcification of tissues and organs, increasing mortality risk. The regulation of phosphate homeostasis is primarily controlled by PTH, 1,25(OH)<sub>2</sub>D, and fibroblast growth factor 23 (FGF23) (<xref rid="ref-30" ref-type="bibr">Peacock, 2021</xref>). Studies have demonstrated associations between FGF23, obesity, and kidney disease, with FGF23 positively correlated with total body fat percentage, visceral fat, and male-pattern adipose tissue while showing a negative correlation with lean body mass (<xref rid="ref-29" ref-type="bibr">Parente et al., 2023</xref>). Additionally, <xref rid="ref-25" ref-type="bibr">Karampatsou et al. (2022)</xref> concluded that FGF23, osteoblasts, and osteosclerotic proteins are influenced by overweight and obesity, varying with BMI, and highlighted the interplay between adipose and bone tissues. These findings align with our results, which revealed that FGF23 levels were higher in the obese group compared to the overweight and healthy weight groups.</p><p>Our study has several strengths and limitations. First, interpretable ML aims to strike a balance between prediction accuracy and model comprehensibility, making it a powerful tool for researchers and practitioners, particularly in contexts where the transparency and reliability of results are critical. Second, we constructed a total of fifteen models using five ML algorithms and ultimately selected the best-performing CatBoost model. This model was further combined with a traditional linear regression model to overcome the drawback of linear models that are difficult to capture nonlinear variables and provide a comprehensive analysis of the relationship between the TyG index and BTMs. Third, the CatBoost model we constructed can provide a reliable skeletal metabolism monitoring tool for prepubertal children with IR, which has important clinical applications. Although our model performs well, there may be some population limitations due to geographic constraints of the sample source. Future studies should introduce cross-regional and multi-ethnic samples to improve the model&#x02019;s generalization ability.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>This study demonstrated for the first time that the TyG index can be used as a potential biomarker for assessing bone metabolic status in prepubertal children and provided accurate and highly interpretable predictive results by CatBoost modeling. In the future, its applicability in multicenter samples should be further validated and clinical tools based on this model should be developed. Applying the methods of this study to the management of bone health in prepubertal obese children may significantly reduce the risk of skeletal fragility in adulthood or old age.</p></sec><sec id="supplemental-information" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplemental Information</title><supplementary-material id="supp-1" position="float" content-type="local-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19483/supp-1</object-id><label>Supplemental Information 1</label><caption><title>R code and raw data for Tables 1 and 2.</title></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-13-19483-s001.rar"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="supp-2" position="float" content-type="local-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19483/supp-2</object-id><label>Supplemental Information 2</label><caption><title>Part of the Python code and the raw data for Table 3 and Figures 2-9.</title></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-13-19483-s002.rar"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="supp-3" position="float" content-type="local-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19483/supp-3</object-id><label>Supplemental Information 3</label><caption><title>Part of the Python code.</title></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-13-19483-s003.rar"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="supp-4" position="float" content-type="local-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19483/supp-4</object-id><label>Supplemental Information 4</label><caption><title>Categorized Data R Code.</title></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-13-19483-s004.rar"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="supp-5" position="float" content-type="local-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19483/supp-5</object-id><label>Supplemental Information 5</label><caption><title>The SVM model predicting BTMs (&#x003b2;-CTx/ T-P1NP/ N-MID).</title><p>(A), (D), and (G) Denote the confusion matrices of SVM models predicting &#x003b2;-CTx, T-P1NP, and N-MID, respectively. (B), (E), and (H) Denote the ROC curves of SVM models predicting &#x003b2;-CTx, T-P1NP, and N-MID, respectively. (C), (F), and (I) Denote the P-R curves of SVM models predicting &#x003b2;-CTx, T-P1NP, and N-MID, respectively.</p></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-13-19483-s005.png"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="supp-6" position="float" content-type="local-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19483/supp-6</object-id><label>Supplemental Information 6</label><caption><title>The XGBoost model predicting BTMs (&#x003b2;-CTx/ T-P1NP/ N-MID).</title><p>(A), (D), and (G) Denote the confusion matrices of XGBoost models predicting &#x003b2;-CTx, T-P1NP, and N-MID, respectively. (B), (E), and (H) Denote the ROC curves of XGBoost models predicting &#x003b2;-CTx, T-P1NP, and N-MID, respectively. (C), (F), and (I) Denote the P-R curves of XGBoost models predicting &#x003b2;-CTx, T-P1NP, and N-MID, respectively.</p></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-13-19483-s006.png"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="supp-7" position="float" content-type="local-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19483/supp-7</object-id><label>Supplemental Information 7</label><caption><title>The RF model predicting BTMs (&#x003b2;-CTx/ T-P1NP/ N-MID).</title><p>(A), (D), and (G) Denote the confusion matrices of RF models predicting &#x003b2;-CTx, T-P1NP, and N-MID, respectively. (B), (E), and (H) Denote the ROC curves of RF models predicting &#x003b2;-CTx, T-P1NP, and N-MID, respectively. (C), (F), and (I) Denote the P-R curves of RF models predicting &#x003b2;-CTx, T-P1NP, and N-MID, respectively.</p></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-13-19483-s007.png"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="supp-8" position="float" content-type="local-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19483/supp-8</object-id><label>Supplemental Information 8</label><caption><title>The LGBM model predicting BTMs (&#x003b2;-CTx/ T-P1NP/ N-MID).</title><p>(A), (D), and (G) Denote the confusion matrices of LGBM models predicting &#x003b2;-CTx, T-P1NP, and N-MID, respectively. (B), (E), and (H) Denote the ROC curves of LGBM models predicting &#x003b2;-CTx, T-P1NP, and N-MID, respectively. (C), (F), and (I) Denote the P-R curves of LGBM models predicting &#x003b2;-CTx, T-P1NP, and N-MID, respectively.</p></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-13-19483-s008.png"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="supp-9" position="float" content-type="local-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19483/supp-9</object-id><label>Supplemental Information 9</label><caption><title>The initial variables of the model.</title></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-13-19483-s009.docx"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank all participants who agreed to participate in the study.</p></ack><sec sec-type="additional-information"><title>Additional Information and Declarations</title><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing Interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec sec-type="author-contributions"><title>Author Contributions</title><p><xref rid="author-1" ref-type="contrib">Shunshun Cao</xref> conceived and designed the experiments, analyzed the data, authored or reviewed drafts of the article, and approved the final draft.</p><p><xref rid="author-2" ref-type="contrib">Aolei Chen</xref> conceived and designed the experiments, performed the experiments, prepared figures and/or tables, authored or reviewed drafts of the article, and approved the final draft.</p><p><xref rid="author-3" ref-type="contrib">Botian Song</xref> conceived and designed the experiments, performed the experiments, prepared figures and/or tables, authored or reviewed drafts of the article, and approved the final draft.</p><p><xref rid="author-4" ref-type="contrib">Yangyang Hu</xref> conceived and designed the experiments, analyzed the data, authored or reviewed drafts of the article, and approved the final draft.</p></sec><sec sec-type="other"><title>Human Ethics</title><p>The following information was supplied relating to ethical approvals (<italic toggle="yes">i.e</italic>., approving body and any reference numbers):</p><p>The Ethics Committee of the Second Affiliated Hospital of Wenzhou Medical University approved the study in its facilities (Ethics Application Ref. 2024-K-031-02).</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data Availability</title><p>The following information was supplied regarding data availability:</p><p>The original data and code are available in the <xref rid="supplemental-information" ref-type="sec">Supplemental Files</xref>.</p></sec></sec><ref-list content-type="authoryear"><title>References</title><ref id="ref-1"><label>Abdollahian et al. (2023)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Abdollahian</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ghazizadeh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mohammadi-Bajgiran</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pashirzad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yaghooti Khorasani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bohn</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Steele</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roudi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kamel Khodabandeh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ghazi Zadeh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alami-Arani</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Badakhshan</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Esmaily</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ferns</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Assaran-Darban</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Adeli</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ghayour-Mobarhan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Age-specific reference intervals for routine biochemical parameters in healthy neonates, infants, and young children in Iran</article-title><source>Journal of Cellular and Molecular Medicine</source><year iso-8601-date="2023">2023</year><volume>27</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>158</fpage><lpage>162</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jcmm.17646</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36524863</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-2"><label>Ani&#x0015b;ko, Siatkowski &#x00026; W&#x000f3;jcik (2024)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ani&#x0015b;ko</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Siatkowski</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>W&#x000f3;jcik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Body mass composition analysis as a predictor of overweight and obesity in children and adolescents</article-title><source>Frontiers in Public Health</source><year iso-8601-date="2024">2024</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1371420</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2024.1371420</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38721538</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-3"><label>Aslan &#x000c7;in et al. (2020)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Aslan &#x000c7;in</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yard&#x00131;mc&#x00131;</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ko&#x000e7;</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>U&#x000e7;akt&#x000fc;rk</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ak&#x000e7;il Ok</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Triglycerides/high-density lipoprotein cholesterol is a predictor similar to the triglyceride-glucose index for the diagnosis of metabolic syndrome using International Diabetes Federation criteria of insulin resistance in obese adolescents: a cross-sectional study</article-title><source>Journal of Pediatric Endocrinology &#x00026; Metabolism: JPEM</source><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><volume>33</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>777</fpage><lpage>784</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1515/jpem-2019-0310</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32447329</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-4"><label>Badakhshan et al. (2023)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Badakhshan</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ghazizadeh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mohammadi-Bajgiran</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Esmaily</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Khorasani</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bohn</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pashirzad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Khodabandeh</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zadeh</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alami-Arani</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rahimi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ferns</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Boskabadi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Assaran-Darban</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Adeli</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ghayour-Mobarhan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Age-specific reference intervals for liver function tests in healthy neonates, infants, and young children in Iran</article-title><source>Journal of Clinical Laboratory Analysis</source><year iso-8601-date="2023">2023</year><volume>37</volume><issue>23&#x02013;24</issue><elocation-id>e24995</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jcla.24995</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38087776</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-5"><label>Baik et al. (2024)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Baik</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Machine learning model for osteoporosis diagnosis based on bone turnover markers</article-title><source>Health Informatics Journal</source><year iso-8601-date="2024">2024</year><volume>30</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>14604582241270778</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/14604582241270778</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39115269</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-6"><label>Bilinski, Paradowski &#x00026; Sypniewska (2020)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bilinski</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Paradowski</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sypniewska</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Bone health and hyperglycemia in pediatric populations</article-title><source>Critical Reviews in Clinical Laboratory Sciences</source><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><volume>57</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>444</fpage><lpage>457</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10408363.2020.1739619</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32216595</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-7"><label>Blazek et al. (2021)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Blazek</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Van Zwieten</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Saglimbene</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Teixeira-Pinto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>A practical guide to multiple imputation of missing data in nephrology</article-title><source>Kidney International</source><year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year><volume>99</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>68</fpage><lpage>74</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.kint.2020.07.035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32822702</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-8"><label>Cao &#x00026; Hu (2024)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Interpretable machine learning framework to predict gout associated with dietary fiber and triglyceride-glucose index</article-title><source>Nutrition &#x00026; Metabolism</source><year iso-8601-date="2024">2024</year><volume>21</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>25</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12986-024-00802-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38745171</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-9"><label>Chen et al. (2023)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>An artificial intelligence-based prognostic prediction model for hemorrhagic stroke</article-title><source>European Journal of Radiology</source><year iso-8601-date="2023">2023</year><volume>167</volume><fpage>111081</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejrad.2023.111081</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37716178</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-10"><label>Chen et al. (2024)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McDowell</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ditchfield</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gue</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lip</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Exploring the prognostic impact of triglyceride-glucose index in critically ill patients with first-ever stroke: insights from traditional methods and machine learning-based mortality prediction</article-title><source>Cardiovascular Diabetology</source><year iso-8601-date="2024">2024</year><volume>23</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>443</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12933-024-02538-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39695656</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-11"><label>Chung, Krenek &#x00026; Magge (2023)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Krenek</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Magge</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Childhood obesity and cardiovascular disease risk</article-title><source>Current Atherosclerosis Reports</source><year iso-8601-date="2023">2023</year><volume>25</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>405</fpage><lpage>415</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11883-023-01111-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37256483</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-12"><label>Cipriani et al. (2022)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cipriani</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Minisola</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Colangelo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Martino</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ferrone</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Biamonte</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Danese</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sonato</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Santori</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Occhiuto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pepe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>FGF23 functions and disease</article-title><source>Minerva Endocrinology</source><year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year><volume>47</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>437</fpage><lpage>448</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.23736/S2724-6507.21.03378-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33792238</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-13"><label>Dang et al. (2024)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ming</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The association between triglyceride-glucose index and its combination with obesity indicators and cardiovascular disease: NHANES 2003&#x02013;2018</article-title><source>Cardiovascular Diabetology</source><year iso-8601-date="2024">2024</year><volume>23</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>8</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12933-023-02115-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38184598</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-14"><label>Dicken &#x00026; Batterham (2024)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dicken</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Batterham</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Ultra-processed food and obesity: what is the evidence</article-title><source>Current Nutrition Reports</source><year iso-8601-date="2024">2024</year><volume>13</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>38</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13668-024-00517-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38294671</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-15"><label>Dole et al. (2024)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dole</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Betancourt-Torres</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kaya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Obata</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schurman</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yee</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Khanal</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Luna</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Salinas</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Miclau</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Acevedo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alliston</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>High-fat and high-carbohydrate diets increase bone fragility through TGF-&#x003b2;-dependent control of osteocyte function</article-title><source>JCI Insight</source><year iso-8601-date="2024">2024</year><volume>9</volume><issue>16</issue><elocation-id>e175103</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/jci.insight.175103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39171528</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-16"><label>Eckert-Lind et al. (2020)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Eckert-Lind</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Busch</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Biro</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Br&#x000e4;uner</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Juul</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Worldwide secular trends in age at pubertal onset assessed by breast development among girls: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>JAMA Pediatrics</source><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><volume>174</volume><issue>4</issue><elocation-id>e195881</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamapediatrics.2019.5881</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32040143</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-17"><label>Fan et al. (2023)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Construction and validation of prognostic models in critically Ill patients with sepsis-associated acute kidney injury: interpretable machine learning approach</article-title><source>Journal of Translational Medicine</source><year iso-8601-date="2023">2023</year><volume>21</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>406</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12967-023-04205-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37349774</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-18"><label>Fang et al. (2022)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>She</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Adipose tissue spexin in physical exercise and age-associated diseases</article-title><source>Ageing Research Reviews</source><year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>101509</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arr.2021.101509</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34752956</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-19"><label>Fieggen et al. (2022)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fieggen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Arora</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Segal</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The role of machine learning in HIV risk prediction</article-title><source>Frontiers in Reproductive Health</source><year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1062387</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/frph.2022.1062387</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36619681</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-20"><label>Fuglsang-Nielsen et al. (2022)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fuglsang-Nielsen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rakvaag</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vestergaard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hermansen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gregersen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Starup-Linde</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The effects of 12-weeks whey protein supplements on markers of bone turnover in adults with abdominal obesity-a post hoc analysis</article-title><source>Frontiers in Endocrinology</source><year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>832897</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fendo.2022.832897</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35422766</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-21"><label>Gkastaris et al. (2020)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gkastaris</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goulis</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Potoupnis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Anastasilakis</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kapetanos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Obesity, osteoporosis and bone metabolism</article-title><source>Journal of Musculoskeletal &#x00026; Neuronal Interactions</source><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><volume>20</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>372</fpage><lpage>381</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32877973</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-22"><label>Hu et al. (2024)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Building gender-specific sexually transmitted infection risk prediction models using CatBoost algorithm and NHANES data</article-title><source>BMC Medical Informatics and Decision Making</source><year iso-8601-date="2024">2024</year><volume>24</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>24</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12911-024-02426-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38267946</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-23"><label>Huang et al. (2023)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>He</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>TyG-BMI and hypertension in Normoglycemia subjects in Japan: a cross-sectional study</article-title><source>Diabetes &#x00026; Vascular Disease Research</source><year iso-8601-date="2023">2023</year><volume>20</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>14791641231173617</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/14791641231173617</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37209031</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-24"><label>Jin, Bertholf &#x00026; Yi (2023)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bertholf</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Advances and challenges in the measurement of 1,25-dihydroxyvitamin D: a comprehensive review</article-title><source>Critical Reviews in Clinical Laboratory Sciences</source><year iso-8601-date="2023">2023</year><volume>60</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>535</fpage><lpage>548</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10408363.2023.2212765</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37272827</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-25"><label>Karampatsou et al. (2022)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Karampatsou</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Paltoglou</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Genitsaridi</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kassari</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Charmandari</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The effect of a comprehensive life-style intervention program of diet and exercise on four bone-derived proteins, FGF-23, osteopontin, NGAL and sclerostin, in overweight or obese children and adolescents</article-title><source>Nutrients</source><year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>3772</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/nu14183772</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36145151</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-26"><label>Lappe et al. (2015)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lappe</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gilsanz</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hangartner</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kalkwarf</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oberfield</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shepherd</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Winer</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zemel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The longitudinal effects of physical activity and dietary calcium on bone mass accrual across stages of pubertal development</article-title><source>Journal of Bone and Mineral Research</source><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><volume>30</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>156</fpage><lpage>164</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jbmr.2319</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25130421</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-27"><label>Liang et al. (2022)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jian</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The causal impact of childhood obesity on bone mineral density and fracture in adulthood: a two-sample Mendelian randomization study</article-title><source>Frontiers in Nutrition</source><year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>945125</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnut.2022.945125</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36185695</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-28"><label>L&#x000f3;pez-Peralta et al. (2022)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>L&#x000f3;pez-Peralta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Romero-Velarde</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>V&#x000e1;squez-Garibay</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez-Hita</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Robles-Robles</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ruiz-Gonz&#x000e1;lez</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>P&#x000e9;rez-Romero</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Bone mineral density and body composition in normal weight, overweight and obese children</article-title><source>BMC Pediatrics</source><year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>249</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12887-022-03317-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35513881</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-29"><label>Parente et al. (2023)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Parente</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ahola</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lehto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Groop</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The relationship between FGF23 and body composition according to albuminuria stage in type 1 diabetes</article-title><source>Diabetes Research and Clinical Practice</source><year iso-8601-date="2023">2023</year><volume>198</volume><fpage>110620</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.diabres.2023.110620</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36914006</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-30"><label>Peacock (2021)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Peacock</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Phosphate metabolism in health and disease</article-title><source>Calcified Tissue International</source><year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year><volume>108</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00223-020-00686-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32266417</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-31"><label>Peinado Fabregat, Saynina &#x00026; Sanders (2023)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Peinado Fabregat</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Saynina</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sanders</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Obesity and overweight among children with medical complexity</article-title><source>Pediatrics</source><year iso-8601-date="2023">2023</year><volume>151</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>e2022058687</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2022-058687</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36572640</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-32"><label>Quarta et al. (2023)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Quarta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guarino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tripodi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Giannini</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chiarelli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Blasetti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Diet and glycemic index in children with Type 1 diabetes</article-title><source>Nutrients</source><year iso-8601-date="2023">2023</year><volume>15</volume><issue>16</issue><fpage>3507</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/nu15163507</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37630698</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-33"><label>Rand et al. (2023)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rand</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Diemar</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>M&#x000f8;llehave</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Heidemann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thuesen</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Johannesen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schou</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wedderkopp</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>M&#x000f8;lgaard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>J&#x000f8;rgensen</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Z-scores of bone turnover markers calculated from new established sex- and age-specific reference curves are associated to future change in BMD in children and adolescents</article-title><source>Bone</source><year iso-8601-date="2023">2023</year><volume>167</volume><fpage>116641</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bone.2022.116641</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36481707</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-34"><label>Riley et al. (2020)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Riley</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ensor</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Snell</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Harrell</surname><given-names>FE</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>
<name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reitsma</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moons</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Van Smeden</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Calculating the sample size required for developing a clinical prediction model</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><volume>368</volume><fpage>m441</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.m441</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32188600</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-35"><label>Rinonapoli et al. (2021)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rinonapoli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pace</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ruggiero</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ceccarini</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bisaccia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Meccariello</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Caraffa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Obesity and bone: a complex relationship</article-title><source>International Journal of Molecular Sciences</source><year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year><volume>22</volume><issue>24</issue><fpage>13662</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms222413662</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34948466</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-36"><label>Schini et al. (2023)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vilaca</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gossiel</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Salam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eastell</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Bone turnover markers: basic biology to clinical applications</article-title><source>Endocrine Reviews</source><year iso-8601-date="2023">2023</year><volume>44</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>417</fpage><lpage>473</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/endrev/bnac031</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36510335</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-37"><label>Singh et al. (2023)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gogtay</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yekula</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Soni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tripathi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Detection of colorectal adenomas using artificial intelligence models in patients with chronic hepatitis C</article-title><source>World Journal of Hepatology</source><year iso-8601-date="2023">2023</year><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>115</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4254/wjh.v15.i1.107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36744168</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-38"><label>Singh et al. (2020)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maurya</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yadav</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Machine learning method using position-specific mutation based classification outperforms one hot coding for disease severity prediction in haemophilia &#x02018;A&#x02019;</article-title><source>Genomics</source><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><volume>112</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>5122</fpage><lpage>5128</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ygeno.2020.09.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32927010</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-39"><label>Sohouli et al. (2024)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sohouli</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bagheri</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fatahi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rohani</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The effects of weight loss interventions on children and adolescents with non-alcoholic fatty liver disease: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Obesity Science &#x00026; Practice</source><year iso-8601-date="2024">2024</year><volume>10</volume><issue>3</issue><elocation-id>e758</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/osp4.758</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38682153</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-40"><label>Sun et al. (2025)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>An</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lian</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Triglyceride glucose (TyG) index: a promising biomarker for diagnosis and treatment of different diseases</article-title><source>European Journal of Internal Medicine</source><year iso-8601-date="2025">2025</year><volume>131</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejim.2024.08.026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39510865</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-41"><label>Sun et al. (2023)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Association analysis of triglyceride glucose-body mass index and bone turnover markers in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus</article-title><source>Diabetes, Metabolic Syndrome and Obesity: Targets and Therapy</source><year iso-8601-date="2023">2023</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1435</fpage><lpage>1447</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/DMSO.S406849</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37229351</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-42"><label>Tahani et al. (2021)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tahani</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Choudhary</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Boivin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dawson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gittoes</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Geberhiwot</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Very high bone mineral density in a monogenic form of obesity-associated insulin resistance</article-title><source>Bone</source><year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year><volume>143</volume><fpage>115756</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bone.2020.115756</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33197640</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-43"><label>Tahapary et al. (2022)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tahapary</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pratisthita</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fitri</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marcella</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wafa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kurniawan</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rizka</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tarigan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Harbuwono</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Purnamasari</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Soewondo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Challenges in the diagnosis of insulin resistance: focusing on the role of HOMA-IR and Tryglyceride/glucose index</article-title><source>Diabetes &#x00026; Metabolic Syndrome</source><year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year><volume>16</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>102581</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.dsx.2022.102581</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35939943</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-44"><label>Tang et al. (2022)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Geng</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Systemic immune-inflammation index and bone mineral density in postmenopausal women: a cross-sectional study of the national health and nutrition examination survey (NHANES) 2007&#x02013;2018</article-title><source>Frontiers in Immunology</source><year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>975400</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2022.975400</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36159805</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-45"><label>Tao et al. (2022)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hua</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Triglyceride-glucose index as a marker in cardiovascular diseases: landscape and limitations</article-title><source>Cardiovascular Diabetology</source><year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year><volume>21</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>68</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12933-022-01511-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35524263</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-46"><label>Thom et al. (2023)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Thom</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Patsch</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Haufler</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pees</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Albinni</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Male</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Raimann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Evaluation of bone mineral density and bone turnover in children on anticoagulation</article-title><source>Frontiers in Endocrinology</source><year iso-8601-date="2023">2023</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1192670</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fendo.2023.1192670</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37600706</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-47"><label>Vasikaran et al. (2024)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vasikaran</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thambiah</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>RZ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Loh</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The use of bone-turnover markers in asia-pacific populations</article-title><source>Annals of Laboratory Medicine</source><year iso-8601-date="2024">2024</year><volume>44</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>126</fpage><lpage>134</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3343/alm.2023.0214</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37869778</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-48"><label>Wang et al. (2021)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Interpretable prediction of 3-year all-cause mortality in patients with heart failure caused by coronary heart disease based on machine learning and SHAP</article-title><source>Computers in Biology and Medicine</source><year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year><volume>137</volume><fpage>104813</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.compbiomed.2021.104813</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34481185</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-49"><label>Zhang et al. (2023)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Variation of bone turnover markers in childhood and adolescence</article-title><source>International Journal of Clinical Practice</source><year iso-8601-date="2023">2023</year><volume>2023</volume><fpage>5537182</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2023/5537182</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37547099</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>