<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cancer Chemother Pharmacol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cancer Chemother Pharmacol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cancer Chemotherapy and Pharmacology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0344-5704</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1432-0843</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer Berlin Heidelberg</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39998586</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11860999</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">4764</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00280-025-04764-x</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Model-informed development of a cost-saving dosing regimen for enfortumab vedotin</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Op &#x02019;t Hoog</surname><given-names>Catharina JP</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rieborn</surname><given-names>Amy</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Moes</surname><given-names>Dirk Jan AR</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hendrikx</surname><given-names>Jeroen JMA</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>van der Heijden</surname><given-names>Michiel S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Franken</surname><given-names>Mira D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>van der Hulle</surname><given-names>Tom</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff7">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>van Kruchten</surname><given-names>Michel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff8">8</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Willemsen</surname><given-names>Annelieke ECAB</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff9">9</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Koolen</surname><given-names>Stijn LW</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff10">10</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff11">11</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Boerrigter</surname><given-names>Emmy</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>ter Heine</surname><given-names>Rob</given-names></name><address><email>R.terHeine@radboudumc.nl</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/05wg1m734</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.10417.33</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0444 9382</institution-id><institution>Department of Pharmacy, Pharmacology &#x00026; Toxicology - Research Institute for Medical Innovation, </institution><institution>Radboud University Medical Center, </institution></institution-wrap>(route 864), P.O. box 9101, Nijmegen, 6500 HB The Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/05xvt9f17</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.10419.3d</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000000089452978</institution-id><institution>Department of Clinical Pharmacy &#x00026; Toxicology, </institution><institution>Leiden University Medical Centre, </institution></institution-wrap>Leiden, The Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/03xqtf034</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.430814.a</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0674 1393</institution-id><institution>Department of Pharmacy &#x00026; Pharmacology, </institution><institution>Netherlands Cancer Institute (NKI-AVL), </institution></institution-wrap>Amsterdam, The Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/03xqtf034</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.430814.a</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0674 1393</institution-id><institution>Department of Nuclear Medicine, </institution><institution>Netherlands Cancer Institute (NKI-AVL), </institution></institution-wrap>Amsterdam, The Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/03xqtf034</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.430814.a</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0674 1393</institution-id><institution>Department of Medical Oncology, </institution><institution>Netherlands Cancer Institute (NKI-AVL), </institution></institution-wrap>Amsterdam, The Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/05wg1m734</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.10417.33</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0444 9382</institution-id><institution>Department of Medical Oncology, Research Institute for Medical Innovation, </institution><institution>Radboud University Medical Center, </institution></institution-wrap>Nijmegen, The Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff7"><label>7</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/05xvt9f17</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.10419.3d</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000000089452978</institution-id><institution>Department of Medical Oncology, </institution><institution>Leiden University Medical Centre, </institution></institution-wrap>Leiden, The Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff8"><label>8</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/03cv38k47</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.4494.d</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9558 4598</institution-id><institution>Department of Medical Oncology, </institution><institution>University Medical Center Groningen, </institution></institution-wrap>Groningen, The Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff9"><label>9</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/045nawc23</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.413202.6</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0626 2490</institution-id><institution>Department of Internal Medicine, </institution><institution>Tergooi Medical Center, </institution></institution-wrap>Hilversum, The Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff10"><label>10</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/018906e22</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5645.2</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">000000040459992X</institution-id><institution>Department of Medical Oncology, Erasmus MC Cancer Institute, </institution><institution>Erasmus University Medical Center, </institution></institution-wrap>Rotterdam, the Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff11"><label>11</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/018906e22</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5645.2</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0459 992X</institution-id><institution>Department of Clinical Pharmacy, </institution><institution>Erasmus University Medical Center, </institution></institution-wrap>Rotterdam, the Netherlands </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>25</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>25</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>95</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>36</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>27</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>12</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Aim</title><p id="Par1">Enfortumab vedotin is an antibody-drug conjugate (ADC) that has been approved for locally advanced or metastatic urothelial cancer, as monotherapy and in combination with pembrolizumab, and has shown significant benefit in progression-free survival and overall survival for these patients. The economic burden of enfortumab vedotin hampers widespread patient access. The aim of this study was to develop a model-informed alternative dosing regimen that results in equivalent drug exposure while reducing the costs and prevent drug spillage.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">Population pharmacokinetic modelling was used to simulate a dosing regimen leading to equivalent exposure by using the published population pharmacokinetic model in the registration reports. The alternative dosing regimen was based on weight-bands derived from the established non-linear relationship between body weight and systemic exposure, and the usage of whole vials based on fixed doses to prevent spillage. Equivalent exposure compared to the approved body weight-based dosing regimen was defined as conservative equivalent boundaries of 90&#x02013;111% for the calculated geometric mean ratios (GMRs) of area under the concentration-time curve and trough concentration.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">A weight-band based dosing regimen for each dose level of enfortumab vedotin was developed. The GMRs for all pharmacokinetic outcomes were within the predefined equivalence boundaries. In addition, a more even exposure distribution was observed across the body weight quartiles. The average costs savings across all dose levels and per weight-band were approximately 15%.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par4">The proposed alternative dosing regimen shows that drug costs and spillage of enfortumab vedotin can be reduced while maintaining an equivalent and more evenly distributed exposure in treated patients.</p></sec><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1007/s00280-025-04764-x.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="nl"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Enfortumab vedotin</kwd><kwd>Alternative dose</kwd><kwd>Model-informed drug development</kwd><kwd>Urethelial cancer</kwd><kwd>Antibody-drug conjugate</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Springer-Verlag GmbH Germany, part of Springer Nature 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par5">Urothelial cancer (UC) cancer, usually occurring in the bladder, is an aggressive tumor type. Approximately 50% of all patients with muscle-invasive bladder cancer will develop metastatic disease. For decades, median overall survival has been less than 2 years for metastatic urothelial cancer (mUC) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>], highlighting the low efficacy of previous available treatments. Management of advanced or metastatic disease previously consisted of cisplatin or carboplatin-combined with gemcitabine in first-line therapy followed by a programmed death receptor 1/programmed death ligand-1 (PD-1/PD-L1) inhibitor as maintenance therapy (avelumab) or in second-line therapy (pembrolizumab or atezolizumab) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. In recent years, the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) and European Medicines Agency (EMA) approved the antibody-drug conjugate enfortumab vedotin (EV) post-platinum and anti-PD-(L)1 checkpoint inhibitors for previously untreated advanced UC [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. These approvals changed the therapeutic landscape for these patients and significantly improved survival rates.</p><p id="Par6">Enfortumab vedotin is composed of an anti-nectin-4 immunoglobulin G1 kappa monoclonal antibody conjugated to the small molecule microtubule-disrupting agent monomethyl auristatin E (MMAE), via a protease cleavable linker [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Nectin-4, an adhesion protein highly expressed in epithelial cells of various malignant tumors including urothelial cancer, is targeted by enfortumab vedotin. Binding to nectin-4 releases MMAE in the target cells, leading to microtubule disruption, mitotic arrest and apoptotic cell death [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>].</p><p id="Par7">Enfortumab vedotin was first approved as third-line palliative treatment for patients with locally advanced or mUC who had received platinum-containing chemotherapy and disease progression during or after treatment with a PD-1/PD-L1 inhibitor [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Data of the pivotal phase III trial (EV-301) demonstrated that enfortumab vedotin significantly improved overall survival (OS; median 12.9 vs. 9.0 months) compared to investigator-chosen chemotherapy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. More recently, the FDA and EMA approved enfortumab vedotin in combination with pembrolizumab as first-line treatment for patients with locally advanced UC or mUC. The phase III study (EV-302) demonstrated an impressive improvement with the combination therapy compared to platinum-based chemotherapy (median OS 31.5 vs. 16.1 months) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>].</p><p id="Par8">Although enfortumab vedotin results in significant improvement in the outcomes of mUC, the drug comes with a hefty price tag, putting serious strains on healthcare budgets. In previous studies, enfortumab vedotin was not deemed as cost-effective in third-line treatment in the United States, United Kingdom and China at the current price point [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Additionally, enfortumab vedotin is dosed based on a linear body weight dosing algorithm (mg/kg) and the limited vial sizes (e.g., 20 and 30&#x000a0;mg) contribute to drug spillage. Body weight-based dosing can result in opening multiple vials, leading to partial usage and waste [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Furthermore, the linear mg/kg dosing paradigm suggests that the dose is already individualized based on body weight. However, as the true relationship between systemic exposure and body weight is less than proportional, this results in relative underdosing in patients with a low body weight and relative overdosing in patients with a high body weight [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. This is reflected in the fact that high body weight is a risk factor for toxicity of enfortumab vedotin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. As more than half of patients experienced grade&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;3 toxicity (e.g. fatigue, peripheral sensory neuropathy, hyperglycemia or cutaneous toxicity), preventing relative overdosing may result in less toxicity while maintaining efficacy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>].</p><p id="Par9">To reduce drug costs and minimize drug spillage multiple strategies have been proposed, including refund of unused drug amounts of single-use vials, the usage of a single-dose vial for multiple patients, and dose rounding of anticancer agents within margins of 10% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Additionally, alternative dosage regimens such as prolongation of the dosing interval, or usage of fixeddoses could further optimize cancer treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. The FDA supports alternative dosage regimens as evidenced by their guideline for PD-1 and PD-L1 inhibitors, which allow the use of alternative dosage regimens based on population pharmacokinetic modelling and simulation without the need for clinical studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Additionally, the FDA guidance for Clinical Pharmacology Considerations for ADCs encourages evaluation of a broad dosage range, including multiple dosage levels and dosing regimens. It also suggests considering both fixed dose and weight-based dosing in early phase development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Clinical studies of enfortumab vedotin have only investigated mg/kg dosing. Our study aims to propose an alternative weight-band based dosing regimen equivalent to the approved dosing regimen and to explore potential cost savings.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>General approach</title><p id="Par10">We performed a population pharmacokinetic simulation of the approved dosing regimen and an alternative dosing regimen using weight-bands, based on representative demographic data. In the approved dosing regimen, the initial dose starts at 1.25&#x000a0;mg/kg and is capped at 100&#x000a0;kg (125&#x000a0;mg). The dose may be reduced to 1&#x000a0;mg/kg, 0.75&#x000a0;mg/kg, or 0.5&#x000a0;mg/kg when a patient experiences toxicity. Enfortumab vedotin is administered on days 1, 8 and 15 of a 28-day cycle as monotherapy and on days 1 and 8 of a 21-day cycle in combination with pembrolizumab [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. The alternative dosing regimen was developed based on the reported less than proportional relationship between body weight and systemic exposure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Doses were determined using weight-bands, ensuring that only complete vials were used to prevent spillage. The predicted pharmacokinetics of alternative dosing regimen for each individual weight-band had to result in equivalent exposure compared to the population mean pharmacokinetics at the approved dose and the associated pharmacokinetic variability should not significantly increase.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Equivalence definition</title><p id="Par11">The primary endpoints of our pharmacokinetic simulations were the area under the concentration-time curve (AUC) and the trough concentration (C<sub>trough</sub>) of enfortumab vedotin during the first cycle and at steady state. Since in our analysis no dose was increased or intervals were changed, no equivalence criteria were set for maximum concentrations (C<sub>max</sub>). The AUC and C<sub>trough</sub> over the first cycle and at steady state of the approved and the alternative dosing regimen for the whole population are compared to assess equivalence. We used more conservative and strict bioequivalence boundaries of 90&#x02013;111% since ADCs are considered to have a narrow therapeutic window. We thus declared bioequivalence if the geometric mean ratios (GMRs) of the pharmacokinetic endpoints of our study fell within the 0.9&#x02013;1.1 boundaries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Population pharmacokinetic modelling and simulation</title><p id="Par12">For our population pharmacokinetic simulations, the population pharmacokinetic model for enfortumab vedotin as published in the EMA Assessment Report and FDA Multidisciplinary Review was used [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. This two-compartment model described the pharmacokinetics of the intact ADC and the unconjugated MMAE. Since the pharmacokinetics of the cytotoxic payload are described by a linear pharmacokinetic process, the pharmacokinetics of the ADC and the cytotoxic payload are directly proportional [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Therefore, the pharmacokinetics of the intact ADC are used as pharmacokinetic endpoints in the current study. A Monte Carlo simulation was performed using the non-linear mixed effects modeling (NONMEM) software package V7.5 (Icon, Dublin, Ireland). The NONMEM model code can be found in the supplementary material (<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). A fictional cohort of 500 European patients, derived from the European ICRP database in the PopGen virtual human population generator, was used to obtain representative demographic data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>].</p><p id="Par13">First, the AUC and C<sub>trough</sub> after the first cycle and at steady state were calculated from the simulated concentrations of the approved dose levels for enfortumab vedotin monotherapy (1.25&#x000a0;mg/kg, 1.0&#x000a0;mg/kg, 0.75&#x000a0;mg/kg and 0.5&#x000a0;mg/kg). Second, the alternative weight-band dosing regimen, based on the same administration days and a 28-day cycle, is calculated on weight-bands with the use of complete vials, while accounting for the allometric non-linear relationship between body size and pharmacokinetics. For all dosing regimens, the average quantity of drug used, based on the number of complete vials, was calculated for the alternative dosing regimen and compared to complete vials used based on the approved dose, under the assumption of complete spillage of a partially used vial. Fractional cost savings based on saved vials were calculated under the assumption of complete spillage of partially used vials as a &#x0201c;worst case scenario&#x0201d;. Average cost savings on a population level from a Dutch perspective were calculated for enfortumab vedotin monotherapy and combined with pembrolizumab, based on a median duration of treatment of 5 months (5 cycles) and 9.4 months (12 cycles) per patient, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. The average quantity of drug used for each dose was used in the calculation. Drug pricing of enfortumab vedotin per vial in the Netherlands was obtained through governmental data. Costs of Padcev<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> in the Netherlands are &#x020ac; 698 for 20&#x000a0;mg and &#x020ac; 1,047 for 30 mg [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Results</title><p id="Par14">The alternative dosing regimen based on weight-band dosing are shown per dose level in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. The results of the pharmacokinetic predictions and savings are presented in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2A-D</xref> for each dose level. The predicted geometric mean C<sub>trough</sub> and AUC for the alternative dosing regimen were within the equivalence criteria of 90&#x02013;111%, although slightly lower than the approved dosing regimen. Furthermore, the proposed weight-band dosing regimen does not increase the pharmacokinetic variability compared to body weight-based dosing, since difference in coefficients of variation (%CV) in AUC and C<sub>trough</sub> between regimens is negligible. As shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, a more even exposure distribution (AUC) across the body weight ranges can be observed in the alternative dosing regimen compared to the approved regimen. Additional visual representations of the exposure distribution at first cycle and at steady state for each dose level can be found in the supplementary material (Figures <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>A&#x02013;B to <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>A-B). The median AUC and interquartile range (IQR) at first cycle and at steady state for the approved dosing regimen was 2558&#x000a0;mg*h/L (IQR 2162&#x02013;2873&#x000a0;mg*h/L) and 2641&#x000a0;mg*h/L (IQR 2222&#x02013;3005&#x000a0;mg*h/L), respectively. The median AUC and IQR at first cycle and at steady state for the alternative dosing regimen was 2304&#x000a0;mg*h/L (IQR 2014&#x02013;2620&#x000a0;mg*h/L) and 2374&#x000a0;mg*h/L (IQR 2058&#x02013;2714&#x000a0;mg*h/L), respectively. As observed in the Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2A-D</xref>, on a population level approximately 15 to 20% savings in drug expenses can be realized while maintaining equivalent exposure. The average costs per treatment per patient of enfortumab vedotin monotherapy and in combination with pembrolizumab from a Dutch perspective are shown in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">3</xref>.</p><p id="Par15">
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>The alternative dosing regimen based on weight-band dosing for each dose level</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Dose level</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">1.25&#x000a0;mg/kg</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">1.0&#x000a0;mg/kg</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">0.75&#x000a0;mg/kg</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">0.5&#x000a0;mg/kg</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Weight band</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">&#x0003c;&#x02009;45&#x000a0;kg</td><td align="left">50&#x000a0;mg</td><td align="left">40&#x000a0;mg</td><td align="left">30&#x000a0;mg</td><td align="left">20&#x000a0;mg</td></tr><tr><td align="left">45&#x02013;55&#x000a0;kg</td><td align="left">60&#x000a0;mg</td><td align="left">50&#x000a0;mg</td><td align="left">40&#x000a0;mg</td><td align="left">20&#x000a0;mg</td></tr><tr><td align="left">55&#x02013;65&#x000a0;kg</td><td align="left">70&#x000a0;mg</td><td align="left">60&#x000a0;mg</td><td align="left">40&#x000a0;mg</td><td align="left">30&#x000a0;mg</td></tr><tr><td align="left">65&#x02013;75&#x000a0;kg</td><td align="left">80&#x000a0;mg</td><td align="left">60&#x000a0;mg</td><td align="left">50&#x000a0;mg</td><td align="left">30&#x000a0;mg</td></tr><tr><td align="left">75&#x02013;95&#x000a0;kg</td><td align="left">90&#x000a0;mg</td><td align="left">70&#x000a0;mg</td><td align="left">50&#x000a0;mg</td><td align="left">40&#x000a0;mg</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x0003e;&#x02009;95&#x000a0;kg</td><td align="left">100&#x000a0;mg</td><td align="left">80&#x000a0;mg</td><td align="left">60&#x000a0;mg</td><td align="left">40&#x000a0;mg</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par16">
<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2A</label><caption><p>Results of pharmacokinetic simulation for the intact antibody-drug conjugate for dose level 1.25&#x000a0;mg/kg</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Dosing regimen</th><th align="left">AUC first cycle</th><th align="left">C<sub>trough</sub> first cycle</th><th align="left">AUC steady state</th><th align="left">C<sub>trough</sub> steady state</th><th align="left">Quantity of drug used for each dose</th><th align="left">Quantity of drug saved for each dose per weight-band</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Geometric mean (%CV)</th><th align="left">Geometric mean (%CV)</th><th align="left">Geometric mean (%CV)</th><th align="left">Geometric mean (%CV)</th><th align="left">Average</th><th align="left">Average</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">
<bold>Reference dose</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">2510&#x000a0;mg*h/L (22%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">0.25&#x000a0;mg/L (99%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">2589&#x000a0;mg*h/L (23%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">0.29&#x000a0;mg/L (85%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">90.2&#x000a0;mg</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"/></tr><tr><td align="left">1.25&#x000a0;mg/kg</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<bold>Alternative dose</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="7">2284&#x000a0;mg*h/L (21%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="7">0.21&#x000a0;mg/L (99%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="7">2356&#x000a0;mg*h/L (22%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="7">0.26&#x000a0;mg/L (85%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="7">76.5&#x000a0;mg</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">8.5&#x000a0;mg</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x0003c;&#x02009;45&#x000a0;kg: 50&#x000a0;mg</td></tr><tr><td align="left">45&#x02013;55&#x000a0;kg: 60&#x000a0;mg</td><td align="left">7.2&#x000a0;mg</td></tr><tr><td align="left">55&#x02013;65&#x000a0;kg: 70&#x000a0;mg</td><td align="left">10.6&#x000a0;mg</td></tr><tr><td align="left">65&#x02013;75&#x000a0;kg: 80&#x000a0;mg</td><td align="left">13.9&#x000a0;mg</td></tr><tr><td align="left">75&#x02013;95&#x000a0;kg: 90&#x000a0;mg</td><td align="left">17.9&#x000a0;mg</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x0003e;&#x02009;95&#x000a0;kg: 100&#x000a0;mg</td><td align="left">30&#x000a0;mg</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<bold>Ratio Alternative dose/Reference dose</bold>
</td><td align="left">0.910</td><td align="left">0.910</td><td align="left">0.910</td><td align="left">0.910</td><td align="left">0.848</td><td align="left"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par17">
<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 2B</label><caption><p>Results of pharmacokinetic simulation for the intact antibody-drug conjugate for dose level 1&#x000a0;mg/kg</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Dosing regimen</th><th align="left">AUC first cycle</th><th align="left">C<sub>trough</sub> first cycle</th><th align="left">AUC steady state</th><th align="left">C<sub>trough</sub> steady state</th><th align="left">Quantity of drug used for each dose</th><th align="left">Quantity of drug saved for each dose per weight-band</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Geometric mean(%CV)</th><th align="left">Geometric mean (%CV)</th><th align="left">Geometric mean (%CV)</th><th align="left">Geometric mean (%CV)</th><th align="left">Average</th><th align="left">Average</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">
<bold>Reference dose</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">2008&#x000a0;mg*h/L (22%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">0.19&#x000a0;mg/L (99%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">2071&#x000a0;mg*h/L (23%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">0.23&#x000a0;mg/L (85%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">72.9&#x000a0;mg</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"/></tr><tr><td align="left">1.0&#x000a0;mg/kg</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<bold>Alternative dose</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="7">1825&#x000a0;mg*h/L (21%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="7">0.17&#x000a0;mg/L (99%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="7">1883&#x000a0;mg*h/L (22%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="7">0.21&#x000a0;mg/L (84%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="7">70.0&#x000a0;mg</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">8.8&#x000a0;mg</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x0003c;&#x02009;45&#x000a0;kg: 40&#x000a0;mg</td></tr><tr><td align="left">45&#x02013;55&#x000a0;kg: 50&#x000a0;mg</td><td align="left">5.3&#x000a0;mg</td></tr><tr><td align="left">55&#x02013;65&#x000a0;kg: 60&#x000a0;mg</td><td align="left">5.7&#x000a0;mg</td></tr><tr><td align="left">65&#x02013;75&#x000a0;kg: 60&#x000a0;mg</td><td align="left">15.7&#x000a0;mg</td></tr><tr><td align="left">75&#x02013;95&#x000a0;kg: 70&#x000a0;mg</td><td align="left">17.1&#x000a0;mg</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x0003e;&#x02009;95&#x000a0;kg: 80&#x000a0;mg</td><td align="left">20&#x000a0;mg</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<bold>Ratio Alternative dose/Reference dose</bold>
</td><td align="left">0.909</td><td align="left">0.909</td><td align="left">0.909</td><td align="left">0.909</td><td align="left">0.836</td><td align="left"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par18">
<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 2C</label><caption><p>Results of pharmacokinetic simulation for the intact antibody-drug conjugate for dose level 0.75&#x000a0;mg/kg</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Dosing regimen</th><th align="left">AUC first cycle</th><th align="left">C<sub>trough</sub> first cycle</th><th align="left">AUC steady state</th><th align="left">C<sub>trough</sub> steady state</th><th align="left">Quantity of drug used for each dose</th><th align="left">Quantity of drug saved for each dose per weight-band</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Geometric mean(%CV)</th><th align="left">Geometric mean (%CV)</th><th align="left">Geometric mean (%CV)</th><th align="left">Geometric mean (%CV)</th><th align="left">Average</th><th align="left">Average</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">
<bold>Reference dose</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">1506&#x000a0;mg*h/L (22%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">0.14&#x000a0;mg/L (99%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">1553&#x000a0;mg*h/L (23%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">0.17&#x000a0;mg/L (85%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">55.9&#x000a0;mg</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"/></tr><tr><td align="left">0.75&#x000a0;mg/kg</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<bold>Alternative dose</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="7">1365&#x000a0;mg*h/L (22%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="7">0.13&#x000a0;mg/L (100%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="7">1408&#x000a0;mg*h/L (23%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="7">0.16&#x000a0;mg/L (86%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="7">45.6&#x000a0;mg</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">8.8&#x000a0;mg</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x0003c;&#x02009;45&#x000a0;kg: 30&#x000a0;mg</td></tr><tr><td align="left">45&#x02013;55&#x000a0;kg: 40&#x000a0;mg</td><td align="left">1.8&#x000a0;mg</td></tr><tr><td align="left">55&#x02013;65&#x000a0;kg: 40&#x000a0;mg</td><td align="left">10&#x000a0;mg</td></tr><tr><td align="left">65&#x02013;75&#x000a0;kg: 50&#x000a0;mg</td><td align="left">8.1&#x000a0;mg</td></tr><tr><td align="left">75&#x02013;95&#x000a0;kg: 50&#x000a0;mg</td><td align="left">16.6&#x000a0;mg</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x0003e;&#x02009;95&#x000a0;kg: 60&#x000a0;mg</td><td align="left">20&#x000a0;mg</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<bold>Ratio Alternative dose/Reference dose</bold>
</td><td align="left">0.906</td><td align="left">0.906</td><td align="left">0.906</td><td align="left">0.906</td><td align="left">0.814</td><td align="left"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par19">
<table-wrap id="Tab5"><label>Table 2D</label><caption><p>Results of pharmacokinetic simulation for the intact antibody-drug conjugate for dose level 0.5&#x000a0;mg/kg</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Dosing regimen</th><th align="left">AUC first cycle</th><th align="left">C<sub>trough</sub> first cycle</th><th align="left">AUC steady state</th><th align="left">C<sub>trough</sub> steady state</th><th align="left">Quantity of drug used for each dose</th><th align="left">Quantity of drug saved for each dose per weight-band</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Geometric mean(%CV)</th><th align="left">Geometric mean (%CV)</th><th align="left">Geometric mean (%CV)</th><th align="left">Geometric mean (%CV)</th><th align="left">Average</th><th align="left">Average</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">
<bold>Reference dose</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">1004&#x000a0;mg*h/L (22%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">0.09&#x000a0;mg/L (99%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">1036&#x000a0;mg*h/L (23%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">0.11&#x000a0;mg/L (85%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">38.9&#x000a0;mg</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"/></tr><tr><td align="left">0.5&#x000a0;mg/kg</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<bold>Alternative dose</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="7">911&#x000a0;mg*h/L (23%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="7">0.08&#x000a0;mg/L (99%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="7">939&#x000a0;mg*h/L (24%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="7">0.10&#x000a0;mg/L (85%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="7">31.0&#x000a0;mg</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">8.8&#x000a0;mg</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x0003c;&#x02009;45&#x000a0;kg: 20&#x000a0;mg</td></tr><tr><td align="left">45&#x02013;55&#x000a0;kg: 20&#x000a0;mg</td><td align="left">10&#x000a0;mg</td></tr><tr><td align="left">55&#x02013;65&#x000a0;kg: 30&#x000a0;mg</td><td align="left">5.7&#x000a0;mg</td></tr><tr><td align="left">65&#x02013;75&#x000a0;kg: 30&#x000a0;mg</td><td align="left">10&#x000a0;mg</td></tr><tr><td align="left">75&#x02013;95&#x000a0;kg: 40&#x000a0;mg</td><td align="left">6.1&#x000a0;mg</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x0003e;&#x02009;95&#x000a0;kg: 40&#x000a0;mg</td><td align="left">10&#x000a0;mg</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<bold>Ratio Alternative dose/Reference dose</bold>
</td><td align="left">0.907</td><td align="left">0.907</td><td align="left">0.907</td><td align="left">0.907</td><td align="left">0.796</td><td align="left"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par20">
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Boxplots of the predicted enfortumab vedotin steady state AUC per weight quartile of the approved and alternative dosing regimen</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="280_2025_4764_Fig1_HTML" id="d33e1189"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par21">
<table-wrap id="Tab6"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Average costs per treatment per patient on a population level for enfortumab vedotin monotherapy and in combination with pembrolizumab from a Dutch perspective</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="3">Dose level</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Approved dosing regimen</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Alternative dosing regimen</th><th align="left" rowspan="3">Average savings</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Enfortumab vedotin monotherapy</th><th align="left">Enfortumab vedotin combination therapy</th><th align="left">Enfortumab vedotin monotherapy</th><th align="left">Enfortumab vedotin combination therapy</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Average costs per treatment per patient</th><th align="left">Average costs per treatment per patient</th><th align="left">Average costs per treatment per patient</th><th align="left">Average costs per treatment per patient</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">
<bold>1.25&#x000a0;mg/kg</bold>
</td><td align="left">&#x020ac; 47,218.35</td><td align="left">&#x020ac; 75,549.36</td><td align="left">&#x020ac; 40,046.60</td><td align="left">&#x020ac; 64,074.56</td><td align="left">15%</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<bold>1.0&#x000a0;mg/kg</bold>
</td><td align="left">&#x020ac; 38,162.06</td><td align="left">&#x020ac; 61,059.29</td><td align="left">&#x020ac; 36,643.95</td><td align="left">&#x020ac; 58,630.32</td><td align="left">4%</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<bold>0.75&#x000a0;mg/kg</bold>
</td><td align="left">&#x020ac; 29,262.81</td><td align="left">&#x020ac; 46,820.50</td><td align="left">&#x020ac; 23,870.92</td><td align="left">&#x020ac; 38,193.47</td><td align="left">18%</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<bold>0.5&#x000a0;mg/kg</bold>
</td><td align="left">&#x020ac; 20,363.57</td><td align="left">&#x020ac; 32,581.71</td><td align="left">&#x020ac; 16,228.04</td><td align="left">&#x020ac; 25,964.86</td><td align="left">20%</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par22">Our investigation shows that an alternative dosing regimen based on weight-bands for enfortumab vedotin will reduce drug spillage and reduce drug expenses. Up to 20% of drug costs can be saved while maintaining an equivalent exposure for the population across the weight range. Moreover, the observed exposure appears more evenly distributed across the bodyweight range in the alternative regimen compared to the approved regimen. The pharmacokinetic variability with this weight-band dosing regimen does not increase and shows that variability does not increase with weightband dosing compared to linear mg/kg dosing.</p><p id="Par23">The predicted GMRs of the AUC and C<sub>trough</sub> of the alternative dosing regimen lie within the equivalence boundaries for drugs with a narrow therapeutic window. In our analysis, the reduction for all calculated AUC and C<sub>trough</sub> for the whole population in the alternative dosing regimen were less than 10%. In the exposure-response analysis performed by the manufacturer, no statistically significant exposure-efficacy relationship was found for OS. However, a positive trend was observed for the response rate for all exposure quartiles. In this analysis, the average concentrations (C<sub>avg</sub>) was used as the exposure metric [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. Although this metric can be linked to AUC, other metrics, such as C<sub>max</sub> and C<sub>trough</sub>, were not explored. Additionally, exposure levels of MMAE based on C<sub>avg</sub> negatively correlated with OS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. Due to the absence of a significant exposure-efficacy relationship for OS and the observed response across the studied dosing range of 0.5&#x000a0;mg/kg to 1.25&#x000a0;mg/kg, the slight reduction in exposure is unlikely to impact efficacy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. Moreover, in the exposure-response analysis a significant exposure-toxicity relationship was observed. Patients in higher body weight quartiles had a relatively greater exposure, leading to an increased safety risk [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. Specifically, enfortumab vedotin-induced peripheral neuropathy is a common adverse event leading to potentially permanent symptoms and disability, and which could significantly impact treatment adherence and interfere with long-term treatment outcomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. In our analysis, the proposed alternative dosing regimen resulted in a slight reduction in exposure for the population and a more even distribution across all body weight quartiles, which may improve safety and lower the risk of adverse events. This also implies some nuance to the conclusion by the manufacturer that a weight-based dosing regimen suggests a smaller variability in exposure compared to fixed dosing. In their exposure-response analysis, the weight-based dosing regimen was compared to a fixed-dose of 95&#x000a0;mg (based on an average body weight of 75&#x000a0;kg) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>], as opposed to the proposed rounded weight-band dosing regimen in our study. In addition to the accordance of the exposure metrics of the alternative dosing regimen with the FDA guideline for PD-1/PD-L1 inhibitors, the used equivalence boundaries of 90&#x02013;111% in our analysis are conservative. Since our analysis relied on the pharmacokinetic model provided by the manufacturer and employed conservative criteria for equivalence, we propose that this dosing regimen can be readily implemented in clinical practice. Analogous dosing regimens developed through modelling and simulation for PD-1/PD-L1 inhibitors are endorsed by FDA guidelines, supporting their implementation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>].</p><p id="Par24">Major advances in anticancer therapy developments with a hefty price tag support the need for cost reduction. The ADCs are an emerging class of potent anticancer drugs that provide highly effective therapy advances in the treatment of hematologic and solid malignancies. Coupled with these advances are economic challenges related to the ability to pay for these therapies together with the growing number of eligible patients and the expansion of approved indications. Enfortumab vedotin is no exception. In the Netherlands, total costs of enfortumab vedotin monotherapy were over &#x020ac;2,300,000 in 2023 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. Although the results of the phase 3 study in combination with pembrolizumab are impressive, the addition of pembrolizumab will even further increase drug expenses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Furthermore, the shift to first-line therapy will increase the number of eligible patients. It is estimated that in the Netherlands alone around 1,200 patients with advanced or metastatic UC per year will be eligible for the first-line combination therapy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Based on a median 12 cycles per patient [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>], the total costs per patient are estimated to be &#x020ac; 152,411.04 and in total more than &#x020ac; 182,000,000 per year, from a Dutch perspective, with long-term responders having even a more pronounced effect on costs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. This emphasizes the need to optimize the cost-effectiveness of enfortumab vedotin treatment and further reduce the drug costs without compromising effective exposure. In our analysis, a reduction at the 1.25&#x000a0;mg/kg dose level of 15% could be achieved. This could lead to cost savings up to approximately &#x020ac; 22,000 per patient based on whole vials, and a reduction of &#x020ac; 27.000.000 each year from a Dutch perspective. When conducting a cost-effectiveness analysis based on our proposed alternative dosing regimen, all factors remain the same with the exception of the drug costs. Since drug costs will be lower, the alternative dosing regimen will have a higher probability to be cost-effective. Since drug prices of enfortumab vedotin and the variation in body weight may vary across countries, the reduction in costs could potentially be even greater. For example, body weight in the United States of America is generally higher, thus the cost savings of the alternative dosing regimen on a population level will be greater with an increasing body weight [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>].</p><p id="Par25">In addition to the cost savings, using rounded doses based on weight-bands and the use of whole vials can have added benefit in reducing drug spillage compared to individual weight-based dosing with partially used vials. In clinical practice, it may happen that a drug has already been prepared, but the patient is not able to receive the drug. In the case of individual weight-based dosing, the prepared infusion bag will be thrown away, whereas with a rounded dose, the infusion bag could potentially be used for another patient with a similar body weight.</p><p id="Par26">In conclusion, this study shows that drug costs and drug spillage of enfortumab vedotin can be reduced by using a weight-based dosing regimen while maintaining an equivalent exposure and achieving a more evenly distributed exposure across the body weight range. Although potential cost reduction and waste avoidance begins with the manufacturer, the possibilities that are provided with alternative dosing regimens should be further explored by both clinical healthcare providers and government. Since the costs of enfortumab vedotin together with the growing number of patients that are eligible for combination therapy with pembrolizumab are substantial, implementation of the presented alternative dosing regimen should be considered.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.</p><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="280_2025_4764_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><caption><p>Supplementary Material 1</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>Conception and design: CJPOtH, EB and RtH. Acquisition of data (acquired and managed virtual patients): RtH and CJPOtH. Analysis and interpretation of data: All authors. Writing, review, and/or revision of the manuscript: All authors. Final approval of manuscript: All authors.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>Data are available on reasonable request from the authors.Code AvailabilityCode available in the supplemental material.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par27">RtH has received research funding from AMGEN and consulting fees from Samsung Bioepis (paid to the institute). CJPOtH, AR, SK, JH, MvK, DJM, MF, TvdH and EB declare no potential conflicts of interest. MSvdH has received institutional research funding from Bristol Myers Squibb, 4SC, Roche, Merck Sharp &#x00026; Dohme, and AstraZeneca, and consulting fees from Bristol Myers Squibb, Roche, Merck Sharp &#x00026; Dohme, AstraZeneca, Pfizer, Janssen, Seattle Genetics and Daiichi Sankyo.AW has received consulting fees from AstraZeneca, Pfizer, Daiichi-Sankyo and Novartis.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Piombino</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Tonni</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Oltrecolli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pirola</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pipitone</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldessari</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Immunotherapy in urothelial cancer: current status and future directions</article-title><source>Expert Rev Anticancer Ther</source><year>2023</year><volume>23</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1141</fpage><lpage>1155</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14737140.2023.2265572</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37772970</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Piombino C, Tonni E, Oltrecolli M, Pirola M, Pipitone S, Baldessari C et al (2023) Immunotherapy in urothelial cancer: current status and future directions. Expert Rev Anticancer Ther 23(11):1141&#x02013;1155<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37772970</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">National Cancer Institute Surveillance, Epidemiology, and End Results Program (SEER). Cancer Stat Facts: Bladder Cancer: U. S. National Institutes of Health; 2024 [4 June 2024]. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://seer.cancer.gov/statfacts/html/urinb.html">https://seer.cancer.gov/statfacts/html/urinb.html</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Powles</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellmunt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Comperat</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>De Santis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Huddart</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Loriot</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Bladder cancer: ESMO Clinical Practice Guideline for diagnosis, treatment and follow-up</article-title><source>Ann Oncol</source><year>2022</year><volume>33</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>244</fpage><lpage>258</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.annonc.2021.11.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34861372</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Powles T, Bellmunt J, Comperat E, De Santis M, Huddart R, Loriot Y et al (2022) Bladder cancer: ESMO Clinical Practice Guideline for diagnosis, treatment and follow-up. Ann Oncol 33(3):244&#x02013;258<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34861372</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Center for Drug Evaluation and Research (2019) Multi-disciplinary review and evaluation Padcev. Food and Drug Administration (FDA)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Committee for Medicinal Products for Human Use (CHMP) (2022) Public assessment report Padcev. European Medicines Agency (EMA)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Challita-Eid</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Satpayev</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>An</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Shostak</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Enfortumab Vedotin antibody-drug Conjugate Targeting Nectin-4 is a highly potent Therapeutic Agent in multiple preclinical Cancer models</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2016</year><volume>76</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>3003</fpage><lpage>3013</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-15-1313</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27013195</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Challita-Eid PM, Satpayev D, Yang P, An Z, Morrison K, Shostak Y et al (2016) Enfortumab Vedotin antibody-drug Conjugate Targeting Nectin-4 is a highly potent Therapeutic Agent in multiple preclinical Cancer models. Cancer Res 76(10):3003&#x02013;3013<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27013195</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Powles</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonpavde</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Loriot</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Duran</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>EV-301 long-term outcomes: 24-month findings from the phase III trial of enfortumab vedotin versus chemotherapy in patients with previously treated advanced urothelial carcinoma</article-title><source>Ann Oncol</source><year>2023</year><volume>34</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1047</fpage><lpage>1054</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.annonc.2023.08.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37678672</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Rosenberg JE, Powles T, Sonpavde GP, Loriot Y, Duran I, Lee JL et al (2023) EV-301 long-term outcomes: 24-month findings from the phase III trial of enfortumab vedotin versus chemotherapy in patients with previously treated advanced urothelial carcinoma. Ann Oncol 34(11):1047&#x02013;1054<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37678672</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Powles</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonpavde</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Loriot</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Duran</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Enfortumab Vedotin in previously treated Advanced Urothelial Carcinoma</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2021</year><volume>384</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1125</fpage><lpage>1135</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa2035807</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33577729</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Powles T, Rosenberg JE, Sonpavde GP, Loriot Y, Duran I, Lee JL et al (2021) Enfortumab Vedotin in previously treated Advanced Urothelial Carcinoma. N Engl J Med 384(12):1125&#x02013;1135<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33577729</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Powles</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Valderrama</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bedke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kikuchi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffman-Censits</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Enfortumab Vedotin and Pembrolizumab in Untreated Advanced Urothelial Cancer</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2024</year><volume>390</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>875</fpage><lpage>888</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa2312117</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38446675</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Powles T, Valderrama BP, Gupta S, Bedke J, Kikuchi E, Hoffman-Censits J et al (2024) Enfortumab Vedotin and Pembrolizumab in Untreated Advanced Urothelial Cancer. N Engl J Med 390(10):875&#x02013;888<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38446675</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cost-effectiveness of enfortumab vedotin in previously treated advanced urothelial carcinoma</article-title><source>Ther Adv Med Oncol</source><year>2022</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>17588359211068733</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/17588359211068733</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35096146</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Wu Q, Qin Y, Liao W, Zhang M, Yang Y, Zhang P, Li Q (2022) Cost-effectiveness of enfortumab vedotin in previously treated advanced urothelial carcinoma. Ther Adv Med Oncol 14:17588359211068733<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35096146</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bach</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>Conti</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schnorr</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Saltz</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Overspending driven by oversized single dose vials of cancer drugs</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>2016</year><volume>352</volume><fpage>i788</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.i788</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26932932</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Bach PB, Conti RM, Muller RJ, Schnorr GC, Saltz LB (2016) Overspending driven by oversized single dose vials of cancer drugs. BMJ 352:i788<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26932932</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jorga</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Xin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Damico-Beyer</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A guide to rational dosing of monoclonal antibodies</article-title><source>Clin Pharmacokinet</source><year>2012</year><volume>51</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>119</fpage><lpage>135</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2165/11596370-000000000-00000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22257150</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Bai S, Jorga K, Xin Y, Jin D, Zheng Y, Damico-Beyer LA et al (2012) A guide to rational dosing of monoclonal antibodies. Clin Pharmacokinet 51(2):119&#x02013;135<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22257150</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vlachou</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Matoso</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>McConkey</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Jing</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffman-Censits</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enfortumab Vedotin-related cutaneous toxicity and Radiographic Response in patients with Urothelial Cancer: a single-center experience and review of the literature</article-title><source>Eur Urol Open Sci</source><year>2023</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>100</fpage><lpage>103</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.euros.2023.01.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36820243</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Vlachou E, Matoso A, McConkey D, Jing Y, Johnson BA, Hahn NM, Hoffman-Censits J (2023) Enfortumab Vedotin-related cutaneous toxicity and Radiographic Response in patients with Urothelial Cancer: a single-center experience and review of the literature. Eur Urol Open Sci 49:100&#x02013;103<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36820243</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petrylak</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Chia</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name><name><surname>Powles</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Flaig</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name><surname>Loriot</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Impact of exposure on outcomes with enfortumab vedotin in patients with locally advanced or metastatic urothelial cancer</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>2024</year><volume>42</volume><issue>16suppl</issue><fpage>4503</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/JCO.2024.42.16_suppl.4503</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Petrylak DP, Chia YL, Yu EY, Powles T, Flaig TW, Loriot Y et al (2024) Impact of exposure on outcomes with enfortumab vedotin in patients with locally advanced or metastatic urothelial cancer. J Clin Oncol 42(16suppl):4503</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohn</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bach</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Review of current policy strategies to reduce US Cancer Drug costs</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>2020</year><volume>38</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>372</fpage><lpage>379</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/JCO.19.01628</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31804856</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Green AK, Ohn JA, Bach PB (2020) Review of current policy strategies to reduce US Cancer Drug costs. J Clin Oncol 38(4):372&#x02013;379<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31804856</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fahrenbruch</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kintzel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bott</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilmore</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Markham</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dose rounding of Biologic and cytotoxic Anticancer agents: a position Statement of the Hematology/Oncology Pharmacy Association</article-title><source>J Oncol Pract</source><year>2018</year><volume>14</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>e130</fpage><lpage>e6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/JOP.2017.025411</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29400987</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Fahrenbruch R, Kintzel P, Bott AM, Gilmore S, Markham R (2018) Dose rounding of Biologic and cytotoxic Anticancer agents: a position Statement of the Hematology/Oncology Pharmacy Association. J Oncol Pract 14(3):e130&#x02013;e6<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29400987</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Overbeek</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Ter Heine</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Verheul</surname><given-names>HMW</given-names></name><name><surname>Chatelut</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Rudek</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gurney</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Off-label, but on target: the evidence needed to implement alternative dosing regimens of anticancer drugs</article-title><source>ESMO Open</source><year>2023</year><volume>8</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>100749</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.esmoop.2022.100749</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36603522</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Overbeek JK, Ter Heine R, Verheul HMW, Chatelut E, Rudek MA, Gurney H et al (2023) Off-label, but on target: the evidence needed to implement alternative dosing regimens of anticancer drugs. ESMO Open 8(1):100749<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36603522</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Center for Drug Evaluation and Research OCoE (2022) Pharmacokinetic-based criteria for supporting alternative dosing regimens of programmed cell death Receptor-1 (PD-1) or programmed cell death-ligand 1 (PD-L1) blocking antibodies for treatment of patients with Cancer. Food &#x00026; Drug Administration (FDA)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Center for Drug Evaluation and Research, Center for Biologics Evaluation and Research (2024) Clinical pharmacology considerations for antibody-drug conjugates. Food and Drug Administation (FDA)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Center for Drug Evaluation and Research (2023) Supplement approval padcev. Food and Drug Administration (FDA)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Holford</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanism-based concepts of size and maturity in pharmacokinetics</article-title><source>Annu Rev Pharmacol Toxicol</source><year>2008</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>303</fpage><lpage>332</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.pharmtox.48.113006.094708</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17914927</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Anderson BJ, Holford NH (2008) Mechanism-based concepts of size and maturity in pharmacokinetics. Annu Rev Pharmacol Toxicol 48:303&#x02013;332<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17914927</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>LX</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Lionberger</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Makhlouf</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuirmann</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Novel bioequivalence approach for narrow therapeutic index drugs</article-title><source>Clin Pharmacol Ther</source><year>2015</year><volume>97</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>286</fpage><lpage>291</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cpt.28</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25669762</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">Yu LX, Jiang W, Zhang X, Lionberger R, Makhlouf F, Schuirmann DJ et al (2015) Novel bioequivalence approach for narrow therapeutic index drugs. Clin Pharmacol Ther 97(3):286&#x02013;291<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25669762</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McNally</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Cotton</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hogg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Loizou</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PopGen: a virtual human population generator</article-title><source>Toxicology</source><year>2014</year><volume>315</volume><fpage>70</fpage><lpage>85</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tox.2013.07.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23876857</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">McNally K, Cotton R, Hogg A, Loizou G (2014) PopGen: a virtual human population generator. Toxicology 315:70&#x02013;85<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23876857</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Medicijnkosten.nl Zorginstituut Nederland; [8 May 2024]. Available from: www.medicijnkosten.nl</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zuo P, Bonate P, Garg A, Matsangou M, Tang M (2024) Population Pharmacokinetic modeling and exposure-response analysis for the antibody-drug Conjugate Enfortumab Vedotin in locally Advanced or Metastatic Urothelial Carcinoma. Clin Pharmacol Ther</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR26" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sridhar</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruether</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Flaig</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>EV-101: a phase I study of single-Agent Enfortumab Vedotin in patients with nectin-4-Positive solid tumors, including metastatic urothelial carcinoma</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>2020</year><volume>38</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1041</fpage><lpage>1049</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/JCO.19.02044</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32031899</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26" publication-type="journal">Rosenberg J, Sridhar SS, Zhang J, Smith D, Ruether D, Flaig TW et al (2020) EV-101: a phase I study of single-Agent Enfortumab Vedotin in patients with nectin-4-Positive solid tumors, including metastatic urothelial carcinoma. J Clin Oncol 38(10):1041&#x02013;1049<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32031899</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR27" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Garg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonate</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsangou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kadokura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clinical pharmacology of the antibody-drug Conjugate Enfortumab Vedotin in Advanced Urothelial Carcinoma and other malignant solid tumors</article-title><source>Clin Pharmacokinet</source><year>2024</year><volume>63</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>423</fpage><lpage>438</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40262-024-01369-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38609704</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27" publication-type="journal">Tang M, Garg A, Bonate PL, Rosenberg JE, Matsangou M, Kadokura T et al (2024) Clinical pharmacology of the antibody-drug Conjugate Enfortumab Vedotin in Advanced Urothelial Carcinoma and other malignant solid tumors. Clin Pharmacokinet 63(4):423&#x02013;438<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38609704</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR28" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kagedal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Samineni</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gillespie</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Fine</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Girish</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Time-to-event modeling of Peripheral Neuropathy: platform analysis of eight valine-citrulline-monomethylauristatin E antibody-drug conjugates</article-title><source>CPT Pharmacometrics Syst Pharmacol</source><year>2019</year><volume>8</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>606</fpage><lpage>615</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/psp4.12442</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31207190</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28" publication-type="journal">Kagedal M, Samineni D, Gillespie WR, Lu D, Fine BM, Girish S et al (2019) Time-to-event modeling of Peripheral Neuropathy: platform analysis of eight valine-citrulline-monomethylauristatin E antibody-drug conjugates. CPT Pharmacometrics Syst Pharmacol 8(8):606&#x02013;615<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31207190</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">National Health Care Institute Vergoeding 2019&#x02013;2023 voor ATC-subgroep L01FX13: Enfortumab vedotine 2024 [5 August 2024]. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.gipdatabank.nl/databank?infotype=d%26;label=00-totaal%26;tabel=B_01-basis%26;geg=vg%26;item=L01FX13">https://www.gipdatabank.nl/databank?infotype=d%26;label=00-totaal%26;tabel=B_01-basis%26;geg=vg%26;item=L01FX13</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">National Health Care Institute Horizonscan enfortumab vedotin 2023 [3 July 2024]. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.horizonscangeneesmiddelen.nl/geneesmiddelen/enfortumab-vedotin-oncologie-blaaskanker%5B2%5D/versie2?lang=en">https://www.horizonscangeneesmiddelen.nl/geneesmiddelen/enfortumab-vedotin-oncologie-blaaskanker%5B2%5D/versie2?lang=en</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR31" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boutari</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mantzoros</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A 2022 update on the epidemiology of obesity and a call to action: as its twin COVID-19 pandemic appears to be receding, the obesity and dysmetabolism pandemic continues to rage on</article-title><source>Metabolism</source><year>2022</year><volume>133</volume><fpage>155217</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.metabol.2022.155217</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35584732</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR31" publication-type="journal">Boutari C, Mantzoros CS (2022) A 2022 update on the epidemiology of obesity and a call to action: as its twin COVID-19 pandemic appears to be receding, the obesity and dysmetabolism pandemic continues to rage on. Metabolism 133:155217<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35584732</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article>