<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" id="jeo270107" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Exp Orthop</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Exp Orthop</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.1002/(ISSN)2197-1153</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JEO2</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Experimental Orthopaedics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2197-1153</issn><publisher><publisher-name>John Wiley and Sons Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Hoboken</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39807094</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11725761</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jeo2.70107</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">JEO270107</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Original Paper</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Paper</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Navigated instrumentation and ligament tensioning device enhances initial gap acquisition during total knee arthroplasty procedure: A cadaveric study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="jeo270107-cr-0001" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Boux de Casson</surname><given-names>Fran&#x000e7;ois</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-7567-2651</contrib-id><xref rid="jeo270107-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><address><email>francois.bouxdecasson@blue-ortho.com</email></address></contrib><contrib id="jeo270107-cr-0002" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Angibaud</surname><given-names>Laurent</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0009-0006-5291-0155</contrib-id><xref rid="jeo270107-aff-0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="jeo270107-cr-0003" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kerveillant</surname><given-names>Florian</given-names></name><xref rid="jeo270107-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="jeo270107-cr-0004" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nogaret</surname><given-names>Faustine</given-names></name><xref rid="jeo270107-aff-0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="jeo270107-cr-0005" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ruffin</surname><given-names>Joris</given-names></name><xref rid="jeo270107-aff-0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="jeo270107-cr-0006" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Duport&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>L&#x000e9;onard</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-2691-7197</contrib-id><xref rid="jeo270107-aff-0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="jeo270107-cr-0007" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Giordano</surname><given-names>G&#x000e9;rard</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-9180-8448</contrib-id><xref rid="jeo270107-aff-0004" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="jeo270107-cr-0008" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dagneaux</surname><given-names>Louis</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-7629-5560</contrib-id><xref rid="jeo270107-aff-0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref rid="jeo270107-aff-0005" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="jeo270107-aff-0001">
<label>
<sup>1</sup>
</label>
<institution>Blue&#x02010;Ortho</institution>
<city>Meylan</city>
<country country="FR">France</country>
</aff><aff id="jeo270107-aff-0002">
<label>
<sup>2</sup>
</label>
<institution>Exactech Inc</institution>
<city>Gainesville</city>
<named-content content-type="country-part">Florida</named-content>
<country country="US">USA</country>
</aff><aff id="jeo270107-aff-0003">
<label>
<sup>3</sup>
</label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Department of Orthopaedic Surgery and Trauma</named-content>
<institution>University Center of Montpellier, University of Montpellier</institution>
<city>Montpellier</city>
<country country="FR">France</country>
</aff><aff id="jeo270107-aff-0004">
<label>
<sup>4</sup>
</label>
<institution>Joseph Ducuing Hospital</institution>
<city>Toulouse</city>
<country country="FR">France</country>
</aff><aff id="jeo270107-aff-0005">
<label>
<sup>5</sup>
</label>
<institution>Laboratoire de M&#x000e9;canique et G&#x000e9;nie Civil (LMGC)</institution>
<institution>Montpellier University of Excellence</institution>
<city>Montpellier</city>
<country country="FR">France</country>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="correspondenceTo">
<label>*</label>
<bold>Correspondence</bold> Fran&#x000e7;ois Boux de Casson, Blue&#x02010;Ortho, 22 Chemin du Vieux Ch&#x000ea;ne, Meylan 38240, France.<break/>
Email: <email>francois.bouxdecasson@blue-ortho.com</email>
<break/>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>13</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><issue seq="72">1</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jeo2.v12.1</issue-id><elocation-id>e70107</elocation-id><history>
<date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>05</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date>
</history><permissions><!--&#x000a9; 2025 The Author(s). Journal of Experimental Orthopaedics published by John Wiley & Sons Ltd on behalf of European Society of Sports Traumatology, Knee Surgery and Arthroscopy.--><copyright-statement content-type="article-copyright">&#x000a9; 2025 The Author(s). <italic toggle="yes">Journal of Experimental Orthopaedics</italic> published by John Wiley &#x00026; Sons Ltd on behalf of European Society of Sports Traumatology, Knee Surgery and Arthroscopy.</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link> License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="file:JEO2-12-e70107.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><sec id="jeo270107-sec-0010"><title>Purpose</title><p>Gap&#x02010;balanced total knee arthroplasty (TKA) technique relies on initial ligament evaluation, particularly in patient&#x02010;specific implantation using computer&#x02010;assisted technologies. This cadaveric study aimed to compare the reproducibility and reliability of medial and lateral gap measurements between manual stress testing and dynamic ligament balancer.</p></sec><sec id="jeo270107-sec-0020"><title>Methods</title><p>Initial gap acquisitions were assessed from eight cadaveric knees (four specimens) during the same navigated TKA procedure by five differently skilled surgeons (three seniors and two juniors). Medial and lateral gaps were sequentially acquired from extension to maximum knee flexion, applying manual stress prior to any bone cuts (conventional technique), and using intra&#x02010;articular tensioning device placed between the tibial cut and the native femur (instrumented technique). Reproducibility was assessed using intraclass correlation coefficient (ICC), stratified by the measurement technique, the type of gaps and the operator experience. Differences in gaps (mm) between techniques were assessed using the Bland and Altmann method.</p></sec><sec id="jeo270107-sec-0030"><title>Results</title><p>The instrumented technique showed higher ICCs than the conventional technique for medial and lateral gaps (0.87 vs. 0.60, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.002, and 0.92 vs. 0.25, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001, respectively), and showed no difference in ICCs between medial and lateral gap acquisitions (0.87 vs. 0.92, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.8). Senior surgeons achieved higher ICCs than juniors, while non&#x02010;significant with both techniques. Differences in gaps between techniques increased with knee flexion angle (0.8, 2.8 and 3.5&#x02009;mm at 10&#x000b0;, 45&#x000b0; and 90&#x000b0; of flexion angle, respectively) and decreased with the operator experience (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.003).</p></sec><sec id="jeo270107-sec-0040"><title>Conclusion</title><p>The instrumented balancing technique offered better reproducibility than using manual valgus and varus stress, when measuring medial and lateral gaps. Tensioning devices may play a significant role in enhancing initial gap acquisition, disregarding the flexion angle and the operator experience.</p></sec><sec id="jeo270107-sec-0050"><title>Level of Evidence</title><p>Level IV (observational study involving cadaveric specimens).</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd id="jeo270107-kwd-0001">alignment</kwd><kwd id="jeo270107-kwd-0002">experimental model</kwd><kwd id="jeo270107-kwd-0003">joint laxity</kwd><kwd id="jeo270107-kwd-0004">kinematics</kwd><kwd id="jeo270107-kwd-0005">ligament</kwd><kwd id="jeo270107-kwd-0006">tensor</kwd><kwd id="jeo270107-kwd-0007">TKA</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="funding-0001"><funding-source>Institutional research support from Exactech</funding-source></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="4"/><table-count count="5"/><page-count count="9"/><word-count count="4771"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>source-schema-version-number</meta-name><meta-value>2.0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>January 2025</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>details-of-publishers-convertor</meta-name><meta-value>Converter:WILEY_ML3GV2_TO_JATSPMC version:6.5.4 mode:remove_FC converted:27.02.2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><p content-type="self-citation">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270107-cit-0030">
<string-name>
<surname>Boux de Casson</surname>, <given-names>F.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Angibaud</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Kerveillant</surname>, <given-names>F.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Nogaret</surname>, <given-names>F.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ruffin</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Duport&#x000e9;</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names>
</string-name> et al. (<year>2025</year>) <article-title>Navigated instrumentation and ligament tensioning device enhances initial gap acquisition during total knee arthroplasty procedure: a cadaveric study</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Orthopaedics</source>, <volume>12</volume>, <elocation-id>e70107</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jeo2.70107</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39807094</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
</p><fn-group><fn id="jeo270107-note-0001"><p>This work was performed at the University of Montpellier, Montpellier, France.</p></fn></fn-group></notes></front><body><def-list list-content="abbreviations"><title>Abbreviations</title><def-item><term>BA</term><def><p>Bland and Altman</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CAOS</term><def><p>computer&#x02010;assisted orthopaedic surgery</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ICC</term><def><p>intraclass correlation coefficient</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TKA</term><def><p>total knee arthroplasty</p></def></def-item></def-list><sec id="jeo270107-sec-0060"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Appropriate ligament balancing is one of the criteria for a successful total knee arthroplasty (TKA). The increasing use of unconstrained implants and the popularity of new alignment techniques have led to a heightened rate of revision for instability, which has been the second or third cause of TKA revision in several national registries for several years, including in the United States [<xref rid="jeo270107-bib-0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>].</p><p>Achieving a proper soft&#x02010;tissue balance remains challenging in regard to the wide range of knee phenotypes and arthritic conditions [<xref rid="jeo270107-bib-0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. As such, computer&#x02010;assisted orthopaedic surgery (CAOS) technologies have been developed to assist new alignment strategies focusing on the gap&#x02010;balancing technique. These technologies allow surgeons to evaluate knee gaps prior to planning the bone cuts, enabling adjustment of the bony cuts to achieve patient&#x02010;specific targets based on alignment and implant sizing considerations. Traditionally, medial and lateral gaps in extension and at 90&#x000b0; knee flexion are acquired by consecutively applying manual varus and valgus stress to the knee joint. However, this intraoperative planning depends on the reliability of the gap acquisitions [<xref rid="jeo270107-bib-0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="jeo270107-bib-0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="jeo270107-bib-0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], which may be questionable in this subjective technique [<xref rid="jeo270107-bib-0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Indeed, one surgeon may apply different magnitudes of varus and valgus forces and/or handling of the lower limb than another, leading to different gap assessments, and subsequently translating into different implant positioning, and tibial insert thickness selection for the same patient [<xref rid="jeo270107-bib-0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. In addition, gap assessment during the entire arc of knee flexion, versus at a limited number of static positions, can be an asset for properly balancing the knee [<xref rid="jeo270107-bib-0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="jeo270107-bib-0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>].</p><p>To address this limitation, gap assessment can rely on a dynamic ligament balancer, distracting both knee compartments simultaneously while recording the gaps throughout the full arc of motion without applying manual varus or valgus stress. There are several types of devices, based on different mechanisms or actuations (e.g., mechanical or motorized) [<xref rid="jeo270107-bib-0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. A particular class of balancer relates to intraarticular force&#x02010;controlled devices allowing simultaneous acquisition of both the medial and lateral gaps under distraction during the manipulation of the limb throughout the arc of motion in neutral alignment. As such, this experimental study aimed to compare gap measurements between the conventional (i.e., free&#x02010;handed technique with valgus and varus stress) and the instrumented balancing (i.e., using a dynamic balancer) techniques, with a particular emphasis on reproducibility and factors influencing the measurements' reliability. We hypothesized that the instrumented balancing technique would provide more reliable and reproducible gap measurements than the manual conventional technique, disregarding the operator's experience.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials-and-methods" id="jeo270107-sec-0070"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec id="jeo270107-sec-0080"><title>Cadaver specimens</title><p>Eight lower limbs from four fresh frozen cadavers were studied. There were four women aged from 79 to 96 years at death (median&#x02009;=&#x02009;92&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;8 years). The lower limbs were harvested after approval by the local ethical committee. Each entire body was stored at &#x02212;20&#x000b0;C, and then allowed to thaw at room temperature for 12&#x02009;h before the experiments. Lower&#x02010;limb deformity included two knee varus, one knee valgus and one normoaxed. One specimen showed a slight contracture (~5&#x000b0;) on both legs. No cases of osteoarthritis of the knee were encountered.</p></sec><sec id="jeo270107-sec-0090"><title>Data acquisition</title><p>All TKAs were performed by the same senior surgeon through a medial parapatellar approach using a CAOS system (ExactechGPS, Blue&#x02010;Ortho). After cruciate ligament resection and osteophytes removal, active femoral and tibial trackers were secured to each bone and anatomical landmarks were acquired to enable patient&#x02010;specific anatomic planification of a posterior stabilized implant (Optetrak Logic PS, Exactech). Medial and lateral gaps were sequentially acquired by the CAOS system from extension to maximum knee flexion, using the conventional technique prior to any bone cuts (Step 1). Then, the proximal tibial cut was performed perpendicular to the tibial mechanical axis, and the intra&#x02010;articular force&#x02010;controlled tensioning device (Newton, Exactech, see Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="jeo270107-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) was placed between the tibial cut and the native femur. This mechanical tensioning device applies the same constant 90&#x02009;N distraction force, independently on each compartment. After the release of the tensioning device, the lower limb was manipulated from extension to maximum flexion in neutral alignment (i.e., no varus or valgus stress) for the simultaneous acquisition of the medial and lateral gaps by the CAOS system, using the instrumented technique (Step 2). All acquisitions were done with the patella in place.</p><fig position="float" fig-type="Figure" id="jeo270107-fig-0001"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>The dynamic ligament balancer was used after the proximal tibial cut, while recording the knee laxities throughout the arc of motion, from knee in extension (a) to knee in flexion (b).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JEO2-12-e70107-g004" position="anchor" id="jats-graphic-1"/></fig></sec><sec id="jeo270107-sec-0100"><title>Data processing</title><p>Medial and lateral gaps were defined as the smallest distances between the medial and lateral condyles of the native femur and the checked tibial cut plane, respectively. For the conventional technique, distances were post&#x02010;processed after digitizing the tibial cut plane of the corresponding thickness (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="jeo270107-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Gaps were recorded in the same coordinate system between acquisitions for each specimen, extracted continuously from 0&#x000b0; to 100&#x000b0; of knee flexion, and then plotted by each 5&#x000b0; flexion increments using house&#x02010;made software.</p><fig position="float" fig-type="Figure" id="jeo270107-fig-0002"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Gaps are computed by the navigation system as the smallest distance between the native femoral condyles surface and the plane of the tibia proximal cut.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JEO2-12-e70107-g001" position="anchor" id="jats-graphic-3"/></fig></sec><sec id="jeo270107-sec-0110"><title>Reproducibility analysis</title><p>Each gap was assessed with both techniques by five differently skilled operators, all right&#x02010;handed, including three senior surgeons (labelled S1, S2 and S3) and two junior surgeons (labelled J1 and J2). For each knee, each laxity measure (varus, valgus and instrumented) was repeated six times by each operator, alternating between operators, resulting in 960 gap acquisitions in total. Each evaluation was blinded from one operator to another. Intra&#x02010;operator and inter&#x02010;operator reproducibility were assessed by the intraclass correlation coefficient (ICC) with their 95% confidence intervals (95% CIs), stratified by the acquisition technique (conventional and instrumented), the type of gaps (both medial and lateral, lateral only and medial only), and the operator experience level (senior and junior). Inter&#x02010;operator reliability was assessed using a two&#x02010;way mixed effect mean of five raters with absolute agreement, while the intra&#x02010;operator reliability was assessed using a two&#x02010;way mixed effect, mean of six measurements with absolute agreement. The hypothesis was tested overall and specifically for medial and lateral gap measurements.</p></sec><sec id="jeo270107-sec-0120"><title>Agreement analysis</title><p>To ensure whether measurement agreement between techniques was dependent on confounding factors (i.e., flexion angle, knee side, gap side and operator experience), Bland and Altman (BA) graphs [<xref rid="jeo270107-bib-0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] and their mean bias (expressed in millimetres) were assessed at 0&#x000b0;, 45&#x000b0; and 90&#x000b0; of knee flexion. The bias was defined as the gap from the instrumented technique minus the gap from the conventional technique. The impact of each confounding factor on bias between the two methods was measured using one&#x02010;way ANOVA (Tukey Post Hoc Test) for the knee flexion and using Student's or Welch's <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> tests (depending on whether variances were equivalent between groups) for the knee side, gap side and operator experience.</p></sec><sec id="jeo270107-sec-0130"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>All results were presented as means with ranges. Normal distribution was examined using the Shapiro&#x02013;Wilk test, and the homogeneity of variance was examined using the <italic toggle="yes">F</italic> test. Differences in continuous variables were analyzed using the unpaired t&#x02010;test for normally distributed variables or Welch's two&#x02010;sample <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test for non&#x02010;normally distributed variables. Superiority in continuous variables was analyzed using one&#x02010;sided <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test. A power analysis was conducted to validate the sample size for comparing ICC between the two techniques using unpaired <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test. An effect size of 0.1 was deemed relevant according to reference [<xref rid="jeo270107-bib-0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. With an <italic toggle="yes">&#x003b1;</italic> level of 0.05 and a desired power of 80%, it was calculated that 143 measures per group would be required to detect a statistically significant difference. This sample size ensures sufficient power to minimize the risk of a Type II error. This recommended volume was far exceeded. Statistical analyses were performed using R software (version 4.3.1, R Foundation for Statistical Computing [<xref rid="jeo270107-bib-0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]). The <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> value was set as &#x0003c;0.05 for significance.</p></sec><sec id="jeo270107-sec-0140"><title>Ethical aspects</title><p>Each author certifies that his institution has approved the reporting of these cases and that all investigations were conducted in accordance with ethical research principles.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="jeo270107-sec-0150"><title>RESULTS</title><sec id="jeo270107-sec-0160"><title>Inter&#x02010;operator reproducibility</title><p>Overall, ICCs were significantly higher with the instrumented technique than with the conventional technique (0.90 vs. 0.43, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001, respectively) (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="jeo270107-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref> and Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="jeo270107-tbl-0001" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The same result was found when stratifying by medial gap (0.87 vs. 0.60, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.002) and lateral gap (0.92 vs. 0.25, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001). As such, a difference in reproducibility was found between medial and lateral gap acquisitions (0.60 vs. 0.25, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.01) with the conventional technique, while no difference with the instrumented technique was found (0.87 vs. 0.92, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.8) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="jeo270107-tbl-0002" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Senior surgeons achieved higher ICC than juniors, while non&#x02010;significant for either the conventional (0.55 vs. 0.39, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.3, respectively) or the instrumented technique (0.92 vs. 0.90, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.1, respectively) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="jeo270107-tbl-0002" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p><fig position="float" fig-type="Figure" id="jeo270107-fig-0003"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Mean lateral compartment gap measured along the leg flexion by each operator for specimen 4, left knee, by the conventional (a) and instrumented (b) techniques.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JEO2-12-e70107-g003" position="anchor" id="jats-graphic-5"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="jeo270107-tbl-0001" content-type="Table"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Inter&#x02010;operator and intra&#x02010;operator intraclass correlation coefficient (ICC) per technique of laxity measurements for all, varus and valgus tests.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="left" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="left" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="left" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><thead valign="bottom"><tr valign="bottom"><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th colspan="2" style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">Mean ICC (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1">One&#x02010;sided <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test</th></tr><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" valign="bottom"><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Conventional technique</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Instrumented technique</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="2" valign="top" rowspan="1">Inter&#x02010;operator</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All tests</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43 (0.23&#x02013;0.60)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90 (0.76&#x02013;0.96)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Varus tests (lat. gaps)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25 (0.09&#x02013;0.43)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92 (0.81&#x02013;0.97)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Valgus tests (med. gaps)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60 (0.37&#x02013;0.76)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87 (0.71&#x02013;0.95)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.002</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="2" valign="top" rowspan="1">Intra&#x02010;operator</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All tests</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51 (0.33&#x02013;0.70)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78 (0.64&#x02013;0.88)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Varus tests (lat. gaps)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40 (0.22&#x02013;0.60)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84 (0.71&#x02013;0.92)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Valgus tests (med. gaps)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63 (0.44&#x02013;0.80)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71 (0.57&#x02013;0.84)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.07</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="jeo270107-tbl1-note-0001"><p>Abbreviation: CI, confidence interval.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd.</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="jeo270107-tbl-0002" content-type="Table"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Inter&#x02010;operator and intra&#x02010;operator intraclass correlation coefficient (ICC) between measurement of lateral and medial gaps and between juniors and seniors surgeons.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="left" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="left" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="left" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="left" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><thead valign="bottom"><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" valign="bottom"><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th colspan="3" align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">Mean ICC (95% CI)</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Two&#x02010;sided <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="3" valign="top" rowspan="1">Inter&#x02010;operator</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1">Varus tests (lat. gaps)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Valgus tests (med. gaps)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Conventional technique</td><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1">0.25 (0.09&#x02013;0.43)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60 (0.37&#x02013;0.76)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Instrumented technique</td><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1">0.92 (0.81&#x02013;0.97)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87 (0.71&#x02013;0.95)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1">Juniors</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Seniors</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Conventional technique</td><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1">0.39 (0.08&#x02013;0.62)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55 (0.27&#x02013;0.72)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Instrumented technique</td><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1">0.90 (0.66&#x02013;0.96)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92 (0.78&#x02013;0.97)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="3" valign="top" rowspan="1">Intra&#x02010;operator</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1">Varus tests (lat. gaps)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Valgus tests (med. gaps)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Conventional technique</td><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1">0.40 (0.22&#x02013;0.60)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63 (0.44&#x02013;0.80)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Instrumented technique</td><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1">0.84 (0.71&#x02013;0.92)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71 (0.57&#x02013;0.84)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1">Juniors</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Seniors</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Conventional technique</td><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1">0.53 (0.34&#x02013;0.71)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50 (0.32&#x02013;0.69)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Instrumented technique</td><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1">0.75 (0.61&#x02013;0.87)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79 (0.66&#x02013;0.89)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.2</td></tr></tbody></table><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd.</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap></sec><sec id="jeo270107-sec-0170"><title>Intra&#x02010;operator reproducibility</title><p>Overall, ICCs were significantly higher with the instrumented technique than with the conventional technique (0.78 vs. 0.51, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001) (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="jeo270107-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">4</xref> and Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="jeo270107-tbl-0001" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The same result was found for lateral gap acquisition (0.84 vs. 0.63, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.07). Medial gap acquisition was associated with higher ICC than lateral gap acquisition with the conventional technique, in contrast with the instrumented technique (0.71 vs. 0.84, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.01, respectively) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="jeo270107-tbl-0002" ref-type="table">2</xref>). No significant differences in ICC were found regarding the operator experience for both techniques (conventional, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.7 and instrumented, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.2).</p><fig position="float" fig-type="Figure" id="jeo270107-fig-0004"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Repeated six acquisitions of the lateral compartment gap measured along the leg flexion by operator S3 for specimen 1, left knee, by the conventional (a) and instrumented (b) techniques.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JEO2-12-e70107-g002" position="anchor" id="jats-graphic-7"/></fig></sec><sec id="jeo270107-sec-0180"><title>Agreement results between techniques</title><p>Gaps from the instrumented technique were larger than those from the conventional technique at 10&#x000b0; (bias&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.8&#x02009;mm [&#x02212;1.91 to 3.60]), 45&#x000b0; (bias&#x02009;=&#x02009;2.1&#x02009;mm [&#x02212;0.44 to 4.69]) and 90&#x000b0; (bias&#x02009;=&#x02009;3.5&#x02009;mm [0.63&#x02013;6.28]) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="jeo270107-tbl-0003" ref-type="table">3</xref>), and this bias increases significantly with the knee flexion angle (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="jeo270107-tbl-0004" ref-type="table">4</xref>). Differences in gap measurements were found to be dependent on the knee side, showing significantly higher bias for right knees than left knees (1.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.0&#x02009;mm vs. 2.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.7&#x02009;mm, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.049, respectively). Differences were dependent on operator experience, showing significantly higher bias for juniors than senior surgeons (2.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.4&#x02009;mm vs. 1.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.5&#x02009;mm; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.003, respectively). Agreement between techniques was not influenced by the type of deformity (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.77) or the gap side, showing similar bias between medial and lateral gaps (2.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.6&#x02009;mm vs. 2.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.3&#x02009;mm; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.8, respectively) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="jeo270107-tbl-0005" ref-type="table">5</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="jeo270107-tbl-0003" content-type="Table"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Bland and Altman bias and lower and upper limits of agreement (LOA) for gaps measurements at different flexion angles (instrumented technique minus conventional).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="char" char="&#x000b1;" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="char" char="&#x000b1;" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="char" char="&#x000b1;" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><thead valign="bottom"><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" valign="bottom"><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexion (&#x000b0;)</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bias mean (mm)</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower LOA (mm)</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Upper LOA (mm)</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.67</td><td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.91&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.67</td><td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.60&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.48</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td><td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.13&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.81</td><td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.44&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.57</td><td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.69&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.60</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</td><td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.46&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.33</td><td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.08</td><td align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.28&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.42</td></tr></tbody></table><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd.</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="jeo270107-tbl-0004" content-type="Table"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Bland and Altman bias for gaps measurements at different flexion angles between the two different techniques (instrumented minus conventional).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="left" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="left" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="left" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="left" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><thead valign="bottom"><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" valign="bottom"><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flexion angle (&#x000b0;)</th><th colspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1">Mean difference of bias (mm)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.28</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2.62</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.002</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1">Mean difference of bias (mm)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.33</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="jeo270107-tbl4-note-0001"><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Note</italic>: One&#x02010;way ANOVA&#x02014;Tukey post hoc test.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd.</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="jeo270107-tbl-0005" content-type="Table"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Bland and Altman bias (instrumented minus conventional) for gaps measurements comparing left and right knees, lateral and medial gaps and juniors and seniors surgeons.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="left" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col align="left" style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><thead valign="bottom"><tr valign="bottom"><th colspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">Bland and Altman bias</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" valign="bottom"><th colspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">Bias mean (mm)</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Two&#x02010;sided <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left knees</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right knees</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.73&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.98</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.55&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.71</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.049</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Juniors</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Seniors</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.72&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.45</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.80&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.52</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.003</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lateral gaps</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medial gaps</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.19&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.59</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.10&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.31</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.8</td></tr></tbody></table><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd.</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="jeo270107-sec-0190"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>This study investigated the reproducibility of two techniques measuring knee gaps throughout the full range of motion, during navigated tibia&#x02010;first TKA. The most important finding of this study was that the instrumented balancing technique provided a more reliable and reproducible gap measurement, along the full arc of flexion, than the manual conventional technique.</p><p>Disregarding the differences between alignment and implant philosophies [<xref rid="jeo270107-bib-0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], recent literature has supported that postoperative knee gaps can be predicted and achieved when using a CAOS system coupled with a dynamic ligament balancer [<xref rid="jeo270107-bib-0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. As such, an accurate and reproducible laxity assessment remains essential to provide valuable quantitative information to perform patient&#x02010;specific surgical planning.</p><p>This study established that the instrumented balancing technique offered better reproducibility than using manual valgus/varus stress when measuring medial/lateral gaps. Considering the level of reliability [<xref rid="jeo270107-bib-0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], inter&#x02010;operator reproducibility ranged from poor with the conventional technique to excellent with the balancing technique, as expected. These results were consistent with those from previous work [<xref rid="jeo270107-bib-0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>], highlighting the high degree of variability when assessing gaps from manual, inconsistent valgus/varus stress from operators. The instrumented device used in this study was designed for applying a distraction force of 90&#x02009;N, independently to the medial and lateral compartments, which explains the improved reproducibility between operators. Several in&#x02010;vitro [<xref rid="jeo270107-bib-0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="jeo270107-bib-0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="jeo270107-bib-0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="jeo270107-bib-0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] or in&#x02010;vivo [<xref rid="jeo270107-bib-0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="jeo270107-bib-0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="jeo270107-bib-0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] studies have analyzed the average forces required to tension the collateral ligaments of the knee. According to these studies, these forces vary between 50 and 130&#x02009;N for the medial compartment and 50&#x02013;100&#x02009;N for the lateral compartment, with respective averages of 89 and 78&#x02009;N. 90&#x02009;N therefore represents an average force enabling measurement of the distances between the femoral and tibial spaces in extension and flexion without excessive or insufficient ligament tension.</p><p>The same trend was observed when focusing on lateral gap reproducibility, ranging from moderate with the conventional technique to good with the balancing technique. However, this trend was not observed for the medial gap reproducibility. These results also emphasize that the distracting device has played a significant role in enhancing initial lateral gap acquisition, which was less reproducible than the medial gap acquisition using conventional technique. Yet, accurate lateral gap assessment is crucial, as high lateral laxity in extension is associated with lower improvement in functional ability [<xref rid="jeo270107-bib-0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. The distracting device can mitigate the factors influencing the lateral gap reproducibility, namely right or left&#x02010;handed surgeons and operator's experience.</p><p>Another factor influencing reproducibility in this study was the knee flexion. It is commonly accepted by surgeons that valgus or varus stress are challenging to manually apply consistently as the knee is moved from extension to deep flexion, and this trend was demonstrated experimentally by a recent cadaveric study [<xref rid="jeo270107-bib-0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. As such, the difference in gap measures between techniques increased with knee flexion. As the dynamic ligament balancer aimed to apply the same distracting force to each compartment, disregarding the knee flexion angle, the BA bias indirectly captured the heterogenous varus/valgus forces applied with the conventional technique when flexing the knee. The dynamic ligament balancer also enhanced the gap acquisition when manipulating a right knee, as all the operators in this study were right&#x02010;handed and traditionally expressed more difficulties when applying varus stress on a right knee.</p><p>Concerning the influence of the operator's experience, BA analysis showed significantly greater differences between techniques for juniors, probably highlighting their difficulty to effectively manually distract the joints, notably in flexion. The instrumented technique eliminates the differences between juniors and seniors, with excellent inter&#x02010;operator ICC reproducibility for both groups.</p><p>Previous studies have shown near&#x02010;identical flexion gap measurement between surgeon vs. ligament tensor coupled with robot [<xref rid="jeo270107-bib-0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], or no difference in range of motion, reoperation rate or functional outcomes when compared to manually balanced TKA [<xref rid="jeo270107-bib-0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], but they focused only on flexion and extension gap assessments. Although it is beyond the scope of this study to assess the influence of a more precise and reproducible measurement of joint laxity on functional results, and studies have shown us to be cautious on this point [<xref rid="jeo270107-bib-0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], we do believe that assessing these gaps continuously over the entire arc of flexion can provide the practitioner with information that should make it possible to reduce mid&#x02010;flexion instabilities [<xref rid="jeo270107-bib-0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>].</p><p>There are some limitations to discuss. First, cadaveric conditions cannot reflect the mechanical properties of ligamentous laxities in live subjects. Similarly, the number of manipulations carried out on the same specimen may have influenced the extent of deviation due to soft tissue stretching. This seems to be corroborated by the fact that intra&#x02010;operator reproducibility results were not as good as those for inter&#x02010;operator reproducibility, and probably increased the BA bias for the latest acquisitions. Additionally, this study was carried out on a relatively small number of cadaveric specimens with a low body mass index compared to standard TKA patients [<xref rid="jeo270107-bib-0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Third, the results found in this experimental study were linked to the tensioning device and the navigated instrumentation utilized in this study and cannot be extrapolated to all CAOS technologies or tensioning devices, even though some recent work has shown similar results [<xref rid="jeo270107-bib-0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="jeo270107-sec-0200"><title>CONCLUSION</title><p>This study confirmed the hypothesis that the instrumented balancing technique would provide more reliable and reproducible medial and lateral gap measurements than using manual valgus and varus stress, disregarding the operator's experience. Tensioning devices may play a significant role in enhancing initial gap acquisition along the full arc of motion, regardless of the operator's experience.</p></sec><sec id="jeo270107-sec-0210"><title>AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS</title><p>
<bold>Fran&#x000e7;ois Boux de Casson, Laurent Angibaud, Florian Kerveillant</bold>: Conceptualization; review analysis; writing&#x02014;original draft. <bold>Louis Dagneaux and G&#x000e9;rard Giordano</bold>: Conceptualization; supervision; writing&#x02014;review and editing. <bold>Joris Ruffin, Faustine Nogaret and L&#x000e9;onard Duport&#x000e9;</bold>: Experimental data; writing&#x02014;review and editing.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="jeo270107-sec-0230"><title>CONFLICT OF INTEREST STATEMENT</title><p>Fran&#x000e7;ois Boux de Casson and Florian Kerveillant are employees of Blue&#x02010;Ortho, a subsidiary of Exactech. Laurent Angibaud is an employee of Exactech. Laurent Angibaud also serves an unpaid position as the Chair of the Scientific Committee for the Personalized Arthroplasty Society G&#x000e9;rard Giordano received consulting fees from Exactech during the conduct of the study. Louis Dagneaux reports a MUSE Explorer Grant from the University of Montpelier, a Research Fellowship Grant from SOFCOT, consulting fees from Zimmer Biomet, DePuy Synthes and Newclip Technics, speaker payments from Stryker and expenses from Zimmer Biomet, all of which are unrelated to this study. Louis Dagneaux also holds an unpaid position on the Board of Directors for SOFCOT, is on the Board of Directors for CAOS France, is the Director of the AFCP Scientific Council, and is Associate Editor of OTSR. L&#x000e9;onard Duport&#x000e9;, Joris Ruffin and Faustine Nogaret declare no conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec id="jeo270107-sec-0260"><title>ETHICS STATEMENT</title><p>Local IRB from the University of Montpellier.</p></sec></body><back><ack id="jeo270107-sec-0220"><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title><p>The authors sincerely thank those who donated their bodies to science so that anatomical research could be performed. Results from such research can potentially increase mankind's overall knowledge, which can then improve patient care. Therefore, these donors and their families deserve our highest gratitude. The authors are indebted to Mrs. Maud Moulin from the Laboratory of Anatomy (University of Montpellier, France) for her support during the conduct of the study.</p></ack><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="jeo270107-sec-0250"><title>DATA AVAILABILITY STATEMENT</title><p>The data that support the findings of this study are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request.</p></sec><ref-list content-type="cited-references" id="jeo270107-bibl-0001"><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="jeo270107-bib-0001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="jeo270107-cit-0001">
<collab collab-type="authors">American Academy of Orthopaedic Surgeons (AAOS)</collab>
. (<year>2023</year>) <source>American Joint Replacement Registry (AJRR): 2023 annual report</source>. <publisher-loc>Rosemont, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Academy of Orthopaedic Surgeons (AAOS)</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270107-bib-0002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270107-cit-0002">
<string-name>
<surname>Angibaud</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Fan</surname>, <given-names>W.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Dubard</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Rueff</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Prieto</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names>
</string-name> &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Parvataneni</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2022</year>) <article-title>Reliability of laxity acquisitions during navigated total knee arthroplasty&#x02014;comparison of two techniques</article-title>. <source>EPiC Series in Health Sciences EasyChair</source>, <volume>5</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270107-bib-0003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270107-cit-0003">
<string-name>
<surname>Basselot</surname>, <given-names>F.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Gicquel</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Common</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Herv&#x000e9;</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Berton</surname>, <given-names>E.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ropars</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name> et al. (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>Are ligament&#x02010;tensioning devices interchangeable? A study of femoral rotation</article-title>. <source>Orthopaedics &#x00026; Traumatology: Surgery &#x00026; Research</source>, <volume>102</volume>(<issue>4 Suppl</issue>), <fpage>S213</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>S219</lpage>. Available from: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.otsr.2016.02.001</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270107-bib-0004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270107-cit-0004">
<string-name>
<surname>Batailler</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Swan</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Marinier</surname>, <given-names>E.S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Servien</surname>, <given-names>E.</given-names>
</string-name> &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Lustig</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2021</year>) <article-title>Current role of intraoperative sensing technology in total knee arthroplasty</article-title>. <source>Archives of Orthopaedic and Trauma Surgery</source>, <volume>141</volume>(<issue>12</issue>), <fpage>2255</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2265</lpage>. Available from: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00402-021-04130-5</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34427757</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270107-bib-0005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270107-cit-0005">
<string-name>
<surname>Bland</surname>, <given-names>J.M.</given-names>
</string-name> &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Altman</surname>, <given-names>D.G.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Measuring agreement in method comparison studies</article-title>. <source>Statistical Methods in Medical Research</source>, <volume>8</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>135</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>160</lpage>. Available from: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/096228029900800204</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10501650</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270107-bib-0006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270107-cit-0006">
<string-name>
<surname>Craik</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Bircher</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name> &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Rickman</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>Hip and knee arthroplasty implants contraindicated in obesity</article-title>. <source>The Annals of the Royal College of Surgeons of England</source>, <volume>98</volume>(<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>295</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>299</lpage>. Available from: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1308/rcsann.2016.0103</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27023636</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270107-bib-0007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270107-cit-0007">
<string-name>
<surname>Dai</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Bolch</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Jensen</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name> &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Jung</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Variability in coronal knee laxity measured during computer&#x02010;assisted total knee arthroplasty</article-title>. <source>EPiC Series in Health Sciences EasyChair</source>, <volume>4</volume>, <fpage>45</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>48</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270107-bib-0008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="miscellaneous" id="jeo270107-cit-0008">Digital tensioner for total knee arthroplasty (TKA): ligament tensioning and assessment prior to bone resections.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270107-bib-0009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270107-cit-0009">
<string-name>
<surname>Edelstein</surname>, <given-names>A.I.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Wakelin</surname>, <given-names>E.A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Plaskos</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names>
</string-name> &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Suleiman</surname>, <given-names>L.I.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2023</year>) <article-title>Laxity, balance, and alignment of a simulated kinematic alignment total knee arthroplasty</article-title>. <source>Arthroplasty Today</source>, <volume>23</volume>, <elocation-id>101204</elocation-id>. Available from: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.artd.2023.101204</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37745959</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270107-bib-0010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270107-cit-0010">
<string-name>
<surname>Elmasry</surname>, <given-names>S.S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Sculco</surname>, <given-names>P.K.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Kahlenberg</surname>, <given-names>C.A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Mayman</surname>, <given-names>D.J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Cross</surname>, <given-names>M.B.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Pearle</surname>, <given-names>A.D.</given-names>
</string-name> et al. (<year>2022</year>) <article-title>Arthroplasty surgeons differ in their intraoperative soft tissue assessments: a study in human cadavers to quantify surgical decision&#x02010;making in TKA</article-title>. <source>Clinical Orthopaedics &#x00026; Related Research</source>, <volume>480</volume>(<issue>8</issue>), <fpage>1604</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1615</lpage>. Available from: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/CORR.0000000000002184</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35323146</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270107-bib-0011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270107-cit-0011">
<string-name>
<surname>Erard</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Olivier</surname>, <given-names>F.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Kafelov</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Servien</surname>, <given-names>E.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Lustig</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name> &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Batailler</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2024</year>) <article-title>Enhancing soft tissue balance: evaluating robotic&#x02010;assisted functional positioning in varus knees across flexion and extension with quantitative sensor&#x02010;guided technology</article-title>. <source>Knee Surgery, Sports Traumatology, Arthroscopy</source>, <volume>32</volume>(<issue>9</issue>), <fpage>2318</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2327</lpage>. Available from: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ksa.12255</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270107-bib-0012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270107-cit-0012">
<string-name>
<surname>Grosso</surname>, <given-names>M.J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Wakelin</surname>, <given-names>E.A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Plaskos</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names>
</string-name> &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Lee</surname>, <given-names>G.C.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2024</year>) <article-title>Alignment is only part of the equation: high variability in soft tissue distractibility in the varus knee undergoing primary TKA</article-title>. <source>Knee Surgery, Sports Traumatology, Arthroscopy</source>, <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>1516</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1524</lpage>. Available from: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ksa.12115</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270107-bib-0013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270107-cit-0013">
<string-name>
<surname>Inokuchi</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Muratsu</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Kamenaga</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Tsubosaka</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Nakano</surname>, <given-names>N.</given-names>
</string-name> &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Hayashi</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name> et al. (<year>2024</year>) <article-title>Intraoperative lateral laxity greater than 4&#x000b0; is associated with inferior functional improvement in posterior&#x02010;stabilised total knee arthroplasty</article-title>. <source>Knee Surgery, Sports Traumatology, Arthroscopy</source>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12</lpage>. Available from: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ksa.12327</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270107-bib-0014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270107-cit-0014">
<string-name>
<surname>Jhurani</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Agarwal</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Aswal</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Meena</surname>, <given-names>I.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Srivastava</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name> &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Sheth</surname>, <given-names>N.P.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Do spacer blocks accurately estimate deformity correction and gap balance in total knee arthroplasty? A prospective study with computer navigation</article-title>. <source>The Knee</source>, <volume>27</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>214</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>220</lpage>. Available from: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.knee.2019.09.006</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31918963</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270107-bib-0015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270107-cit-0015">
<string-name>
<surname>Kono</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Dorthe</surname>, <given-names>E.W.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Tomita</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Tanaka</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Angibaud</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names>
</string-name> &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>D'Lima</surname>, <given-names>D.D.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2022</year>) <article-title>Intraoperative knee kinematics measured by computer&#x02010;assisted navigation and intraoperative ligament balance have the potential to predict postoperative knee kinematics</article-title>. <source>Journal of Orthopaedic Research</source>, <volume>40</volume>(<issue>7</issue>), <fpage>1538</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1546</lpage>. Available from: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jor.25182</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34559437</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270107-bib-0016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270107-cit-0016">
<string-name>
<surname>Koo</surname>, <given-names>T.K.</given-names>
</string-name> &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Li</surname>, <given-names>M.Y.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>A guideline of selecting and reporting intraclass correlation coefficients for reliability research</article-title>. <source>Journal of Chiropractic Medicine</source>, <volume>15</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>155</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>163</lpage>. Available from: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jcm.2016.02.012</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27330520</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270107-bib-0017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270107-cit-0017">
<string-name>
<surname>MacDessi</surname>, <given-names>S.J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Gharaibeh</surname>, <given-names>M.A.</given-names>
</string-name> &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Harris</surname>, <given-names>I.A.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>How accurately can soft tissue balance be determined in total knee arthroplasty?</article-title>
<source>The Journal of Arthroplasty</source>, <volume>34</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>290</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>294.e1</lpage>. Available from: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arth.2018.10.003</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30389257</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270107-bib-0018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="miscellaneous" id="jeo270107-cit-0018">
<collab collab-type="authors">R Core Team RF for SC</collab>
(<year>2021</year>) <article-title>R: a language and environment for statistical computing</article-title>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270107-bib-0019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270107-cit-0019">
<string-name>
<surname>Roth</surname>, <given-names>J.D.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Howell</surname>, <given-names>S.M.</given-names>
</string-name> &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Hull</surname>, <given-names>M.L.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Native knee laxities at 0&#x000b0;, 45&#x000b0;, and 90&#x000b0; of flexion and their relationship to the goal of the gap&#x02010;balancing alignment method of total knee arthroplasty</article-title>. <source>Journal of Bone and Joint Surgery</source>, <volume>97</volume>(<issue>20</issue>), <fpage>1678</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1684</lpage>. Available from: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2106/JBJS.N.01256</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270107-bib-0020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270107-cit-0020">
<string-name>
<surname>Sanz&#x02010;Pena</surname>, <given-names>I.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Zapata</surname>, <given-names>G.E.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Verstraete</surname>, <given-names>M.A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Meere</surname>, <given-names>P.A.</given-names>
</string-name> &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Walker</surname>, <given-names>P.S.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>Relationship between ligament forces and contact forces in balancing at total knee surgery</article-title>. <source>The Journal of Arthroplasty</source>, <volume>34</volume>(<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>1261</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1266</lpage>. Available from: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arth.2019.02.016</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30890388</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270107-bib-0021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270107-cit-0021">
<string-name>
<surname>Sava</surname>, <given-names>M.&#x02010;P.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Hara</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Alexandra</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>H&#x000fc;gli</surname>, <given-names>R.W.</given-names>
</string-name> &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Hirschmann</surname>, <given-names>M.T.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2023</year>) <article-title>Verasense sensor&#x02010;assisted total knee arthroplasty showed no difference in range of motion, reoperation rate or functional outcomes when compared to manually balanced total knee arthroplasty: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Knee Surgery, Sports Traumatology, Arthroscopy</source>, <volume>31</volume>(<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>1851</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1858</lpage>. Available from: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00167-023-07352-9</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270107-bib-0022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270107-cit-0022">
<string-name>
<surname>Shalhoub</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Lawrence</surname>, <given-names>J.M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Keggi</surname>, <given-names>J.M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Randall</surname>, <given-names>A.L.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>DeClaire</surname>, <given-names>J.H.</given-names>
</string-name> &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Plaskos</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>Imageless, robotic&#x02010;assisted total knee arthroplasty combined with a robotic tensioning system can help predict and achieve accurate postoperative ligament balance</article-title>. <source>Arthroplasty Today</source>, <volume>5</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>334</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>340</lpage>. Available from: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.artd.2019.07.003</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31516978</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270107-bib-0023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270107-cit-0023">
<string-name>
<surname>Shalhoub</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Moschetti</surname>, <given-names>W.E.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Dabuzhsky</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Jevsevar</surname>, <given-names>D.S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Keggi</surname>, <given-names>J.M.</given-names>
</string-name> &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Plaskos</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Laxity profiles in the native and replaced knee&#x02010;application to robotic&#x02010;assisted gap&#x02010;balancing total knee arthroplasty</article-title>. <source>The Journal of Arthroplasty</source>, <volume>33</volume>(<issue>9</issue>), <fpage>3043</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3048</lpage>. Available from: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arth.2018.05.012</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29909956</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270107-bib-0024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270107-cit-0024">
<string-name>
<surname>Song</surname>, <given-names>S.J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Lee</surname>, <given-names>H.W.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Kim</surname>, <given-names>K.I.</given-names>
</string-name> &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Park</surname>, <given-names>C.H.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Load imbalances existed as determined by a sensor after conventional gap balancing with a tensiometer in total knee arthroplasty</article-title>. <source>Knee Surgery, Sports Traumatology, Arthroscopy</source>, <volume>28</volume>(<issue>9</issue>), <fpage>2953</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2961</lpage>. Available from: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00167-019-05699-6</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270107-bib-0025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270107-cit-0025">
<string-name>
<surname>Takashima</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Takayama</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ishida</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Muratsu</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Matsushita</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Niikura</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names>
</string-name> et al. (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Comparison of intraoperative soft tissue balance measurement between two tensor systems in total knee arthroplasty</article-title>. <source>The Knee</source>, <volume>27</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>1071</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1077</lpage>. Available from: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.knee.2020.03.011</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32305234</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270107-bib-0026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270107-cit-0026">
<string-name>
<surname>Valtanen</surname>, <given-names>R.S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Seligson</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Huddleston</surname>, <given-names>H.G.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Angibaud</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names>
</string-name> &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Huddleston</surname>, <given-names>J.I.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2024</year>) <article-title>Improved clinical outcomes with dynamic, force&#x02010;controlled, gap&#x02010;balancing in posterior&#x02010;stabilized total knee arthroplasty</article-title>. <source>Journal of Artroplasty</source>, <volume>39</volume>, <fpage>S218</fpage>. Available from: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arth.2024.02.022</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270107-bib-0027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270107-cit-0027">
<string-name>
<surname>Verstraete</surname>, <given-names>M.A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Meere</surname>, <given-names>P.A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Salvadore</surname>, <given-names>G.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Victor</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name> &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Walker</surname>, <given-names>P.S.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Contact forces in the tibiofemoral joint from soft tissue tensions: implications to soft tissue balancing in total knee arthroplasty</article-title>. <source>Journal of Biomechanics</source>, <volume>58</volume>, <fpage>195</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>202</lpage>. Available from: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jbiomech.2017.05.008</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28579262</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270107-bib-0028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270107-cit-0028">
<string-name>
<surname>Weiner</surname>, <given-names>T.R.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Shah</surname>, <given-names>R.P.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Neuwirth</surname>, <given-names>A.L.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Geller</surname>, <given-names>J.A.</given-names>
</string-name> &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Cooper</surname>, <given-names>H.J.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2024</year>) <article-title>Soft tissue laxity is highly variable in patients undergoing total knee arthroplasty</article-title>. <source>Arthroplasty</source>, <volume>6</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>45</fpage>. Available from: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s42836-024-00268-w</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39107828</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jeo270107-bib-0029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jeo270107-cit-0029">
<string-name>
<surname>Woelfle</surname>, <given-names>C.A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Weiner</surname>, <given-names>T.R.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Sculco</surname>, <given-names>P.K.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Sarpong</surname>, <given-names>N.O.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Shah</surname>, <given-names>R.P.</given-names>
</string-name> &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Cooper</surname>, <given-names>H.J.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2024</year>) <article-title>Surgeon&#x02010;applied stress and a ligament tensor instrument provide a similar assessment of preresection flexion laxity during robotic total knee arthroplasty</article-title>. <source>Arthroplasty Today</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <elocation-id>101450</elocation-id>. Available from: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.artd.2024.101450</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39071093</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>