<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" id="jch70074" xml:lang="en" article-type="article-commentary"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Clin Hypertens (Greenwich)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Clin Hypertens (Greenwich)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.1111/(ISSN)1751-7176</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JCH</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Journal of Clinical Hypertension</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1524-6175</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1751-7176</issn><publisher><publisher-name>John Wiley and Sons Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Hoboken</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40407360</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12100758</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jch.70074</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">JCH70074</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Commentary</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Commentary</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Can Cardiovascular Risk Factors Be Predicted? The Case of Weight&#x02010;Adjusted Waist Index</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="jch70074-cr-0001" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Borghi</surname><given-names>Claudio</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8039-8781</contrib-id><xref rid="jch70074-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><address><email>claudio.borghi@unibo.it</email></address></contrib><contrib id="jch70074-cr-0002" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fiorini</surname><given-names>Giulia</given-names></name><xref rid="jch70074-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="jch70074-aff-0001">
<label>
<sup>1</sup>
</label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Department of Cardiovascular Medicine</named-content>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">IRCCS Azienda Ospedaliero&#x02010;Universitaria di Bologna</named-content>
<institution>University of Bologna</institution>
<city>Bologna</city>
<country country="IT">Italy</country>
</aff><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>23</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>27</volume><issue seq="400">5</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jch.v27.5</issue-id><elocation-id>e70074</elocation-id><history>
<date date-type="rev-recd"><day>14</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></date>
<date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>05</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></date>
</history><permissions><!--&#x000a9; 2025 Wiley Periodicals LLC.--><copyright-statement content-type="article-copyright">&#x000a9; 2025 The Author(s). <italic toggle="yes">The Journal of Clinical Hypertension</italic> published by Wiley Periodicals LLC.</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link> License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="file:JCH-27-e70074.pdf"/><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="0"/><page-count count="3"/><word-count count="1921"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>source-schema-version-number</meta-name><meta-value>2.0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>May 2025</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>details-of-publishers-convertor</meta-name><meta-value>Converter:WILEY_ML3GV2_TO_JATSPMC version:6.5.6 mode:remove_FC converted:23.05.2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="opening-section" id="jch70074-sec-0010"><label>1</label><p>In recent years, the quest for reliable indicators of metabolic health has intensified, particularly in the context of rising global obesity rates [<xref rid="jch70074-bib-0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. The increase in the prevalence of obesity is associated with an increase in cardiovascular and metabolic&#x02010;related mortality and morbidity that can be partially explained with the increase in the prevalence of several cardiometabolic risk factors, including hypertension, diabetes, lipid disorders, and elevated serum uric acid [<xref rid="jch70074-bib-0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. The traditional methods for assessing obesity, such as body mass index (BMI) and waist circumference, have their limitations since BMI does not account for fat distribution, while waist circumference fails to consider body weight. This problem has been recently emphasized by a publication of the Lancet Diabetes &#x00026; Endocrinology Commission [<xref rid="jch70074-bib-0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] suggesting the need for a new estimate of overweight/obesity to overcome the limitations of the current definitions. This is the reason why several alternative measures of overweight have come into play. Among the plethora of metrics available, the Weight&#x02010;Adjusted Waist Index (WWI) estimated by dividing the waist circumference (in cm) by the square root of body weight (in kg) [<xref rid="jch70074-bib-0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] has emerged as a promising contender [<xref rid="jch70074-bib-0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. By adjusting waist circumference for weight, the WWI offers a more nuanced perspective on an individual's metabolic status. It effectively combines the advantages of both waist measurement and weight, providing a clearer picture of visceral fat accumulation, which is more closely associated with metabolic diseases.</p><p>In the present issue of the Journal, Miao et&#x000a0;al. [<xref rid="jch70074-bib-0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] have explored the potential of WWI as a predictive tool in patients with hypertension and hyperuricemia (HTN&#x02010;HUA), two conditions that are increasingly prevalent and often interlinked. Hypertension is a major risk factor for cardiovascular diseases and is often exacerbated by obesity [<xref rid="jch70074-bib-0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Hyperuricemia, characterized by elevated uric acid levels in the blood, is not only a precursor to gout but is also associated with various metabolic disorders, including hypertension [<xref rid="jch70074-bib-0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Hypertension and elevated urate levels are frequently associated in the same patients, particularly in the presence of obesity [<xref rid="jch70074-bib-0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="jch70074-bib-0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] that could represent an early promoter of both cardiometabolic risk factors. The interplay between these three conditions underscores the need for effective screening tools that can identify individuals at risk before the onset of more severe health issues.</p><p>The study has examined the population of the National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey (NHANES) database during the period 1999&#x02013;2018 and has reached the conclusion of a significant and nonlinear association between WWI and HTN&#x02010;HUA. A weaker, but significant correlation has also been observed between WWI and SUA or HTN alone, suggesting the predictive role of such a novel index of overweight in the identification of patients with multiple cardiometabolic risk factors.</p><p>The results agree with emerging studies suggest that WAWI may be a strong predictor of HTN&#x02010;HUA [<xref rid="jch70074-bib-0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Increased blood pressure and serum uric acid are closely correlated, and several papers in the past years [<xref rid="jch70074-bib-0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="jch70074-bib-0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] have demonstrated that elevated SUA can precede the increase in blood pressure values according to a mechanistic relationship mainly based on the level of oxidative stress produced by the activity of xanthine&#x02010;oxidase, that is, the primary pathway to produce circulating uric acid [<xref rid="jch70074-bib-0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. The rationale behind the evidence provided by the paper of Miao et&#x000a0;al. [<xref rid="jch70074-bib-0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] is straightforward: a higher WWI indicates a greater proportion of abdominal fat relative to body weight, which is a significant risk factor for both conditions. The best support to this interpretation is probably the metabolic syndrome, which often combines the presence of overweight with high blood pressure and increased SUA levels, resulting in an excess in the risk of cardiovascular disease [<xref rid="jch70074-bib-0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. In particular, overweight, hypertension, and elevated SUA contribute to reduce insulin sensitivity that is largely known as a common promoter of cardiometabolic mortality and morbidity. As visceral fat is known to produce inflammatory markers and disrupt metabolic regulation, it becomes imperative to monitor this index, particularly in populations with high obesity rates. The evaluation of WWI might represent a simple approach to identify the presence of an underlying condition of insulin resistance and could be adopted for the extensive screening of the general population with the scope of an early prevention of cardiometabolic diseases. Interestingly, the results of the paper of Miao et&#x000a0;al. [<xref rid="jch70074-bib-0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] suggest that the predictive role of WWI on HTN&#x02010;SUA condition is more evident in younger subjects and in patients with normal body weight, where the future onset of cardiometabolic diseases is usually hard to predict. This observation has remarkable practical implications since the measure of WWi can be easily achieved and could be introduced to improve the preventive policies in to the general population of the world. Furthermore, the implementation of WWI in clinical practice could enhance our ability to stratify risk among subjects with mild to moderate risk of cardiometabolic disease and contribute to the reclassification of subjects amenable of a more aggressive preventive strategy. For healthcare providers, incorporating WWI into routine assessments could facilitate early intervention strategies, such as lifestyle modifications or pharmacotherapy, aimed at reducing hypertension and managing uric acid levels. This proactive approach could lead to improve patient outcomes and potentially reduce the burden on healthcare systems.</p><p>However, while the initial findings surrounding WWI are promising, further research is necessary to validate its efficacy across diverse populations and age groups. Longitudinal studies that track the relationship between WAWI and the onset of HTN&#x02010;HUA will be crucial in establishing its utility as a standard clinical tool. Additionally, understanding the mechanisms underlying the association between WWI and these conditions will inform targeted prevention strategies.</p><p>In the paper of Miao et al. [<xref rid="jch70074-bib-0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], the major limitation of the use of WWI as a predictive tool, is the fact that the information that can be drawn is limited to only two of the components of the composite cardiometabolic risk profile. No evidence is provided about the relationship between WWI and glucose control or lipid profile, considered the major determinants of future cardiometabolic profile Included&#x000a0;a strong impact on the development of high blood pressure and uric acid disorders. This drawback can be partially limited by statistical adjustments, whose impact is, however, significantly reduced by the confounding effects of collinearity and pathophysiological interactions among risk factors. An additional limitation of the study is the definition of hyperuricemia, that is, based on a &#x0201c;rheumatological&#x0201d; approach that identifies abnormal serum uric acid levels based on the risk of developing gout. Conversely, many evidence has been published supporting a lower threshold of serum urate for the development of cardiovascular disease, including myocardial infarction, stroke, and heart failure [<xref rid="jch70074-bib-0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="jch70074-bib-0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="jch70074-bib-0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Virdis et&#x000a0;al. [<xref rid="jch70074-bib-0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] have reported a significant increase in the relative risk of cardiovascular disease in subjects with serum uric acid levels between 4.5 and 5.5&#x000a0;mg/dL. Similar results have been provided in the population of the Rotterdam study [<xref rid="jch70074-bib-0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] and in a large Chinese population where the cardiovascular impact of elevated uric acid has been evaluated in subjects without additional risk factors for cardiovascular disease [<xref rid="jch70074-bib-0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. A lower threshold for the definition of hyperuricemia might increase the predictive role of the WWI with the inclusion of a proportion of subjects at risk of cardiometabolic disease and currently included in the normal subgroup and, for this reason, excluded from the preventive strategies. This broader approach would not produce an increase in the resources required for the measure and interpretation of the potential role of WWI with a potential advantage in terms of a number of subjects that could benefit of an early approach to cardiometabolic prevention.</p><p>In conclusion, the WWI presents a compelling case as a predictive measure for HTN&#x02010;HUA. As we strive to address the growing epidemic of metabolic disorders, it is vital that we embrace innovative tools that provide deeper insights into our patients&#x02019; health. The adoption of WAWI could represent a significant step forward in our efforts to combat these interconnected health challenges, ultimately paving the way for a healthier future.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="jch70074-bibl-0001"><title>References</title><ref id="jch70074-bib-0001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jch70074-cite-0001">
<string-name>
<given-names>P. Z.</given-names>
<surname>Zimmet</surname>
</string-name> and <string-name>
<given-names>K. G. M. M.</given-names>
<surname>Alberti</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>Global and Societal Implications of the Diabetes Epidemic</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Nature</source>
<volume>414</volume>, no. <issue>6865</issue> (<year>2016</year>): <fpage>782</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>787</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/414782a</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jch70074-bib-0002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jch70074-cite-0002">
<string-name>
<given-names>F.</given-names>
<surname>Lopez&#x02010;Jimenez</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>W.</given-names>
<surname>Almahmeed</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
<surname>Bays</surname>
</string-name>, et&#x000a0;al., &#x0201c;<article-title>Obesity and Cardiovascular Disease: Mechanistic Insights and Management Strategies. A Joint Position Paper by the World Heart Federation and World Obesity Federation</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>European Journal of Preventive Cardiology</source>
<volume>29</volume> (<year>2022</year>): <fpage>2218</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2237</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36007112</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jch70074-bib-0003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jch70074-cite-0003">
<string-name>
<given-names>F.</given-names>
<surname>Rubino</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>D. E.</given-names>
<surname>Cummings</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>R. H.</given-names>
<surname>Eckel</surname>
</string-name>, et&#x000a0;al., &#x0201c;<article-title>Definition and Diagnostic Criteria of Clinical Obesity</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Lancet Diabetes Endocrinology</source>
<volume>13</volume>, no. <issue>3</issue> (<year>2025</year>): <fpage>221</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>262</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2213-8587(24)00316-4</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39824205</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jch70074-bib-0004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jch70074-cite-0004">
<string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Liu</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Yu</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
<surname>Wang</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>X.</given-names>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>F.</given-names>
<surname>Wang</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
<surname>Zhu</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>Weight&#x02010;Adjusted Waist Index as a Practical Predictor for Diabetes, Cardiovascular Disease, and Non&#x02010;Accidental Mortality Risk</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Nutrition, Metabolism and Cardiovascular Diseases</source>
<volume>34</volume> (<year>2024</year>): <fpage>2498</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2510</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jch70074-bib-0005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jch70074-cite-0005">
<string-name>
<given-names>S. A.</given-names>
<surname>Toh</surname>
</string-name> and <string-name>
<given-names>Y. H.</given-names>
<surname>Kwan</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>The Weight&#x02010;Adjusted Waist Index: A Novel Indicator of Obesity and Its Relationship With Cardiovascular Risk Factors</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Journal of Clinical Hypertension</source>
<volume>22</volume>, no. <issue>5</issue> (<year>2020</year>): <fpage>825</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>832</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jch.13933</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jch70074-bib-0006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jch70074-cite-0006">
<string-name>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
<surname>Miao</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>Z.</given-names>
<surname>Zhou</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>Z.</given-names>
<surname>Yin</surname>
</string-name>, et&#x000a0;al., &#x0201c;<article-title>Weight&#x02010;Adjusted Waist Index May Predict Hypertension plus Hyperuricemia</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Journal of Clinical Hypertension</source>
<volume>27</volume>, no. <issue>3</issue> (<year>2025</year>): <elocation-id>e70022</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40101112</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jch70074-bib-0007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jch70074-cite-0007">
<collab collab-type="authors">NCD Risk Factor Collaboration</collab>
, <article-title>Worldwide Trends in Hypertension Prevalence and Progress in Treatment and Control From 1990 to 2019: A Pooled Analysis of 1201 Population&#x02010;Representative Studies With 104 Million Participants</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>
<volume>398</volume> (<year>2021</year>): <fpage>957</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>980</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34450083</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jch70074-bib-0008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jch70074-cite-0008">
<string-name>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
<surname>Borghi</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
<surname>Agnoletti</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A. F. G.</given-names>
<surname>Cicero</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
<surname>Lurbe</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Virdis</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>Uric Acid and Hypertension: A Review of Evidence and Future Perspectives for the Management of Cardiovascular Risk</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Hypertension</source>
<volume>79</volume>, no. <issue>9</issue> (June <year>2022</year>): <fpage>1927</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1936</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35658505</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jch70074-bib-0009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jch70074-cite-0009">
<string-name>
<given-names>H. S.</given-names>
<surname>Kahn</surname>
</string-name> and <string-name>
<given-names>D. F.</given-names>
<surname>Williamson</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>The Relationship of Waist Circumference and Body Mass Index With Hypertension and Hyperuricemia</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>International Journal of Obesity</source>
<volume>14</volume>, no. <issue>9</issue> (<year>1990</year>): <fpage>725</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>730</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ijo.1990.116</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jch70074-bib-0010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jch70074-cite-0010">
<string-name>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
<surname>Yang</surname>
</string-name> and <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Wang</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>The Role of Visceral Fat in Hypertension and Hyperuricemia: A Review</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Current Hypertension Reports</source>
<volume>20</volume>, no. <issue>9</issue> (<year>2018</year>): <fpage>77</fpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11906-018-0910-2</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29992362</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jch70074-bib-0011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jch70074-cite-0011">
<string-name>
<given-names>Q.</given-names>
<surname>Sun</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
<surname>Yang</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Liu</surname>
</string-name>, et&#x000a0;al., &#x0201c;<article-title>Association of the Weight&#x02010;Adjusted Waist Index With Hypertension in the Context of Predictive, Preventive, and Personalized Medicine</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>EPMA Journal</source>
<volume>15</volume> (<year>2024</year>): <fpage>491</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>500</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39239106</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jch70074-bib-0012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jch70074-cite-0012">
<string-name>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
<surname>Borghi</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
<surname>Agabiti&#x02010;Rosei</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>R. J.</given-names>
<surname>Johnson</surname>
</string-name>, et&#x000a0;al., &#x0201c;<article-title>Hyperuricaemia and Gout in Cardiovascular, Metabolic and Kidney Disease</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>European Journal of Internal Medicine</source>
<volume>80</volume> (<year>2020</year>): <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32739239</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jch70074-bib-0013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jch70074-cite-0013">
<string-name>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
<surname>Massimo</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>R. S.</given-names>
<surname>Khambata</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
<surname>Chapman</surname>
</string-name>, et&#x000a0;al., &#x0201c;<article-title>Natural Mutations of Human <italic toggle="yes">XDH</italic> Promote the Nitrite (NO2<sup>&#x02212;</sup>)&#x02010;Reductase Capacity of Xanthine Oxidoreductase: A Novel Mechanism to Promote Redox Health?</article-title>&#x0201d; <source>Redox Biology</source>
<volume>67</volume> (<year>2023</year>): <elocation-id>102864</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37713777</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jch70074-bib-0014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jch70074-cite-0014">
<string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Maloberti</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
<surname>Tognola</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>I.</given-names>
<surname>Garofani</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>Uric Acid and Metabolic Syndrome: Importance of Hyperuricemia Cut&#x02010;Off</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>International Journal of Cardiology</source>
<volume>417</volume> (<year>2024</year>): <elocation-id>132527</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39244097</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jch70074-bib-0015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jch70074-cite-0015">
<string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Virdis</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Masi</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
<surname>Casiglia</surname>
</string-name>, et&#x000a0;al., &#x0201c;<article-title>Identification of the Uric Acid Thresholds Predicting an Increased Total and Cardiovascular Mortality over 20 Years</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Hypertension</source>
<volume>75</volume>, no. <issue>2</issue> (<year>2020</year>): <fpage>302</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>308</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31813345</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jch70074-bib-0016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jch70074-cite-0016">
<string-name>
<given-names>M. J.</given-names>
<surname>Bos</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>P. J.</given-names>
<surname>Koudstaal</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Hofman</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J. C.</given-names>
<surname>Witteman</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>M. M.</given-names>
<surname>Breteler</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>Uric Acid Is a Risk Factor for Myocardial Infarction and Stroke: The Rotterdam Study</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Stroke</source>
<volume>37</volume> (<year>2006</year>): <fpage>1503</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1507</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16675740</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jch70074-bib-0017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jch70074-cite-0017">
<string-name>
<given-names>X.</given-names>
<surname>Tian</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
<surname>Wang</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Chen</surname>
</string-name>, et&#x000a0;al., &#x0201c;<article-title>Association of Normal Serum Uric Acid Level and Cardiovascular Disease in People without Risk Factors for Cardiac Diseases in China</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Journal of the American Heart Association</source>
<volume>12</volume> (<year>2023</year>): <elocation-id>e029633</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37183869</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>