<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Chem Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Chem Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SC</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="coden">CSHCBM</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Chemical Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2041-6520</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2041-6539</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Royal Society of Chemistry</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40271041</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12013506</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">d5sc01663k</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/d5sc01663k</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Chemistry</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Pt-free MoS<sub>2</sub> co-catalyst enables record photocurrent density in Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> photocathodes for highly efficient solar hydrogen production<xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">&#x02020;</xref></article-title><fn-group><fn id="fn1"><label>&#x02020;</label><p>Electronic supplementary information (ESI) available. See DOI: <uri xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1039/d5sc01663k">https://doi.org/10.1039/d5sc01663k</uri></p></fn></fn-group></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9402-5468</contrib-id><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>Munir</given-names></name><xref rid="affa" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gul</surname><given-names>Anadil</given-names></name><xref rid="affb" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5228-0882</contrib-id><name><surname>Aziz</surname><given-names>Hafiz Sartaj</given-names></name><xref rid="affa" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0657-8423</contrib-id><name><surname>Imran</surname><given-names>Tahir</given-names></name><xref rid="affa" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5308-7811</contrib-id><name><surname>Ishaq</surname><given-names>Muhammad</given-names></name><xref rid="affa" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Abbas</surname><given-names>Muhammad</given-names></name><xref rid="affa" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2137-3933</contrib-id><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>Zhenghua</given-names></name><xref rid="affa" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1512-376X</contrib-id><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Shuo</given-names></name><xref rid="affa" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><aff id="affa">
<label>a</label>
<institution>Institute of Thin Film Physics and Applications, Shenzhen Key Laboratory of Advanced Thin Films and Applications, Key Laboratory of Optoelectronic Devices and Systems of Ministry of Education and Guangdong Province, State Key Laboratory of Radio Frequency Heterogeneous Integration, College of Physics and Optoelectronic Engineering, Shenzhen University</institution>
<city>Shenzhen</city>
<postal-code>518060</postal-code>
<country>China</country>
<email>chensh@szu.edu.cn</email>
</aff><aff id="affb">
<label>b</label>
<institution>College of Health Science and Environmental Engineering, Shenzhen Technology University</institution>
<city>Shenzhen</city>
<postal-code>518118</postal-code>
<country>China</country>
</aff></contrib-group><pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pub" iso-8601-date="2025-04-16"><day>16</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="collection" iso-8601-date="2025-05-21"><day>21</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>16</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><!--PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>.--><volume>16</volume><issue>20</issue><fpage>8946</fpage><lpage>8958</lpage><history><date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="2025-03-02"><day>2</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="2025-04-14"><day>14</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>This journal is &#x000a9; The Royal Society of Chemistry</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Royal Society of Chemistry</copyright-holder><ali:free_to_read xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/"/><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense" start_date="2025-04-16">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported Licence</ext-link>. You can use material from this article in other publications without requesting further permissions from the RSC, provided that the correct acknowledgement is given.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Antimony selenide (Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>) emerges as a potential light-absorbing material for thin film photovoltaics and photoelectrochemical (PEC) water-splitting devices, due to its earth-abundant constituents and excellent photoelectric properties. However, losses caused by corrosion and sluggish charge transfer at the semiconductor/electrolyte interface require a co-catalyst to enhance these kinetic factors. In this study, MoS<sub>2</sub> is employed as a cost-effective, noble-metal-free catalyst to enhance the photocurrent density (<italic toggle="yes">J</italic><sub>ph</sub>), half-cell solar-to-hydrogen (HC-STH) conversion efficiency and stability of Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>-based photocathodes. Optimized thermodynamic/kinetic physical vapor deposition of MoS<sub>2</sub> substantially improves PEC performance, resulting champion Mo/Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS/MoS<sub>2</sub> photocathode that achieves a record <italic toggle="yes">J</italic><sub>ph</sub> of 31.03 mA cm<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> at 0 <italic toggle="yes">V</italic><sub>RHE</sub> and the highest HC-STH efficiency of 3.08%, along with stability for over 5 hours in an acidic (pH 1) buffer solution. It is systematically revealed that MoS<sub>2</sub> reduces the photo-corrosion effect, decreases electron&#x02013;hole recombination, and provides a significant increase in charge transfer efficiency at the semiconductor/electrolyte interface. This work highlights the potential of cost-effective, high-performance Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>-based photocathodes in advancing efficient PEC devices for solar hydrogen production.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="toc"><p>MoS<sub>2</sub> serves as low-cost and Pt-free co-catalyst that improves charge carrier dynamics in Mo/Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS/MoS<sub>2</sub> photocathode. Its optimized integration minimizes interfacial recombination, leading to record <italic toggle="yes">J</italic><sub>ph</sub> of 31.03 mA cm<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> and HC-STH of 3.08%.<graphic xlink:href="d5sc01663k-ga.jpg" id="ga" position="float"/></p></abstract><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>National Natural Science Foundation of China</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100001809</institution-id></institution-wrap>
</funding-source><award-id>62474114</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>Basic and Applied Basic Research Foundation of Guangdong Province</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100021171</institution-id></institution-wrap>
</funding-source><award-id>2023A1515011256</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>Science and Technology Planning Project of Shenzen Municipality</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100013093</institution-id></institution-wrap>
</funding-source><award-id>JCYJ20240813141620027</award-id></award-group></funding-group><counts><page-count count="13"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pubstatus</meta-name><meta-value>Paginated Article</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><label>1.</label><title>Introduction</title><p>Hydrogen production by solar-driven water splitting in photoelectrochemical (PEC) devices is one of the most attractive strategies to convert clean and abundant radiation into non-polluting and storable chemical fuels.<sup><xref rid="cit1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> Hydrogen energy is a carbon-free fuel that can be used in various industries, transportation, and heating applications. Currently, burning fossil fuels produces the majority of hydrogen, which leads to serious carbon emission problems.<sup><xref rid="cit2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> Production of green hydrogen energy through sunlight harvesting is a highly efficient approach for overcoming worldwide environmental problems and energy shortages; however, it remains challenging.<sup><xref rid="cit3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> Recently, different research groups have focused on introducing new photocatalysts or advanced methods to produce hydrogen energy through water splitting. Among these technologies, PEC solar water splitting is a clean, sustainable, and cost-effective, technique to produce hydrogen from solar irradiation.<sup><xref rid="cit4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> Some well-studied oxides, for example, CuFeO<sub>2</sub><sup><xref rid="cit5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> and Cu<sub>2</sub>O,<sup><xref rid="cit6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> and different chalcogenides like CuInS<sub>2</sub>,<sup><xref rid="cit7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> CuGaSe<sub>2</sub>,<sup><xref rid="cit8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> and CuIn<sub>1&#x02212;<italic toggle="yes">x</italic></sub>Ga<sub><italic toggle="yes">x</italic></sub>Se<sub>2</sub> (ref. <xref rid="cit9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> and <xref rid="cit10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>) as well as newly emerging materials like Cu<sub>2</sub>ZnSn(S,Se)<sub>4</sub>,<sup><xref rid="cit2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> Cu<sub>2</sub>BaSn(S,Se)<sub>4</sub>&#x02009;<sup><xref rid="cit11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> and Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> &#x02009;<sup><xref rid="cit12" ref-type="bibr">12&#x02013;14</xref></sup> are studied as photocathode materials.</p><p>Among the materials for hydrogen production, Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> has emerged as an excellent light-absorbing material for PEC applications because of its earth-abundant elements, low-cost, eco-friendly, high absorption coefficient (&#x0003e;10<sup>5</sup> cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), suitable bandgap (&#x0223c;1.2 eV), and remarkable photoelectric properties. Additionally, Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> exhibits intrinsic stability in neutral and acidic electrolytes, with negligible self-reduction or photo-corrosion, making it a suitable material for efficient PEC photocathodes.<sup><xref rid="cit15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> Despite these advantages, Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>-based photocathodes face many challenges such as surface corrosion caused by multiple functional layers, electron&#x02013;hole non-radiative recombination caused by defects, and sluggish charge transfer at the semiconductor/electrolyte interface, which limit their PEC efficiency and long-term stability. To address these challenges, employing a suitable co-catalyst on the photocathode surface is very important. Noble metals like platinum (Pt) have been widely used as co-catalysts in Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>-based photocathodes, but their high cost and rare availability limit their commercial applications.<sup><xref rid="cit16" ref-type="bibr">16,17</xref></sup> Hence, the search for cost-effective and non-toxic alternative co-catalysts is highly desirable for developing efficient Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>-based photocathodes.</p><p>Recently, the development of co-catalysts like metal alloys, carbides, phosphides, nitrides, borides, and chalcogenides for the representative hydrogen evolution reaction (HER) has made significant progress.<sup><xref rid="cit18" ref-type="bibr">18,19</xref></sup> Among them, molybdenum sulfide (MoS<sub>2</sub>) has gained attention as a promising noble-metal-free co-catalyst. As a transition metal dichalcogenide (TMD), MoS<sub>2</sub> possesses a suitable 2D layered structure, excellent chemical stability, and favorable band alignment for inducing the HER.<sup><xref rid="cit20" ref-type="bibr">20,21</xref></sup> Additionally, amorphous MoS<sub>2</sub> has a high concentration of active sites at the edge layers, which enhances its electrocatalytic activity as compared to the crystalline form.<sup><xref rid="cit22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> A solution-based approach to synthesize MoS<sub>2</sub> (crystalline/amorphous) has been used in different photocathodes (<italic toggle="yes">e.g.</italic>, Cu<sub>2</sub>O, Cu<sub>2</sub>ZnSnS<sub>4</sub>, and Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>).<sup><xref rid="cit23" ref-type="bibr">23,24</xref></sup> Actually, it still encounters challenges in terms of scalability, thickness uniformity, and composition variability.<sup><xref rid="cit24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> In contrast, physical vapor deposition (PVD) techniques, such as sputtering, provide a suitable preparation method for producing uniform, large-scale, and stable MoS<sub>2</sub> thin film co-catalysts; however, this approach remains underexplored.<sup><xref rid="cit25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup></p><p>This work started the preparation of eco-friendly Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> light-harvesting films with favorable growth orientation and large crystal grains through an efficient combination reaction involving pre-sputtered and post-selenized Sb metallic precursors. After CdS buffer layer deposition, the binary compound MoS<sub>2</sub> was sputtered as a co-catalyst instead of using noble-metal Pt, with a focus on MoS<sub>2</sub> co-catalyst thickness engineering to enhance both light-harvesting efficiency and HER activity. In short, the introduction of optimized MoS<sub>2</sub> could significantly alleviate the photo-corrosion effect, suppress charge carrier recombination loss, and reduce the charge transfer resistance at the semiconductor/electrolyte interface. Moreover, the MoS<sub>2</sub> incorporation contributed to a favorable surface wettability with more reaction sites and favorable surface band bending with accelerated photoelectron transfer characteristics. As a result, the champion MoS<sub>2</sub>-modified Pt-free Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> photocathode exhibited a record photocurrent density (<italic toggle="yes">J</italic><sub>ph</sub>) of 31.03 mA cm<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> at 0 V <italic toggle="yes">versus</italic> the reversible hydrogen electrode (RHE, <italic toggle="yes">V</italic><sub>RHE</sub>), and the highest half-cell solar-to-hydrogen (HC-STH) conversion efficiency of 3.08% in a pH 1 acid buffer solution. Furthermore, the device exhibited a significant improvement in long-term stability as compared to its Pt-involved counterpart. This work highlights the potential of PVD-processed MoS<sub>2</sub> as a cost-effective and highly-efficient co-catalyst, advancing the development of efficient and stable Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>-based photocathodes for solar hydrogen production.</p></sec><sec><label>2.</label><title>Experimental section</title><sec><label>2.1.</label><title>Preparation of Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS/MoS<sub>2</sub> photocathodes</title><p>The Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> light-absorbing layer and CdS buffer layer were sequentially deposited on a Mo-coated soda lime glass substrate according to our previously reported work.<sup><xref rid="cit26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> After the deposition of Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> and CdS, the MoS<sub>2</sub> layer with different thicknesses ranging from 20 to 40 nm was deposited as a co-catalyst by RF (radio frequency) magnetron sputtering using a MoS<sub>2</sub> target. It was carried out with a 50 W sputtering power, an Ar gas flow of 50 sccm, and a working pressure of 2 Pa. The MoS<sub>2</sub> layer thickness was controlled by sputtering deposition times of 400 s, 600 s, and 800 s, yielding 20, 30, and 40 nm MoS<sub>2</sub> layers based on a 0.05 nm s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> deposition rate, and the corresponding samples were labelled as M-20, M-30, and M-40 respectively. Finally, the Mo layer was exposed at the thin film edge to achieve a conductive back contact, and Ag colloids were deposited on its surface by thermal evaporation. The schematic of the synthesis process of glass/Mo/Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS/MoS<sub>2</sub> photocathode is shown in Fig. S1 (ESI).<xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">&#x02020;</xref></p></sec><sec><label>2.2.</label><title>Characterization</title><p>The crystallinity of Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>-based photocathodes was studied by X-ray diffraction (XRD) using an Ultima-IV diffractometer with Cu K<sub>&#x003b1;</sub> radiation. The morphologies of the surface, cross-section, and structure were acquired using a scanning electron microscope (SEM, Zeiss SUPRA 55) and the corresponding elemental composition was studied by using an energy dispersive spectroscope (EDS, BRUKER QUANTAX 200). The valence states of the involved elements were studied using X-ray photoelectron spectroscopy (XPS, Thermo Scientific ESCALAB 250Xi). <italic toggle="yes">In situ</italic> sputter etching was performed using a 10 kV Gas Cluster Ion Beam (GCIB) with a 6 &#x000d7; 6 mm<sup>2</sup> surface treatment area during the XPS measurement. Atomic force microscopy (AFM) operated, <italic toggle="yes">via</italic> NT-MDT spectrum instruments in semi-contact mode, was used for the investigation of thin film morphology and surface roughness. Surface potential and topography characterization were further analyzed through a Kelvin probe force microscope (KPFM, Bruker Dimension ICON). Raman spectroscopy (Renishaw, InVia) was used for studying bonding information. PEC performance characterization was performed with an electrochemical workstation (CHI660e) under a three-electrode configuration, <italic toggle="yes">i.e.</italic>, Ag/AgCl electrode as the reference electrode, Pt-wire as the counter electrode, and the as-fabricated photocathode as the working electrode. All tests were performed in acid electrolyte under simulated sunlight illumination (AM 1.5G) at a calibrated light intensity of 100 mW cm<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>. Photoelectrochemical impedance spectroscopy (PEIS) was performed under simulated sunlight illumination in a 10<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> to 10<sup>2</sup> kHz frequency range at 0 <italic toggle="yes">V</italic><sub>RHE</sub>. Mott&#x02013;Schottky (M&#x02013;S) experiments were performed in the dark using a 30 mV AC amplitude, scanning voltage between &#x02212;0.5 and 0.1 V and a frequency of 10<sup>4</sup> Hz.</p></sec></sec><sec><label>3.</label><title>Results and discussion</title><p>Mo/Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS/MoS<sub>2</sub> thin-film photocathodes with different MoS<sub>2</sub> co-catalyst loading amounts (<italic toggle="yes">i.e.</italic>, 20 nm, 30 nm, and 40 nm) were prepared and studied; the corresponding devices were labelled as M-20, M-30, and M-40, respectively. Their PEC performance was measured using a classical 3-electrode PEC workstation, as shown in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1a</xref>. Upon light illumination, continuous visible hydrogen bubbles were observed on the photocathode surface, which migrated toward the acidic electrolyte (<italic toggle="yes">i.e.</italic>, 0.5 M H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>), indicating the efficient HER through water splitting (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1b</xref>). The as-prepared Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> photocathodes of area 2 &#x000d7; 2 cm<sup>2</sup> were quasi-homogenous, as shown in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1b</xref> (inset), suggesting great potential in scalable applications. Before performing PEC measurements, a defined active area of 0.95 cm<sup>2</sup> was exposed using a water-resistant, light-resistant glue to ensure accurate and reproducible performance evaluation. Generally, the thickness of both the light-absorbing layer (Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>) and co-catalysts (MoS<sub>2</sub>) is very important for balancing charge carrier generation and HER activity. The current density&#x02013;potential (<italic toggle="yes">J</italic>&#x02013;<italic toggle="yes">V</italic>) curves of the M-20, M-30, and M-40 photocathodes under chopped light illumination and continuous light illumination are depicted in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1c and d</xref>, respectively. The M-20 photocathode with a 20 nm MoS<sub>2</sub> layer exhibited relatively low PEC performance, with a low <italic toggle="yes">J</italic><sub>ph</sub> of &#x0223c;21.93 mA cm<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> at 0 <italic toggle="yes">V</italic><sub>RHE</sub>. Moreover, its unsatisfactory HC-STH conversion efficiency of 2.22% was measured using the following equation:<sup><xref rid="cit2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup><disp-formula id="eqn1"><label>1</label>HC-STH (%) = <italic toggle="yes">J</italic><sub>ph</sub> &#x000d7; (<italic toggle="yes">V</italic><sub>RHE</sub> &#x02212; <italic toggle="yes">V</italic><sub>H<sup>+</sup>/H<sub>2</sub></sub>)/<italic toggle="yes">P</italic><sub>SUN</sub> &#x000d7; 100%</disp-formula>where <italic toggle="yes">J</italic><sub>ph</sub> is the photocurrent density at an applied potential of <italic toggle="yes">V</italic><sub>RHE</sub>, <italic toggle="yes">V</italic><sub>H<sup>+</sup>/H<sub>2</sub></sub> represents the equilibrium redox potential for hydrogen (0 <italic toggle="yes">V</italic><sub>RHE</sub>), and <italic toggle="yes">P</italic><sub>SUN</sub> denotes the sunlight intensity, set at 100 mW cm<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>. This low PEC performance can be attributed to insufficient active sites, poor protection against photo-corrosion and higher recombination rates. When the MoS<sub>2</sub> layer thickness was increased to 30 nm (M-30), an obvious increase in <italic toggle="yes">J</italic><sub>ph</sub> was observed, reaching &#x0223c;31.03 mA cm<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1c</xref>), along with an impressive HC-STH conversion efficiency exceeding 3%. This optimized MoS<sub>2</sub> could provide ideal surface coverage with more active sites and photoelectron transport pathways, while decreasing surface defects and recombination centers. It effectively achieved a balance between light absorption and catalytic activity, allowing efficient solar water splitting and hydrogen production. However, further increasing the MoS<sub>2</sub> layer thickness to 40 nm (M-40) led to a decrease in <italic toggle="yes">J</italic><sub>ph</sub> (&#x0223c;26.97 mA cm<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>) and HC-STH efficiency (2.34%). This indicates that beyond a certain thickness, the MoS<sub>2</sub> layer impeded light penetration into the Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> absorber layer to generate charge carriers due to serious parasitic light absorption losses.<sup><xref rid="cit27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> To further validate the optimization, additional samples with 25 nm (M-25) and 35 nm (M-35) MoS<sub>2</sub> thicknesses were investigated, both of which exhibited inferior PEC performance compared to M-30, with lower <italic toggle="yes">J</italic><sub>ph</sub> (&#x0223c;25.84 mA cm<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> and 29.21 mA cm<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>) and HC-STH efficiencies (2.60% and 2.75%) respectively (Fig. S2a and b<xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">&#x02020;</xref>). These results further confirm that 30 nm represents the optimal MoS<sub>2</sub> thickness for maximizing PEC performance in our Mo/Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS/MoS<sub>2</sub> photocathode system. Additionally, another indicator of onset potential (<italic toggle="yes">V</italic><sub>on</sub>), usually defined as the potential at which the steep <italic toggle="yes">J</italic>&#x02013;<italic toggle="yes">V</italic> curves start, herein, was precisely measured by extrapolating the <italic toggle="yes">J</italic>&#x02013;<italic toggle="yes">V</italic> curves in the quickly increasing regions (Fig. S3<xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">&#x02020;</xref>). It is very important to mention that the obtained <italic toggle="yes">J</italic><sub>ph</sub> (&#x0223c;31.03 mA cm<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>) and <italic toggle="yes">V</italic><sub>on</sub> (&#x0223c;0.43 <italic toggle="yes">V</italic><sub>RHE</sub>) values belonging to the champion M-30 photocathode are obviously higher than those of previously reported MoS<sub>2</sub>-coated Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>-based photocathodes (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1f, g</xref> and <xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). They also provide a comparative analysis of the PEC performance against previously reported state-of-the-art MoS<sub>2</sub> co-catalyst-based Si, InP, GaP, and CZTS photocathodes; our device demonstrates comparable performance, especially with a higher <italic toggle="yes">J</italic><sub>ph</sub>. Finally, the statistical distributions of different performance parameters are shown in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1h&#x02013;j</xref>, presenting synchronous variation with key MoS<sub>2</sub> thickness, confirming satisfactory reproducibility for efficient scalable solar hydrogen evolution applications.</p><fig position="float" id="fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>(a) Schematic diagram of a typical three-electrode PEC measurement system. (b) A picture of hydrogen bubbles originating from the surface of the photocathode and moving towards the electrolyte; (inset) photograph of a typical Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> photocathode. <italic toggle="yes">J</italic>&#x02013;<italic toggle="yes">V</italic> curves of the photocathodes under dark conditions and chopped sunlight illumination (c), and under dark conditions and continuous sunlight illumination (d). (e) The obtained HC-STH conversion efficiencies. (f and g) A comparison of our work with some state-of-the-art chalcogenide-based photocathodes. Statistical plots of M-20, M-30, and M-40 photocathodes, <italic toggle="yes">i.e.</italic>, (h) <italic toggle="yes">J</italic><sub>ph</sub>, (i) <italic toggle="yes">V</italic><sub>on</sub>, and (j) HC-STH conversion efficiencies.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="d5sc01663k-f1" position="float"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Summary of the PEC performances of different photocathodes using MoS<sub><italic toggle="yes">x</italic></sub> compound as a co-catalyst</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Photoelectrode</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">HER co-catalyst</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Buffer solution</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">J</italic>
<sub>ph</sub> (mA cm<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">V</italic>
<sub>on</sub> (<italic toggle="yes">V</italic><sub>RHE</sub>)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">HC-STH (%)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stability (time, remain)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Sb</bold>
<sub>
<bold>2</bold>
</sub>
<bold>Se</bold>
<sub>
<bold>3</bold>
</sub>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>MoS</bold>
<sub>
<bold>2</bold>
</sub>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>pH 1</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>31.03</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.43</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>3.08</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>5 h, 90%</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>This work</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MoS<sub><italic toggle="yes">x</italic></sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pH 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5 h, 93%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="cit28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MoS<sub><italic toggle="yes">x</italic></sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pH 0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 h, 70%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="cit29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MoS<sub><italic toggle="yes">x</italic></sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pH 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.8</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="cit30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MoS<sub>2</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pH 6.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="cit20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CZTS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MoS<sub><italic toggle="yes">x</italic></sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pH 3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 h, 70%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="cit27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Si</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MoS<sub>2</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pH 0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.6</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 h, 78%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="cit31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GaP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MoS<sub><italic toggle="yes">x</italic></sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pH 0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.4</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="cit32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-Si</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MoS<sub>2</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pH 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.3</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 h</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="cit33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n<sup>+</sup>n p<sup>+</sup>-Si</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MoS<sub>2</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pH 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.34</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 h</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="cit34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">InP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MoS<sub>3</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pH 0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 h, 90%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="cit35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>
</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>A detailed morphological and structural investigation was first carried out to validate the quality of the Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> light-absorbing thin film, the interface modification <italic toggle="yes">via</italic> MoS<sub>2</sub> as a co-catalyst, and its impact on PEC performance of the device. The XRD patterns of the pure Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> and Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS/MoS<sub>2</sub> thin films are presented in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2a</xref>. The high purity and crystallinity of the as-deposited Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> films are confirmed by the presence of four major diffraction peaks, corresponding to the (211), (221), (321), and (002) planes, consistent with the standard Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> (JCPDS Card No. 15-0861). These distinct peaks suggest the formation of a highly crystalline light-absorbing layer, which is crucial for minimizing defect states and optimizing charge carrier mobility within the film. After deposition of CdS and MoS<sub>2</sub>, two additional peaks appear at 24.97&#x000b0; and 58.9&#x000b0; corresponding to the (111) plane of CdS and (110) plane of MoS<sub>2</sub>, according to JCPDS Card No. 41-1049 and JCPDS Card No. 37-1492, respectively. The peak observed for MoS<sub>2</sub> is assigned to pure MoS<sub>2</sub> highlighted in Fig. S4a,<xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">&#x02020;</xref> while its compact granular structure can also be observed from the SEM image of MoS<sub>2</sub> in Fig. S4d<xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">&#x02020;</xref>. The (111) plane of CdS, known for its optimal electron transport properties, combined with the catalytic (110) plane of MoS<sub>2</sub>, suggests, improved charge transfer and catalytic activity at the semiconductor/electrolyte interface, likely contributing to enhanced PEC performance observed in the Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS/MoS<sub>2</sub> photocathode.<sup><xref rid="cit36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup> The obtained results were further confirmed by analyzing the texture coefficient (TC) to examine the preferred orientation in Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> and Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS/MoS<sub>2</sub> thin films, using the following equation:<sup><xref rid="cit37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup><disp-formula id="eqn2"><label>2</label><graphic xlink:href="d5sc01663k-t1.jpg" id="ugt1" position="float"/></disp-formula>where <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">I</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">hkl</italic>), and <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sub>0</sub>(<italic toggle="yes">hkl</italic>) show the peak number utilised during calculations, the intensity of the measured diffraction, and the reported diffraction intensity (PDF card), respectively. <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2b</xref> illustrates an overall increase in the TC of (<italic toggle="yes">hk</italic>1) planes, coupled with a decrease in the TC of the (<italic toggle="yes">hk</italic>0) planes after the deposition of CdS and MoS<sub>2</sub> layers on the Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> thin film, suggesting a reorientation of the crystallographic structure of Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> driven by the post-deposition processes. The improvement of the (<italic toggle="yes">hk</italic>1) planes is typically associated with optimal carrier transport and high charge mobility, resulting improved charge transfer pathways in the Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS/MoS<sub>2</sub> photocathode.<sup><xref rid="cit37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup><xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2c</xref> presents the Raman spectra of pure Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> and Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS/MoS<sub>2</sub> thin-film photocathodes. In the Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> spectrum, the most prominent peak of Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> phase around 190 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> is observed, which refers to the A<sub>2u</sub> mode of the Sb&#x02013;Sb bond, one of the most common vibrational modes in the Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> phase. The additional peak around 210 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> corresponds to Sb&#x02013;Se bond vibration within the Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> unit. In the Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS/MoS<sub>2</sub> spectrum, an intense peak appears around 300 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> corresponding to the longitudinal optical mode of the hexagonal CdS buffer layer. Moreover, two additional peaks at about 385 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and 405 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> are observed, which correspond to the in-plane E<sub>2g</sub> and out-plan A<sub>1g</sub> modes of MoS<sub>2</sub>, respectively.<sup><xref rid="cit38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></sup> The presence of these characteristic peaks in Raman spectra of the pure as-deposited MoS<sub>2</sub> thin film (Fig. S4c<xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">&#x02020;</xref>) confirms the successful deposition and integration of the crystalline MoS<sub>2</sub> layer within the Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS/MoS<sub>2</sub> photocathode via the PVD process. Importantly, its layered structure and beneficial crystallographic orientation might interact synergistically with the Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS layers to reduce the photo-corrosion effect, and provide a substantial decrease in charge transfer resistance.<sup><xref rid="cit39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup></p><fig position="float" id="fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><title>(a) XRD, (b) texture coefficient of XRD peaks, and (c) Raman spectra of bare Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> and Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS/MoS<sub>2</sub> samples. (d) XPS survey graph of Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS/MoS<sub>2</sub>, the binding energy displacement of (e) Sb and (f) Se. XPS spectra for (g) Cd 3d, (h) S 2p, and (i) Mo 3d.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="d5sc01663k-f2" position="float"/></fig><p>X-ray photoelectron spectroscopy (XPS) investigations were performed to better understand the chemical composition. <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2d</xref> shows the XPS survey spectra of Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS/MoS<sub>2</sub>. <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2e</xref> demonstrates the Sb 3d spectra with binding energies b/w 525 and 545 eV for both bare Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> and Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS/MoS<sub>2</sub>. The separation between the peaks of Sb 3d doublet pairs was retained at 9.58 eV.<sup><xref rid="cit40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup> It was also confirmed from the Se spectra shown in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2f</xref>, that two doublets of Se (3d<sub>5/2</sub> and 3d<sub>3/2</sub>), separated by 0.78 eV energy, showing the presence of Se<sup>2&#x02212;</sup>. Moreover, <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2e</xref> reveals a prominent shift in the Sb 3d peak toward lower binding energy in the case of Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS/MoS<sub>2</sub>. As an explanation, at the Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS/MoS<sub>2</sub> interface, the higher Fermi levels of n-type CdS and MoS<sub>2</sub> cause electron flow to p-type Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> until equilibrium is reached, resulting in band bending, with Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> bands shifting upward and the CdS/MoS<sub>2</sub> bands bending downward, also confirming the favorable formation of the Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS/MoS<sub>2</sub> junction. Two notable peaks positioned at 412.2 eV and 405 eV (shown in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2g</xref>) are assigned to Cd 3d<sub>3/2</sub> and 3d<sub>5/2</sub> respectively. <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2h</xref> shows two distinguished peaks located at 162.8 eV and 161.5 eV, which correspond to S 2p<sub>1/2</sub> and S 2P<sub>3/2</sub> respectively. The Mo 3d and S 2s core level regions, with binding energies ranging from 222 to 242 eV, are depicted in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2i</xref>. The Mo 3d doublet peaks demonstrating the presence of Mo<sup>4+</sup> (Mo 3d<sub>5/2</sub> and Mo 3d<sub>3/2</sub>) appear around 229 and 232 eV, respectively. These peaks are characteristic of the MoS<sub>2</sub> structure, confirming that Mo occurs primarily in its active Mo<sup>4+</sup> state, which is important for promoting efficient charge transfer and catalyzing the HER. Furthermore, the S 2s peak around 226 eV confirms the presence of sulfur (S<sup>2&#x02212;</sup>) in the MoS<sub>2</sub> layer.<sup><xref rid="cit41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup> The Mo 3d third peak around 235 eV corresponding to the Mo<sup>6+</sup> state of MoO<sub>3</sub> shows the presence of a Mo oxide state in MoS<sub>2</sub>. The presence of MoO<sub>3</sub> shows the oxidation of the MoS<sub>2</sub> layer, which may results from sulfur vacancies during deposition or exposure to air, where sulfur vacancies react with oxygen, or from interactions between Mo and the substrate surface.<sup><xref rid="cit42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup></p><p>Scanning electron microscopy (SEM) images show the surface morphologies of Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>, Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS and Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS/MoS<sub>2</sub> thin films depicted in <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3a&#x02013;c</xref>. Additionally, the corresponding energy dispersive spectroscopy (EDS) information is presented in Fig. S5a&#x02013;c,<xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">&#x02020;</xref> which supports the elemental composition. The smooth surface morphology of pristine Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> becomes rougher gradually after the deposition of the CdS and MoS<sub>2</sub> layers. This enhanced surface roughness indicates the successful deposition of CdS and MoS<sub>2</sub> layers and is predicted to have an impact on the photocathode's light absorption and charge carrier dynamics. The cross-sectional SEM images (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3d&#x02013;f</xref>) confirm the compact deposition of all three layers. MoS<sub>2</sub> forms a conformal layer over the CdS-coated Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> surface, potentially covering grain boundaries and interfaces without significantly altering the surface topography. This homogeneous distribution of MoS<sub>2</sub> is very important for enhancing charge separation and creating efficient electron transport pathways, thus enhancing PEC performance.<sup><xref rid="cit27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> Wettability is an important parameter assessed by measuring the contact angle (CA) between solid and fluid surfaces and can be classified as completely wettable (CA = 0&#x000b0;), hydrophobic or poorly wettable (CA &#x0003e; 90&#x000b0;) and hydrophilic or partially wettable (CA &#x0003c; 90&#x000b0;).<sup><xref rid="cit40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup> The wettability of Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>, Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS, and Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS/MoS<sub>2</sub> (M-30) samples was examined through CAs formed between the sample surfaces and H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> electrolyte droplets. According to <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3g&#x02013;i</xref>, the Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>, Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS, and Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS/MoS<sub>2</sub> (M-30) sample surfaces exhibit hydrophilic nature with CAs of 88.6&#x000b0;, 79.5&#x000b0;, and 69.8&#x000b0;, respectively. To further validate this, the CAs of 89.2&#x000b0;, 67.6&#x000b0;, and 56.3&#x000b0; for the same samples were also measured by using glycerol droplets which display similar trends as depicted in Fig. S7a&#x02013;c.<xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">&#x02020;</xref> Importantly, the M-30 sample depicts the minimum CA, demonstrating a significant enhancement in wettability after MoS<sub>2</sub> deposition. Additionally, the M-20 and M-40 samples display higher CAs values of 76.9&#x000b0; and 72.2&#x000b0; (Fig. S6a and b<xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">&#x02020;</xref>), respectively, which are still lower than that of Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS but higher than that of the M-30 sample which suggests that the M-30 sample achieves optimal wettability among the other samples. This variation is closely related to changes in roughness, surface tension of liquids, free energy, and grain size of the solid surface. Such enhanced wettability improves the PEC performance of photocathodes by increasing the number of exposed reaction sites and enabling photoelectron transfer.<sup><xref rid="cit26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> The roughness and surface morphologies of the corresponding Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>, Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS, and Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS/MoS<sub>2</sub> thin films were studied using atomic force microscopy (AFM) (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3j&#x02013;l</xref>). Additionally, 2D and 3D images of the pure MoS<sub>2</sub> thin film are shown in Fig. S9a and b.<xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">&#x02020;</xref> The average root mean square (RMS) surface roughness value of Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> is 105 nm, followed by 117 nm for Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS, and 154 nm for the Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS/MoS<sub>2</sub> (M-30) thin film surface. Notably, the M-20 and M-40 samples exhibit RMS roughness values of 129 nm and 146 nm, respectively (Fig. S8a and b<xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">&#x02020;</xref>), which are lower than that of the M-30 sample. This indicates that the M-30 sample has the most textured surface among the MoS<sub>2</sub>-coated samples, which may contribute to its higher PEC performance. Thus, it can be speculated that the improvement in wettability of Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS/MoS<sub>2</sub> might be result from the evolution of surface roughness, which matches well with the roughness-dependent wettability model presented by Wenzel, <italic toggle="yes">i.e.</italic>, the roughness will make a naturally hydrophilic surface more hydrophilic.<sup><xref rid="cit43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></sup></p><fig position="float" id="fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><title>SEM micrographs of (a) Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>, (b) Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS, and (c) Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS/MoS<sub>2</sub> samples. (d&#x02013;f) The corresponding cross-sectional SEM images. (g&#x02013;i) The measured CAs (using H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> electrolyte droplets) of the samples, and (j&#x02013;l) AFM images of the sample surfaces.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="d5sc01663k-f3" position="float"/></fig><p>Kelvin probe force microscopy (KPFM) analysis was then performed; this advanced technique allowed us to study the topography and contact potential difference (<italic toggle="yes">V</italic><sub>CPD</sub>) across thin films, providing critical insights into their surface properties. <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4a, e and i</xref> show the micrographs, and <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4b, f, and j</xref> show the surface potential distributions for Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>, Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS, and Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS/MoS<sub>2</sub> samples, respectively. The AFM images indicate that the surface morphology of the Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> thin films remains consistent across different layer depositions, which correlates well with the top-view SEM micrographs (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3a&#x02013;c</xref>). The pronounced contrast in CPD between grain interiors and boundaries indicates a strong intergranular carrier extraction, which facilitates efficient charge separation and carrier transport, contributing to enhanced PEC performance. The white arrow line scans, which show CPD variations for Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>, Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS, and Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS/MoS<sub>2</sub> (M-30), are depicted in <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4c, g, and k</xref>, and those for M-20 and M-40 are shown in Fig. S10a and b,<xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">&#x02020;</xref> respectively; these scans show the electronic landscape of the samples. The CPD values for Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>, Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS, and Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS/MoS<sub>2</sub> samples lie in the range of &#x02212;50 to 30 mV, and a similar decrease in CPD from the grain interior (GI) to the grain boundary (GB) can be observed. This indicates that the sample work function at the GB is lower, <italic toggle="yes">i.e.</italic>, the Fermi energy level <italic toggle="yes">E</italic><sub>F</sub> at the GB is closer to the vacuum level, leading to a downward band bending at the GB. The corresponding schematic diagrams of the energy band structure are presented in <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4d, h and l</xref>. Upon further comparison, the average potential difference between the GB and GI for Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>, Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS, and Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS/MoS<sub>2</sub> are 23, 35, and 45 mV, respectively. Thus, the increased band bending after the deposition of CdS and MoS<sub>2</sub> would effectively separate electron&#x02013;hole pairs by attracting electrons (minority carriers) towards the GBs while promoting holes (majority carriers) to flow into GIs. This mechanism is very important for improving electron extraction and minimizing electron&#x02013;hole recombination, as well as guiding the charge carriers towards the interface to improve photocurrent generation. Thus, it is predicted to contribute to a higher <italic toggle="yes">J</italic><sub>ph</sub> in photocathode, improving the PEC performance.<sup><xref rid="cit44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></sup></p><fig position="float" id="fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><title>KPFM scanning surface topography and CPD maps for (a and b) Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>, (e and f) Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS, and (i and j) Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS/MoS<sub>2</sub> samples, respectively. (c, g and k) The corresponding topography and potential line scans acquired from the white arrow lines. (d, h and l) Schematic of the energy band structure and CPD near the GBs, where &#x0201c;e<sup>&#x02212;</sup>&#x0201d; represents electrons; &#x0201c;h<sup>+</sup>&#x0201d; represents holes.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="d5sc01663k-f4" position="float"/></fig><p>The photocurrent response and charge transport kinetics of the Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>-based photocathodes were thoroughly examined. In <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5a</xref>, the transient photocurrent decay spectra show that M-20 and M-40 photocathodes exhibited a prominent &#x0201c;spike-like&#x0201d; transient behavior upon light illumination, indicating substantial charge carrier recombination since the temporarily accumulated photoelectrons might easily recombine before reaching a steady state. Conversely, the M-30 photocathode exhibits a very small &#x0201c;spike-like&#x0201d; transient, suggesting reduced charge recombination and improved carrier transport, which is closely related to its optimized surface co-catalyst coverage and photoelectron transport.<sup><xref rid="cit26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> Specifically, the charge transfer efficiency (<italic toggle="yes">&#x003b7;</italic><sub>tran</sub>) is defined as the ratio of the steady-state photocurrent density (<italic toggle="yes">J</italic><sub>ss</sub>) to the instantaneous photocurrent density (<italic toggle="yes">J</italic><sub>inst</sub>). The charge separation efficiency (<italic toggle="yes">&#x003b7;</italic><sub>sep</sub>) can also be obtained using the following equations:<sup><xref rid="cit26" ref-type="bibr">26,45</xref></sup><disp-formula id="eqn3"><label>3</label><graphic xlink:href="d5sc01663k-t2.jpg" id="ugt2" position="float"/></disp-formula><disp-formula id="eqn4"><label>4</label><italic toggle="yes">J</italic><sub>ph</sub> = <italic toggle="yes">J</italic><sub>abs</sub> &#x000d7; <italic toggle="yes">&#x003b7;</italic><sub>tran</sub> &#x000d7; <italic toggle="yes">&#x003b7;</italic><sub>sep</sub></disp-formula></p><fig position="float" id="fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><title>(a) Transient photocurrent response of M-20, M-30, and M-40 photocathodes. (b) Light harvesting efficiency (LHE) of M-20, M-30 and M-40 photocathodes. (c) Energy density flux for the AM 1.5G standard solar spectrum and integrated <italic toggle="yes">J</italic><sub>ph</sub> of the M-30 sample. (d) Nyquist plots and (e) the equivalent Bode plots of M-20, M-30, and M-40 photocathodes. (f) Schematic diagram along with the corresponding equivalent circuit system related to charge carrier dynamics procedures. (g) UPS characterization derived <italic toggle="yes">V</italic><sub>B</sub> positions and SEC edges of the MoS<sub>2</sub> thin film. (h) M&#x02013;S plots of the pure MoS<sub>2</sub>-30 thin film at a frequency of 1 kHz. (i) Schematic energy band alignment of the Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS/MoS<sub>2</sub> photocathode. H<sub>2</sub> generation amount as a function of AM 1.5G solar light illumination time over the (j) M-20, (k) M-30, and (l) M-40 photocathodes at 0 <italic toggle="yes">V</italic><sub>RHE</sub> for 2 h in pH 1 buffer solution.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="d5sc01663k-f5" position="float"/></fig><p>As a result, the M-30 photocathode achieved the highest <italic toggle="yes">&#x003b7;</italic><sub>tran</sub> of 97.31%, as compared to 81.39% and 93.05% for M-20 and M-40, respectively. In parallel, the <italic toggle="yes">&#x003b7;</italic><sub>sep</sub> for M-30 was also the highest at 82.04%, while M-20 and M-40 exhibited lower values of 51.42% and 69.74%, respectively. The optimized M-30 device simultaneously achieved high charge separation and transport, resulting in improved PEC performance. The theoretical <italic toggle="yes">J</italic><sub>ph</sub> (<italic toggle="yes">i.e.</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">J</italic><sub>abs</sub>) of the Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>-based photocathodes was also calculated (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5b, c</xref>, S11a, b and Note S1, ESI<xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">&#x02020;</xref>) by using the standard solar spectrum (AM 1.5G) and wavelength-dependent light harvesting efficiency (LHE), and assuming 100% conversion of the absorbed photons to current density. Since <italic toggle="yes">&#x003bb;</italic><sub>e</sub> is &#x02248;1070 nm, the calculations show that the M-30 photocathode achieves a theoretical <italic toggle="yes">J</italic><sub>abs</sub> of 38.23 mA cm<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5c</xref>), which is the highest among the three samples (<italic toggle="yes">J</italic><sub>abs</sub> values of 30.04 mA cm<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> and 33.82 mA cm<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> for M-20 and M-40, respectively). The enhanced <italic toggle="yes">J</italic><sub>abs</sub> for M-30 can be attributed to its ideal MoS<sub>2</sub> thickness and light absorption capacity. Photoelectrochemical impedance spectroscopy (PEIS) investigation of Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>-based photocathodes was conducted to evaluate the charge transfer resistance and specific charge carrier recombination mechanisms within the system. <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5d</xref> represents the Nyquist plots for M-20, M-30, and M-40 photocathodes, displaying two distinct arcs for each sample, consistent with the corresponding Bode plots shown in <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5e</xref>. The Bode diagram illustrates two different regions, covering the low and high frequencies in the range of 1 to 100 kHz. The PEIS data were fitted using an equivalent circuit model consisting of a series resistance (<italic toggle="yes">R</italic><sub>S</sub>) and two pairs of parallel resistor&#x02013;capacitor (<italic toggle="yes">R</italic>&#x02013;<italic toggle="yes">C</italic>) elements, as shown in <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5f</xref>. The as-fitted results for M-20, M-30, and M-40 photocathodes are presented in Table S1.<xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">&#x02020;</xref> In <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5f</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">R</italic><sub>S</sub> represents the series resistance at the Mo/Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> back contact interface, and the comparable <italic toggle="yes">R</italic><sub>S</sub> values (&#x02248;5&#x02013;6 &#x003a9;) across the device indicated a well-established and favorable back interface contact. The high-frequency arc-derived <italic toggle="yes">R</italic><sub>HF</sub> and <italic toggle="yes">C</italic><sub>HF</sub> reflect the charge transfer resistance at the semiconductor heterojunction interface and the associated capacitance within the space charge region. In contrast, <italic toggle="yes">R</italic><sub>LF</sub> and <italic toggle="yes">C</italic><sub>LF</sub> (low frequency arc derivatives) represent the electrochemical charge transfer/reaction resistance within the Helmholtz layer at the electrode&#x02013;electrolyte interface, along with the corresponding interface/surface-states capacitance.<sup><xref rid="cit46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></sup> Notably, the smaller <italic toggle="yes">C</italic><sub>HF</sub> value (5.03 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup> F) for the M-30 photocathode implies a shorter charge accumulation time, while the reduced <italic toggle="yes">R</italic><sub>HF</sub> value suggests less interface defects and more effective charge carrier transport and separation efficiencies at the Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS heterojunction interface. Furthermore, the minimum <italic toggle="yes">R</italic><sub>LF</sub> value of 4.599 &#x003a9; for M-30 as compared to 16.955 &#x003a9; for M-20 and 7.929 &#x003a9; for M-40 counterparts indicates more efficient HER at the electrode&#x02013;electrolyte interface under suitable MoS<sub>2</sub> co-catalyst loading.</p><p>Bulk and interface charge carrier dynamic characteristics strongly affect the PEC performance of the Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>-based thin films photocathodes. Therefore, ultraviolet photoelectron spectroscopy (UPS) characterization was performed to examine the energy band alignment of the Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> absorber, CdS buffer layer (Fig. S11c and d<xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">&#x02020;</xref>) and MoS<sub>2</sub> (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5g</xref>) thin films to further understand the recombination, transport and separation of charge carriers. According to the secondary electron cut-off (SEC) edge and valence band (<italic toggle="yes">V</italic><sub>B</sub>) position, the conduction band (<italic toggle="yes">E</italic><sub>C</sub>) of MoS<sub>2</sub> is &#x02212;3.94 eV. Compared with the normal hydrogen electrode (NHE), it is &#x02212;0.50 <italic toggle="yes">V</italic><sub>NHE</sub>, with the conversion implemented by using the following formula:<sup><xref rid="cit47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></sup><disp-formula id="eqn5"><label>5</label>Energy = &#x02212;<italic toggle="yes">eE</italic><sub>appl</sub>(<italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> NHE) &#x02212; 4.44 eV</disp-formula></p><p>The conduction band minimum (CBM) of the MoS<sub>2</sub> thin film is located above the hydrogen reduction potential, which thermodynamically enhances water reduction with hydrogen evolution through solar water splitting, resulting in an enhanced <italic toggle="yes">J</italic><sub>ph</sub>. Mott&#x02013;Schottky (M&#x02013;S) measurements were further performed to investigate the capacitance of MoS<sub>2</sub> thin films by examining film capacitance (<italic toggle="yes">C</italic>) at the semiconductor/electrolyte interface as a function of the applied potential (<italic toggle="yes">V</italic>). <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5h</xref>, S12a and b<xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">&#x02020;</xref> demonstrate that 1/<italic toggle="yes">C</italic><sup>2</sup> increases with potential <italic toggle="yes">V</italic> in the presence of the space charge region (SCR), demonstrating evident n-type characteristics for MoS<sub>2</sub> films.<sup><xref rid="cit48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></sup> Furthermore, the acceptor density (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic><sub>A</sub>) and flat band potential (<italic toggle="yes">E</italic><sub>fb</sub>) were calculated using the following equation:<sup><xref rid="cit2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup><disp-formula id="eqn6"><label>6</label><graphic xlink:href="d5sc01663k-t3.jpg" id="ugt3" position="float"/></disp-formula>where <italic toggle="yes">e</italic> is the electron unit, <italic toggle="yes">&#x003b5;</italic> is the relative dielectric constant, <italic toggle="yes">&#x003b5;</italic><sub>0</sub> is the vacuum permittivity, <italic toggle="yes">T</italic> represents the temperature, <italic toggle="yes">k</italic> represents the Boltzmann constant, <italic toggle="yes">A</italic> represents the active device area, <italic toggle="yes">N</italic><sub>A</sub> represents the accepter density, and <italic toggle="yes">C</italic> is the SCR capacitance forms at the semiconductor&#x02013;electrolyte interface. The analysis shows that the pure MoS<sub>2</sub>-30 (30 nm) thin film exhibited the lowest <italic toggle="yes">N</italic><sub>A</sub> (3.54 &#x000d7; 10<sup>17</sup> cm<sup>&#x02212;3</sup>), compared to pure MoS<sub>2</sub>-20 (20 nm) (4.21 &#x000d7; 10<sup>18</sup> cm<sup>&#x02212;3</sup>) and pure MoS<sub>2</sub>-40 (40 nm) (7.81 &#x000d7; 10<sup>17</sup> cm<sup>&#x02212;3</sup>) (Fig. S12a and b<xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">&#x02020;</xref>). This lower <italic toggle="yes">N</italic><sub>A</sub> value in pure MoS<sub>2</sub>-30 suggests fewer traps for charge carriers, enhanced charge dynamics and a larger space charge region, which together improve charge separation efficiency and reduce recombination losses at the optimal thickness. The valence band (<italic toggle="yes">V</italic><sub>B</sub>) position of MoS<sub>2</sub> can also be calculated from <italic toggle="yes">N</italic><sub>A</sub>, <italic toggle="yes">E</italic><sub>fb</sub>, effective mass of hole <inline-graphic xlink:href="d5sc01663k-t4.jpg" id="ugt4"/>, and valence band effective density of states function (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic><sub>v</sub>), by using the following formula:<sup><xref rid="cit49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></sup><disp-formula id="eqn7"><label>7</label><graphic xlink:href="d5sc01663k-t5.jpg" id="ugt5" position="float"/></disp-formula><disp-formula id="eqn8"><label>8</label><graphic xlink:href="d5sc01663k-t6.jpg" id="ugt6" position="float"/></disp-formula></p><p>The MoS<sub>2</sub> thin film possesses a similar <italic toggle="yes">E</italic><sub>V</sub> value (&#x02212;5.74 eV), which matches well with the UPS-derived <italic toggle="yes">E</italic><sub>V</sub> (&#x02212;5.74 eV). Finally, band bending and energy band alignment for Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS/MoS<sub>2</sub> are depicted in <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5i</xref>. The CdS and MoS<sub>2</sub> thin films exhibit stronger n-type conductive characteristics, suggesting that MoS<sub>2</sub> would increase the electron carrier density. The valence band offset (VBO) values for n-CdS/p-Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> and n-CdS/n-MoS<sub>2</sub> are 1.18 eV and 0.57 eV, respectively, which are similar to those reported in previous work (1.14 &#x000b1; 0.10 eV);<sup><xref rid="cit50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></sup> these values provide the required energy barrier that efficiently stops photo-generated holes from moving toward the electrode&#x02013;electrolyte interface for recombination. The conduction band alignment between Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> and CdS exhibits a &#x0201c;spike-like&#x0201d; band alignment, with a positive conduction band offset (CBO of +0.06 eV), which falls within the optimal range of 0&#x02013;0.4 eV, suitable for high quality semiconductor heterojunctions. This band alignment decreases energy barriers, enhances charge carrier separation and transport while reducing recombination. After that, the electrons migrate from CdS to the MoS<sub>2</sub> layer, which has a slightly higher conduction band edge, further facilitating electron flow. MoS<sub>2</sub> acts as a co-catalyst and provides active sites for the HER at the photocathode surface. This layered band structure, with suitable band-bending, confirms efficient electron transport from Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> through CdS to MoS<sub>2</sub>, while holes are directed toward the back contact. Thus, the MoS<sub>2</sub> layer improves charge separation and enables effective utilization of photo-generated carriers for hydrogen production, increasing overall PEC efficiency.</p><p>Gas chromatography (GC) was used to <italic toggle="yes">in situ</italic> measure the production of H<sub>2</sub> and O<sub>2</sub>, and then evaluate the photon utilization capability and faradaic efficiency. As shown in <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5j&#x02013;l</xref>, the champion M-30 photocathode demonstrated continuous H<sub>2</sub> and O<sub>2</sub> evolution at rates of 8.50 and 5.68 &#x003bc;mol min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, respectively, which are higher than those of M-20 (4.97 and 2.79 &#x003bc;mol min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) and M-40 (6.51 and 4.47 &#x003bc;mol min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) photocathodes. Faradaic efficiencies of 91%, 94% and 92% (calculated from the ratio of H<sub>2</sub> to e<sup>&#x02212;</sup>/2) were obtained for M-20, M-30, and M-40 photocathodes, indicating minimal side reactions or competing redox processes on the photoelectrode surface. After 2 h of continuous irradiation, approximately 1020 &#x003bc;mol of H<sub>2</sub> and 682 &#x003bc;mol of O<sub>2</sub> were generated by the champion M-30 photocathode, further confirming the durability and versatility of the champion M-30 device for PEC processed solar water splitting. The recorded video in 0.5 M H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> buffer solution under AM 1.5G continuous sunlight irradiation during operation shows continues hydrogen production (Movie S1, ESI<xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">&#x02020;</xref>), confirming the excellent PEC performance of the device.</p><p>After the successful demonstration of MoS<sub>2</sub> as an efficient HER co-catalyst, its secondary role as a protective layer was also examined. The current density&#x02013;time (<italic toggle="yes">J</italic>&#x02013;<italic toggle="yes">T</italic>) curves for those three devices are shown in <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6a</xref>, S13a and b,<xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">&#x02020;</xref> under AM 1.5G simulated sunlight illumination at 0 <italic toggle="yes">V</italic><sub>RHE</sub>. As illustrated in <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6a</xref>, when the light was switched on, the <italic toggle="yes">J</italic><sub>ph</sub> of M-30 quickly increased from 0 mA cm<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> to 31.03 mA cm<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>, and when the light was turned off, it quickly returned to its initial value. This fast and stable response demonstrates the excellent reversibility and stability of the MoS<sub>2</sub>-based Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> photocathodes. In addition to developing a highly efficient photocathode, assessing its real long-term PEC stability is also crucial for practical applications. <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6b</xref> displays the photocurrent stability of the champion device (M-30) over 5 h at 0 <italic toggle="yes">V</italic><sub>RHE</sub> under AM 1.5G continuous light irradiation in an H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> buffer solution (pH 1), while Fig. S14a and b<xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">&#x02020;</xref> show the stability tests for M-20 and M-40 devices. The thinner MoS<sub>2</sub> layer in M-20 likely provides insufficient surface protection due to limited surface coverage to directly expose part of the underlying Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS layer to the electrolyte, leading to a higher rate of photo-corrosion and reduced PEC stability. By contrast, the champion M-30 photocathode demonstrated remarkable stability over the 5 h testing period, retaining approximately 90% of its initial <italic toggle="yes">J</italic><sub>ph</sub> under continuous light irradiation. The LSV curves and PEC performance before and after the stability test are shown in Fig. S14c, d and Movie S2.<xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">&#x02020;</xref> Its excellent stability is closely related to the MoS<sub>2</sub> layer with appropriate thickness, which effectively protects the Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS surface, avoiding localized dissolution that could induce thermodynamic photo-corrosion and degradation during prolonged operation. This finding is consistent with other studies in which Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> photocathodes were protected by additional layers like C<sub>60</sub> or TiO<sub>2</sub> to prevent CdS degradation.<sup><xref rid="cit26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> Table S2<xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">&#x02020;</xref> presents a comparative analysis of the PEC performance and stability of Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>-based photocathodes using MoS<sub>2</sub> and Pt as co-catalysts. This comparison highlights the effectiveness of MoS<sub>2</sub> as a low-cost alternative to noble metal catalysts while maintaining competitive PEC activity and durability. To further evaluate the intrinsic stability and lifespan of the Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> absorber (Fig. S13c<xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">&#x02020;</xref>), bare MoS<sub>2</sub> film (Fig. S13d<xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">&#x02020;</xref>), and M-30 thin-film photocathode (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6c</xref>), a photo-corrosion stress test was conducted using cyclic voltammetry. No significant photo-corrosion currents or redox peaks were observed in any of the samples after 100 cycles, strongly suggesting their exceptional tolerance to photo-corrosion during practical PEC applications. As shown in <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6d&#x02013;g</xref>, the PEC performance and stability of the champion M-30 photocathode also varies significantly across different pH buffer solutions. Specifically, it exhibited a <italic toggle="yes">J</italic><sub>ph</sub> of 31.01, 19.67, and 9.60 mA cm<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>, and HC-STH efficiencies of 3.06%, 1.67%, and 0.75% in pH 1, pH 3, and pH 6.5 buffer solutions, respectively, confirming the faster and more efficient HER in acidic buffer solution. Moreover, its photocurrent stability (3 h duration) under acidic conditions (pH 1) is superior to that in neutral (pH 6.5) electrolytes. It is similar to some previous reports, <italic toggle="yes">e.g.</italic>, MoS<sub><italic toggle="yes">x</italic></sub> co-catalyst modified CZTS and InP photocathodes, both of which exhibit high photocurrent and good stability in acidic conditions as compared to neutral buffer solution.<sup><xref rid="cit29" ref-type="bibr">29,35</xref></sup> As shown in <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6h</xref>, this behavior can be described by the fact that, in acidic environments with a higher concentration of H<sup>+</sup> ions, photo-excited electrons can more easily and efficiently combine ionically to produce hydrogen gas.<sup><xref rid="cit51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref></sup> The rapid transport of photo-excited electrons in an acidic buffer solution could also mitigate the photo-corrosion of the photoelectrode, and hence increase the PEC stability of the photocathode.<sup><xref rid="cit3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> These findings are particularly important for optimizing photocathode design for practical solar-driven hydrogen production applications. The enhanced PEC performance under acidic conditions expands the potential applications of these photocathodes to electrocatalysis, sensors, and environmental remediation, where stability under harsh conditions is often a critical requirement.</p><fig position="float" id="fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><title>(a) <italic toggle="yes">J</italic>&#x02013;<italic toggle="yes">T</italic> curve of the M-30 photocathode at 0 <italic toggle="yes">V</italic><sub>RHE</sub> under AM 1.5G simulated solar irradiation. (b) Photocurrent stability experiment of the champion M-30 photocathode at 0 <italic toggle="yes">V</italic><sub>RHE</sub> under continuous sunlight illumination within 5 hours. (c) CV measurement of the M-30 photocathode in 0.5 M H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> under illumination. <italic toggle="yes">J</italic>&#x02013;<italic toggle="yes">V</italic> curves of the M-30 photocathode at different pH solution, and (d) under chopped light, and (e) under continuous light irradiation. (f) The calculated HC-STH conversion efficiencies. (g) Stability of M-30 photocathodes in pH 1, pH 3, and pH 6.5 solution under AM 1.5G simulated light irradiation. (h) Mechanism schematic representation of the PEC performance Mo/Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS/MoS<sub>2</sub> photocathodes.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="d5sc01663k-f6" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec><label>4.</label><title>Conclusion</title><p>In this work, we successfully demonstrated the enhancement of Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>-based photocathodes for solar hydrogen generation by the introduction of MoS<sub>2</sub> as a cost-effective, noble-metal-free co-catalyst. The optimized Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS/MoS<sub>2</sub> photocathode achieved a record <italic toggle="yes">J</italic><sub>ph</sub> of 31.03 mA cm<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> at 0 <italic toggle="yes">V</italic><sub>RHE</sub> and a HC-STH efficiency of 3.08% in a pH 1 buffer solution. The MoS<sub>2</sub> co-catalyst played an important role in increasing the overall performance by decreasing photo-corrosion, electron&#x02013;hole recombination, and charge transfer resistance at the semiconductor/electrolyte interface. Our systematic investigation shows that MoS<sub>2</sub> not only facilitated efficient charge carrier transport but also improved light-harvesting efficiency by optimizing the band alignment at the Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>/CdS interface. This dual function of MoS<sub>2</sub>, as a co-catalyst and a protective layer, contributed to a stable, high-performance photocathode capable of sustained hydrogen evolution over extended periods under acidic conditions. Additionally, the photocathode exhibited improved stability and performance across a range of pH conditions, making it a promising candidate for practical applications in solar hydrogen production. In short, the combination of Sb<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> and MoS<sub>2</sub> offers a feasible, eco-friendly alternative to Pt-based devices, advancing the development of efficient and cost-effective photocathodes for hydrogen production.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The data supporting this article have been included as part of the ESI.<xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">&#x02020;</xref></p></sec><sec><title>Author contributions</title><p>Munir Ahmad: data curation, investigation, methodology, conceptualization, writing &#x02013; original draft. Anadil Gul: methodology, investigation. Hafiz Sartaj Aziz: methodology, investigation. Tahir Imran: data curation, formal analysis. Muhammad Ishaq: data curation, investigation. Muhammad Abbas: data curation, investigation. Zhenghua Su: methodology, investigation. Shuo Chen: conceptualization, formal analysis, writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing, supervision, funding acquisition.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflicts of interest</title><p>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="SC-016-D5SC01663K-s001" position="float" content-type="local-data"><label>SC-016-D5SC01663K-s001</label><media xlink:href="SC-016-D5SC01663K-s001.mp4" id="d67e2630" position="anchor" mimetype="video" mime-subtype="mp4"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SC-016-D5SC01663K-s002" position="float" content-type="local-data"><label>SC-016-D5SC01663K-s002</label><media xlink:href="SC-016-D5SC01663K-s002.mp4" id="d67e2633" position="anchor" mimetype="video" mime-subtype="mp4"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SC-016-D5SC01663K-s003" position="float" content-type="local-data"><label>SC-016-D5SC01663K-s003</label><media xlink:href="SC-016-D5SC01663K-s003.pdf" id="d67e2636" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>This work was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (No. 62474114), Guangdong Basic and Applied Basic Research Foundation (2023A1515011256), China, Science and Technology plan project of Shenzhen (JCYJ20240813141620027), China. The authors are grateful to Prof. Yu-Jia Zeng for assistance with KPFM characterization, at Shenzhen University.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="cit1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Energy Mater.</source><year>2023</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>300004</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.20517/energymater.2022.55</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ishaq</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Adv. Energy Mater.</source><year>2023</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>2300215</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/aenm.202300215</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Boppella</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Adv. Energy Mater.</source><year>2019</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1900179</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/aenm.201900179</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Chem. Eng. J.</source><year>2021</year><volume>403</volume><fpage>126350</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cej.2020.126350</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Reyes-Lillo</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.-S.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Toma</surname><given-names>F. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Prendergast</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>I. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>J. K.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Chem. Mater.</source><year>2019</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>2524</fpage><lpage>2534</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.chemmater.9b00009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hisatomi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nakabayashi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shibata</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Domen</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Delaunay</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Appl. Phys. Lett.</source><year>2016</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>033902</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.4959098</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Minegishi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kaneko</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nakabayashi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hisatomi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Katayama</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shibata</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Chem. Commun.</source><year>2019</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>470</fpage><lpage>473</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C8CC08623K</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30547175</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="cit8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>DeAngelis</surname><given-names>A. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Horsley</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gaillard</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>J. Phys. Chem. C</source><year>2018</year><volume>122</volume><fpage>14304</fpage><lpage>14312</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jpcc.8b02915</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Energy Environ. Sci.</source><year>2018</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>2025</fpage><lpage>2034</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C7EE03650G</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Koo</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Boonmongkolras</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pae</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Byun</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>B. T.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>ACS Appl. Energy Mater.</source><year>2020</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>2296</fpage><lpage>2303</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acsaem.9b02387</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Teymur</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ngaboyamahina</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mitzi</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>ACS Appl. Energy Mater.</source><year>2021</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>87</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acsaem.0c01892</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Nat. Energy</source><year>2022</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>537</fpage><lpage>547</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41560-022-01042-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hutter</surname><given-names>O. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>L. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shim</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Appl. Catal., B</source><year>2021</year><volume>286</volume><fpage>119890</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apcatb.2021.119890</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hutter</surname><given-names>O. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>L. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Major</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Nat. Commun.</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>861</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-020-14704-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32054858</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="cit15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Chem. Eng. J.</source><year>2022</year><volume>429</volume><fpage>132091</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cej.2021.132091</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhen</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>ACS Nano</source><year>2017</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>12753</fpage><lpage>12763</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acsnano.7b07512</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29165986</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="cit17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>H. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hutter</surname><given-names>O. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>L. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tilley</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Major</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Energy Environ. Sci.</source><year>2020</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>4362</fpage><lpage>4370</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/D0EE02959A</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vesborg</surname><given-names>P. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Seger</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chorkendorff</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>J. Phys. Chem. Lett.</source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>951</fpage><lpage>957</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jpclett.5b00306</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26262851</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="cit19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>J. Semicond.</source><year>2023</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>122701</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/1674-4926/44/12/122701</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shinde</surname><given-names>P. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Sol. RRL</source><year>2020</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1900442</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/solr.201900442</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Energy Mater.</source><year>2022</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>200001</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Medina</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Corradini</surname><given-names>P. G.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mascaro</surname><given-names>L. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>J. Braz. Chem. Soc.</source><year>2019</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>2210</fpage><lpage>2218</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shinde</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fontenot</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Donahue</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Waters</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kung</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McNamara</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hammer</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>J. Mater. Chem. A</source><year>2018</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>9569</fpage><lpage>9582</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C8TA01771A</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Morales-Guio</surname><given-names>C. G.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tilley</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vrubel</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gr&#x000e4;tzel</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Nat. Commun.</source><year>2014</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>3059</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms4059</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24402352</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="cit25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J.-H.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>P. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>L.-S.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C. T.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>C. T.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>W. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>T. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Mater. Res. Express</source><year>2016</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>065007</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/2053-1591/3/6/065007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ishaq</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Chem. Eng. J.</source><year>2022</year><volume>431</volume><fpage>133359</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cej.2021.133359</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ikeda</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Appl. Catal., B</source><year>2020</year><volume>268</volume><fpage>118438</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apcatb.2019.118438</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>J. Mater. Chem. A</source><year>2020</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>23385</fpage><lpage>23394</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/D0TA08874A</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Prabhakar</surname><given-names>R. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Septina</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Siol</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Moehl</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wick-Joliat</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tilley</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>J. Mater. Chem. A</source><year>2017</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>23139</fpage><lpage>23145</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C7TA08993G</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>ACS Appl. Mater. Interfaces</source><year>2018</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>10898</fpage><lpage>10908</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acsami.8b00305</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29546757</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="cit31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>English</surname><given-names>C. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cab&#x000e1;n-Acevedo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shearer</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Daniel</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hamers</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source><year>2014</year><volume>136</volume><fpage>8504</fpage><lpage>8507</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ja5025673</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24892384</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="cit32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Standing</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Assali</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Verheijen</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Van Dam</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Notten</surname><given-names>P. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Haverkort</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bakkers</surname><given-names>E. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Nat. Commun.</source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>7824</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms8824</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26183949</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="cit33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dang</surname><given-names>T. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dai Nguyen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Truong</surname><given-names>T. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Man</surname><given-names>M. T.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bui</surname><given-names>T. T. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>T. K. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Truong</surname><given-names>P. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>C. K.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>V. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Mater. Sci. Semicond. Process.</source><year>2021</year><volume>121</volume><fpage>105308</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mssp.2020.105308</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Alarawi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ramalingam</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>H. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Varadhan</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>He</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Opt. Express</source><year>2019</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>A352</fpage><lpage>A363</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1364/OE.27.00A352</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31052887</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="cit35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cavalli</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Standing</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vu</surname><given-names>T. T.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Verheijen</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Haverkort</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bakkers</surname><given-names>E. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Notten</surname><given-names>P. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Nano Lett.</source><year>2014</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>3715</fpage><lpage>3719</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/nl404540f</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24875657</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="cit36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Nanoscale Res. Lett.</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1556-276X-9-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24380376</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="cit37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>G. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Z. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>Z. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>H. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>G.-X.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>ACS Appl. Mater. Interfaces</source><year>2022</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>31986</fpage><lpage>31997</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acsami.2c06805</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35793154</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="cit38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shinde</surname><given-names>N. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Eswaran</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>J. Phys. Chem. Lett.</source><year>2021</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>6197</fpage><lpage>6202</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jpclett.1c01795</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34191524</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="cit39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>J. Mater. Sci.: Mater. Electron.</source><year>2020</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>4574</fpage><lpage>4581</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10854-020-03008-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit40"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chastain</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> and <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>King Jr</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name></person-group>, <source>Handbook of X-ray photoelectron spectroscopy</source>, <publisher-name>Perkin-Elmer Corporation</publisher-name>, <year>1992</year>, vol. <volume>40</volume>, p. 221</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>F. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Medina</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mascaro</surname><given-names>L. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>ACS Appl. Energy Mater.</source><year>2020</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>9799</fpage><lpage>9808</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acsaem.0c01413</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>Y. T.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>C. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Luong</surname><given-names>T. T.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>L. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yen</surname><given-names>T. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>W. T.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>W. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>Y. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>Y. Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pande</surname><given-names>K. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Phys. Status Solidi RRL</source><year>2015</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>187</fpage><lpage>191</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pssr.201409561</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Foadi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>ten Brink</surname><given-names>G. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mohammadizadeh</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Palasantzas</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>J. Appl. Phys.</source><year>2019</year><volume>125</volume><fpage>244307</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.5092672</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Imran</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>K. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>Y. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>Z. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>G. X.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Small</source><year>2024</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>2306516</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/smll.202306516</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37715101</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="cit45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Adv. Mater.</source><year>2019</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>1806938</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/adma.201806938</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Moehl</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Service</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tilley</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Adv. Energy Mater.</source><year>2021</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>2003569</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/aenm.202003569</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Beranek</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Adv. Phys. Chem.</source><year>2011</year><volume>2011</volume><fpage>786759</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2011/786759</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stride</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Adv. Energy Mater.</source><year>2016</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1600046</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/aenm.201600046</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bhatt</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>J. Mater. Chem. A</source><year>2015</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>10632</fpage><lpage>10659</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C5TA00257E</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>B. K.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stride</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tadich</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Appl. Phys. Lett.</source><year>2014</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>173901</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.4873715</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Chem</source><year>2016</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>699</fpage><lpage>726</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>