<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="issn">2168-8184</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cureus</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2168-8184</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cureus</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Palo Alto (CA)</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11681951</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7759/cureus.74687</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Radiology</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Rheumatology</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Dermatology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Advanced Neuroimaging and Clinical Findings in a Case of Linear Scleroderma En Coup De Sabre Presenting With Seizures</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Muacevic</surname><given-names>Alexander</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>John R</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>Yukiyoshi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Soto-Trujillo</surname><given-names>Dafne</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fernandez-Leon</surname><given-names>Karen</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff-1">
<label>1</label>
Radiology, Grupo CT Scanner, Mexico City, MEX </aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">
Yukiyoshi Kimura <email>yukiyoshikimura@gmail.com</email>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>28</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic"><month>11</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><issue>11</issue><elocation-id>e74687</elocation-id><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2024, Kimura et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Kimura et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License CC-BY 4.0., which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="https://www.cureus.com/articles/320692-advanced-neuroimaging-and-clinical-findings-in-a-case-of-linear-scleroderma-en-coup-de-sabre-presenting-with-seizures">This article is available from https://www.cureus.com/articles/320692-advanced-neuroimaging-and-clinical-findings-in-a-case-of-linear-scleroderma-en-coup-de-sabre-presenting-with-seizures</self-uri><abstract><p>Scleroderma is a rare connective tissue disease categorized as systemic or localized. Linear subtype of localized scleroderma usually manifests as a cutaneous linear scar-like lesion most commonly on the scalp. It may present with neurologic, ophthalmologic, and rheumatologic symptoms. We present a case of a 24-year-old female patient with a band-like scalp brown sclerotic lesion in the left upper frontal region presenting with headaches and a first-time seizure who underwent 3.0-T magnetic resonance and described the structural and advanced neuroimaging findings, including perfusion and spectroscopy, that may help narrow differential diagnosis of linear scleroderma.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>en coup de sabre</kwd><kwd>localized scleroderma</kwd><kwd>mri- magnetic resonance imaging</kwd><kwd>neuro-imaging</kwd><kwd>neurology and epilepsy</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Scleroderma is a rare connective tissue disease categorized as systemic or localized [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>].&#x000a0;Localized scleroderma is classified into five subtypes: linear, circumscribed, generalized, pansclerotic, and mixed [<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>].&#x000a0;The linear subtype is usually diagnosed in pediatric age, up to 67% of cases, and occurs more frequently in white females. It usually manifests as a cutaneous linear scar-like lesion with alopecia in the affected area [<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. This subtype commonly affects the scalp and can extend to the nose, jaw, cheeks, and neck, but it may also involve the limbs [<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>].&#x000a0;&#x0201c;En coup de sabre&#x0201d; linear scleroderma (ECDS) refers to cases involving the forehead: frontoparietal region. ECDS is a rare subtype with an incidence of 0.4 to 2.7 per 100,000 [<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].&#x000a0;Initially thought to be limited to the skin, ECDS may also present with neurologic, ophthalmologic, and rheumatologic symptoms.&#x000a0;Epilepsy is the most common neurologic symptom; however, patients may also experience movement disorders and behavioral changes&#x000a0;[<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Neurological symptoms are a strong predictor of positive characteristic ipsilateral magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) findings. Positive radiological findings such as ipsilateral brain atrophy, calcifications, and T2/FLAIR hyperintense white matter changes have been reported [<xref rid="REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Positive imaging findings may also be seen in asymptomatic patients&#x000a0;[<xref rid="REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].</p><p>In this case report we describe the case of a young adult woman with ECDS with clinical and radiological neurologic manifestations.</p></sec><sec sec-type="cases"><title>Case presentation</title><p>A young 24-year-old Latin-American female was referred to the radiology department for a brain MRI with and without contrast by the neurology department for presenting a first unprovoked complex partial seizure. The patient had a non-significant past medical, family, or surgical history. She only referred headaches starting at age 13 with increased intensity over time. On physical examination, the patient had a band-like sclerotic lesion in the left upper frontal region, with a red plaque and focal volume loss, associated with focal frontal alopecia in this region, which she noted since she was 11&#x000a0;(Figure <xref rid="FIG1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).&#x000a0;</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title> Patient&#x02019;s photographs show cicatricial alopecia in the frontal scalp and paramedian forehead (A), associated with focal scalp hypotrophy with skin color changes and sclerosis at the left frontal region with a linear configuration (B)</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0016-00000074687-i01" position="float"/></fig><p>A brain MRI with and without contrast was performed on a 3-T MR Scanner (Lumina, Siemens Healthcare, Erlangen, Germany) using a dedicated 20-channel coil. Imaging demonstrated, on volumetric T1 images, focal scalp atrophy with minimal frontal bone flattening (Figure <xref rid="FIG2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>), subcortical white matter changes in the ipsilateral frontal-parieto-temporal lobe (Figures <xref rid="FIG3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>, <xref rid="FIG4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>), and blooming artifacts on susceptibility-weighted images with hyperintensities on the phase mask (left-hand MR system), suggesting microhemorrhages (Figure <xref rid="FIG5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>).</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>T1 MPRAGE images (A and B) and volumetric rendered reconstruction (C) show focal scalp hypotrophy with sclerosis in the left fronto-parietal region in a linear configuration (arrow)</title><p>MPRAGE: magnetization prepared rapid gradient echo</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0016-00000074687-i02" position="float"/></fig><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Volumetric T2 FLAIR axial images in the dorsoventral direction (A-C) show subcortical white matter signal abnormalities involving the left fronto-parieto-temporal lobe and the splenium of the corpus callosum (arrows)</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0016-00000074687-i03" position="float"/></fig><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Cinematic-rendered volumetric T2 FLAIR images (A and B) show subcortical white matter signal abnormalities in the left cerebral hemisphere (arrows). The patient is seen from the back</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0016-00000074687-i04" position="float"/></fig><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Susceptibility-weighted image (A) and phase mask (B) show several small focal blooming artifacts that are hyperintense on the phase mask of a left-hand system, suggesting microhemorrhages (hemosiderin)</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0016-00000074687-i05" position="float"/></fig><p>After contrast administration, nodular, curvilinear enhancement at the convexity and at the level of the basal ganglia was observed (Figure <xref rid="FIG6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>).</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Sub-volumetric (0.7 mm) T1 SPACE images show nodular, curvilinear enhancement at the convexity and at the level of the basal ganglia</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0016-00000074687-i06" position="float"/></fig><p>On advanced MRI sequences, the relative cerebral blood flow was diffusely decreased on arterial spin labeling perfusion. Relative cerebral blood volume and blood flow were also decreased on dynamic susceptibility contrast perfusion, with a slightly increased mean transit time (Figure <xref rid="FIG7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>).</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>Relative cerebral blood flow map (A), acquired using an arterial spin labeling perfusion technique, and relative cerebral blood volume maps (B and C), acquired during contrast administration with a dynamic susceptibility contrast technique, shows decreased perfusion in the left fronto-parietal lobes with a slight increase in mean transit time (D)</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0016-00000074687-i07" position="float"/></fig><p>On MR spectroscopy acquired with a short echo time (40 ms), there was a slight increase in the choline concentration and a decrease in N-Acetyl-Aspartate color map (NAA) concentration (Figure <xref rid="FIG8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>).</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG8"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><title>Short echo time color NAA (A) shows decreased NAA in the subcortical white matter signal intensity abnormality. The MR spectroscopy curve (B) shows a slight increase in choline concentration (11.86) and a decrease in NAA concentration (11.32)</title><p>NAA:&#x000a0;N-Acetyl-Aspartate color map</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0016-00000074687-i08" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Localized scleroderma is a rare connective tissue disease of unknown etiology. It is a distinct and separate disease entity from systemic scleroderma. Clinically it is differentiated from systemic sclerosis by the absence of Raynaud&#x02019;s phenomenon, sclerodactyly, and erythema. Linear scleroderma ECDS is a subtype of localized scleroderma.&#x000a0;</p><p>The diagnosis of linear scleroderma ECDS is clinical with no definite imaging, serologic, or pathologic pathognomonic features.&#x000a0;It is more frequent in women at menarche (12-15 years of age) and in the fifth decade of life.</p><p>Linear scleroderma has been associated with several neurologic abnormalities in around 20% of the patients, usually preceded by the development of cutaneous disease in months to years [<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Neurologic symptoms can present after years of cutaneous manifestations; however, they can appear first in 16% of cases [<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Physio-pathologic mechanisms regarding the central nervous system include infiltration of perivascular lymphocytes in angio-inflammatory lesions causing abnormal and dilated blood vessels, astrocyte hyperplasia leading to brain parenchyma, meninges, and vascular scarring and local ischemia by destruction of endothelial cells, fibroblast activation and collagen contraction [<xref rid="REF11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>-<xref rid="REF13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].</p><p>Neurological symptoms with linear scleroderma are variable. The most common neurological manifestations are epilepsy (seen in 73% of patients, 33% of them refractory to treatment), focal neurological deficits, headaches (35% of patients), and movement disorders (11% at presentation and 35% of patients overall). Less prevalent neurological manifestations include trigeminal neuralgia, hemiplegic migraine, behavioral changes, and neuropsychiatric symptoms [<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>].</p><p>CT and MRI have shown central nervous system findings, most of them ipsilateral to the cutaneous lesion. A study by Nadeau, et al. found that 78% of 55 symptomatic patients with linear scleroderma had positive imaging findings only on the side of the skin lesion [<xref rid="REF14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>].</p><p>Most symptomatic patients have abnormalities in imaging studies; however, patients with positive imaging findings may be asymptomatic [<xref rid="REF15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The most prevalent imaging findings are white matter abnormalities, which most commonly affect a single lobe but can also be diffuse and confluent, with multilobar involvement, as seen in our patient. Other imaging findings include subtle brain volume loss with sulcal widening, ex vacuo dilation of the ventricles, cortical thickening, nodular and curvilinear enhancement, and ipsilateral intraparenchymal calcifications, most commonly in the thalami, dentate nuclei, and basal ganglia [<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].</p><p>Focal scalp and less often diploe thinning at the fronto-parietal region can also be seen on imaging studies. Vascular involvement has been described on MR angiograms and cerebral angiographies, which suggest a vasculitis process. Some pathologic specimens point to lymphocytic vasculitis as part of the underlying etiology [<xref rid="REF16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>].</p><p>Our patient presents with diffuse microhemorrhages limited to the white matter, with signal intensity changes represented by punctate blooming artifacts on susceptibility-weighted imaging. To our knowledge, intracranial hemorrhage is a rare imaging finding on ECDS.&#x000a0;Ipsilateral cavernomas have been reported previously in ECDS by Fain, et al. [<xref rid="REF17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>].&#x000a0;Microhemorrhages have also been reported in a case of progressive facial hemiatrophy (Parry-Romberg syndrome), which is a related variant within the scleroderma spectrum of disease [<xref rid="REF18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="REF19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>].&#x000a0;</p><p>Limited information regarding advanced MRI sequences has been described. MRI dynamic susceptibility contrasts perfusion on previous case reports showed decreased relative cerebral blood flow and volume and increased mean transit time at the white matter signal abnormality, such as in our case [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>].&#x000a0;Arterial spin labeling perfusion also showed decreased relative cerebral blood flow. These findings correlate with the nonspecific hypometabolism seen in 18F-FDG PET studies.&#x000a0;At MRI spectroscopy our case shows similar findings to the ones described by Nguyen, et al. with a discrete increase in choline (3.5 ppm) concentration and a decrease in N-Acetyl-Aspartate (2.0 ppm) concentration [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. These advanced imaging findings are nonspecific but useful in narrowing the differential diagnosis, differentiating ECDS from high-grade gliomas and other malignant processes.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Linear scleroderma ECDS is a rare connective tissue disease. There are no pathognomonic imaging or serological findings. However, certain MRI findings such as focal scalp atrophy, ipsilateral white matter hyperintensities, low relative cerebral blood flow/volume associated with increased mean transit time, and nodular/curvilinear enhancement in conjunction with clinical examination may assist in differential diagnosis.</p><p>Advanced imaging sequences, such as MRI perfusion and spectroscopy, may be useful in differentiating central nervous system localized scleroderma infiltrative involvement from high-grade gliomas.&#x000a0;</p></sec></body><back><fn-group content-type="conflict"><title>Disclosures</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Human subjects:</bold> Consent for treatment and open access publication was obtained or waived by all participants in this study.</p><p><bold>Conflicts of interest:</bold> In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following:</p><p><bold>Payment/services info:</bold> All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work.</p><p><bold>Financial relationships:</bold> All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work.</p><p><bold>Other relationships:</bold> All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="other"><title>Author Contributions</title><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Concept and design:</bold>&#x000a0; Yukiyoshi Kimura, Dafne Soto-Trujillo</p><p><bold>Drafting of the manuscript:</bold>&#x000a0; Yukiyoshi Kimura</p><p><bold>Critical review of the manuscript for important intellectual content:</bold>&#x000a0; Dafne Soto-Trujillo, Karen Fernandez-Leon</p><p><bold>Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data:</bold>&#x000a0; Karen Fernandez-Leon</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="REF1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Linear scleroderma en coup de sabre presenting with seizures</article-title><source>Radiol Case Rep</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Atty</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ree</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>2164</fpage><lpage>2170</lpage><volume>15</volume><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32952756</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Localized scleroderma</article-title><source>Curr Opin Rheumatol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Laxer</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zulian</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>606</fpage><lpage>613</lpage><volume>18</volume><year>2006</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17053506</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Morphea (localized scleroderma)</article-title><source>JAMA Dermatol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Fett</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>1124</fpage><volume>149</volume><year>2013</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24048434</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Double-lined frontoparietal scleroderma en coup de sabre</article-title><source>Dermatology</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Itin</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schiller</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>185</fpage><lpage>186</lpage><volume>199</volume><year>1999</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10559595</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Neuroimaging and clinical findings in a case of linear scleroderma en coup de sabre</article-title><source>Radiol Case Rep</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Duman</surname><given-names>IE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ekinci</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>545</fpage><lpage>548</lpage><volume>13</volume><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29849855</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Neurologic manifestations of localized scleroderma: a case report and literature review</article-title><source>Neurology</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Kister</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Inglese</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Laxer</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Herbert</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>1538</fpage><lpage>1545</lpage><volume>71</volume><year>2008</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18981376</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Neuroimaging findings of linear scleroderma of the head and face: a case report</article-title><source>J Int Med Res</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>3000605211066002</fpage><volume>50</volume><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35040339</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Neuroimaging findings in scleroderma en coup de sabre</article-title><source>Neurology</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Appenzeller</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Montenegro</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dertkigil</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>1585</fpage><lpage>1589</lpage><volume>62</volume><year>2004</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15136686</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Neurologic involvement in scleroderma en coup de sabre</article-title><source>Autoimmune Dis</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Amaral</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marques Neto</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lapa</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Peres</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guirau</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Appenzeller</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>719685</fpage><year>2012</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22319646</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Localized scleroderma in adults and children. Clinical and laboratory investigations on 239 cases</article-title><source>Eur J Dermatol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Marzano</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Menni</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Parodi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Borghi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fuligni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fabbri</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Caputo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>176</lpage><volume>13</volume><year>2003</year><uri xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/12695134/">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/12695134/</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12695134</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Linear scleroderma en coup de sabre with associated neurologic abnormalities</article-title><source>Pediatrics</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Holland</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Steffes</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nocton</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schwabe</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jacobson</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Drolet</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>0</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><volume>117</volume><year>2006</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Scleroderma en coup de sabre with central nervous system and ophthalmologic involvement: treatment of ocular symptoms with interferon gamma</article-title><source>J Am Acad Dermatol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Obermoser</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pfausler</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Linder</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sepp</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>543</fpage><lpage>546</lpage><volume>49</volume><year>2003</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12963929</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Childhood scleroderma and its peculiarities</article-title><source>Cutis</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Blaszczyk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Janniger</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jablonska</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>152</lpage><page-range>141-4, 148-52</page-range><volume>58</volume><year>1996</year><uri xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/8864601/">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/8864601/</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8864601</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Neurologic manifestations of connective tissue disease</article-title><source>Neurol Clin</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Nadeau</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>151</fpage><lpage>178</lpage><volume>20</volume><year>2002</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11754305</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Localized scleroderma: imaging features</article-title><source>Pediatr Radiol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Uziel</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chuang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Silverman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Krafchik</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Laxer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>209</lpage><volume>24</volume><year>1994</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7936801</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Scleroderma "en coup de sabre": pathological evidence of intracerebral inflammation</article-title><source>J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Franks</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guthrie</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>382</fpage><lpage>385</lpage><volume>70</volume><year>2001</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11181863</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Brain cavernomas associated with en coup de sabre linear scleroderma: two case reports</article-title><source>Pediatr Rheumatol Online J</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Fain</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mannion</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pope</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Laxer</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cron</surname><given-names>RQ</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>18</fpage><volume>9</volume><year>2011</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21801349</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>MRI of cerebral microhemorrhages</article-title><source>AJR Am J Roentgenol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Blitstein</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tung</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>720</fpage><lpage>725</lpage><volume>189</volume><year>2007</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17715122</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Clinical and serological characteristics of progressive facial hemiatrophy: a case series of 12 patients</article-title><source>J Am Acad Dermatol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Sommer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gambichler</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bacharach-Buhles</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>von Rothenburg</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Altmeyer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kreuter</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>227</fpage><lpage>233</lpage><volume>54</volume><year>2006</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16443052</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>