<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="issn">2168-8184</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cureus</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2168-8184</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cureus</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Palo Alto (CA)</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11681953</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7759/cureus.74680</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Public Health</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Epidemiology/Public Health</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Health Policy</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Utilization of Integrated Ayushman Bharat - Pradhan Mantri Jan Arogya Yojana and Mahatma Jyotirao Phule Jan Arogya Yojana at a Tertiary Care Center in Solapur, India: An Epidemiological Study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Muacevic</surname><given-names>Alexander</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>John R</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Kolekar</surname><given-names>Pravin D</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Todkar</surname><given-names>Sampatti S</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mulaje</surname><given-names>Sanjay M</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff-1">
<label>1</label>
Department of Community Medicine, Dr. V. M. Government Medical College, Solapur, IND </aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">
Pravin D. Kolekar <email>pravinofficial997@gmail.com</email>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>28</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic"><month>11</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><issue>11</issue><elocation-id>e74680</elocation-id><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2024, Kolekar et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Kolekar et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License CC-BY 4.0., which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="https://www.cureus.com/articles/314338-utilization-of-integrated-ayushman-bharat---pradhan-mantri-jan-arogya-yojana-and-mahatma-jyotirao-phule-jan-arogya-yojana-at-a-tertiary-care-center-in-solapur-india-an-epidemiological-study">This article is available from https://www.cureus.com/articles/314338-utilization-of-integrated-ayushman-bharat---pradhan-mantri-jan-arogya-yojana-and-mahatma-jyotirao-phule-jan-arogya-yojana-at-a-tertiary-care-center-in-solapur-india-an-epidemiological-study</self-uri><abstract><p>Background: The Integrated Ayushman Bharat&#x000a0;- Pradhan Mantri Jan Arogya Yojana (AB-PMJAY) and Mahatma Jyotirao Phule Jan Arogya Yojana (MJPJAY) is a public-funded health insurance scheme in the state of Maharashtra. The scheme provides end-to-end cashless services for identified diseases through a network of hospitals from both the government sector as well as the private sector, covered under the scheme. AB-PMJAY is a scheme of the government of India. Such publicly funded health insurance schemes help to reduce out-of-pocket expenditure (OOPE). The study was designed with the objective of describing an epidemiological profile of subjects registered under the Integrated MJPJAY and Pradhan Mantri Jan Arogya Yojana at a tertiary care center and identifying the utilization pattern of the scheme.</p><p>Methods: It was a record-based, retrospective cross-sectional study. The study population comprised all the cases registered under Integrated AB-PMJAY and MJPJAY from September 1, 2023, to November 30, 2023, at the tertiary care center. The sample size consists of all the cases (n=1978) registered under the scheme at the tertiary care center from September 1, 2023, to November 30, 2023.</p><p>Results: The majority of the subjects (44.39%, n=878) belonged to the age group 40-59 years. In our study, 77.45% (n=1532) of the study subjects got pre-authorization approval. In the case of the pattern of utilization, 56.46% (n=865) of the study subjects utilized medical treatment, and 43.54% (n=667) of the study subjects utilized surgical treatment. In surgical treatment, utilization was higher in polytrauma (15.92%, n=244), followed by general surgery (7.70%, n=118) and ear, nose, and throat (ENT) surgery (5.68%, n=87). In the case of medical treatment, utilization was more in general medicine (14.30%, n=219), followed by nephrology (11.49%, n=176) and neurology (10.64%, n=163).</p><p>Conclusion: The majority of the subjects availing themselves of registration in the scheme were in the age group 40-59 years. The majority of the subjects utilized medical treatment. In the case of specialty utilization, polytrauma was utilized more, followed by general medicine. The utilization was least in the case of cardiothoracic surgery, followed by dermatology, hematology, and pediatric surgery.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>ayushman bharat</kwd><kwd>mjpjay</kwd><kwd>oope</kwd><kwd>out-of-pocket expenditure</kwd><kwd>pmjay</kwd><kwd>public funded health insurance</kwd><kwd>utilization pattern</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>The World Health Organization defines universal health coverage&#x000a0;(UHC) as a means to enable all people and communities to use promotive, preventive, curative, rehabilitative, and palliative health services they need, of sufficient quality to be effective, while also ensuring that the use of such services does not expose the user to financial hardship [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>-<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. The International Labour Organization defines health insurance as &#x0201c;the reduction or elimination of the uncertain risk of loss for the individual or household by combining a larger number of similarly exposed individuals or households who are included in a common fund that makes good the loss caused to any one member&#x0201d; [<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. A health insurance policy is a contract between an insurance company and an individual and comes in handy in case of severe emergencies [<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. It is an effective social security mechanism [<xref rid="REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>].</p><p>The Government of India launched the Ayushman Bharat - Pradhan Mantri Jan Arogya Yojana (AB-PMJAY) on September 23, 2018. This Yojana is a government-funded health insurance scheme that covers more than 10.74 crore poor and vulnerable families [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Mahatma Jyotirao Phule Jan Arogya Yojana (MJPJAY) is a flagship health insurance scheme of the Government of Maharashtra, earlier known as Rajiv Gandhi Jeevandayee Arogya Yojana (RGJAY), was relaunched on April 1, 2017, by the Government of Maharashtra [<xref rid="REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. The Integrated AB-PMJAY and MJPJAY have been implemented in revised form across the state from April 1, 2020 [<xref rid="REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. The scheme provides end-to-end cashless services for identified diseases through a network of service providers from the government and private sector [<xref rid="REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. The scheme has many unique features to its credit to proactively reach beneficiaries and guide the beneficiary to avail the services in a cashless manner [<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].</p><p>The high out-of-pocket expenditure (OOPE) on health care has a devastating effect on the lives of low-income individuals [<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. According to the 75th round (2017-18) of the National Sample Survey, 12% of Indians have unmet health needs [<xref rid="REF11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Inability to afford healthcare, i.e., financial inaccessibility, is one of the factors responsible for the unmet needs and, therefore, is a hindrance to UHC in India [<xref rid="REF11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. OOPE, a major source of health financing in the country, contributes to 49.82% of total health expenditure [<xref rid="REF12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. In India, in 2018, 16.51% of people faced catastrophic health expenses, i.e., CHE (at a 10% threshold level), and 3.3% of people were pushed into poverty due to OOPE on health [<xref rid="REF13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].</p><p>A sizable section of the population may avoid the treatment entirely due to financial constraints. The publicly funded health insurance schemes are helping poor patients by increasing healthcare accessibility and by reducing health expenditure. The study done by Rao et al. about the Rajiv Aarogyasri Community Health Insurance Scheme (RACHIS) in the state of Andhra Pradesh found that it improved access and greater benefits to below the poverty line (BPL) families to secondary and tertiary healthcare [<xref rid="REF14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. There are many studies done in India about awareness and coverage of publicly funded health insurance schemes across states. There are very few studies done to assess the pattern of utilization of such schemes. In this study, we aimed to know the utilization pattern of this government-funded health insurance scheme at the tertiary care center in Solapur, which has played an important role in the implementation of the scheme.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><p>Study design and setting</p><p>It was a record-based retrospective cross-sectional study. The study was conducted at a tertiary care center in the Solapur district, India. Permission was obtained from the authorities of Integrated AB-PMJAY and MJPJAY as well as from the authorities of the tertiary care center.</p><p>Study population and duration</p><p>The study population comprised all the cases registered under the scheme from September 1, 2023, to November 30,&#x000a0;2023, at the tertiary care center. The data of all the registered cases during the three months was collected to ensure consistency and adequate data representation.</p><p>Sample size</p><p>The sample consisted of all cases (n=1978) registered under the Integrated AB-PMJAY and MJPJAY scheme from the period September 1, 2023, to November 30, 2023, at the tertiary care center.</p><p>Inclusion criteria</p><p>All the cases registered under the scheme from the period September 1, 2023, to November 30, 2023, at the tertiary care center were included in the study.</p><p>Exclusion criteria</p><p>No exclusion criteria were applied, as every case registered under the scheme during the study period was included.</p><p>Study instrument and data collection</p><p>The data for this study was retrospectively collected from the Integrated AB-PMJAY and MJPJAY records of the tertiary care center. All the records of study subjects registered under the scheme during the period from September 1, 2023, to November 30, 2023, were reviewed. The records included socio-demographic information, pre-authorization data, diagnosis, treatment modalities, department, claim status, package, and claim paid amount under the scheme. The information was collected from online records. The required variables were entered in Microsoft Excel. The demographic information of those availing themselves of registration under the scheme, such as age, gender, and district of residence, was collected. The socioeconomic status was determined on the basis of the type of ration card. The pre-authorization data included pre-authorization status approved, rejected, canceled, or pending. Pre-authorization is required for approval to access services under an insurance scheme. Those subjects who got pre-authorization approval from the State Health Assurance Society (SHAS) were eligible for the treatment under the scheme and so could utilize the scheme. The information on diagnosis, type of treatment provided (medical treatment/surgical treatment), and department was collected. The data on claim approval status, package under the scheme, and claim paid amount under the scheme was collected. All the data was anonymized to protect patient confidentiality. Subsequent analysis was carried out.</p><p>Statistical analysis</p><p>This data was entered in Microsoft Excel and analyzed in Epi Info software (version 7.2). The results were expressed in terms of frequencies and percentages for categorical variables. The analysis was carried out using the chi-square test for goodness of fit for frequency distribution across specialties, and the Z test for proportion was used to check the statistical significance of the proportion of medical treatment.</p><p>Ethical considerations</p><p>The Institutional Ethics Committee approval was taken from Dr. V. M. Government Medical College, Solapur (approval no.: IEC/169/24). The anonymity and confidentiality of the data were maintained as per ethical guidelines and regulations.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p>In our study, the majority of the study subjects (44.39%, n=878) belonged to the age group of 40-59 years. It was followed by 23.15% (n=458) of the study subjects in the age group of 15-39 years and 19.26% (n=381) of subjects in the more than 60 years of age group. The majority of male study subjects as well as female study subjects belonged to the age group of 40-59 years. The number of males was higher in all the age groups except the age group of 40-59 years, where female study subjects were more than males. The findings are outlined in Table <xref rid="TAB1" ref-type="table">1</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Age- and sex-wise distribution of study subjects (n=1978)</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Age group (years)</td><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">&#x000a0; &#x000a0; &#x000a0; &#x000a0; &#x000a0; &#x000a0; &#x000a0; &#x000a0; &#x000a0; &#x000a0; &#x000a0; &#x000a0; &#x000a0; &#x000a0; &#x000a0; &#x000a0; &#x000a0; &#x000a0; &#x000a0; &#x000a0; &#x000a0; &#x000a0;Sex</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="2">&#x000a0; &#x000a0; &#x000a0; &#x000a0; &#x000a0; &#x000a0; &#x000a0; &#x000a0; &#x000a0; &#x000a0; &#x000a0; &#x000a0; &#x000a0; &#x000a0; &#x000a0; &#x000a0; &#x000a0; Total</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Male&#x000a0;</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Female</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency (n)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency (n)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency (n)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage (%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.30</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1-14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">109</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">176</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.90</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15-39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">287</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">171</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">458</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.15</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40-59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">493</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">385</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">878</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.39</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">238</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">143</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">381</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.26</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1184</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">794</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1978</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Most of the study subjects (86.15%, n=1704) were from Solapur district only. It was followed by the Dharashiv district (9.45%, n=187). About 3.08% (n=61) of the study subjects were from the Latur district, and 1.31% (n=26) belonged to other districts. Findings are outlined in Figure <xref rid="FIG1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>.</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>District-wise distribution of study subjects (n=1978)</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0016-00000074680-i01" position="float"/></fig><p>In the study, we found that 54.35% (n=1075) of the study subjects were orange ration card holders. About 39.99% (n=791) were yellow ration card holders, and 5.66% (n=112) of the study subjects held Antyodaya ration cards (Figure <xref rid="FIG2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). A ration card is an official document issued to households as per eligibility to purchase subsidized food grains from the Public Distribution System (PDS).</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Classification of study subjects on basis of type of ration card (n=1978)</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0016-00000074680-i02" position="float"/></fig><p>In our study, 77.45% (n=1532) of the study subjects got pre-authorization approval from the SHAS. Pre-authorization was rejected in 12.03% (n=238) and was canceled in 6.83% (n=135) of the study subjects. It was pending in the case of 3.69% (n=73) of the study subjects. These findings are highlighted in Figure <xref rid="FIG3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>.</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Pre-authorization status of study subjects (n=1978)</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0016-00000074680-i03" position="float"/></fig><p>In the case of the pattern of utilization, 56.46% (n=865) of the study subjects utilized medical treatment, and 43.54% (n=667) of the study subjects utilized surgical treatment (Figure <xref rid="FIG4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>).</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Percentage distribution of patients by type of treatment received (n=1532)*</title><p>*Number of study subjects who got pre-authorization approval during the study duration and could avail themselves of the treatment under the scheme</p><p>p=0.00000042 (Z-test for proportion)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0016-00000074680-i04" position="float"/></fig><p>Overall, the majority of the study subjects utilized polytrauma (15.92%, n=244). It was followed by general medicine (14.30%, n=219), nephrology (11.49%, n=176), and neurology (10.64%, n=163). In the case of surgical treatment, utilization was more polytrauma (15.92%, n=244). It was followed by general surgery (7.70%, n=118) and ear, nose, and throat (ENT) surgery (5.68%, n=87). In the case of medical treatment, utilization was more in general medicine (14.30%, n=219), followed by nephrology (11.49%, n=176) and neurology (10.64%, n=163). The utilization was least in the case of cardiothoracic surgery (0.07%, n=1), followed by dermatology (0.13%, n=2), hematology (0.13%, n=2), and pediatric surgery (0.32%, n=5). These findings are outlined in Table <xref rid="TAB2" ref-type="table">2</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Specialty-wise management of study subjects (n=1532)</title><p>df: degree of freedom; gynec and obgy: gynecology and obstetrics</p><p>Chi-square test for goodness of fit was done</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Specialty</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; Subjects</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; Test</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency (n)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;Percentage (%)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Burns</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72</td><td rowspan="24" colspan="1">&#x000a0;X&#x000b2;=1794.95, df=22, p&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cardiothoracic surgery</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cardiology</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.50</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Critical care</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dermatology</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Endocrinology</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.44</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ENT surgery</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">87</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.68</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gastroenterology</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.02</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">General medicine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">219</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.30</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">General surgery</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">118</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.70</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genitourinary system</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gynec and obgy surgery</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.54</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hematology</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nephrology</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">176</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.49</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neurology</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">163</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.64</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neurosurgery</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.96</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Orthopedics</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.70</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ophthalmology surgery</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.02</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pediatric surgery</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pediatrics</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">122</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.96</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Polytrauma</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">244</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.92</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pulmonology</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">94</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.14</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Surgical oncology</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.44</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1532</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>The claim paid amount in the case of 98.63% (n=1511) of subjects was less than or equal to 50,000 Indian rupees&#x000a0;(INR) (&#x02264;50,000 INR). In the case of 1.37% (n=21) of subjects, the claim paid amount was greater than 50000 INR to less than or equal to 1,00,000 INR (&#x0003e;50,000 INR to &#x02264;1,00,000 INR) (Figure <xref rid="FIG5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>).</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Distribution on basis of claim paid amount (n=1532)</title><p>INR: Indian Rupees</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0016-00000074680-i05" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>In our study, 77.45% (n=1532) of the subjects got pre-authorization approval from SHAS for utilizing the scheme. In the study, the majority of the subjects (56.46%, n=865) utilized medical treatment. Overall, in the case of specialty utilization, more utilization was seen in polytrauma (15.92%, n=244). The utilization was least in the case of cardiothoracic surgery (0.07%, n=1). In the case of 98.6% (n=1511) of the subjects, the claim paid amount was less than or equal to 50,000 INR.</p><p>The Niti Aayog report has highlighted non-uniform accessibility to healthcare across the country. There is a disparity between rural and urban India as far as health access is concerned. It is a fact that many families or individuals have to pay out of their own pockets due to unexpected illnesses and a rise in healthcare expenses [<xref rid="REF15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Publicly funded health insurance schemes are playing an important role in improving healthcare accessibility and reducing OOPE [<xref rid="REF16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Such schemes have been useful in reducing the economic burden of poor and vulnerable families.</p><p>In the study, it was found that the majority of the subjects (44.39%, n=878) were aged between 40 and 59 years. The majority of male study subjects as well as female study subjects belonged to the age group of 40-59 years. This age group is the primary beneficiary of this public health initiative. The study done by Radhakrishnan and Bansode-Gokhe had also similar findings [<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. This may be due to the rising burden of non-communicable diseases (NCDs) in this age group. The study done by Naaz and Nigudgi also found that NCD-related claims were maximum, indicating an NCD burden [<xref rid="REF17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. It was found in the study that the number of males was higher in all the age groups except the age group of 40-59 years, where female study subjects were more than males. This may be due to post-menopausal health problems in the age group along with the burden of NCDs and age-related conditions. This highlights the need for regular health screenings and designing gender-responsive interventions. In the study, the majority of the study subjects (86.15%, n=1704) were from the Solapur district. There is a need as well as opportunities for the decentralization of healthcare services in stepping towards UHC.</p><p>We found that the majority of study subjects (54.35%, n=1075) held orange ration cards, representing those above the poverty line. It was followed by yellow ration card holders (39.99%, n=791), representing those BPL. Those BPL may have lower health literacy and lower awareness about the scheme. Similar findings have been noted in a study done by Radhakrishnan and Bansode-Gokhe [<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. It was emphasized by Balarajan et al. that there are differential trends in inequalities suggesting differential uptake and access to healthcare services by different groups [<xref rid="REF18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].</p><p>In the study, 77.45% (n=1532) of the study subjects got pre-authorization approval from SHAS. Near similar findings have been reported in the study done by Radhakrishnan and Bansode-Gokhe [<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Pre-authorization was rejected in 12.03% (n=238) and was canceled in 6.83% (n=135) of the study subjects. It was pending in the case of 3.69% (n=73) of the study subjects. It may be due to inadequate documentation or delay in online updating of data and protocols. The study shows a relatively high pre-authorization approval rate. The rejection and cancellation rates highlight the challenges in providing universal access to healthcare.</p><p>In the case of utilization pattern, we found that the majority of the study subjects (56.46%, n=865) utilized medical treatment. About 43.54% (n=667) of the study subjects utilized surgical treatment. In the case of specialty utilization, the majority of the study subjects utilized polytrauma (15.92%, n=244), followed by general medicine (14.30%, n=219).</p><p>In the case of surgical treatment, utilization was more in polytrauma (15.92%, n=244), indicating a significant burden of traumatic injuries. It was followed by general surgery (7.70%, n=118) and ENT surgery (5.68%, n=87). In the case of medical treatment, utilization was more in general medicine (14.30%, n=219), consistent with the rising burden of chronic NCDs. It was followed by nephrology (11.49%, n=176) and neurology (10.64%, n=163), indicating the demand for healthcare services for acute and chronic conditions related to kidneys and the nervous system through publicly funded health insurance schemes. The utilization was least in the case of cardiothoracic surgery (0.07%, n=1), followed by dermatology (0.13%, n=2), hematology (0.13%, n=2), and pediatric surgery (0.32%, n=5). The study done by Naaz and Nigudgi found that overall medicine department claims (PMJAY) were at 42% [<xref rid="REF17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>].</p><p>The claim paid amount in the case of the majority of study subjects (98.6%, n=1511) was less than or equal to 50,000 INR. These findings emphasize further capacity building of tertiary care hospitals and frequent package revisions.&#x000a0;</p><p>It is reported in the study by Rao et al. that inpatient care is only consumed by a small proportion of households in a year [<xref rid="REF19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. The lack of adequate knowledge among the beneficiaries is the concern for not utilizing such schemes. The study done by Thomas et al. in three districts of Gujrat found that 43.3% of beneficiaries utilized the benefit of the Ayushman Bharat scheme [<xref rid="REF20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. The study done by Sriee and&#x000a0;Maiya&#x000a0;among 300 households in rural areas found that 47.24% of the households availed themselves of the Ayushman Bharat scheme [<xref rid="REF15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].</p><p>It is recommended based on the findings of the study that the training of resident doctors and/or doctors and health care workers in the empaneled hospitals needs to be done at regular intervals so as to facilitate an increase in the pre-authorization approval and availing of the scheme. There is a need to improve the communication between healthcare workers and beneficiaries. The awareness at the level of empaneled hospitals can be increased through information, education, and communication (IEC) and through a community needs assessment approach. Media platforms will help to increase the outreach of such schemes. The local television channels and radio will be helpful in broad community outreach. Social media platforms like Facebook, X (Twitter), and Instagram can help in targeted interactive communication. These platforms can help to deliver concise information about the scheme. Those who have successfully availed themselves of the scheme can become the champions of the scheme to deliver the message to the community. This will help increase awareness as well as encourage the community to utilize the scheme. There is an urgent necessity to adopt comprehensive preventive approaches. The policy intervention UHC at the level of government will help increase healthcare access and reduce OOPE.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>The study highlights that utilization was least in specialties such as cardiothoracic surgery, dermatology, hematology, and pediatric surgery. There is a need for increasing awareness of such specialties along with strengthening super specialty services as well as, at the level of policy-making, having a comprehensive review of packages in such specialties. The study findings also highlight the scope for further capacity building in trauma care and chronic disease management. The study, through the understanding of patterns of utilization, will help policy stakeholders with resource allocation, healthcare policy, and future research initiatives.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>We are thankful to Dr. Shashikala B. Jagtap (Vhale Patil), medical coordinator, Integrated Ayushman Bharat - Pradhan Mantri Jan Arogya Yojana (AB-PMJAY) and Mahatma Jyotirao Phule Jan Arogya Yojana (MJPJAY), Shri Chhatrapati Shivaji Maharaj Sarvopachar Rugnalaya (SCSMSR), Solapur, India, for guiding us about the scheme.</p></ack><fn-group content-type="conflict"><title>Disclosures</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Human subjects:</bold> Consent for treatment and open access publication was obtained or waived by all participants in this study. The Institutional Ethics Committee of Dr. V. M. Government Medical College, Solapur issued approval IEC/169/24.</p><p><bold>Animal subjects:</bold> All authors have confirmed that this study did not involve animal subjects or tissue.</p><p><bold>Conflicts of interest:</bold> In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following:</p><p><bold>Payment/services info:</bold> All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work.</p><p><bold>Financial relationships:</bold> All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work.</p><p><bold>Other relationships:</bold> All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="other"><title>Author Contributions</title><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Concept and design:</bold>&#x000a0; Pravin D. Kolekar, Sampatti S. Todkar</p><p><bold>Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data:</bold>&#x000a0; Pravin D. Kolekar, Sampatti S. Todkar, Sanjay M. Mulaje</p><p><bold>Drafting of the manuscript:</bold>&#x000a0; Pravin D. Kolekar, Sampatti S. Todkar, Sanjay M. Mulaje</p><p><bold>Critical review of the manuscript for important intellectual content:</bold>&#x000a0; Pravin D. Kolekar, Sampatti S. Todkar, Sanjay M. Mulaje</p><p><bold>Supervision:</bold>&#x000a0; Sampatti S. Todkar</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="REF1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>A study on the utilization of Ayushman Bharat Arogya Karnataka (ABArK) among COVID patients admitted in a tertiary care hospital</article-title><source>Clin Epidemiol Glob Health</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Shrisharath</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hiremat</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nanjesh Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rai</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Erappa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Holla</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>101015</fpage><volume>15</volume><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35342845</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Ayushman Bharat and road to universal health coverage in India</article-title><source>J Mahatma Gandhi Inst Med Sci</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Keshri</surname><given-names>VR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>67</lpage><volume>24</volume><year>2019</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>Universal health coverage (UHC)</article-title><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">
<month>1</month>
<year>2024</year>
</date-in-citation><year>2023</year><uri xlink:href="https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/universal-health-coverage-(uhc)">https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/universal-health-coverage-(uhc)</uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>A Study on awareness, coverage and willingness to avail health insurance among the residents of a rural area in Central Karnataka</article-title><source>Natl J Community Med</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Netra</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>BAV</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>190</fpage><lpage>196</lpage><volume>10</volume><year>2019</year><uri xlink:href="https://njcmindia.com/index.php/file/article/view/483/296">https://njcmindia.com/index.php/file/article/view/483/296</uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>Training manual in health insurance</article-title><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">
<month>4</month>
<year>2024</year>
</date-in-citation><year>2009</year><uri xlink:href="https://iphindia.org/training-manual-in-health-insurance/">https://iphindia.org/training-manual-in-health-insurance/</uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Pattern of utilization of health insurance in two districts of South Karnataka</article-title><source>Int J Community Med Public Health</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Shet</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Qadiri</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Saldanha</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kanalli</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>4310</fpage><lpage>4315</lpage><volume>6</volume><year>2019</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Awareness about health insurance in rural population of South India</article-title><source>Int J Community Med Public Health</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Gowda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Manjunath</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Krishna</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>648</fpage><lpage>650</lpage><volume>2</volume><year>2015</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>Integrated Mahatma Jyotirao Phule Jan Arogya Yojana (MJPJAY) and Ayushman Bharat-Pradhan Mantri Jan Arogya Yojana (ABPMJAY)</article-title><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">
<month>12</month>
<year>2023</year>
</date-in-citation><year>2020</year><uri xlink:href="https://www.jeevandayee.gov.in/MJPJAY/FrontServlet?requestType=CommonRH&#x00026;actionVal=RightFrame&#x00026;page=undefined%3E%3E%3Cb%3EMJPJAY%3C/b%3E&#x00026;pageName=MJPJAY&#x00026;mainMenu=About&#x00026;subMenu=MJPJAY.%20Accessed">https://www.jeevandayee.gov.in/MJPJAY/FrontServlet?requestType=CommonRH&#x00026;actionVal=RightFrame&#x00026;page=undefined%3E%3E%3Cb%3EMJPJAY%3C/b%3E&#x00026;pageName=MJPJAY&#x00026;mainMenu=About&#x00026;subMenu=MJPJAY.%20Accessed</uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Awareness about Mahatma Jyotiba Phule Jan Arogya Yojna among the residential population of an urban community: a cross-sectional study</article-title><source>Int J Community Med Public Health</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Sapkal</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Deshpande</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>3848</fpage><lpage>3852</lpage><volume>6</volume><year>2019</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>An epidemiological study of utilization of Rajiv Gandhi Jeevandayee Arogya Yojana in a municipal tertiary care hospital located in a metro city</article-title><source>Int J Community Med Public Health</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Radhakrishnan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bansode-Gokhe</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>2515</fpage><lpage>2519</lpage><volume>4</volume><year>2017</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Evolution of Government-funded health insurance for universal health coverage in India</article-title><source>Lancet Reg Health Southeast Asia</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Dubey</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Deshpande</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Krishna</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zadey</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>100180</fpage><volume>13</volume><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37383549</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>Out-of-pocket expenditure (% of current health expenditure)</article-title><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">
<month>10</month>
<year>2024</year>
</date-in-citation><year>2024</year><uri xlink:href="https://data.worldbank.org/indicator/SH.XPD.OOPC.CH.ZS">https://data.worldbank.org/indicator/SH.XPD.OOPC.CH.ZS</uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>A study of catastrophic health expenditures in India - evidence from nationally representative survey data: 2014-2018</article-title><source>F1000Res</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Sriram</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Albadrani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>141</fpage><volume>11</volume><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35464045</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Addressing healthcare needs of people living below the poverty line: a rapid assessment of the Andhra Pradesh Health Insurance Scheme</article-title><source>Natl Med J India</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ramachandra</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bandyopadhyay</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>335</fpage><lpage>341</lpage><volume>24</volume><year>2011</year><uri xlink:href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/225288212">https://www.researchgate.net/publication/225288212 </uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22680257</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Coverage, utilization, and impact of Ayushman Bharat scheme among the rural field practice area of Saveetha Medical College and Hospital, Chennai</article-title><source>J Family Med Prim Care</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Sriee</surname><given-names>GV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maiya</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>1171</fpage><lpage>1176</lpage><volume>10</volume><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34041146</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>A study to assess feedback of patients who received benefit of Rajeev Gandhi Jeevandayi Arogya Yojana during first year of phase I in a private tertiary care network hospital in Maharashtra</article-title><source>Int J Community Med Public Health</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Katke</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wadke</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Waigankar</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>2495</fpage><lpage>2499</lpage><volume>5</volume><year>2018</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Evaluation of Pradhan Mantri Jan Arogya Yojana (PM-JAY) utilization in a teaching hospital of Kalaburagi City, Karnataka</article-title><source>Indian J Public Health Res Dev</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Naaz</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nigudgi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>181</lpage><volume>13</volume><year>2022</year><uri xlink:href="https://medicopublication.com/index.php/ijphrd/article/view/18578/16154">https://medicopublication.com/index.php/ijphrd/article/view/18578/16154 </uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Health care and equity in India</article-title><source>Lancet</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Balarajan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Selvaraj</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Subramanian</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>505</fpage><lpage>515</lpage><volume>377</volume><year>2011</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21227492</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Changes in addressing inequalities in access to hospital care in Andhra Pradesh and Maharashtra states of India: a difference-in-differences study using repeated cross-sectional surveys</article-title><source>BMJ Open</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Katyal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>0</fpage><volume>4</volume><year>2014</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Study of awareness, enrolment, and utilization of Ayushman Bharat Pradhan Mantri Jan Arogya Yojana in Gujarat, India</article-title><source>Int J Community Med Public Health</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Raykundaliya</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bhatt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vadhel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>2741</fpage><lpage>2747</lpage><volume>10</volume><year>2023</year></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>