<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Clin Oncol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int J Clin Oncol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>International Journal of Clinical Oncology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1341-9625</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1437-7772</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer Nature Singapore</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Singapore</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39692835</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11785660</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2670</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10147-024-02670-5</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Efficacy of androgen receptor signaling inhibitors in combination with androgen deprivation therapy for castration-sensitive metastatic prostate cancer: a retrospective analysis in a Japanese cohort</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Taga</surname><given-names>Minekatsu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>Takeshi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Higashi</surname><given-names>Shinichiro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>Shoichi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sawada</surname><given-names>Atsuro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tsuchiyama</surname><given-names>Katsuki</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>Takahiro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kamoto</surname><given-names>Toshiyuki</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0009-0005-1082-6089</contrib-id><name><surname>Terada</surname><given-names>Naoki</given-names></name><address><email>nterada@u-fukui.ac.jp</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/00msqp585</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.163577.1</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0692 8246</institution-id><institution>Department of Urology, Faculty of Medical Science, </institution><institution>University of Fukui, </institution></institution-wrap>23-3 Matsuoka-shimoaizuki, Eiheiji-cho, Yoshida-gun, Fukui, 910-1193 Japan </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/01529vy56</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.260026.0</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0372 555X</institution-id><institution>Department of Nephro-Urologic Surgery and Andrology, </institution><institution>Mie University Graduate School of Medicine, </institution></institution-wrap>Tsu, Japan </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/0447kww10</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.410849.0</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0657 3887</institution-id><institution>Department of Urology, </institution><institution>University of Miyazaki, </institution></institution-wrap>Miyazaki, Japan </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>18</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>18</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>30</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>351</fpage><lpage>357</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>6</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2024</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">This study aimed to evaluate the efficacy of androgen receptor signaling inhibitors (ARSIs) combined with androgen deprivation therapy (ADT) for treating castration-sensitive metastatic prostate cancer in Japanese patients, focusing on the effects on time to the development of castration-resistant prostate cancer (CRPC) and overall survival (OS).</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">This retrospective muti-institutional analysis included 332 patients diagnosed with metastatic prostate cancer in Japan between 2018 and 2023. The patients were categorized into two groups: patients receiving ADT combined with ARSI (ARSI group) and those receiving ADT alone or with bicalutamide (ADT group). Data on demographics, treatments, and outcomes were compared using the Kaplan&#x02013;Meier method with propensity score matching.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">We found an increasing trend in ARSI use over time. The median time to CRPC was significantly longer in the ARSI group than in the ADT group (47.1 vs. 15.2&#x000a0;months, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001); however, no significant differences in OS were observed before or after propensity score matching. The 1-year-survival rate of patients in the ARSI group tended to be higher than that of patients in the ADT group in subgroups with high tumor volume (96.1% vs. 85.0%) and high Gleason grade (98.1% vs. 85.9%).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par4">Adding ARSI to ADT extended the time to CRPC but did not significantly affect OS. However, it potentially suppressed the short-term risk of death in high-risk subgroups. This study highlights the need for further research to explore the characteristics of Japanese patients with metastatic prostate cancer in whom upfront ARSIs are effective.</p></sec><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1007/s10147-024-02670-5.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Metastatic prostate cancer</kwd><kwd>Androgen deprivation therapy</kwd><kwd>Androgen receptor signaling inhibitor</kwd><kwd>Overall survival</kwd><kwd>Castration-resistant prostate cancer</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>University of Fukui</institution></funding-source></award-group><open-access><p>Open Access funding provided by University of Fukui.</p></open-access></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Japan Society of Clinical Oncology 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par5">Metastatic prostate cancer is among the leading causes of cancer-related deaths in men, making early detection and treatment both a social and medical priority [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Traditionally, androgen deprivation therapy (ADT) with medical or surgical castration has been the cornerstone treatment for metastatic prostate cancer. However, most patients acquire resistance to castration therapy resulting in castration-resistant prostate cancer (CRPC). Androgen receptor signaling inhibitors (ARSIs) were introduced as a treatment option for CRPC to improve patient prognosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. In recent years, adding ARSIs to ADT as an initial treatment has been shown to improve the survival of patients, and the use of ARSIs as first-line treatment for metastatic prostate cancer has become common [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>].</p><p id="Par6">However, Japanese patients with metastatic prostate cancer are generally considered to have a good prognosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Therefore, the efficacy of adding ARSIs to ADT in Japanese patients with metastatic prostate cancer remains unclear. This uncertainty poses a significant barrier to optimizing treatment choices and strategies for individual patients. Therefore, in this study, we aimed to retrospectively analyze the effects of combining ARSIs with ADT on the prognosis of patients with metastatic prostate cancer across institutions in Fukui, Mie, and Miyazaki. Our objective was to provide insights into the efficacy of ARSIs in Japanese patients and to contribute to the advancement of personalized medicine for treating metastatic prostate cancer.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Study population</title><p id="Par7">In this study, we used data from patients diagnosed with metastatic prostate cancer between 2018 and 2023 at the University of Miyazaki, Mie, and Fukui Hospitals and other associated hospitals. This study was approved by the Institutional Review Board of each institute. The approval number for the University of Fukui Hospital was 20,230,132. Informed consent was obtained through an opt-out process. All patients had pathologically proven adenocarcinoma of the prostate, and extra-regional lymph node or distant metastasis was detected using computed tomography or bone scan at the time of diagnosis. Patient backgrounds and survival data were retrospectively obtained from medical records. The data included patient demographic and clinical information (age; prostate-specific antigen [PSA] level at diagnosis; Gleason grade group; Tumor, Node, Metastasis [TNM] classification; and metastatic sites) and treatment details. Metastatic burden was defined as high or low volume based on the Chemohormonal Therapy Versus Androgen Ablation Randomized Trial for Extensive Disease in Prostate Cancer (CHAARTED) classification system (high volume: presence of visceral metastases or four or more bone lesions with at least one beyond the vertebral bodies and pelvis; low volume: all others) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. All patients underwent ADT with a luteinizing hormone-releasing hormone&#x000a0;(LHRH) agonist, an LHRH antagonist, or surgical castration. The ARSIs included abiraterone plus prednisolone, enzalutamide, or apalutamide. The ARSI used was at the discretion of the attending physician. Patients who received treatment with ARSI at the same time as or within 3&#x000a0;months of ADT initiation were categorized into the ARSI group. Patients who received ADT monotherapy or ADT plus bicalutamide as first-line therapy and who did not receive ARSI within 3&#x000a0;months of ADT initiation or before the development of treatment resistance to ADT were categorized into the ADT group. Resistance to ADT, with or without ARSI administration, was defined as CRPC. The duration from ADT initiation to CRPC onset (time to CRPC) and overall survival (OS) were examined. Treatment resistance was defined as PSA, radiological, or clinical progression. PSA progression was defined as an increase of 25% in PSA levels from the nadir, resulting in levels&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;2.0&#x000a0;ng/ml [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. When the therapy was changed before treatment resistance, the time to change the therapy was defined as CRPC onset.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par8">Data are presented as medians and ranges. Time to CRPC and OS were compared using a two-sided log-rank test with the Kaplan&#x02013;Meier method. Baseline characteristics were compared between the groups using Fisher&#x02019;s exact test and the Mann&#x02013;Whitney U test. To match the patients&#x02019; backgrounds between the groups, propensity score matching was performed using a caliper for neighborhood-based estimation; the propensity scores used were calculated using logistic regression models with the following parameters: age, PSA level, clinical TNM stage, Gleason grade group, and metastatic volume. Thereafter, time to CRPC and OS were compared in all patients and between subgroups based on Gleason grade group (5 vs.&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;4) and metastatic volume (high vs. low). The 1- and 2-year survival rates were also compared. All statistical analyses were performed using EZR (Saitama Medical Center, Jichi Medical University, Saitama, Japan), a graphical user interface for R (R Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna, Austria). Values of <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Results</title><p id="Par9">A total of 332 patients with metastatic prostate cancer were included in this study. Among them, 184 and 148 patients were assigned to the ARSI and ADT groups, respectively. The number of patients in the ARSI group increased annually (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). The median age of the patients was 72&#x000a0;years (range 44&#x02013;89) in the ARSI group and 75&#x000a0;years (range 52&#x02013;90) in the ADT group; patients were significantly younger in the ARSI group than in the ADT group (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001). The median PSA level at diagnosis was 299&#x000a0;ng/ml (range 0.95&#x02013;15,030) in the ARSI group and 249&#x000a0;ng/ml (range: 4.47&#x02013;122,875) in the ADT group, with no significant difference between the groups (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.303). The rate of visceral metastases was 27.1% (50 of 184 cases) in the ARSI group and 7.4% (11 of 148 cases) in the ADT group; this rate was significantly higher in the ARSI group than in the ADT group (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001). No significant differences in the clinical T and N stages or Gleason grade groups were observed between the groups (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Number of patients receiving ADT plus ARSI (ARSI group) and those receiving ADT alone or ADT plus bicalutamide (ADT group) in each period from treatment initiation for metastatic prostate cancer. <italic>ADT</italic> androgen deprivation therapy, <italic>ARSI</italic> androgen receptor signal inhibitor</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10147_2024_2670_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Patient characteristics in ARSI and ADT group</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left">ARSI</th><th align="left">ADT</th><th align="left"><italic>p</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Number</td><td align="left">184</td><td align="left">148</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Median (range) age (years)</td><td align="left">72 (44&#x02013;89)</td><td align="left">75 (52&#x02013;90)</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Median (range) initial PSA (ng/ml)</td><td align="left">299 (0.95&#x02013;15,030)</td><td align="left">249 (4.47&#x02013;122,875)</td><td align="left">0.303</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">T stage</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;2</td><td align="left">25</td><td align="left">22</td><td align="left" rowspan="4">0.28</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;3</td><td align="left">93</td><td align="left">80</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;4</td><td align="left">62</td><td align="left">36</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;NA</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">N stage</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;0</td><td align="left">65</td><td align="left">50</td><td align="left" rowspan="3">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;1</td><td align="left">118</td><td align="left">93</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;NA</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">M stage</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;1a</td><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">16</td><td align="left" rowspan="3">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;1b</td><td align="left">126</td><td align="left">121</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;1c</td><td align="left">50</td><td align="left">11</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Gleason grade group</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;2</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="5">0.85</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;3</td><td align="left">12</td><td align="left">12</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;4</td><td align="left">53</td><td align="left">38</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;5</td><td align="left">109</td><td align="left">78</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;NA</td><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">18</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Metastatic volume</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;High</td><td align="left">136</td><td align="left">82</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Low</td><td align="left">48</td><td align="left">66</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>ADT</italic> androgen deprivation therapy, <italic>ARSI</italic> androgen receptor signal inhibitor, <italic>PSA</italic> prostate-specific antigen, <italic>T</italic> tumor, <italic>N</italic> node, <italic>M</italic> metastasis</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par10">In the ARSI group, 100 (54%) patients received abiraterone plus prednisolone, 57 (31%) received enzalutamide, and 27 (15%) received apalutamide. In the ADT group, 136 patients (91.9%) received bicalutamide in addition to ADT. The median time to CRPC was 47&#x000a0;months in the ARSI group and 15&#x000a0;months in the ADT group; the duration was significantly longer in the ARSI group than in the ADT group (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001). The median OS was 48&#x000a0;months in the ARSI group and 64&#x000a0;months in the ADT group, with no significant difference between the groups (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.42) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Kaplan&#x02013;Meier curves of the time to CRPC (<bold>a</bold>) and OS (<bold>b</bold>) in all patients in the ARSI and ADT groups. The <italic>p</italic> values were determined using log-rank tests. <italic>CRPC</italic> castration-resistant prostate cancer, <italic>OS</italic> overall survival, <italic>ADT</italic> androgen deprivation therapy, <italic>ARSI</italic> androgen receptor signal inhibitor</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10147_2024_2670_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p><p id="Par11">Propensity score matching was performed to reduce selection bias between the ARSI and ADT groups. Consequently, the backgrounds of the patients were not significantly different between the ARSI (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;107) and ADT (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;107) groups (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). The median time to CRPC was not reached in the ARSI group but was 15&#x000a0;months in the ADT group; the time was significantly longer in the ARSI group than in the ADT group (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001). The median OS was not reached in the ARSI group but was 62&#x000a0;months in the ADT group, and no significant difference was observed in the log-rank test (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.193). Conversely, the 1- and 2-year survival rates were higher in the ARSI group than in the ADT group (98.1% vs. 89.9% and 92.2% vs. 84.3%, respectively) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Patient characteristics in ARSI and ADT group after propensity score matching</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left">ARSI</th><th align="left">ADT</th><th align="left"><italic>p</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Number</td><td align="left">107</td><td align="left">107</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Median (range) age (years)</td><td align="left">75 (44&#x02013;89)</td><td align="left">74 (52&#x02013;90)</td><td char="." align="char">0.934</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Median (range) initial PSA (ng/ml)</td><td align="left">299 (0.95&#x02013;15,030)</td><td align="left">249 (4.47&#x02013;122,875)</td><td char="." align="char">0.756</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">T stage</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;2</td><td align="left">14</td><td align="left">20</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="3">0.492</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;3</td><td align="left">64</td><td align="left">57</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;4</td><td align="left">29</td><td align="left">30</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">N stage</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;0</td><td align="left">44</td><td align="left">42</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="2">0.856</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;1</td><td align="left">63</td><td align="left">65</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">M stage</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;1a</td><td align="left">7</td><td align="left">8</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="3">0.856</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;1b</td><td align="left">88</td><td align="left">90</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;1c</td><td align="left">12</td><td align="left">9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Gleason grade group</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;2</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">2</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="4">0.708</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;3</td><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;4</td><td align="left">28</td><td align="left">29</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;5</td><td align="left">69</td><td align="left">72</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Metastatic volume</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;High</td><td align="left">43</td><td align="left">39</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="2">0.673</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Low</td><td align="left">64</td><td align="left">68</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>ADT</italic> androgen deprivation therapy, <italic>ARSI</italic> androgen receptor signal inhibitor, <italic>PSA</italic> prostate-specific antigen, <italic>T</italic> tumor, <italic>N</italic> node, <italic>M</italic> metastasis</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Kaplan&#x02013;Meier curves of the time to CRPC (<bold>a</bold>) and OS (<bold>b</bold>) after propensity score matching in the ARSI and ADT groups. The <italic>p</italic> values were determined using log-rank tests. <italic>CRPC</italic> castration-resistant prostate cancer, <italic>OS</italic> overall survival, <italic>ADT</italic> androgen deprivation therapy, <italic>ARSI</italic> androgen receptor signal inhibitor, <italic>PSM</italic> propensity score matching</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10147_2024_2670_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p><p id="Par12">Patients were subcategorized based on risk categories in order to identify those in whom upfront ARSI added to ADT improved survival. They were classified into groups with high- and low-volume metastasis according to the CHAARTED criteria; the OS was not significantly different between patients in the ARSI and ADT groups in the log-rank test in these subgroups (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.102 and <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.976, respectively). The 1- and 2-year survival rates tended to be higher in patients in the ARSI group than in those in the ADT group in both the high-volume (96.1% vs. 85.0% and 90.6% vs. 81.6%, respectively) and low-volume metastasis subgroups (100% vs. 94.9% and 93.8% vs. 86.9%, respectively). The difference in the 1-year survival rate was higher in the high-volume subgroup (11.1%) than in the low-volume subgroup (5.1%). Patients were also classified into subgroups based on Gleason grade groups of 5 and&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;4. In both these subgroups, OS was not significantly different between patients in the ARSI and ADT groups in the log-rank test (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.434 and <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.17, respectively). The 1- and 2-year survival rates tended to be higher in patients in the ARSI group than in those in the ADT group in both the Gleason grade group 5 (98.1% vs. 85.9% and 89.8% vs. 81.3%, respectively) and Gleason grade group&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;4 (96.3% vs. 94.1% and 96.3% vs. 88.0%, respectively) subgroups. The difference in the 1-year survival rate was higher in the Gleason grade group 5 (12.2%) than in the Gleason grade group&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;4 (2.2%) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Kaplan&#x02013;Meier curves of OS after propensity score matching in patients with low metastatic volume (<bold>a</bold>), high metastatic volume (<bold>b</bold>), Gleason grade group 5 (<bold>c</bold>), and Gleason grade group&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;4 (<bold>d</bold>) in the ARSI and ADT groups. The <italic>p</italic> values were determined using log-rank tests. The 1- and 2-year cumulative survival rates were determined in each group. <italic>OS</italic> overall survival, <italic>ADT</italic> androgen deprivation therapy, <italic>ARSI</italic> androgen receptor signal inhibitor</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10147_2024_2670_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par13">In this study, we compared treatment effects between patients who received ADT plus ARSI and those who received ADT alone or ADT plus bicalutamide by adjusting for background factors using propensity score matching. The time to CRPC was significantly longer with ADT plus ARSI than with ADT alone or ADT plus bicalutamide; however, no significant differences were observed in OS. In addition, no significant difference was observed when analyzing the high- and low-volume subgroups and high- and low-Gleason grades subgroups separately. These findings suggest that adding ARSI to ADT prolongs the time to CRPC; however, it does not consistently affect OS. Interestingly, these results are not consistent with those of a globally conducted randomized control trial (RCT) that demonstrated the efficacy of ARSI added to ADT in treating patients with castration-sensitive metastatic prostate cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>].</p><p id="Par14">The results of retrospective studies conducted to determine the efficacy of ARSIs in Japanese patients with castration-sensitive metastatic prostate cancer were reported after 2021. Patients with LATITUDE high-risk disease (meeting at least two of the following three criteria: (i) Gleason score&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;8, (ii) presence of&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;3 lesions on bone scan, and (iii) presence of measurable visceral lesions) receiving ADT plus abiraterone were compared with those previously treated with ADT plus bicalutamide. Two studies did not report a significant difference in OS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. A study that focused only on CHAARTED high-volume disease reported a significantly prolonged OS in patients treated with ADT plus abiraterone or docetaxel [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Another study indicated that treatment with ADT plus abiraterone resulted in prolonged OS only in patients with Gleason grade 5 primary lesions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. In the largest retrospective multi-institutional study in Japan, named the J-ROCK study, OS was significantly longer in patients receiving any ARSI added to ADT than in those receiving bicalutamide added to ADT; however, the patient backgrounds were not matched [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Another study suggested that patients treated with ADT and apalutamide may have better OS than patients treated with bicalutamide alone [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>].</p><p id="Par15">These retrospective studies indicate that the efficacy of ARSI in combination with ADT in Japanese patients with castration-sensitive metastatic prostate cancer is controversial. In our retrospective multi-institutional study, OS was not significantly different between the ARSI and ADT groups. An important factor that could explain the lack of observed differences is the approach to treatment initiation. In the ADT group, PSA levels were regularly monitored and ARSI treatment was initiated at the first indication of any increase in PSA. In the global RCT, ARSI treatment was delayed until radiological progression occurred in the ADT group to evaluate radiological progression-free survival. Approximately 90% of patients started ARSI treatment only in PSA progression without radiological progression in ADT group, although the accurate number of patients was not examined in this study. This practice may have mitigated the potential benefits of initiating ADT plus ARSI from the outset, thereby influencing study outcomes.</p><p id="Par16">Global RCTs conducted to determine the efficacy of abiraterone (LATITUDE), apalutamide (TITAN), and enzalutamide (ARCHES) included Japanese patients and reported on the results of subgroup analyses in these patients. All the studies clearly revealed the efficacy of ARSIs in improving OS in all patient subgroups [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. However, no significant improvement in OS was observed in the Japanese subgroup analyses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. One reason for this discrepancy could be the inclusion of small number of patients in the Japanese cohort. Another reason is that the OS in the ADT group in the Japanese cohort was better than that in the global cohort. Therefore, the addition of ARSI might not have prolonged the OS further. Previous reports have indicated that patients with metastatic prostate cancer in Japan have better prognoses than those of patients in the United States [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. The efficacy of ADT for treating prostate cancer is higher in Asians than in Caucasians [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Despite advances in treatment strategies, the question regarding whether Japanese patients, who are known to have a better prognosis with ADT, benefit equally from the addition of ARSI to treatment regimens remains unanswered. This gap not only highlights the need for further investigations but also underscores the potential for gaining novel insights into personalized cancer treatment strategies.</p><p id="Par17">As shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, the median OS tended to be shorter in the ARSI group than in the ADT group (48&#x000a0;months and 64&#x000a0;months, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.42), although the time to CRPC was significantly longer in the ARSI group than in the ADT group. It was suggested that the death from causes other than prostate cancer was higher in the ARSI group. Therefore, the cancer-specific survival was evaluated. Although the median cancer-specific survival time was not reached in both ARSI group and ADT group, the Kaplan&#x02013;Meier curves show similar trends with those of OS (Supplemental Fig. 1). These results indicated that most of the death in the ARSI group was caused by prostate cancer. The reasons for the discrepancies between time to CRPC and OS might be the differences in the follow-up duration between the groups. The follow-up duration was not enough for evaluating the median OS in the ARSI group.</p><p id="Par18">To explore the characteristics of Japanese patients with metastatic prostate cancer in whom the addition of ARSI was effective, OS was compared in the subgroups based on metastatic volume and Gleason grade between the ARSI and ADT groups after propensity score matching. No significant differences were observed between the high- and low-volume subgroups or between the high and low Gleason grade subgroups. However, the Kaplan&#x02013;Meier survival curves indicated that the survival rate tended to be better at the short-term follow-up after treatment initiation. Therefore, we compared the 1- and 2-year survival rates. The 1-year survival rate was 6% higher in the high-volume group than in the low-volume group (11.1% vs. 5.1%) and 10% higher in the high Gleason grade group than in the low Gleason grade group (12.2 vs. 2.2%). These results indicate that the addition of ARSI may suppress the short-term risk of death in high-risk subgroups of Japanese patients with metastatic prostate cancer, although the difference was not significant in log-rank test.</p><p id="Par19">This study has several limitations. Because of the retrospective multi-institutional nature of the study, treatment selection, including ADT or ADT plus ARSI and the type of ARSI (abiraterone, apalutamide, or enzalutamide), for each patient differed among institutes and was based on the physician&#x02019;s preferences. Due to the observational nature of this study, biases originating from unmeasured covariates could not be completely eliminated. In comparing the differences between the treatment groups, especially in the subgroup analyses, the sample size was insufficient to draw definitive conclusions. Moreover, the follow-up duration is not enough to compare the OS in this study. To see the efficacy of ARSI to prolong the prognosis of metastatic prostate cancer patients, further study is needed with longer follow-up duration. However, this is the first study to show the efficacy of adding ARSI to the treatment regimen in subgroups of Japanese patients with metastatic prostate cancer based on metastatic volume and Gleason grade. The results may help in deciding between starting with ADT and adding ARSI at the time of PSA increase or starting with ADT plus ARSI as the first-line therapy for metastatic prostate cancer in Japan.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="10147_2024_2670_MOESM1_ESM.tif"><caption><p>Supplementary file1 Supplement Fig. 1 Kaplan&#x02013;Meier curves of cancer-specific survival (a) and that after propensity score matching (b) in the ARSI and ADT groups. The p values were determined using log-rank tests. Abbreviations: ADT, androgen deprivation therapy; ARSI, androgen receptor signal inhibitor; PSM, propensity score matching (TIF 91 KB)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Tadashi Kakitsuba, Wonseok Seo (Department of Urology, University of Fukui), Yoshifumi Kadono, Kazuto Komatsu (Department of Urology, Japan Red Cross Fukui Hospital), Hideaki Ito, Tadahiro Kobayashi (Department of Urology, Fukui Prefectural Hospital), Takahiro Kojima (Department of Urology, Aichi Cancer Center), Hiroshi Matsuura (Department of Urology, Mie Prefectural General Medical Center), Shigenori Yonemura (Department of Urology, Matsusaka Manucipal Hospital), Takehisa Ohnishi (Department of Urology, Ise Red Cross Hospital) and Tetsuya Imamura (Department of Urology, Ise Municipal General Hospital) for the efforts in collection and management of the clinical data. We thank Miyuki Akino (Department of Urology, University of Miyazaki) for the efforts in data cleaning.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>Minekatsu Taga analyzed the results and wrote the manuscript. Minekatsu Taga, Takeshi Sasaki, Shiniticho Higashi, Shoichi Kimura collected data. Naoki Terada, Atsuro Sawada, Katsuki Tsuchiyama, Takahiro Inoue, Toshiyuki Kamoto contributed to the research conceptualization and design. Naoki Terada supervised the project.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>Open Access funding provided by University of Fukui.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The datasets generated during and/or analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p id="Par20">Toshiyuki Kamoto received honoraria from Janssen, Takeda, Astellas, AstraZeneca, and Sanofi, and research funding from Janssen, MSD, Bayer and AstraZeneca. Takahiro Inoue received honoraria from Janssen, Takeda, Astellas, AstraZeneca, Sanofi and Bayer. Naoki Terada received honoraria from Janssen, Takeda, Astellas, AstraZeneca, Sanofi, and Bayer. Other authors had no conflict of interest to declare.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Siegel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cancer statistics, 2014</article-title><source>CA Cancer J Clin</source><year>2014</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3322/caac.21208</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24399786</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Siegel R, Ma J, Zou Z et al (2014) Cancer statistics, 2014. CA Cancer J Clin 64:9&#x02013;29<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24399786</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Bono</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Logothetis</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Molina</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Abiraterone and increased survival in metastatic prostate cancer</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2011</year><volume>364</volume><fpage>1995</fpage><lpage>2005</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa1014618</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21612468</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">de Bono JS, Logothetis CJ, Molina A et al (2011) Abiraterone and increased survival in metastatic prostate cancer. N Engl J Med 364:1995&#x02013;2005<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21612468</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beer</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rathkopf</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Enzalutamide in metastatic prostate cancer before chemotherapy</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2014</year><volume>371</volume><fpage>424</fpage><lpage>433</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa1405095</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24881730</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Beer TM, Armstrong AJ, Rathkopf DE et al (2014) Enzalutamide in metastatic prostate cancer before chemotherapy. N Engl J Med 371:424&#x02013;433<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24881730</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fizazi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Fein</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Abiraterone acetate plus prednisone in patients with newly diagnosed high-risk metastatic castration-sensitive prostate cancer (LATITUDE): final overall survival analysis of a randomised, double-blind, phase 3 trial</article-title><source>Lancet Oncol</source><year>2019</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>686</fpage><lpage>700</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1470-2045(19)30082-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30987939</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Fizazi K, Tran N, Fein L et al (2019) Abiraterone acetate plus prednisone in patients with newly diagnosed high-risk metastatic castration-sensitive prostate cancer (LATITUDE): final overall survival analysis of a randomised, double-blind, phase 3 trial. Lancet Oncol 20:686&#x02013;700<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30987939</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>ID</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Stockler</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Enzalutamide with standard first-line therapy in metastatic prostate cancer</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2019</year><volume>381</volume><fpage>121</fpage><lpage>131</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa1903835</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31157964</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Davis ID, Martin AJ, Stockler MR et al (2019) Enzalutamide with standard first-line therapy in metastatic prostate cancer. N Engl J Med 381:121&#x02013;131<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31157964</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name><name><surname>Agarwal</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bjartell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Apalutamide for metastatic, castration-sensitive prostate cancer</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2019</year><volume>381</volume><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa1903307</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31150574</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Chi KN, Agarwal N, Bjartell A et al (2019) Apalutamide for metastatic, castration-sensitive prostate cancer. N Engl J Med 381:13&#x02013;24<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31150574</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cooperberg</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hinotsu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Namiki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Trans-Pacific variation in outcomes for men treated with primary androgen-deprivation therapy (ADT) for prostate cancer</article-title><source>BJU Int</source><year>2016</year><volume>117</volume><fpage>102</fpage><lpage>109</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/bju.12937</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25238114</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Cooperberg MR, Hinotsu S, Namiki M et al (2016) Trans-Pacific variation in outcomes for men treated with primary androgen-deprivation therapy (ADT) for prostate cancer. BJU Int 117:102&#x02013;109<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25238114</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sweeney</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Carducci</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chemohormonal therapy in metastatic hormone-sensitive prostate cancer</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2015</year><volume>373</volume><fpage>737</fpage><lpage>746</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa1503747</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26244877</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Sweeney CJ, Chen YH, Carducci M et al (2015) Chemohormonal therapy in metastatic hormone-sensitive prostate cancer. N Engl J Med 373:737&#x02013;746<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26244877</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scher</surname><given-names>HI</given-names></name><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Stadler</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Trial design and objectives for castration-resistant prostate cancer: updated recommendations from the Prostate Cancer Clinical Trials Working Group 3</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>2016</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>1402</fpage><lpage>1418</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/JCO.2015.64.2702</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26903579</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Scher HI, Morris MJ, Stadler WM et al (2016) Trial design and objectives for castration-resistant prostate cancer: updated recommendations from the Prostate Cancer Clinical Trials Working Group 3. J Clin Oncol 34:1402&#x02013;1418<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26903579</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Naiki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparison of clinical outcomes between androgen deprivation therapy with up-front abiraterone and bicalutamide for Japanese patients with LATITUDE high-risk prostate cancer in a real-world retrospective analysis</article-title><source>Int J Clin Oncol</source><year>2022</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>592</fpage><lpage>601</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10147-021-02071-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34779958</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Naiki T, Takahara K, Ito T et al (2022) Comparison of clinical outcomes between androgen deprivation therapy with up-front abiraterone and bicalutamide for Japanese patients with LATITUDE high-risk prostate cancer in a real-world retrospective analysis. Int J Clin Oncol 27:592&#x02013;601<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34779958</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yanagisawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Abiraterone acetate versus nonsteroidal antiandrogen with androgen deprivation therapy for high-risk metastatic hormone-sensitive prostate cancer</article-title><source>Prostate</source><year>2022</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pros.24243</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34559410</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Yanagisawa T, Kimura T, Mori K et al (2022) Abiraterone acetate versus nonsteroidal antiandrogen with androgen deprivation therapy for high-risk metastatic hormone-sensitive prostate cancer. Prostate 82:3&#x02013;12<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34559410</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Narita</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatakeyama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Real-world survival outcomes of adding docetaxel or abiraterone in patients with high-volume metastatic castration-sensitive prostate cancer: historically controlled, propensity score matched comparison with androgen deprivation therapy</article-title><source>World J Urol</source><year>2022</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>1135</fpage><lpage>1141</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00345-022-03963-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35218371</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Narita S, Kimura T, Hatakeyama S et al (2022) Real-world survival outcomes of adding docetaxel or abiraterone in patients with high-volume metastatic castration-sensitive prostate cancer: historically controlled, propensity score matched comparison with androgen deprivation therapy. World J Urol 40:1135&#x02013;1141<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35218371</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ueda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishimoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Predictive factors for the efficacy of abiraterone acetate therapy in high-risk metastatic hormone-sensitive prostate cancer patients</article-title><source>World J Urol</source><year>2022</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>2939</fpage><lpage>2946</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00345-022-04200-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36331614</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Ueda T, Fujita K, Nishimoto M et al (2022) Predictive factors for the efficacy of abiraterone acetate therapy in high-risk metastatic hormone-sensitive prostate cancer patients. World J Urol 40:2939&#x02013;2946<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36331614</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miyake</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujimoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clinical outcomes of patients with high-risk metastatic hormone-na&#x000ef;ve prostate cancer: a 3-year interim analysis of the Observational J-ROCK study</article-title><source>Eur Urol Oncol</source><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.euo.2023.12.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38296736</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Miyake H, Matsumoto R, Fujimoto K et al (2024) Clinical outcomes of patients with high-risk metastatic hormone-na&#x000ef;ve prostate cancer: a 3-year interim analysis of the Observational J-ROCK study. Eur Urol Oncol. 10.1016/j.euo.2023.12.013. (<bold>in press</bold>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38296736</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ueda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Shiraishi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyashita</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Apalutamide versus bicalutamide in combination with androgen deprivation therapy for metastatic hormone sensitive prostate cancer</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2024</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>705</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-024-51389-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38184704</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Ueda T, Shiraishi T, Miyashita M et al (2024) Apalutamide versus bicalutamide in combination with androgen deprivation therapy for metastatic hormone sensitive prostate cancer. Sci Rep 14:705<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38184704</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukasawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Efficacy and safety of abiraterone acetate plus prednisone in Japanese patients with newly diagnosed, metastatic hormone-naive prostate cancer: final subgroup analysis of LATITUDE, a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, phase 3 study</article-title><source>Jpn J Clin Oncol</source><year>2020</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>810</fpage><lpage>820</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jjco/hyaa030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32188988</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Suzuki H, Shin T, Fukasawa S et al (2020) Efficacy and safety of abiraterone acetate plus prednisone in Japanese patients with newly diagnosed, metastatic hormone-naive prostate cancer: final subgroup analysis of LATITUDE, a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, phase 3 study. Jpn J Clin Oncol 50:810&#x02013;820<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32188988</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Uemura</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Arai</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Safety and efficacy of apalutamide in Japanese patients with metastatic castration-sensitive prostate cancer receiving androgen deprivation therapy: final report for the Japanese subpopulation analysis of the randomized, placebo-controlled, phase III TITAN study</article-title><source>Int J Urol</source><year>2022</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>533</fpage><lpage>540</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/iju.14843</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35293030</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Uemura H, Arai G, Suzuki H et al (2022) Safety and efficacy of apalutamide in Japanese patients with metastatic castration-sensitive prostate cancer receiving androgen deprivation therapy: final report for the Japanese subpopulation analysis of the randomized, placebo-controlled, phase III TITAN study. Int J Urol 29:533&#x02013;540<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35293030</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iguchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukasawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Enzalutamide with androgen deprivation therapy in Japanese men with metastatic hormone-sensitive prostate cancer: a subgroup analysis of the phase III ARCHES study</article-title><source>Int J Urol</source><year>2021</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>765</fpage><lpage>773</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/iju.14568</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33955599</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Iguchi T, Kimura G, Fukasawa S et al (2021) Enzalutamide with androgen deprivation therapy in Japanese men with metastatic hormone-sensitive prostate cancer: a subgroup analysis of the phase III ARCHES study. Int J Urol 28:765&#x02013;773<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33955599</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fukagai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Namiki</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlile</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparison of the clinical outcome after hormonal therapy for prostate cancer between Japanese and Caucasian men</article-title><source>BJU Int</source><year>2006</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>1190</fpage><lpage>1193</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1464-410X.2006.06201.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16686710</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Fukagai T, Namiki TS, Carlile RG et al (2006) Comparison of the clinical outcome after hormonal therapy for prostate cancer between Japanese and Caucasian men. BJU Int 97:1190&#x02013;1193<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16686710</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article>