<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Dermatopathology (Basel)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Dermatopathology (Basel)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">dermatopathology</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Dermatopathology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2296-3529</issn><publisher><publisher-name>MDPI</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40407483</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12101269</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/dermatopathology12020015</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">dermatopathology-12-00015</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Clinicopathological Challenge</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Skin-Colored Papules on the Neck of a Postmenopausal Woman: A Diagnostic Challenge</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>El Jalkh</surname><given-names>Jason</given-names></name><xref rid="af1-dermatopathology-12-00015" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Obeid</surname><given-names>Pia Maria</given-names></name><xref rid="af1-dermatopathology-12-00015" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3638-909X</contrib-id><name><surname>Guermazi</surname><given-names>Dorra</given-names></name><xref rid="af2-dermatopathology-12-00015" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Soubra</surname><given-names>Aya</given-names></name><xref rid="af3-dermatopathology-12-00015" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5994-3212</contrib-id><name><surname>Saliba</surname><given-names>Elie</given-names></name><xref rid="af1-dermatopathology-12-00015" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="c1-dermatopathology-12-00015" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Kaya</surname><given-names>G&#x000fc;rkan</given-names></name><role>Academic Editor</role></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af1-dermatopathology-12-00015"><label>1</label>Department of Dermatology, Gilbert and Rose-Marie Chagoury School of Medicine, Lebanese American University, Beirut 13-5053, Lebanon; <email>jason.eljalkh01@lau.edu</email> (J.E.J.); <email>piamaria.obeid@lau.edu</email> (P.M.O.)</aff><aff id="af2-dermatopathology-12-00015"><label>2</label>Department of Dermatology, The Warren Alpert Medical School of Brown University, Providence, RI 02903, USA; <email>dorra_guermazi@brown.edu</email></aff><aff id="af3-dermatopathology-12-00015"><label>3</label>Department of Pathology, Gilbert and Rose-Marie Chagoury School of Medicine, Lebanese American University, Beirut 13-5053, Lebanon; <email>aya.soubra@laumcrh.com</email></aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1-dermatopathology-12-00015"><label>*</label>Correspondence: <email>elie.saliba01@lau.edu.lb</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>6</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><issue>2</issue><elocation-id>15</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>07</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>12</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2025 by the authors.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>Published by MDPI on behalf of the European Society of Dermatopathology. Licensee MDPI, Basel, Switzerland. This article is an open access article distributed under the terms and conditions of the Creative Commons Attribution (CC BY) license (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>A 64-year-old patient presented for management of symptomatic skin-colored papules symmetrically distributed over the lateral neck over the past two years, which failed to improve on multiple topical corticosteroids, antifungal creams, and topical calcineurin inhibitor. Histopathologic examination showed a regular epidermis with increased melanophages in the papillary dermis, without vacuolar degeneration of the basement membrane. Verhoeff Van Gieson stain highlighted a band-like zone of attenuated elastic fibers in the papillary dermis, while Von Kossa stain was negative for calcified fibers. PAS staining was negative for fungal organisms and Alcian blue showed no increase in dermal mucin.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>pseudoxanthoma elasticum-like papillary dermal elastolysis</kwd><kwd>acquired elastic tissue disorder</kwd><kwd>trifarotene therapy</kwd><kwd>histopathology</kwd><kwd>dermatopathology</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><funding-statement>This research received no external funding.</funding-statement></funding-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1-dermatopathology-12-00015"><title>1. Case Presentation</title><p>A 64-year-old patient with a medical history of irritable bowel syndrome, depression, and endometriosis presented for management of symptomatic lesions on her neck, which has been present for the past 2 years. The patient denied significant sun exposure in the past years but reported that heat exposure triggered itching and burning sensation in the affected area. On physical examination, skin-colored papules were noted, symmetrically distributed over the lateral neck (<xref rid="dermatopathology-12-00015-f001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>A).</p><p>Over the past two years, the patient has attempted various treatments, including multiple topical corticosteroids, antifungal creams, and topical calcineurin inhibitor, without achieving symptomatic relief or clinical improvement in the lesions.</p><p>A 3 mm punch biopsy was performed on the right lateral neck. Histopathologic examination showed a regular epidermis with increased melanophages in the papillary dermis, without vacuolar degeneration of the basement membrane (<xref rid="dermatopathology-12-00015-f002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>A,B). Given that the findings on hematoxylin&#x02013;eosin (H&#x00026;E) largely resembled normal skin and the clinical presentation mimicked PXE, additional stains were performed to aid in diagnosis. Verhoeff Van Gieson stain highlighted a band-like zone of attenuated elastic fibers in the papillary dermis (<xref rid="dermatopathology-12-00015-f003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>), while Von Kossa stain was negative for calcified fibers (<xref rid="dermatopathology-12-00015-f004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>). PAS staining was negative for fungal organisms and Alcian blue showed no increase in dermal mucin.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-dermatopathology-12-00015"><title>2. What Is the Diagnosis?</title><list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>&#x000a0;<bold>A.</bold></label><p>Pseudoxanthoma elasticum;</p></list-item><list-item><label>&#x000a0;<bold>B.</bold></label><p>Pseudoxanthoma elasticum-like papillary dermal elastolysis;</p></list-item><list-item><label>&#x000a0;<bold>C.</bold></label><p>White fibrous papulosis;</p></list-item><list-item><label>&#x000a0;<bold>D.</bold></label><p>Papillary dermal elastosis;</p></list-item><list-item><label>&#x000a0;<bold>E.</bold></label><p>Mid-dermal elastolysis.</p></list-item></list></sec><sec id="sec3-dermatopathology-12-00015"><title>3. Diagnosis</title><sec><title>Pseudoxanthoma Elasticum-like Papillary Dermal Elastolysis</title><p>The patient was advised to apply trifarotene cream, one pump daily on each side of the neck, alternating with a topical corticosteroid cream to minimize irritation. Three months later, she reported improvement in both pruritus and clinical lesions (<xref rid="dermatopathology-12-00015-f001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>B).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec4-dermatopathology-12-00015"><title>4. Discussion</title><p>Our article contributes a new case of PXE-PDE to the literature. This entity was first described in 1992 by Rongioletti and Rebora [<xref rid="B1-dermatopathology-12-00015" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Clinically, it is characterized by non-follicular, dome-shaped, soft, yellowish papules measuring 2 to 3 mm, which coalesce into plaques and show predilection for the lateral and posterior neck areas [<xref rid="B2-dermatopathology-12-00015" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. In the most recent case series, 100% of reported PXE-like PDE cases were asymptomatic, unlike our patient, who experienced pruritus since lesion onset. While PXE-like PDE is typically asymptomatic, symptomatic cases have been documented, including a 65-year-old Caucasian woman who reported mild itching since lesion development in 2013 [<xref rid="B1-dermatopathology-12-00015" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>].</p><p>Since its initial description, few cases of PXE-like papillary dermal elastolysis (PDE) have been reported [<xref rid="B3-dermatopathology-12-00015" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Although a case has been described in a middle-aged woman, most cases affect postmenopausal women, consistent with our case. Notably, no cases in the literature have involved men [<xref rid="B4-dermatopathology-12-00015" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="B5-dermatopathology-12-00015" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].</p><p>The pathogenesis of PXE-like PDE is thought to involve abnormal elastic fiber formation, intrinsic aging, and ultraviolet (UV) radiation [<xref rid="B6-dermatopathology-12-00015" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="B7-dermatopathology-12-00015" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. UV radiation is a contributing factor in PXE-like PDE, though it does not fully explain the disease&#x02019;s pathogenesis, as over 30% of cases affect non-sun-exposed areas like the axilla, and more than half of patients report no history of prolonged sun exposure [<xref rid="B4-dermatopathology-12-00015" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Histologic evidence supports UV radiation&#x02019;s role, with increased melanophages in sun-exposed skin compared to protected areas [<xref rid="B8-dermatopathology-12-00015" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], and melanophages in the papillary dermis in nearly all reported cases [<xref rid="B4-dermatopathology-12-00015" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. This suggests that repeated UV-induced injury at the dermo-epidermal junction, as seen in chronic heliodermatitis, could drive pathologic changes [<xref rid="B9-dermatopathology-12-00015" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. However, our patient did not report significant sun exposure, reflected by the lack of solar elastosis on pathology.</p><p>Intrinsic aging is another factor, with loss of both elastin and fibrillin-1 in the dermis [<xref rid="B3-dermatopathology-12-00015" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Fibrillin-1 is also absent in the neck skin of elderly individuals, potentially contributing to dermal component loss in PXE-like PDE [<xref rid="B7-dermatopathology-12-00015" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. In the previous literature, approximately 40% of PXE-like PDE cases have not been linked to systemic conditions. In the most recent case series, the distribution of systemic diseases was as follows: 17.6% with hypertension, 11.8% with hyperlipidemia, and 5.9% each with hypothyroidism, anemia, and atopic disease [<xref rid="B4-dermatopathology-12-00015" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. However, these comorbidities appear to be related to natural aging in postmenopausal women and not directly linked to PXE-PDE. Notably, our patient is a 64-year-old postmenopausal woman with no significant systemic comorbidities.</p><p>Histologically, hematoxylin&#x02013;eosin staining often reveals minimal findings, with the skin appearing nearly normal (invisible dermatosis). Thus, in the absence of clear clinicopathologic correlation, diagnosis can be easily missed. Special stains for elastic fibers such as orcein, Verhoeff Van Gieson, or Weigert are essential for confirmation. The epidermis is typically normal or slightly thinned, with the most characteristic finding being a band-like loss or marked reduction in eulanin and oxytalan elastic fibers in the papillary dermis, often accompanied by sparse melanophages within the zone of elastic loss. Additionally, a mild perivascular lymphocytic infiltrate in the papillary dermis may be observed [<xref rid="B4-dermatopathology-12-00015" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>].</p><p>The presence of melanophages without vacuolar degeneration in this case likely reflects a secondary response to chronic epidermal stress, mechanical friction, and age-related dermal changes, in addition to the PXE-like pathology.</p><p>The primary elastic tissue disorders in the clinical and histologic differential diagnosis of PXE-like papillary dermal elastolysis (PXE-PDE) include pseudoxanthoma elasticum (PXE), white fibrous papulosis, papillary dermal elastosis, and mid-dermal elastolysis. PXE presents clinically similarly to PXE-PDE but is distinguished by associated comorbidities. Histologically, elastic changes are found in the reticular dermis with sparing of the papillary dermis, showing fragmented, calcified elastic fibers without melanophages [<xref rid="B4-dermatopathology-12-00015" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. White fibrous papulosis is characterized by non-confluent, whitish, firm papules on the posterior neck. Histologic findings may include loss of elastic fibers with dermal fibrosis and possible melanophages [<xref rid="B10-dermatopathology-12-00015" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="B11-dermatopathology-12-00015" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Papillary dermal elastosis has a similar clinical appearance to PXE-PDE. Histologically, it shows focal clumps of elastic fibers alternating with areas of oxytalan and elaunin fiber loss, along with an increase in elastic fibers in the reticular dermis. Melanophages are typically absent [<xref rid="B12-dermatopathology-12-00015" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Finally, mid-dermal elastolysis presents with well-circumscribed patches of fine wrinkles or perifollicular papules on the trunk and proximal extremities. Histologic findings are confined to the reticular dermis, with a loss of elastic fibers and no melanophages present [<xref rid="B13-dermatopathology-12-00015" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec5-dermatopathology-12-00015"><title>5. Conclusions</title><p>PXE-like PDE is a chronic, slowly progressing condition with limited effective treatments. Therapeutic attempts with topical retinoids have generally shown minimal improvement, although one isolated report indicated marked improvement. Intralesional triamcinolone provided no clinical benefit in one case, despite two rounds of treatment. Lasers, particularly ablative CO<sub>2</sub> lasers, have shown promise by improving skin texture and appearance by approximately 50%, as reported by a patient in 2018 [<xref rid="B14-dermatopathology-12-00015" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Given the lack of established treatments for PXE-like conditions, the use of this retinoid is exploratory. The mix between a retinoid and a steroid was to mitigate potential irritation given the sensitivity of the neck area where the lesions appeared. Notably, our patient achieved significant improvement with trifarotene cream, introducing a new therapeutic option for PXE-like PDE not previously documented in the literature.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Disclaimer/Publisher&#x02019;s Note:</bold> The statements, opinions and data contained in all publications are solely those of the individual author(s) and contributor(s) and not of MDPI and/or the editor(s). MDPI and/or the editor(s) disclaim responsibility for any injury to people or property resulting from any ideas, methods, instructions or products referred to in the content.</p></fn></fn-group><notes><title>Author Contributions</title><p>Conceptualization, J.E.J., A.S. and E.S. Original draft preparation, P.M.O., J.E.J., D.G., A.S. and E.S. Writing, review and editing, D.G. and E.S. All authors have read and agreed to the published version of the manuscript.</p></notes><notes><title>Institutional Review Board Statement</title><p>Not applicable.</p></notes><notes><title>Informed Consent Statement</title><p>Written informed consent has been obtained from the patient to publish this paper.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The original contributions presented in this study are included in the article. Further inquiries can be directed to the corresponding author.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflicts of Interest</title><p>The authors declare no conflicts of interest.</p></notes><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1-dermatopathology-12-00015"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pranteda</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Muscianese</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marmo</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fidanza</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pranteda</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tamburi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bottoni</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nistic&#x000f2;</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Role of steroid therapy in pseudoxanthoma elasticum-like papillary dermal elastolysis</article-title><source>Int. J. Immunopathol. Pharmacol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>1013</fpage><lpage>1018</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/039463201302600423</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24355240</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B2-dermatopathology-12-00015"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rongioletti</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rebora</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Pseudoxanthoma elasticum-like papillary dermal elastolysis</article-title><source>J. Am. Acad. Dermatol.</source><year>1992</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>648</fpage><lpage>650</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0190-9622(08)80797-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1597557</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B3-dermatopathology-12-00015"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Byun</surname><given-names>J.Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Do</surname><given-names>M.O.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S.H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>H.Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Myung</surname><given-names>K.B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>Y.W.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Pseudoxanthoma elasticum-like papillary dermal elastolysis developed in early middle age</article-title><source>J. Dermatol.</source><year>2007</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>709</fpage><lpage>711</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1346-8138.2007.00365.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17908144</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B4-dermatopathology-12-00015"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rongioletti</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Izakovic</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Romanelli</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lanuti</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Miteva</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Pseudoxanthoma elasticum-like papillary dermal elastolysis: A large case series with clinicopathological correlation</article-title><source>J. Am. Acad. Dermatol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>128</fpage><lpage>135</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaad.2011.09.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22018757</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B5-dermatopathology-12-00015"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Orlandi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bianchi</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nini</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Spagnoli</surname><given-names>L.G.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Familial occurrence of pseudoxanthoma-elasticum-like papillary dermal elastolysis</article-title><source>J. Eur. Acad. Dermatol. Venereol.</source><year>1998</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>175</fpage><lpage>178</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9553919</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B6-dermatopathology-12-00015"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>K.G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bercovitch</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dill</surname><given-names>S.W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Robinson-Bostom</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Acquired disorders of elastic tissue, part II: Decreased elastic tissue</article-title><source>J. Am. Acad. Dermatol.</source><year>2004</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>165</fpage><lpage>185</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaad.2004.03.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15280835</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B7-dermatopathology-12-00015"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rongioletti</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rebora</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Fibroelastolytic patterns of intrinsic skin aging: Pseudoxanthoma-elasticum-like papillary dermal elastolysis and white fibrous papulosis of the neck</article-title><source>Dermatology</source><year>1995</year><volume>191</volume><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000246478</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8589477</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B8-dermatopathology-12-00015"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bhawan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Labadie</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Solares</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Photoaging versus intrinsic aging: A morphologic assessment of facial skin</article-title><source>J. Cutan. Pathol.</source><year>1995</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>154</fpage><lpage>159</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-0560.1995.tb01399.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7560349</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B9-dermatopathology-12-00015"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fabre</surname><given-names>V.C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lear</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reichlin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hodge</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Callen</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Twenty percent of biopsy specimens from sun-exposed skin of normal young adults demonstrate positive immunofluorescence</article-title><source>Arch. Dermatol.</source><year>1991</year><volume>127</volume><fpage>1006</fpage><lpage>1011</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archderm.1991.01680060080008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2064397</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B10-dermatopathology-12-00015"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nishikawa</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>White fibrous papulosis of the neck: A new clinicopathologic entity?</article-title><source>J. Am. Acad. Dermatol.</source><year>1989</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>1073</fpage><lpage>1077</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0190-9622(89)70135-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2666457</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B11-dermatopathology-12-00015"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gencoglan</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ceylan</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kazandi</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>White fibrous papulosis of the neck</article-title><source>Cutan. Ocul. Toxicol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/15569527.2010.521223</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20954818</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B12-dermatopathology-12-00015"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Robinson-Bostom</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Papillary dermal elastosis: A unique elastic tissue disorder or an unusual manifestation of pseudoxanthoma elasticum-like papillary dermal elastolysis?</article-title><source>J. Cutan. Pathol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>1010</fpage><lpage>1013</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-0560.2008.01183.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19210582</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B13-dermatopathology-12-00015"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gambichler</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Mid-dermal elastolysis revisited</article-title><source>Arch. Dermatol. Res.</source><year>2010</year><volume>302</volume><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00403-009-1004-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19936772</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B14-dermatopathology-12-00015"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Foering</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Torbeck</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>M.P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Saedi</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Treatment of pseudoxanthoma elasticum-like papillary dermal elastolysis with nonablative fractional resurfacing laser resulting in clinical and histologic improvement in elastin and collagen</article-title><source>J. Cosmet. Laser Ther.</source><year>2018</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>382</fpage><lpage>384</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14764172.2017.1358457</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28759289</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig position="float" id="dermatopathology-12-00015-f001"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Dome-shaped skin-colored papules and plaques over the lateral neck. (<bold>B</bold>) Marked improvement after treatment.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="dermatopathology-12-00015-g001" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="dermatopathology-12-00015-f002"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Biopsy shows a regular orthokeratotic epidermis with increased dermal melanophages (H&#x00026;E, 10&#x000d7;). (<bold>B</bold>) High-power magnification showing attenuated elastic fibers in the papillary dermis (arrow) (H&#x00026;E, 20&#x000d7;).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="dermatopathology-12-00015-g002" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="dermatopathology-12-00015-f003"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Verhoeff Stain (elastic stain) highlights the curved elastic fibers of the reticular dermis. Note the attenuation of the elastic fibers in the papillary dermis (Elastic stain, 20&#x000d7;).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="dermatopathology-12-00015-g003" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="dermatopathology-12-00015-f004"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Von Kossa staining of the tissue sample, highlighting the absence of calcium deposits at the level of the mid-dermis (Von Kossa, 5&#x000d7;).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="dermatopathology-12-00015-g004" position="float"/></fig></floats-group></article>