<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Microb Ecol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Microb Ecol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Microbial Ecology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0095-3628</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1432-184X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer US</publisher-name><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40407874</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12101996</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2546</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00248-025-02546-9</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Light-Driven Changes in Macrophyte Tissue Quality Affect the Composition of Associated Microbial Communities</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Velthuis</surname><given-names>Mandy</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zoccarato</surname><given-names>Luca</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Veraart</surname><given-names>Annelies J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Monaghan</surname><given-names>Michael T.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff7">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Funke</surname><given-names>Elisabeth</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Verdonschot</surname><given-names>Piet</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff8">8</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Grossart</surname><given-names>Hans-Peter</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff9">9</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Hilt</surname><given-names>Sabine</given-names></name><address><email>sabine.hilt@igb-berlin.de</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/01nftxb06</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.419247.d</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2108 8097</institution-id><institution>Leibniz Institute of Freshwater Ecology and Inland Fisheries (IGB), </institution></institution-wrap>Berlin, Germany </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/04qw24q55</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.4818.5</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0791 5666</institution-id><institution>Wageningen University and Research, </institution></institution-wrap>Wageningen, the Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/01g25jp36</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.418375.c</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 1013 0288</institution-id><institution>Netherlands Institute of Ecology (NIOO-KNAW), </institution></institution-wrap>Wageningen, the Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/057ff4y42</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5173.0</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2298 5320</institution-id><institution>Vienna, Core Facility Bioinformatics, </institution><institution>University of Natural Resources and Life Sciences, </institution></institution-wrap>Muthgasse 18, 1190 Vienna, Austria </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/057ff4y42</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5173.0</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2298 5320</institution-id><institution>Vienna, Department of Biotechnology, Institute of Computational Biology, </institution><institution>University of Natural Resources and Life Sciences, </institution></institution-wrap>Muthgasse 18, 1190 Vienna, Austria </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/016xsfp80</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5590.9</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2293 1605</institution-id><institution>Department of Ecology, </institution><institution>Radboud Institute for Biological and Environmental Sciences, Radboud University, </institution></institution-wrap>P.O. Box 9010, 6500 GL Nijmegen, the Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff7"><label>7</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/046ak2485</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.14095.39</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2185 5786</institution-id><institution>Institut F&#x000fc;r Biologie, </institution><institution>Freie Universit&#x000e4;t Berlin, </institution></institution-wrap>Berlin, Germany </aff><aff id="Aff8"><label>8</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/04dkp9463</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.7177.6</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 8499 2262</institution-id><institution>University of Amsterdam, </institution></institution-wrap>Amsterdam, the Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff9"><label>9</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/03bnmw459</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.11348.3f</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0942 1117</institution-id><institution>Potsdam University, </institution></institution-wrap>Potsdam, Germany </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>23</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>23</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>88</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>52</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>8</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Microbial biofilms are important components in macrophyte decomposition, and their composition depends on the decomposition stage and host plant quality. Here, we investigated how macrophyte tissue quality (i.e., C:N:P stoichiometry and phenolic contents) influences epiphytic microbial biofilms during litter decomposition. Consecutive experiments were conducted to (1) modify the C:N:P stoichiometry and phenolic content of the freshwater macrophyte <italic>Elodea nuttallii</italic> by manipulating light and nutrient availability and (2) test how the modified tissue quality affected epiphytic microbial biofilm diversity and community composition before and during macrophyte decomposition. Our results showed that shading led to lower C:N ratios (28.6 to 12.6) and higher phenolic content (10.8 to 19.2&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/mg dry weight). Simultaneously, shading affected the epiphytic bacterial and fungal community composition, and these shifts correlated with the macrophyte C:N ratio. While no effects of macrophyte tissue quality on decomposition rates were observed, the epiphytic bacterial community composition on the litter was significantly affected by light treatment, time, and their interaction. Bacterial community composition shifted from a high abundance of Comamonadaceae to a more diverse community over time. Overall bacterial diversity was lower on the litter grown in the shaded mesocosms. Fungal diversity and community composition during litter decomposition were not affected by litter quality. Overall, our results reveal a structuring role of macrophyte tissue quality on its associated microbial biofilm and uniquely show a continuation of light-driven changes in epiphytic bacterial community composition after exposure. We conclude that light-driven changes in C:N stoichiometry are a crucial factor in shaping epiphytic microbial communities during macrophyte decomposition.</p><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1007/s00248-025-02546-9.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Bacterial 16S</kwd><kwd>Ecological stoichiometry</kwd><kwd><italic>Elodea nuttallii</italic></kwd><kwd>Fungal LSU</kwd><kwd>Macrophyte decomposition</kwd><kwd>Phenolic content</kwd><kwd>Epiphytic biofilm</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>International IGB fellowship program 'Frontiers in Freshwater Science'</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/501100003246</institution-id><institution>Nederlandse Organisatie voor Wetenschappelijk Onderzoek</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>Veni.202.053</award-id></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Leibniz-Institut f&#x000fc;r Gew&#x000e4;sser&#x000f6;kologie und Binnenfischerei (IGB) im Forschungsverbund Berlin e.V. (3473)</institution></funding-source></award-group><open-access><p>Open Access funding enabled and organized by Projekt DEAL.</p></open-access></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Springer Science+Business Media, LLC, part of Springer Nature 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Submerged macrophytes are key elements of organic carbon (C) cycling in freshwater ecosystems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. Decomposition of macrophyte detritus is relevant for both C burial [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>] and greenhouse gas emissions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. The relationships between microbial communities in freshwater ecosystems and the functioning of those systems are often closely intertwined [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Epiphytic microbial biofilms, for instance, are known to affect decomposition of macrophyte detritus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. Existing studies of epiphytic microbial biofilms focus primarily on bacterial and algal components [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>], and more recently, on their fungal community component [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. A large variety of bacterial classes are represented in epiphytic biofilms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Generally, bacterial diversity is higher on macrophytes than in the surrounding water [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. Biofilms can also host a diverse community of fungi [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>], and while these organisms play an important role in macrophyte decomposition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>], their community composition and ecology has been less frequently studied.</p><p id="Par3">Microbial diversity and community composition of epiphytic biofilms are highly variable, and dependent on time, environmental conditions, as well as organic matter composition of the host plant [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. Environmental stress can have a destabilizing effect on microbial communities, leading to decreased diversity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Macrophytes can contain and exude polyphenols [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>], which can have antimicrobial properties [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>] and alter the bacterial community composition of macrophyte biofilms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. In a similar manner, the elemental composition of primary producers in general is often used as a food quality predictor for higher trophic levels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. Bacterial assemblages in lakes are relatively phosphorus (P)-rich compared to environmental concentrations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>], indicating that macrophytes with a low C:P ratio could pose a more suitable environment for bacterial growth. Similar investigations on the role of macrophyte stoichiometry and metabolites for epiphytic fungal diversity are lacking for freshwater habitats.</p><p id="Par4">Both the elemental and the polyphenolic content of freshwater macrophytes can vary depending on their environmental conditions. For instance, macrophyte C:N and C:P ratios are dependent on environmental nutrient availability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. The effect of light availability on macrophyte tissue stoichiometry is debated in the scientific literature with examples of increased [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>] and decreased [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>] C:N ratios under shaded conditions, as well as no obvious light effects on macrophyte tissue stoichiometry [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Phenolic content can vary significantly between and within macrophyte species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>] and are among other environmental variables dependent on light availability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. How light- and nutrient-driven changes in macrophyte quality influence structure and functions of microbial biofilms on living and decaying macrophytes remains to be investigated.</p><p id="Par5">Here, two consecutive experiments were conducted to (1) modify the C:N:P stoichiometry and phenolic content of a submerged macrophyte by a full factorial combination of light and nutrient availability and (2) test how the modified tissue quality affected microbial macrophyte decomposition under field conditions. The freshwater macrophyte <italic>Elodea nuttallii</italic> was chosen as a model species due to the widespread occurrence in its native (North America) and invasive (most European countries, China, Japan, T&#x000fc;rkiye, and the Philippines) range where it can form large monospecific stands with high biomass [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>], its flexible tissue nutrient stoichiometry [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>], and the presence of phenolic substances in its tissue [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. In our experiments, the potential effects of the modified tissue quality on the diversity of the epiphytic microbial biofilm on <italic>E. nuttallii</italic> were evaluated. We hypothesized in the first experiment that tissue carbon (C):nitrogen (N) and C:P ratios decrease under high nutrient availability, while phenolic content is elevated under high light conditions. Under low light conditions, macrophytes may need to invest in more N-rich chlorophyll molecules [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>], thus leading to decreased C:N ratio. We hypothesized in the second experiment that decomposition rates of <italic>E. nuttallii</italic> decrease with increasing carbon:nutrient ratios as well as with increasing phenolic content. Additionally, we anticipated that differences in the biofilm bacterial and fungal community composition and diversity during decomposition are related to macrophyte tissue quality. In general, microbial diversity is hypothesized to be impoverished under environmental stress(i.e., decreased light availability).</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Experimental Modification of Macrophyte Tissue Quality</title><p id="Par6"><italic>E. nuttallii</italic> was grown in outdoor mesocosms (66 L water and 24 L sediment) with distinct nutrient and light treatments. The two sediment nutrient treatments consisted of 10 and 100% pond soil and were achieved by mixing commercial pond soil (FloraGard Vertriebs-GmbH, Germany) and sand, according to Velthuis et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>] (Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). The mixed sediment was topped by a 1 cm layer of sand to provide a barrier for nutrient leaching from sediments into the water. The mesocosms were filled with tap water and half of them were covered with a green mesh shade cloth to achieve a light reduction of 78 &#x000b1;&#x02009;3.5% (mean &#x000b1;&#x02009;SD) at the water surface (measured with a spherical PAR sensor (QSPL2101, Biospherical Instruments, USA)). The experiment was performed in a full-factorial design (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;= 3) for a period of 2&#x000a0;months (from 15 June to 15 August 2018). To prevent excessive phytoplankton growth in the mesocosms, 5 L of water was refreshed twice a week from 26 th of July onwards. Detailed information on the experimental setup is included in the supplementary methodology.</p><p id="Par7">After 2&#x000a0;months, the aboveground <italic>E. nuttallii</italic> biomass was harvested by cutting the stems just above the sediment surface. In the lab, the plants were carefully rinsed with tap water to remove any loosely attached algae. From each mesocosm, one plant tip (the top 5&#x000a0;cm) of a randomly selected <italic>E. nuttallii</italic> plant was weighed and freeze-dried for the determination of phenolic content, and one plant tip was weighed and frozen at &#x02212;&#x02009;80 &#x000b0;C for the analysis of microbial community composition. The remaining plant material, as well as the removed attached algae, was dried at 60 &#x000b0;C for 3&#x000a0;days and weighed. The plant material was then stored dry and in the dark for the decomposition experiment. The relative growth rate (RGR) was calculated as in Velthuis et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>].</p><p id="Par8">The phenolic content was determined by the extraction of polyphenols from powdered, freeze-dried (1&#x02013;4 mg) plant material [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. The samples were incubated with 1&#x000a0;mL of 80% ethanol at 80 &#x000b0;C for 10 min and centrifuged for another 10 min at 10.000 rpm to separate the supernatant from the plant pellet. SDS/TEA solution (1% (w/v) and 5% (v/v), respectively) and a 0.01 M FeCl<sub>3</sub> reagent were added to the supernatant in a 2:1 volume ratio. For the SDS/TEA solution, 2&#x000a0;g of sodium dodecyl sulfate (SDS) was dissolved in 190 mL demineralized water and mixed with 10 mL Triethanolamine (TEA). To create the ferrous chloride solution, 0.27 g of iron(III) chloride hexahydrate was dissolved in 100 mL 0.01 M HCl. Absorption at 510 nm was measured on a microtiter plate reader (BioTek, Bad Friedrichshall, Germany) using a tannic acid calibration curve as a reference. The P content was determined by combusting 1&#x02013;2 mg of dry plant material at 550 &#x000b0;C for 30 min and converting all organic P to PO<sub>4</sub><sup>3&#x02212;</sup> by digestion with a 2.5% (w/v) persulfate solution for 30 min at 121 &#x000b0;C. Thereafter, PO<sub>4</sub><sup>3&#x02212;</sup> was measured colorimetrically on a QuAAtro39 Auto-Analyzer (SEAL Analytical Ltd. Southampton, UK). The C and N contents were determined on a Vario Micro Cube elemental analyzer (Elementar Langenselbold, Germany).</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Macrophyte Decomposition Under Field Conditions</title><p id="Par9">Microbial decomposition of <italic>E. nuttallii</italic> aboveground biomass was determined using a litter bag method. Polyester litter bags of 6&#x02009;&#x000d7; 10 cm and 300 &#x000b5;m mesh size were filled with 0.1 g of dried <italic>E. nuttallii</italic> biomass. These litter bags were placed in five 50 &#x000d7;&#x02009;50 cm PVC-coated galvanized wire mesh cages with 2.5 cm mesh size (to exclude most herbivores and to facilitate retrieval at individual time points with limited disturbance of the remaining litter bags). Each cage contained 12 litter bags with <italic>E. nuttallii</italic> litter material. To correct for possible periphyton growth on and erosion of the litter bags, two empty litter bags were included in each cage as a control. The cages were deployed on the sediment of Lake M&#x000fc;ggelsee at 2&#x000a0;m depth (52&#x000b0;26&#x02032;51.4&#x02033; N 13&#x000b0;38&#x02032;51.6&#x02033; E) on the 5&#x02009;th of August 2019. After 7, 14, 28, 42, and 58 days, one of the cages was retrieved from the field location, and the litter bags were brought into the lab for further processing. Upon arrival in the lab, DNA samples were taken from the contents of the litter bags by swabbing them with a sterile cotton swab. This swab was flash frozen in liquid nitrogen and stored at &#x02212;&#x02009;80 &#x000b0;C until further processing for microbial sequencing analysis. Thereafter, the outside of the bags was rinsed with deionized water to remove any macroinvertebrates, and its contents were dried at 60 &#x000b0;C for 72 h and weighed. The mass loss of the litter bags with <italic>E. nuttallii</italic> biomass was corrected for the mass loss of the empty litter bags (0.01 &#x000b1;&#x02009;0.72%, <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;= 10).</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Community Composition and Diversity of the Microbial Biofilm</title><p id="Par10">To quantify the microbial community grown on the plants in the mesocosms, frozen plants were swabbed with a sterile cotton swab, in a similar manner to the swabs from the litter bag samples as described above. DNA was extracted according to Nercessian et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. In short, each sample (i.e., the tip of the cotton swab) was mixed with 0.5 g of each 0.1 and 0.7 mm zirconia-silica beads, 750 &#x000b5;L extraction buffer (10% CTAB in 1.6 M NaCl and 240 mM potassium phosphate buffer at pH 8.0, mixed in a 1:1 ratio), 75 &#x000b5;L 10% sodium dodecyl sulfate, and 75 &#x000b5;L 10% N-lauroylsarcosin solution. To this mixture, 750 &#x000b5;L phenol&#x02013;chloroform-isoamyl alcohol (25:24:1) was added, and the samples were vortexed for 35 s at 6.0 m/s (FastPrep-24&#x02122; 5G, Bio-Connect, Huissen, The Netherlands). After centrifugation at 14,000 g for 10 min at 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, 500 &#x000b5;L of the upper phase was recovered and further mixed with 500 &#x000b5;L chloroform-isoamyl alcohol (24:1). After another round of centrifugation at 14,000 g for 10 min at 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, the upper phase was mixed with 2 volumes of PEG buffer (30% PEG 6000 in 1.6 M NaCl) and 1 &#x000b5;L of LPA and incubated at room temperature in the dark for 2&#x000a0;h. After centrifugation at 17,000 g for 10 min at 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, the precipitated DNA was recovered by removing the supernatant. This pellet was washed with 800 &#x000b5;L ice-cold 70% ethanol, centrifuged at 17,000 g for 10 min at 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. After discarding the supernatant, the pellet was dissolved in 30 &#x003bc;L PCR water and stored at &#x02212;&#x02009;80 &#x000b0;C until further analysis.</p><p id="Par11">For DNA samples from the growth experiment, PCR amplification (oligonucleotide primers in Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>), library preparation, and sequencing (300-bp paired-end reads, Illumina Miseq v3 sequencing kit) of the bacterial 16S V5-V6 region of the rRNA gene and the fungal LSU rRNA gene regions were carried out by LGC Genomics GmbH (Berlin, Germany). For the decomposition experiment, bacterial 16S PCR amplification and sequencing-library preparation steps were performed at the Berlin Center for Genomics in Biodiversity Research on an automated workstation Biomek i7 hybrid (Beckman Coulter GmbH, Krefeld, Germany) in two PCR steps and using dual indexing, as described by Warter et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. Fungal LSU was PCR-amplified and sequenced as follows: a first PCR (96 &#x000b0;C for 30 s; 20 cycles of 96 &#x000b0;C for 30 s, 50 &#x000b0;C for 30 s, 72 &#x000b0;C for 60 s; 72 &#x000b0;C for 3&#x000a0;min) was carried out using 10 ng template DNA, 1 &#x003bc;L of each primer (10 &#x000b5;M), 2.5 &#x003bc;L mi-Taq Crystal buffer, and 0.2 &#x003bc;L polymerase (both Mi-Taq Only, Metabion International AG, Planegg/Steinkirchen, Germany), 0.5 &#x003bc;L dNTP-Mix and 0.25 &#x003bc;L 100 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub> (Metabion International AG) and RO-filtered water for a total reaction volume of 25 &#x003bc;L. A second PCR (96 &#x000b0;C for 30 s; 20 cycles of 96 &#x000b0;C for 30 s, 55 &#x000b0;C for 30 s, 72 &#x000b0;C for 60 s; 72 &#x000b0;C for 5&#x000a0;min) was performed using 1 &#x000b5;L PCR product from the first step as a template. PCR products were purified using a magnetic bead protocol (Agencourt AMPure XP, Beckman Coulter, Indianapolis, IN, USA) following the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. DNA concentration was measured using a Quantus fluorometer and the QuantiFluor dsDNA System (Promega, Madison, WI, USA), and all PCR products were normalized to a concentration of 5&#x000a0;ng/&#x003bc;L. An indexing PCR (95 &#x000b0;C for 2&#x000a0;min; 8 cycles of 95 &#x000b0;C for 20 s, 52 &#x000b0;C for 30 s, 72 &#x000b0;C for 30 s; 72 &#x000b0;C for 3&#x000a0;min) added unique 12-bp inline sequence barcodes (Nextera Index Kit, Illumina, San Diego, CA, USA) to each sample using 10 &#x003bc;L of PCR product mixed with 5 &#x003bc;L reaction buffer and 0.25 &#x003bc;L polymerase (both Herculase II Fusion DNA Polymerase, Agilent), 0.25 &#x003bc;L dNTP-Mix (25 mM each, Agilent), 0.625 &#x003bc;L each of index primers P5 and P7, and 1 &#x003bc;L DMSO and RO-filtered water. PCR products were purified twice and quantified as above. All samples were then pooled in equimolar amounts and sequenced (300-bp paired-end reads, Illumina MiSeq v3 sequencing kit, 600 cycles) at the Berlin Center for Genomics in Biodiversity Research. Due to insufficient fungal DNA yield from samples of day 14 and 28 of the light treatment, these were omitted from further analysis.</p><p id="Par12">The resulting sequences were analyzed with the DADA2 bioinformatics workflow [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. After visual inspection of the quality of the bacterial 16S sequences, forward reads were trimmed at a length of 230 and 280 bp for the growth and decomposition experiment, respectively, while reverse reads were all trimmed at a length of 200 bp, with maximum expected errors (maxEE) of 2 (function <italic>filterAndTrim</italic>). Fungal LSU sequences were trimmed with a minimal read length of 50 bp, maximum read length of 210 bp, and a maxEE of 2. The reads were denoised (function <italic>dada</italic>, <italic>pool</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;<italic>TRUE</italic>) and merged, and any chimeras were removed (function <italic>removeBimeraDenovo</italic>). Around 60% of raw reads were maintained and used for downstream analyses (Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>). Taxonomy was assigned for the obtained amplicon sequence variants (ASVs) using Silva v138.1 and Eukaryome LSU v1.9.2 databases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. As we were specifically interested in fungal LSU sequences, ASVs classified to other kingdoms were omitted from further analysis (52 and 37% of growth and decomposition sequences, respectively). Similarly, 16S ASVs that were classified as Archaea (&#x0003c; 1% for both growth and decomposition sequences) were omitted from further analysis. The accuracy of the taxonomic identification is summarized in Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Statistics</title><p id="Par13">All statistical analyses were carried out in R [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. Plant parameters (relative growth rate, phenolic content, C:N:P stoichiometry, and elemental composition) were tested for effects of nutrient treatment, light treatment, and their interaction using two-way ANOVA models (function <italic>aov</italic>). Models were tested for normality by visual examination of the residuals, and data was transformed when necessary. Litter decomposition was described with a two-phase model [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>] to obtain estimates for the decomposition rate <italic>k</italic> and recalcitrant fraction <italic>s</italic> (function <italic>nlsLM</italic>. Differences in the fraction of remaining dry weight in the litter bags over time were tested using a three-way ANOVA model (including nutrient treatment, light treatment, and time; function <italic>aov</italic>).</p><p id="Par14">ASV diversity for both bacterial and fungal communities was calculated using the bias-corrected Chao1 index with the function <italic>estimateR</italic> from the vegan package [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>] and tested for treatment effects in the same manner as the plant parameters. Differences in microbial community composition were assessed by testing the Bray&#x02013;Curtis dissimilarity matrix for treatment effects with a Permutational Multivariate Analysis of Variance (PERMANOVA; <italic>adonis2</italic> function, vegan package). Furthermore, general patterns and clustering were assessed using distance-based redundancy analysis (dbRDA; function <italic>capscale</italic>, vegan package). In this analysis, Bray&#x02013;Curtis distances were related to the nutrient and light treatments in a first model and to <italic>E. nuttallii</italic> quality characteristics (phenolic content, C:N, and C:P ratio) in a second model. The resulting models were tested for significance (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c; 0.05) using a permutation test with 999 permutations (function <italic>anova</italic>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec8"><title>Experimental Modification of Macrophyte Growth and Tissue Quality</title><p id="Par15">Throughout the growth experiment, mean (&#x000b1; SD) temperature was 19.66 &#x000b1;&#x02009;2.37 &#x000b0;C, pH 7.99 &#x000b1;&#x02009;0.23, and oxygen concentrations 8.32 &#x000b1;&#x02009;1.47 mg/L (see Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref> for experimental conditions). Relative growth rates of <italic>E. nuttallii</italic> were significantly higher at high light availability (0.01 &#x000b1;&#x02009;0.003) compared to shaded conditions (&#x02212; 0.01 &#x000b1;&#x02009;0.006, Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a, Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). There was a significant interaction between light and nutrient treatments (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). In the high nutrient treatments, the negative effects of shading on macrophyte growth were stronger than under low nutrient conditions (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Growth and tissue quality (mean &#x000b1;&#x02009;SE) of aboveground biomass of <italic>Elodea nuttallii</italic> grown in high and low sediment nutrient conditions in outdoor mesocosms, with (<bold>a</bold>) relative growth rate (RGR), (<bold>b</bold>) total phenolic content (TPC), (<bold>c</bold>) molar C:N ratio, and (<bold>d</bold>) molar C:P ratio. Light treatments include full light (&#x025cc;) and shaded (&#x025cf;) conditions, and letters indicate significant pairwise differences</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="248_2025_2546_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Effects of nutrient treatment and light treatment and their interaction on growth, elemental composition, and phenolic content of <italic>Elodea nuttallii</italic> (two-way ANOVA). Bacterial (16S rRNA gene) and fungal (LSU rRNA gene) community composition was tested with a PERMANOVA test on Bray&#x02013;Curtis distances</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left" colspan="3"><italic>F</italic> values</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Factor</th><th align="left">Nutrient treatment</th><th align="left">Light treatment</th><th align="left">Nutrient<bold> * </bold>light treatment</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="4"><italic>Plant parameters</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Relative growth rate</td><td char="." align="char">5.29&#x002d9;</td><td char="." align="char"><bold>141.19***</bold></td><td char="." align="char"><bold>8.71*</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Total phenolic content</td><td char="." align="char">2.18</td><td char="." align="char"><bold>35.43***</bold></td><td char="." align="char">0.066</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C:N</td><td char="." align="char">1.17</td><td char="." align="char"><bold>22.17**</bold></td><td char="." align="char">1.02</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C:P</td><td char="." align="char">0.14</td><td char="." align="char">0.08</td><td char="." align="char">0.10</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C content</td><td char="." align="char">2.02</td><td char="." align="char">0.002</td><td char="." align="char">1.41</td></tr><tr><td align="left">N content</td><td char="." align="char">0.004</td><td char="." align="char"><bold>48.69***</bold></td><td char="." align="char">0.28</td></tr><tr><td align="left">P content</td><td char="." align="char">0.025</td><td char="." align="char">0.022</td><td char="." align="char">0.003</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4"><italic>Microbial parameters</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Bacterial ASV diversity</td><td char="." align="char">0.02</td><td char="." align="char">1.17</td><td char="." align="char">2.86</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Fungal ASV diversity</td><td char="." align="char">2.98</td><td char="." align="char">2.54</td><td char="." align="char">0.08</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Bacterial community composition</td><td char="." align="char">1.16</td><td char="." align="char"><bold>2.20***</bold></td><td char="." align="char">1.14</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Fungal community composition</td><td char="." align="char">0.90</td><td char="." align="char"><bold>2.13**</bold></td><td char="." align="char">0.99</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Significant <italic>F</italic>-values are indicated in bold, with ***<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c; 0.001, **<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c; 0.01, *<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c; 0.05, &#x002d9;<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c; 0.10</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par16">Phenolic content in macrophyte tissue was significantly higher under shaded conditions (19.2 &#x000b1;&#x02009;2.9 versus 10.8 &#x000b1;&#x02009;2.0 &#x000b5;g mg DW<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), while C:N ratios were significantly lower (12.6 &#x000b1;&#x02009;2.7 versus 28.6 &#x000b1;&#x02009;7.9; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Concurrent to the changes in C:N ratios, the N content of <italic>E. nuttallii</italic> was significantly higher under shaded conditions (6.77 &#x000b1;&#x02009;0.88 mmol g DW<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) compared to high light availability (3.09 &#x000b1;&#x02009;0.77 mmol g DW<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>; Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). No effects of light treatment on C:P ratios, nor on C and P contents were observed. Furthermore, no effects of nutrient treatment on any of the measured growth or quality parameters of the plants were detected. The observed changes in phenolic content and C:N ratio were significantly correlated with each other (Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>) in the sense that macrophyte tissues with high C:N ratios contained low phenolic content (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,10)</sub>&#x02009;= 10.46, <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x02009;= 0.46, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;= 0.009).</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Linking Microbial Community Composition to Macrophyte Tissue Quality During the Growth Experiment</title><p id="Par17">In the growth experiment, 1507 bacterial ASVs were retrieved from the biofilm of <italic>E. nuttallii</italic> and were classified as Pseudomonadota (55%), Bacteroidota (15%), Actinomycetota (7%), and Bdellovibrionota (6%) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a). The remaining sequences were allocated to various low-abundance (&#x0003c; 5%) bacterial phyla, with 1% of sequences not classified to any bacterial phylum. For the fungal community, 312 ASVs were revealed in our analysis and belonged to Ascomycota (34%), Basidiomycota (29%), Chytridiomycota (11%), and Mucoromycota (10%) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b). Remaining sequences belonged to various low-abundant fungal phyla (&#x0003c; 5%), and 11% of the sequences could not be assigned with the Eukaryome database. Microbial alpha diversity did not differ between nutrient or light treatments for both bacterial and fungal communities (Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>, Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Relative abundance of the bacterial (<bold>a</bold>) and fungal (<bold>b</bold>) phyla in the <italic>Elodea nuttallii</italic> growth experiment. Each panel represents three replicates of a unique combination of nutrient and light treatment, with low (N0) and high (N1) nutrient treatments and shaded (L0) and full light (L1) treatments. Unknown sequences are indicated with NA. Bacterial phyla with a low abundance (&#x0003c; 0.5%) were grouped into the category &#x0201c;Other&#x0201d;</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="248_2025_2546_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p><p id="Par18">Potential differences between treatments in bacterial and fungal community composition were visualized and related to the environmental parameters measured in the growth experiment. For both bacterial and fungal datasets, light treatment significantly affected the community composition (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,6)</sub>&#x02009;= 2.09, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;= 0.004, and <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,6)</sub>&#x02009;= 2.33, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;= 0.007, respectively), while no other measured environmental factors showed any correlation (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). These results aligned with Permutational Multivariate Analysis of Variance (PERMANOVA) on Bray&#x02013;Curtis distances, which showed significant differences in community composition between light treatments (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Under shaded conditions, the relative abundance of the bacterial family Methylophilaceae increased (Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>). For the fungal community, relative abundance of Saksenaeaceae increased in the shaded treatment at the expense of Cladosporiaceae (Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref>). Interestingly, when experimental light and nutrient treatment were not included as explanatory factors, differences in bacterial community composition significantly correlated with <italic>E. nuttallii</italic> C:N ratio (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,8)</sub>&#x02009;= 1.65, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;= 0.04). Similarly, differences in fungal community composition showed significant correlations with <italic>E. nuttallii</italic> C:N ratio (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,8)</sub>&#x02009;= 2.04, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;= 0.006) and C:P ratio (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,8)</sub>&#x02009;= 1.85, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;= 0.02).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Distance-based Redundancy Analysis results of bacterial (<bold>a</bold>) and fungal (<bold>b</bold>) community composition on <italic>Elodea nuttallii</italic>. Significant parameters are indicated by solid arrows and different nutrient (high (N1) and low (N0)) and light (full light (L1), shaded (L0)) treatments are indicated by color</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="248_2025_2546_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Macrophyte Decomposition Under Field Conditions</title><p id="Par19">Decomposition of <italic>E. nuttallii</italic> in eutrophic Lake M&#x000fc;ggelsee occurred rapidly. The percentage of remaining biomass declined significantly over time, and no effects of light or nutrient treatment on this decline was observed (Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S6</xref>; Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Across treatments, the percentage of recalcitrant material (<italic>s</italic>) was 17.9 &#x000b1;&#x02009;1.1% (mean &#x000b1;&#x02009;SD). Decomposition rates <italic>k</italic> were on average 0.122 &#x000b1;&#x02009;0.007 day<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> across all treatments.
<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Effects of nutrient treatment, light treatment, time, and their interactions on <italic>Elodea nuttallii</italic> decomposition and microbial diversity during the decomposition experiment in Lake M&#x000fc;ggelsee (three-way ANOVA). Bacterial (16S rRNA gene) and fungal (LSU rRNA gene) community compositions were tested with a PERMANOVA test on Bray&#x02013;Curtis distances</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left" colspan="5"><italic>F</italic> values</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Factor</th><th align="left">%DW remaining</th><th align="left">BacterialASVdiversity(log<bold>-</bold>transformed)</th><th align="left">Bacterial community compositi<bold>on</bold></th><th align="left">Fungal ASV diversity (log-transformed)</th><th align="left">Fungal community composition</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Nutrient treatment</td><td char="." align="char">0.00</td><td char="." align="char">1.53</td><td char="." align="char">1.28</td><td char="." align="char"><bold>3.47&#x002d9;</bold></td><td char="." align="char">1.11</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Light treatment</td><td char="." align="char">0.00</td><td char="." align="char"><bold>8.00**</bold></td><td char="." align="char"><bold>7.44***</bold></td><td char="." align="char"><bold>3.39&#x002d9;</bold></td><td char="." align="char"><bold>1.60&#x002d9;</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Time</td><td char="." align="char"><bold>57.04***</bold></td><td char="." align="char"><bold>19.24***</bold></td><td char="." align="char"><bold>23.53***</bold></td><td char="." align="char">1.34</td><td char="." align="char"><bold>11.38***</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Nutrient treatment * light treatment</td><td char="." align="char">0.20</td><td char="." align="char">0.56</td><td char="." align="char">1.24</td><td char="." align="char">0.82</td><td char="." align="char">1.14</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Nutrient treatment * time</td><td char="." align="char">0.05</td><td char="." align="char">0.38</td><td char="." align="char">0.94</td><td char="." align="char">0.87</td><td char="." align="char">1.16</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Light treatment * time</td><td char="." align="char">0.03</td><td char="." align="char">1.30</td><td char="." align="char"><bold>2.06*</bold></td><td char="." align="char">1.35</td><td char="." align="char">1.37</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Nutrient treatment * light treatment * time</td><td char="." align="char">0.01</td><td char="." align="char">1.39</td><td char="." align="char">0.76</td><td char="." align="char">0.46</td><td char="." align="char">1.06</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Significant results are indicated in bold, with ***<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c; 0.001, **<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c; 0.01, *<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c; 0.05, &#x002d9;<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c; 0.10</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Biofilm Microbial Community Composition During Macrophyte Decomposition</title><p id="Par20">While no effects of light or nutrient treatment on macrophyte decomposition rates were observed under field conditions, bacterial ASV diversity significantly increased over time and was lower on the decomposing plants previously grown in the shaded mesocosm treatment (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>a). The most abundant bacterial phyla were Pseudomonadota (40%), Bacteroidota (25%), Bdellovibrionota (8%), and Myxococcota (6%) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>a). The remaining 21% of sequences were allocated to various non-abundant (&#x0003c; 5%) bacterial phyla.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Bacterial (<bold>a</bold>) and fungal (<bold>b</bold>) alpha diversity, expressed as the bias-corrected Chao1 index (mean &#x000b1;&#x02009;SE) over time during decomposition of <italic>Elodea nuttallii</italic> in Lake M&#x000fc;ggelsee grown on low and high nutrient availability. Light treatments include full light (&#x025cc;) and shaded (&#x025cf;) condition. Note that no fungal diversity data is available for day 14 and 28 in the light treatment due to insufficient DNA yield</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="248_2025_2546_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig><fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Mean relative abundance of bacterial (<bold>a</bold>) and fungal (<bold>b</bold>) phyla over time during decomposition of <italic>Elodea nuttallii</italic> in Lake M&#x000fc;ggelsee (sample size varies between 1 and 3). Each panel represents a unique combination of nutrient and light treatment, with low (N0) and high (N1) nutrient treatments and shaded (L0) and full light (L1) treatments. Unknown sequences are indicated with NA. Note that no fungal community composition data is available for day 14 and 28 in the light treatment due to insufficient DNA yield</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="248_2025_2546_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p><p id="Par21">Over time, the bacterial community composition shifted from a high abundance of Comamonadaceae (Pseudomonadota) to a more diverse bacterial community (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>a, Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S7</xref>). Patterns and clustering of the bacterial community composition were assessed using dbRDA (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). The overall model was significant (<italic>F</italic><sub>(3,54)</sub>&#x02009;= 10.55, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;= 0.001), and differences in bacterial community composition were significantly related to both light, sampling date, and their interaction (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Distance-based Redundancy Analysis (dbRDA) results of bacterial (<bold>a</bold>) and fungal (<bold>b</bold>) community composition during the decomposition of <italic>Elodea nuttallii</italic>. Different nutrient and light treatments are indicated by color (see Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>) and sampling dates by symbols. The first dbRDA axis is related to changes in community composition over time, whereas the effect of light treatment is visualized by the second dbRDA axis. Significant parameters (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c; 0.10) are indicated by solid arrows. Note that light treatment was marginally significant (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;= 0.08) in the fungal community composition (<bold>b</bold>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="248_2025_2546_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p><p id="Par22">The fungal community composition during macrophyte decomposition was significantly affected by time and displayed a marginally significant effect of light treatment (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, significant dbRDA model; <italic>F</italic><sub>(3,39)</sub>&#x02009;= 4.61, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;= 0.001). The most abundant phyla, similar to the growth experiment, were Mucoromycota (29%), Chytridiomycota (21%), and Ascomycota (11%) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>b). Twenty percent were allocated to various fungal phyla, and 19% of the sequences could not be assigned with the Eukaryome database. The initial community contained a high abundance of Saksenaeaceae (Mucoromycota), and the proportion of unknown sequences increased over time (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>b, Fig. S8). Fungal ASV diversity was not affected by nutrient treatment, light treatment, nor by sampling time (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>b).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par23">Understanding the effects of macrophyte tissue quality on their microbial decomposition is important, as quality can vary strongly depending on environmental conditions. In our experiments, light rather than nutrient availability altered macrophyte tissue nutrient stoichiometry and phenolic content, partially confirming our first hypothesis. As expected, the altered macrophyte tissue quality affected the fungal and bacterial community composition of epiphytic microbial biofilms. Surprisingly, no effects on macrophyte decomposition rates were observed. Lower light availability in freshwater ecosystems due to processes related to global change, such as eutrophication, brownification, or species invasions, may thus affect both macrophyte tissue quality and their associated microbial community structure. Ecosystem functioning such as macrophyte decomposition may still remain unchanged due to counteracting effects of tissue stoichiometry and polyphenols or functional redundancies in microbial communities.</p><sec id="Sec13"><title>Macrophyte Tissue Quality in Response to Changes in Nutrient and Light Availability</title><p id="Par24">Plants can adapt to low light conditions by investing more in N-rich chlorophyll compounds to enhance light acquisition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. In an experiment by Twilley and Barko [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>], shaded conditions led to increased chlorophyll contents in three freshwater macrophytes. This may explain why shaded conditions led to increased N contents and decreased C:N ratios in <italic>E. nuttallii</italic>, though chlorophyll content was not measured. Under full light conditions, similar N content has been observed in a previous study using the same species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>].</p><p id="Par25">In contrast to our hypotheses, C:N:P stoichiometry was unaffected by nutrient treatments, and shaded conditions led to increased phenolic content. These observations contradict previous research, where increased phenolic content under high light availability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>] and decreased C:P ratios with high nutrient availability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>] were observed. A possible explanation for this discrepancy could be the observed overall low growth rates of <italic>E. nuttallii</italic> in the experiment, and, in particular, the negative growth rates under the shaded conditions. These low growth rates could reduce stress by nutrient limitation and thereby avoid stoichiometric shifts. Similarly, growth stagnation under shaded conditions may have led to a relative buildup of phenolic content compared to the full light conditions, where plants may have invested in growth instead of secondary metabolite synthesis. The hypothesized light-driven increase of phenolic contents was based on studies in <italic>Myriophyllum spicatum</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>] and the observed light-driven decrease in phenolic contents in <italic>Elodea nuttallii</italic> could thus indicate species-specific differences as well. In general, terrestrial literature suggests that slow-growing shade-tolerant plant species typically have a higher phenolic content [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>], which fits with our experimental findings. Overall, our experimental results point to the dependence of macrophyte responses on variations in light and nutrient conditions and highlight the need for further research to better understand and predict phenolic acid synthesis in aquatic macrophytes.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Effects of Macrophyte Tissue Quality on Decomposition</title><p id="Par26">Previous studies have observed that both tissue stoichiometry and phenolic content of submerged macrophytes can affect their decomposition under field conditions. Faster decomposition rates are, for instance, reported for freshwater macrophytes with lower C:N ratios [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Alternatively, plants with higher phenolic content decompose slower, as illustrated, for instance, in salt marsh vegetation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. However, changes in tissue quality do not always lead to changes in decomposition rates, as Smith and Bradford [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>] found no difference in decomposition rates of single species grass litter with different N content. In this study, no differences in decomposition rates between <italic>E. nuttallii</italic> plants were observed, despite the manipulated differences in both C:N ratio and phenolic content. Possibly, the lack of changes in decomposition rates of <italic>E. nuttallii</italic> of different quality in our study may be explained by a simultaneous increase in phenolic content and decrease in C:N ratio under shaded conditions. Alternatively, the changes in microbial community composition observed in our experimental setup during decomposition may have counteracted any changes in decomposition rates due to a high functional redundancy in their effects on macrophyte decomposition. As interspecific differences related to C:N:P stoichiometry in decomposition rates can be observed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>], intraspecific differences in C:N and phenolic content in our study were either not strong enough to elicit a response in decomposition rates, or these parameters are less important on an intraspecific level to drive decomposition rates. Whether any of these hypothesized processes are major causes of our experimental findings remains an open question and would be an interesting avenue for future research.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Macrophyte Tissue Quality Altered Microbial Community Composition</title><p id="Par27">Both nutrient and light treatments affected bacterial and fungal community composition in epiphytic biofilms, and the effects of the light treatment during the growth experiment continued during the following decomposition experiment. As no effects of experimental treatments on ASV diversity were observed (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>), these findings indicate an ASV (i.e., species) replacement in the bacterial community. It should be noted that during the growth experiment, attached algae were present on the macrophytes, and their biomass responses to the light treatments was similar as their host plants (Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref>). As attached algae can release exudates that affect microbial community composition and abundance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>], the observed changes in biofilm composition may be the result of both macrophytes and their attached algae. An earlier study on epiphytic bacterial communities on the macrophyte <italic>Cabomba caroliniana</italic> did not reveal any differences in ASV richness across a range of shading treatments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. The experimental effects of the light treatment persisted during macrophyte decomposition, as epiphytic bacterial ASV diversity and community composition differed significantly between light treatments. To our knowledge, this is the first demonstration of a continuation of the selecting effects of light on epiphytic microbial community composition after exposure.</p><p id="Par28">Bacterial communities in epiphytic biofilms in all experiments were dominated by Pseudomonadota (formerly known as Proteobacteria), which are a diverse phylum of gram-negative bacteria commonly observed in freshwater ecosystems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. In particular, the families Comamonadaceae and Methylophilaceae dominated the bacterial community composition during the growth experiment (Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>). The first family is diverse and commonly observed as a dominant bacterial group in oxic freshwater habitats [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. Methylophilaceae, on the other hand, are a phylogenetically small group of methylotrophic bacteria which can be associated with the turnover of single-carbon compounds from phytoplankton blooms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>], and their presence in macrophyte biofilms has been described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. During the initial phase in the decomposition experiment, characterized by fast litter decomposition, the bacterial community composition was dominated by Comamonadaceae as well. When decomposition rates decreased and the recalcitrant fraction was reached, this community was replaced by a more diverse bacterial assemblage (Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S7</xref>). In particular, the Saprospiraceae family made up a larger proportion at the end of the decomposition experiment. This bacterial family is known for its role in the breakdown of complex organic compounds [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>], and its presence in decomposition of recalcitrant litter is thus consistent. It is possible that the shift in the bacterial community on the decomposing macrophytes toward the Saprospiraceae indicates a beneficial selective environment for their proliferation.</p><p id="Par29">The fungal community in our experiments mainly consisted of Saksenaeaceae (Figs. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S8</xref>), a family within the Mucoromycota, of which <italic>Saksenaea oblongispora</italic> was the dominant species during macrophyte decomposition. In a laboratory setting, this species is able to grow on a large range of carbon sources compared to other fungi within the Mucoromycota [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Its hypothesized associations with decomposition processes are reinforced here by its presence during macrophyte decomposition in Lake M&#x000fc;ggelsee. During the growth experiment, shading led to a significantly altered fungal community as the proportion of unknown fungal sequences increased and the relative abundances of Aspergillaceae, Mycosphaerellaceae, and Psathyrellaceae decreased (Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref>). These changes in fungal community composition were correlated with light-driven changes in macrophyte stoichiometry (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). As there is an overall lack of data on the effects of litter stoichiometry on aquatic fungi [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>], these results contribute to our collective understanding of the link between macrophyte stoichiometry and its associated fungal community composition.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par30">We conclude that changes in light availability, a common phenomenon in freshwater environments during processes, such as eutrophication and brownification, significantly affect <italic>E. nuttallii</italic> tissue quality and their epiphytic bacterial and fungal biofilm composition during macrophyte decomposition. These alterations in macrophyte tissue quality and their associated biofilm may indicate either a high functional redundancy of diverse epiphytic microbial communities or were simply not sufficient to illicit changes in macrophyte decomposition rates. Nonetheless, our findings indicate that C:N:P stoichiometry of litter material, rather than phenolic content, appears to be a crucial factor in shaping the microbial communities during decomposition.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="248_2025_2546_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><caption><p>Supplementary file1 (DOCX 543 KB)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors thank Solvig Pinnow, Femke van Beersum, Nico Helmsing, Jonas Peters, Sarah Krocker, Liu Liu, Sarah Sparmann, Susan Mbedi, and Sven Teurlincx for their help with setting up, carrying out, and analyzing the experiment. Furthermore, the authors would like to thank Jason Woodhouse for valuable discussions on the content of this work.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author Contribution</title><p>MV, HG and SH conceived the ideas and designed the methodology; MV and EH collected the data; MV and LZ analyzed the data and MV led the writing of the manuscript. All authors contributed critically to the drafts and gave final approval for publication.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>Open Access funding enabled and organized by Projekt DEAL. The work of MV was funded by the International IGB Fellowship Program &#x0201c;Frontiers in Freshwater Science&#x0201d; of the Leibniz Institute of Freshwater Ecology and Inland Fisheries and NWO-Veni grant 202.053.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data Availability</title><p>The data and R scripts that support the findings of this paper&#x000a0;are&#x000a0;publicly available within the DANS Data Station Life Sciences at&#x000a0;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://dans.knaw.nl/en/life-sciences/">https://dans.knaw.nl/en/life-sciences/</ext-link>, with the following&#x000a0;identifier: 10.17026/LS/IKCDHS.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing Interests</title><p id="Par31">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>&#x000c1;vila</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira-Junior</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Reis</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hester</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Diamantino</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Veraart</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamers</surname><given-names>LPM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kosten</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nascimento</surname><given-names>AMA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The water hyacinth microbiome: link between carbon turnover and nutrient cycling</article-title><source>Microb Ecol</source><year>2019</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>575</fpage><lpage>588</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00248-019-01331-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30706113</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">&#x000c1;vila MP, Oliveira-Junior ES, Reis MP, Hester ER, Diamantino C, Veraart AJ, Lamers LPM, Kosten S, Nascimento AMA (2019) The water hyacinth microbiome: link between carbon turnover and nutrient cycling. Microb Ecol 78:575&#x02013;588<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30706113</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bakker</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Nolet</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Experimental evidence for enhanced top-down control of freshwater macrophytes with nutrient enrichment</article-title><source>Oecologia</source><year>2014</year><volume>176</volume><fpage>825</fpage><lpage>836</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00442-014-3047-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25194349</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Bakker ES, Nolet BA (2014) Experimental evidence for enhanced top-down control of freshwater macrophytes with nutrient enrichment. Oecologia 176:825&#x02013;836<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25194349</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Banks</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name><surname>Frost</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biomass loss and nutrient release from decomposing aquatic macrophytes: effects of detrital mixing</article-title><source>Aquat Sci</source><year>2017</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>881</fpage><lpage>890</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00027-017-0539-y</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Banks LK, Frost PC (2017) Biomass loss and nutrient release from decomposing aquatic macrophytes: effects of detrital mixing. Aquat Sci 79:881&#x02013;890</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barko</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Filbin</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influences of light and temperature on chlorophyll composition in submersed freshwater macrophytes</article-title><source>Aquat Bot</source><year>1983</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>249</fpage><lpage>255</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0304-3770(83)90072-4</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Barko JW, Filbin GJ (1983) Influences of light and temperature on chlorophyll composition in submersed freshwater macrophytes. Aquat Bot 15:249&#x02013;255</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Blaschke</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Beutler</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jenett-Siems</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Siems</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hilt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Seasonal and interannual dynamics of polyphenols in Myriophyllum verticillatum and their allelopathic activity on Anabaena variabilis</article-title><source>Aquat Bot</source><year>2009</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>110</fpage><lpage>116</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aquabot.2009.03.005</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Bauer N, Blaschke U, Beutler E, Gross EM, Jenett-Siems K, Siems K, Hilt S (2009) Seasonal and interannual dynamics of polyphenols in Myriophyllum verticillatum and their allelopathic activity on Anabaena variabilis. Aquat Bot 91:110&#x02013;116</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boedeltje</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Smolders</surname><given-names>AJP</given-names></name><name><surname>Roelofs</surname><given-names>JGM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Combined effects of water column nitrate enrichment, sediment type and irradiance on growth and foliar nutrient concentrations of Potamogeton alpinus</article-title><source>Freshw Biol</source><year>2005</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>1537</fpage><lpage>1547</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2427.2005.01426.x</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Boedeltje G, Smolders AJP, Roelofs JGM (2005) Combined effects of water column nitrate enrichment, sediment type and irradiance on growth and foliar nutrient concentrations of Potamogeton alpinus. Freshw Biol 50:1537&#x02013;1547</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brothers</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hilt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Attermeyer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Grossart</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><name><surname>Kosten</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lischke</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Mehner</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Scharnweber</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#x000f6;hler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A regime shift from macrophyte to phytoplankton dominance enhances carbon burial in a shallow, eutrophic lake</article-title><source>Ecosphere</source><year>2013</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1890/ES13-00247.1</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Brothers SM, Hilt S, Attermeyer K, Grossart HP, Kosten S, Lischke B, Mehner T, Meyer N, Scharnweber K, K&#x000f6;hler J (2013) A regime shift from macrophyte to phytoplankton dominance enhances carbon burial in a shallow, eutrophic lake. Ecosphere 4:1&#x02013;17</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Callahan</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>McMurdie</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>AJA</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DADA2: high-resolution sample inference from Illumina amplicon data</article-title><source>Nat Methods</source><year>2016</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>581</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.3869</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27214047</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Callahan BJ, McMurdie PJ, Rosen MJ, Han AW, Johnson AJA, Holmes SP (2016) DADA2: high-resolution sample inference from Illumina amplicon data. Nat Methods 13:581<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27214047</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>CDK</given-names></name><name><surname>Urmi-K&#x000f6;nig</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A revision of the genus <italic>Elodea</italic> (Hydrocharitaceae)</article-title><source>Aquat Bot</source><year>1985</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>156</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0304-3770(85)90084-1</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Cook CDK, Urmi-K&#x000f6;nig K (1985) A revision of the genus <italic>Elodea</italic> (Hydrocharitaceae). Aquat Bot 21:111&#x02013;156</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cronin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lodge</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of light and nutrient availability on the growth, allocation, carbon/nitrogen balance, phenolic chemistry, and resistance to herbivory of two freshwater macrophytes</article-title><source>Oecologia</source><year>2003</year><volume>137</volume><fpage>32</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00442-003-1315-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12820064</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Cronin G, Lodge DM (2003) Effects of light and nutrient availability on the growth, allocation, carbon/nitrogen balance, phenolic chemistry, and resistance to herbivory of two freshwater macrophytes. Oecologia 137:32&#x02013;41<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12820064</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crump</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Attached bacterial populations shared by four species of aquatic angiosperms</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2008</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>5948</fpage><lpage>5957</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.00952-08</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18676705</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Crump BC, Koch EW (2008) Attached bacterial populations shared by four species of aquatic angiosperms. Appl Environ Microbiol 74:5948&#x02013;5957<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18676705</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Danger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gessner</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x000e4;rlocher</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ecological stoichiometry of aquatic fungi: current knowledge and perspectives</article-title><source>Fungal Ecol</source><year>2016</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>100</fpage><lpage>111</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.funeco.2015.09.004</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Danger M, Gessner MO, B&#x000e4;rlocher F (2016) Ecological stoichiometry of aquatic fungi: current knowledge and perspectives. Fungal Ecol 19:100&#x02013;111</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Paula</surname><given-names>CCP</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x000e1;rta</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rejm&#x000e1;nkov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kom&#x000e1;rkov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohoutov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Sirov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of macrophyte-associated microbiomes in lacustrine wetlands: an example of the littoral zone of lake Atitlan, Guatemala</article-title><source>Hydrobiologia</source><year>2024</year><volume>851</volume><fpage>1637</fpage><lpage>1655</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10750-022-05043-z</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">de Paula CCP, B&#x000e1;rta J, Rejm&#x000e1;nkov&#x000e1; E, Kom&#x000e1;rkov&#x000e1; J, Lin Q, Kohoutov&#x000e1; I, Sirov&#x000e1; D (2024) The role of macrophyte-associated microbiomes in lacustrine wetlands: an example of the littoral zone of lake Atitlan, Guatemala. Hydrobiologia 851:1637&#x02013;1655</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dudt</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Shure</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The influence of light and nutrients on foliar phenolics and insect herbivory</article-title><source>Ecology</source><year>1994</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>86</fpage><lpage>98</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/1939385</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Dudt JF, Shure DJ (1994) The influence of light and nutrients on foliar phenolics and insect herbivory. Ecology 75:86&#x02013;98</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Erhard</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Allelopathic activity of Elodea canadensis and Elodea nuttallii against epiphytes and phytoplankton</article-title><source>Aquat Bot</source><year>2006</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>203</fpage><lpage>211</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aquabot.2006.04.002</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Erhard D, Gross EM (2006) Allelopathic activity of Elodea canadensis and Elodea nuttallii against epiphytes and phytoplankton. Aquat Bot 85:203&#x02013;211</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grasset</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Abril</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Mendon&#x000e7;a</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Roland</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Sobek</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The transformation of macrophyte-derived organic matter to methane relates to plant water and nutrient contents</article-title><source>Limnol Oceanogr</source><year>2019</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>1737</fpage><lpage>1749</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/lno.11148</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31598008</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Grasset C, Abril G, Mendon&#x000e7;a R, Roland F, Sobek S (2019) The transformation of macrophyte-derived organic matter to methane relates to plant water and nutrient contents. Limnol Oceanogr 64:1737&#x02013;1749<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31598008</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential response of tellimagrandin II and total bioactive hydrolysable tannins in an aquatic angiosperm to changes in light and nitrogen</article-title><source>Oikos</source><year>2003</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>497</fpage><lpage>504</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1034/j.1600-0706.2003.12666.x</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Gross EM (2003) Differential response of tellimagrandin II and total bioactive hydrolysable tannins in an aquatic angiosperm to changes in light and nitrogen. Oikos 103:497&#x02013;504</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hagerman</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Choosing appropriate methods and standards for assaying tannin</article-title><source>J Chem Ecol</source><year>1989</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>1795</fpage><lpage>1810</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF01012267</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24272183</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Hagerman AE, Butler LG (1989) Choosing appropriate methods and standards for assaying tannin. J Chem Ecol 15:1795&#x02013;1810<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24272183</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Halvorson</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Barry</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lodato</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Findlay</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Francoeur</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuehn</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Periphytic algae decouple fungal activity from leaf litter decomposition via negative priming</article-title><source>Funct Ecol</source><year>2019</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>188</fpage><lpage>201</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1365-2435.13235</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31673197</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Halvorson HM, Barry JR, Lodato MB, Findlay RH, Francoeur SN, Kuehn KA (2019) Periphytic algae decouple fungal activity from leaf litter decomposition via negative priming. Funct Ecol 33:188&#x02013;201<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31673197</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Harmon ME, Silver WL, Fasth B, Chen HUA, Burke IC, Parton WJ, Hart SC, Currie WS, Lidet (2009) Long-term patterns of mass loss during the decomposition of leaf and fine root litter: an intersite comparison. Global Change Biol 15:1320-1338</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hempel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Grossart</surname><given-names>H-P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Community composition of bacterial biofilms on two submerged macrophytes and an artificial substrate in a pre-alpine lake</article-title><source>Aquat Microb Ecol</source><year>2009</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>79</fpage><lpage>94</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3354/ame01353</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Hempel M, Grossart H-P, Gross E (2009) Community composition of bacterial biofilms on two submerged macrophytes and an artificial substrate in a pre-alpine lake. Aquat Microb Ecol 58:79&#x02013;94</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hernandez</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>David</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Menges</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Searcy</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Afkhami</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Environmental stress destabilizes microbial networks</article-title><source>ISME J</source><year>2021</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>1722</fpage><lpage>1734</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41396-020-00882-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33452480</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">Hernandez DJ, David AS, Menges ES, Searcy CA, Afkhami ME (2021) Environmental stress destabilizes microbial networks. ISME J 15:1722&#x02013;1734<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33452480</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hilt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Brothers</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeppesen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Veraart</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kosten</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Translating regime shifts in shallow lakes into changes in ecosystem functions and services</article-title><source>Bioscience</source><year>2017</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>928</fpage><lpage>936</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/biosci/bix106</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Hilt S, Brothers S, Jeppesen E, Veraart AJ, Kosten S (2017) Translating regime shifts in shallow lakes into changes in ecosystem functions and services. Bioscience 67:928&#x02013;936</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hilt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghobrial</surname><given-names>MGN</given-names></name><name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In situ allelopathic potential of Myriophyllum verticillatum (Haloragaceae) against selected phytoplankton species</article-title><source>J Phycol</source><year>2006</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>1189</fpage><lpage>1198</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1529-8817.2006.00286.x</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">Hilt S, Ghobrial MGN, Gross EM (2006) In situ allelopathic potential of Myriophyllum verticillatum (Haloragaceae) against selected phytoplankton species. J Phycol 42:1189&#x02013;1198</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kolmakova</surname><given-names>OV</given-names></name><name><surname>Gladyshev</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Fonvielle</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ganzert</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hornick</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Grossart</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of zooplankton carcasses degradation on freshwater bacterial community composition and implications for carbon cycling</article-title><source>Environ Microbiol</source><year>2019</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>34</fpage><lpage>49</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1462-2920.14418</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30246449</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="journal">Kolmakova OV, Gladyshev MI, Fonvielle JA, Ganzert L, Hornick T, Grossart HP (2019) Effects of zooplankton carcasses degradation on freshwater bacterial community composition and implications for carbon cycling. Environ Microbiol 21:34&#x02013;49<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30246449</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR26" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Levi</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Starnawski</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Poulsen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Baattrup-Pedersen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schramm</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Riis</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microbial community diversity and composition varies with habitat characteristics and biofilm function in macrophyte-rich streams</article-title><source>Oikos</source><year>2017</year><volume>126</volume><fpage>398</fpage><lpage>409</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/oik.03400</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26" publication-type="journal">Levi PS, Starnawski P, Poulsen B, Baattrup-Pedersen A, Schramm A, Riis T (2017) Microbial community diversity and composition varies with habitat characteristics and biofilm function in macrophyte-rich streams. Oikos 126:398&#x02013;409</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR27" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lichtenthaler</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Buschmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x000f6;ll</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fietz</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bach</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kozel</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Meier</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahmsdorf</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Photosynthetic activity, chloroplast ultrastructure, and leaf characteristics of high-light and low-light plants and of sun and shade leaves</article-title><source>Photosynth Res</source><year>1981</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>141</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00028752</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24470202</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27" publication-type="journal">Lichtenthaler HK, Buschmann C, D&#x000f6;ll M, Fietz HJ, Bach T, Kozel U, Meier D, Rahmsdorf U (1981) Photosynthetic activity, chloroplast ultrastructure, and leaf characteristics of high-light and low-light plants and of sun and shade leaves. Photosynth Res 2:115&#x02013;141<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24470202</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR28" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>QL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of shading levels on the composition and co-occurrence patterns of bacterioplankton and epibiotic bacterial communities of Cabomba caroliniana</article-title><source>Sci Total Environ</source><year>2021</year><volume>785</volume><fpage>147286</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.147286</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33932676</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28" publication-type="journal">Lu S, He R, Zhao D, Zeng J, Huang X, Li K, Yu Z, Wu QL (2021) Effects of shading levels on the composition and co-occurrence patterns of bacterioplankton and epibiotic bacterial communities of Cabomba caroliniana. Sci Total Environ 785:147286<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33932676</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR29" publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McIlroy</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>DeLong</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><name><surname>Lory</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Stackebrandt</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Family Saprospiraceae</article-title><source>The prokaryotes: other major lineages of bacteria and the Archaea</source><year>2014</year><publisher-loc>Berlin Heidelberg, Berlin, Heidelberg</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name><fpage>863</fpage><lpage>889</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29" publication-type="book">McIlroy SJ, Nielsen PH (2014) The Family Saprospiraceae. In: Rosenberg E, DeLong EF, Lory S, Stackebrandt E, Thompson F (eds) The prokaryotes: other major lineages of bacteria and the Archaea. Springer, Berlin Heidelberg, Berlin, Heidelberg, pp 863&#x02013;889</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR30" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Okuda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishijima</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Hosomi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Okada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Polyphenols and fatty acids responsible for anti-cyanobacterial allelopathic effects of submerged macrophyte Myriophyllum spicatum</article-title><source>Water Sci Technol</source><year>2012</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>993</fpage><lpage>999</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2166/wst.2012.272</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22797226</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30" publication-type="journal">Nakai S, Zou G, Okuda T, Nishijima W, Hosomi M, Okada M (2012) Polyphenols and fatty acids responsible for anti-cyanobacterial allelopathic effects of submerged macrophyte Myriophyllum spicatum. Water Sci Technol 66:993&#x02013;999<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22797226</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR31" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nercessian</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Noyes</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalyuzhnaya</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Lidstrom</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Chistoserdova</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bacterial populations active in metabolism of C<sub>1</sub> compounds in the sediment of Lake Washington, a freshwater lake</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>6885</fpage><lpage>6899</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.71.11.6885-6899.2005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16269723</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR31" publication-type="journal">Nercessian O, Noyes E, Kalyuzhnaya MG, Lidstrom ME, Chistoserdova L (2005) Bacterial populations active in metabolism of C<sub>1</sub> compounds in the sediment of Lake Washington, a freshwater lake. Appl Environ Microbiol 71:6885&#x02013;6899<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16269723</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR32" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Newton</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Eiler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>McMahon</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Bertilsson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A guide to the natural history of freshwater lake bacteria</article-title><source>Microbiol Mol Biol Rev</source><year>2011</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>14</fpage><lpage>49</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/MMBR.00028-10</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21372319</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32" publication-type="journal">Newton RJ, Jones SE, Eiler A, McMahon KD, Bertilsson S (2011) A guide to the natural history of freshwater lake bacteria. Microbiol Mol Biol Rev 75:14&#x02013;49<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21372319</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Oksanen J, Blanchet FG, Kindt R, Legendre P, Minchin PR, O&#x02019;hara R, Simpson GL, Solymos P, Stevens M, Wagner H (2015) Vegan: community ecology package. R Package Version 2.0-10:2013</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR34" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>&#x000d6;zkan</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name><name><surname>Ko&#x000e7;er</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Aksoy</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new invasive neophyte Elodea nuttallii (Planch.) H. St. John for the flora of T&#x000fc;rkiye</article-title><source>BioInvasions Record</source><year>2024</year><volume>13</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>159</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3391/bir.2024.13.1.13</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR34" publication-type="journal">&#x000d6;zkan NG, Ko&#x000e7;er N, Aksoy N (2024) A new invasive neophyte Elodea nuttallii (Planch.) H. St. John for the flora of T&#x000fc;rkiye. BioInvasions Record 13(1):149&#x02013;159</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR35" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paw&#x00142;owska</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Okrasi&#x00144;ska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kis&#x00142;o</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Aleksandrzak-Piekarczyk</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Szatraj</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolatabadi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Muszewska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Carbon assimilation profiles of mucoralean fungi show their metabolic versatility</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2019</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>11864</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-48296-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31413281</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR35" publication-type="journal">Paw&#x00142;owska J, Okrasi&#x00144;ska A, Kis&#x00142;o K, Aleksandrzak-Piekarczyk T, Szatraj K, Dolatabadi S, Muszewska A (2019) Carbon assimilation profiles of mucoralean fungi show their metabolic versatility. Sci Rep 9:11864<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31413281</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR36" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quast</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pruesse</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Yilmaz</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerken</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Schweer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yarza</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Peplies</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gl&#x000f6;ckner</surname><given-names>FO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The SILVA ribosomal RNA gene database project: improved data processing and web-based tools</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2012</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>D590</fpage><lpage>D596</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gks1219</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23193283</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR36" publication-type="journal">Quast C, Pruesse E, Yilmaz P, Gerken J, Schweer T, Yarza P, Peplies J, Gl&#x000f6;ckner FO (2012) The SILVA ribosomal RNA gene database project: improved data processing and web-based tools. Nucleic Acids Res 41:D590&#x02013;D596<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23193283</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">R Core Team (2015) R: a language and environment for statistical computing. R Foundation for statistical computing, Vienna, Austria. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.R-project.org/">https://www.R-project.org/</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR38" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salcher</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Neuenschwander</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Posch</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Pernthaler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The ecology of pelagic freshwater methylotrophs assessed by a high-resolution monitoring and isolation campaign</article-title><source>ISME J</source><year>2015</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>2442</fpage><lpage>2453</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ismej.2015.55</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25942006</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR38" publication-type="journal">Salcher MM, Neuenschwander SM, Posch T, Pernthaler J (2015) The ecology of pelagic freshwater methylotrophs assessed by a high-resolution monitoring and isolation campaign. ISME J 9:2442&#x02013;2453<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25942006</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR39" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>VC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradford</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Do non-additive effects on decomposition in litter-mix experiments result from differences in resource quality between litters?</article-title><source>Oikos</source><year>2003</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>235</fpage><lpage>242</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1034/j.1600-0706.2003.12503.x</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR39" publication-type="journal">Smith VC, Bradford MA (2003) Do non-additive effects on decomposition in litter-mix experiments result from differences in resource quality between litters? Oikos 102:235&#x02013;242</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR40" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smolders</surname><given-names>AJP</given-names></name><name><surname>Vergeer</surname><given-names>LHT</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Der Velde</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Roelofs</surname><given-names>JGM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phenolic contents of submerged, emergent and floating leaves of aquatic and semi-aquatic macrophyte species: why do they differ?</article-title><source>Oikos</source><year>2000</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>307</fpage><lpage>310</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1034/j.1600-0706.2000.910211.x</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR40" publication-type="journal">Smolders AJP, Vergeer LHT, Van Der Velde G, Roelofs JGM (2000) Phenolic contents of submerged, emergent and floating leaves of aquatic and semi-aquatic macrophyte species: why do they differ? Oikos 91:307&#x02013;310</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR41" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stenzel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Rofner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>P&#x000e9;rez</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Sommaruga</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stoichiometry of natural bacterial assemblages from lakes located across an elevational gradient</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>5875</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-06282-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28725017</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR41" publication-type="journal">Stenzel B, Rofner C, P&#x000e9;rez MT, Sommaruga R (2017) Stoichiometry of natural bacterial assemblages from lakes located across an elevational gradient. Sci Rep 7:5875<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28725017</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR42" publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sterner</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Elser</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><source>Ecological stoichiometry: the biology of elements from molecules to the biosphere</source><year>2002</year><publisher-loc>Princeton, U.S.</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR42" publication-type="book">Sterner RW, Elser JJ (2002) Ecological stoichiometry: the biology of elements from molecules to the biosphere. Princeton University Press, Princeton, U.S.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Tedersoo L, Hosseyni Moghaddam MS, Mikryukov V, Hakimzadeh A, Bahram M, Nilsson RH, Yatsiuk I, Geisen S, Schwelm A, Piwosz K, Prous M, Sildever S, Chmolowska D, Rueckert S, Skaloud P, Laas P, Tines M, Jung J-H, Choi JH, Alkahtani S, Anslan S (2024) EUKARYOME: the rRNA gene reference database for identification of all eukaryotes. Database 2024</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR44" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Twilley</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Barko</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The growth of submersed macrophytes under experimental salinity and light conditions</article-title><source>Estuaries</source><year>1990</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>311</fpage><lpage>321</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/1351922</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR44" publication-type="journal">Twilley RR, Barko JW (1990) The growth of submersed macrophytes under experimental salinity and light conditions. Estuaries 13:311&#x02013;321</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR45" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Velthuis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>van Deelen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>van Donk</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bakker</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of temperature and nutrients on carbon:nutrient tissue stoichiometry of submerged aquatic plants: an experiment and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Front Plant Sci</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>655</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2017.00655</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28523005</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR45" publication-type="journal">Velthuis M, van Deelen E, van Donk E, Zhang P, Bakker ES (2017) Impact of temperature and nutrients on carbon:nutrient tissue stoichiometry of submerged aquatic plants: an experiment and meta-analysis. Front Plant Sci 8:655<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28523005</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR46" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Warter</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tetzlaff</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ring</surname><given-names>A-M</given-names></name><name><surname>Christopher</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kissener</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Funke</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Sparmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mbedi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Soulsby</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Monaghan</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Environmental DNA, hydrochemistry and stable water isotopes as integrative tracers of urban ecohydrology</article-title><source>Water Res</source><year>2024</year><volume>250</volume><fpage>121065</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2023.121065</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38159541</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR46" publication-type="journal">Warter MM, Tetzlaff D, Ring A-M, Christopher J, Kissener HL, Funke E, Sparmann S, Mbedi S, Soulsby C, Monaghan MT (2024) Environmental DNA, hydrochemistry and stable water isotopes as integrative tracers of urban ecohydrology. Water Res 250:121065<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38159541</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR47" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wijewardene</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Fohrer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Riis</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epiphytic biofilms in freshwater and interactions with macrophytes: current understanding and future directions</article-title><source>Aquat Bot</source><year>2022</year><volume>176</volume><fpage>103467</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aquabot.2021.103467</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR47" publication-type="journal">Wijewardene L, Wu N, Fohrer N, Riis T (2022) Epiphytic biofilms in freshwater and interactions with macrophytes: current understanding and future directions. Aquat Bot 176:103467</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR48" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name><name><surname>Buchsbaum</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Valiela</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Swain</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Decomposition in salt marsh ecosystems: phenolic dynamics during decay of litter of Spartina alterniflora</article-title><source>Mar Ecol Prog Ser</source><year>1986</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>187</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3354/meps029177</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR48" publication-type="journal">Wilson JO, Buchsbaum R, Valiela I, Swain T (1986) Decomposition in salt marsh ecosystems: phenolic dynamics during decay of litter of Spartina alterniflora. Mar Ecol Prog Ser 29:177&#x02013;187</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR49" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zehnsdorf</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hussner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Eismann</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>R&#x000f6;nicke</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Melzer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Management options of invasive Elodea nuttallii and Elodea canadensis</article-title><source>Limnologica</source><year>2015</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>110</fpage><lpage>117</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.limno.2014.12.010</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR49" publication-type="journal">Zehnsdorf A, Hussner A, Eismann F, R&#x000f6;nicke H, Melzer A (2015) Management options of invasive Elodea nuttallii and Elodea canadensis. Limnologica 51:110&#x02013;117</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR50" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Habitat species pools shape algal and bacterial communities and their correlations</article-title><source>Environ Microbiol Rep</source><year>2019</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>275</fpage><lpage>286</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1758-2229.12754</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30924315</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR50" publication-type="journal">Zhang W, Wang H, Zhang J, Chen J, Shen H, Xie P (2019) Habitat species pools shape algal and bacterial communities and their correlations. Environ Microbiol Rep 11:275&#x02013;286<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30924315</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR51" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>QL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interactions between bacteria and fungi in macrophyte leaf litter decomposition</article-title><source>Environ Microbiol</source><year>2021</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>1130</fpage><lpage>1144</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1462-2920.15261</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33015932</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR51" publication-type="journal">Zhao B, Xing P, Wu QL (2021) Interactions between bacteria and fungi in macrophyte leaf litter decomposition. Environ Microbiol 23:1130&#x02013;1144<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33015932</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR52" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zwart</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Crump</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamst-van Agterveld</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hagen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>S-K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Typical freshwater bacteria: an analysis of available 16S rRNA gene sequences from plankton of lakes and rivers</article-title><source>Aquat Microb Ecol</source><year>2002</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>155</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3354/ame028141</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR52" publication-type="journal">Zwart G, Crump BC, Kamst-van Agterveld MP, Hagen F, Han S-K (2002) Typical freshwater bacteria: an analysis of available 16S rRNA gene sequences from plankton of lakes and rivers. Aquat Microb Ecol 28:141&#x02013;155</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article>