<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39730718</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11681000</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">82434</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-024-82434-3</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Recovery in soil carbon stocks but reduced carbon stabilization after near-natural restoration in degraded alpine meadows</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Guoxing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Xiaoni</given-names></name><address><email>liuxn@gsau.edu.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Yali</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Heguang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>Tong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Zhuoli</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>Hao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Chenglong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Yunjun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Degang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Dong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Yafei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Jiachang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/05ym42410</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411734.4</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1798 5176</institution-id><institution>College of Grassland Science, </institution><institution>Gansu Agricultural University, </institution></institution-wrap>No. 1, Yingmen Village, Anning District, Lanzhou, 730070 Gansu China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/05ym42410</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411734.4</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1798 5176</institution-id><institution>Key Laboratory of Grassland Ecosystem, Ministry of Education, </institution><institution>Gansu Agricultural University, </institution></institution-wrap>Lanzhou, 730070 Gansu China </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Sino-U.S. Centers for Grazing Land Ecosystem Sustainability, Lanzhou, 730070 Gansu China </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>Pratacultural Engineering Laboratory of Gansu Province, Lanzhou, 730070 Gansu China </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label>Grassland Technique Extension Station of Gansu Province, Lanzhou, 730000 Gansu China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>28</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>31124</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>3</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>5</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2024</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Near-natural restoration is acknowledged as an effective strategy for enhancing soil organic carbon (SOC) sequestration in degraded grasslands. However, the alterations in SOC fractions, stability, and relative sequestration capacity after restoration of degraded alpine meadows remain uncertain. In this study, we utilized the degraded alpine meadows on the northeastern edge of the Tibetan Plateau as a research area, with grazing as the control (CK) and restoration of 20 years of banned grazing (BG) and growing season resting grazing (RG). We analyzed the characteristics of SOC, SOC fractions, recalcitrant index (RI), and relative capacity of soil C sequestration (SCS<sub>capacity</sub>) under near-natural restoration measures. The objective of this study was to assess the recovery of SOC following near-natural restoration. The results showed that soil water content (SWC), SOC, soil total nitrogen (TN), and soil total phosphorus (TP) increased, while bulk density (BD) decreased in the degraded alpine meadow after near-natural restoration. In addition, near-natural restoration led to significant increases in particulate organic carbon (POC), readily oxidizable carbon (ROC), dissolved organic carbon (DOC), and microbial biomass carbon (MBC) content (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). The SOC stock significantly increased, while the RI decreased. Compared to RG, BG had a greater increase in SOC stock. The study showed that 20 years of near-natural restoration in degraded alpine meadows mainly enhanced soil active carbon pools, while short-term restoration did not increase soil carbon stability. Therefore, avoiding re-exposure to overgrazing is essential to maintaining the restoration effect.</p></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Tibetan Plateau</kwd><kwd>Alpine meadow</kwd><kwd>Degradation</kwd><kwd>Near-natural restoration measures</kwd><kwd>Soil organic carbon fractions</kwd><kwd>Soil carbon stability</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Grassland ecology</kwd><kwd>Restoration ecology</kwd><kwd>Environmental sciences</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Grassland Monitoring and Evaluation in Gansu Province</institution></funding-source><award-id>GSZYTC-ZCJC-21010</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Xiaoni</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>A New Round of Grassland Reward and Subsidy Benefit Evaluation and Grassland Ecological Evaluation in Gansu Province</institution></funding-source><award-id>XZ20191225</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Xiaoni</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>National Natural Science Foundation of China</institution></funding-source><award-id>32260354</award-id><award-id>32301326</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Dong</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Yafei</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Natural Science Foundation of Gansu Province</institution></funding-source><award-id>20JR10RA525</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Dong</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Self-Listed Provincial Forestry and Grassland Science and Technology Project in 2021</institution></funding-source><award-id>2021kj071</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Jiachang</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Springer Nature Limited 2024</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Soil serves as a critical carbon pool in terrestrial ecosystems, holding more soil organic carbon (SOC) than both vegetation and the atmosphere combined<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. A little reduction in soil carbon may substantially impact atmospheric carbon dioxide (CO<sub>2</sub>) levels, significantly influencing the Earth&#x02019;s climate system<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. Consequently, the restoration of soil organic carbon stocks has become an important topic of current research, especially in degraded ecosystems. Grasslands are the largest terrestrial ecosystem in the world, accounting for about 40% of the land area<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. The global grassland contributes about 34% to the soil organic carbon pools<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>, playing an important role in soil carbon cycle and carbon sequestration<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par3">However, approximately 49% of the world&#x02019;s grasslands have experienced varying degrees of degradation due to the combined pressures of global warming and overgrazing in recent decades<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. Grassland degradation accelerates SOC depletion, especially in alpine meadow ecosystems on the Tibetan Plateau<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. The ecosystem exhibits considerable sensitivity and vulnerability due to its unique natural factors of high altitude, low temperatures, and intense radiation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>. Alpine meadows are an important grassland type on the Tibetan Plateau, playing a crucial role in enhancing carbon sequestration and carbon sink. But its degradation has become increasingly serious due to fragile ecosystems, homogenous vegetation structure, and overgrazing<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par4">Sustained and high-intensity grazing activities in alpine meadows have limited plant regeneration and recovery, resulting in a decrease in vegetation coverage, aboveground biomass (AGB), belowground biomass (BGB), and accumulation of litter<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. These factors reduce the ability of vegetation to protect the topsoil, leading to increased soil exposure, massive decomposition of soil organic matter, and ultimately the loss of soil organic carbon<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. Moreover, local herders frequently utilize animal excrement as fuel, so diminishing the return of carbon to the soil and transforming the soil carbon pools from a &#x0201c;sink&#x0201d; to a &#x0201c;source&#x0201d;<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>. Therefore, the restoration of degraded grassland SOC is crucial for mitigating global climate change and a necessary safeguard for the sustainable development of grasslands.</p><p id="Par5">In response to grassland degradation, scientists have proposed the concept of &#x0201c;near-natural restoration&#x0201d;<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. This methodology emphasizes the &#x0201c;nature-based, return-to-nature&#x0201d; theory, utilizing the self-regulating properties of natural ecosystems to promote the restoration of degraded grasslands<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. Banning grazing (BG) and resting grazing during the growing season (RG) are two commonly practiced near-natural restoration measures<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. The main objectives of these measures are to reduce disturbance, enhance grassland quality, improve soil physicochemical properties, thereby mitigating the depletion of soil carbon pools and increasing the capacity of SOC sequestration in degraded grasslands<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. Unlike BG, RG is closed to grazing throughout the growing season. Livestock forage on plants that have completed their life history, which protects the growing environment of the grassland<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par6">
Currently, scholars use the recalcitrant index (RI) and the relative capacity of soil C sequestration (SCS<sub>capacity</sub>) when assessing the effects of ecological restoration measures on SOC fractions and soil carbon stability<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. The RI could effectively reflect the effects of ecological restoration measures on soil carbon stability, while SCS<sub>capacity</sub> could assess the relative sequestration capacity of SOC<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. However, current research on grassland restoration measures mainly focused on SOC content<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>, and lacked research on the effects of near-natural restoration on SOC fractions and soil carbon stability in degraded alpine meadows. This study selected alpine meadows that had undergone near-natural restoration for 20 years on the northeastern edge of the Tibetan Plateau as research objective, aiming to explore the impact of near-natural restoration measures on SOC fractions and stability. We hypothesized that improvements in vegetation productivity and soil physicochemical properties following near-natural restoration would lead to an increase in the active SOC fractions, thereby increasing SOC stock, but soil carbon stability may not necessarily be improved. The increase in active SOC fractions due to near-natural restoration may lead to a decrease in soil carbon stability. We further utilized the soil active and recalcitrant carbon fractions to calculate the RI and SCS<sub>capacity</sub>, which were used to quantitatively assess the relative capacity of soil carbon sequestration after near-natural restoration.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Variations of vegetation characteristics</title><p id="Par7">The coverage of BG and RG increased by 30% and 29% compared to CK, respectively (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a). The AGB, BGB, and Litter of BG and RG significantly increased compared to CK (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>b&#x02013;d).</p><p id="Par8">
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Variations of vegetation characteristics under different restoration measures. <italic>Note</italic>: Different lowercase letters indicate significant differences between the three restoration measures (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, n&#x02009;=&#x02009;9). <italic>Coverage</italic> vegetation total coverage; <italic>AGB</italic> aboveground biomass, <italic>Litter</italic> litter biomass, <italic>BGB</italic> belowground biomass.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2024_82434_Fig1_HTML" id="d33e456"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Variations of soil properties</title><p id="Par10">Overall, both restoration measures significantly altered soil physicochemical properties (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p><p id="Par11">In the topsoil, the SWC, TN, TP, and C:N were significantly higher in the BG than the CK. Between the two restoration measures, the soil TN content and C:P were significantly higher in the BG compared to the RG.</p><p id="Par12">The physicochemical properties of the subsoil were less affected by the restoration measures compared to the topsoil (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The SWC and soil TP contents in the BG and RG were significantly higher than those in the CK. (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The BD of BG was significantly lower compared to CK (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p><p id="Par13">
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Variations of soil physicochemical properties.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Depth (cm)</th><th align="left">Measures</th><th align="left">SWC (%)</th><th align="left">BD (g cm<sup>&#x02212;3</sup>)</th><th align="left">TN (g kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</th><th align="left">TP (g kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</th><th align="left">C:N</th><th align="left">C:P</th><th align="left">N:P</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">0&#x02013;20</td><td align="left">BG</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">26.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.5<sup>a</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.75&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.05<sup>b</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6.75&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.21<sup>a</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.79&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.04<sup>a</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">13.02&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.75<sup>a</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">111.59&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.81<sup>a</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">8.63&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.38<sup>ab</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">RG</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">23.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.5<sup>b</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.78&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01<sup>b</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6.07&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.12<sup>b</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.82&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.05<sup>a</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">12.21&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.23<sup>ab</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">92.14&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.37<sup>b</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">7.54&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.40<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">CK</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">18.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.8<sup>c</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.04&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.03<sup>a</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">5.79&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.10<sup>b</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.65&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.03<sup>b</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">10.81&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.30<sup>b</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">97.88&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.18<sup>ab</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">9.05&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.41<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">20&#x02013;40</td><td align="left">BG</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">22.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.4<sup>a</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.89&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.03<sup>b</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6.12&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.19<sup>a</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.74&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.06<sup>a</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">10.81&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.38<sup>a</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">93.90&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;7.81<sup>a</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">8.79&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.81<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">RG</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">21.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.5<sup>a</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.98&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02<sup>a</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">5.40&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.14<sup>b</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.62&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.04<sup>a</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">11.85&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.54<sup>a</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">104.27&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.73<sup>a</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">8.97&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.70<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">CK</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">18.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.0<sup>b</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.01&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02<sup>a</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">5.26&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.17<sup>b</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.59&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02<sup>b</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">11.58&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.48<sup>a</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">103.63&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.73<sup>a</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">9.01&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.42<sup>a</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Note: Different lowercase letters indicate significant differences between the three repair methods (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, n&#x02009;=&#x02009;9).</p><p><italic>BG</italic> banned grazing, <italic>RG</italic> rest grazing during the growing season, <italic>CK</italic> grazing, <italic>SWC</italic> soil water content, <italic>BD</italic> bulk density, <italic>TN</italic> total nitrogen, <italic>TP</italic> total phosphorus, <italic>C: N</italic> carbon-to-nitrogen ratio, <italic>C:P</italic> carbon-to-phosphorus ratio, <italic>N:P</italic> nitrogen-to-phosphorus ratio.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Variations of SOC content and SOC stock</title><p id="Par14">In the topsoil, the SOC content significantly increased by 39% and 18% in BG and RG, respectively, compared to CK (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a). In the subsoil, the SOC content significantly increased by 9% under BG compared to CK (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a).</p><p id="Par15">The two restoration measures significantly increased SOC stock (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b). In the topsoil, SOC stock significantly increased by 26% and 13% in BG and RG (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05), respectively, compared to CK (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b). In the subsoil, the SOC stock of BG and RG significantly increased by 9% and 5% (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05), respectively, compared to CK (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b).</p><p id="Par16">
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Comparison of SOC and SOC stock under different restoration measures. <italic>Note</italic>: Different lowercase letters indicate significant differences (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, n&#x02009;=&#x02009;9); <italic>SOC</italic> soil organic carbon, <italic>SOC stock</italic> soil organic carbon stock.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2024_82434_Fig2_HTML" id="d33e818"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>SOC fractions and RI</title><p id="Par18">In the physical classification of the SOC fractions, the POC content showed BG&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;RG&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;CK in the topsoil (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a). In the subsoil, the POC content was significantly higher in the BG than the CK (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). But there was no significant difference between the two restoration measures in the subsoil (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a). Both the two restoration measures showed no significant difference in MOC content compared to the CK (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.05) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>b). Furthermore, the physical RI values exhibited an inverse relationship with POC content. The physical RI significantly decreased after near-natural restoration, with significant differences between BG, RG, and CK (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>c).</p><p id="Par19">In the chemistry classification of the SOC fractions, the soil ROC content was significantly increased for BG and RG compared to CK (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>d). The Non-ROC content showed significant differences between BG and CK (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>e). The chemical RI values exhibited similarities to the physical RI values. The BG and RG were significantly lower compared to the CK (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>f).</p><p id="Par20">In the topsoil, the DOC content of BG and RG increased significantly by 56% and 41%, compared to CK, respectively. There was no significant difference between the DOC content in the subsoil (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>g).</p><p id="Par21">The soil MBC content was significantly increased in the BG and RG (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>h).</p><p id="Par22">
<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Comparison of SOC fractions under different restoration measures. <italic>Note</italic>: Different lowercase letters indicate significant differences (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, n&#x02009;=&#x02009;9); <italic>POC</italic> particulate organic carbon, <italic>MOC</italic> mineral-associated organic carbon, <italic>ROC</italic> readily oxidizable carbon, <italic>Non-ROC</italic> non-readily oxidizable carbon, <italic>RI</italic> POC/MOC or Non-ROC/ROC, <italic>DOC</italic> dissolved organic carbon, <italic>MBC</italic> microbial biomass carbon.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2024_82434_Fig3_HTML" id="d33e917"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par24">The proportions of MOC/SOC and Non-ROC/SOC were 58.5-80.7% and 97.2-98.4%, respectively. This indicated that MOC and Non-ROC collectively constituted a significant proportion of the SOC (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). In the topsoil, the proportions of POC/SOC and ROC/SOC both BG and RG were significantly higher than CK (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). Conversely, the proportions of MOC/SOC and Non-ROC/SOC were significantly lower than in the CK (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). Additionally, the proportions of DOC/SOC in the RG were significantly higher than CK (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). In the subsoil, the proportions of POC/SOC, ROC/SOC, and MBC/SOC in the BG were all significantly higher than CK (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p><p id="Par25">
<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>The proportions of SOC fractions accounting for SOC in different restoration measures.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Depth (cm)</th><th align="left">Measures</th><th align="left">POC/SOC (%)</th><th align="left">MOC/SOC (%)</th><th align="left">ROC/SOC (%)</th><th align="left">Non-ROC/SOC (%)</th><th align="left">DOC/SOC (&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02013;4</sup>)</th><th align="left">MBC/SOC (&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02013;4</sup>)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">0&#x02013;20</td><td align="left">BG</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">40.07&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.81<sup>a</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">58.75&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.80<sup>c</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2.43&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.11<sup>a</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">97.57&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.11<sup>c</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">56.78&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.61<sup>ab</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">81.35&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.75<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">RG</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">30.36&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.19<sup>b</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">68.26&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.19<sup>b</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.96&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.04<sup>b</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">98.04&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.03<sup>b</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">59.40&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.67<sup>a</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">82.31&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.63<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">CK</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">20.06&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.73<sup>c</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">78.16&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.69<sup>a</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.72&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.04<sup>c</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">98.28&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.04<sup>a</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">50.03&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.31<sup>b</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">83.45&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.93<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">20&#x02013;40</td><td align="left">BG</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">21.64&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.29<sup>a</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">76.73&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.23<sup>b</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2.80&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.05<sup>a</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">97.20&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.05<sup>c</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">42.61&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.48<sup>a</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">75.83&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.94<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">RG</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">20.60&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.31<sup>ab</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">77.71&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.28<sup>ab</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2.06&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.08<sup>b</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">97.94&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.08<sup>b</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">42.51&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.71<sup>a</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">74.66&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.41<sup>ab</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">CK</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">17.51&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.54<sup>b</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">80.67&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.53<sup>a</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.64&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.05<sup>c</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">98.35&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.05<sup>a</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">40.17&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.53<sup>a</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">64.60&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.62<sup>b</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Note: Different lowercase letters indicate significant differences (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05).</p><p><italic>SOC</italic> soil organic carbon, <italic>MOC</italic> mineral-associated organic carbon, <italic>POC</italic> particulate organic carbon, <italic>ROC</italic> readily oxidizable carbon, <italic>Non-ROC</italic> non-readily oxidizable carbon, <italic>DOC</italic> dissolved organic carbon, <italic>MBC</italic> microbial biomass carbon.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Relative capacity of soil C sequestration</title><p id="Par26">The implementation of the two restoration measures led to a significant increase in SOC<sub>stock</sub> (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05), whereas there was no significant increase in SCS<sub>capacity</sub> (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).</p><p id="Par27">In topsoil, SCS<sub>stock</sub> of BG and RG was significantly higher than CK (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). This indicated that the relative accumulation of SOC significantly increased following the implementation of the two restoration measures (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). The SCS<sub>RI</sub> showed a consistent pattern in the physical and chemical groups. The SCS<sub>RI</sub> values under BG and RG exhibited significantly lower compared to CK (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05), as shown in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>. Based on the SCS<sub>capacity</sub> of physical components, BG and RG were significantly lower than CK (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). There was no significant difference (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.05) between BG, RG, and CK based on SCS<sub>capacity</sub> of chemical components (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).</p><p id="Par28">In subsoil, the SCS<sub>capacity</sub> based on physical components was not significantly different between BG, RG, and CK, while the SCS<sub>capacity</sub> based on chemical components was significantly lower for BG and RG than CK (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).</p><p id="Par29">
<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Comparative analysis of SOC fraction sequestration capacity based on physical and chemical methods under different restoration measures.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Depth (cm)</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">Measures</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">SCS<sub>stock</sub></th><th align="left" colspan="2">Physical analyses</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Chemistry analyses</th></tr><tr><th align="left">SCS<sub>RI</sub></th><th align="left">SCS<sub>capacity</sub></th><th align="left">SCS<sub>RI</sub></th><th align="left">SCS<sub>capacity</sub></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">0&#x02013;20</td><td align="left">BG</td><td align="left">1.40&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.06<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">0.39&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.05<sup>c</sup></td><td align="left">0.52&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.05<sup>c</sup></td><td align="left">0.71&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.04<sup>c</sup></td><td align="left">1.01&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.09<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">RG</td><td align="left">1.19&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.04<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">0.61&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.08<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">0.70&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.08<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">0.88&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.03<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">1.06&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.07<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">CK</td><td align="left">1<sup>c</sup></td><td align="left">1<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">1<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">1<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">1<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">20&#x02013;40</td><td align="left">BG</td><td align="left">1.09&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">0.81&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.11<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">0.88&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.11<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">0.58&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02<sup>c</sup></td><td align="left">0.64&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.03<sup>c</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">RG</td><td align="left">1.05&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.03<sup>ab</sup></td><td align="left">0.85&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.11<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">0.87&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.08<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">0.80&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.04<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">0.85&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.05<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">CK</td><td align="left">1<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">1<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">1<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">1<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">1<sup>a</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Note: Different lowercase letters indicate significant differences (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05).</p><p><italic>SCS</italic><sub><italic>stock</italic></sub> SOC of restoration/SOC of CK, <italic>SCS</italic><sub><italic>RI</italic></sub> RI of restoration/RI of CK, <italic>SCS</italic><sub><italic>capacity</italic></sub> relative capacity of soil C sequestration.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="Sec9"><title>Effects of near-natural restoration measures on SOC content and stocks</title><p id="Par30">In this study, we found that the SOC content increased significantly following near-natural restoration in degraded alpine meadows. It suggests that BG and RG measures are favorable to the soil carbon sink enhancement in alpine meadows. At the same time, we observed that the BG and RG measures significantly increased vegetation coverage compared to CK (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a). Increased vegetation coverage effectively reduces the bare area of soil, thereby protecting the soil from wind and water erosion. This protective effect prevents the loss of SOC in grassland<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par31">On the other hand, both BG and RG measures significantly increased AGB (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>b). The increase in AGB contributes to the formation of the litter layer (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>c), which serves as a rich source of organic matter input for the soil. BG and RG measures also promoted the formation of well-developed plant root systems (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>d), resulting in greater production of root residue material. The surface litter and plant root residues are gradually decomposed by soil microorganisms and protozoa<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. During this decomposition process, carbon from plant residue is released into the soil, and this released carbon serves as an important source of SOC<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par32">In addition, BG and RG measures significantly reduced soil BD (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Previous studies have shown that soils with lower BD can store more organic matter<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. Since organic matter can move through soil pores, soils exhibiting lower BD usually have more macro-pores, thereby increasing the contact area between soil microorganisms and organic matter. This allowed more organic matter to decompose, thereby increasing SOC contents<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. Consequently, near-natural restoration measures reduced the amount of soil carbon loss and increased carbon input in degraded alpine meadows. These are the main reasons for the increase in SOC content.</p><p id="Par33">The study showed that banned grazing had a significant effect on increasing SOC stocks in degraded grassland<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. This is consistent with the results of this study. The SOC stock significantly increased after the implementation of near-natural restoration measures in degraded alpine meadows (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Effects of near-natural restoration measures on SOC fractions and stability</title><p id="Par34">In this study, BG and RG measures significantly increased soil POC content (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a), but they did not lead to an increase in the more stable MOC content (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>b). BG was more effective in enhancing soil POC content compared to RG (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a). The POC is often defined as an important indicator of the soil active carbon pools and is sensitive to changes in soil quality. Thus it is also more responsive to restoration measures<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>. After near-natural restoration, plant litter is decomposed and enters the soil as POC, which is an important source of SOC<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. The MOC has excellent stability because it is protected by physical and chemical interactions. Microbial breakdown and utilization for MOC is difficult, and consequently, its persistence usually lasts for decades to centuries<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>. Hence, the MOC is less responsive to near-natural restoration measures. The pattern of soil ROC content was similar to that of POC (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>d). The above results showed that near-natural restoration measures mainly increased the active carbon pools of the soil, and BG was more effective compared to RG in degraded alpine meadows.</p><p id="Par35">Notably, the increased soil carbon pools after near-natural restoration, particularly in the active carbon pools, do not necessarily imply an improvement in the long-term sequestration capacity and stability of soil carbon pools<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>. The stability of soil carbon pools is directly related to the quality and sustainability of soil carbon sequestration, which is an important reflection of the function of soil carbon sinks. The RI and SCS<sub>capacity</sub> are usually used to assess the sensitivity of SOC sequestration<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>. They are important for assessing soil carbon pools after near-natural restoration<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. Specifically, following the restoration of alpine meadows, a significant increase in SOC stocks was observed (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b), whereas both physical RI and chemical RI decreased significantly (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>c,f). This was associated with a significant increase in the active carbon pool, whereas the recalcitrant carbon pool remained stable following near natural restoration of degraded alpine meadows. This was attributed to the fact that BG and RG measures facilitate sustained vegetation recovery such as significant increases in AGB, BGB, and Litter biomass and changes in soil structure. Consequently, plant residues that input the soil are more readily decomposed, and the resultant decomposed organic matter accumulates as POC, thereby leading to a decrease in RI values<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. In addition, the active carbon fraction always recovers in a short period of time, but the recovery of the stabilized carbon fraction takes several decades. And plant roots may grow rapidly to take up more nutrients from the active organic carbon fraction<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>. This indicated that near-natural restoration measures significantly increased the active carbon fractions (POC and ROC), but the inert carbon (MOC and Non-ROC) remained stable in the degraded alpine meadow. As a result, RI decreased significantly and SCS<sub>capacity</sub> remained constant or decreased (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p><p id="Par36">In conclusion, the soil active carbon fraction increased significantly and RI decreased significantly after the near-natural restoration of degraded alpine meadows. This indicated that these measures can effectively enhance the SOC content, but the soil carbon stability did not increase. When alpine meadows are disturbed again, this may result in the loss of significant active carbon pools. This is because it has a low stabilizing capacity of the soil carbon pools. Therefore, it is particularly important to avoid overgrazing after restoration. Meanwhile, it was found that BG was more favorable to enhance soil active carbon pools than RG in degraded alpine meadows. The relative sequestration capacity of soil carbon had not been enhanced by either BG or RG. Thus, its carbon pool is relatively unstable. The restoration period in this study was relatively short, spanning only 20 years, and future studies need longer time scales to comprehensively assess the long-term stability characteristics and sequestration capacity of soil carbon pools following near-natural restoration of degraded alpine meadows.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec11" sec-type="conclusion"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par37">After 20 years of near-natural restoration of degraded alpine meadows, both BG and RG significantly increased SOC, POC and ROC contents, but MOC contents were not significantly increased. Meanwhile, the POC and ROC contents in the BG were significantly higher than those in the RG. On the other hand, the relative sequestration capacity of SOC has not improved due to the decline of soil RI. These results indicated that short-term restoration of degraded alpine meadows was mainly accompanied by the accumulation of soil active carbon pools, particularly those that were relatively unstable and vulnerable to disturbance over the short-term. Therefore, it is particularly important to avoid overgrazing again after the near-natural restoration of degraded alpine meadows.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec13"><title>Study site</title><p id="Par38">The study area is located in Wuwei City, Gansu Province, China (37&#x000b0; 11&#x02032; N, 102&#x000b0; 46&#x02032; E), and lies on the northeastern edge of the Tibetan Plateau (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). The climate in the study area resembles that of the Tibetan Plateau, characterized by cold and humid conditions throughout most of the year, along with low air pressure, reduced oxygen levels, intense sunshine, and high levels of ultraviolet radiation. This region is characterized by a continental plateau monsoon climate, with mean annual temperature and precipitation of 0.16&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C and 416.9&#x000a0;mm, respectively. The majority of precipitation falls between July and September in the study area. The duration of the growing season ranges from 120 d to 140 d. The soil type is an alpine chernozem. The grasslands ecosystem is classified as an alpine meadow. The dominant vegetation comprises <italic>Elymus nutans</italic>, <italic>Poa crymophila</italic> and <italic>Kobresia humilis</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>. The animals primarily forage on the leaves and stems of herbaceous plants that have completed their growing cycle during the non-growing season.</p><p id="Par39">
<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Spatial distribution of sampling sites. Note: BG: banned grazing; RG: rest grazing during the growing season; CK: grazing. *Statement. Based on the standard map supervised by the Ministry of Natural Resources of the People&#x02019;s Republic of china [No. GS (2022) 4316] and [No. ZS(2022) 004] retrieved from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bzdt.ch.mnr.gov.cn/browse.html?picId=%224o28b0625501ad13015501ad2bfc0690%22">http://bzdt.ch.mnr.gov.cn/browse.html?picId=%224o28b0625501ad13015501ad2bfc0690%22</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://zrzyt.xizang.gov.cn/fw/zyxz/202004/t20200430/139102.html">http://zrzyt.xizang.gov.cn/fw/zyxz/202004/t20200430/139102.html</ext-link>. The map was created using Arc GIS 10.2 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.esri.com/software/ArcGIS">https://www.esri.com/software/ArcGIS</ext-link>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2024_82434_Fig4_HTML" id="d33e1647"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Experimental design and sample collection</title><p id="Par40">The study site selected for analysis was a moderate-deteriorated alpine meadow<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>, which underwent the &#x0201c;Returning Grazing Land to Grassland&#x0201d; initiative in 2003. The site&#x02019;s natural characteristics, including terrain, slope direction, and steepness, remained consistent throughout the project. The grazing animals present in the area were indigenous Tibetan sheep and yaks. Two types of near-natural restoration measures were implemented, specifically BG and RG. A randomized block experimental design was utilized, with grazed sample plots serving as the control (CK). Three blocks were established, each containing three treatments, resulting in a total of nine sample plots. Each sample plot covered an area of 100&#x000a0;m &#x000d7; 100&#x000a0;m. BG involved no grazing throughout the year, stocking rates: 0 sheep unit hm<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> a<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. RG entailed no grazing from the end of April to the end of September annually, stocking rates: 3.07 sheep unit hm<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> a<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. CK represented continuous grazing throughout the year, stocking rates: 6.13 sheep unit hm<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> a<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>).</p><p id="Par41">Plant community surveys and soil sampling were conducted in mid-August 2022, with three random quadrats (1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;1&#x000a0;m) set up in each sampling plot, maintaining a minimum distance of 50&#x000a0;m between quadrats. A total of 27 quadrats were established (three blocks &#x000d7; three treatments &#x000d7; three quadrats per treatment). Vegetation coverage, AGB, BGB, and litter biomass (Litter) within each quadrat were surveyed. Vegetation coverage was measured using point-intercept sampling, employing a 1&#x000a0;m &#x000d7; 1&#x000a0;m square frame, with 100 sampling points spaced equidistantly within the frame. AGB was measured using the harvest method. Subsequently, within each harvested plot, a root auger (&#x003a6;&#x02009;=&#x02009;90&#x000a0;mm) and a soil auger (&#x003a6;&#x02009;=&#x02009;38&#x000a0;mm) were used to collect belowground biomass and soil samples, respectively, following the soil layers of 0&#x02013;20&#x000a0;cm (topsoil) and 20&#x02013;40&#x000a0;cm (subsoil). Soil samples were collected using the &#x0201c;five-point method&#x0201d;, where every five augers were combined to form one replicate. Three replicates were collected per plot, resulting in a total of 54 soil samples. Soil bulk density (BD) was determined using the &#x0201c;ring cutter method&#x0201d; during the soil sampling process. Roots were separated from the soil using the mesh bag method. All aboveground vegetation, litter, and root samples were killed green at 105&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 30&#x000a0;min, then dried to a constant weight in a 65&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C oven. After drying, the samples were weighed and the biomass was calculated. Soil samples were air-dried, roots and debris were removed, and the samples were sifted through a 2&#x000a0;mm mesh screen before analyzing the soil&#x02019;s physicochemical properties and SOC fractions.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Sample analysis</title><p id="Par42">Soil water content (SWC) was determined by weighing 10&#x000a0;g of wet soil samples and subsequently drying them in an oven at 105&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 24&#x000a0;h. Soil bulk density (BD) was determined using the ring knife method with a volume of 100&#x000a0;cm<sup>3</sup> to collect undisturbed soil samples. Subsequently, the samples were dried in an oven until reaching a constant weight, after which they were weighed<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par43">SOC content was assessed through the oxidation of concentrated sulfuric acid-potassium dichromate and subsequent titration with ferrous sulfate. The soil total nitrogen (TN) content was analyzed using an automatic carbon and nitrogen analyzer (Primacs SNC 100-IC-E; Sklar, Netherlands). The soil total phosphorus (TP) content was employed by the molybdenum-antimony-ascorbic acid colorimetric method<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>. Dissolved organic carbon (DOC) in the soil was extracted using a 0.5&#x000a0;mol L<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> potassium sulfate (K<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>) solution with a soil-water ratio of 1:4. DOC was separated using a 0.45&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m filter membrane and quantified using an automatic carbon and nitrogen analyzer<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>. Microbial biomass carbon (MBC) was quantified using the chloroform fumigation extraction method<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par44">Soil particulate organic carbon (POC) and mineral-associated organic carbon (MOC) content were isolated using wet sieving<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>. 10&#x000a0;g of soil samples were weighed and extracted from a 2&#x000a0;mm mesh screen. The samples were dispersed using 30 mL of a 5&#x000a0;g L<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> solution of sodium hexametaphosphate ((NaPO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>6</sub>) and subjected to agitation in a reciprocating vibrator operating at 90 r min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> for 6&#x000a0;h. Subsequently, the samples were further dispersed with deionized water. The fraction retained on the sieve and the fraction that passed through the sieve were subsequently transferred to a beaker for drying at 60&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, followed by weighing and individual analysis of soil carbon content. Soil POC content (&#x0003e;&#x02009;53&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m) and MOC content (&#x0003c;&#x02009;53&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m) can be determined.</p><p id="Par45">The concentration of readily oxidizable carbon (ROC) was determined through oxidation using 0.02&#x000a0;mol L<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> potassium manganate (KMnO<sub>4</sub>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>. Non-ROC, classified as a non-labile fraction of carbon, was determined by subtracting ROC from SOC.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>SOC sequestration capacity</title><p id="Par46">Zhang et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup> proposed the concept of SCS<sub>capacity</sub>, which can be expressed as follows:<disp-formula id="Equ1"><label>1</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\text{SCS}}_{{{\text{capacity}}}} = {\text{SCS}}_{{{\text{stock}}}} \times {\text{SCS}}_{{{\text{RI}}}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2024_82434_Article_Equ1.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par48">where SCS<sub>stock</sub> and SCS<sub>RI</sub> represent the changes in soil carbon stock and its RI when comparing restored alpine meadow plots to those without restoration. SCS<sub>stock</sub> and SCS<sub>RI</sub> can be calculated as follows:<disp-formula id="Equ2"><label>2</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M2">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\text{SCS}}_{{{\text{stock}}}} = {\text{SOC of restoration}}/{\text{SOC of CK}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2024_82434_Article_Equ2.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula><disp-formula id="Equ3"><label>3</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\text{SCS}}_{{{\text{RI}}}} = {\text{RI of restoration}}/{\text{RI of CK}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2024_82434_Article_Equ3.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula><disp-formula id="Equ4"><label>4</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M4">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\text{RI}} = {\text{MOC}}/{\text{POC or Non-ROC}}/{\text{ROC}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2024_82434_Article_Equ4.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>SOC stock</title><p id="Par52">The &#x0201c;equivalent soil mass&#x0201d; method is used to estimate SOC stock across different layers of a 40&#x000a0;cm soil profile, typically evaluating every 20&#x000a0;cm segment<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>.<disp-formula id="Equ5"><label>5</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M5">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${M}_{soil, i}={BD}_{i}\times {T}_{i}\times 10000$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2024_82434_Article_Equ5.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula><disp-formula id="Equ6"><label>6</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M6">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${SOC}_{stock}=\sum_{i=1}^{n}[{M}_{soil, i}\times {con}_{i}+({M}_{o,i}-{M}_{soil, i})\times {conc}_{i+1}]\times {A}_{i}\times 0.001$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2024_82434_Article_Equ6.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par53">where <italic>M</italic><sub><italic>soil</italic>, <italic>i</italic></sub> is the soil mass (Mg ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) of the <italic>i</italic>th layer (<italic>i</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1, 2, representing the depths of 0&#x02013;40&#x000a0;cm, respectively); BD<sub><italic>i</italic></sub> and T<sub><italic>i</italic></sub> are BD (g cm<sup>&#x02212;3</sup>) and thickness (m) in the <italic>i</italic>th layer, respectively; conc<sub><italic>i</italic></sub> and conc<sub><italic>i</italic>+1</sub> are the concentrations of SOC in the <italic>i</italic>th and <italic>i</italic>&#x02009;+&#x02009;1th layers (g kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), respectively; and <italic>M</italic><sub><italic>o</italic>, <italic>i</italic></sub> is the maximum soil mass from the first layer to the <italic>n</italic>th layer.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par54">The homogeneity of variances in all data sets was assessed using the least significant difference (LSD) test available in the &#x02018;car&#x02019; package<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>, followed by a normality test conducted using Shapiro-Wilk test<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. The analyses were conducted utilizing R version 4.0.3<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>.</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors are grateful for the support of the National Natural Science Foundation of China (32260354, 32301326), Grassland Monitoring and Evaluation in Gansu Province (GSZYTC-ZCJC-21010), Self-Listed Provincial Forestry and Grassland Science and Technology Project in 2021 (2021kj071), A New Round of Grassland Reward and Subsidy Benefit Evaluation and Grassland Ecological Evaluation in Gansu Province (XZ20191225), Natural Science Foundation of Gansu Province (20JR10RA525).</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>G.H. and X.L. conceived this study and designed the experiments. G.H., Y.L., H.X., T.J., Z. Y., H.Q., C. M., Y. W., D.L., Y. S. and J. J. conducted the experiments. G.H. and Y.L. analyzed the data and prepared the figures. G.H. wrote the manuscript. X.L. and D. Z. edited the language. All authors reviewed the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>Data available on reasonable request from corresponding author.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar4" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par56">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Batjes</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Total carbon and nitrogen in the soils of the world</article-title><source>Eur. J. Soil Sci.</source><year>1996</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>151</fpage><lpage>163</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2389.1996.tb01386.x</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Batjes, N. H. Total carbon and nitrogen in the soils of the world. <italic>Eur. J. Soil Sci.</italic><bold>47</bold>, 151&#x02013;163 (1996).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Batjes</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Harmonized soil property values for broad-scale modelling (WISE30sec) with estimates of global soil carbon stocks</article-title><source>Geoderma</source><year>2016</year><volume>269</volume><fpage>61</fpage><lpage>68</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.geoderma.2016.01.034</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Batjes, N. H. Harmonized soil property values for broad-scale modelling (WISE30sec) with estimates of global soil carbon stocks. <italic>Geoderma</italic><bold>269</bold>, 61&#x02013;68 (2016).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bradford</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Managing uncertainty in soil carbon feedbacks to climate change</article-title><source>Nat. Clim. Change</source><year>2016</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>751</fpage><lpage>758</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nclimate3071</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Bradford, M. A. et al. Managing uncertainty in soil carbon feedbacks to climate change. <italic>Nat. Clim. Change</italic><bold>6</bold>, 751&#x02013;758 (2016).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Cotrufo</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Grassland soil carbon sequestration: Current understanding, challenges, and solutions</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2022</year><volume>377</volume><fpage>603</fpage><lpage>608</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.abo2380</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35926033</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Bai, Y. &#x00026; Cotrufo, M. F. Grassland soil carbon sequestration: Current understanding, challenges, and solutions. <italic>Science</italic><bold>377</bold>, 603&#x02013;608 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35926033</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Pilot Analysis of Global Ecosystems: Grassland Ecosystems</source><year>2000</year><publisher-name>World Resources Institute</publisher-name></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="book">White, R. P. et al. <italic>Pilot Analysis of Global Ecosystems: Grassland Ecosystems</italic> (World Resources Institute, 2000).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bardgett</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Combatting global grassland degradation</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Earth Environ.</source><year>2021</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>720</fpage><lpage>735</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s43017-021-00207-2</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Bardgett, R. D. et al. Combatting global grassland degradation. <italic>Nat. Rev. Earth Environ.</italic><bold>2</bold>, 720&#x02013;735 (2021).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>You</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Meta-analysis of the effects of grassland degradation on plant and soil properties in the alpine meadows of the Qinghai-Tibetan Plateau</article-title><source>Glob. Ecol. Conserv.</source><year>2019</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>e00774</fpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Zhang, W., Xue, X., Peng, F., You, Q. &#x00026; Hao, A. Meta-analysis of the effects of grassland degradation on plant and soil properties in the alpine meadows of the Qinghai-Tibetan Plateau. <italic>Glob. Ecol. Conserv.</italic><bold>20</bold>, e00774 (2019).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Impact of restoration measures on plant and soil characteristics in the degraded alpine grasslands of the Qinghai Tibetan Plateau: A meta-analysis</article-title><source>Agric. Ecosyst. Environ.</source><year>2023</year><volume>347</volume><fpage>108394</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.agee.2023.108394</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Li, W. et al. Impact of restoration measures on plant and soil characteristics in the degraded alpine grasslands of the Qinghai Tibetan Plateau: A meta-analysis. <italic>Agric. Ecosyst. Environ.</italic><bold>347</bold>, 108394 (2023).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effect of grassland degradation on aggregate-associated soil organic carbon of alpine grassland ecosystems in the Qinghai-Tibetan Plateau</article-title><source>Eur. J. Soil Sci.</source><year>2020</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>79</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ejss.12835</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Dong, S. et al. Effect of grassland degradation on aggregate-associated soil organic carbon of alpine grassland ecosystems in the Qinghai-Tibetan Plateau. <italic>Eur. J. Soil Sci.</italic><bold>71</bold>, 69&#x02013;79 (2020).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Long-term grazing improved soil chemical properties and benefited community traits under climatic influence in an alpine typical steppe</article-title><source>J. Environ. Manag.</source><year>2023</year><volume>348</volume><fpage>119184</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jenvman.2023.119184</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Zhang, Y. et al. Long-term grazing improved soil chemical properties and benefited community traits under climatic influence in an alpine typical steppe. <italic>J. Environ. Manag.</italic><bold>348</bold>, 119184 (2023).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Growing season grazing promotes the shallow stratification of soil nutrients while non-growing season grazing sequesters the deep soil nutrients in a typical alpine meadow</article-title><source>Geoderma</source><year>2022</year><volume>426</volume><fpage>116111</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.geoderma.2022.116111</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Zhang, Y. et al. Growing season grazing promotes the shallow stratification of soil nutrients while non-growing season grazing sequesters the deep soil nutrients in a typical alpine meadow. <italic>Geoderma</italic><bold>426</bold>, 116111 (2022).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effects of grazing regimes on plant traits and soil nutrients in an alpine steppe, northern Tibetan Plateau</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>e108821</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0108821</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25268517</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Sun, J. et al. Effects of grazing regimes on plant traits and soil nutrients in an alpine steppe, northern Tibetan Plateau. <italic>PLoS ONE</italic><bold>9</bold>, e108821 (2014).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25268517</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Impacts of dung combustion on the carbon cycle of alpine grassland of the North Tibetan Plateau</article-title><source>Environ. Manag.</source><year>2013</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>441</fpage><lpage>449</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00267-013-0107-8</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Xu, Z. et al. Impacts of dung combustion on the carbon cycle of alpine grassland of the North Tibetan Plateau. <italic>Environ. Manag.</italic><bold>52</bold>, 441&#x02013;449 (2013).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Review on soil carbon sequestration potential in grassland ecosystems</article-title><source>Acta Ecol. Sin.</source><year>2015</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>3908</fpage><lpage>3918</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Dai, E., Huang, Y. &#x00026; Zhao, D. Review on soil carbon sequestration potential in grassland ecosystems. <italic>Acta Ecol. Sin.</italic><bold>35</bold>, 3908&#x02013;3918 (2015).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Close-to-nature restoration of degraded alpine grasslands: Theoretical basis and technical approach</article-title><source>Chin. Sci. Bull.</source><year>2020</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>3898</fpage><lpage>3908</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1360/TB-2020-0405</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">He, J. et al. Close-to-nature restoration of degraded alpine grasslands: Theoretical basis and technical approach. <italic>Chin. Sci. Bull.</italic><bold>65</bold>, 3898&#x02013;3908 (2020).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reme&#x00161;</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development and present state of close-to-nature silviculture</article-title><source>J. Landsc. Ecol.</source><year>2018</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2478/jlecol-2018-0010</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Reme&#x00161;, F. Development and present state of close-to-nature silviculture. <italic>J. Landsc. Ecol.</italic><bold>11</bold>, 17&#x02013;32 (2018).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schutz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Close-to-nature silviculture: Is this concept compatible with species diversity?</article-title><source>Forestry</source><year>1999</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>359</fpage><lpage>366</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/forestry/72.4.359</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Schutz, J. Close-to-nature silviculture: Is this concept compatible with species diversity?. <italic>Forestry</italic><bold>72</bold>, 359&#x02013;366 (1999).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new perspective on the concept of grassland management</article-title><source>Chin. Sci. Bull.</source><year>2019</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>1106</fpage><lpage>1113</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1360/N972018-01036</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Wang, D. &#x00026; Wang, L. A new perspective on the concept of grassland management. <italic>Chin. Sci. Bull.</italic><bold>64</bold>, 1106&#x02013;1113 (2019).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Changes in soil organic carbon pools after 10 years of continuous manuring combined with chemical fertilizer in a Mollisol in China</article-title><source>Soil Tillage Res.</source><year>2012</year><volume>122</volume><fpage>36</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.still.2012.02.002</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Ding, X. et al. Changes in soil organic carbon pools after 10 years of continuous manuring combined with chemical fertilizer in a Mollisol in China. <italic>Soil Tillage Res.</italic><bold>122</bold>, 36&#x02013;41 (2012).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The impact of agricultural land use changes on soil organic carbon dynamics in the Danjiangkou Reservoir area of China</article-title><source>Plant Soil</source><year>2013</year><volume>366</volume><fpage>415</fpage><lpage>424</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11104-012-1446-6</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">Cheng, X., Yang, Y., Li, M., Dou, X. &#x00026; Zhang, Q. The impact of agricultural land use changes on soil organic carbon dynamics in the Danjiangkou Reservoir area of China. <italic>Plant Soil</italic><bold>366</bold>, 415&#x02013;424 (2013).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Recovery in soil carbon stock but reduction in carbon stabilization after 56-year forest restoration in degraded tropical lands</article-title><source>For. Ecol. Manag.</source><year>2019</year><volume>441</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foreco.2019.03.037</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Zhang, et al. Recovery in soil carbon stock but reduction in carbon stabilization after 56-year forest restoration in degraded tropical lands. <italic>For. Ecol. Manag.</italic><bold>441</bold>, 1&#x02013;8 (2019).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Does grazing exclusion improve soil carbon and nitrogen stocks in alpine grasslands on the Qinghai-Tibetan Plateau? A meta-analysis</article-title><source>Sustainability</source><year>2020</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>977</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/su12030977</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">Liu, X. et al. Does grazing exclusion improve soil carbon and nitrogen stocks in alpine grasslands on the Qinghai-Tibetan Plateau? A meta-analysis. <italic>Sustainability</italic><bold>12</bold>, 977 (2020).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of grazing exclusion on carbon sequestration and plant diversity in grasslands of China-A meta-analysis</article-title><source>Ecol. Eng.</source><year>2016</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>647</fpage><lpage>655</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecoleng.2016.06.124</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Xiong, D., Shi, P., Zhang, X. &#x00026; Zou, C. B. Effects of grazing exclusion on carbon sequestration and plant diversity in grasslands of China-A meta-analysis. <italic>Ecol. Eng.</italic><bold>94</bold>, 647&#x02013;655 (2016).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Amelung</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Lehmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#x000e4;stner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantitative assessment of microbial necromass contribution to soil organic matter</article-title><source>Glob. Change Biol.</source><year>2019</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>3578</fpage><lpage>3590</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/gcb.14781</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">Liang, C., Amelung, W., Lehmann, J. &#x00026; K&#x000e4;stner, M. Quantitative assessment of microbial necromass contribution to soil organic matter. <italic>Glob. Change Biol.</italic><bold>25</bold>, 3578&#x02013;3590 (2019).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effect of grazing exclusion and rotational grazing on labile soil organic carbon in north China</article-title><source>Eur. J. Soil Sci.</source><year>2021</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>372</fpage><lpage>384</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ejss.12952</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="journal">Dong, L. et al. Effect of grazing exclusion and rotational grazing on labile soil organic carbon in north China. <italic>Eur. J. Soil Sci.</italic><bold>72</bold>, 372&#x02013;384 (2021).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR26" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effects of establishing cultivated grassland on soil organic carbon fractions in a degraded alpine meadow on the Tibetan Plateau</article-title><source>PeerJ</source><year>2022</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>e14012</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.14012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36117537</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26" publication-type="journal">Liu, X. et al. Effects of establishing cultivated grassland on soil organic carbon fractions in a degraded alpine meadow on the Tibetan Plateau. <italic>PeerJ</italic><bold>10</bold>, e14012 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36117537</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR27" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anh</surname><given-names>PTQ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Linkages among land use, macronutrient levels, and soil erosion in northern Vietnam: A plot-scale study</article-title><source>Geoderma</source><year>2014</year><volume>232&#x02013;234</volume><fpage>352</fpage><lpage>362</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.geoderma.2014.05.011</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27" publication-type="journal">Anh, P. T. Q. et al. Linkages among land use, macronutrient levels, and soil erosion in northern Vietnam: A plot-scale study. <italic>Geoderma</italic><bold>232&#x02013;234</bold>, 352&#x02013;362 (2014).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR28" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The effects of hummock-hollow microtopography on soil organic carbon stocks and soil labile organic carbon fractions in a sedge peatland in Changbai Mountain, China</article-title><source>CATENA</source><year>2021</year><volume>201</volume><fpage>105204</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.catena.2021.105204</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28" publication-type="journal">Wang, M. et al. The effects of hummock-hollow microtopography on soil organic carbon stocks and soil labile organic carbon fractions in a sedge peatland in Changbai Mountain, China. <italic>CATENA</italic><bold>201</bold>, 105204 (2021).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR29" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>K&#x000f6;lbl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Grazing changes topography-controlled topsoil properties and their interaction on different spatial scales in a semi-arid grassland of Inner Mongolia, P.R. China</article-title><source>Plant Soil</source><year>2011</year><volume>340</volume><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>58</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11104-010-0473-4</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29" publication-type="journal">K&#x000f6;lbl, A. et al. Grazing changes topography-controlled topsoil properties and their interaction on different spatial scales in a semi-arid grassland of Inner Mongolia, P.R. China. <italic>Plant Soil</italic><bold>340</bold>, 35&#x02013;58 (2011).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR30" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Storage and dynamics of carbon and nitrogen in soil after grazing exclusion in <italic>Leymus chinensis</italic> grasslands of northern China</article-title><source>J. Environ. Qual.</source><year>2008</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>663</fpage><lpage>668</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2134/jeq2007.0196</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18396553</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30" publication-type="journal">Wu, L., He, N., Wang, Y. &#x00026; Han, X. Storage and dynamics of carbon and nitrogen in soil after grazing exclusion in <italic>Leymus chinensis</italic> grasslands of northern China. <italic>J. Environ. Qual.</italic><bold>37</bold>, 663&#x02013;668 (2008).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18396553</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR31" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lavallee</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Soong</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Cotrufo</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Conceptualizing soil organic matter into particulate and mineral-associated forms to address global change in the 21st century</article-title><source>Glob. Change Biol.</source><year>2020</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>261</fpage><lpage>273</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/gcb.14859</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR31" publication-type="journal">Lavallee, J. M., Soong, J. L. &#x00026; Cotrufo, M. F. Conceptualizing soil organic matter into particulate and mineral-associated forms to address global change in the 21st century. <italic>Glob. Change Biol.</italic><bold>26</bold>, 261&#x02013;273 (2020).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR32" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Responses of soil organic carbon fractions to different vegetation restoration n a typical kart depression</article-title><source>Acta Ecol. Sin.</source><year>2021</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>8535</fpage><lpage>8544</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32" publication-type="journal">Zhao, Y., Zhang, W., Hu, P., Xiao, J. &#x00026; Wang, K. Responses of soil organic carbon fractions to different vegetation restoration n a typical kart depression. <italic>Acta Ecol. Sin.</italic><bold>41</bold>, 8535&#x02013;8544 (2021).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR33" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Six years of grazing exclusion is the optimum duration in the alpine meadow-steppe of the north-eastern Qinghai-Tibetan Plateau</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2018</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>17269</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-35273-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30467363</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR33" publication-type="journal">Li, W., Liu, Y., Wang, J., Shi, S. &#x00026; Cao, W. Six years of grazing exclusion is the optimum duration in the alpine meadow-steppe of the north-eastern Qinghai-Tibetan Plateau. <italic>Sci. Rep.</italic><bold>8</bold>, 17269 (2018).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30467363</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR34" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The rangeland degradation in north China and its preventive strategy</article-title><source>Sci. Agric. Sin.</source><year>1997</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>2</fpage><lpage>10</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR34" publication-type="journal">Li, B. The rangeland degradation in north China and its preventive strategy. <italic>Sci. Agric. Sin.</italic><bold>30</bold>, 2&#x02013;10 (1997).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR35" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x000fc;</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Soil quality regime in relation to land cover and slope position across a highly modified slope landscape</article-title><source>Ecol. Res.</source><year>2004</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>118</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1440-1703.2003.00614.x</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR35" publication-type="journal">Fu, B., Liu, S., Chen, L., L&#x000fc;, Y. &#x00026; Qiu, J. Soil quality regime in relation to land cover and slope position across a highly modified slope landscape. <italic>Ecol. Res.</italic><bold>19</bold>, 111&#x02013;118 (2004).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR36" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Management-induced change in labile soil organic matter under continuous corn in eastern Canadian soils</article-title><source>Biol. Fertil. Soils</source><year>1997</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>88</fpage><lpage>94</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s003740050348</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR36" publication-type="journal">Liang, B. C. et al. Management-induced change in labile soil organic matter under continuous corn in eastern Canadian soils. <italic>Biol. Fertil. Soils</italic><bold>26</bold>, 88&#x02013;94 (1997).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR37" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vance</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><name><surname>Brookes</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Jenkinson</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An extraction method for measuring soil microbial biomass C</article-title><source>Soil Biol. Biochem.</source><year>1987</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>703</fpage><lpage>707</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0038-0717(87)90052-6</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR37" publication-type="journal">Vance, E. D., Brookes, P. C. &#x00026; Jenkinson, D. S. An extraction method for measuring soil microbial biomass C. <italic>Soil Biol. Biochem.</italic><bold>19</bold>, 703&#x02013;707 (1987).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR38" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cambardella</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Particulate soil organic-matter changes across a grassland cultivation sequence</article-title><source>Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J.</source><year>1992</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>777</fpage><lpage>783</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2136/sssaj1992.03615995005600030017x</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR38" publication-type="journal">Cambardella, C. A. &#x00026; Elliott, E. T. Particulate soil organic-matter changes across a grassland cultivation sequence. <italic>Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J.</italic><bold>56</bold>, 777&#x02013;783 (1992).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR39" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Six</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name><name><surname>Paustian</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Doran</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aggregation and soil organic matter accumulation in cultivated and native grassland soils</article-title><source>Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J.</source><year>1998</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>1367</fpage><lpage>1377</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2136/sssaj1998.03615995006200050032x</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR39" publication-type="journal">Six, J., Elliott, E. T., Paustian, K. &#x00026; Doran, J. W. Aggregation and soil organic matter accumulation in cultivated and native grassland soils. <italic>Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J.</italic><bold>62</bold>, 1367&#x02013;1377 (1998).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR40" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Changes in soil organic carbon stocks and its physical fractions along an elevation in a subtropical mountain forest</article-title><source>J. Environ. Manag.</source><year>2024</year><volume>351</volume><fpage>119823</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jenvman.2023.119823</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR40" publication-type="journal">Wu, G. et al. Changes in soil organic carbon stocks and its physical fractions along an elevation in a subtropical mountain forest. <italic>J. Environ. Manag.</italic><bold>351</bold>, 119823 (2024).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR41" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weil</surname></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Estimating active carbon for soil quality assessment: A simplified method for laboratory and field use</article-title><source>Am. J. Altern. Agric.</source><year>2003</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1079/AJAA2003003</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR41" publication-type="journal">Weil, et al. Estimating active carbon for soil quality assessment: A simplified method for laboratory and field use. <italic>Am. J. Altern. Agric.</italic><bold>18</bold>, 3&#x02013;17 (2003).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR42" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ellert</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Bettany</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Calculation of organic matter and nutrients stored in soils under contrasting management regimes</article-title><source>Can. J. Soil Sci.</source><year>1995</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>529</fpage><lpage>538</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4141/cjss95-075</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR42" publication-type="journal">Ellert, B. H. &#x00026; Bettany, J. R. Calculation of organic matter and nutrients stored in soils under contrasting management regimes. <italic>Can. J. Soil Sci.</italic><bold>75</bold>, 529&#x02013;538 (1995).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR43" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Improving soil aggregates stability and soil organic carbon sequestration by no-till and legume-based crop rotations in the North China Plain</article-title><source>Sci. Total Environ.</source><year>2022</year><volume>847</volume><fpage>157518</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2022.157518</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35878862</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR43" publication-type="journal">Liu, W. et al. Improving soil aggregates stability and soil organic carbon sequestration by no-till and legume-based crop rotations in the North China Plain. <italic>Sci. Total Environ.</italic><bold>847</bold>, 157518 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35878862</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR44" publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Weisberg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><source>An R Companion to Applied Regression</source><year>2019</year><publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR44" publication-type="book">Fox, J. &#x00026; Weisberg, S. <italic>An R Companion to Applied Regression</italic> (Sage, 2019).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">R Core Team. <italic>R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing</italic> (2023).</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>