<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39730465</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11680714</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">81077</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-024-81077-8</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Spatiotemporal patterns and drivers of orchard meadow loss in South Tyrol, Italy</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-4634-9414</contrib-id><name><surname>Sch&#x000f6;nafinger</surname><given-names>Alexander</given-names></name><address><email>alexander.schoenafinger@eurac.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-2684-029X</contrib-id><name><surname>Egarter Vigl</surname><given-names>Lukas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-9179-7494</contrib-id><name><surname>Tasser</surname><given-names>Erich</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/01xt1w755</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.418908.c</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 1089 6435</institution-id><institution>Institute for Alpine Environment, </institution><institution>Eurac Research, </institution></institution-wrap>Drususallee/Viale Druso 1, Bolzano/Bozen, 39100 Italy </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/054pv6659</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5771.4</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2151 8122</institution-id><institution>Department of Ecology, </institution><institution>University of Innsbruck, </institution></institution-wrap>Sternwartestrasse 15/Technikerstra&#x000df;e 25, Innsbruck, 6020 Austria </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>28</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>30812</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>9</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2024</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Orchard meadows, a specific agroforestry system characterised by scattered high-stem fruit trees, are a traditional element of several cultural landscapes in Central Europe and provide important ecosystem services. Since the middle of the 20th century, orchard meadows have drastically declined across Europe. Spatial information on the drivers and patterns of such a decline in several regions in Central Europe is lacking. In this study, we aimed to provide the first detailed insights into the development of orchard meadows in South Tyrol. We assessed the current distribution of orchard meadows in South Tyrol (Northern Italy) and analysed the patterns and drivers of their decline over the last 75 years. Aerial images of the orchard meadows in South Tyrol from the 1950s up to the 2020s were examined, and changes in their distribution were statistically analysed. The results revealed that the historical orchard meadow area in South Tyrol has decreased by more than 6,000 ha (&#x02212;95%) over the past 75 years, showing one of the largest reductions in Central Europe. Orchard meadow loss was highest at lower elevations (&#x02013;5,155&#x000a0;ha), shallow slopes (&#x02013;4,313&#x000a0;ha), and expositions towards the south (&#x02013;5,035&#x000a0;ha). Orchard meadows have declined due to agricultural intensification towards the establishment of modern fruit orchards (56%) and intensively managed grasslands (8%), urbanisation (23%), and reforestation (6%), and other types of land use/land cover (6.5%). Only 0.5% of the traditional orchard meadows have been preserved. The results suggest that orchard meadows are at a high risk of disappearing from the South Tyrolean landscape, resulting in the loss of genetic diversity of many local or indigenous fruit varieties (especially apples and pears). Immediate action is needed to safeguard the current orchard meadow population and appropriate management measures are needed to highlight the multiple values of orchard meadows and provide a valuable alternative to intensive arable farming.</p><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1038/s41598-024-81077-8.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Agroforestry</kwd><kwd>Cultural landscape</kwd><kwd>Land use/Land cover change</kwd><kwd>Temperate climate</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Agroecology</kwd><kwd>Biodiversity</kwd><kwd>Ecosystem ecology</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Springer Nature Limited 2024</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Agroforestry has been practiced in Europe for a long time. Agroforestry practices encompass the agricultural management of the understory in the presence of scattered, usually high-stemmed trees. These trees can be used either for forestry or for both forestry and agriculture<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. Wood pasture, one of the earliest forms of agroforestry, can be traced back to the Neolithic Period<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. Other ancient agroforestry systems such as &#x02018;Dehesas&#x02019; in Spain and &#x02018;Montados&#x02019; in Portugal, wherein pastures were integrated with oak woodlands, date back to 4,500 B.C.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. In Europe, agroforestry can be mainly categorized into silvoarable (arable or horticultural crops planted underneath trees) or silvopastoral (forage and livestock production in forests, woodland, or open forest trees) systems. A specialised form of silvoarable and -pastoral systems are orchard intercropping systems, where the understory management is associated with the cultivation of fruit trees<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. Additionally, agroforestry systems can be encompassed by linear or small woody feature elements, such as riparian tree strips, avenue trees, or hedgerows<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>. Agroforestry systems are estimated to extend across a total area of over 10.6&#x000a0;million hectares in Europe, with approximately 1.2&#x000a0;million hectares dedicated to orchard intercropping systems<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. Orchard meadows (also referred to as traditional orchards), also called &#x02018;Streuobstwiese&#x02019; (German)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>, &#x02018;pr&#x000e9;-verger&#x02019; (French), &#x02018;lu&#x0010d;n&#x000ed; sad&#x02019; (Czech), and &#x02019;sadov&#x000e1; l&#x000fa;ka&#x02019; (Slovak)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>, is the prevalent type of orchard intercropping system implemented in European regions with temperate climate. Orchard meadows are characterised by high-stemmed (1.6&#x02013;1.8 m) fruit trees such as apples, pears, plums, apricots, and cherries, and nut trees such as walnuts or chestnuts<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup> distributed across meadows, pastures, or arable land<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. The tree density in orchard meadows typically ranges from 20 to 100 trees ha<sup>&#x02212;&#x02009;1</sup><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>. The main principles of modern fruit cultivation practices, such as reproduction and grafting, were already applied in Ancient Greece and the Roman Empire; such practices were introduced to Central Europe by the Romans<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. Orchards became a prominent element of the Central European landscape as early as the 17th century until the 18th and 19th centuries. During this period, government authorities played an important role in the expansion and rejuvenation of old orchard meadows by establishing nurseries and enacting policies such as granting citizenship and marriage license upon fulfilling the citizens&#x02019; obligation to plant fruit trees<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. The economic motivation behind these policies promoted the development of traditional orchards<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>, which still were mostly silvoarable systems at this time<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. It was only at the beginning of the 20th century when orchards were increasingly combined with grasslands in response to economic shift to dairy farming<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par3">Since then, traditional agroforestry systems, especially orchard meadows, have played key roles in providing habitats for various plant and animal species. These systems create ecological niches that support plants and animals from both forest and open-land communities as well as specialised species that rely on complex and varied structures within these ecosystems<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>. For example, orchard meadows provide habitat for a considerable number of specialised wild bees, such as solitary bees<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. Furthermore, unlike intensively managed orchards, they are frequently associated with apiculture due to their limited exposure to pesticides<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. In addition to their significant role in supporting biodiversity, orchard meadows deliver a multitude of ecosystem services (ES) such as preserving the genetic diversity of old fruit varieties, increasing the aesthetic value of landscapes, and providing habitats for pollinators<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. A strong interconnection between ecological and sociocultural values also exists within traditional agroforestry systems<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>, making them substantial contributors to human well-being. However, the socioeconomic developments in the 20th century have led to a dramatic decline in orchard meadows and their associated ecosystem services and, thus, have negatively affected cultural heritage through the loss of numerous traditional fruit varieties<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>. Most of the modern fruit varieties and agricultural practices associated with fruit cultivation and propagation originated in the Persian, Egyptian, and Indian Empires. Over time, several fruit varieties have been developed. For example, there are 2,504 apple, 1,623 pear, and 1,696 plum/damson varieties in Switzerland; 1,067 apple, 168 pears, and 1,000 plum/damson varieties in Germany; and approximately 2,000 apple, 1,500 pear, and 1,000 plum/damson varieties in Austria<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. Along with agricultural intensification and modernisation in the 20th century, fruit varieties cultivated in orchard meadows were standardised due to exchanges, trade, and variety recommendations across Central Europe<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>, leading to the declining importance of traditional orchard varieties in general and that of regional and local varieties in particular<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. The decrease in the area occupied by orchard meadows ranges from 15% in Bohemia, Czech Republic<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>, to 94% in Belgium<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. Other fruit-intercropping agroforestry systems in Europe, such as the cider orchards in Great Britain (&#x02212;56%), have also suffered significant losses in terms of traditional orchard area<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par4">The historical evolution of fruit cultivation in the Autonomous Province of South Tyrol (S&#x000fc;dtirol/Alto Adige, northern Italian province), which is reported in the literature, indicates a spatiotemporal development comparable to that observed in Central Europe<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. The most prevalent agroforestry systems in this region are larch meadows<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup> and chestnut groves<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>; however, orchard meadows also form an integral part of the cultural landscape in South Tyrol<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par5">Nevertheless, the impact of these historical developments on the past and present spatial distribution of orchard meadows in South Tyrol remains largely unknown. This knowledge gap can be partly attributed to agricultural statistical assessments that predominantly concentrate on intensive agricultural systems. However, numerous studies have omitted the inclusion of South Tyrol in the broader context of Central Europe<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. In this study, we aimed to provide the first detailed insights into the development of orchard meadows in South Tyrol. In view of the development of agriculture in Central Europe, we hypothesised that South Tyrol has experienced a significant reduction in orchard meadow areas since the middle of the 20th century. To test this hypothesis, we quantitatively assessed the spatiotemporal dynamics of changes in orchard meadow areas since the mid-20th century and identified the key drivers behind their transformations.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec6"><title>Spatiotemporal development of orchard meadows</title><p id="Par7">The number of contiguous orchard meadows in South Tyrol has decreased by approximately 3000 single fields (&#x02212;78%) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) over the last 75 years. Although this decline was consistent across all districts, the highest losses (96% reduction) were observed in &#x000dc;beretsch-S&#x000fc;dtiroler Unterland and Bozen; in contrast, the smallest reduction (48%) was observed in Vinschgau.</p><p id="Par8">
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Distribution of orchard meadows in South Tyrol in 1955 (6,365&#x000a0;ha) and 2020 (296&#x000a0;ha) as well as the distribution of conserved orchard meadows (33&#x000a0;ha). The conserved map segment shows the orchard meadows present in both 1955 and 2020. The points represent the centre of corresponding orchard meadow polygons. The orchard meadow count (n) is displayed in the bottom-right corner of each map segment. The elevation gradient layer has been generated using the Digital Elevation Model of South Tyrol dataset<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. The compilation of maps was generated using ArcGis Pro 3.3.1<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2024_81077_Fig1_HTML" id="d33e393"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par9">In the 1950s, the total area covered by orchard meadows was 6,365&#x000a0;ha, contributing to 6.6% of agricultural land in favourable areas (UAA) in 1954. Over the past 75 years, it has decreased by over 95% (&#x02212;6,069&#x000a0;ha), leaving only 296&#x000a0;ha (0.3% of the UAA in 2010) today (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a; Supplementary Table S4). Bozen (&#x02212;99.5%) and &#x000dc;beretsch-S&#x000fc;dtiroler Unterland (&#x02212;99.4%) suffered the most significant losses, whereas Wipptal (&#x02212;82.7%) and Pustertal (&#x02212;79.2%) suffered the least.</p><p id="Par10">
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Historical and recent distribution of orchard meadows within South Tyrol (bold)&#x000a0;and its districts.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2"/><th align="left" colspan="2">Area (ha)</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">Area change (%)</th></tr><tr><th align="left">1955</th><th align="left">2020</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Bozen</td><td align="left">320.2</td><td align="left">1.6</td><td align="left">&#x02212;99.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Burggrafenamt</td><td align="left">1,964.1</td><td align="left">65.5</td><td align="left">&#x02212;96.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Eisacktal</td><td align="left">497.4</td><td align="left">41.8</td><td align="left">&#x02212;91.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Pustertal</td><td align="left">250.2</td><td align="left">52.1</td><td align="left">&#x02212;79.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Salten-Schlern</td><td align="left">211.3</td><td align="left">35.6</td><td align="left">&#x02212;83.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000dc;beretsch-S&#x000fc;dtiroler Unterland</td><td align="left">1,637.5</td><td align="left">10.2</td><td align="left">&#x02212;99.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Vinschgau</td><td align="left">1,455.8</td><td align="left">84.7</td><td align="left">&#x02212;94.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Wipptal</td><td align="left">28.5</td><td align="left">5.0</td><td align="left">&#x02212;82.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<bold>South Tyrol</bold>
</td><td align="left">
<bold>6,364.9</bold>
</td><td align="left">
<bold>296.4</bold>
</td><td align="left">
<bold>&#x02212;95.3</bold>
</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par11">The largest contiguous orchard meadow in the 1950s covered approximately 340&#x000a0;ha; however, the area of the largest traditional orchard in 2020 shrank to only 3&#x000a0;ha (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;S1). At the same time, the average area of orchard meadows has decreased from 0.54&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.38 to 0.25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.14&#x000a0;ha (Welch&#x02019;s t-test: t<sub>4003</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;39.7, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001) (Supplementary Fig. S3a). This trend was consistent across all districts, especially for Bozen, &#x000dc;beretsch-S&#x000fc;dtiroler Unterland, and Burggrafenamt, which showed the most substantial changes (Supplementary Fig. S4). Finally, the mapping inaccuracy was less than 2% of the total area following cross-referencing a comprehensive agricultural land use map with the 2020 orchard meadow dataset.</p><p id="Par12">The tree density observed in the district of Vinschgau was frequently higher in historic orchard meadows (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>d). On average, it declined from 56&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;19 trees ha<sup>&#x02212;&#x02009;1</sup> to 45&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;23 trees ha<sup>&#x02212;&#x02009;1</sup> (Welch&#x02019;s t-test: t<sub>374</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3.5, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001) (Supplementary Fig. S3b). In current orchard meadows, only the districts of Bozen and &#x000dc;beretsch-S&#x000fc;dtiroler Unterland, which together contribute to just 4% of the current orchard meadow area (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>), show a higher average tree density than the historic mean in Vinschgau (Supplementary Fig. S5).</p><p id="Par13">Moreover, there was a reduction in the total area of orchard meadows across all elevation belts. During the 1950s, approximately 82% of the orchard meadow area was situated at elevations below 800&#x000a0;m asl (colline belt). Currently, however, orchard meadows are predominantly located in the submontane belt (800&#x02013;1,200&#x000a0;m asl), constituting 52% of the total area (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b; Supplementary Table S3a). Thus, the most significant reduction in orchard meadow area occurred in the colline belt (&#x02212;98.8%), followed by those in the submontane belt (&#x02212;82.3%) and the montane belt (&#x02212;71.2%) (Supplementary Table S3a, Fig. S8). Notably, the average elevation in Salten-Schlern has remained relatively stable, indicating a consistent decrease across all elevations. Conversely, the average elevation in Wipptal decreased, indicating a more pronounced reduction in orchard meadow area at higher elevations (Supplementary Fig. S6).</p><p id="Par14">
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Changes in the total area of orchard meadows from the 1950s (<bold>a</bold>) and relative distribution by elevation (<bold>b</bold>), slope (<bold>c</bold>), tree density (only for the district of Vinschgau) (<bold>d</bold>), and exposition (<bold>e</bold>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2024_81077_Fig2_HTML" id="d33e580"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par15">Regarding the distribution of orchard meadows based on slope, 76% of the orchard meadows in the 1950s were situated on surfaces with gentle inclinations (&#x02264;&#x02009;11&#x000b0;). In contrast, 74% of the orchard meadows are currently distributed along moderate and steep slopes (&#x0003e;&#x02009;11&#x000b0;) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>c; Supplementary Table S3b, Fig. S9). The decline in the distribution of orchard meadows gradually diminished as the slope increased; thus, the areas with the steepest slopes had the lowest reduction in the distribution of orchard meadows. This trend was consistent across all districts; &#x000dc;beretsch-S&#x000fc;dtiroler Unterland, Burggrafenamt, and Bozen exhibited the most significant changes, whereas Salten-Schlern showed the smallest changes (Supplementary Fig. S7).</p><p id="Par16">The distribution of orchard meadows by exposition decreased toward the southeast and south; thus, more orchard meadows are now facing southwest (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>e; Supplementary Table S3c, Fig. S10).</p></sec><sec id="Sec454"><title>Land-use/land-cover change</title><p id="Par18">The loss of historical orchard meadows in South Tyrol was due to their conversion into modern orchards (56%), built-up areas (14.3%), infrastructure (8.4%), grasslands (8.2%), and forests (6%) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>; Supplementary Table S6, Fig. S12). Only a small portion of the orchard meadows (0.5%) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>; Supplementary Table S6) has been retained since the 1950s. In summary, 68.8% of the area was transformed into intensive agricultural land-use/land-cover (LULC) types (arable land, intensively used grasslands, orchards, and vineyards). Urbanisation (22.7% occupied by built-up areas and infrastructure) and land abandonment (7.7% occupied by forests, woody features, and shrublands) also contributed to significant LULC changes.</p><p id="Par19">
<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Transformation of historical orchard meadows into current land-use/land-cover (LULC) in the districts of South Tyrol.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2024_81077_Fig3_HTML" id="d33e610"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par20">There were regional variations in LULC changes among the districts of South Tyrol. The orchard meadows in &#x000dc;beretsch-S&#x000fc;dtiroler Unterland (68%), Vinschgau (66%), Bruggrafenamt (61%), and Bozen (57%) were mostly converted into modern orchards. Meanwhile, the orchard meadows in Eisacktal were mainly transformed into grasslands and built-up areas, whereas those in Pustertal, Salten-Schlern, and Wipptal were converted into grasslands and forests (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>; Supplementary Table S6).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec3" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="Sec8"><title>Changing cultural landscape</title><p id="Par22">Orchard meadows are the most recent agroforestry system implemented in South Tyrol; they emerged in response to the Napoleonic War to enhance food security after the 1820s<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. Orchard meadows covered approximately 6,400&#x000a0;ha in 1955; however, the area covered by orchard meadows in the following years subsequently declined by 95%, which is significantly above the Central European average of 75%<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup> (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). The decline in the total area of orchard meadows in Central Europe is mainly driven by agricultural intensification, urbanisation, and land abandonment<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>. Our study revealed a similar trend in South Tyrol, where orchard meadow loss is primarily attributed to agricultural intensification, leading to the transformation of over half of the area into modern orchards with densely planted, small-sized trees. The separation of fruit and fodder production has been strongly promoted in South Tyrol since the 1920s through the use of pesticides in fruit production as they have been adversely affecting the health of livestock<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. Other contributing factors include increased mechanisation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>, fertiliser usage<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>, and production costs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>, changes in farming practices, transition from full-time to part-time farming, and reduction in household size and available family labour resources<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par23">
<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Literature collection of the decline in orchard meadows in eight European countries and in cider orchards (silvoarable system similar to orchard meadows) in Britain. All listed countries are situated in the temperate climate zone<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. * marks countries that entirely belong to Central Europe and ** mark countries that are partially belonging to Central Europe.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="2">Country / Territory</th><th align="left">Time period</th><th align="left">Change (&#x02013;%)</th><th align="left">Reference</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">Belgium**</td><td align="left">1944&#x02013;1976</td><td align="left">94</td><td align="left">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">Luxembourg*</td><td align="left">1902&#x02013;1993</td><td align="left">78</td><td align="left">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">Germany*</td><td align="left">Since 1950s</td><td align="left">75</td><td align="left">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2"> North-west</td><td align="left">1979&#x02013;2009</td><td align="left">74</td><td align="left">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2"> South</td><td align="left">1965&#x02013;2005</td><td align="left">48</td><td align="left">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2"> East</td><td align="left">1964&#x02013;2008</td><td align="left">46</td><td align="left">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2"> South-west</td><td align="left">1968&#x02013;2009</td><td align="left">22</td><td align="left">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2"> Hessen</td><td align="left">1938&#x02013;1983</td><td align="left">92</td><td align="left">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2"> North Rhine-Westphalia</td><td align="left">1951&#x02013;1990</td><td align="left">92</td><td align="left">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2"> Hamburg</td><td align="left">1951&#x02013;1965</td><td align="left">87</td><td align="left">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2"> Rhineland-Palatinate</td><td align="left">1951&#x02013;1990</td><td align="left">84</td><td align="left">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2"> Niedersachsen</td><td align="left">1951&#x02013;1965</td><td align="left">76</td><td align="left">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2"> Bremen</td><td align="left">1951&#x02013;1965</td><td align="left">71</td><td align="left">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2"> Baden-W&#x000fc;rttemberg</td><td align="left">1938&#x02013;1990</td><td align="left">70</td><td align="left">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2"> Thuringia</td><td align="left">1981&#x02013;1988</td><td align="left">67</td><td align="left">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2"> BRD-West</td><td align="left">1951&#x02013;1982</td><td align="left">65</td><td align="left">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2"> Saarland</td><td align="left">1965&#x02013;1988</td><td align="left">61</td><td align="left">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2"> Bavaria</td><td align="left">1951&#x02013;1965</td><td align="left">33</td><td align="left">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">Switzerland*</td><td align="left">1954&#x02013;1991</td><td align="left">70</td><td align="left">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">Austria*</td><td align="left">1960&#x02013;1984</td><td align="left">65</td><td align="left">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2"> Burgenland</td><td align="left">19th century</td><td align="left">85</td><td align="left">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2"> Mostviertel</td><td align="left">1953&#x02013;2002</td><td align="left">70</td><td align="left">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">Britain</td><td align="left">1950&#x02013;2007</td><td align="left">56</td><td align="left">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2"> England</td><td align="left">1950&#x02013;2007</td><td align="left">81</td><td align="left">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2"> Wales</td><td align="left">1950&#x02013;2007</td><td align="left">81</td><td align="left">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">France**</td><td align="left">1982&#x02013;2003</td><td align="left">44</td><td align="left">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">Slovakia*</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2"> Central</td><td align="left">Since 1950s</td><td align="left">75</td><td align="left">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">Czech Republic*</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2"> Bohemia</td><td align="left">Since mid-1950s</td><td align="left">15</td><td align="left">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>
</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par24">Moreover, the transformation of historical orchard meadows in South Tyrol was notably influenced by urbanisation. Since the 1950s, the population has surged by a factor of 3.2 (from 168,301 in 1951 to 532,616 inhabitants in 2020)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>. Consequently, the expansion of built-up areas has become necessary, leading to the removal of several orchard meadows that are often situated in belts around settlements<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>. Urbanisation also involves the expansion of infrastructure networks, including roads and railways<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>. A key development was the construction of the A22 highway in 1972, which, coupled with the adoption of new plantation and conservation technologies, further facilitated specialisation in intensive fruit production, particularly after the 1970s<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. Such technologies involved, for example, an even more compact plantation of trees with up to 10,000 trees ha<sup>&#x02212;&#x02009;1</sup> or more advanced cooling techniques for fruit storage<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par25">A small portion of the orchard meadows in South Tyrol has been abandoned and reforested. Land abandonment typically occurs in areas with less favourable topographic conditions, characterised by high elevations, steep inclinations, and north-facing slopes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>, whereas agricultural intensification and urbanisation mainly occur in areas with more suitable topographic conditions (low elevation and inclination and south-facing slopes)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par26">The results of this study, along with those of other studies, demonstrate that the development of the landscape in South Tyrol has resulted in the displacement of traditional cultural elements, such as orchard meadows, into less favourable agricultural areas. Such areas are frequently inaccessible for agricultural machinery, leading to a general association with an extensive type of cultivation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. In contrast, areas that are cultivated extensively in topographically favourable locations frequently find themselves in competition with intensive agriculture, as these areas are more accessible and suitable for the use of machinery, allowing for more intensive farming practices. Furthermore, the suitable climatic conditions facilitate intensive farming, particularly in the valley floors at elevations up to approximately 1,000&#x000a0;m asl<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>. However, the rising temperatures associated with climate change may allow intensive agriculture to advance further into the montane vegetation belt, potentially displacing traditional and extensive agriculture into even less favourable areas or even eliminating some traditional agricultural practices entirely.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4000"><title>Ecological and social consequences</title><p id="Par28">Agroforestry systems, such as orchard meadows, offer numerous ecosystem services (ES) including provisioning, regulation and maintenance, and cultural services (Supplementary Table S8). Accordingly, every change in the land-use/land-cover (LULC) results in alterations in ES provisions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>. The loss of orchard meadows due to the intensification of agriculture, urbanisation, and land abandonment primarily leads to a reduction in landscape heterogeneity and loss of the cultural, historical, and aesthetic values of a landscape element<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>. Moreover, agroforestry systems are generally considered beneficial for climate change mitigation and adaptation in agriculture, as the presence of perennial woody plants on agricultural land increases aboveground and belowground carbon stocks and simultaneously leads to a reduction in temperature and improves the water supply of the crops below<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>. Furthermore, orchard meadows are recognised as biodiversity hotspots<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>. For example, extensively managed orchard meadows in South Tyrol exhibit significantly higher taxonomic richness and diversity of soil macro-invertebrate communities as well as greater diversity of vascular plants, grasshoppers, butterflies, and birds than intensively managed orchards<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par29">Guariento et al. (2024) reported that orchard meadows in South Tyrol harboured endangered and/or rare species<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup> such as <italic>Allium vineale</italic> and <italic>Orobanche lutea</italic> (vascular plants), <italic>Pachytrachis striolatus</italic> and <italic>Meconema thalassinum</italic> (grasshoppers), <italic>Melitaea didyma</italic> and <italic>Lycaena tityrus</italic> (butterflies), and <italic>Lanius collurio</italic> and <italic>Emberiza cia</italic> (birds). The study further identified 77 bee species in orchard meadows, including a significant proportion of solitary and specialised bees. In contrast, only 29 bee species were found in intensive apple orchards<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. As orchard meadows need pollinators and support them, they are often paired with beekeeping<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup>. However, the high abundance of honeybees (<italic>Apis melifera</italic>) in orchard meadows may lead to the displacement of wild bee species<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. Thus, orchard meadows offer a viable restoration solution in agriculture to support the recovery of degraded, damaged, or destroyed ecosystems and reintroduce more nature and biodiversity to the cultural landscape<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>. Furthermore, they could play a central role in the implementation of the EU Nature Restoration Law (Regulation 2022/869) and the EU Biodiversity Strategy for 2030 (COM/2020/380).</p><p id="Par30">Another essential aspect of ES in orchard meadows is the genetic diversity of native fruit species, which contributes to cultural ecosystem services. Apple and pear trees are commonly found in traditional orchards. At the beginning of the 20th century, South Tyrol was still commercially producing approximately 200 apple and pear varieties<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. Furthermore, 0.17&#x000a0;million tonnes (Mt) of apples and 36,860 t of pears were harvested in 1955<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup>. However, the current fruit production landscape has changed dramatically in favour of intensive apple production<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup>, yielding an annual harvest of approximately 1 Mt (peak of 1.2 Mt in 2014) and focusing primarily on just 11 apple varieties (77% of total production in 2022), with &#x02018;Golden Delicious&#x02019; being the most predominant (25% of the total apple cultivation area)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup>. Moreover, pear production has significantly diminished, contributing to only 432 tons of the annual harvest of pomaceous fruits (predominantly &#x02018;Williams Christ&#x02019;, 70% of the pear harvest)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup>. In summary, pomaceous fruit production has increased by approximately 500%, apple production by 600% and pear production has decreased by 98.8% since the 1950s. As a consequence, the intensification of fruit production has led to the depletion of genetic diversity in favour of the mass production of apples; hence, orchard meadows constitute a refugium for autochthonous fruit varieties. &#x02018;Initiative Baumgart&#x02019;, for example, collected a list of fruit varieties that can be found in orchard meadows in South Tyrol<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref></sup>. This list includes over 80 apple, 40 pear, and 10 apricot, plum, and damson varieties (Supplementary Table S9).</p></sec><sec id="Sec534"><title>Management considerations for the preservation of orchard meadows</title><p id="Par32">Nature conservation and intensive agriculture are antagonistic to each other<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref></sup>. Over the last 50 years, European agricultural policies regarding orchard conservation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref></sup> have pursued different concepts and objectives as a result of socioeconomic changes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref></sup>. Agricultural goals and subsidies have often prevailed over nature conservation, resulting in endangered orchards and other species-rich and high-quality semi-natural habitats<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref></sup>. Therefore, the coexistence of agricultural production and nature conservation should be improved through comprehensive political coordination, including harmonised spatial planning. Environmental subsidies and farmers&#x02019; moral judgements are probably the most important factors<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup> that would facilitate a paradigm shift supporting both agricultural sector and natural conservation. Nevertheless, it can be observed that the majority of farmers in Central Europe are primarily focused on maximising their income. It is only in circumstances where support has a significant impact on this goal that it can have a tangible influence on the decisions of farmers<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup>. Under the &#x02018;programme for landscape conservation&#x02019; in South Tyrol, subsidies worth a premium of 550&#x020ac; ha<sup>&#x02212;&#x02009;1</sup> are exclusive for agriculturally managed orchard meadows and chestnut groves<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup>. These subsidies entail additional administrative requirements, including a minimum tree canopy of 20%, a minimum area of 0.36&#x000a0;ha, and a commitment to maintaining the orchards for a minimum of 5 years. Furthermore, the use of mineral or liquid fertilisers and pesticides is prohibited, and the removal of fallen branches and competing shrubs is mandatory. Of the approximately 500 sites that have been enrolled in this subsidy program in 2021, the majority were chestnut groves and only 20 were orchard meadows<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref></sup>. The existing programme may lack the capacity to sufficiently address the financial requirements for cultivating orchard meadows while simultaneously meeting the necessary conditions for landscape conservation. This becomes particularly apparent considering that 99% of the mapped traditional orchards did not submit applications for subsidies. In contrast, Switzerland has subsidy programs for high-stemmed fruit trees in agroforestry systems, wherein farmers receive annual support ranging from 13.5 to 31.5 CHF per tree<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref></sup> (e.g., 80 trees ha<sup>&#x02212;&#x02009;1</sup>: 1,080 to 2,520 CHF ha<sup>&#x02212;&#x02009;1</sup> a<sup>&#x02212;&#x02009;1</sup>). Additionally, various organisations provide financial support to actively promote the establishment of agroforestry systems<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref></sup>. For instance, the association &#x02018;Hochstamm Suisse&#x02019;, in collaboration with &#x02018;Stiftung myclimate&#x02019;, currently supports the replanting and maintenance of high-stem trees with 105 CHF per tree<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref></sup>. Indeed, financial support, coupled with favourable market prices, enhances the economic competitiveness of agroforestry systems, including orchard meadows<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref></sup>. Accordingly, 30% of the former orchard meadows still exist today<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par33">For most orchard meadow owners, factors other than subsidies affect their agricultural practices. Despite these challenges, some farmers in South Tyrol sell harvested fruits as sustainable regional products to local fruit associations, gastronomic facilities, or farmers&#x02019; markets. Moreover, the orchard meadows in South Tyrol are integrated with agrotourism to provide visitors with aesthetic and recreational landscape elements; occasionally, the orchard meadows serve as a retreat for guests participating in the &#x02018;holiday on a farm&#x02019; program<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref></sup>. In the context of sustainable land use, the quantity of ES provided by orchard meadows is more significant than their economic efficiency (Herzog 1998). Local initiatives such as Sortengarten S&#x000fc;dtirol<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref></sup> and Initiative Baumgart<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup>, are actively working to raise awareness among the public, local stakeholders, and administrative authorities about the importance of the functionalities and ES offered by orchard meadows.</p><p id="Par34">Despite such initiatives, orchard meadows face economic challenges compared with modern agricultural systems in South Tyrol. Consequently, they remain under constant pressure and are at a high risk of extinction because of the ongoing intensification of agriculture and unfavourable economic conditions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec76768"><title>Methodological limitations</title><p id="Par36">The mapping process employed in this study is subject to inaccuracies. These issues include discrepancies in the digital orthophotos utilised, which exhibit variations in resolution and quality, including pixel size and colour spectrum. The orthophotos did not perfectly align in all areas, leading to small discrepancies, primarily attributed to georectification issues. In addition, both orthophotos were influenced by factors such as topography, camera angle, and illumination conditions.</p><p id="Par37">In the historical orthophoto, identifying orchard meadows proved challenging in darker areas, and distinguishing fruit trees from other tree cover was more difficult because of grayscale tones. Conversely, the current orthophotos present challenges in identifying potential orchard meadow areas shaded by nearby forests or buildings, which may have resulted in some areas being overlooked. Nevertheless, identifying fruit trees during the current time step was easier and occasionally aided by detailed tree shadows under suitable light conditions. There may have been instances of confusion between fruit trees and other deciduous tree cover, potentially leading to an error rate similar to that observed in the historical distribution (personal estimation: &#x0003c; 1% average error rate).</p><p id="Par38">Although on-site verification of the identified orchard meadows could enhance mapping accuracy, it was impractical in this study because of resource limitations. In addition, verification is only feasible for the current distribution, introducing potential challenges in maintaining comparability between datasets. Nonetheless, periodic monitoring of the orchard meadow distribution is essential to safeguard the persistence of this rare LULC type. The verification method employed for the existing orchard meadows involved cross-referencing a detailed agricultural land use map, resulting in a mapping inaccuracy of less than 2%. However, no polygons were excluded from the 2020 dataset in order to maintain comparability between the two analysed datasets, due to the unavailability of a detailed agricultural land use map for the years 1954 to 1956.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec4" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec9"><title>Study area</title><p id="Par40">This study focused on the orchard meadows in South Tyrol (S&#x000fc;dtirol/Alto Adige; 10.37&#x02013;12.51&#x000b0;E and 47.12&#x02013;46.19&#x000b0;N), the northernmost province of Italy. South Tyrol covers a total area of 7,400&#x000a0;km&#x000b2; and is organised into eight districts (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). It is characterised by a continental climate with western Atlantic and Mediterranean influences; however, the climate in South Tyrol varies greatly due to its location in the Southern and Central Alps and large differences in its elevation, ranging from 180 to 3,900&#x000a0;m above sea level (asl)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par41">
<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>South Tyrol, the study area, is the northernmost province of Italy (IT) and is adjacent to Switzerland (CH) and Austria (AT). It is divided into eight districts: Bozen (1), Burggrafenamt (2), Eisacktal (3), Pustertal (4), Salten-Schlern (5), &#x000dc;beretsch-S&#x000fc;dtiroler Unterland (6), Vinschgau (7), and Wipptal (8). The map was generated using ArcGis Pro 3.3.1<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2024_81077_Fig4_HTML" id="d33e1437"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par42">The cultural landscape in South Tyrol has drastically changed since the middle of the 19th century, when it still belonged to the County of Tyrol. During this period, most of the broad valley floors were occupied by arable land in response to the Napoleonic War and subsequent famine and grain shortage<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref></sup>. The crops were then increasingly interspersed with fruit trees to improve the self-sufficiency of South Tyrol residents. The construction of railways, first linking Bozen (Italy) and Innsbruck (Austria) in 1867 and then extending between Bozen and Mals (Italy) in the early 20th century, opened new opportunities for the export of South Tyrol&#x02019;s goods<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref></sup>. In the second half of the 19th century, fruit cultivation became increasingly important for earning additional income. In the 1920s, fruit cultivation began gaining prominence in the South Tyrolean region (which became an Italian province following World War I) and grassland, arable land, and vineyard areas were converted into traditional orchards<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref></sup>. Concurrently, the tree density in orchard meadows gradually increased, leading to the subsequent separation of fruit, crop, and grassland production. This shift was further accelerated by concerns over the adverse effects of pesticides on cattle<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. Finally, the construction of Highway A22 in 1972 and the subsequent high demand for fruit exports (mainly apples) intensified fruit production in South Tyrol<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par43">Currently, the landscape of South Tyrol is characterised by forests (50%), agricultural land (37%), marginal land (10%), and settlement areas (3%). The agricultural land is further divided into pastures (59%), hay meadows (27%), orchards (8%), vineyards (3%), and arable land (3%)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref></sup>. Notably, the agricultural land in Bozen and &#x000dc;beretsch-S&#x000fc;dtiroler Unterland, is predominantly occupied by apple plantations and vineyards, whereas permanent hay meadows and pastures are the predominant land-use types in the other districts<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref></sup>. The total area of agricultural land used in favourable sites (Supplementary Table S1) has only slightly changed since the middle of the 20th century; however, there has been large-scale intensification of land use.</p></sec><sec id="Sec876666666666666"><title>Mapping approach of orchard meadows</title><p id="Par45">Orchard meadows are defined in this study as grasslands containing tall fruit trees arranged either regularly or irregularly, with a minimum distance of 5&#x000a0;m between the edges of their canopies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref></sup>. Moreover, orchard meadows should have a minimum area of 0.1&#x000a0;ha and a tree density of 20&#x02013;100 trees ha<sup>&#x02212;&#x02009;1</sup><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>. For spatiotemporal analysis, the historical and current distribution of orchard meadows in South Tyrol was mapped, following an approach similar to that of Plieninger et al. (2015)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>. Single orchard meadows were manually mapped at a working scale of 1:2,500 using orthophotos captured in 1954&#x02013;1956 (resolution: 1.5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;1.5&#x000a0;m) and in 2020 (resolution: 0.2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;0.2&#x000a0;m)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. Polygon boundaries were delineated based on visible field margins or around the outermost trees (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). In order to validate the mapping process of currently existing orchard meadows, the recorded polygons were cross-referenced with the South Tyrol land use cadastre for agriculture and forestry of the Autonomous Province of South Tyrol (LAFIS) from 2020<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref></sup>. Furthermore, trees within the orchard meadows were recorded as points at each time step to assess tree density. Given the extensive number of orchard meadows in the 1950s, the historical point dataset exclusively covered trees within the district of Vinschgau as it showed the most resilient development of orchard meadows. Tree densities for recent time steps were mapped in all orchard meadows.</p><p id="Par46">
<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Example of the mapping approach using orthophotos of 1954&#x02013;56<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup> (resolution: 1.5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;1.5&#x000a0;m) (<bold>a</bold>) and 2020<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup> (resolution: 0.2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;0.2&#x000a0;m) (<bold>b</bold>) in detail at Prad am Stilfserjoch (Vinschgau; 10.584635&#x000b0;E, 46.616560&#x000b0;N). The compilation of maps was generated using ArcGis Pro 3.3.1<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2024_81077_Fig5_HTML" id="d33e1536"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec53536"><title>Drivers of changes</title><p id="Par48">The spatial and topographic distribution of orchard meadows was temporally compared to gain a deeper understanding of their development in South Tyrol. The elevation, slope, and exposition of South Tyrol, which were determined using the digital elevation model of South Tyrol, were analysed as potential site parameters<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par49">To determine the trend towards which orchard meadows have developed since the 1950s, land-use/land-cover (LULC) changes within the historical areas were analysed. The current LULC dataset<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref></sup> was updated based on the current distribution of mapped orchard meadows. The resulting LULC dataset featured a pixel size of 5&#x000a0;m &#x000d7; 5&#x000a0;m and encompassed 52 different LULC categories in South Tyrol, which were aggregated into 12 main groups (Supplementary Table S5). Changes were assessed for South Tyrol as a whole and its individual districts.</p></sec><sec id="Sec86768"><title>Data handling</title><p id="Par51">The map datasets were calculated and modified using ArcMap v10.7<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref></sup>. The raw data were evaluated and the results were visualized in RStudio v2023.12.1.402<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref></sup> with R v4.3.1<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref></sup> (Supplementary Table S7). Figures containing maps were generated using ArcGis Pro v3.3.1<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par52">Spatial and temporal differences were subjected to statistical testing. Levene&#x02019;s test<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref></sup> was performed to assess homoscedasticity (package &#x02018;psych v2.4.1&#x02019;)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref></sup>. The means of two independent samples were compared by employing Welch&#x02019;s t-test<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref></sup> for heterogeneous variances and Student&#x02019;s t-test<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref></sup> for homogeneous variances.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec5" sec-type="conclusion"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par53">Orchard meadows face severe risks of disappearing entirely from the cultural landscape of South Tyrol. With a decline of 95%, they marked one of the most substantial recorded declines in Central Europe since the middle of the 20th century. Despite serving as genetic reservoirs for numerous fruit varieties, particularly apples and pears, their potential decline is exacerbated by agricultural intensification. Orchard meadows play a crucial role in supporting biodiversity and providing ecosystem services, thus offering an opportunity to enhance the ecological sustainability of the cultural landscape in South Tyrol. Recognising the importance of extensive management within the implementation and realisation of the EU Nature Restoration Law and the EU Biodiversity Strategy for 2030 is important for orchard meadow conservation and the provision of various ecosystem services, especially habitat and biodiversity support, as well as climate mitigation. However, current regional subsidy programs focus solely on conserving valuable landscape elements, and do not address the economic competitiveness of traditional agroforestry systems. Regarding the subsidy standards in Switzerland and given the average tree density, a typical South Tyrolean orchard meadow should be annually supported by at least 620 to 1,450&#x020ac; ha<sup>&#x02212;&#x02009;1</sup> in order to reach economic sustainability. Consequently, there is a pressing need to give orchard meadows social value, intensify monitoring efforts, and incorporate orchard meadows into upcoming agricultural censuses to facilitate conservation strategies, identify key challenges in promoting their expansion, and identify the spectrum of fruit species to preserve the genetic diversity of autochthonous varieties.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.</p><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41598_2024_81077_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><caption><p>Supplementary Material 1</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This work was supported by the European Regional Development Fund through the Interreg Alpine Space Programme (&#x02018;LUIGI: Linking Urban and Inner-alpine Green Infrastructure&#x02019;, project number ASP 863). The realisation of the manuscript was also supported by the Lesser Foundation for Nature Conservation (Germany) within the project Baumgart and by the Autonomous Province of Bozen/Bolzano-South Tyrol within the Biodiversity Monitoring South Tyrol.&#x000a0;The authors thank the Department of Innovation, Research University and Museums of the Autonomous Province of Bozen/Bolzano for covering the Open Access publication costs.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>All authors contributed to the study conception and design. Material preparation, data collection and analysis were performed by A.S. The first draft of the manuscript was written by A.S. and E.T. and all authors commented on previous versions of the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The datasets generated and/or analysed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par57">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>den Herder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Current extent and stratification of agroforestry in the European Union</article-title><source>Agric. Ecosyst. Environ.</source><year>2017</year><volume>241</volume><fpage>121</fpage><lpage>132</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.agee.2017.03.005</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">den Herder, M. et al. Current extent and stratification of agroforestry in the European union. <italic>Agric. Ecosyst. Environ.</italic><bold>241</bold>, 121&#x02013;132 (2017).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nerlich</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Graeff-H&#x000f6;nninger</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Claupein</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Agroforestry in Europe: a review of the disappearance of traditional systems and development of modern agroforestry practices, with emphasis on experiences in Germany</article-title><source>Agrofor. Syst.</source><year>2013</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>475</fpage><lpage>492</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10457-012-9560-2</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Nerlich, K., Graeff-H&#x000f6;nninger, S. &#x00026; Claupein, W. Agroforestry in Europe: a review of the disappearance of traditional systems and development of modern agroforestry practices, with emphasis on experiences in Germany. <italic>Agrofor. Syst.</italic><bold>87</bold>, 475&#x02013;492 (2013).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Nair, P. K. R., Gordon, A. M. &#x00026; Rosa Mosquera-Losada, M. Agroforestry. In: (eds J&#x000f8;rgensen, S. E. &#x00026; Fath, B. D.) Encycl. Ecol. 101&#x02013;110 (Elsevier, 2008).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Plieninger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Monitoring directions and rates of change in trees outside forests through multitemporal analysis of map sequences</article-title><source>Appl. Geogr.</source><year>2012</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>566</fpage><lpage>576</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apgeog.2011.06.015</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Plieninger, T. Monitoring directions and rates of change in trees outside forests through multitemporal analysis of map sequences. <italic>Appl. Geogr.</italic><bold>32</bold>, 566&#x02013;576 (2012).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rubio-Delgado</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Schnabel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lavado-Contador</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmutz</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Small woody features in agricultural areas: Agroforestry systems of overlooked significance in Europe</article-title><source>Agric. Syst.</source><year>2024</year><volume>218</volume><fpage>103973</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.agsy.2024.103973</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Rubio-Delgado, J., Schnabel, S., Lavado-Contador, J. F. &#x00026; Schmutz, U. Small woody features in agricultural areas: Agroforestry systems of overlooked significance in Europe. <italic>Agric. Syst.</italic><bold>218</bold>, 103973 (2024).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kleeschulte, S. et al. Quantification of landscape features in agricultural areas using copernicus products: an overview of recent developments. In: ETC-DI Report 2023/X. European Environment Agency. (2023).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weller</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Hampicke</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x000f6;cker</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Konold</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Streuobstwiesen</article-title><source>Handb. Naturschutz Landschaftspflege</source><year>2014</year><publisher-loc>Weinheim, Germany</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Wiley-VCH Verlag GmbH &#x00026; Co. KGaA</publisher-name><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>42</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="book">Weller, F. Streuobstwiesen. In: (eds Hampicke, U., B&#x000f6;cker, R. &#x00026; Konold, W.) Handb. Naturschutz Landschaftspflege. Wiley-VCH Verlag GmbH &#x00026; Co. KGaA, Weinheim, Germany, 1&#x02013;42 (2014).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Forejt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Syrbe</surname><given-names>R-U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The current status of orchard meadows in Central Europe: multi-source area estimation in Saxony (Germany) and the Czech Republic</article-title><source>Morav Geogr. Rep.</source><year>2019</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>217</fpage><lpage>228</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Forejt, M. &#x00026; Syrbe, R-U. The current status of orchard meadows in Central Europe: multi-source area estimation in saxony (Germany) and the Czech Republic. <italic>Morav. Geogr. Rep.</italic><bold>27</bold>, 217&#x02013;228 (2019).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Plieninger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Patterns and drivers of scattered tree loss in Agricultural landscapes: Orchard Meadows in Germany (1968&#x02013;2009)</article-title><source>PLOS ONE</source><year>2015</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>e0126178</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0126178</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25932914</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Plieninger, T. et al. Patterns and drivers of scattered tree loss in agricultural landscapes: Orchard meadows in Germany (1968&#x02013;2009). <italic>PLoS ONE</italic><bold>10</bold>, e0126178 (2015).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25932914</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herzog</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Streuobst</italic>: a traditional agroforestry system as a model for agroforestry development in temperate Europe</article-title><source>Agrofor. Syst.</source><year>1998</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>61</fpage><lpage>80</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1006152127824</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Herzog, F. <italic>Streuobst</italic>: a traditional agroforestry system as a model for agroforestry development in temperate Europe. <italic>Agrofor. Syst.</italic><bold>42</bold>, 61&#x02013;80 (1998).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oberhofer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Oberhofer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Zur Geschichte Des S&#x000fc;dtiroler Obstbaues</article-title><source>Obst- Weinbau Im Wandel Zeit:<italic>50 Jahre Beratungsring</italic></source><year>2007</year><publisher-loc>Lana</publisher-loc><publisher-name>S&#x000fc;dtiroler Beratungsring f&#x000fc;r Obst- und Weinbau</publisher-name><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>238</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="book">Oberhofer, H. Zur Geschichte Des S&#x000fc;dtiroler Obstbaues. In: (ed Oberhofer, H.) Obst- Weinbau Im Wandel Zeit: <italic>50 Jahre Beratungsring</italic>. S&#x000fc;dtiroler Beratungsring f&#x000fc;r Obst- und Weinbau, Lana, 15&#x02013;238 (2007).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eichhorn</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Silvoarable systems in Europe &#x02013; Past, Present and Future prospects</article-title><source>Agrofor. Syst.</source><year>2006</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10457-005-1111-7</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Eichhorn, M. P. et al. Silvoarable systems in Europe &#x02013; past, present and future prospects. <italic>Agrofor. Syst.</italic><bold>67</bold>, 29&#x02013;50 (2006).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guariento</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Management intensification of Hay Meadows and Fruit Orchards alters Soil Macro- Invertebrate communities differently</article-title><source>Agronomy</source><year>2020</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>767</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/agronomy10060767</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Guariento, E. et al. Management intensification of hay meadows and Fruit Orchards alters soil macro- invertebrate communities differently. <italic>Agronomy</italic><bold>10</bold>, 767 (2020).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heller</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Hutter</surname><given-names>C-P</given-names></name><name><surname>Corbaz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Streuobst im Alpenraum</article-title><source>Die Bedeutung von Hochstamm-Obstb&#x000e4;umen f&#x000fc;r den Naturschutz</source><year>2004</year><publisher-loc>Stuttgart</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Wissenschaftliche Verl.Ges.</publisher-name><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>28</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="book">Heller, S. Streuobst im Alpenraum. In: (eds Hutter, C-P. &#x00026; Corbaz, R.) Die Bedeutung von Hochstamm-Obstb&#x000e4;umen f&#x000fc;r den Naturschutz. Wissenschaftliche Verl.Ges., Stuttgart, 25&#x02013;28 (2004).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guariento</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Meadow orchards as a good practice example for improving biodiversity in intensive apple orchards</article-title><source>Biol. Conserv.</source><year>2024</year><volume>299</volume><fpage>110815</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biocon.2024.110815</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Guariento, E. et al. Meadow orchards as a good practice example for improving biodiversity in intensive apple orchards. <italic>Biol. Conserv.</italic><bold>299</bold>, 110815 (2024).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kornprobst, M. Landschaftspflegekonzept Bayern:<italic> Band II.5 Lebensraumtyp Streuobst. B</italic>ayerisches Staatsministerium f&#x000fc;r Landesentwicklung und Umweltfragen, M&#x000fc;nchen (1994).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zehnder, M. &#x00026; Weller, F. Streuobstbau: Obstwiesen erleben und erhalten, 3. Auflage. Verlag Eugen Ulmer, Stuttgart (2016).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fagerholm</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Torralba</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Burgess</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Plieninger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A systematic map of ecosystem services assessments around European agroforestry</article-title><source>Ecol. Indic.</source><year>2016</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecolind.2015.11.016</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Fagerholm, N., Torralba, M., Burgess, P. J. &#x00026; Plieninger, T. A systematic map of ecosystem services assessments around European agroforestry. <italic>Ecol. Indic.</italic><bold>62</bold>, 47&#x02013;65 (2016).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rolo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Challenges and innovations for improving the sustainability of European agroforestry systems of high nature and cultural value: stakeholder perspectives</article-title><source>Sustain. Sci.</source><year>2020</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>1301</fpage><lpage>1315</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11625-020-00826-6</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Rolo, V. et al. Challenges and innovations for improving the sustainability of European agroforestry systems of high nature and cultural value: stakeholder perspectives. <italic>Sustain. Sci.</italic><bold>15</bold>, 1301&#x02013;1315 (2020).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schramayr</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Holler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Spornberger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Entwicklung, Bestand und Gef&#x000e4;hrdung des Streuobstbaues in Europa - Ein &#x000dc;berblick</article-title><source>Beitrag zum Streuobstbau in Europa: Stand, Entwicklung und Probleme.<italic> Int. Streuobst-Fachtag. POMILLENIUM 2000</italic>, 23 bis 25 Oktober 2000, Burg G&#x000fc;ssing, Burgenland</source><year>2001</year><edition>28</edition><publisher-loc>Wien</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Umweltbundesamt</publisher-name><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>13</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="book">Schramayr, G. Entwicklung, Bestand und Gef&#x000e4;hrdung des Streuobstbaues in Europa - Ein &#x000dc;berblick. In: (eds Holler, C. &#x00026; Spornberger, A.) Beitrag zum Streuobstbau in Europa: Stand, Entwicklung und Probleme. <italic>Int. Streuobst-Fachtag. POMILLENIUM 2000</italic>, 23 bis 25 Oktober 2000, Burg G&#x000fc;ssing, Burgenland, 28th ed. Umweltbundesamt, Wien, 9&#x02013;13 (2001).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gantar</surname><given-names>E-M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dianat</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Holler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Zur Situation des Streuobstbaus und der Obst-genetischen Ressourcen in &#x000d6;sterreich</article-title><source>L&#x000e4;ndlicher Raum</source><year>2011</year><volume>06</volume><fpage>9</fpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Gantar, E-M., Dianat, K. &#x00026; Holler, C. Zur Situation des Streuobstbaus und der Obst-genetischen Ressourcen in &#x000d6;sterreich. <italic>L&#x000e4;ndlicher. Raum.</italic><bold>06</bold>, 9 (2011).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Plieninger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Exploring futures of Ecosystem Services in Cultural landscapes through Participatory Scenario Development in the swabian alb</article-title><source>Ger. Ecol. Soc.</source><year>2013</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>art39</fpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">Plieninger, T. et al. Exploring futures of ecosystem services in cultural landscapes through participatory scenario development in the swabian alb. <italic>Ger. Ecol. Soc.</italic><bold>18</bold>, art39 (2013).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Burrough, A. E., Oines, C., Oram, S. P. &#x00026; Robertson, H. J. <italic>Traditional Orchard Project in England: The Creation of an Inventory to Support the UK Habitat Action Plan</italic> (Natural England, 2011).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fontana</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>What plant traits tell us: consequences of land-use change of a traditional agro-forest system on biodiversity and ecosystem service provision</article-title><source>Agric. Ecosyst. Environ.</source><year>2014</year><volume>186</volume><fpage>44</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.agee.2014.01.006</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">Fontana, V. et al. What plant traits tell us: consequences of land-use change of a traditional agro-forest system on biodiversity and ecosystem service provision. <italic>Agric. Ecosyst. Environ.</italic><bold>186</bold>, 44&#x02013;53 (2014).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nagler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Different management of larch grasslands in the European Alps shows low impact on above- and belowground carbon stocks</article-title><source>Agric. Ecosyst. Environ.</source><year>2015</year><volume>213</volume><fpage>186</fpage><lpage>193</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.agee.2015.08.005</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="journal">Nagler, M. et al. Different management of larch grasslands in the European Alps shows low impact on above- and belowground carbon stocks. <italic>Agric. Ecosyst. Environ.</italic><bold>213</bold>, 186&#x02013;193 (2015).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Loos, C. Nur Kulturlandschaftsrelikt oder von aktueller Bedeutung? Master thesis, (University of Innsbruck, 2020).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR27" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Radtke</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Traditional coppice forest management drives the invasion of <italic>Ailanthus altissima</italic> and <italic>Robinia pseudoacacia</italic> into deciduous forests</article-title><source>Ecol. Manag</source><year>2013</year><volume>291</volume><fpage>308</fpage><lpage>317</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foreco.2012.11.022</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27" publication-type="journal">Radtke, A. et al. Traditional coppice forest management drives the invasion of <italic>Ailanthus altissima</italic> and <italic>Robinia pseudoacacia</italic> into deciduous forests. <italic>Ecol. Manag.</italic><bold>291</bold>, 308&#x02013;317 (2013).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR28" publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oberrauch</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Holler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Spornberger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Streuobstbau Und Sortenerhaltung in Europa: Sortengarten S&#x000fc;dtirol</article-title><source>Beitrag zum Streuobstbau in Europa: Stand, Entwicklung und Probleme. <italic>Int. Streuobst-Fachtag. POMILLENIUM 2000</italic>, 23 bis 25 Oktober 2000, Burg G&#x000fc;ssing, Burgenland</source><year>2001</year><edition>28</edition><publisher-loc>Wien</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Umweltbundesamt</publisher-name><fpage>39</fpage><lpage>40</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28" publication-type="book">Oberrauch, F. Streuobstbau und Sortenerhaltung in Europa: Sortengarten S&#x000fc;dtirol. In: (eds Holler, C. &#x00026; Spornberger, A.) Beitrag zum Streuobstbau in Europa: Stand, Entwicklung und Probleme. <italic>Int. Streuobst-Fachtag. POMILLENIUM 2000,</italic> 23 bis 25 Oktober 2000, Burg G&#x000fc;ssing, Burgenland, 28th ed. Umweltbundesamt, Wien, 39&#x02013;40 (2001).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Autonome Provinz Bozen. GeoKatalog. In: S&#x000fc;dtiroler B&#x000fc;rgernetz. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://geokatalog.buergernetz.bz.it/geokatalog/#!">http://geokatalog.buergernetz.bz.it/geokatalog/#!</ext-link> [Accessed 19 Feb 2024] (2024).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Esri ArcGIS<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> Pro 3.3.1. (2024).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Blume, C. Die Streuobstwiese: <italic>Vielfalt erhalten - Lebensr&#x000e4;ume schaffen - Besonderes genie&#x000df;en</italic> (Pala-Verl, 2010).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR32" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sch&#x000f6;nhart</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schauppenlehner</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Muhar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysing the maintenance and establishment of orchard meadows at farm and landscape levels applying a spatially explicit integrated modelling approach</article-title><source>J. Environ. Plan. Manag</source><year>2011</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>143</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09640568.2010.502763</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32" publication-type="journal">Sch&#x000f6;nhart, M., Schauppenlehner, T., Schmid, E. &#x00026; Muhar, A. Analysing the maintenance and establishment of orchard meadows at farm and landscape levels applying a spatially explicit integrated modelling approach. <italic>J. Environ. Plan. Manag.</italic><bold>54</bold>, 115&#x02013;143 (2011).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR33" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ch&#x000e9;telat</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A contextual analysis of land-use and vegetation changes in two wooded pastures in the Swiss Jura Mountains</article-title><source>Ecol. Soc.</source><year>2013</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>art39</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5751/ES-05287-180139</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR33" publication-type="journal">Ch&#x000e9;telat, J. et al. A contextual analysis of land-use and vegetation changes in two wooded pastures in the Swiss jura mountains. <italic>Ecol. Soc.</italic><bold>18</bold>, art39 (2013).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Thieme, E., Schneider, J. &#x00026; Will, M. Streuobstwiesen:<italic> Alte Obstsorten neu entdeckt</italic> (Thorbecke, 2008).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hammel, K. &#x00026; Arnold, T. Understanding the loss of traditional agricultural systems: a case study of Orchard Meadows in Germany. <italic>J. Agric. Food Syst. Community Dev.</italic> 119&#x02013;136 (2012).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR36" publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Holler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Spornberger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantitative Streuobsterhebung im Burgenland: Im Rahmen des Leader II Projektes der Wieseninitiative</article-title><source>Beitrag zum Streuobstbau in Europa: Stand, Entwicklung und Probleme, <italic>Int. Streuobst-Fachtag. POMILLENIUM 2000</italic>, 23 bis 25 Oktober 2000, Burg G&#x000fc;ssing, Burgenland</source><year>2001</year><edition>28</edition><publisher-loc>Wien</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Umweltbundesamt</publisher-name><fpage>24</fpage><lpage>28</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR36" publication-type="book">Holler, C. Quantitative Streuobsterhebung im Burgenland: Im Rahmen des Leader II Projektes der Wieseninitiative. In: (eds Holler, C. &#x00026; Spornberger, A.) Beitrag zum Streuobstbau in Europa: Stand, Entwicklung und Probleme, <italic>Int. Streuobst-Fachtag. POMILLENIUM 2000</italic>, 23 bis 25 Oktober 2000, Burg G&#x000fc;ssing, Burgenland, 28th ed. Umweltbundesamt, Wien, 24&#x02013;28 (2001).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">ASTAT. Bev&#x000f6;lkerung.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://astat.provinz.bz.it/de/bevoelkerung.asp">https://astat.provinz.bz.it/de/bevoelkerung.asp</ext-link>. [Accessed 6 Feb 2024] (2023). .</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Tappeiner, U., Marsoner, T. &#x00026; Niedrist, G. <italic>Landwirtschaftsreport zur Nachhaltigkeit S&#x000fc;dtirols</italic> (Eurac Research, 2020).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Oberrauch, F. Streuobstbau in S&#x000fc;dtirol - Teil 1:<italic> Geschichtliche Entwicklung Und Bestandesaufnahme in den Gemeinden Schluderns, Feldthurns und Kiens</italic> (Diplomarbeit, Universit&#x000e4;t f&#x000fc;r Bodenkultur, 1997).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR40" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Plieninger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Schleyer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mantel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hostert</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Is there a forest transition outside forests? Trajectories of farm trees and effects on ecosystem services in an agricultural landscape in Eastern Germany</article-title><source>Land. Use Policy</source><year>2012</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>233</fpage><lpage>243</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.landusepol.2011.06.011</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR40" publication-type="journal">Plieninger, T., Schleyer, C., Mantel, M. &#x00026; Hostert, P. Is there a forest transition outside forests? Trajectories of farm trees and effects on ecosystem services in an agricultural landscape in Eastern Germany. <italic>Land Use Polic.</italic><bold>29</bold>, 233&#x02013;243 (2012).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR41" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tasser</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Leitinger</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Tappeiner</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Schirpke</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Shaping the European alps: Trends in landscape patterns, biodiversity and ecosystem services</article-title><source>CATENA</source><year>2024</year><volume>235</volume><fpage>107607</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.catena.2023.107607</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR41" publication-type="journal">Tasser, E., Leitinger, G., Tappeiner, U. &#x00026; Schirpke, U. Shaping the European alps: Trends in landscape patterns, biodiversity and ecosystem services. <italic>CATENA</italic><bold>235</bold>, 107607 (2024).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR42" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Foley</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Global consequences of Land Use</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2005</year><volume>309</volume><fpage>570</fpage><lpage>574</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1111772</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16040698</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR42" publication-type="journal">Foley, J. A. et al. Global consequences of land use. <italic>Science</italic><bold>309</bold>, 570&#x02013;574 (2005).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16040698</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR43" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>&#x0017d;arnovi&#x0010d;an</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Traditional orchard management in the western carpathians (Slovakia): evolution between 1955 and 2015</article-title><source>Biol. (Bratisl)</source><year>2020</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>535</fpage><lpage>546</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2478/s11756-020-00434-w</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR43" publication-type="journal">&#x0017d;arnovi&#x0010d;an, H. et al. Traditional orchard management in the western carpathians (Slovakia): evolution between 1955 and 2015. <italic>Biologia (Bratisl)</italic><bold>75</bold>, 535&#x02013;546 (2020).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR44" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cardinael</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Cadisch</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gosme</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Oelbermann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Noordwijk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Climate change mitigation and adaptation in agriculture: why agroforestry should be part of the solution</article-title><source>Agric. Ecosyst. Environ.</source><year>2021</year><volume>319</volume><fpage>107555</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.agee.2021.107555</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR44" publication-type="journal">Cardinael, R., Cadisch, G., Gosme, M., Oelbermann, M. &#x00026; Van Noordwijk, M. Climate change mitigation and adaptation in agriculture: why agroforestry should be part of the solution. <italic>Agric. Ecosyst. Environ.</italic><bold>319</bold>, 107555 (2021).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR45" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Noordwijk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Climate change adaptation in and through agroforestry: four decades of research initiated by Peter Huxley</article-title><source>Mitig Adapt. Strateg Glob Change</source><year>2021</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>18</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11027-021-09954-5</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR45" publication-type="journal">Van Noordwijk, M. et al. Climate change adaptation in and through agroforestry: four decades of research initiated by Peter Huxley. <italic>Mitig. Adapt. Strateg. Glob. Chang.</italic><bold>26</bold>, 18 (2021).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR46" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sattler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Schrader</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#x000fc;ttner</surname><given-names>M-L</given-names></name><name><surname>Henle</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of management, habitat and landscape characteristics on biodiversity of orchard meadows in Central Europe: a brief review</article-title><source>Nat. Conserv.</source><year>2024</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>103</fpage><lpage>134</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/natureconservation.55.108688</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR46" publication-type="journal">Sattler, C., Schrader, J., H&#x000fc;ttner, M-L. &#x00026; Henle, K. Effects of management, habitat and landscape characteristics on biodiversity of orchard meadows in Central Europe: a brief review. <italic>Nat. Conserv.</italic><bold>55</bold>, 103&#x02013;134 (2024).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mosg&#x000f6;ller, B. <italic>Effect of land-use, management intensity and landscape heterogeneity on ground-dwelling macro-arthropods in mountain landscapes. Master thesis</italic>, (University of Innsbruck, 2023).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zerbe, S. Renaturierung von &#x000d6;kosystemen im Spannungsfeld von Mensch und Umwelt: ein interdisziplin&#x000e4;res Fachbuch.10.1007/978-3-662-58650-1 (2019).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">ASTAT. Zeitreihe der Landwirtschaft / Serie storica sull&#x02019;agricoltura &#x02013;&#x02009;1929&#x02013;2016. 31 (2018).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Chamber of Commerce of Bolzano. Erntemenge und Lagerbest&#x000e4;nde. In: Serv. - Landwirtsch. - Obstbau. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.handelskammer.bz.it/en/node/1438">https://www.handelskammer.bz.it/en/node/1438</ext-link> (2023).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Initiative Baumgart. Streuobstwiesen in S&#x000fc;dtirol. In: Vielfalt Erhalt. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.baumgart.it/">https://www.baumgart.it/</ext-link>. [Accessed 7 Feb 2024] (2023).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sch&#x000f6;nafinger, A. <italic>Orchard Meadows in South Tyrol: Spatio-temporal development and agro-ecological evaluation. master thesis</italic>, (University of Innsbruck, 2023).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR53" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kremen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Merenlender</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Landscapes that work for biodiversity and people</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2018</year><volume>362</volume><fpage>eaau6020</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aau6020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30337381</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR53" publication-type="journal">Kremen, C. &#x00026; Merenlender, A. M. Landscapes that work for biodiversity and people. <italic>Science</italic><bold>362</bold>, eaau6020 (2018).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30337381</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR54" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hinojosa</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Geographical heterogeneity in mountain grasslands dynamics in the austrian-italian Tyrol region</article-title><source>Appl. Geogr.</source><year>2019</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>50</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apgeog.2019.03.006</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR54" publication-type="journal">Hinojosa, L. et al. Geographical heterogeneity in mountain grasslands dynamics in the Austrian-Italian Tyrol region. <italic>Appl. Geogr.</italic><bold>106</bold>, 50&#x02013;59 (2019).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR55" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Farkas</surname><given-names>JZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kov&#x000e1;cs</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nature conservation versus agriculture in the light of socio-economic changes over the last half-century&#x02013;case study from a Hungarian national park</article-title><source>Land. Use Policy</source><year>2021</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>105131</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.landusepol.2020.105131</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR55" publication-type="journal">Farkas, J. Z. &#x00026; Kov&#x000e1;cs, A. D. Nature conservation versus agriculture in the light of socio-economic changes over the last half-century&#x02013;case study from a Hungarian national park. <italic>Land. Use Polic.</italic><bold>101</bold>, 105131 (2021).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR56" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Auffray</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Clement</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Looking for the local &#x02018;grant-grabbers&#x02019;: cattle farmers&#x02019; criticisms and emerging environmental subjectivities in southwestern France</article-title><source>J. Rural Stud.</source><year>2023</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>103091</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jrurstud.2023.103091</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR56" publication-type="journal">Auffray, M. &#x00026; Clement, F. Looking for the local &#x02018;grant-grabbers&#x02019;: cattle farmers&#x02019; criticisms and emerging environmental subjectivities in southwestern France. <italic>J. Rural Stud.</italic><bold>102</bold>, 103091 (2023).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR57" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nishizawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ecological&#x02013;economic modelling of traditional agroforestry to promote Farmland Biodiversity with cost-effective payments</article-title><source>Sustainability</source><year>2022</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>5615</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/su14095615</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR57" publication-type="journal">Nishizawa, T. et al. Ecological&#x02013;economic modelling of traditional agroforestry to promote farmland biodiversity with cost-effective payments. <italic>Sustainability</italic><bold>14</bold>, 5615 (2022).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Autonome Provinz Bozen. Landschaftspflegepr&#x000e4;mie: Kastanienhaine und Streuobstwiesen. In: Beitr. F&#x000f6;rderungen Pflegepr&#x000e4;mie. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://natur-raum.provinz.bz.it/de/landschaftspflegepramien">https://natur-raum.provinz.bz.it/de/landschaftspflegepramien</ext-link>. [Accessed 6 Dec 2022] (2021) .</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Autonome Provinz Bozen. <italic>Land- und Forstwirtschaft</italic> (Autonome Provinz Bozen - Amt f&#x000fc;r landwirtschaftliche Informationssysteme, 2021).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bundesamt f&#x000fc;r Landwirtschaft (BLW). Biodiversit&#x000e4;tsbeitr&#x000e4;ge. In: Schweiz. Eidgenoss. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.blw.admin.ch/blw/de/home/instrumente/direktzahlungen/biodiversitaetsbeitraege.html">https://www.blw.admin.ch/blw/de/home/instrumente/direktzahlungen/biodiversitaetsbeitraege.html</ext-link>. [Accessed 11 Nov 2024] (2024) .</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Schuler, J. <italic>Hier gibt es finanzielle Unterst&#x000fc;tzung f&#x000fc;r Agroforst-Projekte. Bauernztg</italic> (Schweiz. Agrar. AG, 2022).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hochstamm Suisse. F&#x000f6;rderprogramm f&#x000fc;r Hochstammb&#x000e4;ume in der Schweiz (2022&#x02013;2025). In: Klimaschutzprojekte. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.myclimate.org/de/informieren/klimaschutzprojekte/detail-klimaschutzprojekte/schweiz-hochstamm-7831/">https://www.myclimate.org/de/informieren/klimaschutzprojekte/detail-klimaschutzprojekte/schweiz-hochstamm-7831/</ext-link>. [Accessed 4 May 2023] (2022).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kaeser, A., Sereke, F., Dux, D. &#x00026; Herzog, F. Pflanzenbau. 128&#x02013;133 (2011).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Farmers&#x02019; Association of South Tyrol. Red Rooster: Farm Holidays in South Tyrol. In: Roter Hahn. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.roterhahn.it/en/">https://www.roterhahn.it/en/</ext-link>. Accessed 23 Feb 2024 (2023).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sortengarten S&#x000fc;dtirol. SoVie - Obst. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sovie.it/Obst/">http://www.sovie.it/Obst/</ext-link>. [Accessed 23 Feb 2024] (2023).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">EEA. European Digital Elevation Model (EU-DEM): version 1.1. (2016).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Tasser, E., Schermer, M., Siegl, G. &#x00026; Tappeiner, U. (eds) <italic>Wir Landschaftmacher: Vom Sein und Werden der Kulturlandschaft in Nord-, Ost- und S&#x000fc;dtirol</italic> (Athesia, 2012).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR68" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tasser</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruffini</surname><given-names>FV</given-names></name><name><surname>Tappeiner</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An integrative approach for analysing landscape dynamics in diverse cultivated and natural mountain areas</article-title><source>Landsc. Ecol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>611</fpage><lpage>628</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10980-009-9337-9</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR68" publication-type="journal">Tasser, E., Ruffini, F. V. &#x00026; Tappeiner, U. An integrative approach for analysing landscape dynamics in diverse cultivated and natural mountain areas. <italic>Landsc. Ecol.</italic><bold>24</bold>, 611&#x02013;628 (2009).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR69" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anderle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The contribution of landscape features, climate and topography in shaping taxonomical and functional diversity of avian communities in a heterogeneous Alpine region</article-title><source>Oecologia</source><year>2022</year><volume>199</volume><fpage>499</fpage><lpage>512</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00442-022-05134-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35192064</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR69" publication-type="journal">Anderle, M. et al. The contribution of landscape features, climate and topography in shaping taxonomical and functional diversity of avian communities in a heterogeneous Alpine region. <italic>Oecologia</italic><bold>199</bold>, 499&#x02013;512 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35192064</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">ASTAT. 6. Landwirtschaftsz&#x000e4;hlung 2010. 317 (2013).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR71"><label>71.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR71" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marsoner</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Simion</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Giombini</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Egarter Vigl</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Candiago</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A detailed land use/land cover map for the European Alps macro region</article-title><source>Sci. Data</source><year>2023</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>468</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41597-023-02344-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37468492</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR71" publication-type="journal">Marsoner, T., Simion, H., Giombini, V., Egarter Vigl, L. &#x00026; Candiago, S. A detailed land use/land cover map for the European Alps macro region. <italic>Sci. Data</italic><bold>10</bold>, 468 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37468492</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR72"><label>72.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">ESRI. ArcGIS<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> Desktop 10.7.1. (2019).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR73"><label>73.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Posit team. <italic>RStudio v2023.12.1.402</italic> (Integrated Development Environment for R, 2024).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR74"><label>74.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">R Core Team. R v4.3.1: A language and environment for statistical computing. (2023).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR75"><label>75.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR75" publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Levene</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Olkin</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Robust tests for Equality of variances</article-title><source>Contrib. Porbability Stat. Essays Honor Harold Hotel</source><year>1960</year><publisher-loc>Calif</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Stanford</publisher-name><fpage>278</fpage><lpage>292</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR75" publication-type="book">Levene, H. Robust tests for Equality of variances. In: (ed Olkin, I.) Contrib. Porbability Stat. Essays Honor Harold Hotel. Stanford, Calif.: Univ. Press, 278&#x02013;292 (1960).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR76"><label>76.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Revelle, W. <italic>Psych v2.4.1: Procedures for Psychological</italic> (Psychometric, and Personality Research, 2024).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR77"><label>77.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR77" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Welch</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>THE GENERALIZATION OF &#x02018;STUDENT&#x02019;S&#x02019; PROBLEM WHEN SEVERAL DIFFERENT POPULATION VARLANCES ARE INVOLVED</article-title><source>Biometrika</source><year>1947</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>28</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20287819</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR77" publication-type="journal">Welch, B. L. The generalization of &#x02018;student&#x02019;s&#x02019; problem when several different population varlances are involved.<italic>Biometrika</italic><bold>34</bold>, 28&#x02013;35 (1947).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20287819</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR78"><label>78.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR78" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Student</surname></name></person-group><article-title>The probable error of a Mean</article-title><source>Biometrika</source><year>1908</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2331554</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR78" publication-type="journal">Student. The probable error of a mean. <italic>Biometrika</italic><bold>6</bold>, 1 (1908).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article>