<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="correction"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Oncol Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Oncol Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Oncology Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1021-335X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1791-2431</issn><publisher><publisher-name>D.A. Spandidos</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40376979</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12099282</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3892/or.2025.8914</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">OR-54-1-08914</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Corrigendum</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>[Corrigendum] miR-504 promotes tumour growth and metastasis in human osteosarcoma by targeting TP53INP1</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Qingchun</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>Sixiang</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>Xing</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Junlong</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Wei</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>7</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>14</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><!--PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>.--><volume>54</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>81</elocation-id><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; 2025 Cai et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, reproduction and adaptation in any medium and for any purpose provided that it is properly attributed. For attribution, the original author(s), title, publication source (PeerJ) and either DOI or URL of the article must be cited.</license-p></license></permissions></article-meta></front><body><p>Oncol Rep 38: <related-article related-article-type="corrected-article" ext-link-type="doi" id="RA1" xlink:href="10.3892/or.2017.5983" vol="38" page="2993">2993&#x02013;3000</related-article>, 2017; DOI: 10.3892/or.2017.5983</p><p>Following the publication of the above article, an interested reader drew to the authors' attention that, concerning the Transwell assay experiments shown in <xref rid="f2-or-54-1-08914" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2F</xref> on p. 2997, the &#x02018;Blank&#x02019; and &#x02018;Normal control&#x02019; data panels featured a strikingly similar overlapping area, such that these data had apparently been derived from the same original source where the results of differently performed experiments were meant to have been shown.</p><p>After having re-examined their original data, the authors realized that <xref rid="f2-or-54-1-08914" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2F</xref> had inadvertently been assembled incorrectly; however, the authors were able to repeat these experiments, and the revised version of <xref rid="f2-or-54-1-08914" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>, now including new data for the experiments shown in <xref rid="f2-or-54-1-08914" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2F</xref>, is shown on the next page. Note that the errors made in terms of assembling the data in <xref rid="f2-or-54-1-08914" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> did not greatly affect either the results or the conclusions reported in this paper, and all the authors agree to the publication of this corrigendum. The authors regret that these errors went unnoticed prior to the publication of their article, and are grateful to the Editor of <italic>Oncology Reports</italic> for allowing them this opportunity to publish this corrigendum. They also apologize to the readership for any inconvenience caused.</p></body><floats-group><fig position="float" id="f2-or-54-1-08914"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>miR-504 enhances 143B cell growth and promotes metastasis <italic>in vitro</italic> by targeting TP53INP1. (A) The Cell Counting Kit-8 assay was performed to evaluate cell proliferation 3&#x02013;7 days post-transfection. (B) The clone formation assay was performed to examine cell activity at 9 days post-transfection. (C) The cell cycle distribution was determined by flow cytometric analysis with propidium iodide staining. (D) The proportion of apoptotic cells was determined by flow cytometric analysis with Annexin-V and propidium iodide staining. (E) Transwell assay results. The images show the cells that travelled through the micropore membrane without Matrigel. (F) Transwell assay results. The images show the cells that travelled through the micropore membrane with Matrigel. Normal control, 143B cells transfected with the normal control; miR-504 mimic, 143B cells transfected with the miR-504 mimic; miR-504 inhibitor, 143B cells transfected with the miR-504 inhibitor. *P&#x0003c;0.05, **P&#x0003c;0.01 vs. the normal control. All experiments were performed in triplicate. TP53INP1, tumour protein p53-inducible nuclear protein 1.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="or-54-01-08914-g00" position="float"/></fig></floats-group></article>