<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Psychol Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Psychol Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PSM</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Psychological Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0033-2917</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1469-8978</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40384216</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12094619</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0033291725001072</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S0033291725001072</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Impact of young adult life transitions on adult mental health problems: a propensity score analysis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1348-7781</contrib-id><name><surname>Copeland</surname><given-names>William E.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Prytherch</surname><given-names>Shania</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rothenberg</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Godwin</surname><given-names>Jennifer W.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gaydosh</surname><given-names>Lauren</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gutin</surname><given-names>Iliya</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>Guangyu</given-names></name><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shanahan</surname><given-names>Lilly</given-names></name><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Psychiatry, <institution>University of Vermont</institution>, <city>Burlington</city>, <state>VT</state>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Center for Child and Family Policy, <institution>Duke University</institution>, <city>Durham</city>, <state>NC</state>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Sociology Department, <institution>University of North Carolina</institution>, <city>Chapel Hill</city>, <state>NC</state>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>Center of Policy Research, <institution>Syracuse University</institution>, <city>Syracuse</city>, <state>NY</state>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff5"><label>5</label>Cardiovascular Medicine, <institution>Yale University</institution>, <city>New Haven</city>, <state>CT</state>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff6"><label>6</label>Department of Psychology, <institution>University of Zurich</institution>, <city>Zurich</city>, <country>Switzerland</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold>Corresponding author:</bold> William E. Copeland; Email: <email>william.copeland@med.uvm.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="collection" iso-8601-date="2025"><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>55</volume><elocation-id>e152</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>24</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>09</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Author(s)</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article, distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution licence (<uri xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</uri>), which permits unrestricted re-use, distribution and reproduction, provided the original article is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="S0033291725001072a.pdf"/><abstract><sec id="sec1"><title>Background</title><p>Mental health problems commonly persist from childhood to adulthood. This study tested whether young adult life transitions can improve adult mental health symptoms after adjusting for childhood mental health symptoms.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>Methods</title><p>The analysis uses data from the prospective, representative Great Smoky Mountains Study. Life transitions (e.g., high school completion, partnering, parenthood, and living independently) were assessed up to three times in young adulthood (ages 18 to 26; 3,241 observations). A cumulative variable counted the number of young adult transitions. Emotional, substance use, and antisocial personality symptoms were assessed at age 30 (1,154 participants or 81.2% of the original sample). Propensity models adjusted for early life adversities and psychiatric symptoms.</p></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>Results</title><p>Multiple young adult transitions were common (m&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;4.62; SD&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1.57). After adjusting for childhood mental health problems and adversities, each additional transition was significantly associated with a reduction in subsequent adult emotional symptoms (&#x003b2;&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;0.34, 95% CI: &#x02212;0.59, &#x02212;0.08, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.01) and adult antisocial personality disorder symptoms (&#x003b2;&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;0.08, 95% CI: &#x02212;0.14, &#x02212;0.02, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001. These associations were stronger in males than in females. Young adult transitions were not associated with reductions in subsequent substance use symptoms (&#x003b2;&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;0.04; 95% CI: &#x02212;0.11, 0.03, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.30). Young adult transitions related to educational milestones and consistent employment were associated with the largest reductions in symptoms.</p></sec><sec id="sec4"><title>Conclusions</title><p>In this cohort study, life transitions during young adulthood were associated with reduced emotional and behavioral symptoms in adulthood. These transitions may constitute a potential mental health turning point and a specific, modifiable target for social policies.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><title>Keywords</title><kwd>epidemiology</kwd><kwd>mental health</kwd><kwd>psychopathology</kwd><kwd>transitions</kwd><kwd>young adulthood</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="2"/><table-count count="3"/><ref-count count="45"/><page-count count="8"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec5"><title>Introduction</title><p>Mental health problems constitute a significant public health burden in childhood, and these problems have the potential to affect both physical and mental health across the lifespan (Erskine et al., <xref rid="r23" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Harhay &#x00026; King, <xref rid="r26" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). Prospective longitudinal studies that have followed participants from childhood into adulthood consistently show, across cohorts and across the high-income countries, that common childhood psychiatric disorders are associated with an increased risk of adult disorders and poorer functional outcomes (Caspi et al., <xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Copeland et al., <xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Copeland, Shanahan, Costello, &#x00026; Angold, <xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Copeland, Wolke, Shanahan, &#x00026; Costello, <xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). However, to date, there is little evidence that treatment of childhood mental health problems via services received in community settings improves adult mental health outcomes at all (Copeland, Tong, &#x00026; Shanahan, <xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>; J&#x000f6;rg et al., <xref rid="r30" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). Therefore, the search continues for interventions, either through the community mental health system or naturally occurring, that might prospectively improve adult functioning. This study investigated whether achieving specific transitions or milestones during young adulthood has the potential to improve adult mental health functioning.</p><p>The period spanning from adolescence to adulthood is a pivotal juncture in an individual&#x02019;s life, marked by profound changes and exploration (Arnett, <xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>). Developmental psychologist, Jefferey Jensen Arnett, characterized the ages between 18 and 25 as &#x0201c;<italic toggle="yes">emerging adulthood,&#x0201d;</italic> distinct from both adolescence and young adulthood, as many individuals at this age report that they do not feel like an adult nor do they see themselves as adolescents (Arnett, <xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>). During this period, some individuals experience increased autonomy, allowing them to make their own choices without the demands of adult responsibilities and giving them freedom to explore different experiences and pathways (Arnett, <xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>). Others may face immediate financial and familial responsibilities. Still others may follow prescribed pathways focused on educational completion, employment, and partnering (Lee et al., <xref rid="r35" ref-type="bibr">2023</xref>; Lee, Wickrama, O&#x02019;Neal, &#x00026; Prado, <xref rid="r36" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). Despite these differences, young adulthood is a period when most young people navigate key educational, vocational, financial, and social transitions that often lead to adult roles and responsibilities. Mastering such transitions or milestones (e.g., college completion) has the potential to have a positive influence on mental well-being.</p><p>The study of young adult transitions has typically focused on individual transitions. For example, obtaining stable full-time employment (i.e., no periods of unemployment) has been associated with a decreased risk of substance use (i.e., cannabis, nicotine, and alcohol) and depressive disorders (Melchior et al., <xref rid="r42" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Howard, Galambos, &#x00026; Krahn, <xref rid="r28" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). Being married by age 32 is associated with higher life satisfaction in both men and women, whereas being divorced or separated is associated with reduced life satisfaction in women (Howard et al., <xref rid="r28" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). Additional studies have highlighted the negative impact of failing to meet specific educational, vocational, and financial milestones (Cadigan, Duckworth, Parker, &#x00026; Lee, <xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>; Howard et al., <xref rid="r28" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Liem, Lustig, &#x00026; Dillon, <xref rid="r39" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Melchior et al., <xref rid="r42" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>) or meeting them prematurely (e.g., parenthood (Grundstr&#x000f6;m, Kiviruusu, Konttinen, &#x00026; Berg, <xref rid="r25" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>). To date, only one study has examined the cumulative impact of multiple young adult transitions on adult functioning and found that an increased number of transitions was associated with a reduction in cannabis and illicit drug use at age 30 (Rothenberg et al., <xref rid="r48" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>). Such investigations are rare as they require studies which follow participants from childhood to adulthood while tracking mental health status and a broad range of educational, social, and employment-related transitions.</p><p>The current study leveraged a prospective cohort study that has followed participants through childhood/adolescence, young adulthood, and into adulthood to examine the impact of young adulthood life transitions on mental health and substance use symptoms after adjusting for child mental health and 24 early adversities. The study focuses on the impact of multiple transitions, as opposed to individual transitions one-at-a-time, to adjust for those who prioritize some transitions over others or those who lag on some transitions. Similar to Rothenberg et al. (<xref rid="r48" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>), the study indexes a person&#x02019;s cumulative rather than individual milestones. The study prospectively assessed &#x02013; and adjusted for &#x02013; childhood experiences, such as adversities and mental health problems that are associated with a person&#x02019;s likelihood of navigating individual transitions. To stringently address our question, we employed the generalized propensity score (GPS) method that uses the inverse probability of treatment weights to balance young adults with varying numbers of positive transitions on the confounding characteristics (Imai &#x00026; van Dyk, <xref rid="r29" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>). This approach approximates a randomized trial within an observational study and adjusts for nonrandomization.(Rosenbaum &#x00026; Rubin, <xref rid="r46" ref-type="bibr">1983</xref>; VanderWeele, <xref rid="r53" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>) As such, this study investigated the impact of cumulative life transitions net of the well-known impact of child mental health problems and adversities on both adult mental health and substance use problems.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="sec6"><title>Methods</title><sec sec-type="other" id="sec7"><title>Participants</title><p>This report follows the STROBE reporting guidelines for cohort studies (von Elm et al., <xref rid="r54" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). The Great Smoky Mountains Study is a longitudinal, representative study of children in 11 predominantly rural counties of Southeastern US (see (Copeland, Angold, Shanahan, &#x00026; Costello, <xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>) that began in 1993. Three cohorts of children, ages 9, 11, and 13&#x000a0;years, were recruited from a pool of some 12,000 children using a two-stage sampling design, resulting in N&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1,420 participants (49% female participants; see also (Costello et al., <xref rid="r21" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>). First, potential participants were randomly selected from the population using a household equal probability design. Next, participants were screened for risk of psychopathology and participants screening high were oversampled in addition to a random sample of the rest. In addition, American Indians were oversampled to constitute 25% of the sample. Sampling weights were applied to adjust for differential probability of selection and allow results to generalize to the broader population (Copeland et al., <xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Costello et al., <xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr">1996</xref>, <xref rid="r21" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>).</p><p>Annual assessments were completed with the participants, and their primary caregivers until participants turned 16&#x000a0;years old; thereafter only participants were interviewed at ages 19, 21, 25, and 30 (data from all are used here). An average of 83% of all possible interviews (N&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;11,233) have been completed; by age 30, 39 participants had died. Additional information is provided in Supplementary <uri xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.1017/S0033291725001072">Tables&#x000a0;S1</uri>&#x000a0;and&#x000a0;<uri xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.1017/S0033291725001072">S2</uri>. Before interviews, all participants, and their parents (up to age 18) signed informed consent forms approved by the Duke University Medical Center ethical review boards. Participants received compensation for their time ($100 for most recent waves).</p></sec><sec sec-type="other" id="sec8"><title>Childhood/adolescent variables</title><p>The structured Child and Adolescent Psychiatric Assessment (CAPA) was completed with the participant and a parent in childhood/adolescence at annual assessments between ages 9 and 16 (Angold &#x00026; Costello, <xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>). The CAPA collected information on sex assigned at birth, race/ethnicity, parental educational attainment, parental income, overall family SES, and urban/rural status. The CAPA interview also assesses information related to child adversities and child psychiatric symptoms. In both cases, information was aggregated across all available observations to indicate if the child or parent ever reported the psychiatric symptom or the adverse experience.</p><p>
<bold>Childhood adversity</bold> variables include scales indexing contextual risk factors (16 variables related to poverty, family structure, parental employment, out-of-home placement), family dysfunction (nine variables including poor parenting, parental conflict, neglect, and poor relationships between family members), and parent problems (nine variables including parent mental health, substance problems, and criminality).</p><p>The CAPA assesses <bold>child psychiatric symptoms</bold> over a 3-month primary period. A symptom was counted as present if reported by either parent or child or both. Scoring programs written in SAS combine information about the date of onset, duration, and intensity of each symptom to create DSM-IV diagnoses. A two-week test&#x02013;retest reliability study of CAPA diagnoses in children aged 10 through 18 found kappa values ranged from 0.5 for conduct disorder to <italic toggle="yes">&#x0039a;</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1.0 for substance dependence (Angold &#x00026; Costello, <xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1995</xref>). Common childhood psychiatric disorders assessed included anxiety disorders, mood disorders, conduct disorder, oppositional defiant disorder, ADHD, and substance disorders. For this analysis, child psychiatric symptoms were estimated with two variables: (1) <bold>emotional symptoms</bold> including all nonoverlapping symptoms of mood and anxiety disorders and (2) <bold>behavioral symptoms</bold> including all nonoverlapping symptoms of conduct disorder, oppositional defiant disorder, ADHD, and substance disorders. A similar set of emotional and behavioral symptom variables were derived based on the young adult observations.</p></sec><sec sec-type="other" id="sec9"><title>Young adult life transitions</title><p>Young adult transitions were assessed using the Young Adult Psychiatric Assessment (YAPA) (Angold et al., <xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>), an upward extension of the CAPA interview administered to the participants at ages 19, 21, and 25. These transitions are related to educational, financial, vocational, social, and familial milestones that many (but not all) eventually meet. These milestones are often generally considered adaptive steps to adult roles and responsibilities. <xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> lists the eight transitions, their descriptions, and their prevalence in the sample. The primary focus of this analysis was a cumulative life transition variable that summed the eight individual transitions.<table-wrap position="float" id="tab1"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Description of young adult positive transitions</p></caption><alternatives><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transition</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Description</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><p>
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Finish high school/GED</p></list-item></list></p>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Completed high school or GED equivalent</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1071</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><p>
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Complete some college</p></list-item></list></p>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Completed at least some college-level coursework</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">676</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><p>
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Obtain steady employment</p></list-item></list></p>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Has 30+ hours/week job with no history of being fired or quitting without another job</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">659</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><p>
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Live independently</p></list-item></list></p>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lives apart from home of origin</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">918</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><p>
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Attain financial stability</p></list-item></list></p>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reports good financial standing, paying bills on time and has health insurance</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">689</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><p>
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Have a steady partner</p></list-item></list></p>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Has long term partner without significant substance use problems or criminality</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">337</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><p>
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Become a parent</p></list-item></list></p>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Became a parent after age 20</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">514</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><p>
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Be connected socially</p></list-item></list></p>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reports frequent contact with peers, best friend and peer confidant</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">648</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.5</td></tr></tbody></table><graphic xlink:href="S0033291725001072_tab1" position="float"/></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Note:</italic> N&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1281; Ns are unweighted and %s are weighted.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec sec-type="other" id="sec10"><title>Adult mental health symptoms</title><p>This study assessed psychiatric disorders and substance disorders at age 30. Adult variables were assessed using the YAPA. The assessment of adult psychiatric functioning resembled that of childhood disorders but relied only on self-reports. <bold>Emotional symptoms</bold> included any symptoms of major depressive disorder, dysthymic disorder, generalized anxiety disorder, panic disorder, social phobia, or specific phobia. <bold>Substance symptoms</bold> included DSM-defined substance use disorder symptoms related to nicotine, alcohol, cannabis, or an illicit drug (e.g. opioids or hallucinogens). To index externalizing symptoms, antisocial personality disorder symptoms (e.g., criminal behavior, lack of empathy, physical violence) were included.</p></sec><sec sec-type="other" id="sec11"><title>Analytic strategy</title><p>All statistical analyses accounted for the two-stage sampling design using sampling weights. Propensity score methods improve the covariate balance through matching, weighting, or stratification to make causal inferences in observational studies (Li, Morgan, &#x00026; Zaslavsky, <xref rid="r38" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; Rosenbaum &#x00026; Rubin, <xref rid="r46" ref-type="bibr">1983</xref>, <xref rid="r47" ref-type="bibr">1984</xref>; VanderWeele, <xref rid="r53" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). Here, we estimate causal effects for the ordinal exposure variable of cumulative transition using GPSs estimated via generalized boosted models (GBMs) (Imai &#x00026; van Dyk, <xref rid="r29" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>; Zhu, Coffman, &#x00026; Ghosh, <xref rid="r56" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). The GPS estimation is achieved through the &#x0201c;twangContinuous&#x0201d; package (Coffman &#x00026; Griffin, <xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>), where the GBM is survey-weighted and set to have 10,000 trees, the amount of shrinkage as 0.01, and the interaction depth as 3 to allow for the exploration of sufficiently complex models. Covariates for the GBM include age, sex assigned at birth, race/ethnicity, parental educational attainment, parental income, overall family SES, urban/rural status, sum scores of childhood adversity variables (i.e., contextual risk, family dysfunction, parent problems), child psychiatric symptoms scores (i.e., total emotional and behavioral symptoms), and young adult psychiatric symptoms scores (i.e., total emotional and behavioral symptoms). The balance measure on covariates as a function of the number of iterations in GBM was checked to ensure satisfactory balance is achieved under our model setup (see Supplementary <uri xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.1017/S0033291725001072">Figure&#x000a0;S1</uri>). Balance of all covariates before and after applying for the GPS weights was assessed by Spearman&#x02019;s correlation between each covariate and cumulative transition.</p><p>The GPS weights were then used to compute inverse probability weights. Inverse probability weights were combined with the survey weights for all outcome models (Austin, Jembere, &#x00026; Chiu, <xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; Lenis, Nguyen, Dong, &#x00026; Stuart, <xref rid="r37" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>), where all variables used to derive the propensity scores were included as covariates in the outcome models to ensure that results are doubly robust. Linear regression models were used for the symptom outcomes. Dose&#x02013;response curves for each level of cumulative transition are presented for each outcome. In addition, each cumulative transition item was modeled independently as an exposure variable, and the propensity score estimation for each item was done through GBM with the same model specifications as that for the cumulative transition score. Balance checks on covariates based on standardized mean differences and survey-weighted linear outcome regression analysis were performed to estimate the effect of each single transition item. All analyses were performed on R 4.3.2 with adapted code from package &#x0201c;PSweight&#x0201d; for all outcome regression models (Zhou et al., <xref rid="r55" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Findings are considered statistically significant at <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05, with point estimates and confidence intervals presented for all findings.</p></sec><sec sec-type="other" id="sec12"><title>Missing data</title><p>Of the original 1420 participants, all were assessed during childhood/adolescence (ages 9 to 16), 1281 (or 90.2%) were assessed in young adulthood (ages 18&#x02013;27), and 1,154 (or 81.2%) were assessed in adulthood (at age 30). Participation in young adult or adult assessments was not associated with childhood mental health symptoms, sex assigned at birth, or race/ethnicity. Missingness of individual adult diagnostic or symptom items within completed adult interviews was rare (~1%). Twenty complete datasets were imputed to address missingness in both outcomes and covariates (Tong, Li, &#x00026; Allen, <xref rid="r50" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>). R package &#x0201c;mice&#x0201d; was employed for both the imputation and synthesis of results in regression analysis (van Buuren &#x00026; Groothuis-Oudshoorn, <xref rid="r52" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec13"><title>Results</title><sec sec-type="other" id="sec14"><title>Patterns of young adult transitions</title><p>
<xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> displays the percentages of participants who had completed the different young adult life transitions between ages 19 and 25 (unweighted ns and weighted percentages). Many of the transitions were completed by more than half of the participants, including finishing high school, completing some college, obtaining steady employment, living independently, and being connected socially. Having a stable partner and becoming a parent were somewhat less common; about 30% of the participants reported each of these transitions. Overall, the mean number was 4.62 out of 8 possible positive transitions (SD&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1.57). A higher number of life transitions was associated with being female (4.98 versus 4.29, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.01) and white (4.72 versus 3.84, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.01). In zero-order correlations, cumulative young adult life transitions were significantly associated with lower subsequent levels of adult emotional and substance use symptoms (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>s&#x000a0;&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.15, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.01 and&#x000a0;&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.19, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.01, respectively).</p></sec><sec sec-type="other" id="sec15"><title>Propensity score analysis</title><p>
<xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> shows the average Spearman&#x02019;s correlations across the 20 imputed datasets between the covariates, as well as the cumulative transition variable before and after the application of the inverse probability of treatment weights obtained from the propensity score model. The unweighted correlations indicate strong associations (rho &#x0003e;0.5) between parental educational attainment and cumulative life transitions and small to moderate (<italic toggle="yes">rs</italic> 0.1 to 0.49) associations of the transition variable with symptom levels, sex, mean parental income, and other early adversity measures. This pattern suggests, as expected, that young adult life transitions are strongly associated with earlier family functioning, mental health functioning, and adversity exposure. All correlations were reduced to less than 0.1 after the application of the propensity score weights, suggesting desirable covariate balance (<xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> and Supplementary <uri xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.1017/S0033291725001072">Figure&#x000a0;S2</uri>).<table-wrap position="float" id="tab2"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Spearman weighted and unweighted correlations for covariates with and without inverse probability of treatment weights from propensity score modeling</p></caption><alternatives><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1" valign="bottom"/><th align="center" colspan="2" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">Overall sample</th><th align="center" colspan="2" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">Males</th><th align="center" colspan="2" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">Females</th></tr><tr><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unweighted correlations</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weighted correlations</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unweighted correlations</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weighted correlations</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unweighted correlations</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weighted correlations</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.216</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.006</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Race</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.078</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.012</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.086</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.078</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.040</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.043</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethnicity</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.067</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.014</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.070</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.085</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.006</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 2</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.031</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.017</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.057</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.016</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.022</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort 3</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.033</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.029</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.060</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.024</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.002</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parent educational attainment</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.509</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.093</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.512</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.072</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.460</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.065</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean parental income</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.282</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.091</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.324</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.034</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.246</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.061</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall SES</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.248</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.063</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.293</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.010</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.204</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.023</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urban vs rural status</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.008</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.016</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.044</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.064</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.033</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.018</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Child adversities</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Contextual risk</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.288</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.070</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.345</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.024</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.243</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.027</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Family dysfunction</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.098</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.014</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.112</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.024</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.056</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Parent problem</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.200</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.003</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.265</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.023</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.131</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.018</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Psychiatric symptoms</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Child emotional sx.</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.155</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.048</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.181</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.053</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.177</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.014</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Child behavioral sx.</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.233</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.044</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.215</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.083</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.168</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.022</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;YA emotional sx.</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.222</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.032</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.211</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.021</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.143</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.015</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;YA behavioral sx.</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.076</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.012</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.097</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.020</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.149</td><td align="char" char="." valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.002</td></tr></tbody></table><graphic xlink:href="S0033291725001072_tab2" position="float"/></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><p>Abbreviations: YA&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;young adult. SES&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;socioeconomic status. sx&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;symptoms.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p>
<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1a&#x02013;c</xref> shows the average treatment effect estimates of the cumulative young adult transition variable on adult emotional, substance use, and antisocial symptoms across the 20 imputed datasets. Values below zero indicate that the cumulative transition variable is associated with a <italic toggle="yes">decrease</italic> in adult psychiatric symptoms. The average treatment effect of the transition variable (pooled across the 20 imputed datasets using Rubin&#x02019;s formula) on adult emotional symptoms was &#x02212;0.34, 95% CI: &#x02212;0.59, &#x02212;0.08, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.01. Thus, each additional life transition was associated with a reduction, by a third of a point, in the total emotional disorder symptoms. The average treatment effect of the cumulative life transition variable on adult substance use symptoms was not statistically significant (&#x02212;0.04; 95% CI: &#x02212;0.11, 0.03, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.30). Finally, the average treatment effect of the life transition variable on adult antisocial personality disorder symptoms was &#x02212;0.08, 95% CI: &#x02212;0.14, &#x02212;0.02, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001. The estimated average dose&#x02013;response functions between cumulative young adult transitions and adult emotional, antisocial, or substance use symptoms are presented in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>. The emotional symptoms decreased with each additional transition for up to 4+ life transitions, after which the association attenuated, while antisocial personality disorder symptoms continued to decrease linearly.<fig position="float" id="fig1"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Average treatment effect of life transitions for emotional, antisocial personality, and substance-related psychiatric symptoms in adulthood for (a) the overall sample, (b) Males, (c) Females.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="S0033291725001072_fig1" position="float"/></fig>
<fig position="float" id="fig2"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Dose&#x02013;response relationship between number of life transitions and adult emotional, antisocial personality, and substance-use-related psychiatric symptoms.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="S0033291725001072_fig2" position="float"/></fig></p></sec><sec sec-type="other" id="sec16"><title>Sex differences</title><p>
<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1b,c</xref> shows the average regression coefficient estimates of cumulative young adult transitions on adult emotional and substance-related symptoms for <italic toggle="yes">males</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">females.</italic> The average treatment effects of the transition variable (pooled across 20 imputed datasets using Rubin&#x02019;s formula) on male adults&#x02019; emotional symptoms was &#x02212;0.43 (95% CI-0.76, &#x02212;0.19, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.01, which means that for each additional positive transition, there was nearly a half-point reduction in the total emotional disorder symptoms for males. However, the average treatment effect of the transition variable for females was of smaller magnitude and not statistically significant (&#x02212;0.09; 95% CI-0.40, 0.21, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.55. The average treatment effect of the cumulative life transitions on substance-related psychiatric symptoms was not significant for either males (0.04; 95% CI-0.14, 0.06 <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.42) or females (&#x02212;0.03; 95% CI-0.14, 0.08 <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.62). The average treatment effect of the cumulative life transitions on antisocial personality disorder was significant for males (&#x02212;0.12; 95% CI: &#x02212;0.19, &#x02212;0.04, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.001) but not females (&#x02212;0.06; 95% CI: &#x02212;0.12, 0.01, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.12). Additional models compared findings for different symptom groups in American Indian and non-American Indian groups (Supplementary <uri xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.1017/S0033291725001072">Table&#x000a0;S3</uri>). Significant associations for emotional and antisocial personality disorder symptoms were observed for the non-American Indian group only.</p></sec><sec sec-type="other" id="sec17"><title>Individual transitions</title><p>In the follow-up analyses, propensity score methods were applied to each of the individual life transitions to test which transitions had the strongest associations with adult symptoms. In terms of formal statistical significance, few individual young adult transitions showed significant effects on either emotional, antisocial personality, or substance-related symptoms in adulthood (see <xref rid="tab3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). In terms of effect size, individual life transitions with the largest average treatment effect sizes for emotional symptoms were completing high school, financial independence, and stable employment. For antisocial and substance use symptoms, the life transitions with the largest average treatment effects were completing some college coursework, completing high school, and stable employment. In contrast, the smallest average treatment effect sizes were associated with social transitions, including social connectedness, becoming a parent, and living independently.<table-wrap position="float" id="tab3"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Associations of each individual positive transition with adult emotional, antisocial, and substance-related symptoms</p></caption><alternatives><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1" valign="bottom"/><th align="center" colspan="3" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">Emotional symptoms</th><th align="center" colspan="3" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">Antisocial personality symptoms</th><th align="center" colspan="3" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">Substance use symptoms</th></tr><tr><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transition</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Standard Error</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Standard Error</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Standard Error</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Social connectedness</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.07</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.62,0.49</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.02</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.13, 0.09</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.13</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.48,0.21</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stable job</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.51</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.12,0.11</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.26</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.37, &#x02212;0.14</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.23</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.60,0.14</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy partner</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.44</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.03,0.15</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.12</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.23, &#x02212;0.01</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.19</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.45,0.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Financial independence</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.65</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.35,0.04</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.12</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.23, 0.00</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.27,0.39</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High school diploma</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.93</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2.45,0.59</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.30</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.61, 0.01</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.35</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.17,0.47</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Complete some college</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.37</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.09,0.35</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.32</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.50, &#x02212;0.13</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.93</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2.45,0.59</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Becoming a parent</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.59,0.67</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.10, 0.15</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.04</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.31,0.23</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Living independently</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.09</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.77,0.60</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.07</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.20, 0.05</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.05</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.33,0.23</td></tr></tbody></table><graphic xlink:href="S0033291725001072_tab3" position="float"/></alternatives></table-wrap></p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec18"><title>Discussion</title><p>There are good reasons to look at young adult life transitions as possible turning points for mental health symptoms (Laub &#x00026; Sampson, <xref rid="r31" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>). The young adult period represents the handoff between development and maturity and between dependence and independence. It presents many individuals with the first opportunity to have more autonomy in making key life decisions that may support or undermine their mental health. This study tested whether transitions during this period could constitute turning points for improved mental health regardless of childhood struggles. Evidence was seen that young adult transitions may be turning points for some individuals: cumulative life transitions between ages 19 and 25 were associated with lower levels of subsequent emotional symptoms and antisocial personality disorder symptoms at age 30. This effect was generally limited to males and Non-American Indian participants and did not extend to substance use symptoms. These results provide a ray of hope that the choices and opportunities given to young adults can improve their subsequent health and well-being.</p><p>The current study advances our knowledge of young adult life transitions in the following ways. First, it prospectively followed participants throughout childhood and adolescence. This research design allowed us to account for individual factors, such as emotional and behavioral functioning in childhood and young adulthood and for family factors, such as family income and parental educational attainment, which were strongly associated with young adult transitions. Second, it assessed a range of young adult educational, financial, and social transitions throughout an extended period of young adulthood from ages 19 to 25. As such, this approach accounts for young adults who may prioritize some transitions over others and for young adults who may lag others in their developmental progression. Finally, this combination of prospective design, limited attrition, and in-depth assessment of childhood and young adulthood was coupled with the GPS method to provide a rigorous test of the impact of positive young adult transitions on subsequent mental health.</p><sec sec-type="other" id="sec19"><title>Caveats</title><p>At the same time, these findings should be interpreted with caution for several reasons. First, this study included a representative sample of participants from 11 rural counties in North Carolina, but it is not representative of the U.S. population. African Americans and Latinos were underrepresented, and American Indians were overrepresented as compared to the US population. Second, the optimal design for testing the impact of positive adult transitions on mental health symptoms would involve a randomized trial. As that was not feasible, this study applied a causal analytic approach to propensity score modeling in the context of an observational longitudinal study. This approach approximates a randomized control trial to the degree that all relevant covariates can be balanced. While this study accounted for many childhood and young adult correlates of life transitions, unmeasured confounding is still possible. Finally, the valence of specific transitions may vary between individuals based on their life circumstances and cultural values. For example, the American Community Survey has consistently shown significant race and ethnicity differences in patterns of residential independence that are not accounted for by financial circumstances alone (Treas &#x00026; Batalova, <xref rid="r51" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). Similarly, the milestone of stable employment may run counter to the values of subpopulations where family responsibilities are prioritized over employment success. It is important to be careful and aware of the questionable assumptions about the valence of specific milestones.</p><p>The current findings affirm the importance of studying cumulative life transitions across multiple domains. The only other study that looked at multiple young adult transitions at the same times suggested a beneficial effect on adult cannabis and illicit drug misuse, but they did not look at emotional or antisocial personality symptoms (Rothenberg et al., <xref rid="r48" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>). In that study, the benefit of positive transitions was limited to the experience of 0&#x02013;4 transitions with minimal additional benefit after 4+ transitions. This pattern is similar to that reported in other studies on the effects of protective factors earlier in the lifespan as well as associations of cumulative childhood risk factors/adversities with later health outcomes (Collishaw et al., <xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Putnam, Harris, &#x00026; Putnam, <xref rid="r45" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). In each of these cases, the effect of individual risk or protective factors was found to be additive until a particular threshold of diminishing returns was reached. In this study, all the benefits of young adult transitions were limited to men. As noted above, the literature on positive young adults&#x02019; transitions is limited, especially on potential sex-specific effects. At the same time, young adulthood is a period of peak risk for males for substance use, criminality and other risky behaviors. Our findings suggest this period of peak risk may also be a period of second opportunities given the right social and educational, and employment contexts. Future studies of the impacts of positive transitions on mental health in adulthood should adjust for childhood mental health symptoms and test for sex differences to further understand which transitions have sex-specific effects and why.</p><p>Not all individual young adult transitions had similar effects on adult emotional and antisocial personality symptoms. The follow-up analyses suggested that the main drivers of improved symptoms were vocational, educational, and financial transitions. This conclusion was generally supported by previous studies of these individual milestones. Obtaining full-time employment has been found to protect against depressive disorders (Howard et al., <xref rid="r28" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). Completing high school and obtaining a college degree have been found to be associated with a lower number of depressive symptoms than dropping out of high school or not going to college, even after controlling for disadvantages such as parental education level (Lee &#x00026; Yang, <xref rid="r34" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>; Liem et al., <xref rid="r39" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; McFarland &#x00026; Wagner, <xref rid="r40" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Ou, <xref rid="r44" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). On the other hand, social transitions such as having a strong support system and parenthood had minimal impact on mental health symptoms into adulthood. Research on these milestones has reflected their sometimes-heterogeneous impact. For example, parenthood has been linked to an increase in life satisfaction in the first year but to a decrease to below pre-pregnancy levels 3&#x02013;4&#x000a0;years after (Clark, Diener, Georgellis, &#x00026; Lucas, <xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Dyrdal &#x00026; Lucas, <xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). In addition, living independently by age 25 has not shown any benefit for later mental health (Grundstr&#x000f6;m et al., <xref rid="r25" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>; Howard et al., <xref rid="r28" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>).</p><p>The origins of adult mental health problems often lie in childhood and adolescence but not always (Caspi et al., <xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Copeland et al., <xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Copeland, Shanahan, Costello, &#x00026; Angold, <xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Copeland, Wolke, Shanahan, &#x00026; Costello, <xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). A key aim of population mental health research is to identify those interventions and experiences that have the potential to disrupt this common continuity of distress. Thus far, the candidates are limited, and the knowledge base is shallow. Even childhood mental health treatment has, thus far, failed to demonstrate such cross-developmental beneficial effects when studied in the real world (Copeland et al., <xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>; J&#x000f6;rg et al., <xref rid="r30" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). The current study suggests that some promising candidates may be naturally occurring and lying in the open. None of the transitions studied here are novel or necessarily out of reach for most young adults, but there are certainly more challenges for some than others. Most young adults &#x02013; even those from challenging backgrounds &#x02013; have already experienced multiple such life transitions. Moreover, these transitions appear to have a notable cumulative impact on psychiatric symptoms. Our findings suggest experiencing all six transitions could lead to an average of two symptoms of emotional disorders being reduced, regardless of one&#x02019;s mental health history or the early adversity they faced. This current study suggests that efforts to support these transitions have the potential to pay dividends in reducing adult distress and promoting prosocial adult behavior. The aspirations of educational success and consistent employment are shared across the ideological spectrum providing a potential source of consensus and leverage for successful public policy efforts.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec21"><title>Supporting information</title><supplementary-material id="sm01" position="float" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Copeland et al. supplementary material</title><p>Copeland et al. supplementary material</p></caption><media xlink:href="S0033291725001072sup001.docx" id="d67e1310" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="nts1"><title>Supplementary material</title><p>The supplementary material for this article can be found at <uri xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.1017/S0033291725001072">http://doi.org/10.1017/S0033291725001072</uri>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="sec20"><title>Competing interests</title><p>We have no conflicts of interests to disclose.</p></sec><ref-list id="refs1" content-type="normal"><title>References</title><ref id="r1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ref1"><string-name><surname>Angold</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Costello</surname>, <given-names>E. J.</given-names></string-name> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>A test-retest reliability study of child-reported psychiatric symptoms and diagnoses using the Child and Adolescent Psychiatric Assessment (CAPA-C)</article-title>. <source>Psychological Medicine</source>, <volume>25</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>755</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>762</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/s0033291700034991</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7480452</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ref2"><string-name><surname>Angold</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Costello</surname>, <given-names>E. J.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>The Child and Adolescent Psychiatric Assessment (CAPA)</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Academy of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry</source>, <volume>39</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>39</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>48</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00004583-200001000-00015</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10638066</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r3"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="ref3"><string-name><surname>Angold</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cox</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Prendergast</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rutter</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Simonoff</surname>, <given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Costello</surname>, <given-names>E. J.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Ascher</surname>, <given-names>B. H.</given-names></string-name> (<year>1999</year>). <source>The young adult psychiatric assessment (YAPA)</source>. <publisher-name>Duke University Medical Center</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ref4"><string-name><surname>Arnett</surname>, <given-names>J. J.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Emerging adulthood. A theory of development from the late teens through the twenties</article-title>. <source>The American Psychologist</source>, <volume>55</volume>(<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>469</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>480</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10842426</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ref6"><string-name><surname>Austin</surname>, <given-names>P. C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jembere</surname>, <given-names>N.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Chiu</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Propensity score matching and complex surveys</article-title>. <source>Statistical Methods in Medical Research</source>, <volume>27</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>1240</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1257</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0962280216658920</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27460539</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ref8"><string-name><surname>Cadigan</surname>, <given-names>J. M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duckworth</surname>, <given-names>J. C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Parker</surname>, <given-names>M. E.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>, <given-names>C. M.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Influence of developmental social role transitions on young adult substance use</article-title>. <source>Current Opinion in Psychology</source>, <volume>30</volume>, <fpage>87</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>91</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.copsyc.2019.03.006</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31048248</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ref9"><string-name><surname>Caspi</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Houts</surname>, <given-names>R. M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ambler</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Danese</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Elliott</surname>, <given-names>M. L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hariri</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harrington</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hogan</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Poulton</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ramrakha</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rasmussen</surname>, <given-names>L. J. H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reuben</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Richmond-Rakerd</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sugden</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wertz</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Williams</surname>, <given-names>B. S.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Moffitt</surname>, <given-names>T. E.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Longitudinal assessment of mental health disorders and comorbidities across 4 decades among participants in the Dunedin Birth Cohort study</article-title>. <source>JAMA Network Open</source>, <volume>3</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>e203221</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2020.3221</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32315069</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ref10"><string-name><surname>Clark</surname>, <given-names>A. E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Diener</surname>, <given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Georgellis</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Lucas</surname>, <given-names>R. E.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Lags and leads in life satisfaction: A test of the Baseline hypothesis</article-title>. <source>The Economic Journal</source>, <volume>118</volume>(<issue>529</issue>), <fpage>F222</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>F243</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r11"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="ref11"><string-name><surname>Coffman</surname>, <given-names>D. L.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Griffin</surname>, <given-names>B. A.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2021</year>). <italic toggle="yes">Brief Tutorial for twangContinuous. CRAN R-Project Website (2021).</italic>
<uri xlink:href="https://www.rand.org/pubs/external_publications/EP68549.html">https://www.rand.org/pubs/external_publications/EP68549.html</uri>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ref12"><string-name><surname>Collishaw</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pickles</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Messer</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rutter</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shearer</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Maughan</surname>, <given-names>B.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Resilience to adult psychopathology following childhood maltreatment: Evidence from a community sample</article-title>. <source>Child Abuse &#x00026; Neglect</source>, <volume>31</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>211</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>229</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chiabu.2007.02.004</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17399786</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ref13"><string-name><surname>Copeland</surname>, <given-names>W. E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Adair</surname>, <given-names>C. E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smetanin</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stiff</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Briante</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Colman</surname>, <given-names>I.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fergusson</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Horwood</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Poulton</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Costello</surname>, <given-names>E. J.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Angold</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Diagnostic transitions from childhood to adolescence to early adulthood</article-title>. <source>Journal of Child Psychology and Psychiatry, and Allied Disciplines</source>, <volume>54</volume>(<issue>7</issue>), <fpage>791</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>799</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jcpp.12062</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23451804</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ref14"><string-name><surname>Copeland</surname>, <given-names>W. E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Angold</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shanahan</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Costello</surname>, <given-names>E. J.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Longitudinal patterns of anxiety from childhood to adulthood: The Great Smoky Mountains Study</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Academy of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry</source>, <volume>53</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>21</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>33</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaac.2013.09.017</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24342383</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ref15"><string-name><surname>Copeland</surname>, <given-names>W. E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shanahan</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Costello</surname>, <given-names>E. J.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Angold</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Childhood and adolescent psychiatric disorders as predictors of young adult disorders</article-title>. <source>Archives of General Psychiatry</source>, <volume>66</volume>(<issue>7</issue>), <fpage>764</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>772</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archgenpsychiatry.2009.85</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19581568</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ref16"><string-name><surname>Copeland</surname>, <given-names>W. E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tong</surname>, <given-names>G.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Shanahan</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2022</year>). <article-title>Do &#x0201c;real world&#x0201d; childhood mental health services reduce risk for adult psychiatric disorders?</article-title>
<source>Journal of the American Academy of Child &#x00026; Adolescent Psychiatry</source>, <volume>61</volume>(<issue>8</issue>), <fpage>1041</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1049</lpage>, e7. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaac.2021.12.014</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35063586</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ref17"><string-name><surname>Copeland</surname>, <given-names>W. E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wolke</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shanahan</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Costello</surname>, <given-names>E. J.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Adult functional outcomes of common childhood psychiatric problems: A prospective, longitudinal study</article-title>. <source>JAMA Psychiatry</source>, <volume>72</volume>(<issue>9</issue>), <fpage>892</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>899</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamapsychiatry.2015.0730</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26176785</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ref20"><string-name><surname>Costello</surname>, <given-names>E. J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Angold</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Burns</surname>, <given-names>B. J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stangl</surname>, <given-names>D. K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tweed</surname>, <given-names>D. L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Erkanli</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Worthman</surname>, <given-names>C. M.</given-names></string-name> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>The Great Smoky Mountains Study of Youth. Goals, design, methods, and the prevalence of DSM-III-R disorders</article-title>. <source>Archives of General Psychiatry</source>, <volume>53</volume>(<issue>12</issue>), <fpage>1129</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1136</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archpsyc.1996.01830120067012</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8956679</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ref21"><string-name><surname>Costello</surname>, <given-names>E. J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mustillo</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Erkanli</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Keeler</surname>, <given-names>G.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Angold</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Prevalence and development of psychiatric disorders in childhood and adolescence</article-title>. <source>Archives of General Psychiatry</source>, <volume>60</volume>(<issue>8</issue>), <fpage>837</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>844</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archpsyc.60.8.837</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12912767</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ref22"><string-name><surname>Dyrdal</surname>, <given-names>G. M.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Lucas</surname>, <given-names>R. E.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Reaction and adaptation to the birth of a child: A couple-level analysis</article-title>. <source>Developmental Psychology</source>, <volume>49</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>749</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>761</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/a0028335</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22686177</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ref23"><string-name><surname>Erskine</surname>, <given-names>H. E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moffitt</surname>, <given-names>T. E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Copeland</surname>, <given-names>W. E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Costello</surname>, <given-names>E. J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ferrari</surname>, <given-names>A. J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Patton</surname>, <given-names>G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Degenhardt</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vos</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Whiteford</surname>, <given-names>H. A.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Scott</surname>, <given-names>J. G.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>A heavy burden on young minds: The global burden of mental and substance use disorders in children and youth</article-title>. <source>Psychological Medicine</source>, <volume>45</volume>(<issue>7</issue>), <fpage>1551</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1563</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0033291714002888</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25534496</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ref25"><string-name><surname>Grundstr&#x000f6;m</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kiviruusu</surname>, <given-names>O.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Konttinen</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Berg</surname>, <given-names>N.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2024</year>). <article-title>Reciprocal associations between parenthood and mental well-being &#x02013; A prospective analysis from age 16 to 52&#x000a0;years</article-title>. <source>Current Psychology</source>, <volume>43</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>2238</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2252</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12144-023-04487-3</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ref26"><string-name><surname>Harhay</surname>, <given-names>M. O.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>King</surname>, <given-names>C. H.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Global burden of disease in young people aged 10-24 years</article-title>. <source>Lancet (London, England)</source>, <volume>379</volume>(<issue>9810</issue>), <fpage>27</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(12)60019-1</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ref28"><string-name><surname>Howard</surname>, <given-names>A. L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Galambos</surname>, <given-names>N. L.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Krahn</surname>, <given-names>H. J.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Paths to success in young adulthood from mental health and life transitions in emerging adulthood</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Behavioral Development</source>, <volume>34</volume>(<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>538</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>546</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0165025410365803</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ref29"><string-name><surname>Imai</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>van Dyk</surname>, <given-names>D. A.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Causal inference with general treatment regimes: Generalizing the propensity score</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Statistical Association</source>, <volume>99</volume>(<issue>467</issue>), <fpage>854</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>866</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1198/016214504000001187</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ref30"><string-name><surname>J&#x000f6;rg</surname>, <given-names>F.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ormel</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reijneveld</surname>, <given-names>S. A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jansen</surname>, <given-names>D. E. M. C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Verhulst</surname>, <given-names>F. C.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Oldehinkel</surname>, <given-names>A. J.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Puzzling findings in studying the outcome of &#x0201c;real world&#x0201d; adolescent mental health services: The TRAILS study</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>, <volume>7</volume>(<issue>9</issue>), <fpage>e44704</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0044704</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23028584</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r31"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="ref31"><string-name><surname>Laub</surname>, <given-names>J. H.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Sampson</surname>, <given-names>R. J.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2003</year>). <source>Shared beginnings, divergent lives: Delinquent boys to age 70</source> (pp. ix, <fpage>338</fpage>). <publisher-name>Harvard University Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ref34"><string-name><surname>Lee</surname>, <given-names>K. S.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Yang</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2022</year>). <article-title>Educational attainment and emotional well-being in adolescence and adulthood</article-title>. <source>SSM. Mental Health</source>, <volume>2</volume>, <fpage>100138</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ssmmh.2022.100138</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36704067</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ref35"><string-name><surname>Lee</surname>, <given-names>T. K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wickrama</surname>, <given-names>K. A. S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>O&#x02019;Neal</surname>, <given-names>C. W.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Neppl</surname>, <given-names>T. K.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Reeb</surname>, <given-names>B. T.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2023</year>). <article-title>Life transition events and depressive symptom trajectories during young adulthood: The influence of adverse family and individual contexts in adolescence</article-title>. <source>Developmental Psychology</source>, <volume>59</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>460</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>473</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/dev0001496</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36455021</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ref36"><string-name><surname>Lee</surname>, <given-names>T. K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wickrama</surname>, <given-names>K. A. S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>O&#x02019;Neal</surname>, <given-names>C. W.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Prado</surname>, <given-names>G.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Identifying diverse life transition patterns from adolescence to young adulthood: The influence of early socioeconomic context</article-title>. <source>Social Science Research</source>, <volume>70</volume>, <fpage>212</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>228</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ssresearch.2017.12.001</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29455745</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ref37"><string-name><surname>Lenis</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nguyen</surname>, <given-names>T. Q.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dong</surname>, <given-names>N.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Stuart</surname>, <given-names>E. A.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>It&#x02019;s all about balance: Propensity score matching in the context of complex survey data</article-title>. <source>Biostatistics (Oxford, England)</source>, <volume>20</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>147</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>163</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/biostatistics/kxx063</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29293896</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ref38"><string-name><surname>Li</surname>, <given-names>F.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morgan</surname>, <given-names>K. L.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Zaslavsky</surname>, <given-names>A. M.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Balancing covariates via propensity score weighting</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Statistical Association</source>, <volume>113</volume>(<issue>521</issue>), <fpage>390</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>400</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/01621459.2016.1260466</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ref39"><string-name><surname>Liem</surname>, <given-names>J. H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lustig</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Dillon</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Depressive symptoms and life satisfaction among emerging adults: A comparison of high school dropouts and graduates</article-title>. <source>Journal of Adult Development</source>, <volume>17</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>33</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>43</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10804-009-9076-9</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ref40"><string-name><surname>McFarland</surname>, <given-names>M. J.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Wagner</surname>, <given-names>B. G.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Does a college education reduce depressive symptoms in American young adults?</article-title>
<source>Social Science &#x00026; Medicine</source>, <volume>146</volume>, <fpage>75</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>84</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.socscimed.2015.09.029</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26513116</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ref42"><string-name><surname>Melchior</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chollet</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Elidemir</surname>, <given-names>G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gal&#x000e9;ra</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Youn&#x000e8;s</surname>, <given-names>N.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Unemployment and substance use in young adults: Does educational attainment modify the association?</article-title>
<source>European Addiction Research</source>, <volume>21</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>115</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>123</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000365887</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25472491</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ref44"><string-name><surname>Ou</surname>, <given-names>S.-R.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Do GED recipients differ from graduates and school dropouts?: Findings from an inner-city Cohort</article-title>. <source>Urban Education</source>, <volume>43</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>83</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>117</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0042085907305187</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ref45"><string-name><surname>Putnam</surname>, <given-names>K. T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harris</surname>, <given-names>W. W.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Putnam</surname>, <given-names>F. W.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Synergistic childhood adversities and complex adult psychopathology</article-title>. <source>Journal of Traumatic Stress</source>, <volume>26</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>435</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>442</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jts.21833</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23893545</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ref46"><string-name><surname>Rosenbaum</surname>, <given-names>P. R.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Rubin</surname>, <given-names>D. B.</given-names></string-name> (<year>1983</year>). <article-title>The central role of the propensity score in observational studies for causal effects</article-title>. <source>Biometrika</source>, <volume>70</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>41</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>55</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2335942</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ref47"><string-name><surname>Rosenbaum</surname>, <given-names>P. R.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Rubin</surname>, <given-names>D. B.</given-names></string-name> (<year>1984</year>). <article-title>Reducing bias in observational studies using subclassification on the propensity score</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Statistical Association</source>, <volume>79</volume>(<issue>387</issue>), <fpage>516</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>524</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2288398</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r48"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="ref48"><string-name><surname>Rothenberg</surname>, <given-names>W. A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Copeland</surname>, <given-names>W. E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shanahan</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gaydosh</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Gutin</surname>, <given-names>I.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2024</year>). <italic toggle="yes">Taking John Schulenberg&#x02019;s &#x0201c;Long View&#x0201d; on successful transitions to adulthood: Associations with adult substance use.</italic></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r50"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="ref50"><string-name><surname>Tong</surname>, <given-names>G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>, <given-names>F.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Allen</surname>, <given-names>A. S.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2022</year>). <part-title>Missing data</part-title>. In <string-name><given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Piantadosi</surname></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><given-names>C. L.</given-names>
<surname>Meinert</surname></string-name> (Eds.), <source>Principles and practice of clinical trials</source> (pp. <fpage>1681</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1701</lpage>). <publisher-name>Springer International Publishing</publisher-name>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-319-52636-2_117</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ref51"><string-name><surname>Treas</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Batalova</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Residential independence: Race and ethnicity on the road to adulthood in two US immigrant gateways</article-title>. <source>Advances in Life Course Research</source>, <volume>16</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>13</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>24</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ref52"><string-name><surname>van Buuren</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Groothuis-Oudshoorn</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>mice: Multivariate imputation by chained equations in R</article-title>. <source>Journal of Statistical Software</source>, <volume>45</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>67</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18637/jss.v045.i03</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ref53"><string-name><surname>VanderWeele</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>The use of propensity score methods in psychiatric research</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Methods in Psychiatric Research</source>, <volume>15</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>95</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>103</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/mpr.183</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19722290</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ref54"><string-name><surname>von Elm</surname>, <given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Altman</surname>, <given-names>D. G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Egger</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pocock</surname>, <given-names>S. J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>G&#x000f8;tzsche</surname>, <given-names>P. C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vandenbroucke</surname>, <given-names>J. P.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <collab>STROBE Initiative</collab>. (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>The strengthening the reporting of observational studies in epidemiology (STROBE) statement: Guidelines for reporting observational studies</article-title>. <source>Journal of Clinical Epidemiology</source>, <volume>61</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>344</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>349</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jclinepi.2007.11.008</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18313558</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r55"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="ref55"><string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tong</surname>, <given-names>G.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>, <given-names>F.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thomas</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Li</surname>, <given-names>F.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2020</year>). <italic toggle="yes">PSweight: Propensity Score Weighting for Causal Inference with Observational Studies and Randomized Trials</italic> (p. 1.2.0) [Dataset]. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.32614/CRAN.package.PSweight</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ref56"><string-name><surname>Zhu</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Coffman</surname>, <given-names>D. L.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Ghosh</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names></string-name> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>A boosting algorithm for estimating generalized propensity scores with continuous treatments</article-title>. <source>Journal of Causal Inference</source>, <volume>3</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>25</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>40</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1515/jci-2014-0022</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26877909</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>