<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PeerJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PeerJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">peerj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PeerJ</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2167-8359</issn><publisher><publisher-name>PeerJ Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Diego, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40191760</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11972564</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">19137</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19137</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Genetics</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Dentistry</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Pathology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Histology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Medical Genetics</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A multi-center cross-sectional investigation of <italic toggle="yes"> BRAF</italic> V600E mutation in Ameloblastoma</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="author-1" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tun</surname><given-names>Khin Mya</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lapthanasupkul</surname><given-names>Puangwan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Iamaroon</surname><given-names>Anak</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Thosaporn</surname><given-names>Wacharaporn</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-5" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Klanrit</surname><given-names>Poramaporn</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-6" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kintarak</surname><given-names>Sompid</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-5" ref-type="aff">5</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-7" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Thanasan</surname><given-names>Siwaporn</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-6" ref-type="aff">6</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-8" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Srimaneekarn</surname><given-names>Natchalee</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-7" ref-type="aff">7</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-9" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Kitkumthorn</surname><given-names>Nakarin</given-names></name><email>nakarinkit@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff-8" ref-type="aff">8</xref></contrib><aff id="aff-1"><label>1</label><institution>Faculty of Dentistry, Mahidol University</institution>, <city>Bangkok</city>, <country>Thailand</country></aff><aff id="aff-2"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Oral and Maxillofacial Pathology, Faculty of Dentistry, Mahidol University</institution>, <city>Bangkok</city>, <country> Thailand</country></aff><aff id="aff-3"><label>3</label><institution>Department of Oral Biology and Diagnostic Sciences, Faculty of Dentistry, Chiang Mai University</institution>, <city>Chiang Mai</city>, <country>Thailand</country></aff><aff id="aff-4"><label>4</label><institution>Department of Oral Biomedical Sciences, Faculty of Dentistry, Khon Kaen University</institution>, <city>Khon Kaen</city>, <country>Thailand</country></aff><aff id="aff-5"><label>5</label><institution>Department of Stomatology, Faculty of Dentistry, Prince of Songkla University</institution>, <city>Songkhla</city>, <country>Thailand</country></aff><aff id="aff-6"><label>6</label><institution>Department of Pathology, Rajavithi Hospital</institution>, <city>Bangkok</city>, <country>Thailand</country></aff><aff id="aff-7"><label>7</label><institution>Department of Anatomy, Faculty of Dentistry, Mahidol University</institution>, <city>Bangkok</city>, <country>Thailand</country></aff><aff id="aff-8"><label>8</label><institution>Department of Oral Biology, Faculty of Dentistry, Mahidol University</institution>, <city>Bangkok</city>, <country>Thailand</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>de Souza</surname><given-names>Renan</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>3</day><month>4</month><year iso-8601-date="2025">2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>13</volume><elocation-id>e19137</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="2024-12-23"><day>23</day><month>12</month><year iso-8601-date="2024">2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="2025-02-19"><day>19</day><month>2</month><year iso-8601-date="2025">2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9;2025 Tun et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Tun et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, reproduction and adaptation in any medium and for any purpose provided that it is properly attributed. For attribution, the original author(s), title, publication source (PeerJ) and either DOI or URL of the article must be cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/19137"/><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>B-Raf proto-oncogene, serine/threonine kinase (<italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic>) V600E mutation stands as a pivotal genetic alteration strongly associated with several neoplasms and contributes significantly to their pathogenesis as well as potential targeted treatment strategies.</p></sec><sec><title>Objective</title><p>This cross-sectional study aimed to determine the frequency of <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E mutation in ameloblastoma in a multi-center of Thailand.</p></sec><sec><title>Method</title><p>Anti-BRAF V600E (clone VE1) immunohistochemistry was performed on 227 conventional ameloblastoma (AM) and 113 unicystic ameloblastoma (UA) samples collected from four major dental schools located in the Central, North, South, and Northeast regions of Thailand. Tumor cells from randomly chosen AM cases were also micro-dissected from the FFPE sections and subjected to DNA sequencing to confirm the immunohistochemical results.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p><italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E mutation was detected in 71.8% of the AM samples, while 65.5% of samples with UAs demonstrated <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E positivity. The <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E mutation was significantly different in the histological subtypes of AMs in the four centers (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.012) and the location of UA in three centers (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.013). There was no significant association between the <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E mutation and the location of ameloblastoma in the overall prevalence of our multi-center study; nonetheless, a statistically significant association was found between the <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E mutation and the mandible location of AMs from the Central Faculty of Dentistry, Mahidol University (MU) center (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.033), as well as with the histological subtypes of AMs from the Southern Faculty of Dentistry, Prince of Songkla University (PSU) center (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.009). No statistical association was observed between the <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E mutation and AM and UA recurrence (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.920 and <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.312), respectively. The results of DNA sequencing performed in randomly selected 40 <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E-positive and 20 <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E-negative ameloblastoma tissues were in accordance with the immunohistochemical findings.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>As a result of a notable prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E in Thai individuals diagnosed with ameloblastoma, they may benefit from the utilization of adjunctive anti-BRAF targeted therapy for treatment.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>Ameloblastoma</kwd><kwd><italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E</kwd><kwd>Immunohistochemistry</kwd><kwd>DNA sequencing</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="fund-1"><funding-source>International Dental Collaboration of the Mekong River Region (IDCMR)</funding-source></award-group><award-group id="fund-2"><funding-source>Faculty of Dentistry, Mahidol University</funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>The present study was supported by grants from the International Dental Collaboration of the Mekong River Region (IDCMR) scholarship, Faculty of Dentistry, Mahidol University. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Ameloblastoma is the most common locally invasive benign odontogenic tumor. This slow-growing jaw tumor of odontogenic origin is implicated in approximately 1% of all oral tumors and 9%&#x02013;11% of all odontogenic tumors (<xref rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr">Masthan et al., 2015</xref>). Although the lesions can develop in the mandible or the maxilla, 80% of ameloblastomas occur in the mandibular molar region (<xref rid="ref-25" ref-type="bibr">Petrovic et al., 2018</xref>). In the fifth edition of the World Health Organization (WHO) Classification of Head and Neck Tumors (2022) (<xref rid="ref-34" ref-type="bibr">WHO Classification of Tumours Editorial Board, 2022</xref>), ameloblastomas were classified as unicystic ameloblastoma (UA), conventional ameloblastoma (hereafter referred to as AM), extraosseous/peripheral ameloblastoma and metastasizing ameloblastoma. In addition, adenoid ameloblastoma was also added as a new distinct entity in the group of benign epithelial odontogenic tumors (<xref rid="ref-34" ref-type="bibr">WHO Classification of Tumours Editorial Board, 2022</xref>).</p><p>Most cases of AM demonstrate aggressive behaviors that can potentially invade tissues, resorb the nearby tooth roots, infiltrate medullary spaces, and erode cortical bone (<xref rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr">Kumar et al., 2021</xref>; <xref rid="ref-26" ref-type="bibr">Qiao et al., 2021</xref>). Wide surgical excision is typically considered as the most effective treatment for AM. However, it may lead to significant facial disfigurement and substantial morbidity. The recurrence rate of ameloblastoma varies substantially ranging from 55% to 90% (<xref rid="ref-1" ref-type="bibr">Bera &#x00026; Tiwari, 2024</xref>). Hence, efforts are underway to reduce the invasiveness of these treatments. Rapid advancements in gene mutation research and the application of targeted drug therapy to combat cancer offer less aggressive alternatives to surgical excision.</p><p>B-Raf proto-oncogene, serine/threonine kinase (<italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic>) is frequently affected by a somatic point mutation of <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E in human cancers. The valine (V) to glutamic acid (E) substitution at codon 600 (<italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E) represents a <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> missense mutation that constitutively activates the mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) pathway (<xref rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr">Michaloglou et al., 2008</xref>). The <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E mutation has been identified as the most common oncogenic driver mutation in malignant melanoma, thyroid cancer, colon cancer, and other malignant neoplasms (<xref rid="ref-28" ref-type="bibr">Ritterhouse &#x00026; Barletta, 2015</xref>).</p><p>In our previous study conducted in 2020, a substantial occurrence of this mutation was observed in a cohort of Thai patients with AM and UA in the central region of Thailand (<xref rid="ref-18" ref-type="bibr">Lapthanasupkul et al., 2021</xref>). However, the information on <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E mutation frequency in AM and UA in other regions of Thai population is still scarce. Therefore, this study aimed to determine the prevalence of this mutation in AM and UA patients at four major dental schools in different regions (Central, North, South, and Northeast) of Thailand. Additionally, we conducted a clinicopathological association analysis to identify any clinicopathological factors associated with the <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E mutation.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials &#x00026; Methods</title><sec><title>Study design and tissue samples</title><p>A cross-sectional design was used to investigate the frequencies of <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E mutation in AM and UA tissue samples; collected from four major dental schools in Thailand&#x02019;s central, north, south, and northeast regions. This study was approved by the Institutional Review Board of the Faculty of Dentistry/Faculty of Pharmacy, Mahidol University (COA.No.MU-DT/PY-IRB 2020/032.0906), Human Experimentation Committee of the Faculty of Dentistry, Chiang Mai University (No. 45/2020), Human Research Ethics Committee of the Faculty of Dentistry, Prince of Songkla University (EC6308-032), and the Ethics Committee of the Human Research Panel 2 of the Faculty of Medicine, Khon Kaen University. A total of 340 formalin-fixed paraffin-embedded (FFPE) samples were collected from the four centers. The delegate centers consisted of the following: the Faculty of Dentistry, Mahidol University (MU), in Bangkok province, representing the Central region; the Faculty of Dentistry, Chiang Mai University (CMU), in Chiang Mai province, representing the Northern region; the Faculty of Dentistry, Khon Kaen University (KKU), in Khon Kaen province, representing the Northeastern region; and the Faculty of Dentistry, Prince of Songkla University (PSU) in Songkla province, representing the Southern region. A total of 227 AM samples from MU, CMU, KKU, and PSU, 113 UA samples from MU, CMU, and PSU were included in this study. All experiments were performed at the laboratory of Oral and Maxillofacial Pathology at Mahidol University. The clinical information about the patients (age and sex) and the tumors, duration (time since the patient first noticed the tumor), tumor size, location, and recurrence were retrieved from the pathology request forms or clinical chart records. The exclusion criteria are low amounts of pathologic tissues and a lack of clinical data. Written informed consent was obtained from all patients. The histological variants of AM are categorized into follicular, plexiform, and mixed type (a combination of follicular and plexiform types). The histological variants of UA are classified as luminal, intraluminal, and mural in this study. The histological diagnosis of all of the AM and UA subtypes was confirmed by two pathologists (KMT and PL).</p></sec><sec><title>VE1 immunohistochemistry</title><p><italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E mutation was observed using VE1 immunohistochemical staining, as described previously (<xref rid="ref-18" ref-type="bibr">Lapthanasupkul et al., 2021</xref>). Briefly, the FFPE samples were cut into 3-&#x000b5;m-thick sections using a microtome (Microm HM355S, Thermo Fisher Scientific, Walldorf, Germany). Immunohistochemistry with anti-BRAF V600E VE1 mouse monoclonal primary antibody (catalog number 760-5095, Ventana Medical Systems, Tucson, AZ, US) was performed using an automated Ventana BenchMark Ultra autostainer (Ventana Medical Systems, Tucson, AZ, US) with incubation at 37&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, 1&#x000a0;h. VE1 immunoreactivity was visualized using an OptiView DAB IHC detection kit (Ventana Medical Systems, Tucson, AZ, US) and then counterstained with Hematoxylin II and Bluing Reagent for 16 min and 4&#x000a0;min, respectively. Melanoma tissues known to be positive and negative for <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E mutation were used as positive control and negative control, respectively (<xref rid="ref-22" ref-type="bibr">Meevassana et al., 2022</xref>). Both control tissues were included in each run of the experiment. Two pathologists (KMT and PL), who scored the <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E status, were blinded to the clinicopathological data at the time of interpretation. Immunoreactions were evaluated as positive, when cytoplasmic staining was observed for a significant number of tumor cells (&#x0003e;80%) in the sections. A negative score was recorded for weak nuclear staining, isolated nuclear staining, weak staining of single interspersed cells, and staining of monocytes/macrophages (<xref rid="ref-18" ref-type="bibr">Lapthanasupkul et al., 2021</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Tissue microdissection and DNA extraction</title><p><italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E immunohistochemical 40 positive cases and 20 negative cases of AM were randomly selected for manual microdissection, which was performed as described previously (<xref rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr">Kitkumthorn &#x00026; Mutirangura, 2010</xref>). Briefly, 5-&#x000b5;m-thick sections of FFPE blocks were serially cut into five levels. The first and last levels were stained with Hematoxylin and Eosin (H&#x00026;E) to ensure that the outlines of the samples across all slides were identical. The area under the microscope was examined and outlined with a Startmark-pen&#x02122;&#x000a0;(NC1523755, Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, US). Using the H&#x00026;E slides as a reference, the tumor areas were marked on the remaining unstained slides (levels 2&#x02013;4). Finally, the selected areas were dissected using a sterile needle-gauge 21 and stored in phosphate-buffered saline until DNA extraction.</p><p>Genomic DNA was extracted using the standard phenol-chloroform protocol (<xref rid="ref-29" ref-type="bibr">Sambrook &#x00026; Russell, 2006</xref>), and the concentration was evaluated using a NanoDrop 2000 spectrophotometer (ND-1000 Spectrophotometer, NanoDrop Technologies, Wilmington, DE, US). A 260/280 optical density ratio of 1.8 was considered acceptable for DNA purity.</p></sec><sec><title><italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E DNA sequencing</title><p>DNA sequencing was conducted to validate the <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E immunostaining results. DNA from micro-dissected tumor tissues was amplified and sequenced at <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> exon 15 using the following primers: forward 5&#x02032;-GAAATTAGATCTCTTACCTAAACTCTTCATA-3&#x02032;&#x000a0;and reverse 5&#x02032;-GACCCACTCCATCGAGATTT-3&#x02032;. The results were compared with the <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> nucleotide sequence available in the National Center for Biotechnology Information database using the MEGA X (Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis) software, version 10.2.4 (MEGA-X, Allenstown, NH, US) to detect the mutation sequence (<xref rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr">Kumar et al., 2018</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>The frequency of <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E mutation was reported as a percentage. Chi-square test was used to investigate the associations between clinicopathologic variables and <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E status in all samples and subgroup analyses. A <italic toggle="yes">p-</italic>value of less than 0.05 was regarded as statistically significant. SPSS, version 28.0 (IBM, Armonk, NY, USA) was used to analyze the data in this study.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Clinicopathological characteristics and <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E mutation in AMs</title><p>As shown in <xref rid="table-1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, 227 AM patients (125 males and 102 females) were included in the study. The median age of the patients was 33 years (range, 11&#x02013;79 years). The tumors were located in the mandible in the majority of cases (90%), and the median tumor size was four cm (range, 0.8&#x02013;15 cm). The average duration of follow-up was 6 months (range, 3.5&#x02013;30 months). Multilocular AM was more frequent than unilocular AM (66% <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> 34%). Furthermore, 40% of the AM cases were histologically diagnosed as follicular, followed by plexiform (28%) and mixed (32%) types. The <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E mutation significantly differed in the histological subtypes of AM in the four centers (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.012, <xref rid="table-1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p><p><italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E staining was positive in 71.8% of the total AM cases from the four centers (<xref rid="table-1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The negative cases lacked the cytoplasmic expression of <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E protein in the ameloblastic epithelium, thus indicating the expression of wild-type <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> (<xref rid="fig-1" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;1A</xref>). The positive cases revealed the brown-colored cytoplasmic staining of <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E protein in the ameloblastic epithelium, whereas no staining was observed in the stromal components and non-neoplastic tissues (<xref rid="fig-1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1B</xref>). In concordance with the immunostaining results, <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> sequencing revealed a base substitution (GTG &#x0003e;&#x000a0;GAG) in all 40 cases with positive <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E immunostaining (<xref rid="fig-1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1D</xref>). In contrast, no base substitution was detected in the 20 cases, being negative for <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E (<xref rid="fig-1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1C</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="table-1"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19137/table-1</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Clinicopathological characteristics of <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E mutation in conventional ameloblastomas from four dental centers.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-13-19137-g002" position="float"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical characteristics</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> wild type <break/>N (row %)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E <break/>N (row%)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total number <break/>N (%)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>64 (28.2)</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>163 (71.8)</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>227 (100)</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years; Median 33)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;33 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (30.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">82 (69.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">118 (52)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.420</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;33 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (25.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81 (74.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">109 (48)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (30.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">87 (69.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">125 (55.1)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.413</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (25.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76 (74.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">102 (44.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tumor duration</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;6 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (28.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67 (71.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">94 (41.4)</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.698</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;6 months- 1 year</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (31.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39 (68.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57 (25.1)</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;1 year</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57 (75)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76 (33.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Size (Median 4 cm)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;4 cm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (26.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85 (73.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">116 (51.1)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.615</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;4 cm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (29.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78 (70.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">111 (48.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Location</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maxilla</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (39.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (60.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (10.2)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.219</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mandible</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55 (27.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">149 (73)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">204 (89.8)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Radiographic Feature</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unilocular</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (29.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 (70.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77 (33.9)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.688</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multilocular</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 (27.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">109 (72.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">150 (66.1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Histologic Subtype</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Follicular</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (24.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69 (75.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">91 (40.1)</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.012<xref rid="table-1fn1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plexiform</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (42.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (57.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64 (28.2)</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (20.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57 (79.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72 (31.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recurrence</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absent</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58 (28.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">147 (71.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">205 (90.3)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.920</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Present</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (27.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (72.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (9.7)</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-1fn"><p>
<bold>Notes.</bold>
</p></fn><fn id="table-1fn1"><label>*</label><p><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05 (Chi-square test).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="fig-1"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19137/fig-1</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Immunohistochemical staining and Sanger sequencing of <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E in ameloblastoma.</title><p>(A) A representative picture of conventional ameloblastoma showed no BRAF V600E protein expression in the odontogenic epithelium (200x magnification). (B) A representative picture of conventional ameloblastoma showed moderate brown cytoplasmic BRAF V600E protein expression in the odontogenic epithelium (200x magnification). (C) DNA sequencing electropherogram of the wild-type allele of <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E mutation (the same case from A), characterized by the nucleotide sequence coding for the amino acid valine in the underline area (A-adenine, C-cytosine, G-guanine, T-thymine) (D) DNA sequencing electropherogram of ameloblastoma, forward mutation of <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> codon encoding Val600Glu (V600E) (the same case from B.), characterized by the substitution of thymine with adenine in the position of 1799 T &#x0003e; A as shown in the underline region. (E) A representative of unicystic ameloblastoma showed an absence of BRAF V600E protein expression in the cystic lining epithelium (200x magnification). (F) A representative of unicystic ameloblastoma with presence of BRAF V600E protein expression, indicated by brown cytoplasmic staining in the cystic lining epithelium (200x magnification).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-13-19137-g001" position="float"/></fig><p>As demonstrated in <xref rid="table-2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, the number of patients with <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E mutation was slightly different at each center: 75.9% at the Central MU center, 68.5% at the Northern CMU center, 61.4% in the Southern PSU center, and 84.9% in the Northeastern KKU center. A statistically significant (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05) association was observed between the presence of <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E mutation and the mandible location of the AMs from the Central MU center (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.033) and the histological subtypes of the AMs from the Southern PSU center (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.009) (<xref rid="table-2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Detailed data on AM is presented in <xref rid="supp-2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Tables S1</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="supp-2" ref-type="supplementary-material">S4</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="table-2"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19137/table-2</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Clinicopathological characteristics of <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E mutation in conventional ameloblastomas from the individual center.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-13-19137-g003" position="float"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Variables</bold>
</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<bold>MU</bold>
<sup>
<bold>a</bold>
</sup>
</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<bold>CMU</bold>
<sup>
<bold>b</bold>
</sup>
</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<bold>PSU</bold>
<sup>
<bold>c</bold>
</sup>
</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<bold>KKU</bold>
<sup>
<bold>d</bold>
</sup>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>
</bold>
<bold>-value</bold>
</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Wild-type</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Mutant</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Wild-type</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Mutant</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Wild-type</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Mutant</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Wild-type</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Mutant</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<bold>Number of patients</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (24)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63 (75.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (31.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (68.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (38.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (61.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (15.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (84.8)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<bold>Age (years; Median 33)</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;33 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (18.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39 (81.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (42.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (57.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (50)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (50.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (12.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (87.5)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.182<sup>a</sup><break/>0.099<sup>b</sup><break/>0.082<sup>c</sup><break/>0.680<sup>d</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;33 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (31.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (68.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (21.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (78.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (27.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (72.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (17.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (82.4)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<bold>Sex</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (30.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (69.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (38.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (61.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (32.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (67.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (11.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (88.2)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.175<sup>a</sup><break/>0.164<sup>b</sup><break/>0.283<sup>c</sup><break/>0.576<sup>d</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (17.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (82.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (20.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (80.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (46.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (53.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (18.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (81.2)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<bold>Tumor duration</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;6 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (32.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (68.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (32.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (67.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (35.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (64.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (100)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.412<sup>a</sup><break/>0.356<sup>b</sup><break/>0.819<sup>c</sup><break/>0.095<sup>d</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;6 months&#x02013;1 year</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (25.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (75.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (42.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (57.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (33.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (66.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (33.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (66.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;1 year</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (16.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (83.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (16.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (83.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (43.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (56.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (18.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (81.8)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<bold>Location</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maxilla</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (57.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (42.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (50.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (50.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (42.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4(57.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (14.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (85.7)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.033<sup><italic toggle="yes">a</italic></sup><xref rid="table-2fn3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*</sup></xref><break/>0.566<sup>b</sup><break/>0.805<sup>c</sup><break/>0.943<sup>d</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mandible</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (21.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60 (78.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (30.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (69.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (38.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (62.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (15.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (84.6)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<bold>Size (Median 4 cm)</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;4 cm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (21.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (78.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (30.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (70.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (32.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (67.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (22.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (77.8)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.636<sup>a</sup><break/>0.793<sup>b</sup><break/>0.283<sup>c</sup><break/>0.215<sup>d</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;4 cm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (26.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 (73.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (33.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (66.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (46.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (53.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (6.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (93.3)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<bold>Radiographic feature</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unilocular</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (30.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (69.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (26.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (73.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (40.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (60.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (12.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (87.5)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.403<sup>a</sup><break/>0.785<sup>b</sup><break/>0.873<sup>c</sup><break/>0.810<sup>d</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multilocular</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (21.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47 (78.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (35.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (64.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (37.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (62.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (16.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (84.0)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<bold>Histologic subtype</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Follicular</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (25.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (75.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (11.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (88.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (34.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (65.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (19.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (81.0)</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.529<sup>a</sup><break/>0.690<sup>b</sup><break/>0.009<sup><italic toggle="yes">c</italic></sup><xref rid="table-2fn3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*</sup></xref><break/>0.605<sup>d</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plexiform</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (30.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (69.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (45.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (54.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (80.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (20.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (100)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (18.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (81.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (30.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (69.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (22.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (77.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (12.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (87.5)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<bold>Recurrence</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No recur</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (22.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60 (77.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (32.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (67.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (41.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (58.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (16.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (83.9)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.123<sup>a</sup><break/>0.669<sup>b</sup><break/>0.243<sup>c</sup><break/>0.538<sup>d</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recur</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (50.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (50.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (25.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (75.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (16.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (83.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (100)</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-2fn"><p>
<bold>Notes.</bold>
</p></fn><fn id="table-2fn1" fn-type="other"><p>MU, Mahidol University; CMU, Chiang Mai University; PSU, Prince of Songkhla University and KKU, Khon Kaen University.</p></fn><fn id="table-2fn2" fn-type="other"><p>Percentages are given in parentheses.</p></fn><fn id="table-2fn3"><label>*</label><p><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05 (Chi-square test).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Clinicopathological characteristics and <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E mutation in UA</title><p>As shown in <xref rid="table-3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>, 113 patients (median age, 20 years; range, 1&#x02013;77 years) diagnosed with UA from the Central MU, Northern CMU and Southern PSU centers were enrolled in this study. The median tumor size was three cm (range, 0.9&#x02013;10 cm), and most lesions occurred in the mandible (89.4%). The average follow-up duration was 6 months (range, 6&#x02013;26.5 months). Regarding the histological subtype, the mural subtype accounted for 65.5% of the cases, followed by the intraluminal (21.2%), and luminal (13.3%) subtypes in <xref rid="table-3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="table-3"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19137/table-3</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Clinicopathological characteristics of <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E mutation in unicystic ameloblastomas from three centers.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-13-19137-g004" position="float"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Clinical characteristics</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic>
</bold>
<bold> wild type</bold>
<break/>
<bold>N (row %)</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic>
</bold>
<bold> V600E</bold>
<break/>
<bold>N (row %)</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Total number</bold>
<break/>
<bold>N (%)</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic toggle="yes">p-</italic>
</bold>
<bold>value</bold>
</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>39 (34.5)</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>74 (65.5)</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>113 (100)</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Age (years; Median 20)</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;20 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (39)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (61)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59 (52.2)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.296</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;20 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (29.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (70.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 (47.8)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Sex</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (32.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (67.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53 (46.9)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.608</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (36.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (63.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60 (53.1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Tumor duration</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;6 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (42.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39 (57.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68 (60.2)</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.060</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;6 months- 1year</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (29.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (70.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (15)</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;1 year</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (17.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (82.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (24.8)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Size (Median 3 cm)</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;3 cm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (31.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 (68.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72 (63.7)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.447</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;3 cm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (39)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (61)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 (36.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Location</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maxilla</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (66.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (33.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (10.6)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.013<xref rid="table-3fn1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mandible</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (30.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70 (69.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">101 (89.4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Histologic subtype</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Luminal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (46.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (53.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (13.3)</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.566</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intraluminal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (33.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (66.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (21.2)</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mural</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (34.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 (67.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74 (65.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Recurrence</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absent</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (35.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66 (64.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">103 (91.2)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.312</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Present</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (20)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (80)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (8.8)</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-3fn"><p>
<bold>Notes.</bold>
</p></fn><fn id="table-3fn1"><label>*</label><p><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05 (Chi-square test).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The absence of cytoplasmic <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E protein expression in the cystic epithelium of UA is indicative of wild-type <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> (<xref rid="fig-1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1E</xref>). In contrast, the cytoplasmic <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E expression observed in the UA cystic epithelial lining cells indicates the presence of a <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E mutation in UA (<xref rid="fig-1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1F</xref>). Overall, 65.5% of UAs were positive for <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E (<xref rid="table-3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). A statistically significant association was only observed between the presence of <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E mutation and the location of the mandible (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.013) in three dental centers (<xref rid="table-3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>) and (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.004) for mandibular cases at the MU center (<xref rid="table-4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). Interestingly, UA patients from the Central MU center (92.3%) had a considerably higher rate of <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E mutation than those from the Northern CMU (43.8%, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001) and the Southern PSU centers (41.4%, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001; <xref rid="table-4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). Further details are presented in <xref rid="supp-2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Tables S5</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="supp-2" ref-type="supplementary-material">S7</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="table-4"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19137/table-4</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Clinicopathological characteristics of <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E mutation in UA cases from the individual center.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-13-19137-g005" position="float"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Variables</bold>
</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<bold>MU-UA</bold>
<sup>
<bold>a</bold>
</sup>
</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<bold>CMU-UA</bold>
<sup>
<bold>b</bold>
</sup>
</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<bold>PSU-UA</bold>
<sup>
<bold>c</bold>
</sup>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>
</bold>
<bold>-value</bold>
</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Wild-type</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Mutant</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Wild-type</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Mutant</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Wild-type</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Mutant</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Number of the patients</bold>
<break/>
<bold>Age (years; Median 20)</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (7.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 (92.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (56.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (43.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (58.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (41.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;20 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (9.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (90.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (55.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (45.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (55.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (44.4)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.683<sup>a</sup><break/>0.854<sup>b</sup><break/>0.668<sup>c</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;20 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (6.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (93.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (58.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (41.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (63.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (36.4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Sex</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (7.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (92.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (63.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (36.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (57.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (42.9)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.872<sup>a</sup><break/>0.542<sup>b</sup><break/>0.876<sup>c</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (8.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (91.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (52.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (47.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (60.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (40.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Tumor duration</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;6 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (13.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (87.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (54.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (45.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (61.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (38.1)</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.293<sup>a</sup><break/>0.903<sup>b</sup><break/>0.469<sup>c</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;6 months- 1year</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (9.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (90.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (60.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (40.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (100)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;1 year</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (100)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (66.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (33.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (42.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (57.1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Location</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maxilla</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (40.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (60.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (75.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (25.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (100)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.004<sup><italic toggle="yes">a</italic></sup><xref rid="table-4fn2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*</sup></xref><break/>0.419<sup>b</sup><break/>0.124<sup>c</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mandible</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (4.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 (95.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (53.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (46.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (53.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (46.2)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Size (median 3 cm)</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;3 cm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (9.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (90.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (50.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (50.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (47.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (52.9)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.514<sup>a</sup><break/>0.217<sup>b</sup><break/>0.132<sup>c</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;3 cm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (4.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (95.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (75.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (25.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (75.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (25.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Histologic Subtype</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Luminal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (100)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (75.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (25.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (100)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.707<sup>a</sup><break/>0.411<sup>b</sup><break/>0.119<sup>c</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intraluminal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (6.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (93.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (60.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (40.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (100)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mural</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (9.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (90.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (47.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (52.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (50.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (50.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Recurrence</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No recur</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (9.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 (90.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (54.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (45.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (57.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (42.9)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.375<sup>a</sup><break/>0.370<sup>b</sup><break/>0.393<sup>c</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recur</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (100)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (100)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (100)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-4fn"><p>
<bold>Notes.</bold>
</p></fn><fn id="table-4fn1" fn-type="other"><p>MU, Mahidol University; CMU, Chiang Mai University; PSU, Prince of Songkhla University; UA, Unicystic ameloblastoma. Percentages are given in parentheses.</p></fn><fn id="table-4fn2"><label>*</label><p><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05 (Chi-square test).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Ameloblastoma is characterized by excessive cell proliferation, which is primarily regulated by the mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) signaling pathway (<xref rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr">Brown &#x00026; Betz, 2015</xref>). Mutations in the MAPK pathway have been shown to play a key role in the pathogenesis of AM, especially the <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E (<xref rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr">Brown &#x00026; Betz, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="ref-17" ref-type="bibr">Kurppa et al., 2014</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E immunostaining was positive in 71.8% of the total AM cases from the four dental centers in Thailand. Our result is consistent with the previous meta-analysis reporting a pooled prevalence of 70.49% for <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E in 833 AM cases (<xref rid="ref-20" ref-type="bibr">Mamat Yusof, Ch&#x02019;ng &#x00026; Radhiah Abdul Rahman, 2022</xref>). Although varying frequencies (33.3%&#x02013;92%) of <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E mutation have been documented (<xref rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr">Kokubun et al., 2022</xref>; <xref rid="ref-17" ref-type="bibr">Kurppa et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="ref-18" ref-type="bibr">Lapthanasupkul et al., 2021</xref>; <xref rid="ref-31" ref-type="bibr">Shirsat et al., 2018</xref>), the high frequency of <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E mutation in AM remains observed from each center of Thailand, with a range between 61.4% to 84.8%. These findings underscore a crucial role of <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E in the molecular pathogenesis of this common odontogenic tumor, and substantiate a novel alternative therapeutic approach for Thai patients diagnosed with AM.</p><p>DNA sequencing was further performed to confirm the immunohistochemical findings in the current study. Similar to the study by <xref rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr">Kokubun et al. (2022)</xref>, <xref rid="ref-23" ref-type="bibr">Mendez et al. (2022)</xref>, a high agreement was observed between the immunohistochemical staining and sequencing of <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E in the present study. The superior results observed in the current study may be attributed to meticulous microdissection, enabling precise analysis of the epithelial tumor tissue. However, whereas our analysis included a large number of AM specimens, only a portion of the specimens with tissue available was permitted for DNA sequencing. In addition, the concordance between <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> immunohistochemistry and sequencing techniques has been documented previously in various other tumor types, including xanthoastrocytoma, colorectal cancer, and papillary thyroid cancer (<xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr">Day et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="ref-11" ref-type="bibr">Ida et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="ref-19" ref-type="bibr">Loo et al., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr">Qiu et al., 2015</xref>).</p><p>We found no significant association between <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E mutation and tumor size in any of the AM cases in this study; on the contrary, <xref rid="ref-5" ref-type="bibr">Do Canto et al. (2019)</xref> reported a higher frequency of <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E mutant in patients with large AM. There was no significant association between <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E mutation and the location of ameloblastoma in the overall prevalence of our multi-center study. Nevertheless, tumor location at the mandible was significantly associated with <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E mutations only in AM patients from the Central dental center of Thailand. This result is comparable to those reported by <xref rid="ref-33" ref-type="bibr">Togni et al. (2022)</xref>, <xref rid="ref-2" ref-type="bibr">Bonacina et al. (2022)</xref>, wherein a higher frequency of mandibular AM was associated with <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E mutation. This significant finding may be attributed to different demographic patterns in the Central region, compared to the other centers in Thailand. Therefore, further investigations may be required to validate our findings. Furthermore, in the study of <xref rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr">Kokubun et al. (2022)</xref> no association was observed between <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E mutation and AM recurrence. Although no statistical association was found between <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> mutation and ameloblastoma recurrence, adjunctive anti-BRAF therapy may improve the quality of life. The sequelae of extensive surgical resection, including functional impairment and aesthetic deformities, underscore the need for alternative treatment strategies. BRAF inhibitors may be utilized as an adjuvant presurgical treatment, especially in older patients with large lesions, to assist in conservative surgical interventions for tumor shrinkage and induction of appropriate peripheral bone formation. Such utilization ensures safer resection with less deformity and better preservation of function (<xref rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr">Grynberg et al., 2024</xref>). Furthermore, the use of BRAF inhibitors as adjuvant presurgical therapy is particularly recommended in younger patients to mitigate potentially detrimental effects on mandibular growth and facial aesthetics (<xref rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr">Grynberg et al., 2024</xref>).</p><p>This study revealed a notable disparity of <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E frequency in UA patients from various regions of Thailand. Interestingly, UA from the Central center showed the highest frequency (92.3%) compared to other centers. This unexpected outcome may be associated with differences in demographic data and a slightly higher proportion of the UA samples in the central center. The high frequency of <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E mutation in UA (88.9&#x02013;100%) was previously reported by <xref rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr">Kelppe et al. (2019)</xref>, <xref rid="ref-8" ref-type="bibr">Goes et al. (2023)</xref> and <xref rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr">Heikinheimo et al. (2019)</xref>. These findings implicated that UA may be mainly driven by <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E mutation compared to AM, and supported BRAF inhibitors as a promising future treatment option for UA. UA is frequently found in young patients when the jaws are still growing. The radical treatment of extensive or multiple recurrent UA cases often poses a challenge (<xref rid="ref-30" ref-type="bibr">Scariot et al., 2012</xref>). Adjunctive treatment with targeted drug therapy may offer a superior clinical outcome for these patients. In addition, consistent with the study by <xref rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr">Heikinheimo et al. (2019)</xref>, a statistically significant association between mandibular UA and <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E was observed in this study (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.013), highlighting the probable role of the MAPK pathway in the pathogenesis of UA in the mandible.</p><p>Development of targeted therapy for AM is tempting, based on the high frequency of <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E in this disease. A prior clinical investigation focused on the MAPK pathway as a potential therapeutic approach for AM-targeted drug treatment has been documented previously, wherein advanced AM was managed with dabrafenib, a BRAF inhibitor (<xref rid="ref-6" ref-type="bibr">Faden &#x00026; Algazi, 2017</xref>). The treatment resulted in a remarkable shrinkage of the tumor after 8 months. However, it is important to note that this was reported in a single case. BRAF and mitogen-activated extracellular signal-regulated kinase (MEK) inhibitors, including vemurafenib, dabrafenib, and trametinib, have shown significant reductions in tumor size with promising results in AM patients with <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E (<xref rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr">Fernandes et al., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="ref-32" ref-type="bibr">Tan et al., 2016</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E inhibitors may be used as pre-operative therapy in <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E-positive AM patients to reduce the primary tumor size. However, additional studies with different clinical settings are needed to confirm the outcome of the targeted treatment.</p><p>Our study possesses a strength in terms of its scale, representing the largest investigation of AM-<italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E mutation conducted in Thailand. This comprehensive investigation covers all four regions of the country. However, a notable limitation of our study is the potential benefit of expanding the sample size to include data from different countries, which could enhance the robustness and generalizability of our findings.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Our study revealed a significantly high prevalence of the <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E mutation among patients diagnosed with AM at four dental centers in Thailand. Additionally, a statistically significant association was found between the <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E mutation and the histological subtype of AM, as well as the location of UA in three dental centers, and with the location of AM and UA cases at the MU center. In contrast, other clinicopathological factors, including age, sex, tumor duration, radiological features, and recurrence, showed no significance among ameloblastoma cases with the <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E mutation. Despite the lack of a statistical association between <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> mutation and ameloblastoma recurrence, adjunctive anti-BRAF targeted therapy may improve the quality of life, addressing functional and aesthetic impairments, especially for ameloblastoma patients who cannot undergo extensive surgical intervention. The significant prevalence of the <italic toggle="yes">BRAF</italic> V600E mutation in the pathogenesis of ameloblastoma in Thai patients suggests the future potential use of BRAF inhibitors as targeted therapy, combined with surgical treatment, to improve treatment outcomes.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="supplemental-information"><title> Supplemental Information</title><supplementary-material id="supp-1" position="float" content-type="local-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19137/supp-1</object-id><label>Supplemental Information 1</label><caption><title>DNA sequencing raw data</title></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-13-19137-s001.zip"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="supp-2" position="float" content-type="local-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19137/supp-2</object-id><label>Supplemental Information 2</label><caption><title>Supplementary Tables</title></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-13-19137-s002.xlsx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="supp-3" position="float" content-type="local-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.19137/supp-3</object-id><label>Supplemental Information 3</label><caption><title>STROBE checklist</title></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-13-19137-s003.docx"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="additional-information"><title>Additional Information and Declarations</title><fn-group content-type="competing-interests"><title>Competing Interests</title><fn id="conflict-1" fn-type="COI-statement"><p>The authors declare there are no competing interests.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="author-contributions"><title>Author Contributions</title><fn id="contribution-1" fn-type="con"><p><xref rid="author-1" ref-type="contrib">Khin Mya Tun</xref> conceived and designed the experiments, performed the experiments, analyzed the data, prepared figures and/or tables, authored or reviewed drafts of the article, and approved the final draft.</p></fn><fn id="contribution-2" fn-type="con"><p><xref rid="author-2" ref-type="contrib">Puangwan Lapthanasupkul</xref> conceived and designed the experiments, performed the experiments, analyzed the data, prepared figures and/or tables, authored or reviewed drafts of the article, and approved the final draft.</p></fn><fn id="contribution-3" fn-type="con"><p><xref rid="author-3" ref-type="contrib">Anak Iamaroon</xref> performed the experiments, prepared figures and/or tables, and approved the final draft.</p></fn><fn id="contribution-4" fn-type="con"><p><xref rid="author-4" ref-type="contrib">Wacharaporn Thosaporn</xref> performed the experiments, prepared figures and/or tables, and approved the final draft.</p></fn><fn id="contribution-5" fn-type="con"><p><xref rid="author-5" ref-type="contrib">Poramaporn Klanrit</xref> performed the experiments, prepared figures and/or tables, and approved the final draft.</p></fn><fn id="contribution-6" fn-type="con"><p><xref rid="author-6" ref-type="contrib">Sompid Kintarak</xref> performed the experiments, prepared figures and/or tables, and approved the final draft.</p></fn><fn id="contribution-7" fn-type="con"><p><xref rid="author-7" ref-type="contrib">Siwaporn Thanasan</xref> performed the experiments, prepared figures and/or tables, and approved the final draft.</p></fn><fn id="contribution-8" fn-type="con"><p><xref rid="author-8" ref-type="contrib">Natchalee Srimaneekarn</xref> analyzed the data, prepared figures and/or tables, and approved the final draft.</p></fn><fn id="contribution-9" fn-type="con"><p><xref rid="author-9" ref-type="contrib">Nakarin Kitkumthorn</xref> conceived and designed the experiments, performed the experiments, analyzed the data, prepared figures and/or tables, authored or reviewed drafts of the article, and approved the final draft.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="other"><title>Ethics</title><fn id="addinfo-2"><p>The following information was supplied relating to ethical approvals (i.e., approving body and any reference numbers):</p><p>The research was approved by the Institutional Review Board of Faculty of Dentistry/Faculty of Pharmacy, Mahidol University (COA.No.MU-DT/PY-IRB 2020/032.0906), Human Experimentation Committee of Faculty of Dentistry, Chiang Mai University (No. 45/2020), Human Research Ethics Committee of Faculty of Dentistry, Prince of Songkla University (EC6308-032) and Ethics Committee of Human Research Panel 2 of Faculty of Medicine, Khon Kaen University.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="other"><title>DNA Deposition</title><fn id="addinfo-3"><p>The following information was supplied regarding the deposition of DNA sequences:</p><p>The sequences are available at GenBank: <ext-link xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/bioproject/?term=PRJNA1200226" ext-link-type="uri">PRJNA1200226</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="other"><title>Data Availability</title><fn id="addinfo-4"><p>The following information was supplied regarding data availability:</p><p>The raw measurements are available in the <xref rid="supplemental-information" ref-type="sec">Supplementary Files</xref>.</p></fn></fn-group></sec><ref-list content-type="authoryear"><title>References</title><ref id="ref-1"><label>Bera &#x00026; Tiwari (2024)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bera</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tiwari</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2024">2024</year><article-title>Factors related to risk of recurrence and recurrence free survival in ameloblastoma of the Jaws: a single centre retrospective analysis</article-title><source>Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery</source><volume>29</volume><fpage>22</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10006-024-01321-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39739058</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-2"><label>Bonacina et al. (2022)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bonacina</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Indini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Massazza</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rulli</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gianatti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mandal&#x000e0;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year><article-title>Correlation of BRAF mutational status with clinical characteristics and survival outcomes of patients with ameloblastoma: the experience of 11 Italian centres</article-title><source>Journal of Clinical Pathology</source><volume>75</volume><fpage>555</fpage><lpage>559</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/jclinpath-2021-207527</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33827932</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-3"><label>Brown &#x00026; Betz (2015)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Betz</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Ameloblastoma: a review of recent molecular pathogenetic discoveries</article-title><source>Biomark Cancer</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4137/bic.S29329</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-4"><label>Day et al. (2015)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Muranyi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shanmugam</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Byrne</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pham</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Palmieri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tie</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Grogan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gibbs</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sieber</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Waring</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Desai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>A mutant BRAF V600E-specific immunohistochemical assay: correlation with molecular mutation status and clinical outcome in colorectal cancer</article-title><source>Targeted Oncology</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>109</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11523-014-0319-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24859797</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-5"><label>Do Canto et al. (2019)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Do Canto</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Da Silva Marcelino</surname><given-names>BMR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schussel</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wastner</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sassi</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Corr&#x000ea;a</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>De Freitas</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hass&#x000e9;us</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kjeller</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Junior</surname><given-names>CAL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Braz-Silva</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>Immunohistochemical analysis of BRAF V600E mutation in ameloblastomas</article-title><source>Clinical Oral Investigations</source><volume>23</volume><fpage>779</fpage><lpage>784</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00784-018-2494-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29855709</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-6"><label>Faden &#x00026; Algazi (2017)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Faden</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Algazi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Durable treatment of ameloblastoma with single agent BRAFi Re: clinical and radiographic response with combined BRAF-targeted therapy in stage 4 ameloblastoma</article-title><source>Journal of the National Cancer Institute</source><volume>109</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>djw190</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jnci/djw190</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27671684</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-7"><label>Fernandes et al. (2018)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Girardi</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bernardes</surname><given-names>JPG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fonseca</surname><given-names>FP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fregnani</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Clinical benefit and radiological response with BRAF inhibitor in a patient with recurrent ameloblastoma harboring V600E mutation</article-title><source>BMC Cancer</source><volume>18</volume><fpage>887</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12885-018-4802-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30208863</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-8"><label>Goes et al. (2023)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Goes</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Spadigam</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dhupar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cota</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Syed</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2023">2023</year><article-title>Detection and evaluation of the presence of the BRAF V600E mutation in ameloblastomas in an Indian population</article-title><source>Indian Journal of Pathology and Microbiology</source><volume>66</volume><fpage>246</fpage><lpage>251</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/ijpm.ijpm_398_21</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37077063</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-9"><label>Grynberg et al. (2024)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Grynberg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vered</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shapira-Frommer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Asher</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ben-Betzalel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stoff</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Steinberg</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Amariglio</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barshack</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2024">2024</year><article-title>Neoadjuvant BRAF-targeted therapy for ameloblastoma of the mandible: an organ preservation approach</article-title><source>JNCI: Journal of the National Cancer Institute</source><volume>116</volume><fpage>539</fpage><lpage>546</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jnci/djad232</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37966914</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-10"><label>Heikinheimo et al. (2019)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Heikinheimo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huhtala</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thiel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kurppa</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Heikinheimo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kovac</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kragelund</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Warfvinge</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dawson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Elenius</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ristim&#x000e4;ki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baumhoer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>The mutational profile of unicystic ameloblastoma</article-title><source>Journal of Dental Research</source><volume>98</volume><fpage>54</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0022034518798810</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30216733</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-11"><label>Ida et al. (2013)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ida</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vrana</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jentoft</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Caron</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Giannini</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year><article-title>Immunohistochemistry is highly sensitive and specific for detection of BRAF V600E mutation in pleomorphic xanthoastrocytoma</article-title><source>Acta Neuropathologica Communications</source><volume>1</volume><fpage>20</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/2051-5960-1-20</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24252190</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-12"><label>Kelppe et al. (2019)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kelppe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thor&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ristim&#x000e4;ki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Haglund</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sorsa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hagstr&#x000f6;m</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>BRAF V600E expression in ameloblastomas-A 36-patient cohort from Helsinki University Hospital</article-title><source>Oral Diseases</source><volume>25</volume><fpage>1169</fpage><lpage>1174</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/odi.13072</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30811720</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-13"><label>Kitkumthorn &#x00026; Mutirangura (2010)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kitkumthorn</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mutirangura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year><article-title>LINE-1 methylation difference between ameloblastoma and keratocystic odontogenic tumor</article-title><source>Oral Diseases</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>286</fpage><lpage>291</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1601-0825.2009.01640.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20374511</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-14"><label>Kokubun et al. (2022)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kokubun</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Akashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chujo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nakajima</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Matsuzaka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year><article-title>Genetic study of BRAF V600E and SMO L412F mutations in Japanese patients with ameloblastoma</article-title><source>International Journal of Surgical Pathology</source><volume>30</volume><fpage>378</fpage><lpage>384</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/10668969211064203</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34994576</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-15"><label>Kumar et al. (2018)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stecher</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Knyaz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>MEGA X: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis across computing platforms</article-title><source>Molecular Biology and Evolution</source><volume>35</volume><fpage>1547</fpage><lpage>1549</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msy096</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29722887</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-16"><label>Kumar et al. (2021)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vanagundi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Manchanda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mohanty</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Meher</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year><article-title>Radiolucent jaw lesions: imaging approach</article-title><source>Indian Journal of Radiology and Imaging</source><volume>31</volume><fpage>224</fpage><lpage>236</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34316130</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-17"><label>Kurppa et al. (2014)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kurppa</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cat&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ristim&#x000e4;ki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ruhin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kellokoski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Elenius</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Heikinheimo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>High frequency of BRAF V600E mutations in ameloblastoma</article-title><source>The Journal of Pathology</source><volume>232</volume><fpage>492</fpage><lpage>498</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/path.4317</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24374844</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-18"><label>Lapthanasupkul et al. (2021)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lapthanasupkul</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Laosuk</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ruangvejvorachai</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aittiwarapoj</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kitkumthorn</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year><article-title>Frequency of BRAF V600E mutation in a group of Thai patients with ameloblastomas</article-title><source>Oral Surgery, Oral Medicine, Oral Pathology, and Oral Radiology</source><volume>132</volume><elocation-id>e180-e185</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.oooo.2020.06.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32665205</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-19"><label>Loo et al. (2018)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Loo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Khalili</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Beuhler</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Siddiqi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vasef</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>BRAF V600E Mutation across multiple tumor types: correlation between DNA-based sequencing and mutation-specific immunohistochemistry</article-title><source>Applied Immunohistochemistry &#x00026; Molecular Morphology</source><volume>26</volume><fpage>709</fpage><lpage>713</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/pai.0000000000000516</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29271794</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-20"><label>Mamat Yusof, Ch&#x02019;ng &#x00026; Radhiah Abdul Rahman (2022)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mamat Yusof</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ch&#x02019;ng</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Radhiah Abdul Rahman</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year><article-title>BRAF V600E mutation in ameloblastoma: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Cancers</source><volume>14</volume><fpage>5593</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/cancers14225593</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36428683</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-21"><label>Masthan et al. (2015)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Masthan</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Anitha</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Krupaa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Manikkam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Ameloblastoma</article-title><source>Journal of Pharmacy And Bioallied Sciences</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>S167</fpage><lpage>S170</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0975-7406.155891</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26015700</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-22"><label>Meevassana et al. (2022)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Meevassana</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Anothaisatapon</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Subbalekha</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kamolratanakul</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Siritientong</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ruangritchankul</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pungrasami</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hamill</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Angsapatt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kitkumthorn</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year><article-title>BRAF V600E immunohistochemistry predicts prognosis of patients with cutaneous melanoma in Thai population</article-title><source>Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery&#x02013;Global Open</source><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>e4605</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/GOX.0000000000004605</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36299811</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-23"><label>Mendez et al. (2022)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mendez</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wolsefer</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Asa</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wasman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yoest</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stojanov</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year><article-title>The diagnostic utility of BRAF VE1 mutation-specific immunohistochemistry in ameloblastoma</article-title><source>Modern Pathology</source><volume>35</volume><fpage>1570</fpage><lpage>1577</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41379-022-01105-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35676332</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-24"><label>Michaloglou et al. (2008)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Michaloglou</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vredeveld</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mooi</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Peeper</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year><article-title>BRAF(E600) in benign and malignant human tumours</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><volume>27</volume><fpage>877</fpage><lpage>895</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.onc.1210704</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17724477</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-25"><label>Petrovic et al. (2018)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Petrovic</surname><given-names>ID</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Migliacci</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ganly</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ghossein</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huryn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Ameloblastomas of the mandible and maxilla</article-title><source>Ear Nose Throat</source><volume>97</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>E26</fpage><lpage>E32</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-26"><label>Qiao et al. (2021)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Qiao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year><article-title>Recurrence rates of intraosseous ameloblastoma cases with conservative or aggressive treatment: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Frontiers in Oncology</source><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>647200</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fonc.2021.647200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34094934</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-27"><label>Qiu et al. (2015)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ying</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Detection of BRAF mutation in Chinese tumor patients using a highly sensitive antibody immunohistochemistry assay</article-title><source>Scientific Reports</source><volume>5</volume><fpage>9211</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep09211</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25784606</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-28"><label>Ritterhouse &#x00026; Barletta (2015)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ritterhouse</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barletta</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>BRAF V600E mutation-specific antibody: a review</article-title><source>Seminars in Diagnostic Pathology</source><volume>32</volume><fpage>400</fpage><lpage>408</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.semdp.2015.02.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25744437</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-29"><label>Sambrook &#x00026; Russell (2006)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sambrook</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>Purification of nucleic acids by extraction with phenol: chloroform</article-title><source>Cold Spring Harbor Protocols</source><volume>1</volume><elocation-id>pdb.prot4455</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/pdb.prot4455</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-30"><label>Scariot et al. (2012)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Scariot</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Da Silva</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Da Silva Felix Jr</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Da Costa</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rebellato</surname><given-names>NLB</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><article-title>Conservative treatment of ameloblastoma in child: a case report</article-title><source>Stomatologija</source><volume>14</volume><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22617333</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-31"><label>Shirsat et al. (2018)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shirsat</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bansal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Prasad</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Desai</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Low frequency of BRAF V600E immunoexpression in mandibular ameloblastomas: an institutional study</article-title><source>Journal of Oral and Maxillofacial Pathology</source><volume>22</volume><fpage>353</fpage><lpage>359</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/jomfp.JOMFP_174_17</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30651680</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-32"><label>Tan et al. (2016)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pollack</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Colevas</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>West</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>BRAF inhibitor treatment of primary BRAF-mutant ameloblastoma with pathologic assessment of response</article-title><source>Oral Surgery, Oral Medicine, Oral Pathology, and Oral Radiology</source><volume>122</volume><elocation-id>e5-e7</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.oooo.2015.12.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27209484</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-33"><label>Togni et al. (2022)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Togni</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zizzi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mazzucchelli</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Santarelli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rubini</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mascitti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year><article-title>Identification of BRAF V600E mutation in odontogenic tumors by high-performance MALDI-TOF analysis</article-title><source>International Journal of Oral Science</source><volume>14</volume><fpage>22</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41368-022-00170-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35468886</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-34"><label>WHO Classification of Tumours Editorial Board (2022)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>WHO Classification of Tumours Editorial Board</collab>
</person-group><year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year><source>Head and neck tumours</source><publisher-name>International Agency for Research on Cancer</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Lyon</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>