<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Microb Genom</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Microb Genom</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">mgen</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">mgen</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Microbial Genomics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2057-5858</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Microbiology Society</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40408139</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12102497</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">001412</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/mgen.0.001412</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="display-channel"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Pathogens and Epidemiology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The pet caf&#x000e9; is a neglected site for transmission of antimicrobial-resistant Escherichia coli in urban life</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Ruan-Yang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="equal-contrib1" ref-type="author-notes">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>Xiao-Ling</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="equal-contrib1" ref-type="author-notes">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>Ya-Li</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Xi-Ran</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Xiao-Hui</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Jian</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>Xiao-Ping</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Ya-Hong</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">5</xref><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>Hao</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">5</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref><email>hao.ren@scau.edu.cn</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Lian</surname><given-names>Xin-Lei</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">5</xref><xref rid="cor2" ref-type="corresp">*</xref><email>xinlei_lian@scau.edu.cn</email></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution content-type="department">National Risk Assessment Laboratory for Antimicrobial Resistance of Animal Original Bacteria</institution>, <institution>South China Agricultural University</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Guangzhou</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Guangdong</addr-line>, <country>PR China</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution content-type="department">Guangdong Provincial Key Laboratory of Veterinary Pharmaceutics Development and Safety Evaluation</institution>, <institution>South China Agricultural University</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Guangzhou</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Guangdong</addr-line>, <country>PR China</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution content-type="department">Institute of Pediatrics, Guangzhou Women and Children&#x02019;s Medical Center</institution>, <institution>Guangzhou Medical University</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Guangzhou</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Guangdong</addr-line>, <country>PR China</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><institution content-type="department">Department of Medical Genetics, School of Basic Medical Sciences</institution>, <institution>Southern Medical University</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Guangzhou</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Guangdong</addr-line>, <country>PR China</country></aff><aff id="aff5"><label>5</label><institution>Guangdong Laboratory for Lingnan Modern Agriculture</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Guangzhou</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Guangdong</addr-line>, <country>PR China</country></aff><aff id="aff6"><label>6</label><institution content-type="department">Jiangsu Co-Innovation Center for the Prevention and Control of Important Animal Infectious Diseases and Zoonoses</institution>, <institution>Yangzhou University</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Yangzhou</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Jiangsu</addr-line>, <country>PR China</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>The authors declare that there are no conflicts of interest.</p></fn><fn fn-type="equal" id="equal-contrib1"><label>&#x02020;</label><p>These authors contributed equally to this work</p></fn><corresp id="cor1">Hao Ren, <email xlink:href="hao.ren@scau.edu.cn">hao.ren@scau.edu.cn</email></corresp><corresp id="cor2">Xin-Lei Lian, <email xlink:href="xinlei_lian@scau.edu.cn">xinlei_lian@scau.edu.cn</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>23</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>23</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><!--PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>.--><volume>11</volume><issue>5</issue><elocation-id>001412</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2025 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="mgen-11-5-01412.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><p>The process of urbanization has brought with it several novel lifestyles, but it remains to be seen whether such lifestyles are the potential driver behind the spread of antimicrobial resistance (AMR) in modern society. Hence, this study employs the pet caf&#x000e9; as a proof of concept to observe how one pathway of AMR transmission occurs within a megacity. A total of 111&#x02009;samples were collected from consumers, workers, animals and the surrounding environment from three pet caf&#x000e9;s in Guangzhou, and 163 bacterial strains were isolated, with <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=60) being the most dominant species. The sequence type and genomic diversity of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> were observed in all three caf&#x000e9;s. Notably, 19 highly related ST328 strains were isolated in a single pet caf&#x000e9; from both workers (skin and faeces) and animals (faeces), suggesting transmission between distinct hosts. The number of SNPs between ST328 <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> isolated in this study and strains from other provinces in China was minimal, with the possibility of clonal transmission. In terms of AMR, 90% of the isolates exhibited resistance to at least three distinct classes of antimicrobials (multidrug resistance). Multiple antimicrobial resistance genes (ARGs) such as <italic toggle="yes">tet</italic>(X4) were detected in this study, and plasmid, especially hybrid plasmid, is the main transmission vector of these ARGs. Our findings highlight that the pet caf&#x000e9; is a neglected site for the transfer of ARGs among <italic toggle="yes">Enterobacteriaceae</italic>, with a propensity for continuous contamination through either clonal or horizontal transmission of ARGs.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>antimicrobial resistance</kwd><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic></kwd><kwd>pet caf&#x000e9;</kwd><kwd>plasmid</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution>Local Innovative and Research Teams Project of Guangdong Pearl River Talents Program</institution>
</funding-source><award-id>2019BT02N054</award-id><principal-award-recipient>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Yahong</given-names></name>
</principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution>Innovation Team Project of Guangdong University</institution>
</funding-source><award-id>2019KCXTD001</award-id><principal-award-recipient>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Yahong</given-names></name>
</principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution-id>http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100001809</institution-id></institution-wrap>
<institution>National Natural Science Foundation of China</institution>
</funding-source><award-id>32121004</award-id><principal-award-recipient>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Yahong</given-names></name>
</principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution>National Key Research and Development Program of China</institution>
</funding-source><award-id>2023YFD1800101</award-id><principal-award-recipient>
<name><surname>Applicable</surname><given-names>Not</given-names></name>
</principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group></article-meta></front><body><boxed-text id="BX1" position="float"><sec><title>Impact Statement</title><p><italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> is one of the most frequently isolated Gram-negative pathogens globally. It is both a widespread gut commensal of vertebrates and a versatile pathogen, with the potential to cause severe invasive disease, for which antimicrobial treatment is warranted. Consequently, the emergence of multidrug-resistant strains poses a significant challenge to effective treatment and is regarded as one of the major threats to global health. This study demonstrates the transmission of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> from shared pets to customers in the pet caf&#x000e9;, a novel urban innovation. The close interaction between shared pets and multiple batches of customers increases the risk of the transmission of multidrug-resistant (MDR) <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> and antimicrobial resistance genes (ARGs), especially acquired resistance to extended-spectrum cephalosporins and tigecycline, antibiotics that are critically important in the treatment of humans. These results raise concerns about the potential transmission of ARGs to the broader community in megacities. It is, therefore, necessary to implement corresponding intervention measures to reduce the possibility of ARGs and MDR bacteria transmission.</p></sec></boxed-text><sec id="s1"><title>Data Summary</title><p>The newly sequenced genomes are listed in Table S1. These genomes have been submitted to the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI), and their BioProject number is PRJNA1021388.</p></sec><sec sec-type="intro" id="s2"><title>Introduction</title><p>Antimicrobial resistance (AMR) is one of the top global public health and development threats. A range of factors, including antimicrobial consumption and high-density urbanization, have been identified as key drivers for AMR [<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref><xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. However, the full extent of the impact of emerging lifestyles and economic patterns associated with urbanization on AMR remains unclear. This knowledge gap underscores the need for further investigation to elucidate the potential effects of novel urban living and economic practices on the development and spread of antibiotic resistance. Animals, especially companion animals, are one of the important reservoirs of antimicrobial resistance genes (ARGs), posing a threat to the spread of ARGs to humans and the environment. Several studies have shown that there was a higher abundance and diversity of ARGs in the pets than in their owners, the composition of ARGs and mobile genetic element (MGE) between companion animals and their owners was found to be significantly similar and <italic toggle="yes">Enterobacteriaceae</italic> was the dominant ARG host co-occurring in the pet gut, human gut and living environment [<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref><xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Nevertheless, the considerable financial implications of pet ownership deter young people from maintaining a pet in their residence. Consequently, the trend of pet caf&#x000e9; sharing animals with customers is gaining popularity in China&#x02019;s major urban cities. This consumption model fulfils the human desire for interaction with animals while circumventing the high costs associated with pet ownership. These services have a public service aspect, given that animals frequently come into close contact with different individuals. Unlike pets kept at home, where owners share a stable and intimate living relationship with their pets, animals in pet caf&#x000e9;s serve multiple batches of different customers. Unlike animals in zoos, animals in pet caf&#x000e9;s have direct contact with customers at close quarters. Additionally, the pet caf&#x000e9; serves as a social venue, offering patrons the opportunity to engage in conversation, consume food and beverages and interact with the pets. The characteristics of pet caf&#x000e9;s make this consumption model unique and distinct from others, potentially acting as intermediaries for the spread of antibiotic-resistant genes and leading to significant public health risks [<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> is a diverse species of enteric bacteria that has the potential to cause severe clinical outcomes, including diarrhoea, urinary tract infections, meningitis and bloodstream infections [<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. It is well documented that <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> can be either commensal or pathogenic. Due to the considerable genetic plasticity, the carriage of known pathotype-associated diarrheagenic virulence factors by <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> underscores their potential to be more pathogenic [<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref><xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. For instance, ST131 <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>, a globally dominant highly virulent multidrug-resistant (MDR) clone causing urinary tract infections and bloodstream infections, has been reported to be found in companion animals, suggesting the possibility of inter-species transmission from animals to their owners [<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref><xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Additionally, <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> is regarded as a significant reservoir for multiple clinically important ARGs and an excellent indicator of AMR transmission between distinct hosts [<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. The first reports of multiple clinically important ARGs, including <italic toggle="yes">mcr-1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">tet</italic>(X4), were published in the context of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> [<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref><xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Often, the horizontal gene transfer of ARGs between bacteria was facilitated by MGEs, such as transposons, integrons and plasmids [<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Various plasmid types such as IncF and IncHI2 plasmids have been extensively documented as vectors for the horizontal spread of ARGs, playing an important role in ARG transmission [<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref><xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. The co-occurrence of virulence genes and ARGs could contribute to the higher mortality of immunocompromised patients with <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> bacteremia [<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], representing a significant public health threat.</p><p>In this study, we compared the phylogenetic relationship and the ARG profile of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> collected from pets, humans and surfaces in the caf&#x000e9; environments and explored the potential inter-host transmission between pets and customers. In summary, our findings elucidate the genomic structure and population diversity of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> from pet caf&#x000e9;s in a megacity to understand the potential impact of close contact between customers and shared pets.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s3"><title>Methods</title><sec id="s3-1"><title>General characteristics of pet caf&#x000e9;s</title><p>Three pet caf&#x000e9;s were selected for sample collection in this study. Two caf&#x000e9;s were located in Tianhe district, the other one was in Yuexiu district and each caf&#x000e9; was located over 7&#x02009;km away from the other two caf&#x000e9;s. They exhibited homogeneous spatial configurations and operational protocols. All three investigated pet caf&#x000e9;s were indoor confined environments with limited floor area, each equipped with sanitation facilities (restrooms/handwashing stations). There are more washing stations in caf&#x000e9; 3 than in other caf&#x000e9;s. While designated zones were allocated for different animal species, free-roaming access throughout the pet caf&#x000e9;s was permitted. Faeces from animals were not promptly removed according to standardized hygienic protocols. Customers were permitted to engage in direct interactive activities including tactile contact with animals and the provision of feed. Furthermore, these pet caf&#x000e9;s provided beverage and food services, enabling customers to eat food while engaging in animal interactions.</p></sec><sec id="s3-2"><title>Sample collection</title><p>From January 2022 to June 2022, a total of 111&#x02009;samples of animal faeces (48&#x02009;samples), human faeces (2&#x02009;samples) and skin (including customers and workers, total 14&#x02009;samples), animal skin (13&#x02009;samples) and surrounding environment (34&#x02009;samples) were collected from three pet caf&#x000e9;s in Guangzhou, Guangdong, China. Collection protocols were listed as follows: (1) animal faecal sample collection &#x02013; fresh pet faeces were collected using sterile cotton swabs and transferred into 50-ml centrifuge tubes. (2) Human faecal sample collection: fresh human stool specimens were obtained using sterile collection bags. (3) Human skin sample collection: sterile saline-moistened cotton swabs were used to swab human hand and head surfaces, with subsequent placement of swabs into centrifuge tubes containing 2&#x02009;ml of sterilized saline. (4) Animal skin sample collection: epidermal and fur samples from animals were swabbed using sterile cotton swabs moistened with saline solution. The swabs were then placed in centrifuge tubes containing 2&#x02009;ml of sterilized saline. (5) Environmental sample collection: interaction tools, handwashing sinks, cages and other surfaces in pet caf&#x000e9;s were sampled using sterile saline-moistened cotton swabs. (6) Pet drinking water collection: drinking water samples were directly collected from water dispensers into 50-ml sterile centrifuge tubes. Collected swabs were deposited into centrifuge tubes containing 2&#x02009;ml of sterilized saline. All samples were collected, set into sterile sacks and stored at temperatures underneath 4 &#x02103;.</p></sec><sec id="s3-3"><title>Bacterial isolation</title><p>The samples were transported promptly to the laboratory for further examination (Table S1, available in the online Supplementary Material). The details of bacterial isolation are conducted as follows: (1) animal and human faecal &#x02013; a faecal aliquot was aseptically transferred from the collection tube into a 2-ml sterile centrifuge tube containing 1&#x02009;ml of normal saline (0.9% NaCl). The mixture was vortex-mixed thoroughly for homogeneous suspension. Subsequently, 50&#x02009;&#x000b5;l aliquots of the homogenized faecal suspension were aspirated and evenly spread onto MacConkey agar plates using a sterile spreading rod. (2) Animal/human skin and environmental samples: collected samples were directly subjected to vortex homogenization. Following homogenization, 50&#x02009;&#x000b5;l aliquots of each sample suspension was aseptically transferred and uniformly inoculated onto MacConkey agar plates using a sterile spreading rod. (3) Pet drinking water: a 50&#x02009;&#x000b5;l aliquot was directly aspirated from the water sample and streaked evenly onto MacConkey agar plates employing a sterile spreading rod. Diluted samples were incubated for 18&#x02009;h at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. All colonies from each sample that were bright peach or reddish with a dark peach centre were selected.</p></sec><sec id="s3-4"><title>Genome sequencing and bioinformatics analysis</title><p>The genomic DNA of all isolates was extracted using the TIANamp Bacteria DNA Kit (Tiangen, Beijing, China) and subjected to 250&#x02009;bp paired-end whole-genome sequencing (WGS) using the Illumina HiSeq system (San Diego, CA, USA). Trimmed reads were assembled by SPAdes v3.6.2 [<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Multilocus sequencing typing (MLST) and phylogenetic groups of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> were analysed using the mlst tool (<ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/tseemann/mlst/" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/tseemann/mlst/</ext-link>) and the ClermonTyping method [<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], respectively. A minimum spanning tree of all STs was generated by Phyloviz v2.0 using the BURST algorithm [<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. AMR genes, target mutations in QRDRs, virulence factors and plasmid replicon types were obtained using AMRFinder v3.8.4 [<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] and ABRicate v1.0.1 (<ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/tseemann/abricate" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/tseemann/abricate</ext-link>). The network graph describing the co-occurrence of ARGs and plasmid replicons was constructed using Gephi v0.9.2 [<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], and principal component analysis (PCA) was measured using the &#x02018;ggord&#x02019; package. MOB-suite with MOB-recon and MOB-typer software modules was used to partially reconstruct and type the plasmids from short-read genome assemblies [<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s3-5"><title>Antimicrobial susceptibility testing</title><p>The minimum inhibitory concentrations (MICs) of 18 antimicrobial agents for <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> isolates were determined using the agar dilution method, and the results were interpreted according to the European Committee on Antimicrobial Susceptibility Testing (v10.0, for tigecycline and colistin) and the Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute document (M100-S28 and VET01-S2, for the remaining antibiotics) [<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref><xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> ATCC 25922 served as the quality control strain.</p></sec><sec id="s3-6"><title>Phylogenetic analysis</title><p>All <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> assemblies were used for core-genome alignments to construct phylogenetic trees using Snippy v4.6.0 (<ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/tseemann/snippy" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/tseemann/snippy</ext-link>). SNPs were called, and recombinant regions were removed using Gubbins v2.4.1 and the final SNPs extracted with SNP-sites [<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref><xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Maximum likelihood (ML) phylogenetic trees were inferred using RAxML v8.2.12 (GTRGAMMA substitution model) [<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. The final tree was mid-point rooted and visualized with iTOL v5 [<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Pairwise SNPs between strains were counted from the core SNP alignment with snp-dists v0.7.0. The lineages of the phylogenetic tree were defined using rhierBAPs [<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>].</p><p>To provide a global context, additional ST328 <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> genomes were downloaded from the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI) Pathogen database (<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pathogens/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pathogens/</ext-link>) (access date: 15 July 2024). Basic information of all genomes was collected from the NCBI by using an automated python script. A core-genome non-recombinant ML tree was constructed and visualized, as described above.</p></sec><sec id="s3-7"><title>Pan-genome analysis</title><p>For pan-genome analysis, all <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> genomes were annotated by Prokka v1.14.6 [<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], and annotation files were carried out using Panaroo v1.3.3 to cluster the genes encoding complete protein sequences into core (core and soft core) and accessory (shell and cloud) genomes [<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. We chose a percentage identity of 95% to distinguish between the core genes and the accessory genes. Non-metric multidimensional scaling (NMDS) was performed to calculate the similarity coefficient by Jaccard Index at ARG level, virulence factor level and pan-genome level using the vegan R packages [<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s3-8"><title>Long-read sequencing of a representative <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> strain</title><p>Five representative isolates were selected for long-read sequencing using the ONT MinION Platform (Nanopore, Oxford, UK). Isolates were selected for sequencing based on the diversity of AMR profiles and lineage membership. ONT sequencing was performed using the R9.4 flow cell (FLO-MIN106). Raw reads generated by MinKNOW were basecalled and barcoded using Guppy. The <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> hybrid assembly of both short (Illumina) and long reads (ONT) was performed using Unicycler v0.5.0 [<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Mobility prediction was recognized using MOB-suite v 3.1.9 [<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Sequence comparison of chromosomes and plasmids was conducted using Clinker v0.0.25 and BRIG [<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref><xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s4"><title>Results</title><sec id="s4-1"><title>Bacterial isolation and antimicrobial resistance profile</title><p>Overall, a total of 163 Gram-negative bacteria were obtained by growing the collected samples in MacConkey media. All strains were subjected to WGS, and the combined species identification indicated that 163 isolates belonged to eight <italic toggle="yes">Enterobacteriaceae</italic> species, including <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=60), <italic toggle="yes">Enterobacter cloacae</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=25), <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=10), <italic toggle="yes">Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=9) and other species (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> and Table S1). This demonstrates a high bacterial diversity over pet caf&#x000e9; niches. The predominant species among the entire strain collection is <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>, which was detected in all three pet caf&#x000e9;s. Accordingly, subsequent analysis will concentrate on <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> strains.</p><fig position="float" id="F1" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><title>Geographical distribution of sampled points in the region of Guangzhou city. The locations of three sampled pet caf&#x000e9;s are indicated by circled icons, and the distance between each point is indicated. The total number of bacteria collected from each sampling location is indicated in the centre of the sunburn diagrams. The inner ring represents the proportion of different species, including <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Enterobacter cloacae</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">A. baumannii</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">K. pneumoniae</italic> and others. The middle ring represents the distribution of different bacterial species across a range of hosts in each sampling pet caf&#x000e9;. The outer ring represents the number of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> MDR phenotype.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="mgen-11-01412-g001" position="float"/></fig><p>Antimicrobial susceptibility tests of the 60 <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> strains revealed that these isolates exhibited high resistance to most of the antibiotics tested. Of these strains, 52 were classified as MDR (defined as resistance to more than three categories of antibiotics). The majority of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> strains were resistant to tetracycline (91.7%), sulfamethoxazole/trimethoprim (78.3%), nalidixic acid (63.3%) and ampicillin (55.0%). The resistance rates were found to be lower for florfenicol (33.3%), gentamicin (28.3%), chloramphenicol (25.0%), cefotaxime (11.7%), ceftazidime (10.0%), ceftriaxone (10.0%), ciprofloxacin (10.0%), aztreonam (6.7%), colistin (5.0%) and tigecycline (1.7%). All isolates were susceptible to amikacin, meropenem and fosfomycin (Fig. S1 and Table S2).</p><p>For genotype, 44 acquired antimicrobial resistance genes were identified in the 60 isolates tested. A median of 5 ARGs (range 0&#x02013;17) was detected in the genome of each strain. Genes coding for resistance to tetracyclines [<italic toggle="yes">tet</italic>(A), 41/60], sulfonamides (<italic toggle="yes">sul2</italic>, 34/60; <italic toggle="yes">sul3</italic>, 12/60), aminoglycosides (<italic toggle="yes">strA</italic>, 27/60; <italic toggle="yes">strB</italic>, 31/60) and trimethoprims (<italic toggle="yes">dfrA14</italic>, 33/60) were highly present. Plasmid-mediated quinolone resistance genes (<italic toggle="yes">qnrS1</italic>, 15/60; <italic toggle="yes">qnrS2</italic>, 3/60; <italic toggle="yes">oqxB</italic>, 1/60), third-generation cephalosporins (<italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>CTX-M-15</sub>, 3/60; <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>CTX-M-14</sub>, 2/60; <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>CTX-M-65</sub>, 1/60) and phenicols (<italic toggle="yes">floR</italic>, 14/60) were also detected in the isolates. Surprisingly, the tigecycline resistance gene <italic toggle="yes">tet</italic>(X4) was detected in one of the 60 <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> isolates (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). The AMR genotype was a good predictor of phenotypic MDR and XDR with a high concordance between genotype and phenotype. The contribution of each combination of resistance genes to the MIC of an antimicrobial compound is shown in Fig. S2. The <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> isolates were also found to possess numerous virulence-associated factors, including adherence, effector delivery system, invasion and regulation (Fig. S3). The <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> populations from all three pet caf&#x000e9;s exhibited a notable divergence in the antibiotic resistance gene and virulence factor content (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3a, c</xref>), showing distinct resistance mechanisms to particular antimicrobial classes. However, the sum of genetic resistance determinants carried by <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> within each pet caf&#x000e9; demonstrated no statistically significant difference between each other (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3b</xref>). Furthermore, a significantly higher diversity was observed in the virulence factor from pet caf&#x000e9;s 1 and 2 when compared to pet caf&#x000e9; 3 (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3d</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F2" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><title>Genomic analysis of 60 <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> isolates in three pet caf&#x000e9;s in Guangzhou city. An ML phylogenetic tree was constructed using the core-genome SNPs and midpoint rooted. Internal nodes are labelled with circles indicating branch &#x0003e;70% bootstrap support. The shadow represents the clade, and the rectangular colour blocks represent three different pet caf&#x000e9;s. The presence or absence of different classes of antibiotic resistance genes and plasmid replicons is denoted by filled and empty squares, respectively.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="mgen-11-01412-g002" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F3" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><title>NMDS and violin plots according to Jaccard distance index and the pet caf&#x000e9; (indicated by colours). (<bold>a</bold>) Differential antibiotic resistance gene content. (<bold>b</bold>) Level of antibiotic resistance gene diversity. (<bold>c</bold>) Differential virulence factor content. (<bold>d</bold>) Level of virulence factor diversity. (<bold>e</bold>) Differential genomic content based on pan-genome analysis. (<bold>f</bold>) Level of genomic diversity based on pan-genome analysis. Highly significant differences are indicated by *** (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001). Significant differences are indicated by ** (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x0003c;0.01). Non-significant differences are indicated by <sc>ns</sc>.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="mgen-11-01412-g003" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="s4-2"><title>Genomic diversity of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> in pet caf&#x000e9;s</title><p><italic toggle="yes">In silico</italic> MLST clustered the 60 <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> into 17 distinct sequence types (STs) and 2 unknown STs, with pet caf&#x000e9; 1 clustered in 5 STs and pet caf&#x000e9; 2 and caf&#x000e9; 3 clustered in 6 STs (Table S1). MLST data for the 60 isolates were used to generate a minimum spanning tree. Distinct STs were associated with the different pet caf&#x000e9;s, with a high level of genetic diversity observed overall (Fig. S4). ST328 was the dominant sequence type, accounting for 31.7% (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=19), followed by ST648 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=6) and ST206 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=5). ST328 isolates were detected in the same pet caf&#x000e9; and were associated with isolates from worker skin (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=2), worker faeces (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=1), rabbit faeces (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=12) and other animal (deer, hedgehog and alpaca) faeces (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=4), suggesting this particular pet caf&#x000e9; is the common source of ST328 <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>, and continued contamination of humans and pets occurred. The <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> isolates were classified into four groups using Clermont typing, with the majority of isolates belonging to groups B1 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=27, 45.0%) and A (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=18, 30.0%). These two groups are typically associated with commensal strains [<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. The combined MLST and Clermont typing analysis revealed pronounced genetic diversity among the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> isolates tested in this study.</p><p>To better understand the genetic diversity of the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> in the pet caf&#x000e9;, an ML phylogeny was constructed based on 150,073 core-genome SNPs (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). Five sequence clusters (SCs) were classified by hierBAPs analysis. Lineage 5 encompassed 19 isolates from the same pet caf&#x000e9;, exhibiting a high degree of whole-genome sequence similarity (pairwise SNPs&#x02264;4) between workers&#x02019; skin, workers&#x02019; faeces and shared pets&#x02019; faeces (Table S3). Similarly, the ST648 isolates obtained from the skin of workers and the faeces of pets (cats, rabbits and dogs) were identified as belonging to lineage 2 and exhibited four distinct SNPs. This indicates that they originated from a common ancestor and provides evidence of direct transmission of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> among humans and pets within one pet caf&#x000e9;. Lineage 3 and lineage 4 comprised isolates from all three caf&#x000e9;s. Based on the phylogenetic tree and diversity of MLST types analysis, <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> strains isolated from pet and human faeces and environmental samples in three pet caf&#x000e9;s were diverse and exhibited no obvious clonal spread between pet caf&#x000e9;s in one megacity. Pan-genome analysis based on the 60 isolates showed that a total of 18,909 genes were identified, of which 16,726 were assigned to the accessory genome. The accessory genes accounted for 88.5%, encompassing a remarkable diversity and high plasticity among these strains. Unlike the lower diversity of ARG content observed between each caf&#x000e9;, the genomic diversity of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> was found to be statistically significant. The diversity was higher in the total <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> population from pet caf&#x000e9; 1 compared to the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> population from pet caf&#x000e9; 2 and pet caf&#x000e9; 3, considering the genes that were present and absent in each caf&#x000e9; from the total pan-genome (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3e, f</xref>).</p><p>To provide further contextualization of our data, we conducted a phylogenetic comparison of 19 ST328 isolates from our study with 190 publicly available ST328 sequences (Table S4). ST328 <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> were mainly distributed in the USA (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=61, 29.2%), the UK (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=27, 12.9%) and China (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=23, 11.0%). The ST328 strains were observed to be distributed in the clinic (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=83, 39.7%) and chicken (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=57, 27.3%). All ST328 strains belong to phylogroup B1 and carry the <italic toggle="yes">eae</italic> gene, identified as enteropathogenic <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> (EPEC). The phylogenetic analysis revealed a high degree of diversity, with multiple small clades (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4a</xref> and Table S5). A sheep strain from Jiangsu province, China, in 2019 and another strain from Zhejiang province, China, in the same year had high similarity (133&#x02013;145 SNPs) with the cluster of 19 isolates collected in this study, clustering in the same branch. There was a possibility of transmission between different hosts, indicating that a specific ST328 clone has been circulating for 4&#x02009;years in China and is phylogenetically distinct from European or American isolates. In addition, the number of ARGs carried by this specific type of ST remained high, with a range of 0 to 19 (Table S4). A similarity analysis of ARG and VF composition among ST328 strains was performed using PCA. Although the composition of ARGs was found to be similar between samples from five continents, the strains from Europe were found to be closely clustered, and strains from other continents possessed a level of variance (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4b</xref>). Moreover, the composition of VFs in strains from Europe and Africa was closely clustered, whereas strains from Asia and North America exhibited evident scattering (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4c</xref>). Based on the pan-genome analysis, ST328 <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> comprised 11,395 unique genes, with accessory genes (present in less than 99% of the isolates) accounting for 69.2%, covering a considerable ST328 <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> diversity. NMDS was performed based on the accessory gene content matrix to investigate genetic composition differences between each continent (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4d</xref>). The genes comprising the pan-genomes of ST328 <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> from different continents were found to be statistically different, except between Europe and Africa, indicating that this specific ST type has undergone a localized expansion in each continent.</p><fig position="float" id="F4" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 4.</label><caption><title>Phylogenetic structures of Chinese ST328 <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> in a global context. (<bold>a</bold>) ML tree outlining the phylogenetic structure of 19 ST328 <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> isolates unique to this study (highlighted by the red points) combined with 190 global ST328 <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> isolates. Internal nodes are labelled with circles indicating branch &#x0003e;70% bootstrap support. Metadata are visualized as follows from inner to outer: 1, geographic area of origin; 2, host of isolation; 3, year of isolation; and 4, number of ARGs carriage. (<bold>b</bold>) PCA for antibiotic resistance genes in the five continents. (<bold>c</bold>) PCA for virulence factors in the five continents. (<bold>d</bold>) NMDS and violin plots according to the Jaccard distance index based on ST328 <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> pan-genome analysis. Highly significant differences are indicated by *** (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001). Non-significant differences are indicated by <sc>ns</sc>.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="mgen-11-01412-g004" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="s4-3"><title>Genetic analysis of MDR strains</title><p>To explore the co-relationship between ARGs and plasmid replicons, a correlation analysis was constructed. When the Spearman value &#x0003e;&#x02009;0.3&#x02009;and <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, it was hypothesized that the non-random co-occurrence patterns between ARGs and plasmid replicon could indicate the possible vector information of ARGs [<xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. The visualization of the network consisted of 57 nodes and 334 edges, and the modularity index of the network was 0.621 (values&#x0003e;0.4). Twelve types of plasmids were speculated as the possible ARG vectors based on the co-occurrence results. For instance, <italic toggle="yes">tet</italic>(X4) was strongly associated with the IncF plasmid. Similarly, <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>CTX-M-14</sub> was strongly associated with IncI1 plasmid (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5a</xref>). Using MOB-suite, we were able to partially reconstruct and characterize the 117 plasmids carrying known replicons for 54 draft genome assemblies of overall 60 isolates. Eighty-three (70.9%) of them were predicted as conjugative or mobilizable (Table S8).</p><fig position="float" id="F5" fig-type="figure"><label>Fig. 5.</label><caption><title>Genetic basis of multiple ARGs in this study. (<bold>a</bold>) Co-occurrence pattern of ARGs with plasmid replicons. The nodes represent ARGs or plasmid replicons. Connections between nodes with the same colour indicate that they are related. Moreover, the line&#x02019;s thickness is proportional to the correlation strength, with a thicker line indicating a stronger relationship between the variables. All associated genes in the figure had <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> values less than 0.05. The co-occurrence between ARGs and plasmid replicons is annotated on the bottom right. (<bold>b</bold>) The linear alignment of complete IncF plasmids in this study. (<bold>c</bold>) The circular genetic map of the IncFIB(K)/IncFIA(HI1)/IncX1 plasmid in one animal faeces isolate and other plasmids deposited in the GenBank database. (<bold>d</bold>) The circular genetic map of the IncHI1B/Incp0111 and Incp0111 plasmids from animal faeces and other plasmids deposited in the GenBank database.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="mgen-11-01412-g005" position="float"/></fig><p>The utilization of long- and short-read hybrid assembly enabled the comprehensive elucidation of the genomic structure of five representative <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> strains, selected based on their origin, ST, antibiotic resistance gene composition and plasmid content (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). We found that no ARGs are located on the chromosome in the five complete sequenced isolates, plasmids being the main vector of transmission of these ARGs (Table S9). Based on the MOB-suite, all complete plasmids were predicted to be conjugative or mobilizable. IncFII plasmid is the most prevalent plasmid type among the strains and possesses typical and conserved IncF backbones such as replication genes and transfer genes. However, the variable region is highly diverse. Multiple insertion sequences such as IS<italic toggle="yes">26</italic> and IS<italic toggle="yes">CR2</italic> contribute to the horizontal transfer of ARGs. It is important to note that the <italic toggle="yes">catD</italic> hydrolase with <italic toggle="yes">tet</italic>(X4) is flanked by a complete and a truncated copy of IS<italic toggle="yes">CR2</italic> in the same orientation, which are inserted into the MDR region (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5b</xref>). IS<italic toggle="yes">CR2</italic> has previously been reported to be associated with the generation of the circular form, facilitating the mobilization of <italic toggle="yes">tet</italic>(X4), mediating resistance to last resort antibiotic tigecycline [<xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>].</p><p>Plasmids in pet caf&#x000e9;s also possessed high genetic plasticity. Hybrid and multi-replicon plasmids were detected, and that was likely generated by recombination between different plasmid backbones. The presence of multiple replicons in pet caf&#x000e9;s might prevent plasmid incompatibility and facilitate their interaction with a broad range of hosts [<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Plasmid pPS3T_animalfaeces_2_72&#x02009;kb was identified as an IncFIB(K)/IncFIA(HI1)/IncX1 hybrid plasmid. The sequence organization was found to be similar to that of plasmid p2-Ec387 (AP024584.1, Japan, pig, coverage 76%, identity 99%), plasmid pG3X16-2-3 (CP038140.1, China, pig, coverage 80%, identity 99%) and plasmid p655Rt (CP080058.1, China, human, coverage 76%, identity 99%) (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5c</xref>). Plasmid pPS2C_animalfaeces_3_136&#x02009;kb was likely formed by fusion between the IncHI1 plasmid and an Incp0111 plasmid. <sc>blastn</sc> comparison of the IncHI1/Incp0111 hybrid plasmid with those in the NCBI database showed more than 99% nucleotide identity at 82% coverage to two other plasmids, namely pF1053-2 (OY757951.1, France, human) and pYLMB10a (CP073989.1, Cuba, poultry) (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5d</xref>). Interestingly, we also identified an Incp0111 plasmid (pPS2C_animalfaeces_12_95&#x02009;kb) in the same caf&#x000e9;, two plasmids (pPS2C_animalfaeces_3_136&#x02009;kb and pPS2C_animalfaeces_12_95&#x02009;kb) isolated from different animals (cat and pig) in one caf&#x000e9; shared 99% nucleotide identity and 45% coverage, and IS<italic toggle="yes">5</italic> served as a potential recombination site for plasmid recombination, suggesting the potential for the formation of cointegrate plasmids and continued transmission in one caf&#x000e9; (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5d</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s5"><title>Discussion</title><p>In the present study, we aimed to investigate the antimicrobial traits and genetic characteristics of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> isolates obtained from pet caf&#x000e9;s in Guangzhou, the third megacity in China. Of the multiple bacterial species identified, <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> was the most frequently isolated in the majority of samples. Whole-genome sequencing analysis revealed that 60 <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> from different pet caf&#x000e9;s belonged to 17 different ST types. Luckily, many known to cause extraintestinal infection STs of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> such as ST131, ST10 and ST38 were not detected [<xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref><xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Among STs, ST328 was the most prevalent type, collected from customers, workers, animal faeces and surrounding environments within a single pet caf&#x000e9;. Phylogenetic analysis revealed a high possibility of transmission between workers and shared pets in the same caf&#x000e9;. Pairwise SNP analysis suggested that one ST328 <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> isolate derived from worker faeces (PS1M_humofaeces_1) and the other ten ST328 <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> isolates derived from pet faeces (rabbits and pigs) belonged to a single clone (SNP=0). It is important to note that rabbits are coprophagic, so they are likely to share faecal flora if they are co-housed. Furthermore, the contamination of the skin may be transient and not result in faecal contamination unless handwashing is performed. The detection of similar strains in both the skin and faeces of workers suggests that prolonged contact with animals without adequate disinfection may result in the colonization of the human body. These results showed the high clonality of the strains circulating within the same pet caf&#x000e9;, underlying that pet caf&#x000e9;s in megacities may represent an unexpected site for ARG spillover due to direct contacts between animals and humans, by which the <sc>arb</sc> and ARGs are expected to transmit frequently [<xref rid="R43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. ST328 is an underreported sequence type, and only a few ST328 <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> isolates have been identified in the global collection. The positive rate of the virulence factor <italic toggle="yes">eae</italic> was 100% in ST328 strains, all belonging to EPEC. A similar phenomenon was obtained in ST328 strains collected from rabbits in Sichuan, China [<xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. However, the results of this study showed that these ST328 <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> isolates were all MDR isolates. It is worth noting that only a small number of SNPs differed between the strains isolated from humans and pets in Guangdong in this study and <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> from other Chinese provinces, and there was a possibility of transmission between different hosts in China. It is important to note that the main mode of transmission for ARGs and their hosts in the environment is through direct and indirect contact, such as air and surfaces, and contaminated food and water [<xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref><xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. The exchange of ARGs and their hosting bacteria occurred in the pet caf&#x000e9;. The shared pets have close contact with numerous batches of customers from different areas in the city throughout the day, often without any disinfection measures in place until the caf&#x000e9; closes. This consumer pattern increases the likelihood of shared pets serving as carriers for the spread of ARGs and also presents a potential for sustained transmission.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> isolates from various pet caf&#x000e9;s exhibited distinct genetic compositions, while the level of ARG diversity was similar across all pet caf&#x000e9;s, revealing that horizontal gene transfer is the primary mechanism for ARGs transmission. The pattern of co-occurrence between ARGs and mobile elements revealed by the network analysis helps to better explain the correlation between them [<xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. The network analysis results showed that IncF plasmids were strongly associated with <italic toggle="yes">tet</italic>(X4), <italic toggle="yes">qnrS1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">oqxB</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>CTX-M-15</sub> and <italic toggle="yes">bla</italic><sub>OXA-502</sub> (R&#x0003e;0.3, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05). This phenomenon suggests that plasmids such as IncF (especially IncFII) plasmids play a critical role in facilitating the spread of ARGs [<xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref><xref rid="R48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Tigecycline, one of the few antibiotics used as a last resort, was approved by the FDA in 2005 for the treatment of complicated skin and skin-structure infections as well as complicated intra-abdominal infections [<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Tigecycline is not licensed for veterinary use. However, the production and use of tetracyclines are highest among all antimicrobial compounds in China [<xref rid="R49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. One isolate containing <italic toggle="yes">tet</italic>(X4) located on an IncFII plasmid was detected in animal faeces in one caf&#x000e9;. The core genes including replicon, maintenance and transfer gene cluster were detected in the IncF plasmids, indicating the possibility of transfer of this clinically important ARG from pets to the customers in one caf&#x000e9;. In addition, different types of plasmids were also identified in this study, and most of them are hybrid plasmids. Hybrid plasmids are now commonly observed and possess high genetic plasticity, characterized by an MDR mosaic region and a hybrid backbone likely formed through recombination between different plasmid backbones [<xref rid="R50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref><xref rid="R52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. These recombination events may contribute to expanding the plasmid host range through the integration of multiple replicons and enable adaptation to environmental pressures through the acquisition of ARGs and heavy metal tolerance genes.</p><p>We acknowledge that our study has several limitations. Firstly, our investigation was conducted on a limited scale, involving only three pet caf&#x000e9;s in Guangzhou to examine the persistence of <italic toggle="yes">Enterobacteriaceae</italic>. Secondly, detailed information regarding the origin of the pets in the caf&#x000e9; and their medication history was lacking. Thirdly, no systematic evaluation of the efficacy of cleaning and disinfection of the pet caf&#x000e9;s during the study period was conducted in this study. Therefore, further research is imperative to investigate the potential association between the persistence and transmission of <italic toggle="yes">Enterobacteriaceae</italic> and the effectiveness of cleaning and disinfection practices in these environments.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s6"><title>Conclusion</title><p>In summary, we have described the genetic landscape and relationship of ARGs between shared pets, workers and customers in pet caf&#x000e9;s in China. Moreover, the present study demonstrates that the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> from multiple distinct origins within the same caf&#x000e9; exhibit a close phylogenetic relationship. Moreover, plasmids, particularly hybrid plasmids, facilitate the transmission of ARGs, including <italic toggle="yes">tet</italic>(X4) and others. Overall, in this study, we provided a novel insight into the pet caf&#x000e9;, a neglected site for enrichment and transmission of antimicrobial-resistant <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> in urban life. This novel urban lifestyle may serve as a medium of continuous contamination by either clonal or horizontal transmission of ARGs. This study highlights the potential risk that pet caf&#x000e9;s pose for the transfer of ARGs among <italic toggle="yes">Enterobacteriaceae</italic> and represents a previously underestimated threat from potential health hazards.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s7"><title>Supplementary material</title><supplementary-material id="SM1" position="float" content-type="local-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/mgen.0.001412</object-id><label>Uncited Supplementary Material 1.</label><media xlink:href="mgen-11-01412-s001.pdf" id="d67e1148" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SM2" position="float" content-type="local-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/mgen.0.001412</object-id><label>Uncited Supplementary Material 2.</label><media xlink:href="mgen-11-01412-s002.xlsx" id="d67e1153" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> This work was jointly supported by the National Key Research and Development Programme of China (grant no. 2023YFD1800101), National Natural Science Foundation of China (grant no. 32121004), Innovation Team Project of Guangdong University (grant no. 2019KCXTD001) and Local Innovative and Research Teams Project of Guangdong Pearl River Talents Programme (grant no. 2019BT02N054).</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Author contributions:</bold> R.-Y.S.: Investigation, methodology and writing &#x02013; original draft. X.-L.L., Y.-L.R. and X.-H.W.: Investigation and methodology. X.-R.W.: Visualization. J.S.: Project administration. X.-P. L. and Y.-H.L.: Supervision. H.R.: Writing &#x02013; review and editing. X.-L.L.: Supervision and writing &#x02013; review and editing.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Ethical statement:</bold> This study was approved by the South China Agricultural University Institutional Animal Ethics Committee (2018G002) and the Institutional Review Board of the Guangzhou Women and Children&#x02019;s Medical Center (275A01).</p></fn></fn-group><notes><def-list><title>Abbreviations</title><def-item><term>AMR</term><def><p>antimicrobial resistance</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ARGs</term><def><p>antimicrobial resistance genes</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>EPEC</term><def><p>enteropathogenic <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic></p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MDR</term><def><p>multidrug-resistant</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MGE</term><def><p>mobile genetic elements</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MIC</term><def><p>minimum inhibitory concentration</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ML</term><def><p>maximum likelihood</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MLST</term><def><p>multilocus sequencing typing</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NMDS</term><def><p>non-metric multidimensional scaling</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PCA</term><def><p>principal component analysis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SCs</term><def><p>sequence clusters</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>STs</term><def><p>sequence types</p></def></def-item></def-list></notes><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Danko</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bezdan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Afshin</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ahsanuddin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bhattacharya</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>A global metagenomic map of urban microbiomes and antimicrobial resistance</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2021</year><volume>184</volume><fpage>3376</fpage><lpage>3393</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2021.05.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34043940</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Allel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Furuya-Kanamori</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Global antimicrobial-resistance drivers: an ecological country-level study at the human-animal interface</article-title><source>Lancet Planet Health</source><year>2023</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>e291</fpage><lpage>e303</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2542-5196(23)00026-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37019570</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Pet cats may shape the antibiotic resistome of their owner&#x02019;s gut and living environment</article-title><source>Microbiome</source><year>2023</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>235</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40168-023-01679-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37872584</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>The co-occurrence of antibiotic resistance genes between dogs and their owners in families</article-title><source>
<italic toggle="yes">Imeta</italic>
</source><year>2022</year><volume>1</volume><elocation-id>e21</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/imt2.21</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38868570</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Halsby</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hewitt</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Healthy animals, healthy people: zoonosis risk from animal contact in pet shops, a systematic review of the literature</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>e89309</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0089309</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24586679</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hazen</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Michalski</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tennant</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rasko</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Genomic diversity of non-diarrheagenic fecal <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> from children in sub-Saharan Africa and South Asia and their relatedness to diarrheagenic <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic></article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2023</year><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>1400</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-023-36337-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36918537</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tenaillon</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Skurnik</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Picard</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Denamur</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The population genetics of commensal <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source><year>2010</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>217</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro2298</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20157339</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brumwell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sutton</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lantos</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ruffin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Escherichia coli ST131 associated with increased mortality in bloodstream infections from urinary tract source</article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>2023</year><volume>61</volume><elocation-id>e0019923</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/jcm.00199-23</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37338371</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ewers</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Grobbel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stamm</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kopp</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Diehl</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Emergence of human pandemic O25:H4-ST131 CTX-M-15 extended-spectrum-beta-lactamase-producing <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> among companion animals</article-title><source>J Antimicrob Chemother</source><year>2010</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>651</fpage><lpage>660</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jac/dkq004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20118165</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Distinct increase in antimicrobial resistance genes among <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> during 50 years of antimicrobial use in livestock production in China</article-title><source>Nat Food</source><year>2022</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>205</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s43016-022-00470-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37117646</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Poirel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Madec</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lupo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schink</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kieffer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial resistance in <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>Microbiol Spectr</source><year>2018</year><volume>6</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/microbiolspec.ARBA-0026-2017</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y-Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>L-X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Emergence of plasmid-mediated colistin resistance mechanism MCR-1 in animals and human beings in China: a microbiological and molecular biological study</article-title><source>Lancet Infect Dis</source><year>2016</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>168</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(15)00424-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26603172</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>C-Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Plasmid-encoded tet(X) genes that confer high-level tigecycline resistance in <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>Nat Microbiol</source><year>2019</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1457</fpage><lpage>1464</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41564-019-0496-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31235960</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="preprint"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Arredondo-Alonso</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>P&#x000f6;ntinen</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gama</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gladstone</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Harms</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Plasmid-driven strategies for clone success in <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>Microbiology</source><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2023.10.14.562336</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Arutyunov</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Frost</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>F conjugation: back to the beginning</article-title><source>Plasmid</source><year>2013</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>18</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plasmid.2013.03.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23632276</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Partridge</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kwong</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Firth</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>SO</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Mobile genetic elements associated with antimicrobial resistance</article-title><source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source><year>2018</year><volume>31</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/CMR.00088-17</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Min</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>A retrospective study on <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> bacteremia in immunocompromised patients: microbiological features, clinical characteristics, and risk factors for shock and death</article-title><source>J Clin Lab Anal</source><year>2020</year><volume>34</volume><elocation-id>e23319</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jcla.23319</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32267010</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bankevich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nurk</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Antipov</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gurevich</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dvorkin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>SPAdes: a new genome assembly algorithm and its applications to single-cell sequencing</article-title><source>J Comput Biol</source><year>2012</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>455</fpage><lpage>477</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/cmb.2012.0021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22506599</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Beghain</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bridier-Nahmias</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Le Nagard</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Denamur</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Clermont</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>ClermonTyping: an easy-to-use and accurate <italic toggle="yes">in silico</italic> method for <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia</italic> genus strain phylotyping</article-title><source>Microb Genom</source><year>2018</year><volume>4</volume><elocation-id>e000192</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/mgen.0.000192</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29916797</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Francisco</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vaz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Monteiro</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Melo-Cristino</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ramirez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>PHYLOViZ: phylogenetic inference and data visualization for sequence based typing methods</article-title><source>BMC Bioinformatics</source><year>2012</year><volume>13</volume><elocation-id>87</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-13-87</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22568821</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Feldgarden</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brover</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Haft</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Prasad</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Slotta</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Validating the AMRFinder tool and resistance gene database by using antimicrobial resistance genotype-phenotype correlations in a collection of isolates</article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>2019</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>e00483</fpage><lpage>00419</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.00483-19</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31427293</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bastian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Heymann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jacomy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Gephi: an open source software for exploring and manipulating networks</article-title><source>ICWSM</source><year>2009</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>361</fpage><lpage>362</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1609/icwsm.v3i1.13937</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nash</surname><given-names>JHE</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>MOB-suite: software tools for clustering, reconstruction and typing of plasmids from draft assemblies</article-title><source>Microb Genom</source><year>2018</year><volume>4</volume><elocation-id>e000206</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/mgen.0.000206</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30052170</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>CLSI</collab>
</person-group><part-title>Performance standards for antimicrobial susceptibility testing: twenty-eighth informational supplement M100-S28</part-title><publisher-loc>Wayne, PA, USA</publisher-loc><year>2018</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>CLSI</collab>
</person-group><part-title>Performance standards for antimicrobial disk and dilution susceptibility tests for bacteria isolated from animals: second informational supplement VET01-S2</part-title><publisher-loc>Wayne, PA, USA</publisher-loc><year>2013</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Croucher</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Page</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Connor</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Delaney</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Keane</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Rapid phylogenetic analysis of large samples of recombinant bacterial whole genome sequences using Gubbins</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2015</year><volume>43</volume><elocation-id>e15</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gku1196</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25414349</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Page</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Delaney</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Seemann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">SNP-sites</italic>: rapid efficient extraction of SNPs from multi-FASTA alignments</article-title><source>Microb Genom</source><year>2016</year><volume>2</volume><elocation-id>e000056</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/mgen.0.000056</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28348851</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stamatakis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>RAxML-VI-HPC: maximum likelihood-based phylogenetic analyses with thousands of taxa and mixed models</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2006</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>2688</fpage><lpage>2690</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btl446</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16928733</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Letunic</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bork</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Interactive Tree Of Life (iTOL) v4: recent updates and new developments</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2019</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>W256</fpage><lpage>W259</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkz239</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30931475</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tonkin-Hill</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lees</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bentley</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Frost</surname><given-names>SDW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Corander</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>RhierBAPS: An R implementation of the population clustering algorithm hierBAPS</article-title><source>Wellcome Open Res</source><year>2018</year><volume>3</volume><elocation-id>93</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12688/wellcomeopenres.14694.1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30345380</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Seemann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Prokka: rapid prokaryotic genome annotation</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2014</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>2068</fpage><lpage>2069</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu153</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24642063</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Page</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cummins</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reuter</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Roary: rapid large-scale prokaryote pan genome analysis</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2015</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>3691</fpage><lpage>3693</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv421</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26198102</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Delgado-Blas</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ovejero</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>David</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Montero</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Calero-Caceres</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Population genomics and antimicrobial resistance dynamics of <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> in wastewater and river environments</article-title><source>Commun Biol</source><year>2021</year><volume>4</volume><elocation-id>457</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s42003-021-01949-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33846529</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wick</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Judd</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gorrie</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Holt</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Unicycler: resolving bacterial genome assemblies from short and long sequencing reads</article-title><source>PLoS Comput Biol</source><year>2017</year><volume>13</volume><elocation-id>e1005595</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005595</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28594827</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gilchrist</surname><given-names>CLM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chooi</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>clinker &#x00026; clustermap.js: automatic generation of gene cluster comparison figures</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2021</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>2473</fpage><lpage>2475</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btab007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33459763</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Alikhan</surname><given-names>NF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Petty</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ben Zakour</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Beatson</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>BLAST Ring Image Generator (BRIG): simple prokaryote genome comparisons</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2011</year><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>402</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-12-402</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21824423</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Genomic epidemiology of animal-derived tigecycline-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> across China reveals recent endemic plasmid-encoded tet(X4) gene</article-title><source>Commun Biol</source><year>2020</year><volume>3</volume><elocation-id>412</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s42003-020-01148-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32737421</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Global distribution and genomic characteristics of carbapenemase-producing <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> among humans, 2005-2023</article-title><source>Drug Resist Updat</source><year>2024</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>101031</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drup.2023.101031</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38071860</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>L-X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>C-Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X-P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Emerging high-level tigecycline resistance: novel tetracycline destructases spread via the mobile tet(X)</article-title><source>Bioessays</source><year>2020</year><volume>42</volume><elocation-id>e2000014</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bies.202000014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32567703</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cummins</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Djordjevic</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Plasmid lineages in <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> ST95: Implications for host range, antibiotic resistance, and zoonoses</article-title><source>mSystems</source><year>2022</year><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>e0121221</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/msystems.01212-21</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35076267</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Boll</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Overballe-Petersen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hasman</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Emergence of enteroaggregative <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> within the ST131 lineage as a cause of extraintestinal infections</article-title><source>mBio</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>e00353-20</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mBio.00353-20</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32430467</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Roy Chowdhury</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hastak</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>DeMaere</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wyrsch</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Phylogenomic analysis of a global collection of <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> ST38: evidence of interspecies and environmental transmission?</article-title><source>mSystems</source><year>2023</year><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>e0123622</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/msystems.01236-22</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37675998</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pomba</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rantala</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Greko</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baptiste</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Catry</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Public health risk of antimicrobial resistance transfer from companion animals</article-title><source>J Antimicrob Chemother</source><year>2017</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>957</fpage><lpage>968</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jac/dkw481</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27999066</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Geng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Genetic diversity and virulence gene profiles of <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> from diarrhoeal rabbits in Sichuan Province, China</article-title><source>World Rabbit Sci</source><year>2022</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>140</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4995/wrs.2022.15273</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ginn</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lowry</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>A systematic review of enteric pathogens and antibiotic resistance genes in outdoor urban aerosols</article-title><source>Environ Res</source><year>2022</year><volume>212</volume><fpage>113097</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2022.113097</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35339466</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>D-R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>C-Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Daily occupational exposure in swine farm alters human skin microbiota and antibiotic resistome</article-title><source>
<italic toggle="yes">Imeta</italic>
</source><year>2024</year><volume>3</volume><elocation-id>e158</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/imt2.158</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38868515</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>He</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jiao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>The origin and evolution of IncF33 plasmids based on large-scale data sets</article-title><source>mSystems</source><year>2023</year><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>e0050823</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/msystems.00508-23</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37750716</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Matlock</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chau</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>AbuOun</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stubberfield</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Genomic network analysis of environmental and livestock F-type plasmid populations</article-title><source>ISME J</source><year>2021</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>2322</fpage><lpage>2335</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41396-021-00926-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33649550</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Detection of plasmid-mediated tigecycline-resistant gene <italic toggle="yes">tet</italic>(X4) in <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> from pork, Sichuan and Shandong Provinces, China, February 2019</article-title><source>Euro Surveill</source><year>2019</year><volume>24</volume><elocation-id>1900340</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2807/1560-7917.ES.2019.24.25.1900340</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31241040</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Recombination of NDM-5-producing plasmids mediated by IS26 among <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>Int J Antimicrob Agents</source><year>2020</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>105815</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2019.09.019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31600553</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Identification and characterization of conjugative plasmids that encode ciprofloxacin resistance in <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic></article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>2018</year><volume>62</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.00575-18</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Evolution of ciprofloxacin resistance-encoding genetic elements in <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic></article-title><source>mSystems</source><year>2020</year><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>e01234-20</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mSystems.01234-20</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33361329</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>