<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int J Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Int J Public Health</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>International Journal of Public Health</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1661-8556</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1661-8564</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40012814</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11859580</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1607952</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/ijph.2025.1607952</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Public Health Archive</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Development of Multimorbidity Indexes Based on Common Mental Health Conditions</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="left-running-head">Kose et al.</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="right-running-head">Development of Mental Multimorbidity Indexes</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kose</surname><given-names>Junko</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2359826/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kesse-Guyot</surname><given-names>Emmanuelle</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Duquenne</surname><given-names>Pauline</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hercberg</surname><given-names>Serge</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Galan</surname><given-names>Pilar</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Touvier</surname><given-names>Mathilde</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Andreeva</surname><given-names>Valentina A.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#x02020;</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn002" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#x02021;</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2749047/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Fezeu</surname><given-names>L&#x000e9;opold K.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn002" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#x02021;</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
<institution>Sorbonne Paris Nord University</institution>, <institution>Institut national de la sant&#x000e9; et de la recherche m&#x000e9;dicale (INSERM)/Institut national de recherche pour l&#x02019;agriculture, l&#x02019;alimentation et l&#x02019;environnement (INRAE)/Conservatoire national des arts et m&#x000e9;tiers (CNAM)</institution>, <institution>Center for Research in Epidemiology and Statistics (CRESS)</institution>, <institution>Nutritional Epidemiology Research Team (EREN)</institution>, <addr-line>Bobigny</addr-line>, <country>France</country>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
<institution>Department of Public Health</institution>, <institution>Assistance publique &#x02013; H&#x000f4;pitaux de Paris (AP-HP) Paris Seine-Saint-Denis Hospital System</institution>, <addr-line>Bobigny</addr-line>, <country>France</country>
</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>
<bold>Edited by:</bold>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1002537/overview" ext-link-type="uri">Rana Charafeddine</ext-link>, Scientific Institute of Public Health (WIV-ISP), Belgium</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>
<bold>Reviewed by:</bold> Two reviewers who chose to remain anonymous</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Valentina A. Andreeva, <email>v.andreeva@eren.smbh.univ-paris13.fr</email>
</corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn1"><label>
<sup>&#x02020;</sup>
</label><p>ORCID: Valentina A. Andreeva, <ext-link xlink:href="http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9480-5210" ext-link-type="uri">orcid.org/0000-0001-9480-5210</ext-link>
</p></fn><fn fn-type="equal" id="fn002"><label>
<sup>&#x02021;</sup>
</label><p>These authors have contributed equally to this work</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>70</volume><elocation-id>1607952</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>29</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2025 Kose, Kesse-Guyot, Duquenne, Hercberg, Galan, Touvier, Andreeva and Fezeu.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Kose, Kesse-Guyot, Duquenne, Hercberg, Galan, Touvier, Andreeva and Fezeu</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Objectives</title><p>Numerous multimorbidity indexes exist, focused primarily or solely on somatic conditions. We developed mental multimorbidity indexes as epidemiological tools.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>Participants in the French NutriNet-Sant&#x000e9; cohort (73.5% women; mean age = 59.5 &#x000b1; 13.7&#x000a0;years; index development N = 20,000; index comparison N = 7,259) completed self-report questionnaires (2020&#x02013;2022) regarding depressive symptoms, anxiety, eating disorders, insomnia, alcohol use disorders, cognitive difficulties, and the WHO Disability Assessment Schedule 2.0 (WHODAS 2.0). Using established cutoffs, participants were split into 2 groups for each condition. Tweedie regression analyses were performed with the 6 mental health conditions as exposures and the WHODAS 2.0 score as the outcome. Performance (C-index) and calibration of the indexes were compared with a simple count.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>A general and a sex-specific mental multimorbidity indexes were developed; both were significantly associated with the disability score. The new indexes had slightly better predictive performance than simple counts of mental disorders.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>We developed mental multimorbidity indexes as epidemiological research tools. Future prospective studies could investigate their predictive potential regarding outcomes such as medication use, healthcare utilization, and quality of life.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>mental disorder comorbidity</kwd><kwd>mental health</kwd><kwd>multimorbidity index</kwd><kwd>epidemiological research tool</kwd><kwd>public health</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn001"><institution-wrap><institution>Minist&#x000e8;re des Solidarit&#x000e9;s et de la Sant&#x000e9;
</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100014630</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn002"><institution-wrap><institution>Institut National de Recherche pour l'Agriculture, l'Alimentation et l'Environnement
</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100022077</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn003"><institution-wrap><institution>Institut National de la Sant&#x000e9; et de la Recherche M&#x000e9;dicale
</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100001677</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn004"><institution-wrap><institution>Conservatoire National des Arts et M&#x000e9;tiers
</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100013943</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn005"><institution-wrap><institution>Universit&#x000e9; Paris 13
</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100009506</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn006"><institution-wrap><institution>Agence Nationale de la Recherche
</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100001665</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>The author(s) declare that financial support was received for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article. The NutriNet-Sant&#x000e9; study is supported by the French Ministry of Health and Prevention, the National Agency for Public Health (Sant&#x000e9; Publique France), the National Institute for Health and Medical Research (INSERM), the National Research Institute for Agriculture, Food and Environment (INRAE), the National Conservatory of Arts and Crafts (CNAM), the Center for Epidemiological Research and Statistics (CRESS) and Sorbonne Paris Nord University. JK was funded by a doctoral fellowship provided by the French Ministry of Education via Sorbonne Paris Nord University. PD was funded by the French National Research Agency (grant # ANR-21-CE36-0003; PI: VA). The funders had no role in the design of the study; in the collection, analysis, or interpretation of data; in the writing of the manuscript, or in the decision to publish the results.</funding-statement></funding-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>From a public health perspective, mental health receives less attention than physical health, despite marked reductions in quality of life (QOL) and life expectancy among individuals with mental illness [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. The COVID-19 pandemic further worsened the burden of mental disorders [<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>], which moreover have a high potential for multimorbidity [<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] (i.e., coexistence of &#x02265;2 distinct chronic conditions in the same individual). The World Health Organization (WHO) Mental Health Surveys reported a median hazard ratio of 12.1 for onset of a second mental health disorder following an initial diagnosis [<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. The combined morbidity burden of two mental disorders appears to be greater than the sum of the burden estimates for each disorder; multimorbidity is generally associated with increased symptom severity and with a poorer prognosis [<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. The representative U.S. National Comorbidity Survey was among the first to report that high severity occurred in 9.6%, 25.5%, and 49.9% of those with 1, 2, and &#x02265;3 mental disorders, respectively [<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. A latent psychopathological factor, termed the p-factor, has been suggested to help explain mental multimorbidity, given evidence for activation of the same brain regions (e.g., amygdala, hippocampus) in people suffering from different mental illnesses, common genetic expressions, and pathogenesis [<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. In addition, shared socio-demographic and lifestyle risk factors, such as low socio-economic status, unemployment, living in an urban area, low social support, smoking, and unhealthy eating habits, are well documented [<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Thus, there is a compelling need to advance mental multimorbidity research to develop targeted public health interventions.</p><p>Multimorbidity assessment is typically based on a disease count or, less frequently, on weighted indexes [<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] which account for the number and impact of each condition, providing a better quantification of multimorbidity burden than simple counts [<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Existing indexes mainly reflect physical conditions and are often age- and sex-standardized [<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. While advancing age is one of the most important risk factors for physical morbidity and multimorbidity [<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], that does not seem to be the case with mental illness and multimorbidity [<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. In a systematic review of multimorbidity including 566 studies, &#x0003c;50% included a mental disorder, which was usually major depression and/or dementia [<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. That review identified only 6 studies exclusively focused on mental illness (e.g., major depressive disorder, dysthymia, bipolar disorder, hypomania, panic disorder, various phobias, anxiety disorders, obsessive-compulsive disorder, eating disorders, personality disorders, conduct disorders, attention-deficit hyperactivity disorder, substance abuse/dependence, neurasthenia, cognitive impairment); the inclusion of mental health conditions depended mainly on sample characteristics (e.g., prevalent conditions in outpatients, elderly) and data availability [<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. All of these studies relied on mental disorder counts. One study included in that review investigated physical and mental health conditions (depression, anxiety, alcohol abuse, post-traumatic stress disorder, bipolar disorder, schizophrenia) separately and developed a simple count-based Mental Comorbidity Index applicable to war veterans [<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Indexes measuring somatic and emotional symptoms as adjuncts to clinical diagnosis [<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] or as screening tools for dementia [<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], have long existed. To our knowledge, no mental multimorbidity index considering common mental health conditions in the general population has been developed.</p><p>In turn, commonly used response variables for multimorbidity index development include mortality, primary care consultations, hospitalizations, healthcare expenditures and QOL [<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. No research has addressed the impact of mental multimorbidity on overall disability burden. Our objective was to develop a mental multimorbidity index, assessed against the WHO Disability Assessment Schedule 2.0 (WHODAS 2.0) [<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] using data from a French cohort implemented in the general population (described below).</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="s2-1"><title>The NutriNet-Sant&#x000e9; Cohort</title><p>NutriNet-Sant&#x000e9; is an ongoing general population prospective cohort initiated in France in 2009 (<ext-link xlink:href="https://etude-nutrinet-sante.fr/" ext-link-type="uri">https://etude-nutrinet-sante.fr/</ext-link>). Its design and specific aims are detailed elsewhere [<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. In short, recurrent multimedia calls target adults who can follow an online research protocol in French. NutriNet-Sant&#x000e9; was approved by the Institutional Review Board of the French Institute for Health and Medical Research and by the National Commission on Informatics and Liberty. Eligible volunteers provide informed consent prior to enrollment.</p><p>At inclusion and yearly thereafter, participants complete questionnaires regarding socio-demographics and lifestyle, anthropometrics, physical activity and sedentary behavior, dietary intake (every 6&#x000a0;months), and health status. Additional nutrition- or health-related questionnaires are sent on a monthly basis.</p></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>Data Collection</title><sec id="s2-2-1"><title>Exposure Variables (Mental Health Status)</title><p>Mental health conditions meeting the following criteria that reflect public health relevance were identified: relatively high prevalence in the general population, potential for prevention (especially via dietary and lifestyle interventions), treatment or delay of progression, and relatively high risk of premature all-cause mortality. We thus selected depressive disorders, anxiety disorders, chronic insomnia, eating disorders, alcohol use disorders (AUD), and subjective cognitive difficulties.</p><sec id="s2-2-1-1"><title>Depressive Symptoms</title><p>Depressive symptoms were assessed in 2021 with the 20-item Center for Epidemiologic Studies Depression Scale (CES-D) [<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. The CES-D evaluates depressive symptoms over the previous week. Each item is scored on a 4-point Likert scale ranging from 0 to 3 points [<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. The total score ranges from 0 to 60 points; a score &#x02265;16 identified presence of depressive symptoms. This was the most common cutoff when screening for depression in the general population in various countries [<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s2-2-1-2"><title>Trait Anxiety</title><p>In 2020, we administered the trait anxiety subscale of the State-Trait Anxiety Inventory form Y (STAI-T) evaluating general anxiety proneness [<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. The STAI-T consists of 20 items scored on a 4-point Likert scale ranging from 1 to 4 points. The total score ranges from 20 to 80 points [<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Trait anxiety measured by the STAI-T was reported to be correlated with generalized anxiety disorder [<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Following prior research, and given the lack of an established cutoff, we used a score &#x0003e;40 for high trait anxiety [<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s2-2-1-3"><title>Chronic Insomnia</title><p>Chronic insomnia was assessed using the International Classification of Sleep Disorders &#x02013; 3rd Edition (ICSD-3) [<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] and the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual &#x02013; 5th Edition (DSM-5) [<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>] criteria. These items were integrated in the same battery as the STAI-T. Participants experiencing &#x02265;1 sleep problem (difficulties falling asleep, frequent nighttime wakening, waking up too early, unsatisfactory sleep) &#x02265;3 nights/week over the past &#x02265;3&#x000a0;months, and having &#x02265;1 negative repercussion of such problems in daily life were considered as having chronic insomnia.</p></sec><sec id="s2-2-1-4"><title>Eating Disorders</title><p>Eating disorders were screened with the 5-item Sick-Control-One-Fat-Food (SCOFF) questionnaire [<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] which was integrated in the same battery as the STAI-T. Each item is a Yes/No question; &#x02265;2 positive responses indicate a strong likelihood of having an eating disorder (any type) [<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s2-2-1-5"><title>Alcohol Use Disorders (AUD)</title><p>During 2021-2022, we administered the 10-item Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test (AUDIT) which is designed to detect harmful alcohol consumption and alcohol dependence [<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. It contains 3 items measuring frequency, amount of alcohol consumed, and frequency of heavy drinking, and 5 items measuring drinking behavior over the past year. These 8 items are scored on a 5-point Likert scale ranging from 0 to 4 points. The AUDIT also contains 2 items related to alcohol-related problems, scored as 0, 2 or 4 points respectively. The total AUDIT score ranges from 0 to 40 points; a cutoff &#x02265;8 identifies presence of hazardous and harmful alcohol use [<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s2-2-1-6"><title>Subjective Cognitive Difficulties</title><p>The Cognitive Difficulties Scale (CDS) was integrated in the same battery as the CES-D [<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. It contains 37 items assessing attention, concentration, praxis, prospective memory, speech problems, memory for personal names, and temporal orientation. Each item is scored on a 5-point Likert scale ranging from 0 to 4 points; the total score ranges from 0 to 148 points. A cutoff score &#x02265;40 (corresponding to the 3rd quartile of the score distribution in our sample) was used to identify participants with pronounced subjective cognitive difficulties [<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec id="s2-2-2"><title>Outcome Variable (Disability)</title><p>Disability was assessed during 2021-2022 with the WHODAS 2.0 [<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] which is regarded as suitable for assessing health status and disability in diverse populations [<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. It is based on the conceptual framework of the International Classification of Functioning, Disability, and Health and consists of 36 items distributed across 6 domains: understanding and communication; getting around; self-care; getting along with people; life activities; and participation in society. Each item has unique scoring; the total score ranges from 0 (no disability) to 100 (complete disability) [<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. WHODAS 2.0 was modelled as a continuous variable.</p><p>
<xref rid="s10" ref-type="sec">Supplementary Figure S1</xref> details the mental health assessments.</p></sec><sec id="s2-2-3"><title>Socio-Demographic, Health Status, and Lifestyle Covariates</title><p>Using a validated self-reported socio-demographic questionnaire, we assessed age, sex, education (&#x0003c; high school; high school diploma or equivalent; college/undergraduate degree; graduate degree), employment (without professional activity including homemaker, disabled, unemployed, student; manual/blue-collar worker; office work/administrative staff; professional/executive staff; retired), residential area (rural; semi-urban, urban), marital status (living alone; married/cohabiting), presence of children aged &#x0003c;18&#x000a0;years in the household (yes; no) [<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. A validated self-reported anthropometric questionnaire [<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] allowed us to calculate Body Mass Index (BMI; kg/m<sup>2</sup>) and to categorize participants as: underweight: &#x0003c;18.5; normal weight: 18.5&#x02013;24.9; overweight: 25.0&#x02013;29.9; with obesity: &#x02265;30.0&#x000a0;kg/m<sup>2</sup>. The International Physical Activity Questionnaire (IPAQ) - Short Form assessed sedentariness (minutes/d spent sitting) and physical activity (low, moderate, high) using established criteria [<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. As all of these questionnaires are administered at baseline and annually thereafter, data recorded closest to the WHODAS 2.0 administration were used for this study. Data on lifetime prevalence (yes; no) of major chronic diseases (cancer except basal cell carcinoma; major cardiovascular diseases; diabetes type 1 or type 2) were collected using an annual health status questionnaire. Information on current household financial difficulties (yes; no), self-perceived health status (very good/good; acceptable; poor/very poor), smoking (never, former or current smoker), and perceived lack of affection during childhood (yes; no) was collected at the same time as AUDIT.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title>Statistical Analyses</title><p>Given the large number of retired participants (49.5%) to whom four WHODAS 2.0 items regarding work and school activities were not relevant, we excluded these items from the total score, as in prior studies [<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. We calculated scores for the remaining 32 items based on the WHODAS 2.0 algorithm: 100 &#x000d7; (total score for each domain)/92 [<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Participants with invalid or incomplete mental health or disability data were excluded. To avoid potential acquiescence bias, we also excluded n = 56 for CES-D and n = 39 for STAI-T for marking the same response number for all questions even for inversely-scored items. A total of 27,529 participants were available for the analyses. Using SAS Proc Surveyselect and guided by prior multimorbidity research [<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], participants were randomly assigned in a 3 to 1 ratio into one of two groups: a development subsample N = 20,000 to develop the indexes and a comparison subsample N = 7,529 to test and compare the performance of the developed indexes (<xref rid="s10" ref-type="sec">Supplementary Figure S1</xref>). Participant characteristics are presented as number (%) from chi<sup>2</sup> tests (categorical variables) and median (1st and 3rd quartile) from Wilcoxon&#x02019;s rank sum tests (continuous variables).</p><p>For the index development, we first checked the outcome distribution, expected to be right-skewed [<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Next, we applied Tobit regression and Tweedie regression (logarithm link function and variance power function = 1.4). Both regression models included the 6 mental health conditions as independent variables and the WHODAS 2.0 score as the dependent variable, with adjustment for age and sex. The former is a regression model appropriate for a dependent variable having either left- or right-censoring [<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. The latter is a regression model appropriate for a dependent variable with positive values and exact zeros, and has been previously used to analyze the WHODAS 2.0 score as an outcome [<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. We compared the performance of the two models given the characteristics of the WHODAS 2.0 score distribution (i.e., dependent variable with positive values and exact zeros, right-censoring), to select the one with a better model fit using Akaike&#x02019;s Information Criterion (AIC; smaller values reflect a better fit) [<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Next, interactions of each mental health condition with sex and age were tested with a significance level <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.10, allowing to balance the reduced statistical power of interaction tests [<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>] and the risk of committing type I error. Afterwards, two weighting schemes used in the multimorbidity literature were compared by fitting Tweedie regressions with the developed index as the exposure and WHODAS 2.0 total score as the outcome. The first weighting scheme was the beta coefficient (&#x003b2;) multiplied by 10 for each mental health condition [<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>] and the second was the &#x003b2; divided by the &#x003b2; for age modelled in 5-year increments [<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. Model fit was compared using AIC and the coefficient of determination (R<sup>2</sup>) [<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Finally, mental multimorbidity indexes calculated with two different rounding systems for the weights (integer and one decimal place) were compared using AIC and R<sup>2</sup>. All model fit comparisons were conducted in the development subsample. The score of the developed index represents the sum of the weights attributed to each mental health condition for each individual.</p><p>Next, Tweedie regression models were fitted in the comparison subsample to test whether the developed indexes were associated with disability. Model 1 was unadjusted; Model 2 was adjusted for age and sex; Model 3 was additionally adjusted for confounders selected using a directed acyclic graph (BMI, education, employment, residential area, children in household, lack of affection during childhood, current household financial situation, self-perceived health status, smoking, physical activity, sedentariness, and lifetime prevalence of major chronic disease). Missing covariate values were imputed using the Multiple Imputation by Chained Equations method (20 imputed data sets) [<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Model fit parameters and predictive performance of the indexes were compared against a simple count of mental health conditions using AIC, R<sup>2</sup>, and calibration plots, respectively [<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Finally, we assessed discrimination of the indexes (ability to discriminate among individuals with and without disability) by dichotomizing the WHODAS 2.0 score (disability defined as &#x02265;90th percentile in the full sample [<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>, <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>] = 23.9 points) and using Harrell&#x02019;s concordance index (C-index) corresponding to the area under the receiver operating curve for binary outcomes [<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>].</p><p>All tests were two-sided and <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05 reflected statistical significance. The variance power function of the Tweedie regression was determined using the Tweedie package of R version 2.3.5. SAS<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> version 9.4 (SAS Institute, Inc., Cary NC, United States) was used for all other statistical analyses.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec id="s3-1"><title>Sample Description</title><p>NutriNet-Sant&#x000e9; participants included in this study were more likely to be male, older, married or cohabiting, to have lower education, higher physical activity, depressive symptoms, anxiety, subjective cognitive difficulties, and lifetime prevalence of chronic conditions compared to their excluded counterparts. Likewise, they were less likely to be retired, to live in urban areas, to have financial difficulties, children in the household, eating disorders, chronic insomnia, or AUD than those excluded from the analyses (data not tabulated; all <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01).</p><p>Descriptive characteristics and mental health status in the full sample and in each subsample are presented in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Tables 1</xref>, <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, respectively. Frequency distributions of mental condition pairs are presented in <xref rid="s10" ref-type="sec">Supplementary Table S1</xref>. In the full sample (N = 27,259), mean age was 59.5 &#x000b1; 13.7&#x000a0;years, 73.5% of the participants were women, and the median WHODAS 2.0 score was 5.4 (Interquartile Range 1.1&#x02013;13.0). Overall, 58.1% of the participants had &#x02265;1 mental health condition, with the most prevalent pair being anxiety and depressive symptoms; 15.5% and 17.6% of the participants had 2 and &#x02265;3 mental health conditions, respectively. No significant differences regarding participant profiles were observed between the development and comparison subsamples.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>TABLE 1</label><caption><p>Description of participant characteristics (N = 27,259; NutriNet-Sant&#x000e9; Study, 2020&#x02013;2022; France).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead valign="top"><tr><th rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1"/><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Full sample</th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Index development subsample</th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Index comparison subsample</th><th rowspan="2" align="center" colspan="1">
<italic>p</italic>-value<xref rid="Tfn1" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</th></tr><tr><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">N = 27,259</th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">n = 20,000</th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">n = 7,259</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td colspan="8" align="left" rowspan="1">Sex</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Women</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20,039</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(73.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14,669</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(73.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,370</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(74.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Men</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7,220</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(26.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5331</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(26.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,889</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(26.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, years, median (Q1; Q3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(50.0; 70.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(50.0; 70.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(50.0; 70.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68</td></tr><tr><td colspan="8" align="left" rowspan="1">Age category</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;18&#x02013;39&#x000a0;years</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,875</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(10.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,112</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(10.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">763</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(10.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;40&#x02013;59&#x000a0;years</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9,189</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(33.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,729</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(33.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,460</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(33.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02265;60&#x000a0;years</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15,195</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(55.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,159</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(55.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,036</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(55.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="8" align="left" rowspan="1">Educational level<xref rid="Tfn2" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>b</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Less than high school</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,641</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(13.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,656</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(13.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">985</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(13.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;High school diploma or equivalent</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,318</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(15.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,138</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(15.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,180</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(16.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;College, undergraduate degree</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8,526</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(31.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,303</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(31.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,223</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(30.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Graduate degree</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,616</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(39.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7,783</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(39.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,833</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(39.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="8" align="left" rowspan="1">Employment status<xref rid="Tfn3" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>c</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Without professional activity<xref rid="Tfn4" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>d</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,716</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(6.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,213</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(6.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">503</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(7.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Manual/blue collar</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,656</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(13.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,668</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(13.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">988</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(13.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Office work/administrative staff</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,432</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(8.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,788</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(9.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">644</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(8.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Professional/executive staff</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,933</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(21.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,411</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(22.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,522</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(21.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Retired</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13,466</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(49.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9,882</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(49.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,584</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(49.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="8" align="left" rowspan="1">Residential area<xref rid="Tfn5" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>e</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Rural</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,039</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(22.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,421</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(22.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,618</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(22.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Urban or semi-urban</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20,802</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(77.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15,273</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(77.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,529</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(77.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="8" align="left" rowspan="1">Self-perceived financial difficulties</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;No</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23,195</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(85.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17,064</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(85.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,131</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(84.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,064</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(14.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,936</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(14.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,128</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(15.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="8" align="left" rowspan="1">Self-perceived health status</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Poor</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,343</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(4.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">960</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(4.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">383</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(5.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Acceptable</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7,495</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(27.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,490</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(27.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2005</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(27.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Good or very good</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18,421</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(67.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13,550</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(67.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,871</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(67.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="8" align="left" rowspan="1">Marital status<xref rid="Tfn6" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>f</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Living alone (single, divorced, widowed)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7,542</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(27.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,539</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(27.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,003</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(27.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Married/cohabiting</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19,666</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(72.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14,424</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(72.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,242</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(72.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="8" align="left" rowspan="1">Children aged &#x0003c;18&#x000a0;years in household<xref rid="Tfn7" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>g</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;No</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22,079</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(81.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16,222</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(81.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,857</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(80.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,128</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(18.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,739</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(18.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,389</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(19.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="8" align="left" rowspan="1">Self-perceived lack of affection in childhood</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;No</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23,811</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(87.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17,478</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(87.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,333</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(87.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,448</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(12.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,522</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(12.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">926</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(12.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="8" align="left" rowspan="1">Physical activity level<xref rid="Tfn8" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>h</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Low</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,878</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(17.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,572</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(17.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,306</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(18.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Moderate</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,539</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(38.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7,669</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(38.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,870</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(39.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;High</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,836</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(43.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8,755</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(43.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,081</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(42.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sedentariness (minutes spent sitting/d), median (Q1; Q3)<xref rid="Tfn9" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>i</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">360.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(240.0; 480.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">360.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(240.0; 480.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">360.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(240.0; 480.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body Mass Index (BMI; kg/m<sup>2</sup>), median (Q1; Q3)<xref rid="Tfn10" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>j</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(21.2; 26.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(21.2; 26.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(21.2; 26.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td></tr><tr><td colspan="8" align="left" rowspan="1">BMI category<xref rid="Tfn10" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>j</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Underweight (&#x0003c;18.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,319</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(4.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">960</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(4.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">359</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(5.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Normal weight (18.5&#x02013;24.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16,011</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(58.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,830</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(59.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,181</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(57.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Overweight (25.0&#x02013;29.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,994</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(25.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,095</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(25.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,899</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(26.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Obesity (&#x02265;30.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,881</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(10.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,075</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(10.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">806</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(11.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="8" align="left" rowspan="1">Smoking status</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Never smoker</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17,756</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(65.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13,018</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(65.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,738</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(65.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Former smoker</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7,490</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(27.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,502</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(27.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,988</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(27.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Current smoker</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,013</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(7.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,480</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(7.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">533</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(7.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alcohol use, g ethanol/d, median (Q1; Q3)<xref rid="Tfn11" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>k</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0; 8.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0; 8.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0; 8.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td></tr><tr><td colspan="8" align="left" rowspan="1">Lifetime prevalence of major chronic diseases<xref rid="Tfn12" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>l</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;No</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22,150</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(81.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16,256</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(81.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,894</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(81.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,109</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(18.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,744</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(18.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,365</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(18.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Disability score (WHODAS 2.0), median (Q1; Q3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.1; 13.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.1; 13.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.1; 13.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Values refer to number (%) except when noted otherwise.</p></fn><fn><p>Values are rounded off to one decimal place except for <italic>p</italic>-values.</p></fn><fn id="Tfn1"><label>
<sup>a</sup>
</label><p>Values are obtained from Chi2 or Wilcoxon&#x02019;s rank sum tests, as appropriate.</p></fn><fn id="Tfn2"><label>
<sup>b</sup>
</label><p>Educational level contains 158 missing values.</p></fn><fn id="Tfn3"><label>
<sup>c</sup>
</label><p>Employment status contains 56 missing values.</p></fn><fn id="Tfn4"><label>
<sup>d</sup>
</label><p>Without professional activity includes homemakers, disabled, unemployed, and students.</p></fn><fn id="Tfn5"><label>
<sup>e</sup>
</label><p>Residential area contains 418 missing values.</p></fn><fn id="Tfn6"><label>
<sup>f</sup>
</label><p>Marital status contains 51 missing values.</p></fn><fn id="Tfn7"><label>
<sup>g</sup>
</label><p>Children in household contains 52 missing values.</p></fn><fn id="Tfn8"><label>
<sup>h</sup>
</label><p>Physical activity level was assessed with the International Physical Activity Questionnaire and contains 6 missing values.</p></fn><fn id="Tfn9"><label>
<sup>i</sup>
</label><p>Sedentariness contains 7 missing values.</p></fn><fn id="Tfn10"><label>
<sup>j</sup>
</label><p>BMI, contains 54 missing values.</p></fn><fn id="Tfn11"><label>
<sup>k</sup>
</label><p>Alcohol use contains 54 missing values.</p></fn><fn id="Tfn12"><label>
<sup>l</sup>
</label><p>Major chronic diseases: cancer (except basal cell carcinoma), major cardiovascular diseases, and diabetes mellitus type 1 or type 2.</p></fn><fn><p>Missing covariate values were imputed prior to the index validation analysis.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>TABLE 2</label><caption><p>Mental health status of participants (N = 27,259; NutriNet-Sant&#x000e9; Study, 2020&#x02013;2022; France).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead valign="top"><tr><th rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1"/><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Full sample</th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Index development subsample</th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Index comparison subsample</th><th rowspan="2" align="center" colspan="1">
<italic>p</italic>-value<xref rid="Tfn13" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</th></tr><tr><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">N = 27,259</th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">n = 20,000</th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">n = 7,259</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td colspan="8" align="left" rowspan="1">Depressive symptoms<xref rid="Tfn14" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>b</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;No</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21,278</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(78.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15,590</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(78.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,688</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(78.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,981</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(21.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,410</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(22.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,571</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(21.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="8" align="left" rowspan="1">Anxiety<xref rid="Tfn15" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>c</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Low</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18,433</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(67.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13,524</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(67.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,909</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(67.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;High</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8,826</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(32.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,476</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(32.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,350</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(32.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="8" align="left" rowspan="1">Eating disorders (any type)<xref rid="Tfn16" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>d</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;No</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24,761</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(90.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18,169</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(90.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,592</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(90.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,498</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(9.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,831</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(9.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">667</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(9.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="8" align="left" rowspan="1">Chronic insomnia<xref rid="Tfn17" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>e</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;No</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21,416</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(78.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15,714</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(78.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,702</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(78.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,843</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(21.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,286</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(21.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,557</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(21.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="8" align="left" rowspan="1">Alcohol use disorders<xref rid="Tfn18" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>f</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;No</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25,420</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(93.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18,665</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(93.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,755</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(93.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,839</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(6.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,335</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(6.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">504</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(6.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="8" align="left" rowspan="1">Subjective cognitive difficulties<xref rid="Tfn19" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>g</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;No</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20,178</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(74.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14,798</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(74.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,380</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(74.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7,081</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(26.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,202</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(26.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,879</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(25.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="8" align="left" rowspan="1">Number of mental health conditions</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,418</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(41.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8,364</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(41.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,054</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(42.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,842</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(25.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,044</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(25.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,798</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(24.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,229</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(15.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,090</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(15.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,139</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(15.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,817</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(10.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,063</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(10.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">754</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(10.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,489</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(5.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,099</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(5.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">390</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(5.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">423</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">309</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">114</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Values refer to number (%) except when noted otherwise.</p></fn><fn><p>Values are rounded off to one decimal place except for <italic>p</italic>-values (two decimal places).</p></fn><fn id="Tfn13"><label>
<sup>a</sup>
</label><p>Values are obtained from Chi2 or Wilcoxon&#x02019;s rank sum tests, as appropriate.</p></fn><fn id="Tfn14"><label>
<sup>b</sup>
</label><p>Depressive symptoms were assessed with the CES-D scale (cut-off score = 16).</p></fn><fn id="Tfn15"><label>
<sup>c</sup>
</label><p>Anxiety was assessed with STAI-T form Y (cut-off score = 40).</p></fn><fn id="Tfn16"><label>
<sup>d</sup>
</label><p>Eating disorders were assessed with SCOFF (&#x02265;2 positive responses = likely eating disorder).</p></fn><fn id="Tfn17"><label>
<sup>e</sup>
</label><p>Chronic insomnia was assessed with a questionnaire based on ICSD-3 and DSM-5 criteria.</p></fn><fn id="Tfn18"><label>
<sup>f</sup>
</label><p>Alcohol use disorders were assessed with the AUDIT scale (cut-off score = 8).</p></fn><fn id="Tfn19"><label>
<sup>g</sup>
</label><p>Subjective cognitive difficulties were assessed with the CDS scale (cut-off score = 40 corresponding to 3rd quartile).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3-2"><title>Index Development</title><p>As the Tweedie regression model presented a better fit to the observed data than did the Tobit regression model (AIC = 124,344 for Tweedie; 130,859 for Tobit), the former was retained for subsequent analyses. A significant interaction with sex was observed for AUD (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) and cognitive difficulties (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.07). Thus, we fit separate Tweedie models to develop a general mental multimorbidity index and a sex-specific index.</p><p>All mental health conditions were associated with the disability score except for AUD in women (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). The indexes were calculated with two weighting schemes (&#x003b2;*10 and &#x003b2;/&#x003b2; of age for 5-year increments) and with two rounding systems (integer and one decimal place). Those with &#x003b2;*10 (AIC 124,560.9 for &#x003b2;*10 vs. 124,561.1 for &#x003b2;/&#x003b2; of age for 5-year increments) and one decimal place (AIC 124,560.5 for one decimal place vs. 124,574.6 for integer) seemed to provide the best fit especially for the sex-specific index. The final weights attributed to each mental health condition in each index are presented in <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>. Absolute values of the beta coefficients were generally higher in men than in women, except for depressive symptoms. In both sexes, the highest absolute weight was obtained for subjective cognitive difficulties (6.2 for men, 6.4 for women). The lowest absolute weights were observed for AUD in men (weight = 1.6) and for eating disorders in women (weight = 2.1). The value distribution of the general index (score range: 0&#x02013;20.5) and the sex-specific index (score range: 0&#x02013;22.4) is presented in <xref rid="s10" ref-type="sec">Supplementary Figure S2</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T3"><label>TABLE 3</label><caption><p>Regression (beta) coefficients and assigned weights for each mental health condition in the full sample and according to sex (index development subsample N = 20,000; NutriNet-Sant&#x000e9; Study, 2020&#x02013;2022; France).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead valign="top"><tr><th rowspan="3" align="left" colspan="1"/><th colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1">General index</th><th colspan="8" align="center" rowspan="1">Sex-specific index</th></tr><tr><th colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1">n = 20,000</th><th colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1">Men (n = 5,331)</th><th colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1">Women (n = 14,669)</th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x00392;<xref rid="Tfn20" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SE<xref rid="Tfn20" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>p</italic>-value<xref rid="Tfn20" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weight</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b2;<xref rid="Tfn20" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SE<xref rid="Tfn20" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>p</italic>-value<xref rid="Tfn20" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weight</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b2;<xref rid="Tfn20" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SE<xref rid="Tfn20" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>p</italic>-value<xref rid="Tfn20" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weight</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Depressive simptoms<xref rid="Tfn21" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>b</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.635</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.017</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.618</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.036</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.644</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.020</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anxiety<xref rid="Tfn22" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>c</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.267</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.017</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.312</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.035</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.256</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.019</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eating disorders<xref rid="Tfn23" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>d</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.224</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.022</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.305</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.051</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.205</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.024</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chorionic insomnia<xref rid="Tfn24" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>e</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.219</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.016</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.225</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.035</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.219</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.018</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alcohol use disorders<xref rid="Tfn25" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>f</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.085</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.026</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.002</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.157</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.039</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>0.051</italic>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.034</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>0.14</italic>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>0.0</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subjective cognitive difficulties<xref rid="Tfn26" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>g</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.611</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.015</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.606</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.028</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.597</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.020</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Values are rounded off to three decimal places except for <italic>p</italic>-values.</p></fn><fn id="Tfn20"><label>
<sup>a</sup>
</label><p>Values are obtained from Tweedie regression with WHODAS, 2.0 score as dependent variable (adjustment for age and sex for general index; adjustment for age for sex-specific index).</p></fn><fn id="Tfn21"><label>
<sup>b</sup>
</label><p>Depressive symptoms were assessed with the CES-D scale (cut-off score = 16).</p></fn><fn id="Tfn22"><label>
<sup>c</sup>
</label><p>Anxiety was assessed with STAI-T form Y (cut-off score = 40).</p></fn><fn id="Tfn23"><label>
<sup>d</sup>
</label><p>Eating disorders were assessed with SCOFF (&#x02265;2 positive responses = likely eating disorders).</p></fn><fn id="Tfn24"><label>
<sup>e</sup>
</label><p>Chronic insomnia was assessed with a questionnaire based on ICSD-3 and DSM-5 criteria.</p></fn><fn id="Tfn25"><label>
<sup>f</sup>
</label><p>Alcohol use disorders were assessed with the AUDIT scale (cut-off score = 8).</p></fn><fn id="Tfn26"><label>
<sup>g</sup>
</label><p>Subjective cognitive difficulties were assessed with the CDS scale (cut-off score = 40).</p></fn><fn><p>&#x003b2;, Beta coefficient; SE, Standard error.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3-3"><title>Index Comparison</title><p>The general and the sex-specific indexes were positively associated with disability in the crude, age- and sex-adjusted, and the fully-adjusted Tweedie regression models (<xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T4"><label>TABLE 4</label><caption><p>Associations between mental multimorbidity indexes and disability score (index comparison subsample N = 7,259; NutriNet-Sant&#x000e9; cohort, 2020&#x02013;2022; France).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead valign="top"><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b2;</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value<xref rid="Tfn27" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td rowspan="3" align="left" colspan="1">General mental morbidity index</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crude model</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.107</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.097&#x02013;0.104</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model adjusted for age and sex</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.102</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.098&#x02013;0.106</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Full model<xref rid="Tfn28" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>b</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.079</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.075&#x02013;0.082</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" align="left" colspan="1">Sex-specific mental morbidity index</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crude model</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.107</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.097&#x02013;0.104</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model adjusted for age and sex</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.102</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.098&#x02013;0.106</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Full model<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.079</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.075&#x02013;0.082</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Values are rounded off to three decimal places except for <italic>p</italic>-values.</p></fn><fn id="Tfn27"><label>
<sup>a</sup>
</label><p>Values are obtained from Tweedie regression models with WHODAS 2.0 score as dependent variable.</p></fn><fn id="Tfn28"><label>
<sup>b</sup>
</label><p>Full model adjusted for age, sex, body mass index, educational level, socio-professional category, area of residence, presence of children in household, lack of affection during childhood, current household financial situation, self-perceived current health status, smoking status, physical activity level, sedentariness, and lifetime prevalence of major chronic disease.</p></fn><fn><p>&#x003b2;, Beta coefficient; CI, Confidence interval.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Both indexes showed somewhat lower AIC and higher R<sup>2</sup> values than those obtained with a simple count of mental disorders (<xref rid="s10" ref-type="sec">Supplementary Table S2</xref>). Absolute values of the discrimination parameters (C-index) were also slightly higher than those of a simple count (<xref rid="T5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>). Calibration plots showed that the developed indexes had slightly better calibration than a simple count of mental disorders (<xref rid="s10" ref-type="sec">Supplementary Figure S3</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T5"><label>TABLE 5</label><caption><p>Discrimination of mental multimorbidity indexes and simple count of mental health conditions (index comparison subsample N = 7,259; NutriNet-Sant&#x000e9; Study, 2020&#x02013;2022; France).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead valign="top"><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C-index</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">General mental multimorbidity index</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.814</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.797&#x02013;0.831</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex-specific mental multimorbidity index</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.813</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.796&#x02013;0.830</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Simple count of mental health conditions</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.791</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.775&#x02013;0.809</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>To calculate the C-index the WHODAS 2.0 score was dichotomized using as threshold the 90th percentile in the full sample (disability: &#x02265;23.9 points).</p></fn><fn><p>CI, Confidence interval; C-index, Concordance index.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>We developed a general and a sex-specific mental multimorbidity indexes based on common mental health conditions as predictors of general disability. Upon replication and confirmation, these indexes could be used as epidemiological research tools. To our knowledge, these indexes are the first such tools exclusively based on prevalent mental health conditions in the general population. The included mental disorders met the following criteria: a relatively high prevalence in the general population, a potential for prevention (especially via dietary and lifestyle interventions), treatment or delay of progression, and a relatively high risk of premature all-cause mortality. In this study, 33% of participants had &#x02265;2 mental health conditions, indicating a high rate of mental multimorbidity. Generally, individuals with different mental health conditions exhibit activation of the same brain regions (e.g., amygdala, hippocampus), common genetic expressions, and shared socio-demographic and lifestyle risk factors [<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].</p><p>The large majority of existing multimorbidity indexes pertain to somatic conditions and are developed for elderly populations or outpatients [<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]; mental disorders and general population samples are rare [<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Also, existing mental multimorbidity measures are usually based on simple counts, not on weighted indexes [<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Only one mental multimorbidity index, including depression, anxiety, alcohol abuse, post-traumatic stress disorder, bipolar disorder, and schizophrenia, was identified [<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. That disease count-based index was validated against QOL, outpatient visits, and mortality in war veteran outpatients [<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. The mental disorders included in mental multimorbidity studies depend mainly on sample characteristics (high prevalence in the elderly, in war veterans) and data availability [<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Prior studies have included not only common and potentially preventable mental disorders, but also genetic, autoimmune and trauma-related disorders [<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Our indexes were developed in a sample recruited from the general population and using epidemiological tools, considering the number and relative weight (but not severity) of each condition; they could help identify adults at risk and inform prevention efforts. Existing multimorbidity indexes including physical and mental disorders were developed using outcomes such as risk of mortality, hospitalizations, primary care consultations, healthcare expenditures, and QOL [<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>, <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. Ours are the first multimorbidity indexes based on general disability.</p><p>We developed two mental multimorbidity indexes - a general and a sex-specific index - owing to significant interactions by sex for certain mental disorders. In our sample, AUD were not pertinent among women; in men AUD had a weight of 1.6; AUD prevalence in men and women was 11.2% and 5.1%, respectively. Overall, we observed sex-specific differences in the absolute weights and relative order of importance of the 6 mental disorders. Absolute weights were higher among men than women, except for depressive symptoms. Depressive symptoms and eating disorders had the highest and lowest weights, respectively, among women; subjective cognitive difficulties and AUD had the highest and lowest weights, respectively, among men. Partly owing to sex differences in socialization (e.g., help-seeking, coping, societal expectations), internalizing disorders are generally more common among women whereas externalizing disorders are generally more common among men [<xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>, <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. It is therefore possible that men&#x02019;s mental health status might have an increased impact on subjective disability (i.e., WHODAS 2.0 score) which is an external construct.</p><p>The multimorbidity literature dealing with index development has relied on expert decisions regarding weights or has derived weights from regression coefficients [<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. Consistent with prior methodological research, we used &#x003b2; coefficients derived from age- and sex-adjusted models as weights for each mental disorder [<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. No other statistical adjustments were made, to develop indexes that are context-independent and therefore more versatile and robust [<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. The indexes were significantly associated with the disability score in the validation subsample following adjustment for many covariates. Model fit parameters and psychometric performance were compared against those obtained from a simple count of mental disorders, which is commonly used in multimorbidity measurement [<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Model fit indicators of the indexes were somewhat better (lower AIC, higher R<sup>2</sup>) than those of the simple count. The C-index compared the discrimination potential of the indexes and that of a simple count; values &#x0003c;0.7 are considered as indicating poor discrimination whereas values &#x0003e;0.8 reflect excellent discrimination [<xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. Our results suggest that the indexes discriminate between individuals with and without disability somewhat better than does a simple count of mental disorders (C-index = 0.81 vs. 0.79). Calibration plots also indicated that the predictive performances of our indexes, especially the sex-specific index, were slightly better than that of a simple count. Moreover, unlike the count, the weighted indexes account for the respective burden associated with each disorder.</p><sec id="s4-1"><title>Limitations and Strengths</title><p>We obtained mental health data via self-report questionnaires commonly used in epidemiological research, which is consistent with the intended use of these indexes. Yet, despite the fact that the mental health assessment tools have been validated against diagnostic criteria [<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>], they do not reflect clinical diagnoses; this is a limitation of the study. In addition, CES-D, STAI-T and SCOFF do not distinguish among subtypes of depression, anxiety and eating disorders, respectively. For insomnia, we relied on DSM-5 and ICSD-3 criteria. Future confirmatory research could replicate the analysis using different tools for the same mental disorders assessed in representative adult samples. Overall, mental disorders tend to be under-diagnosed in the general population partly due to stigma and perceived discrimination [<xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. Mental health assessment in epidemiological studies can help identify individuals with symptoms even without a clinical diagnosis. Next, consistent with the objectives and with prior research, we used the 90th percentile as cutoff of the WHODAS 2.0 score [<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>, <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>, <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>] to identify participants with disability. Another limitation stems from the COVID-19 pandemic, which disrupted the way of life and had a deleterious impact of mental health [<xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>, <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>], and which coincided with the 2020&#x02013;2022 questionnaire administration. However, according to a French national survey, average alcohol and tobacco consumption were fairly stable even during the lockdowns [<xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. We can speculate that the context might have had a minimal impact on the measures. Finally, our sample was composed predominantly of women and individuals of higher socio-economic status than the respective proportions in the general population [<xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>, <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>], which might have led to an underestimation of the impact of mental disorders on disability. Thus, it will be necessary to replicate and confirm the findings using other study populations.</p><p>This study has several important strengths. First, we relied on a rich database with available information on a variety of socio-demographic, lifestyle and mental health characteristics. Next, to our knowledge, this is the first mental multimorbidity index development research based on common mental health conditions meeting specific criteria with relevance to public health, and thus applicable in an epidemiological context across age. Moreover, these are the first multimorbidity indexes based on disability, to which mental disorders have a substantial contribution [<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Disability was measured using WHODAS 2.0 which is commonly used in epidemiology [<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Assessment of mental disorders relied on validated instruments [<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] administered in a large and diverse sample of men and women. The prevalence of each mental disorder and that of mental multimorbidity in this study were consistent with those reported in the literature [<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. Further, the performance of two statistical approaches (i.e., Tobit and Tweedie regressions) was compared, allowing us to select the one with the better model-fitting performance (smaller AIC value) to develop the indexes. In addition, several weighting schemes used in the multimorbidity literature were tested to identify the one with the best performance [<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>, <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. The developed multimorbidity indexes had good discrimination and calibration, and were significantly associated with disability in fully-adjusted models. These indexes could help identify at-risk individuals without a full clinical examination, thus could provide cheaper and earlier screening.</p></sec><sec id="s4-2"><title>Conclusion</title><p>We developed a general and a sex-specific mental multimorbidity indexes that could help with needs assessment and prevention. These indexes could help identify at-risk individuals without a full clinical examination, thus could provide earlier and cost-efficient screening. Following validation, future research with representative samples could test their predictive potential regarding health status, medication use, primary care consultations, and QOL in longitudinal analyses.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors thank Prof. Damien L&#x000e9;ger, Prof. Pierre D&#x000e9;chelotte, Dr. Fran&#x000e7;oise Radat, and Dr. Maria Melchior for their respective contribution to the assessment of chronic insomnia, eating disorders, anxiety disorders, and alcohol use disorders in the NutriNet-Sant&#x000e9; cohort. The authors also thank C&#x000e9;dric Agaesse (dietary data manager), Alexandre De-Sa and Laure Legris (dietitians); Selim Aloui (IT manager), Thi Hong Van Duong, R&#x000e9;gis Gatibelza, and Aladi Timera (computer scientists); Julien Allegre, Nathalie Arnault, Laurent Bourhis, Nicolas Dechamp (biostatisticians), and Fabien Szabo de Edelenyi, Ph.D. (biostatistics team manager); Maria Gomes and Mirette Foham (NutriNet-Sant&#x000e9; participant support) and Paola Yvroud, M.D. (health event validator and operations coordinator) for their technical contribution to the cohort. Finally, the authors sincerely thank all the volunteers of the NutriNet-Sant&#x000e9; cohort.</p></ack><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s5"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>Researchers at public institutions can submit a project collaboration request that includes information about their institution and a brief description of the proposed project to: <email>collaboration@etude-nutrinet-sante.fr</email>. All requests are reviewed by the steering committee of the NutriNet-Sant&#x000e9; study. In case of approval, a signed data access agreement will be requested and additional authorizations from the competent administrative authorities may be needed regarding human participants&#x02019; data protection. In accordance with existing regulations, no personally identifiable data will be made available.</p></sec><sec sec-type="ethics-statement" id="s6"><title>Ethics Statement</title><p>The studies involving humans were approved by French Institute for Health and Medical Research (INSERM # 00000388FWA00005831), National Commission on Informatics and Liberty (CNIL # 908450 and # 909216). The studies were conducted in accordance with the local legislation and institutional requirements. The participants provided their written informed consent to participate in this study.</p></sec><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="s7"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>EK-G, SH, PG, and MT designed and implemented the NutriNet-Sant&#x000e9; cohort study; EK-G implemented the Center for Epidemiologic Studies Depression&#x00101; Scale (CES-D) and the Cognitive Difficulties Scale (CDS) and coordinated data collection; PG and VA implemented the State -Trait Anxiety Inventory (STAI) and the sleep health questionnaire and coordinated data collection; VA implemented the Sick-Control-One-Fat-Food (SCOFF) questionnaire and coordinated data collection; VA and JK implemented the Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test (AUDIT) and the World Health Organization Disability Assessment Schedule 2.0 (WHODAS 2.0) and coordinated data collection; VA conceptualized the study; VA and LF designed the analytic strategy and provided theoretical and empirical guidance; VA and JK performed the literature review; JK performed the statistical analyses and led the writing; all authors assisted with interpretation of the data, critically revised the manuscript for important intellectual content. All authors contributed to the article and approved the submitted version.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s9"><title>Conflict of Interest</title><p>The authors declare that they do not have any conflicts of interest.</p></sec><sec id="s10"><title>Supplementary Material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.ssph-journal.org/articles/10.3389/ijph.2025.1607952/full#supplementary-material" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ssph-journal.org/articles/10.3389/ijph.2025.1607952/full#supplementary-material</ext-link>
</p><supplementary-material id="SM1" position="float" content-type="local-data"><media xlink:href="DataSheet1.docx"/></supplementary-material></sec><sec id="s11"><title>Abbreviations</title><p>AIC, Akaike&#x02019;s Information Criterion; AUD, Alcohol Use Disorders; AUDIT, Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test; BMI, Body Mass Index; CDS, Cognitive Difficulties Scale; CES-D, Center for Epidemiologic Studies Depression Scale; CI, Confidence Interval; C-index, Concordance Index; DALY, Disability-Adjusted Life Years; ICSD-3, International Classification of Sleep Disorders &#x02013; 3rd edition; IPAQ, International Physical Activity Questionnaire; DSM-5, Diagnostic and Statistical Manual &#x02013; 5th edition; QOL, Quality of life; SCOFF, Sick-Control-One-Fat-Food scale; SE, Standard Error; STAI-T, Trait subscale of the State-Trait Anxiety Inventory; WHO, World Health Organization; WHODAS 2.0, WHO Disability Assessment Schedule 2.0.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chesney</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodwin</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fazel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Risks of All-Cause and Suicide Mortality in Mental Disorders: A Meta-Review</article-title>. <source>World Psychiatry</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>13</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>153</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>60</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/wps.20128</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24890068</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<collab>The Lancet Psychiatry</collab>. <article-title>COVID-19 and Mental Health</article-title>. <source>Lancet Psychiatry</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>8</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>87</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2215-0366(21)00005-5</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33485416</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coste</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Valderas</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Carcaillon-Bentata</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Estimating and Characterizing the Burden of Multimorbidity in the Community: A Comprehensive Multistep Analysis of Two Large Nationwide Representative Surveys in France</article-title>. <source>PLoS Med</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>18</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>e1003584</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1003584</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33901171</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McGrath</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>CCW</given-names></name><name><surname>Plana-Ripoll</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Holtz</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Agerbo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Momen</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Comorbidity Within Mental Disorders: A Comprehensive Analysis Based on 145 990 Survey Respondents From 27 Countries</article-title>. <source>Epidemiol Psychiatr Sci</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>29</volume>:<fpage>e153</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S2045796020000633</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32782057</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kessler</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name><name><surname>Demler</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Walters</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence, Severity, and Comorbidity of Twelve-Month DSM-IV Disorders in the National Comorbidity Survey Replication (NCS-R)</article-title>. <source>Arch Gen Psychiatry</source> (<year>2005</year>) <volume>62</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>617</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>27</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archpsyc.62.6.617</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15939839</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caspi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Houts</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Belsky</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldman-Mellor</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Harrington</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Israel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>The P Factor: One General Psychopathology Factor in the Structure of Psychiatric Disorders?</article-title>
<source>Clin Psychol Sci</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>2</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>119</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>37</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2167702613497473</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25360393</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kirkbride</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Anglin</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Colman</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Dykxhoorn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>Patalay</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>The Social Determinants of Mental Health and Disorder: Evidence, Prevention and Recommendations</article-title>. <source>World Psychiatry</source> (<year>2024</year>) <volume>23</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>58</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>90</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/wps.21160</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38214615</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lund</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Brooke-Sumner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Baingana</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Baron</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Breuer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandra</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Social Determinants of Mental Disorders and the Sustainable Development Goals: A Systematic Review of Reviews</article-title>. <source>Lancet Psychiatry</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>5</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>357</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>69</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2215-0366(18)30060-9</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29580610</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barr</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>Bigdeli</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyers</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence, Comorbidity, and Sociodemographic Correlates of Psychiatric Disorders Reported in the All of Us Research Program</article-title>. <source>JAMA Psychiatry</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>79</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>622</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamapsychiatry.2022.0685</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35442391</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>ISS</given-names></name><name><surname>Azcoaga-Lorenzo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Akbari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Black</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hodgins</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Examining Variation in the Measurement of Multimorbidity in Research: A Systematic Review of 566 Studies</article-title>. <source>Lancet Public Health</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>6</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>e587</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>97</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2468-2667(21)00107-9</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34166630</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahme</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Calfat</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Sirois</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Multimorbidity Measures From Health Administrative Data Using ICD System Codes: A Systematic Review</article-title>. <source>Pharmacoepidemiol Drug Saf</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>31</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pds.5368</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34623723</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stirland</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez-Saavedra</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Mullin</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ritchie</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Muniz-Terrera</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Russ</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Measuring Multimorbidity Beyond Counting Diseases: Systematic Review of Community and Population Studies and Guide to Index Choice</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>368</volume>:<fpage>m160</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.m160</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32071114</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cassell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Harshfield</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rhodes</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Brimicombe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Payne</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>The Epidemiology of Multimorbidity in Primary Care: A Retrospective Cohort Study</article-title>. <source>Br J Gen Pract</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>68</volume>(<issue>669</issue>):<fpage>e245</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>51</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3399/bjgp18X695465</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29530918</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Byers</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Yaffe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Covinsky</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruce</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>High Occurrence of Mood and Anxiety Disorders Among Older Adults: The National Comorbidity Survey Replication</article-title>. <source>Arch Gen Psychiatry</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>67</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>489</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>96</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archgenpsychiatry.2010.35</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20439830</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jacobi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Wittchen</surname><given-names>HU</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#x000f6;lting</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#x000f6;fler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfister</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Prevalence, Co-Morbidity and Correlates of Mental Disorders in the General Population: Results from the German Health Interview and Examination Survey (GHS)</article-title>. <source>Psychol Med</source> (<year>2004</year>) <volume>34</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>597</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>611</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0033291703001399</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15099415</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Angst</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sellaro</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ries Merikangas</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Multimorbidity of Psychiatric Disorders as an Indicator of Clinical Severity</article-title>. <source>Eur Arch Psychiatry Clin Neurosci</source> (<year>2002</year>) <volume>252</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>147</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>54</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00406-002-0357-6</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12242574</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gamma</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Angst</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Concurrent Psychiatric Comorbidity and Multimorbidity in a Community Study: Gender Differences and Quality of Life</article-title>. <source>Eur Arch Psychiatry Clin Neurosci</source> (<year>2001</year>) <volume>251</volume>(<issue>S2</issue>):<fpage>43</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF03035126</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence, Comorbidity, Disability and Service Utilisation. Overview of the Australian National Mental Health Survey</article-title>. <source>Br J Psychiatry</source> (<year>2001</year>) <volume>178</volume>:<fpage>145</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>53</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1192/bjp.178.2.145</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11157427</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fergusson</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Horwood</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lynskey</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence and Comorbidity of DSM-III-R Diagnoses in a Birth Cohort of 15 Year Olds</article-title>. <source>J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry</source> (<year>1993</year>) <volume>32</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1127</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>34</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00004583-199311000-00004</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8282656</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Selim</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Fincke</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>XS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Comorbidity Assessments Based on Patient Report: Results From the Veterans Health Study</article-title>. <source>J Ambul Care Manage</source> (<year>2004</year>) <volume>27</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>281</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>95</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00004479-200407000-00011</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15287217</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gunderson</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name><surname>Arthur</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A Brief Mental Health Index</article-title>. <source>J Abnorm Psychol</source> (<year>1969</year>) <volume>74</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>100</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/h0027067</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5780492</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pfeffer</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurosaki</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><name><surname>Chance</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Filos</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Use of the Mental Function Index in Older Adults. Reliability, Validity, and Measurement of Change Over Time</article-title>. <source>Am J Epidemiol</source> (<year>1984</year>) <volume>120</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>922</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>35</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/oxfordjournals.aje.a113963</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6507430</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>&#x000dc;st&#x000fc;n</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name><name><surname>Kostanjesek</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Chatterji</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rehm</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> eds. <source>Measuring Health and Disability: Manual for WHO Disability Assessment Schedule WHODAS 2.0</source>. <publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name> (<year>2010</year>). <fpage>90</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hercberg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Castetbon</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Czernichow</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Malon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mejean</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kesse</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>The NutriNet-Sant&#x000e9; Study: A Web-Based Prospective Study on the Relationship Between Nutrition and Health and Determinants of Dietary Patterns and Nutritional Status</article-title>. <source>BMC Public Health</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>242</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2458-10-242</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20459807</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Radloff</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The CES-D Scale: A Self-Report Depression Scale for Research in the General Population</article-title>. <source>Appl Psychol Meas</source> (<year>1977</year>) <volume>1</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>385</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>401</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/014662167700100306</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vilagut</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Forero</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbaglia</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Screening for Depression in the General Population With the Center for Epidemiologic Studies Depression (CES-D): A Systematic Review with Meta-Analysis</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>11</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>e0155431</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0155431</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27182821</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spielberger</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorsuch</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lushene</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Vagg</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Manual for the State-Trait Anxiety Inventory</source>. <publisher-loc>Palo Alto</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Consulting Psychologists Press</publisher-name> (<year>1983</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chambers</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Power</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name><surname>Durham</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The Relationship Between Trait Vulnerability and Anxiety and Depressive Diagnoses at Long-Term Follow-Up of Generalized Anxiety Disorder</article-title>. <source>J Anxiety Disord</source> (<year>2004</year>) <volume>18</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>587</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>607</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.janxdis.2003.09.001</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15275941</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kose</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fezeu</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name><surname>P&#x000e9;neau</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Debras</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Touvier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>A Comparison of Sugar Intake Between Individuals With High and Low Trait Anxiety: Results From the NutriNet-Sant&#x000e9; Study</article-title>. <source>Nutrients</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>13</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1526</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/nu13051526</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33946586</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kose</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Paz Graniel</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>P&#x000e9;neau</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Julia</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hercberg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Galan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>A Population-Based Study of Macronutrient Intake According to Mental Health Status With a Focus on Pure and Comorbid Anxiety and Eating Disorders</article-title>. <source>Eur J Nutr</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>61</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>3685</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>96</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00394-022-02923-x</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35678893</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>American Academy of Sleep Medicine</collab>. <source>International Classification of Sleep Disorders (ICSD)</source>. <edition>3rd ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>Darien</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Academy of Sleep Medicine</publisher-name> (<year>2014</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>American Psychiatric Association</collab>. <source>Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM-5)</source>. <edition>5th ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>Washington</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Psychiatric Association</publisher-name> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lacey</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The SCOFF Questionnaire: Assessment of a New Screening Tool for Eating Disorders</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source> (<year>1999</year>) <volume>319</volume>(<issue>7223</issue>):<fpage>1467</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.319.7223.1467</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10582927</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>FD</given-names></name><name><surname>Grigioni</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Allais</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Houy-Durand</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Thibaut</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x000e9;chelotte</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Detection of Eating Disorders in Patients: Validity and Reliability of the French Version of the SCOFF Questionnaire</article-title>. <source>Clin Nutr</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>30</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>178</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>81</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clnu.2010.09.007</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20971536</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Babor</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name><name><surname>Higgins-Biddle</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Saunders</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Monteiro</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Alcohol Use Disorders Identificaiton Test: Guidelines for Use in Primary Care</source>. <edition>2nd ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name> (<year>2001</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McNair</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kahn</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Self Assessment of Cognitive Deficits</article-title>. In: <source>Assessment in Geriatric Psychopharmacology</source>. <publisher-loc>New Canaan</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Mark Powley Associates</publisher-name> (<year>1983</year>). <fpage>137</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>43</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Derouesn&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dealberto</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lubin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauron</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Piette</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Empirical Evaluation of the &#x02018;Cognitive Difficulties Scale&#x02019; for Assessment of Memory Complaints in General Practice: A Study of 1628 Cognitively Normal Subjects Aged 45&#x02013;75 Years</article-title>. <source>Int J Geriatr Psychiatry</source> (<year>1993</year>) <volume>8</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>599</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>607</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/gps.930080712</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Federici</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bracalenti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Meloni</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Luciano</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>World Health Organization Disability Assessment Schedule 2.0: An International Systematic Review</article-title>. <source>Disabil Rehabil</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>39</volume>(<issue>23</issue>):<fpage>2347</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>80</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09638288.2016.1223177</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27820966</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vergnaud</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Touvier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000e9;jean</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kesse-Guyot</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Pollet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Malon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Agreement Between Web-Based and Paper Versions of a Socio-Demographic Questionnaire in the NutriNet-Sant&#x000e9; Study</article-title>. <source>Int J Public Health</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>56</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>407</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>17</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00038-011-0257-5</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21538094</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lassale</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>P&#x000e9;neau</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Touvier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Julia</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Galan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hercberg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Validity of Web-Based Self-Reported Weight and Height: Results of the NutriNet-Sant&#x000e9; Study</article-title>. <source>J Med Internet Res</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>15</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>e152</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/jmir.2575</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23928492</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Sj&#x000f6;str&#x000f6;m</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bauman</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Booth</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Ainsworth</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>International Physical Activity Questionnaire: 12-Country Reliability and Validity</article-title>. <source>Med Sci Sports Exerc</source> (<year>2003</year>) <volume>35</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1381</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>95</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1249/01.MSS.0000078924.61453.FB</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12900694</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ealing</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>McDermott</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Chalabi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Majeed</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Measuring Disability in Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis/Motor Neuron Disease: The WHODAS 2.0-36, WHODAS 2.0-32, and WHODAS 2.0-12</article-title>. <source>Amyotroph Lateral Scler Front Degener</source> (<year>2023</year>) <volume>24</volume>(<issue>1&#x02013;2</issue>):<fpage>63</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>70</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/21678421.2022.2102926</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Payne</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mendonca</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Saunders</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Development and Validation of the Cambridge Multimorbidity Score</article-title>. <source>Can Med Assoc J</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>192</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>E107</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>E114</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1503/cmaj.190757</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32015079</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Amore</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Murtinu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Tobit Models in Strategy Research: Critical Issues and Applications</article-title>. <source>Glob Strategy J</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>11</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>331</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>55</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/gsj.1363</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gomez-Olive</surname><given-names>FX</given-names></name><name><surname>Schr&#x000f6;ders</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Aboderin</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Byass</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Chatterji</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Variations in Disability and Quality of Life With Age and Sex Between Eight Lower Income and Middle-Income Countries: Data From the INDEPTH WHO-SAGE Collaboration</article-title>. <source>BMJ Glob Health</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>2</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>e000508</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjgh-2017-000508</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akaike</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A New Look at the Statistical Model Identification</article-title>. <source>IEEE Trans Autom Control</source> (<year>1974</year>) <volume>19</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>716</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>23</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/tac.1974.1100705</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Selvin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Statistical Analysis of Epidemiologic Data</source>. <edition>3rd ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name> (<year>2004</year>). p. <fpage>492</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Corrao</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Rea</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Martino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>De Palma</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Scondotto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fusco</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Developing and Validating a Novel Multisource Comorbidity Score From Administrative Data: A Large Population-Based Cohort Study From Italy</article-title>. <source>BMJ Open</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>7</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>e019503</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2017-019503</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Steinman</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jing</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bs</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Covinsky</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Development and Validation of Novel Multimorbidity Indices for Older Adults</article-title>. <source>J Am Geriatr Soc</source> (<year>2023</year>) <volume>71</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>121</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>35</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jgs.18052</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36282202</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A Coefficient of Determination for Generalized Linear Models</article-title>. <source>Am Stat</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>71</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>310</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00031305.2016.1256839</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sterne</surname><given-names>JAC</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlin</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Spratt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Royston</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kenward</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Multiple Imputation for Missing Data in Epidemiological and Clinical Research: Potential and Pitfalls</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source> (<year>2009</year>) <volume>338</volume>:<fpage>b2393</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.b2393</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19564179</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Steyerberg</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name><name><surname>Vickers</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerds</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Obuchowski</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Assessing the Performance of Prediction Models: A Framework for Some Traditional and Novel Measures</article-title>. <source>Epidemiol Camb Mass</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>21</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>128</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>38</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/EDE.0b013e3181c30fb2</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Antunes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Frasquilho</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Azeredo-Lopes</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Neto</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cardoso</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Disability and Common Mental Disorders: Results From the World Mental Health Survey Initiative Portugal</article-title>. <source>Eur Psychiatry J Assoc Eur Psychiatr</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>49</volume>:<fpage>56</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>61</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eurpsy.2017.12.004</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nor&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Karlsson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohlsson-Nevo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000f6;ller</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hermansson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Psychometric Evaluation of the WHODAS 2.0 and Prevalence of Disability in a Swedish General Population</article-title>. <source>J Patient-Rep Outcomes</source> (<year>2023</year>) <volume>7</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>36</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s41687-023-00580-0</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37020121</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Charlson</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Pompei</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ales</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>MacKenzie</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A New Method of Classifying Prognostic Comorbidity in Longitudinal Studies: Development and Validation</article-title>. <source>J Chronic Dis</source> (<year>1987</year>) <volume>40</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>373</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>83</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0021-9681(87)90171-8</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3558716</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawachi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Okereke</surname><given-names>OI</given-names></name><name><surname>Mukamal</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Diverse Cumulative Impact of Chronic Diseases on Physical Health-Related Quality of Life: Implications for a Measure of Multimorbidity</article-title>. <source>Am J Epidemiol</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>184</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>357</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>65</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aje/kwv456</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27530335</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Van de Velde</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Vilagut</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>de Graaf</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x005f3;Neill</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Florescu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Gender Differences in Mental Disorders and Suicidality in Europe: Results From a Large Cross-Sectional Population-Based Study</article-title>. <source>J Affect Disord</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>173</volume>:<fpage>245</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>54</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2014.11.002</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25462424</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eaton</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name><surname>Keyes</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Krueger</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Balsis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Skodol</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Markon</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>An Invariant Dimensional Liability Model of Gender Differences in Mental Disorder Prevalence: Evidence From a National Sample</article-title>. <source>J Abnorm Psychol</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>121</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>282</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/a0024780</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21842958</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><name><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Girman</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Adhikari</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Regression Coefficient&#x02013;Based Scoring System Should Be Used to Assign Weights to the Risk Index</article-title>. <source>J Clin Epidemiol</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>79</volume>:<fpage>22</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jclinepi.2016.03.031</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27181564</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hosmer</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemeshow</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sturdivant</surname><given-names>RX</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Applied Logistic Regression</source>. <edition>3rd ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>Hoboken</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><label>61.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clement</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Schauman</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Maggioni</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans-Lacko</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bezborodovs</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>What Is the Impact of Mental Health-Related Stigma on Help-Seeking? A Systematic Review of Quantitative and Qualitative Studies</article-title>. <source>Psychol Med</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>45</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>11</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>27</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0033291714000129</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24569086</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B62"><label>62.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Waterhouse</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Wielen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Banda</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Channon</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The Impact of Multi-Morbidity on Disability Among Older Adults in South Africa: Do Hypertension and Socio-Demographic Characteristics Matter?</article-title>
<source>Int J Equity Health</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>62</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12939-017-0537-7</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28388911</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B63"><label>63.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Santomauro</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Mantilla Herrera</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Shadid</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashbaugh</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pigott</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Global Prevalence and Burden of Depressive and Anxiety Disorders in 204 Countries and Territories in 2020 Due to the COVID-19 Pandemic</article-title>. <source>Lancet.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>398</volume>(<issue>10312</issue>):<fpage>1700</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(21)02143-7</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34634250</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B64"><label>64.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zipfel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Giel</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The Hidden Burden of Eating Disorders During the COVID-19 Pandemic</article-title>. <source>Lancet Psychiatry</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>9</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>9</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2215-0366(21)00435-1</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34921799</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B65"><label>65.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">
<collab>Sant&#x000e9; publique France</collab>. <article-title>CoviPrev: Une Enqu&#x000ea;te Pour Suivre L&#x02019;&#x000e9;volution des Comportements et de la Sant&#x000e9; Mentale Pendant l&#x02019;&#x000e9;pid&#x000e9;mie de COVID-19 [CoviPrev: A Survey to Track Changes in Behavior and Mental Health During the COVID-19 Epidemic]</article-title>. <comment>Available from: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.santepubliquefrance.fr/etudes-et-enquetes/coviprev-une-enqu&#x000ea;te-pour-suivre-l&#x02019;&#x000e9;volution-des-comportements-et-de-la-sante-mentale-pendant-l-epidemie-de-covid-19" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.santepubliquefrance.fr/etudes-et-enquetes/coviprev-une-enqu&#x000ea;te-pour-suivre-l&#x02019;&#x000e9;volution-des-comportements-et-de-la-sante-mentale-pendant-l-epidemie-de-covid-19</ext-link> (Accessed November 25, 2024)</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B66"><label>66.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andreeva</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name><surname>Salanave</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Castetbon</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Deschamps</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Vernay</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kesse-Guyot</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Comparison of the Sociodemographic Characteristics of the Large NutriNet-Sant&#x000e9; E-Cohort With French Census Data: The Issue of Volunteer Bias Revisited</article-title>. <source>J Epidemiol Community Health</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>69</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>893</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/jech-2014-205263</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25832451</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B67"><label>67.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andreeva</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name><surname>Deschamps</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Salanave</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Castetbon</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Verdot</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kesse-Guyot</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Comparison of Dietary Intakes between a Large Online Cohort Study (Etude NutriNet-Sant&#x000e9;) and a Nationally Representative Cross-Sectional Study (Etude Nationale Nutrition Sant&#x000e9;) in France: Addressing the Issue of Generalizability in E-Epidemiology</article-title>. <source>Am J Epidemiol</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>184</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>660</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aje/kww016</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27744386</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B68"><label>68.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></name><name><surname>Tam</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence of Depression in the Community From 30 Countries Between 1994 and 2014</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>8</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>2861</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-21243-x</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29434331</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B69"><label>69.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Galmiche</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x000e9;chelotte</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambert</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Tavolacci</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence of Eating Disorders over the 2000&#x02013;2018 Period: A Systematic Literature Review</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Nutr</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>109</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1402</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>13</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ajcn/nqy342</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31051507</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B70"><label>70.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chan-Chee</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bayon</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Bloch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Giordanella</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Leger</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>&#x000c9;pid&#x000e9;miologie de l&#x02019;insomnie en France: Etat des lieux [Epidemiology of insomnia in France: Situation report]</article-title>. <source>Revue d'&#x000c9;pid&#x000e9;miologie et de Sant&#x000e9; Publique</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>59</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>409</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>22</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B71"><label>71.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berner</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kriston</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bentele</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#x000e4;rter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test for Detecting At-Risk Drinking: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis</article-title>. <source>J Stud Alcohol Drugs</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>68</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>461</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>73</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15288/jsad.2007.68.461</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17446987</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B72"><label>72.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sachdev</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipnicki</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kochan</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Thalamuthu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>The Prevalence of Mild Cognitive Impairment in Diverse Geographical and Ethnocultural Regions: The COSMIC Collaboration</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>10</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>e0142388</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0142388</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26539987</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B73"><label>73.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jacobi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#x000f6;fler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Siegert</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mack</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerschler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Scholl</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Twelve&#x02010;month Prevalence, Comorbidity and Correlates of Mental Disorders in Germany: The Mental Health Module of the German Health Interview and Examination Survey for Adults (DEGS1&#x02010;MH)</article-title>. <source>Int J Methods Psychiatr Res</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>23</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>304</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>19</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/mpr.1439</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24729411</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>