<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="issn">2168-8184</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cureus</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2168-8184</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cureus</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Palo Alto (CA)</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11680465</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7759/cureus.74572</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Radiology</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Pulmonology</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Oncology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Is FDG-PET/CT Scan Useful in the Detection of Subcentimeter Mediastinal Lymph Node Involvement in Patients With Lung Carcinoma?</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Muacevic</surname><given-names>Alexander</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>John R</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Altaf</surname><given-names>Muhammad Omer</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zahra</surname><given-names>Hamd</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Majied</surname><given-names>Hira</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Niazi</surname><given-names>Imran Khalid</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Farooq</surname><given-names>Hira</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff-1">
<label>1</label>
Department of Radiology, Shaukat Khanum Memorial Cancer Hospital and Research Centre, Lahore, PAK </aff><aff id="aff-2">
<label>2</label>
Department of Radiology, Shalamar Hospital, Shalamar Medical and Dental College, Lahore, PAK </aff><aff id="aff-3">
<label>3</label>
Department of Radiology, University Hospitals of North Midlands NHS Trust, Stoke-on-Trent, GBR </aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">
Hira Majied <email>hiramajied@gmail.com</email>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>27</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic"><month>11</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><issue>11</issue><elocation-id>e74572</elocation-id><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>26</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2024, Altaf et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Altaf et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License CC-BY 4.0., which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="https://www.cureus.com/articles/273275-is-fdg-petct-scan-useful-in-the-detection-of-subcentimeter-mediastinal-lymph-node-involvement-in-patients-with-lung-carcinoma">This article is available from https://www.cureus.com/articles/273275-is-fdg-petct-scan-useful-in-the-detection-of-subcentimeter-mediastinal-lymph-node-involvement-in-patients-with-lung-carcinoma</self-uri><abstract><p>Background</p><p>Early staging of lung carcinoma (CA) is pivotal in planning the treatment. Lymph node metastasis can be detected by imaging and invasive procedures. The 18F-fluorodeoxyglucose positron emission tomography/computed tomography (FDG-PET/CT) is an emerging noninvasive imaging modality in detecting nodal metastasis.</p><p>Objective</p><p>This study aimed to determine the usefulness of the FDG-PET/CT scan in detecting subcentimeter mediastinal lymph node involvement in lung CA patients by taking histopathology as the gold standard.</p><p>Materials and methods</p><p>We conducted a retrospective cross-sectional study at a tertiary care cancer hospital in Pakistan over four and half years, from January 2015 to June 2019. All&#x000a0;patients suffering from non-small cell lung CA (NSCLC) having avid subcentimeter nodes on FDG-PET/CT were included. The findings obtained on FDG-PET/CT were correlated with histopathological findings after endobronchial ultrasound&#x000a0;(EBUS). The results were formulated using&#x000a0;IBM SPSS Statistics for Windows, Version 21 (Released 2012; IBM Corp., Armonk, New York, United States).</p><p>Results</p><p>Results showed that 42/380 total lung CA patients had avid subcentimeter lymph nodes obtained on FDG-PET/CT. A total of 22/42 (52.4%) lymph nodes appeared to be benign, and&#x000a0;20/42 (47.6%) lesions were malignant on histopathology. FDG-PET/CT sensitivity is calculated to be 95%, specificity is 68%, positive predictive value is 73%, negative predictive value is 94%, and accuracy is 80.9%. Using the receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curve,&#x000a0;sensitivity and specificity were seen in nodes of size 7.5 mm and the maximum standardized uptake value (SUV max)&#x000a0;of 5.5 as cutoff values as manifested by area under the curve&#x000a0;(AUC).</p><p>Conclusion</p><p>FDG-PET/CT was proven to have high sensitivity and accuracy but a low specificity rate to detect nodal involvement in lung CA patients. The high false-positive rates are mainly due to increased prevalence of endemic lung infectious disease.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>fdg-pet/ct</kwd><kwd>lung carcinoma</kwd><kwd>lymph nodes</kwd><kwd>nodal metastasis</kwd><kwd>subcentimeter</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Lung carcinoma (CA) is the most common CA worldwide constituting 13% of all the diagnosed cancer cases [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. The highest morbidity and mortality rate associated with lung CA demand for its early diagnosis and treatment [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>].&#x000a0;In addition to this, lung cancer is classified into four main types as seen under a light microscope: adenocarcinoma, squamous cell CA, large cell CA, and small cell CA. Smoking is a key factor in causing all these types [<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>], as it is believed that the substances in cigarette smoke are responsible for causing continuous DNA damage which ultimately leads to genetic mutations seen in lung cancer [<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>].</p><p>The assessment of mediastinal lymphadenopathy holds significant importance in lung cancer staging [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Surgical intervention is favored when lymph nodes remain unaffected, while radiotherapy and chemotherapy become the preferred treatment modalities&#x000a0;if lymph node involvement is detected. Therefore, evaluating lymphadenopathy plays a crucial role in both diagnosis and prognosis [<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].&#x000a0;</p><p>In 2007, the European Society of Thoracic Surgeons (ESTS) introduced an algorithm to identify mediastinal lymphadenopathy in non-small cell lung CA (NSCLC), combining imaging, surgical, and endoscopic techniques. However, these surgical and endoscopic methods were invasive and carried risks of associated complications [<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Computed tomography (CT) scans and magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) are standard imaging modalities for evaluating mediastinal lymph node status, but they have limitations. CT scans offer low sensitivity and specificity of 64% and 62%, respectively [<xref rid="REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], while MRI may fail to detect calcification in the lymph nodes and can misinterpret a group of discrete nodes as a single large one due to poor spatial resolution. Moreover, their efficacy in detecting nodes measuring 1 cm or less remains unestablished. Furthermore, both CT and MRI often miss microinvasions and metastatic lesions [<xref rid="REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].</p><p>Another noninvasive imaging technology introduced lately is 18F-fluorodeoxyglucose positron emission tomography (FDG-PET). It has a sensitivity of 84% and a specificity of 89% in assessing mediastinal lymph node pathology [<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Recent studies have shown that PET and CT, when combined, can provide higher diagnostic accuracy by overcoming the limitations of both PET and CT [<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].</p><p>According to the American Joint Committee on Cancer (AJCC) and the National Comprehensive Cancer Network (NCCN) guidelines for imaging, in case of CA lung suspicion, a chest X-ray is the first imaging modality to be done. Guidelines recommend a contrast-enhanced CT (CECT) scan of the chest and upper abdomen (including the adrenal glands) for further evaluation. In patients who are eligible for curative treatment in addition to having no signs of metastasis on CT scan, an FDG-PET/CT is suggested [<xref rid="REF11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>].</p><p>The significance of&#x000a0;FDG-PET/CT scan in identifying subcentimeter mediastinal lymphadenopathy in&#x000a0;NSCLC patients, taking histopathology as a gold standard, will be discussed in this study. This study will focus mainly on the presence of metastatic subcentimeter lymph nodes depending upon their size and metabolic activity This will aid in sparing patients from unnecessary invasive diagnostic procedures that could potentially result in various complications.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><p>It is a retrospective cross-sectional study conducted at a tertiary care cancer center, Shaukat Khanum Memorial Cancer Hospital and Research Centre, Lahore, in collaboration with its Radiology and Pathology Department. The study duration was from January 1, 2015, to June 30, 2019.</p><p>Following approval from the Institutional Review Board (IRB), we retrospectively analyzed data of patients diagnosed with NSCLC via histopathology between January 1, 2015, and June 30, 2019. Inclusion and exclusion criteria were applied as described ahead. Selection of patients who exhibited metabolically active subcentimeter mediastinal lymph nodes on FDG-PET/CT scan was done. Patients of both sexes, male and female, between 16 and 75 years of age were included. Patients from diverse socioeconomic backgrounds were a part of our study. The socioeconomic status of patients showed variability, including patients from the poor, middle class, and upper class. Additionally, a notable majority of the patients who were included in this study had a history of smoking, with relatively fewer patients with no smoking history. The patients who were left out of this study were the ones with evidence of distant metastases on CT scan or PET done prior to surgical intervention&#x000a0;as well as those who underwent FDG-PET/CT scan within three months before endobronchial nodal biopsy. In addition to the preceding criteria, cases with incomplete patient records stored in the hospital information system were excluded.</p><p>Patients, included in the study, had their presenting complaints, complete imaging investigations, and prior medical and treatment histories&#x000a0;thoroughly reviewed. Complete confidentiality of all records was not overlooked. Detailed cancer staging prior to surgical intervention was ensured in all patients included in the study. Each patient underwent whole-body FDG-PET with an integrated CT scan. In order to reduce observational bias, these scans in each case were then subjected to careful evaluation using reconstructed and reformatted axial, coronal, and sagittal views by two expert radiologists independently, each with over five years of experience in the field.</p><p>To classify a lymph node as active it was established that it exhibits higher metabolic activity in comparison with the background hepatic activity, in each case. Lymph nodes fulfilling either one or both of the two criteria mentioned in the following sentence were marked malignant. Nodes with metabolic activity exceeding 4 to 4.5 SUV and/or a size greater than 7 to 7.5 mm FDG-PET/CT, based on individual assessments by two independent radiologists.</p><p>The body mass index of each subject, time of administration, and administrative activity of 18 FDG at the time of the test were noted to calculate the maximum standardized uptake value (SUV max). Cytopathological staging of each patient on endobronchial ultrasound (EBUS)-guided biopsy was done, and results were categorized into benign or malignant nature.&#x000a0;</p><p>Data analysis was done using&#x000a0;IBM SPSS Statistics for Windows, Version 21 (Released 2012; IBM Corp., Armonk, New York, United States), and inferential tests were applied to describe frequencies and distributions by age, gender, size, and avidity. Sensitivity and specificity were calculated, followed by multivariate analysis and correlations using Pearson&#x02019;s chi-square analysis. A receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curve was constructed to determine SUV max accuracy via the area under the curve (AUC). The results were obtained and correlated using chi-square analysis, keeping the p-value of &#x0003c;0.05 as significant.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p>The total number of patients with lung CA who presented to our department from January 1, 2015, to June 30, 2019, were 380. Out of the total number of patients, 253 (66.5%) had nodal disease with mediastinal nodal size greater than 1 cm in size&#x000a0;at the time of acquisition of PET-CT, while 127 (33.4%) patients had lymph nodes less than 1 cm. Around 85 (22.3%) out of 127 patients had shown no increased activity in the lymph nodes in comparison with the background hepatic metabolic activity which was taken as a control. The remaining 42 (11% of n) out of 127 patients having lung carcinoma had subcentimeter avid lymph nodes; hence, they were included in our study population as per inclusion criteria. These 42 patients, selected to be included in our study, displayed a diverse demographic profile (Tables <xref rid="TAB1" ref-type="table">1</xref>-<xref rid="TAB4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). The mean age of patients was 68 years (age range: 53-84 years) with a standard deviation of 8.142, with the most common age group being 66-70 years (eight patients). Closely following were individuals aged 61-65, 71-75, 76-80, and 81-85 years, each group consisting of seven patients. The lowest number of patients was observed in the 56-60 years age group, with only six patients (Table <xref rid="TAB1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Of all the patients included in our study, only 10 (23.8% of n) were females, and the rest (32, 76.2% of n) were males, with a male-to-female ratio of 3.2: 1 (Table <xref rid="TAB2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). In addition to this, patients of different socioeconomic statuses were a part of our study group. Out of the 42 total patients, 18 (42.8%) belonged to a poor socioeconomic background, 18 (42.8%) were middle class, and six (14.3%) were classified to be from upper socioeconomic status (Table <xref rid="TAB3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Furthermore, a notable majority, 27 (64.2%) patients, had a history of smoking, while 15 (35.7%) patients did not smoke (Table <xref rid="TAB4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). Among the ones who did not have a history of smoking, the majority were females.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Distribution of patients in the study across various age groups</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age group</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of patients</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56-60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61-65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66-70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71-75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76-80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81-85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Gender distribution of patients in the study</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.8%</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Distribution of patients in the study by socioeconomic status</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Socioeconomic status</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of patients</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Middle class</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Upper class</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">06</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Patient distribution based on smoking history in the study</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking history</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of patients</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Present</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not present</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Supported by histopathological evaluation, out of 42 patients, 25 (59.5%) were diagnosed to have adenocarcinoma, while 17 (40.5%) were diagnosed with squamous cell carcinoma. It was revealed that most of the patients with adenocarcinoma presented at stage II B, whereas those with squamous cell carcinoma presented at stage III C. No other types of carcinoma were observed among&#x000a0;patients selected for this study. Out of the total 42 patients, 22 (52.4%) had lymph nodes that were classified as benign. Among 22 patients with lymph nodes labeled as benign, six (14.3%) had lymph nodes showing signs of inflammation, and 16 (38.1%) displayed reactivity. On the other hand, histopathological analysis confirmed malignancy in 20 (47.6%) lesions.</p><p>FDG-PET/CT scan findings showed that sizes of lymph nodes ranged from 5 to 9 mm. Out of the total of 42 patients, 32 (76.2% of the total) had lymph node sizes between 6 and 8 mm (with a mean of 7.1 mm and a standard deviation of 1.284). SUV values, pertaining to metabolic activity, ranged from 2 to 9 (with a mean metabolic activity of 4.93 SUV and a standard deviation of 1.813). The relationship between size and metabolic activity along with the benign and malignant nature of lymph nodes as revealed on histopathology is given in Tables <xref rid="TAB5" ref-type="table">5</xref>-<xref rid="TAB6" ref-type="table">6</xref>, respectively. In this study&#x02019;s findings, larger size and high metabolic activity were the factors that were observed to have an association with the presence of malignant disease, indicating a statistically significant correlation (p-value &#x0003c; 0.05).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><title>Depiction of individual evaluation of pathology results for nodal sizes and metabolic activities</title><p>FDG-PET/CT: 18F-fluorodeoxyglucose positron emission tomography/computed tomography; SUV: standardized uptake value</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FDG-PET/CT &#x000a0;variables</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mm/SUV</td><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Pathology decision</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Benign</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Malignant</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Count</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Table N %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Count</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Table N %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5" colspan="1">Mediastinal node size in millimeters</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.80%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.80%</td><td rowspan="5" colspan="1">&#x000a0; &#x000a0; &#x000a0; 0.033 &#x000a0; &#x000a0;</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.20%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.10%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.80%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.80%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.70%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.70%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.30%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="8" colspan="1">Mediastinal node avidity SUV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.80%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00%</td><td rowspan="8" colspan="1">&#x000a0; &#x000a0; &#x000a0; &#x000a0; &#x000a0; 0.024 &#x000a0; &#x000a0; &#x000a0; &#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.30%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.40%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.40%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.50%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.10%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.80%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.40%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.90%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.40%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.50%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.80%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.80%</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB6"><label>Table 6</label><caption><title>Depiction of combined evaluation of pathology results for nodal sizes and metabolic activities</title><p>FDG-PET/CT: 18F-fluorodeoxyglucose positron emission tomography/computed tomography; SUV: standardized uptake value</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">FDG-PET/CT variable</td><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Pathology decision</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Mediastinal node avidity SUV</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Mediastinal node size in millimeters</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Benign</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Malignant</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Count</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Table N %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Count</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Table N %</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.80%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.50%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.80%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.40%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.80%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.80%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.80%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.90%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.40%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.40%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.80%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.80%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.40%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.40%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.40%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.40%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.80%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.40%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.40%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.40%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.10%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.40%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.40%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.80%</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Multivariate analysis revealed that nodal size and SUV max are predictors of nodal metastasis, with OD of 1.925 (95% CI: 1.115-3.323, p = 0.033) and OD of 2.667 (95% CI: 1.467-4.847, p = 0.024), respectively.</p><p>The concordance between decision taken on FDG-PET/CT and histopathology decision was calculated. It was observed that 15/16(93.8%) patients with benign nodes and 19/26 (73%) patients with malignant nodes labeled on FDG-PET/CT were in concordance with the results on pathology as shown in Figure <xref rid="FIG1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>.</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Depiction of FDG-PET/CT concordance with pathology result for subcentimeter nodal involvement in lung carcinoma patients</title><p>FDG-PET/CT: 18F-fluorodeoxyglucose positron emission tomography/computed tomography</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0016-00000074572-i01" position="float"/></fig><p>Taking into account the size and metabolic activity for benign and malignant lesions on FDG-PET/CT as mentioned in the methodology section, the sensitivity of FDG-PET/CT is 95%, specificity is 68%, positive predictive value is 73%, negative predictive value is 94%, and accuracy is calculated to be&#x000a0;80.9% as shown in Figure <xref rid="FIG2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>. It was obtained after taking the mean of the findings by two experienced radiologists, with a good inter-rater agreement (k value: 0.854).</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>FDG-PET/CT accuracy chart depicting calculated specificity and sensitivity rates based on the results of the study</title><p>FDG-PET/CT: 18F-fluorodeoxyglucose positron emission tomography/computed tomography</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0016-00000074572-i02" position="float"/></fig><p>ROC curves were designed to determine the optimal cutoff values for size and SUV max to maximize the sensitivity and specificity of FDG-PET/CT. It was observed that the maximum sensitivity and specificity values were seen in nodes of size 7.5 mm and SUV max of 5.5 as cutoff values as manifested by the AUC in Figures <xref rid="FIG3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>-<xref rid="FIG4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>.</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>ROC curve depicting graphical plot illustration for the diagnostic ability of optimal nodal metabolic activity (SUV max)</title><p>SUV max: maximum standardized uptake value; ROC: receiver operating characteristic</p><p>Area under the curve = 0.837; standard error = 0.062</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0016-00000074572-i03" position="float"/></fig><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>ROC curve depicting graphical plot illustration for the diagnostic ability of optimal nodal size (mm) </title><p>ROC: receiver operating characteristic</p><p>Area under the curve = 0.714; standard error = 0.083&#x000a0;</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0016-00000074572-i04" position="float"/></fig><p>A 62-year-old man was initially diagnosed with squamous cell carcinoma of the lung. FDG-PET/CT scan was done for staging as seen in Figures <xref rid="FIG5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>-<xref rid="FIG6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>. The CT component showed a prominent pretracheal lymph node measuring 8 mm in dimension (Figure <xref rid="FIG5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). It was noted that this lymph node had an increased metabolic activity of 6 SUV raising concern (Figure <xref rid="FIG6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). PET/CT decision was consistent with it being malignant and also turned out to be malignant on EBUS-guided fine-needle aspiration cytology (FNAC).</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>CT component showing a prominent pretracheal lymph node measuring 8 mm in dimension (arrow)</title><p>CT: computed tomography</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0016-00000074572-i05" position="float"/></fig><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>PET component showing increased metabolic activity of 6 SUV (red circle)</title><p>PET: positron emission tomography; SUV:&#x000a0;standardized uptake value</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0016-00000074572-i06" position="float"/></fig><p>The CT component of the patient mentioned in the preceding paragraph, a 62-year-old man with the initial diagnosis of squamous cell carcinoma of the lung, in the lung window with a cavitary lesion seen in the posterior segment of the right upper lobe (Figure <xref rid="FIG7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>).</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>CT component in lung window, showing a cavitary lesion, seen in the posterior segment of the right upper lobe (arrow)</title><p>CT: computed tomography</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0016-00000074572-i07" position="float"/></fig><p>A 70-year-old male patient was initially diagnosed with lung adenocarcinoma and had a history of old pulmonary tuberculosis. FDG-PET/CT scan done for staging purposes showed a large heterogenous solid mass in the right lung perihilar location (Figure <xref rid="FIG8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>). A prominent subcarinal node was noted measuring 7 mm in the&#x000a0;short axis dimension (Figure <xref rid="FIG9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>) with metabolic activity of 3 SUV. Nodal calcifications, especially in another subcarinal lymph node, were also noted (Figures <xref rid="FIG8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>-<xref rid="FIG9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>). It was interpreted as mediastinal lymphadenopathy related to background tuberculosis rather than metastasis and was further confirmed on EBUS-guided FNAC.</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG8"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><title>CT component showing a large heterogeneous solid mass in the right lung perihilar location, a prominent subcarinal node measuring 7 mm in short-axis dimension (arrow), and nodal calcifications in another subcarinal lymph node (arrowhead)</title><p>CT: computed tomography</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0016-00000074572-i08" position="float"/></fig><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG9"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><title>PET component, axial slice, from the same level, showing high metabolic activity in the right perihilar mass as well as in the mediastinal lymph node, with the mass itself showing metabolic activity of 11 SUV, while the maximum SUV of the subcarinal lymph node measures up to 3, indicating a lesser probability of metastasis</title><p>PET: positron emission tomography; SUV:&#x000a0;standardized uptake value</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0016-00000074572-i09" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Lung cancer is among the top causes of mortality due to malignancy globally, with lower survival rates and impacting males more than females [<xref rid="REF12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="REF13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. However, this gap is seen to be closing due to a shift in the roles that women of this day and age play in our society. This is due to a handful of reasons, to name a few, presentation of men with more advanced stages of lung CA, stronger immune responses in women which lead to better response to treatments in women, and occupational exposures, that are observed to be higher in men. Additionally, cultural influences, like in the population our study was conducted in, often lead to higher smoking rates in men, another fact that contributes to the observed gender disparity in lung CA [<xref rid="REF13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].</p><p>Approximately 75% of patients present with either locally advanced disease or one in which the disease process has metastasized, leaving the option of palliative treatment mostly. A point worth considering is that metastasis that has spread to the lymph nodes frequently appears in early-stage lung cancer and plays a crucial role in disease staging. Aside from malignancy, mediastinal lymph node enlargement can also be encountered in various other clinical conditions, such as inflammatory or infectious processes. CT scans and MRI have been widely used for the early establishment of diagnosis and staging of lung CA. On the one hand, these modalities provide a detailed structure of the involved lymph node; on the other hand, these can easily overlook lymph nodes below 1 cm. Conventionally, lymph nodes below the size threshold of 1 cm are considered normal, assuming metastatic nodes are larger. The CT scan shows a very low sensitivity (57%) when it comes to detecting subcentimeter lymph nodes leading to high false negatives for metastatic subcentimeter nodal involvement. Furthermore, CT can detect tumors that may not cause symptoms or harm, leading to unnecessary treatment and associated costs [<xref rid="REF14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Interestingly, smaller lymph nodes have shown an increased likelihood of metastatic involvement compared to larger nodes, rendering size, when taken independently, an unreliable indicator of lymph node metastasis [<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="REF15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].</p><p>PET imaging has become an emerging means to assess lymph node involvement in metastatic disease taking metabolic activity into account. FDG&#x000a0;is a glucose analog&#x000a0;that is utilized in FDG-PET scans to evaluate glucose metabolic rates. It has been noted that FDG has an affinity for reactive lesions as well, thereby making it rather less specific for malignancy [<xref rid="REF16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. The introduction of combined FDG-PET/CT aims to overcome the limitations of using CT or FDG-PET alone for identifying malignant lesions. This combined approach not only has demonstrated higher sensitivity and specificity compared to CT alone but has improved accuracy in detecting nodal involvement [<xref rid="REF17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>].&#x000a0;</p><p>In this research, we have studied the role of integrating FDG-PET/CT scans in determining the benign or malignant nature of involved subcentimeter lymph nodes in CA lung patients. Our study included 42 lung CA patients with evidence of subcentimeter lymph nodes. The mean age was 68 years, and a male predilection was observed in all patients. On histological evaluation, around 60% of patients had adenocarcinoma, while the remaining 40% had squamous cell CA. It was observed that out of the total of 26 patients with malignant nodes on histopathology, 19 (73.1%) were identified as malignant by FDG-PET/CT, and one out of 16 benign lymph nodes turned out to be malignant.</p><p>Metabolic activity is measured in terms of SUV&#x000a0;and serves as a means to quantify FDG uptake in integrated PET/CT. Both SUV mean and SUV max play a role in diagnosing as well as distinguishing between benign and malignant lesions. However, SUV max is favored due to its ability to significantly reduce interobserver variability, which is seen to drop from 35% to merely 3% when compared to SUV mean [<xref rid="REF18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Based on this, and as indicated in a study conducted by Gambhir, using a cutoff SUV max value has promised more accuracy in differentiating between benign and malignant lesions [<xref rid="REF19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Thus, in our study, SUV max was utilized for calculating metabolic activity.</p><p>In Knight&#x000a0;et al.&#x02019;s study, the cutoff value of SUV in order to differentiate between benign and malignant lesions was found to be 2.5 [<xref rid="REF20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. However, later on, a study done by Goo [<xref rid="REF21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] proved that there is a need to increase the SUV max cutoff value due to significant overlapping and compromised distinction between benign and malignant lesions. In our study, at 2.5 SUV max cutoff value, a very low specificity (10%) was observed. It can be attributed to the increased prevalence of inflammatory disease and reactive nodes in our population. Our study supports the results of Goo and meta-analysis by Liu&#x000a0;et al., and it was shown that the SUV cutoff value when increased from 2.5 to 5.5&#x000a0;resultantly raised the sensitivity and specificity rates to 65% and 91%, respectively, using the ROC curve. Similar results depicting a remarkable increase in sensitivity and specificity by increasing the cutoff value to 5.3 were observed in a meta-analysis done by Liu et al. in 2016 [<xref rid="REF21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="REF22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].</p><p>The optimal size cutoff was obtained to be 7.5 mm at which the highest specificity and sensitivity were seen. Most of the malignant nodes had sizes ranging from 7 to 9 mm, whereas benign nodes had relatively smaller sizes. In a meta-analysis conducted by Wang et al., it was revealed that, in addition to metabolic activity, several other factors can also predict nodal metastasis, with size emerging as another important determinant [<xref rid="REF23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Aligning with the findings of our study, among subcentimeter lymph nodes, a significant proportion of metastatic nodes ranged in size from 7 to 9 mm. Likewise, research conducted by Zhou et al. has highlighted a notable correlation between lymph node size and metastasis [<xref rid="REF24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>].</p><p>Although both SUV max and size can independently direct on the presence of lymph node metastasis, combining both to detect malignant lymph nodes can enhance accuracy. As a diagnostic tool, FDG-PET/CT has shown high sensitivity of 95%, moderate specificity of 68%, positive predictive value of 73%, negative predictive value of 94%, and overall accuracy of 80.9%.</p><p>FDG-PET/CT as a combined modality is more sensitive and specific than CT scan alone as depicted in a study done by Yi&#x000a0;et al. In their study, the CT scan detected sensitivity of lymph node metastasis was 81% and accuracy of 85%, while FDG-PET/CT exhibited both greater sensitivity of 96% and accuracy of 93%. Our study findings align closely with Yi&#x000a0;et al., where FDG-PET/CT displayed a sensitivity of 95% [<xref rid="REF25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>].&#x000a0;Similarly, a meta-analysis by Birim et al. has shown that PET/CT is better than CECT scans. PET/CT has a sensitivity of 57%-68%, and CECT scans have a sensitivity of 79%-85%. Similarly, PET/CT has a specificity of 76%-82%, whereas CECT scans have a specificity of 87%-92% [<xref rid="REF26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Sun et al.&#x000a0;demonstrated a wider range of sensitivity (50%-95%) and specificity (82%-99%) on PET scans alone. Yet, when FDG-PET/CT is utilized, it has shown more favorable and accurate staging compared to conventional imaging methods [<xref rid="REF27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>].</p><p>A study by Pfannenberg et al. in 2007 on staging NSCLC patients found FDG-PET/CT to have lower sensitivity (68%) but higher specificity (90%) for detecting nodal metastasis and achieving precise staging, contrasting our study where sensitivity was higher at 95% but specificity lower at 68% [<xref rid="REF28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Conversely, a study conducted by Behzadi et al., discussing the detection of lymph node metastasis in lung cancer, revealed that FDG-PET/CT has high sensitivity but low specificity, with an accuracy of&#x000a0;90%, which falls close to the accuracy of 80.9% found in our study [<xref rid="REF29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>].</p><p>Size and metabolic activity are used as predictors of nodal metastasis in subcentimeter lymph nodes.&#x000a0;Early staging of NSCLC can be done using FDG-PET/CT as this modality provides high specificity as well as a greater positive predictive value in detecting nodal metastasis. For accurate staging and a better treatment approach, there is a potential for FDG-PET/CT to replace conventional imaging modalities like CT and MRI especially when these are used independently.&#x000a0;Based on the results of our study, we propose further research&#x000a0;on a bigger and more diverse population in order to move toward&#x000a0;considering FDG-PET/CT&#x000a0;as the initial imaging modality, before a CT scan, due to its greater sensitivity in detecting subcentimeter lymph node involvement in metastatic disease. This adjustment in the diagnostic approach could enhance early detection and improve treatment planning. There are approximately 19,000 new cases and 14,000 deaths owing to lung cancer annually in Pakistan [<xref rid="REF30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. This study marks an important leap toward early detection which is crucial due to its time-sensitive nature for patients with subcentimeter metastasis of lung CA and subsequent management of the disease, within the country.</p><p>It is equally important to address notable limitations like increased occurrence of false-positive rates. Moreover, with the setting of this study being Pakistan, challenges like limited access to advanced imaging and trained staff, high cost of this procedure, variable access to healthcare facilities, and difficulty in diagnosing diseases like tuberculosis being prevalent, were faced. However, our study's outcomes in Pakistan can be optimized by taking some steps like possible future collaboration with international institutions for access to advance technology, specialized diagnostic training for more local healthcare professionals, ensuring the implementation of strict quality control measures, and educating the population. These steps are pivotal in overcoming the abovementioned challenges and ensuring our study's success in contributing valuable insights to lung cancer management in Pakistan.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>FDG-PET/CT is a noninvasive imaging modality that can be used in the detection of subcentimeter metastatic lymph node involvement in lung CA. It has high sensitivity and accuracy but a low specificity rate to detect nodal involvement in lung CA patients. The high false-positive rates are mainly due to the increased prevalence of endemic lung infectious diseases.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group content-type="conflict"><title>Disclosures</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Human subjects:</bold> Consent for treatment and open access publication was obtained or waived by all participants in this study. Institutional Review Board of Shaukat Khanum Memorial Cancer Hospital and Research Center issued approval EX-31-01-20-02. IRB considers the fact that all clinical information to be studied in this study already exists in medical/hospital records.
IRB further considers that this information will be recorded on data extraction sheet in such a manner that subjects cannot be identified directly or indirectly through the use of codes. On the basis of the above, IRB grants you exemption for the abovementioned research study.</p><p><bold>Animal subjects:</bold> All authors have confirmed that this study did not involve animal subjects or tissue.</p><p><bold>Conflicts of interest:</bold> In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following:</p><p><bold>Payment/services info:</bold> All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work.</p><p><bold>Financial relationships:</bold> All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work.</p><p><bold>Other relationships:</bold> All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="other"><title>Author Contributions</title><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Concept and design:</bold>&#x000a0; Hira Majied, Muhammad Omer Altaf , Hamd Zahra, Hira Farooq, Imran Khalid Niazi</p><p><bold>Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data:</bold>&#x000a0; Hira Majied, Muhammad Omer Altaf , Hamd Zahra, Hira Farooq, Imran Khalid Niazi</p><p><bold>Drafting of the manuscript:</bold>&#x000a0; Hira Majied, Hamd Zahra, Hira Farooq</p><p><bold>Critical review of the manuscript for important intellectual content:</bold>&#x000a0; Hira Majied, Muhammad Omer Altaf , Hamd Zahra, Hira Farooq, Imran Khalid Niazi</p><p><bold>Supervision:</bold>&#x000a0; Muhammad Omer Altaf , Imran Khalid Niazi</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="REF1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Cancer statistics, 2018</article-title><source>CA Cancer J Clin</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Siegel</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jemal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><volume>68</volume><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29313949</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>Cancer</article-title><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">
<month>7</month>
<year>2024</year>
</date-in-citation><year>2018</year><uri xlink:href="https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/cancer">https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/cancer</uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Epidemiology of lung cancer: diagnosis and management of lung cancer, 3rd ed. American College of Chest Physicians. Evidence-based clinical practice guidelines</article-title><source>Chest</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Alberg</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brock</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Samet</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Spivack</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>0</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><volume>143</volume><year>2013</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Tobacco smoke carcinogens and lung cancer</article-title><source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Hecht</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>1194</fpage><lpage>1210</lpage><volume>91</volume><year>1999</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10413421</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Mediastinoscopy might not be necessary in patients with non-small cell lung cancer with mediastinal lymph nodes having a maximum standardized uptake value of less than 5.3</article-title><source>J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Redwine</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Abella</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lown</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Follette</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>615</fpage><lpage>619</lpage><volume>135</volume><year>2008</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18329480</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>ESTS guidelines for preoperative lymph node staging for non-small cell lung cancer</article-title><source>Eur J Cardiothorac Surg</source><person-group>
<name><surname>De Leyn</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lardinois</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Van Schil</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><volume>32</volume><year>2007</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17448671</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Bronchogenic carcinoma: analysis of staging in the mediastinum with CT by correlative lymph node mapping and sampling</article-title><source>Radiology</source><person-group>
<name><surname>McLoud</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bourgouin</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>319</fpage><lpage>323</lpage><volume>182</volume><year>1992</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1732943</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Preoperative staging of non-small-cell carcinoma of the lung: imaging methods</article-title><source>AJR Am J Roentgenol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Quint</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wahl</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Glazer</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>1349</fpage><lpage>1359</lpage><volume>164</volume><year>1995</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7754872</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Noninvasive staging of non-small cell lung cancer: a review of the current evidence</article-title><source>Chest</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Toloza</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Harpole</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McCrory</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>137</fpage><lpage>146</lpage><volume>123</volume><year>2003</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>The role of 11C-choline positron emission tomography-computed tomography and videomediastinoscopy in the evaluation of diseases of middle mediastinum</article-title><source>Chin Med J</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>ZM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>QW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>SZ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>634</fpage><lpage>639</lpage><volume>119</volume><year>2006</year><uri xlink:href="https://journals.lww.com/cmj/fulltext/2006/04020/the_role_of_11c_choline_positron_emission.4.aspx">https://journals.lww.com/cmj/fulltext/2006/04020/the_role_of_11c_choline_positron_emission.4.aspx</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16635407</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Imaging recommendations for diagnosis, staging and management of lung cancer</article-title><source>Ind J Med Paediatr Oncol </source><person-group>
<name><surname>Irodi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bhalla</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vimala</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>193</lpage><volume>44</volume><year>2023</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>GLOBOCAN 2012, cancer incidence and mortality worldwide in 2012 v1.0: IARC CancerBase no. 11</article-title><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">
<month>6</month>
<year>2024</year>
</date-in-citation><person-group>
<name><surname>Ferlay</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Soerjomataram</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ervik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><year>2012</year><uri xlink:href="https://publications.iarc.fr/Databases/Iarc-Cancerbases/GLOBOCAN-2012-Estimated-Cancer-Incidence-Mortality-And-Prevalence-Worldwide-In-2012-V1.0-2012">https://publications.iarc.fr/Databases/Iarc-Cancerbases/GLOBOCAN-2012-Estimated-Cancer-Incidence-Mortality-And-Prevalence-Worldwide-In-2012-V1.0-2012 </uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Sex differences in lung cancer</article-title><source>Cancers (Basel)</source><person-group>
<name><surname>May</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shows</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nana-Sinkam</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Landry</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>3111</fpage><volume>15</volume><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37370722</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Lung cancer screening beyond low-dose computed tomography: the role of novel biomarkers</article-title><source>Lung</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Hasan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kavuru</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>639</fpage><lpage>648</lpage><volume>192</volume><year>2014</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25108403</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>The size of mediastinal lymph nodes and its relation with metastatic involvement: a meta-analysis</article-title><source>Eur J Cardiothorac Surg</source><person-group>
<name><surname>de Langen</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Raijmakers</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Riphagen</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hoekstra</surname><given-names>OS</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>26</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><volume>29</volume><year>2006</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16337397</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>The additional value of FDG PET imaging for distinguishing N0 or N1 from N2 stage in preoperative staging of non-small cell lung cancer in region where the prevalence of inflammatory lung disease is high</article-title><source>Clin Nucl Med</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Turkmen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sonmezoglu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Toker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>607</fpage><lpage>612</lpage><volume>32</volume><year>2007</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17667432</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Clinical significance of combined assessment of the maximum standardized uptake value of F-18 FDG PET with nodal size in the diagnosis of cervical lymph node metastasis of oral squamous cell carcinoma</article-title><source>Acad Radiol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Matsubara</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kawano</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chikui</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>708</fpage><lpage>717</lpage><volume>19</volume><year>2012</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22484437</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Ratio of the maximum standardized uptake value on FDG-PET of the mediastinal (N2) lymph nodes to the primary tumor may be a universal predictor of nodal malignancy in patients with nonsmall-cell lung cancer</article-title><source>Ann Thorac Surg</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Cerfolio</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bryant</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>1826</fpage><lpage>1830</lpage><volume>83</volume><year>2007</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17462407</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Molecular imaging of cancer with positron emission tomography</article-title><source>Nat Rev Cancer</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Gambhir</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>683</fpage><lpage>693</lpage><volume>2</volume><year>2002</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12209157</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Evaluation of pulmonary lesions with FDG-PET: comparison of findings in patients with and without a history of prior malignancy</article-title><source>Chest</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Delbeke</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sandler</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>982</fpage><lpage>988</lpage><volume>109</volume><year>1996</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8635381</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Pulmonary tuberculoma evaluated by means of FDG PET: findings in 10 cases</article-title><source>Radiology</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Goo</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Im</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Do</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yeo</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>117</fpage><lpage>121</lpage><volume>216</volume><year>2000</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10887236</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Prognostic value of 18F-FDG PET/CT in surgical non-small cell lung cancer: a meta-analysis</article-title><source>PloS one</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>146</fpage><lpage>195</lpage><volume>11</volume><year>2016</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Negative predictive value of positron emission tomography and computed tomography for stage T1-2N0 non-small-cell lung cancer: a meta-analysis</article-title><source>Clin Lung Cancer</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Welch</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>89</lpage><volume>13</volume><year>2012</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22056226</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Potential clinical value of PET/CT in predicting occult nodal metastasis in T1-T2N0M0 lung cancer patients staged by PET/CT</article-title><source>Oncotarget</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>82437</fpage><lpage>82445</lpage><volume>8</volume><year>2017</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29137276</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Tissue characterization of solitary pulmonary nodule: comparative study between helical dynamic CT and integrated PET/CT</article-title><source>J Nucl Med</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>443</fpage><lpage>450</lpage><volume>1</volume><year>2006</year><uri xlink:href="https://jnm.snmjournals.org/content/47/3/443.long">https://jnm.snmjournals.org/content/47/3/443.long</uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Meta-analysis of positron emission tomographic and computed tomographic imaging in detecting mediastinal lymph node metastases in nonsmall cell lung cancer</article-title><source>Ann Thorac Surg</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Birim</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kappetein</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stijnen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bogers</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>375</fpage><lpage>382</lpage><volume>79</volume><year>2005</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15620991</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>(18)FDG-PET/CT for the detection of regional nodal metastasis in patients with head and neck cancer: a meta-analysis</article-title><source>Oral Oncol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>314</fpage><lpage>320</lpage><volume>51</volume><year>2015</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25619735</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Low dose non-enhanced CT versus standard dose contrast-enhanced CT in combined PET/CT protocols for staging and therapy planning in non-small cell lung cancer</article-title><source>Eur J Nucl Med Mol Imaging</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Pfannenberg</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aschoff</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brechtel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>36</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><volume>34</volume><year>2007</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16896664</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>The role of positron emission tomography in the management of non-small cell lung cancer</article-title><source>Can J Surg</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Behzadi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ung</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Deschamps</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>235</fpage><lpage>242</lpage><volume>52</volume><year>2009</year><uri xlink:href="https://www.canjsurg.ca/content/52/3/235">https://www.canjsurg.ca/content/52/3/235</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19503669</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>The burden of cancer, government strategic policies, and challenges in Pakistan: a comprehensive review</article-title><source>Front Nutr</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Manzoor</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>940514</fpage><volume>9</volume><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35938114</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>