<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="abstract"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Eur Psychiatry</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Eur Psychiatry</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">EPA</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>European Psychiatry</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0924-9338</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1778-3585</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11862702</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1192/j.eurpsy.2024.1426</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="other">EPV0798</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S0924933824014263</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Abstract</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="section"><subject>e-Poster Viewing</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Spirituality is Associated with Immune Parameters and Disease Activity in Primary Sj&#x000f6;gren&#x02019;s Syndrome: A Cross-Sectional Study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>M&#x000f3;dis</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3141" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff3142" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor1276" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Aradi</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3143" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Horv&#x000e1;th</surname><given-names>F. I.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3143" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pik&#x000f3;</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3144" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff3145" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sz&#x000e1;nt&#x000f3;</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3143" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bug&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3141" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff3141"><sup>1</sup>Faculty of Medicine, Department of Behavioural Sciences, <institution>University of Debrecen</institution>, <city>Debrecen</city></aff><aff id="aff3142"><sup>2</sup><institution>S&#x000e1;ntha K&#x000e1;lm&#x000e1;n Member Hospital, Szabolcs Szatm&#x000e1;r Bereg County Teaching Hospital</institution>, <city>Nagyk&#x000e1;ll&#x000f3;</city></aff><aff id="aff3143"><sup>3</sup>Faculty of Medicine, Department of Internal Medicine, Division of Clinical Immunology</aff><aff id="aff3144"><sup>4</sup>Faculty of Medicine, Department of Public Health and Epidemiology, <institution>University of Debrecen</institution>, <city>Debrecen</city></aff><aff id="aff3145"><sup>5</sup>National Laboratory for Health Security, Center for Epidemiology and Surveillance, <institution>Semmelweis University</institution>, <city>Budapest</city>, <country>Hungary</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1276"><label>*</label>Corresponding author.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="collection" iso-8601-date="2024-04"><month>4</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>67</volume><issue seq="1401">Suppl 1</issue><issue-title content-type="special_issue">Abstracts of the 32nd European Congress of Psychiatry</issue-title><fpage>S685</fpage><lpage>S686</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2024</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Author(s)</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article, distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution licence (<uri xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</uri>), which permits unrestricted re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="S0924933824014263a.pdf"/><abstract><sec id="sec7670"><title>Introduction</title><p>
The role of spirituality in health and disease is a complex and emerging area of research. Incorporating spirituality into the bio-psycho-social model of health and disease leading to the bio-psycho-social-spiritual model provides a more comprehensive framework. In this context, chronic disorders like primary Sj&#x000f6;gren&#x02019;s syndrome (pSS) are of interest due to their intricate interactions between biological, psychological, and spiritual factors.</p></sec><sec id="sec7671"><title>Objectives</title><p>To study possible relationships between spirituality, immune parameters, and disease activity in pSS patients.</p></sec><sec id="sec7672"><title>Methods</title><p>
Patient recruitment for the study took place at the Autoimmune Sj&#x000f6;gren specialty clinic, University of Debrecen, resulting in 112 patients. Assessing spirituality of the patients happened through 4 direct questions and the Sprituality Transcendence Scale (24 items). Besides, clinical data of the patients were involved in the study including blood cell counts, rheumatoid factor, immunoglobulin G, Sj&#x000f6;gren-specific autoantibodies and disease activity scores (semi-objective and patient reported,). The statistical analysis was conducted applying group comparisons between spiritual and non-spiritual groups, and linear and logistic regression analyses adjusted for sex, age, disease duration, settlement type, education, living in partnership and smoking. Out of the 112 patients 4 gave incomplete response, and therefore got excluded from the analysis, resulting in a total sample size of 108.</p></sec><sec id="sec7673"><title>Results</title><p>Semi-objective disease activity score (ESSDAI) and perceived vaginal dryness was significantly lower in the non-spiritual group. Spirituality was proven as a significant predictor of anti-SSB autoantibody serum activity and ESSDAI, while engaging in prayer/meditation and its duration predicted significantly anti-SSA autoantibody serum activity, perceived skin and tracheal dryness. Concerning logistic regression analysis, we found that an increase of one unit in spirituality reduces the probability with 81.6% of having a detectable, semi-objective disease activity at all. Significant associations were found between the duration of prayer/meditation and both semi-objective and patient reported disease activity scores and autoantibody anti-SSB with an inverse ratio based on logistic regression model.</p></sec><sec id="sec7674"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Spirituality is associated with immune parameters and disease activity in pSS. Patients with spiritual attitude are less likely to have increased disease activity. Besides being spiritual, engagement in individual spiritual activities, such as prayer/meditation has beneficial disease modifying effect. These changes are supposedly due to psychoneuroimmunological pathways. In addition to the biologically measurable variables, the alleviation and aggravation of perceived symptoms (e.g. dryness) are important outcomes of spiritual engagement and practice.</p></sec><sec id="sec7675"><title>Disclosure of Interest</title><p>None Declared</p></sec></abstract><counts><page-count count="2"/></counts></article-meta></front></article>