<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" id="cpr13785" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cell Prolif</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cell Prolif</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.1111/(ISSN)1365-2184</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CPR</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cell Proliferation</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0960-7722</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1365-2184</issn><publisher><publisher-name>John Wiley and Sons Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Hoboken</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39667912</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12099224</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/cpr.13785</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">CPR13785</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="other">Cellprol-10663-24.R1</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A Chemical Reprogramming Approach Efficiently Producing Human Retinal Pigment Epithelium Cells for Retinal Disease Therapies</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="cpr13785-cr-0001" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Ke</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0009-0007-5364-2022</contrib-id><xref rid="cpr13785-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="cpr13785-cr-0002" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Yanqiu</given-names></name><xref rid="cpr13785-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="cpr13785-cr-0003" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>An</surname><given-names>Qi</given-names></name><xref rid="cpr13785-aff-0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="cpr13785-cr-0004" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>Hengjing</given-names></name><xref rid="cpr13785-aff-0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="cpr13785-cr-0005" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Defu</given-names></name><xref rid="cpr13785-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="cpr13785-cr-0006" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Xuri</given-names></name><xref rid="cpr13785-aff-0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="cpr13785-cr-0007" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Suo</surname><given-names>Lingge</given-names></name><xref rid="cpr13785-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="cpr13785-cr-0008" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Chun</given-names></name><xref rid="cpr13785-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cpr13785-aff-0004" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref><address><email>zhangc1@yahoo.com</email></address></contrib><contrib id="cpr13785-cr-0009" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>Xuran</given-names></name><xref rid="cpr13785-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><address><email>xuran8045@163.com</email></address></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="cpr13785-aff-0001">
<label>
<sup>1</sup>
</label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Department of Ophthalmology</named-content>
<institution>Peking University Third Hospital, Beijing Key Laboratory of Restoration of Damaged Ocular Nerve</institution>
<city>Beijing</city>
<country country="CN">China</country>
</aff><aff id="cpr13785-aff-0002">
<label>
<sup>2</sup>
</label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Department of Ophthalmology</named-content>
<institution>The Fifth Affiliated Hospital of Zhengzhou University</institution>
<city>Zhengzhou</city>
<named-content content-type="country-part">Henan</named-content>
<country country="CN">China</country>
</aff><aff id="cpr13785-aff-0003">
<label>
<sup>3</sup>
</label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">State Key Laboratory of Ophthalmology, Zhongshan Ophthalmic Center</named-content>
<institution>Sun Yat&#x02010;Sen University, Guangdong Provincial Key Laboratory of Ophthalmology Visual Science</institution>
<city>Guangzhou</city>
<named-content content-type="country-part">Guangdong</named-content>
<country country="CN">China</country>
</aff><aff id="cpr13785-aff-0004">
<label>
<sup>4</sup>
</label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Beijing Visual Science and Translational Eye Research Institute (BERI), Beijing Tsinghua Changgung Hospital</named-content>
<institution>Tsinghua Medicine, Tsinghua University</institution>
<city>Beijing</city>
<country country="CN">China</country>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="correspondenceTo">
<label>*</label>
<bold>Correspondence:</bold>
<break/>
Chun Zhang (<email>zhangc1@yahoo.com</email>)<break/>
Xuran Dong (<email>xuran8045@163.com</email>)<break/>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>58</volume><issue seq="50">5</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/cpr.v58.5</issue-id><elocation-id>e13785</elocation-id><history>
<date date-type="rev-recd"><day>06</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date>
<date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date>
</history><permissions><!--&#x000a9; 2025 John Wiley & Sons Ltd--><copyright-statement content-type="article-copyright">&#x000a9; 2024 The Author(s). <italic toggle="yes">Cell Proliferation</italic> published by Beijing Institute for Stem Cell and Regenerative Medicine and John Wiley &#x00026; Sons Ltd.</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link> License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="file:CPR-58-e13785.pdf"/><abstract><title>ABSTRACT</title><p>Human induced pluripotent stem cells (hiPSCs) represent a promising cell source for generating functional cells suitable for clinical therapeutic applications, particularly in the context of autologous cell therapies. However, the production of hiPSCs through genetic manipulation, especially involving oncogenes, may raise safety concerns. Furthermore, the complexity and high costs associated with hiPSCs generation have hindered their broad clinical use. In this study, we utilised a recently developed chemical reprogramming method in conjunction with a guided differentiation protocol, introducing a chemically defined strategy for generating functional human retinal pigment epithelium (RPE) cells from adipose tissue, bypassing conventional hiPSCs generation challenges. By utilising small molecule&#x02010;based chemical cocktails, we reprogrammed somatic adipose cells into human chemically induced pluripotent stem cells (hCiPSCs) in a safer and more streamlined manner, entirely free from gene manipulation. Subsequent differentiation of hCiPSCs into functional RPE cells demonstrated their capability for secretion and phagocytosis, emphasising their vital role in maintaining retinal homeostasis and underscoring their therapeutic potential. Our findings highlight the transformative potential of hCiPSCs as a safer, more efficient option for personalised cell therapies, with applications extending beyond ocular disease to a wide range of medical conditions.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="graphical"><p>In this study, we combined a recently reported chemical reprogramming method alongside a guided differentiation approach, introducing a chemically defined scheme for generating functional human retinal pigment epithelium cells from adipose tissue.<boxed-text position="anchor" content-type="graphic" id="cpr13785-blkfxd-0001"><graphic xlink:href="CPR-58-e13785-g003.jpg" position="anchor" id="jats-graphic-1"/></boxed-text>
</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-generated"><kwd id="cpr13785-kwd-0001">cell therapies</kwd><kwd id="cpr13785-kwd-0002">chemically induced pluripotent stem cells</kwd><kwd id="cpr13785-kwd-0003">differentiation</kwd><kwd id="cpr13785-kwd-0004">reprogramming</kwd><kwd id="cpr13785-kwd-0005">retinal diseases</kwd><kwd id="cpr13785-kwd-0006">retinal pigment epithelium</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="funding-0001"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>National Key Research and Development Program of China
</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100012166</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>2023YFC2506100</award-id></award-group><award-group id="funding-0002"><funding-source>Peking University Clinical Scientist Training Program</funding-source><award-id>BMU2023PYJH004</award-id></award-group><award-group id="funding-0003"><funding-source>Clinical Medicine Plus X &#x02010; Young Scholars Project of Peking University, the Fundamental Research Funds for the Central Universities</funding-source><award-id>PKU2024LCXQ013</award-id></award-group><award-group id="funding-0004"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>National Natural Science Foundation of China
</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100001809</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>82000859</award-id><award-id>82201180</award-id></award-group><award-group id="funding-0005"><funding-source>The Changping Key Research Project of the Beijing Natural Science Foundation Program</funding-source><award-id>L234016</award-id></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="5"/><table-count count="0"/><page-count count="13"/><word-count count="7400"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>source-schema-version-number</meta-name><meta-value>2.0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>May 2025</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>details-of-publishers-convertor</meta-name><meta-value>Converter:WILEY_ML3GV2_TO_JATSPMC version:6.5.6 mode:remove_FC converted:23.05.2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><fn-group id="cpr13785-ntgp-0001"><fn fn-type="funding" id="cpr13785-note-0001"><p>
<bold>Funding:</bold> This study was funded by National Key R&#x00026;D Program of China (2023YFC2506100), Peking University Clinical Scientist Training Program (BMU2023PYJH004), and Clinical Medicine Plus X&#x02014;Young Scholars Project of Peking University, the Fundamental Research Funds for the Central Universities (PKU2024LCXQ013). The study was also supported by National Natural Science Foundation of China (82000859, 82201180) and the Changping Key Research Project of the Beijing Natural Science Foundation Program (L234016).</p></fn><fn fn-type="equal" id="cpr13785-note-0002"><p>Ke Zhang and Yanqiu Wang contributed equally to this article.</p></fn></fn-group></notes></front><body id="cpr13785-body-0001"><sec id="cpr13785-sec-0001"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p>Pluripotent stem cells, including embryonic stem cells (ESCs) and induced pluripotent stem cells (iPSCs), possess an unlimited capacity for proliferation and can differentiate into a wide array of functional cell types, making them highly valuable for cell therapy applications [<xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Compared with human ESCs (hESCs) derived from human embryos, human iPSCs (hiPSCs) can be generated from somatic cells, circumventing the ethical issues raised by hESCs while allowing for the generation of autologous iPSCs. This enables the development of personalised cell therapies without the requirement for immunosuppressive treatment [<xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Consequently, the transplantation of autologous iPSC&#x02010;derived functional cells has emerged as a novel therapeutic strategy for various diseases.</p><p>Among various organs, the eye stands out as a major target for hiPSC&#x02010;based cell therapies due to the relatively small number of cells required to achieve therapeutic effects. Furthermore, the non&#x02010;invasive monitoring and direct observation of the engraftment in the eye allow for early detection of potential abnormalities, making it an ideal site for therapeutic interventions. Age&#x02010;related macular degeneration (AMD), the leading cause of central vision loss worldwide, represents a key area of focus in ocular disease research [<xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. The pathophysiology of AMD is characterised by the dysfunction and irreversible loss of retinal pigment epithelium (RPE) cells, which are essential for maintaining the subretinal microenvironment [<xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. As such, the replacement of damaged RPE cells or tissues has emerged as a promising therapeutic strategy for AMD. Over the past decade, RPE cells have garnered significant attention in clinical studies, underscoring their pivotal role in ocular disease research [<xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Notably, a clinical trial by RIKEN in 2013 is a global milestone as the first to investigate autologous hiPSC&#x02010;RPE cell transplantation, highlighting the potential of hiPSC&#x02010;based personalised medicine in clinical settings [<xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. However, the generation of hiPSCs through genetic manipulation, especially involving oncogenes, has raised safety concerns. In RIKEN's study, transplantation was discontinued for the second patient due to genetic abnormalities detected in their hiPSCs [<xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Furthermore, the complex, time&#x02010;consuming and costly process of generating clinical&#x02010;grade autologous hiPSCs restricts their large&#x02010;scale production and widespread clinical application, emphasising the need for technological innovations that can address these practical issues [<xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].</p><p>Recent advances in chemical reprogramming methods offer a promising alternative to traditional hiPSC techniques [<xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The use of human chemically induced pluripotent stem cells (hCiPSCs) may address the safety concerns associated with genetic reprogramming. Unlike transgenic methods, small molecules used in chemical reprogramming do not integrate into the genome [<xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], thereby reducing the risk of genetic instability. Furthermore, these molecules are relatively easy to manufacture, standardise and are cost&#x02010;effective, making them more suitable for large&#x02010;scale clinical applications [<xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. These advantages suggest that hCiPSC technology holds significant promise for the efficient and safe production of autologous iPSCs for therapeutic purposes, particularly in clinical settings. Specifically, RPE cells generated via chemically induced pluripotency may be the promising alternative that bypasses the challenges associated with conventional hiPSCs&#x02010;derived RPE cell generation.</p><p>In this study, we aimed to generate hiPSCs from human somatic adipose tissue through chemical reprogramming approach and to efficiently differentiate them into functional RPE cells. The hCiPSC&#x02010;derived RPE cells exhibited distinct RPE characteristics in terms of morphology, gene expression patterns and functionality, highlighting their potential for future clinical applications.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="cpr13785-sec-0002"><label>2</label><title>Methods</title><sec id="cpr13785-sec-0003"><label>2.1</label><title>Cell Culture</title><p>Human adult adipose tissue&#x02010;derived stromal cells (hADSCs) were selected as the target cells for reprogramming, as they offer higher reprogramming efficiency, shorter induction time and reduced heterogeneity compared to fibroblasts [<xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The cells were obtained from donated adipose tissue with informed consent from participants at Peking University Third Hospital. The tissue was digested using a 2&#x02009;mg/mL Collagenase IV (Solarbio, Beijing, China) at 37&#x000b0;C for 1&#x02009;h, followed by thorough dilution with phosphate&#x02010;buffered saline (PBS) (AQ, Beijing, China). The cell suspension was centrifuged at 400&#x02009;<italic toggle="yes">g</italic> for 5&#x02009;min, after which the cells were resuspended in mesenchymal stem cell growth medium (Promo cell, Heidelberg, Germany) for culture. Within 3&#x02013;5&#x02009;days, hADSCs reached full confluence and were ready for reprogramming into hCiPSCs.</p><p>Adult retinal pigment epithelial cell line&#x02010;19 (ARPE&#x02010;19) was kindly provided by Li from Peking University Third Hospital, while human retinal pigment epithelium (hRPE) cells were a generous gift from Ma at the Affiliated Eye Hospital, Wenzhou Medical University.</p></sec><sec id="cpr13785-sec-0004"><label>2.2</label><title>Reprogramming of <styled-content style="fixed-case" toggle="no">hADSCs</styled-content> to <styled-content style="fixed-case" toggle="no">hCiPSCs</styled-content>
</title><p>We followed a detailed three&#x02010;stage chemical reprogramming protocol [<xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] to reprogram the hADSCs. For optimal results, 12&#x02010;well plates were seeded with 1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>4</sup> cells per well. In the first stage, Stage I induction medium was used for 8&#x02013;10&#x02009;days, until the monolayer of epithelial cells approached full confluence (~100%). Stage II induction medium was then used for 12&#x02009;days, followed by Stage III induction medium during the final 12&#x02010;day stage. At this point, wells containing colonies suitable for passage (passage ratio: 1:12) were selected. Typically, hCiPSCs colonies expanded over a period of 12&#x02009;days, after which they were carefully harvested using a glass needle and seeded on the Matrigel (Corning, NY, USA)&#x02010;coated culture plates. Cell cultivation was maintained using mTeSR Plus medium (Stemcell Technologies, Vancouver, BC, Canada).</p></sec><sec id="cpr13785-sec-0005"><label>2.3</label><title>
<styled-content style="fixed-case" toggle="no">RPE</styled-content> Differentiation</title><p>The directed differentiation of hCiPSCs into RPE cells followed a protocol largely consistent with that of Ye et&#x000a0;al. [<xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Initially, hCiPSCs were treated with Accutase (Stemcell Technologies, Vancouver, BC, Canada) for 5&#x02009;min and then plated onto Martrigel (Corning, NY, USA)&#x02010;coated 12&#x02010;well culture plates at a density of 4.0&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>4</sup> cells per well. During the first 17&#x02009;days of differentiation, the cells were cultured in IMDM/Ham's F12 medium (1:1) (Gibco, CA, USA) containing 10&#x02009;&#x003bc;M Y&#x02010;27632 (Selleck, Houston, USA), 10% KnockOut Serum Replacement (Gibco, CA, USA), 1% Chemically Defined Lipid Concentrate (Gibco, CA, USA), 2&#x02009;mM&#x02009;L&#x02010;glutamine (Gibco, CA, USA), 10&#x02009;mM nicotinamide (Merck, NJ, USA). For the initial 6&#x02009;days, the medium was further supplemented with 100&#x02009;nM LDN193189 (MedChemExpress, NJ, USA), 500&#x02009;nM A&#x02010;83&#x02010;01 (Selleck, Houston, USA), 1&#x02009;&#x003bc;M IWR&#x02010;1&#x02010;endo (MedChemExpress, NJ, USA). From days 6 to 11, 3&#x02009;&#x003bc;M CHIR99021 (MedChemExpress, NJ, USA) and 2&#x02009;&#x003bc;M SU5402 (MedChemExpress, NJ, USA) were added to the medium. From days 18 to 23, the medium was changed to DMEM/F12 supplemented 10% KnockOut Serum Replacement (Gibco, CA, USA), 1% N2 supplement (Gibco, CA, USA), 2&#x02009;mM Glutamax (Gibco, CA, USA) and 10&#x02009;mM nicotinamide (Merck, NJ, USA). After 24&#x02009;days, for further maturation of hCiPSCs&#x02010;derived RPE cells, an RPE maintenance medium containing 67% high&#x02010;glucose DMEM (Gibco, CA, USA), 29% Ham's F12 (Gibco, CA, USA), 2% B27 supplement minus vitamin A (Gibco, CA, USA), 2&#x02009;mM Glutamax (Gibco, CA, USA) was used. Culture medium was changed every day.</p><p>During the differentiation process, we noticed that the original culture wells contained a relatively low proportion of pigment cells. To enhance the purity of hCiPSCs&#x02010;RPE cells, we employed a mechanical separation technique using glass needles to isolate pigmented cell clusters as they became clearly visible, in contrast to the direct digestion and passaging methods mentioned in the original protocol. Once isolated, the pigment cells were digested into single cells using 0.25% Trypsin&#x02013;EDTA (Gibco, CA, USA) for 15&#x02009;min and replated onto 12&#x02010;well culture plates coated with Matrigel (Corning, NY, USA). For further cultivation, RPE growing medium containing Ham's F12 (Gibco, CA, USA), 10% fetal bovine serum (Gibco, CA, USA), 2&#x02009;mM Glutamax (Gibco, CA, USA) was used. After 14&#x02009;days, the medium was changed to an RPE maintenance medium with 10&#x02009;ng/mL basic fibroblast growth factor (R&#x00026;D Systems, MN, USA) and 0.5&#x02009;&#x003bc;M SB431542 (MedChemExpress, NJ, USA).</p></sec><sec id="cpr13785-sec-0006"><label>2.4</label><title>Embryoid Body Formation</title><p>For embryoid bodies (EBs) formation, hCiPSCs were digested as small clumps by ReLeSR (Stemcell Technologies, Vancouver, BC, Canada) and cultured in ultra&#x02010;low attachment culture plates with mTeSR Plus Medium (Stemcell Technologies, Vancouver, BC, Canada) for 1&#x02009;day, and then transformed into differentiation medium for 16&#x02009;days. The differentiation medium was consisted of high&#x02010;glucose DMEM (Gibco, CA, USA) supplemented with 20% FBS (Gibco, CA, USA) and 1% penicillin&#x02013;streptomycin (Gibco, CA, USA). EBs were then collected and attached into culture plates with pre&#x02010;incubated Matrigel (Corning, NY, USA) for 6&#x02009;days in the same medium, fixed and detected using immunostaining analysis.</p></sec><sec id="cpr13785-sec-0007"><label>2.5</label><title>Teratoma Formation</title><p>hCiPSC lines were dissociated into a single&#x02010;cell suspension using ReleSR (Stemcell Technologies, Vancouver, BC, Canada) and subsequently resuspended in mTeSR Plus medium (Stemcell Technologies, Vancouver, BC, Canada) for cell counting. Approximately 2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>6</sup> hCiPSCs were then resuspended in pre&#x02010;cooled 200&#x02009;&#x003bc;L Matrigel (Corning, NY, USA) and subcutaneously injected into the hind limbs of male immunodeficient NPG mice (Vitalstar Biotechnology, Beijing) aged 2&#x02013;3&#x02009;months (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3 for one cell line). Following recovery, the mice were monitored biweekly for the development of teratomas, which typically occurred with 6&#x02013;8&#x02009;weeks. Upon teratomas reached a diameter of approximately 2&#x02009;cm, the mice were euthanised humanely using carbon dioxide asphyxiation. The subcutaneous teratomas were subsequently excised, fixed in 10% neutral buffered formalin, and paraffin&#x02010;embedded. Thin paraffin sections (5&#x02009;&#x003bc;m) were prepared, stained with haematoxylin and eosin (H&#x00026;E) and evaluated using light microscopy (Olympus BX43, Tokyo, Japan) equipped with an attached DP22 digital camera. All animal experiments were approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee of Peking University and performed according to the Animal Protection Guidelines of Peking University. All of the work has been reported in line with the ARRIVE guidelines 2.0.</p></sec><sec id="cpr13785-sec-0008"><label>2.6</label><title>Reverse Transcription&#x02014;Quantitative Polymerase Chain Reaction Analysis</title><p>Total RNA was extracted using the Direct&#x02010;zol RNA MiniPrep Kit (Zymo Research, CA, USA). cDNA was synthesis was performed using 1.5&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of total RNA with the TransScript First&#x02010;Strand cDNA Synthesis SuperMix (TransGen Biotech, Beijing, China). Reverse transcription&#x02013;quantitative polymerase chain reaction (RT&#x02010;qPCR) was conducted with 2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;S6 SYBR Premix EsTaq plus (QIAGEN, Dusseldorf, Germany) on the CFX Connect Real&#x02010;Time System (Bio&#x02010;Rad). Gene expression data were analysed using the 2<sup>&#x02212;&#x00394;&#x00394;Ct</sup> method, with <italic toggle="yes">GAPDH</italic> serving as the internal for normalisation. The primer sequences used in this study are listed in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="cpr13785-supitem-0002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="cpr13785-sec-0009"><label>2.7</label><title>Immunofluorescence</title><p>For immunofluorescence staining, cells were fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde (biosharp, Beijing, China) at room temperature for 30&#x02009;min, followed by blocking in PBS (AQ, Beijing, China) containing 0.1% Triton X&#x02010;100 (Sigma&#x02010;Aldrich, MO, USA) and 2% donkey serum (Jackson, Pennsylvania, USA) at 37&#x000b0;C for 1&#x02009;h. Cells were then incubated overnight at 4&#x000b0;C with primary antibodies in the same buffer. After washing three times with <bold>Dulbecco</bold> phosphate&#x02010;buffered saline (DPBS) (Gibco, CA, USA), secondary antibodies were supplied in PBS (AQ, Beijing, China) containing 2% donkey serum (Jackson, Pennsylvania, USA) for 1&#x02009;h at room temperature. Nuclei were counterstained with DAPI (Roche, Basel, Switzerland). Detailed information on the antibodies is provided in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="cpr13785-supitem-0002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="cpr13785-sec-0010"><label>2.8</label><title>Flow Cytometry</title><p>Cells were harvested using Accutase (Merck, NJ, USA) at 37&#x000b0;C for 5&#x02013;10&#x02009;min and filtered through 40&#x02009;&#x003bc;m cell strainers to obtain single&#x02010;cell suspensions. Flow cytometry was performed on a CytoFLEX S system (Beckman Coulter). Antibody information is detailed in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="cpr13785-supitem-0002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="cpr13785-sec-0011"><label>2.9</label><title>Karyotype Analysis</title><p>The karyotype (chromosomal G&#x02010;band) analysis was outsourced to Beijing Jiaen Hospital, using standard protocols for high&#x02010;resolution G&#x02010;banding (400G&#x02013;500G). Chromosomal analysis was conducted using CytoVision (Leica), with at least 20 metaphases examined to assess the chromosome number and any structural abnormalities.</p></sec><sec id="cpr13785-sec-0012"><label>2.10</label><title>
<styled-content style="fixed-case" toggle="no">STR</styled-content> Analysis</title><p>Short&#x02010;tandem repeat (STR) analysis was conducted by Beijing Microread Genetics. The genomic deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) was amplified using the STR Multi&#x02010;amplification Kit (Microreader 21 ID System) and analysed on an ABI 3730xl DNA Analyzer (Applied Biosystems). The data were processed using GeneMapperID&#x02010;X software. Twenty&#x02010;one loci were assessed for each sample, with no evidence of cross&#x02010;contamination from other cell lines.</p></sec><sec id="cpr13785-sec-0013"><label>2.11</label><title>Population Doubling Time</title><p>The cell growth rate was assessed by a haemocytometer to count cell numbers over time. The doubling time (DT) was calculated following the formula: DT&#x02009;=&#x02009;<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>/[log2/(log<italic toggle="yes">Nt</italic>&#x02212;log<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>0)], where <italic toggle="yes">Nt</italic> is the number of cells at time <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>0 is the initial number of cells at time zero.</p></sec><sec id="cpr13785-sec-0014"><label>2.12</label><title>
<styled-content style="fixed-case" toggle="no">RNA</styled-content> Sequencing (<styled-content style="fixed-case" toggle="no">RNA</styled-content>&#x02010;Seq) and Data Analysis</title><p>Total RNA was extracted using Direct&#x02010;zol RNA MiniPrep Kit (Zymo Research, CA, USA), and its integrity was verified with an Agilent Bioanalyzer 2100. mRNA was enriched from total RNA using oligo (dT)&#x02010;attached magnetic beads, followed by the construction of a strand specific transcriptome library. Sequencing was conducted on the DNBSEQ high&#x02010;throughput platform at BGI Technology. The sequencing data were filtered using SOAPnuke [<xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] to obtain clean reads, which were stored in FASTQ format. Subsequent analysis and data mining were performed on Dr. Tom Multi&#x02010;omics Data mining system (<ext-link xlink:href="https://biosys.bgi.com" ext-link-type="uri">https://biosys.bgi.com</ext-link>). Gene expression levels were calculated by RSEM (v1.3.1) [<xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. The heatmap was drawn by pheatmap (v1.0.8) [<xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] according to the gene expression difference. Essentially, differential expression analysis was performed using the DESeq2 (v1.4.5) [<xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] with <italic toggle="yes">Q</italic> value &#x02264;&#x02009;0.05.</p></sec><sec id="cpr13785-sec-0015"><label>2.13</label><title>Enzyme&#x02010;Linked Immunosorbent Assay</title><p>Cell culture supernatants were collected after a 24&#x02010;h exposure to cells on days 3,6 and 8 following the application of RPE maturation medium, and stored at &#x02212;80&#x000b0;C. The levels of human pigment epithelium&#x02010;derived factor (PEDF) and vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) were quantified using Human VEGF ELISA Kit (Abcam, Cambridge, UK) and Human PEDF ELISA Kit (Abcam, Cambridge, UK).</p></sec><sec id="cpr13785-sec-0016"><label>2.14</label><title>Phagocytosis Assay</title><p>Porcine photoreceptor outer segments (POS) were labelled with fluorescein isothiocyanate (FITC) following the protocol established by Lutz and Lin [<xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. POS were isolated from the fresh porcine eyes obtained from a local abattoir (Beijing, China), and suspended in PBS containing 20&#x02009;&#x003bc;M FITC (MedChemExpress, NJ, USA) overnight in the dark at 4&#x000b0;C. hCiPSCs&#x02010;RPE cells were then exposed to FITC&#x02010;labelled POS in DMEM/F12 (Gibco, CA, USA) for 24&#x02009;h at 37&#x000b0;C. After incubation, the RPE cells were gently washed to remove extracellular FITC&#x02010;labelled POS. Trypan blue was used to quench excess fluorescence. Immunofluorescence staining for ZO&#x02010;1 confirmed the presence of tight junctions between cells and DAPI was used to stain the nuclei.</p></sec><sec id="cpr13785-sec-0017"><label>2.15</label><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>All values are shown as means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;standard deviation (SD). The number of biological replicates, statistical methods and sample sizes (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>) were reported in the figures. Statistical analyses were conducted using GraphPad Prism (version 8).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="cpr13785-sec-0018"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><sec id="cpr13785-sec-0019"><label>3.1</label><title>Derivation of <styled-content style="fixed-case" toggle="no">hCiPSCs</styled-content> From Primary Human Adipose Cells</title><p>To generate hCiPSCs from hADSCs, we adhered to a previously established three&#x02010;step induction protocol [<xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Throughout the chemical reprogramming process, the cells exhibited distinct morphological transformations (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="cpr13785-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1a</xref>). By Day 4 of the first induction stage, the cells transitioned from a spindle&#x02010;shaped, fibrous structural morphology to a monolayer with epithelial characteristics. Upon completion of the second induction stage, numerous multilayered colonies emerged. In the third induction stage, compact, dome&#x02010;shaped clones progressively became evident.</p><fig position="float" fig-type="FIGURE" id="cpr13785-fig-0001"><label>FIGURE 1</label><caption><p>Reprogramming of hADSCs into hCiPSCs. (a) Representative images of initial hADSCs and cells at the end of each stage during hCiPSCs induction. Scale bar, 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;m. (b) Relative expression levels of somatic cell marker genes at the end of the first induction stage, as determined by RT&#x02010;qPCR. Data are presented as means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;standard deviations (SDs); <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3. (c) Relative expression levels of epithelial cell marker genes and <italic toggle="yes">LIN28A</italic> at the end of the first induction stage, as determined by RT&#x02010;qPCR. Data are presented as means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SDs; <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3. (d) Relative expression levels of <italic toggle="yes">LIN28A</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">SALL4</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">OCT4</italic> at the end of the third induction stage, as determined by RT&#x02010;qPCR. Data are presented as means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SDs; <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3. (e) Immunofluorescence analysis of pluripotency markers at the end of the first (LIN28A) and third (OCT4, NANOG, SOX2) induction stages. Scale bar, 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;m. (f) Representative images of established hCiPSC lines with typical hESC morphologies. Scale bar, 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="CPR-58-e13785-g004" position="anchor" id="jats-graphic-3"/></fig><p>Gene expression analyses were performed to monitor the transition from fibroblastic to epithelial states. RT&#x02010;qPCR analysis revealed a marked downregulation of fibroblast&#x02010;associated marker genes (e.g., <italic toggle="yes">MMP1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">ZEB1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">VIM</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">COL5A1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">COL6A2</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">PRRX1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">SNAI2</italic>) by the end of the first induction stage (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="cpr13785-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1b</xref>). In contrast, epithelial marker genes, such as <italic toggle="yes">KRT19</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">KRT18</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">KRT8</italic>, demonstrated substantial upregulation (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="cpr13785-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1c</xref>). We also observed the activation of <italic toggle="yes">LIN28A</italic>, a key marker of pluripotency that was activated during chemical reprogramming [<xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="cpr13785-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1c</xref>). By the end of the third induction stage, in addition to <italic toggle="yes">LIN28A</italic>, two other key pluripotency markers <italic toggle="yes">OCT4</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">SALL4</italic> were expressed (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="cpr13785-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1d</xref>). Immunofluorescence analysis further confirmed the presence of pluripotency markers, including LIN28A, OCT4, NANOG and SOX2 (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="cpr13785-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1e</xref>). These results demonstrate that by the third induction stage, the reprogrammed cells had acquired key features of pluripotency, consistent with the characteristics of hCiPSCs. A total of 42 colonies were selected, from which 40 hCiPSC lines were successfully established and propagated. Of these, 12 randomly selected hCiPSC lines were subjected to further characterisation and differentiation assays. All established cell lines displayed the typical morphology of hESCs (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="cpr13785-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1f</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="cpr13785-sec-0020"><label>3.2</label><title>
<styled-content style="fixed-case" toggle="no">hADSC</styled-content>&#x02010;Derived <styled-content style="fixed-case" toggle="no">hCiPSCs</styled-content> Show Bonafide Pluripotency</title><p>During expansion, the established hADSC&#x02010;derived hCiPSCs exhibited a DT similar to that of hESCs (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="cpr13785-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>). After extensive passaging, these cells strongly expressed key pluripotent surface markers (e.g., TRA&#x02010;1&#x02010;81 and TRA&#x02010;1&#x02010;60, LIN28A), as well as pluripotency&#x02010;associated transcription factors including OCT4, SOX2 and NANOG (Figures&#x000a0;<xref rid="cpr13785-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2b</xref> and <xref rid="cpr13785-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1a,b</xref>). In line with these findings, RT&#x02010;qPCR analysis confirmed that the expression of multiple pluripotency genes in hADSC&#x02010;derived hCiPSCs was comparable to that in hESCs (Figures&#x000a0;<xref rid="cpr13785-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2c</xref> and <xref rid="cpr13785-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1c</xref>). Bulk RNA&#x02010;sequencing analysis of six hCiPSC lines further revealed that hCiPSCs shared similar transcriptomic profiles with hESCs (Figures&#x000a0;<xref rid="cpr13785-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2d,e</xref> and <xref rid="cpr13785-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1d</xref>), indicating that the hCiPSCs had successfully transitioned from the somatic state to a pluripotent state, comparable to hESCs (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="cpr13785-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2f</xref>). Collectively, these data confirm that hADSC&#x02010;derived hCiPSCs exhibited typical pluripotency characteristics analogous to those of hESCs.</p><fig position="float" fig-type="FIGURE" id="cpr13785-fig-0002"><label>FIGURE 2</label><caption><p>Characterisation of hADSC&#x02010;derived hCiPSCs. (a) Calculated doubling times for hCiPSCs and hESCs. Data are presented as means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SDs; <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3. (b) Immunofluorescence staining for pluripotency markers in hADSC&#x02010;derived hCiPSCs. Scale bar, 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;m. (c) Relative expression levels of pluripotency marker genes in hESCs (H1) and hADSC&#x02010;derived hCiPSCs, as determined by RT&#x02010;qPCR. Data are presented as means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SDs; <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3. (d) Scatter plots comparing global transcriptional profiles of hCiPSCs, hESCs (H1) and hADSCs. (e) Hierarchical clustering of the global transcriptional profiles of hCiPSCs, hESCs (H1) and hADSCs. Distances were calculated as 1&#x02013;Spearman correlation coefficient. (f) Heatmap showing the expression patterns of pluripotency marker genes and somatic cell marker genes in hCiPSCs, hESCs (H1) and hADSCs. (g) Immunofluorescence staining for the three germ layer markers in embryoid bodies derived from hCiPSCs (hCiPSCs&#x02010;C40, C4). Scale bar, 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;m. (h) Haematoxylin and eosin staining of hCiPSC&#x02010;derived teratoma sections (hCiPSCs&#x02010;C4). Images showing the endoderm, mesoderm and ectoderm differentiated from a single teratoma. Scale bars, 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;m. (i) Karyotype analysis showing hADSC&#x02010;derived hCiPSCs (hCiPSCs&#x02010;C40) with normal diploid chromosomal content.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="CPR-58-e13785-g005" position="anchor" id="jats-graphic-5"/></fig><p>To assess the differentiation potential of hADSC&#x02010;derived hCiPSCs, we performed in&#x000a0;vitro EB differentiation assays, which revealed the expression of markers from all three germ layers. This included the endoderm marker FOXA2, mesoderm marker GATA4 and Brachyury, and ectoderm markers PAX6 and TUJ1 (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="cpr13785-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2g</xref>). Additionally, in&#x000a0;vivo teratoma formation assays demonstrated that hADSC&#x02010;derived hCiPSCs formed teratomas approximately 1&#x02010;month post&#x02010;injection into immunodeficient mice. H&#x00026;E staining confirmed the presence of cells from all three germ layers with the teratomas (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="cpr13785-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2h</xref>).</p><p>To further evaluate the genomic integrity of the hADSC&#x02010;derived hCiPSCs, we conducted high&#x02010;resolution G&#x02010;banding analysis, which revealed normal diploid karyotypes in all 12 hCiPSC lines (Figures&#x000a0;<xref rid="cpr13785-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2i</xref> and <xref rid="cpr13785-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1e</xref>). DNA fingerprinting analysis also verified that the hCiPSCs were indeed derived from their parental cells (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="cpr13785-supitem-0002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref>). Collectively, these data demonstrate that hADSC&#x02010;derived hCiPSCs closely resemble hESCs in terms of gene expression, differentiation potential and their maintenance of genetic integrity in&#x000a0;vitro.</p><p>The summary of the hCiPS cell lines and all the pluripotency assays performed in this study are presented in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="cpr13785-supitem-0002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S4</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="cpr13785-sec-0021"><label>3.3</label><title>Efficient <styled-content style="fixed-case" toggle="no">RPE</styled-content> Cells Generation From <styled-content style="fixed-case" toggle="no">hCiPSCs</styled-content>
</title><p>To induce hCiPSCs differentiation into the RPE lineage, we employed the protocol described by Ye et&#x000a0;al. [<xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. RPE progenitor cells, originating from the outer layer of the optic cup, represent an intermediate stage in early eye development, and are characterised by the expression of PAX6 and MITF, key transcription factors that regulate RPE progenitor induction [<xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Therefore, we analysed their expression on Day 12 of differentiation. Remarkably, over 90% of the differentiated cells exhibited strong expression of PAX6 and MITF (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="cpr13785-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3a</xref>), indicating highly efficient induction of RPE progenitor cells from hCiPSCs.</p><fig position="float" fig-type="FIGURE" id="cpr13785-fig-0003"><label>FIGURE 3</label><caption><p>Differentiation of RPE cells from hCiPSCs. (a) Immunostaining for PAX6 and MITF in RPE progenitors on Day 12 of differentiation. Scale bar, 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;m. (b) RT&#x02010;qPCR analysis of RPE marker genes and pluripotency&#x02010;related genes throughout the differentiation process. Values are presented as means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SDs; <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3. (c) Flow cytometry analysis of hCiPSCs (C40)&#x02010;derived RPE cells at Day 20 for the positive marker (PAX6) and pluripotency marker (OCT4). (d) Macroscopic photographs of pigmented cells differentiated from various hCiPSC lines on Day 36, shown in 12&#x02010;well plates.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="CPR-58-e13785-g001" position="anchor" id="jats-graphic-7"/></fig><p>To further investigate the differentiation of hCiPSCs into the RPE lineage, we performed RT&#x02010;qPCR to assess the dynamic expression of RPE&#x02010;specific and pluripotency marker genes (Figures&#x000a0;<xref rid="cpr13785-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3b</xref> and <xref rid="cpr13785-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2a</xref>). In alignment with the immunofluorescence data, we observed a gradual upregulation of RPE marker genes (e.g., <italic toggle="yes">TYRP1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">PEDF</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">PAX6</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">MITF</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">RPE65</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">BEST1</italic>) as differentiation progressed, alongside a pronounced downregulation of pluripotency markers (e.g., <italic toggle="yes">LIN28A</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">NANOG</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">SOX2</italic>) (Figures&#x000a0;<xref rid="cpr13785-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3b</xref> and <xref rid="cpr13785-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2a</xref>). Moreover, as differentiation continued, the proportion of PAX6&#x02010;positive cells steadily increased, while OCT4&#x02010;positive cells, indicative of pluripotency, significantly decreased (Figures&#x000a0;<xref rid="cpr13785-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3c</xref> and <xref rid="cpr13785-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2b</xref>). These results suggest that RPE progenitors could be efficiently induced from hADSC&#x02010;derived hCiPSCs. After 5&#x02009;weeks of differentiation, pigmented colonies characteristic of RPE cells became evident, as previously reported [<xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="cpr13785-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3d</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="cpr13785-sec-0022"><label>3.4</label><title>
<styled-content style="fixed-case" toggle="no">hCiPSC</styled-content>&#x02010;<styled-content style="fixed-case" toggle="no">RPE</styled-content> Cells Develop Mature Characteristics</title><p>To obtain purified RPE cells with pigment deposition, pigmented cells were manually selected and cultured in RPE maturation culture medium (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="cpr13785-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2c</xref>). After 10&#x02009;days of additional culture, pigment cells became visible, and by Day 20, RPE pigmentation significantly gathered as evidenced by the emergence of pigmented hexagonal cells (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="cpr13785-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2d</xref>). By Day 40, a notable increase in the number of polygonal, pigmented cells were observed (Figures&#x000a0;<xref rid="cpr13785-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">4a</xref> and <xref rid="cpr13785-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2d</xref>). The morphological characteristics of hCiPSC&#x02010;derived RPE cells closely resemble those of human primary RPE cells, consistent with previous report [<xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Immunostaining analysis performed on Day 40 of maturation revealed strong expression of key RPE markers, including BEST1, ZO&#x02010;1 and RPE65 (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="cpr13785-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">4b</xref>). We compared hCiPSC&#x02010;derived RPE cells derived from hCiPSCs at different stages of differentiation (low pigmentation at D10 and high pigmentation at D40) with hRPE cells. RT&#x02010;qPCR analysis showed that the mRNA levels of <italic toggle="yes">BEST1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">TRP2</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">OTX2</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">PEDF</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">RPE65</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">TYRP1</italic> were significantly upregulated in hCiPSC&#x02010;derived RPE cells compared to retinal progenitor cells and hCiPSCs (Figures&#x000a0;<xref rid="cpr13785-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">4c</xref> and <xref rid="cpr13785-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2f</xref>).</p><fig position="float" fig-type="FIGURE" id="cpr13785-fig-0004"><label>FIGURE 4</label><caption><p>Characterisation of mature RPE cells differentiated from hCiPSCs. (a) Macroscopic photographs and phase&#x02010;contrast images of mature RPE cells. Scale bar, 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;m. (b) Immunostaining for mature RPE marker (BEST1, ZO&#x02010;1 and RPE65) in hCiPSCs&#x02010;RPE cells on day 60. Scale bar, 10&#x02009;&#x003bc;m. (c) Gene expression analysis for mature RPE markers relative to undifferentiated hCiPSCs (C17) in retinal progenitors (~Day 20), low pigmentation RPE cells (~Day 50), high pigmentation RPE cells (~Day 75) and hRPE using RT&#x02010;qPCR. Values are presented as means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SDs; <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3. (d) The hierarchical clustering analysis of the global transcriptional profiles for hCiPSCs, hCiPSC&#x02010;derived RPE cells and adult human primary RPE cells (RNA&#x02010;seq data from GEO database, GSE210331, GSM6428549 (RPE1), GSM6428552 (RPE2), GSM6428550 (RPE3), GSM6428551 (RPE4)). Distances were calculated as 1&#x02013;Spearman correlation coefficient. (e) Heatmap showing the expression of the 154 RPE signature genes in hCiPSCs, hCiPSC&#x02010;derived RPE cells and adult human primary RPE cells. (f) VEGF (left) and PEDF (right) secretion qualification by ELISAs regarding hCiPSC&#x02010;derived mature RPE cell. Values are presented as means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SDs; <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3. (g) Functional phagocytosis activity measurement of hCiPSC (C7)&#x02010;RPE using FITC&#x02010;labelled POS by immunofluorescence microscopy. Immunostaining of ZO&#x02010;1 for defining the cell boundary. The cell nuclei were stained with DAPI. Scale bar, 10&#x02009;&#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="CPR-58-e13785-g002" position="anchor" id="jats-graphic-9"/></fig><p>To further characterise the transcriptional profiles of hCiPSC&#x02010;derived RPE cells, we performed RNA&#x02010;seq analysis on hCiPSC&#x02010;derived RPE cells, hCiPSCs and compared the results with previously published RNA&#x02010;seq data of adult human primary RPE cells (recorded in GEO database, GSE210331) [<xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. The hierarchical clustering analysis showed that hCiPSC&#x02010;derived RPE cells exhibited gene expression patterns similar to adult human primary RPE cells (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="cpr13785-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">4d</xref>). Analysis of 154 RPE signature genes [<xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] confirmed that hCiPSC&#x02010;derived RPE cells displayed expression patterns consistent across different hCiPSC lines, closely resembling adult human primary RPE cells (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="cpr13785-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">4e</xref>).</p><p>Finally, the functional properties of hCiPSC&#x02010;derived RPE cells were accessed. Enzyme&#x02010;linked immunosorbent assays (ELISAs) demonstrated robust secretion of PEDF and VEGF, critical factors for RPE&#x02010;mediated retinal maintenance, with levels increasing over time in culture (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="cpr13785-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">4f</xref>). Furthermore, phagocytic activity, an essential function for RPE cells in maintaining visual cycle and photoreceptor homeostasis in&#x000a0;vivo [<xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], was evaluated by co&#x02010;incubating hCiPSC&#x02010;derived RPE cells with FITC&#x02010;labelled POS. Immunofluorescence analysis confirmed the successful phagocytosis of POS (Figures&#x000a0;<xref rid="cpr13785-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">4g</xref> and <xref rid="cpr13785-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2e</xref>). Overall, these results demonstrated the efficient generation of functional RPE cells from hCiPSCs.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="cpr13785-sec-0023"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p>In the field of regenerative medicine, particularly in the treatment of ocular disease, the selection of an optimal cell source and the refinement of cell preparation protocols are critical to achieve clinical success. Our study presents a chemically defined strategy for generating functional RPE cells using hCiPSCs sourced from adipose tissue. This approach eliminates the need for genetic manipulations, thereby potentially enhancing the safety and applicability of the resulting cells. Following a three&#x02010;step induction process [<xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], we successfully reprogrammed hADSCs into hCiPSCs, which exhibited comparable morphologies, gene expression profiles and differentiation potential to hESCs. These hCiPSCs were then subsequently differentiated into RPE progenitor cells and ultimately into mature, functional RPE cells through a stepwise differentiation process. Our results demonstrate the efficient generation of RPE cells from human somatic cells via chemically induced pluripotency, underscoring the potential of using clinical&#x02010;grade autologous hCiPSCs for cellular therapies in the treatment of ocular diseases.</p><p>Compared to genetic reprogramming approach, chemical induction offers a straightforward and reliable method for hiPSCs generation. In our study, with minimal adjustment to the chemical reprogramming medium, primary hCiPSC colonies emerged within 32&#x02009;days. This approach holds particular promise for researchers who may have limited expertise in genetic manipulation or cell fate reprogramming techniques. Moreover, consistent with recent findings demonstrating the efficient generation of hCiPSCs from human somatic cells [<xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], we successfully established 40 hCiPSC lines. This extensive collection of lines offers a robust platform for evaluating and identifying those with high potential for differentiation into RPE cells. Overall, our results confirmed the practicality of chemical reprogramming approach for hiPSCs generation, offering a valuable resource for autologous applications involving hiPSCs.</p><p>Our study also demonstrated the efficient differentiation of RPE cells from hCiPSCs through a two&#x02010;dimensional differentiation protocol. Compared to three&#x02010;dimensional approaches, two&#x02010;dimensional methods offer greater simplicity and control, leading to enhanced differentiation efficiency [<xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. We utilised a two&#x02010;dimensional protocol developed by Ye [<xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] and incorporated mechanical separation techniques to improve the purity of RPE cells. By utilising small molecules to accelerate the process, instead of relying on spontaneous differentiation method, we successfully generated RPE cells from hCiPSCs. Notably, pigmentation in hCiPSC&#x02010;derived cells emerged as early as Day 23, with nearly all of the 12 tested cell lines exhibiting significant pigmentation by Day 30. This timeline is consistent with previous reports, yet significantly shorter than the 3&#x02013;8&#x02009;months typically required for spontaneous differentiation [<xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, <xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, <xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Additionally, the hCiPSC&#x02010;derived RPE cells demonstrated key functional properties, including the secretion of PEDF and VEGF, as well as the capacity for phagocytosis, indicating their functional maturity. These findings present a promising strategy for generating autologous functional RPE cells in sufficient quantities for the clinical treatment of retinal diseases. For future clinical applications, adipose&#x02010;derived stromal cells (ADSCs) from patients will be utilised as the target cells for reprogramming and further differentiation into functional RPE cells, ensuring a personalised approach to treatment.</p><p>To fully harness the potential of hCiPSC&#x02010;based autologous therapies for retinal diseases, one critical issue must be addressed. A thorough evaluation of the genomic stability and safety of autologous hiPSCs and their retinal derivatives is essential prior to clinical application. Recent studies have highlighted the prevalence of acquired cancer&#x02010;related mutations in numerous hiPSC lines and their derivatives, raising concerns regarding genetic instability [<xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>, <xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. The suspension of the AMD clinical trial at RIKEN was notably attributed to genetic instability observed in hiPSCs and their RPE derivatives [<xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. This instability may stem from the genetic factors employed during hiPSC generation, and these factors have been found to be upregulated in various tumour types [<xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>, <xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, <xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. In contrast, chemical reprogramming circumvents the use of genetic factors. By comparing the gene expression profiles of our hCiPSCs and human embryonic stem cells (hESCs), we did not observe any significant upregulation of Gene Ontology (GO) terms or pathways associated with cellular toxicity, and our hCiPSCs showed great similarity with hESCs. Additionally, according to Guan et&#x000a0;al. [<xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], no toxicity associated with the small molecules used during the chemical induction process has been reported. Recent studies have demonstrated the promise of hCiPSCs in clinical applications, further reinforcing the value of using autologous hCiPSCs and their derivatives in future trails [<xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. These findings, combined with our own transcriptomic data, suggest that the compounds employed may not exert toxic effects on the derived cells. Future studies should explore whether hCiPSCs could bypass the potential safety issues associated with genetic factor overexpression.</p><p>Additionally, given the intricate, multilayered structure of the retina and the involvement of multiple cell layers in disease progression, replacing dysfunctional RPE cells alone may not be sufficient for achieving optimal therapeutic outcomes [<xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Hence, alternative hCiPSC&#x02010;based strategies warrant exploration in the future. These may include co&#x02010;transplantation of RPE cells with retinal progenitor cells derived from hCiPSCs, as well as the transplantation of more sophisticated and structured hCiPSCs&#x02010;derived multilayered retinal cells or organoids [<xref rid="cpr13785-bib-0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Such strategies hold promise for enhancing therapeutic efficacy by addressing the complex pathophysiology of retinal diseases comprehensively.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="cpr13785-sec-0024"><label>5</label><title>Conclusions</title><p>Our study showcased the successful generation of functionally mature human RPE cells through chemically induced pluripotency, highlighting their therapeutic potential in retinal diseases. This chemical reprogramming method offers a promising alternative for personalised cell therapies, particularly in the context of ocular diseases. By harnessing the transformative potential of hCiPSCs, our findings contribute to the advancements of regenerative medicine and personalised treatment strategies, offering insights that may transcend ocular diseases and hold promise for addressing diverse medical conditions.</p></sec><sec id="cpr13785-sec-0025"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>Ke Zhang and Yanqiu Wang conducted the experiments, analysed the data, and prepared the draft of the manuscript. Qi An, Hengjing Ji, Defu Wu and Lingge Suo contributed to experimental design and data analysis. Xuri Li assisted in drafting and revising the manuscript critically for important intellectual content. Xuran Dong and Chun Zhang conceptualised the study, responsible for all data, figure and text, ensured that authorship is granted appropriately to contributors, prepared the draft of the manuscript and supervised the entire project.</p></sec><sec id="cpr13785-sec-0027"><title>Ethics Statement</title><p>This study protocol was reviewed and approved by Peking University Third Hospital Science Research Ethics Committee, approval number IRB00006761&#x02010;M2023591. The title of the approved project was &#x02018;Clinical study on the safety and efficacy of retinal cells derived from autologous pluripotent stem cells in the treatment of advanced AMD&#x02019;, and the date that the ethics approval was granted on 20 September 2023. All procedures performed in studies involving human participants were adhered to the Helsinki Declaration and its lateral amendments.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="cpr13785-sec-0028"><title>Consent</title><p>The patient has provided written informed consent for the use of sample. This manuscript has been read and approved for publication by all authors.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="cpr13785-sec-0029"><title>Conflicts of Interest</title><p>The authors declare no conflicts of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supporting information</title><supplementary-material id="cpr13785-supitem-0001" position="float" content-type="local-data"><caption><p>
Figure S1.
</p><p>
Figure S2.
</p></caption><media xlink:href="CPR-58-e13785-s001.pdf"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="cpr13785-supitem-0002" position="float" content-type="local-data"><caption><p>
Table&#x000a0;S1.
</p><p>
Table&#x000a0;S2.
</p><p>
Table&#x000a0;S3.
</p><p>
Table&#x000a0;S4.
</p></caption><media xlink:href="CPR-58-e13785-s002.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="cpr13785-sec-0026"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors are indebted to Ying Li (Peking University Third Hospital) and Xiaoyin Ma (Affiliated Eye Hospital, Wenzhou Medical University) for giving us gifts of ARPE&#x02010;19 cells and hRPE cells, to Debo You, Tong Sun, Yan Sun, Chen Huang, Yingyu Li, Pei Zhang (Peking University Third Hospital) for their assistance on the experimental procedures and data collections. The authors are also grateful for the help from Qingjian Ou (Department of Ophthalmology and Laboratory of Clinical and Visual Sciences of Tongji Eye Institute, Tongji Hospital, Tongji University School of Medicine), Ganlu Hu (Shanghai Institute for Advanced Immunochemical Studies, ShanghaiTech University) and Hao Qian (Sichuan Provincial People's Hospital) for providing their expert guidance throughout the study. The sincerest gratitude was shown to all contributors who made this research possible. The authors declare that they have not used Artificial Intelligence in this study.</p></ack><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="cpr13785-sec-0031"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>All data are available in this article and its <xref rid="cpr13785-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supporting Information</xref>. RNA&#x02010;seq data have been submitted to the GEO database, and the accession number is GSE267656. Otherwise, the RNA&#x02010;seq data of adult human primary RPE cells are from GEO database, and the accession number is GSE210331 (GSM6428549 (RPE1), GSM6428552 (RPE2), GSM6428550 (RPE3), GSM6428551 (RPE4)).</p></sec><ref-list content-type="cited-references" id="cpr13785-bibl-0001"><title>References</title><ref id="cpr13785-bib-0001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cpr13785-cit-0001">
<string-name>
<given-names>F.</given-names>
<surname>Soldner</surname>
</string-name> and <string-name>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
<surname>Jaenisch</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>Stem Cells, Genome Editing, and the Path to Translational Medicine</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Cell</source>
<volume>175</volume> (<year>2018</year>): <fpage>615</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>632</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2018.09.010</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30340033</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cpr13785-bib-0002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cpr13785-cit-0002">
<string-name>
<given-names>R. G.</given-names>
<surname>Rowe</surname>
</string-name> and <string-name>
<given-names>G. Q.</given-names>
<surname>Daley</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>Induced Pluripotent Stem Cells in Disease Modelling and Drug Discovery</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Nature Reviews. Genetics</source>
<volume>20</volume> (<year>2019</year>): <fpage>377</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>388</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41576-019-0100-z</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cpr13785-bib-0003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cpr13785-cit-0003">
<string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Yamanaka</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>Pluripotent Stem Cell&#x02010;Based Cell Therapy&#x02010;Promise and Challenges</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Cell Stem Cell</source>
<volume>27</volume> (<year>2020</year>): <fpage>523</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>531</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.stem.2020.09.014</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33007237</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cpr13785-bib-0004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cpr13785-cit-0004">
<string-name>
<given-names>A. H.</given-names>
<surname>Kashani</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J. S.</given-names>
<surname>Lebkowski</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>F. M.</given-names>
<surname>Rahhal</surname>
</string-name>, et&#x000a0;al., &#x0201c;<article-title>A Bioengineered Retinal Pigment Epithelial Monolayer for Advanced, Dry Age&#x02010;Related Macular Degeneration</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Science Translational Medicine</source>
<volume>10</volume> (<year>2018</year>): <elocation-id>eaao4097</elocation-id>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/scitranslmed.aao4097</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29618560</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cpr13785-bib-0005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cpr13785-cit-0005">
<string-name>
<given-names>S. D.</given-names>
<surname>Schwartz</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J. P.</given-names>
<surname>Hubschman</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
<surname>Heilwell</surname>
</string-name>, et&#x000a0;al., &#x0201c;<article-title>Embryonic Stem Cell Trials for Macular Degeneration: A Preliminary Report</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Lancet</source>
<volume>379</volume> (<year>2012</year>): <fpage>713</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>720</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(12)60028-2</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22281388</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cpr13785-bib-0006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cpr13785-cit-0006">
<string-name>
<given-names>S. D.</given-names>
<surname>Schwartz</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>C. D.</given-names>
<surname>Regillo</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>B. L.</given-names>
<surname>Lam</surname>
</string-name>, et&#x000a0;al., &#x0201c;<article-title>Human Embryonic Stem Cell&#x02010;Derived Retinal Pigment Epithelium in Patients With Age&#x02010;Related Macular Degeneration and Stargardt's Macular Dystrophy: Follow&#x02010;Up of Two Open&#x02010;Label Phase 1/2 Studies</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Lancet</source>
<volume>385</volume> (<year>2015</year>): <fpage>509</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>516</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(14)61376-3</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25458728</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cpr13785-bib-0007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cpr13785-cit-0007">
<string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Mandai</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
<surname>Kurimoto</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Takahashi</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>Autologous Induced Stem&#x02010;Cell&#x02010;Derived Retinal Cells for Macular Degeneration</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>New England Journal of Medicine</source>
<volume>377</volume> (<year>2017</year>): <fpage>792</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>793</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMc1706274</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cpr13785-bib-0008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cpr13785-cit-0008">
<string-name>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
<surname>da Cruz</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
<surname>Fynes</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>O.</given-names>
<surname>Georgiadis</surname>
</string-name>, et&#x000a0;al., &#x0201c;<article-title>Phase 1 Clinical Study of an Embryonic Stem Cell&#x02010;Derived Retinal Pigment Epithelium Patch in Age&#x02010;Related Macular Degeneration</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Nature Biotechnology</source>
<volume>36</volume> (<year>2018</year>): <fpage>328</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>337</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.4114</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cpr13785-bib-0009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cpr13785-cit-0009">
<string-name>
<given-names>R. H.</given-names>
<surname>Guymer</surname>
</string-name> and <string-name>
<given-names>T. G.</given-names>
<surname>Campbell</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>Age&#x02010;Related Macular Degeneration</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Lancet</source>
<volume>401</volume> (<year>2023</year>): <fpage>1459</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1472</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(22)02609-5</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36996856</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cpr13785-bib-0010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cpr13785-cit-0010">
<string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Kobold</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
<surname>Bultjer</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
<surname>Stacey</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S. C.</given-names>
<surname>Mueller</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Kurtz</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
<surname>Mah</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>History and Current Status of Clinical Studies Using Human Pluripotent Stem Cells</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Stem Cell Reports</source>
<volume>18</volume> (<year>2023</year>): <fpage>1592</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1598</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.stemcr.2023.03.005</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37028422</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cpr13785-bib-0011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cpr13785-cit-0011">
<string-name>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
<surname>Garber</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>RIKEN Suspends First Clinical Trial Involving Induced Pluripotent Stem Cells</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Nature Biotechnology</source>
<volume>33</volume> (<year>2015</year>): <fpage>890</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>891</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt0915-890</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cpr13785-bib-0012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cpr13785-cit-0012">
<string-name>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
<surname>Neofytou</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>C. G.</given-names>
<surname>O'Brien</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>L. A.</given-names>
<surname>Couture</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>J. C.</given-names>
<surname>Wu</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>Hurdles to Clinical Translation of Human Induced Pluripotent Stem Cells</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Journal of Clinical Investigation</source>
<volume>12</volume> (<year>2015</year>): <fpage>2551</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2557</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI80575</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cpr13785-bib-0013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cpr13785-cit-0013">
<string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Liuyang</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
<surname>Wang</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
<surname>Wang</surname>
</string-name>, et&#x000a0;al., &#x0201c;<article-title>Highly Efficient and Rapid Generation of Human Pluripotent Stem Cells by Chemical Reprogramming</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Cell Stem Cell</source>
<volume>30</volume>, no. <issue>4</issue> (<year>2023</year>): <fpage>450</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>459.e9</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.stem.2023.02.008</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36944335</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cpr13785-bib-0014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cpr13785-cit-0014">
<string-name>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
<surname>Hou</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
<surname>Li</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>X.</given-names>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
</string-name>, et&#x000a0;al., &#x0201c;<article-title>Pluripotent Stem Cells Induced From Mouse Somatic Cells by Small&#x02010;Molecule Compounds</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Science</source>
<volume>341</volume> (<year>2013</year>): <fpage>651</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>654</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1239278</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23868920</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cpr13785-bib-0015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cpr13785-cit-0015">
<string-name>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Guan</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
<surname>Wang</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Wang</surname>
</string-name>, et&#x000a0;al., &#x0201c;<article-title>Chemical Reprogramming of Human Somatic Cells to Pluripotent Stem Cells</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Nature</source>
<volume>605</volume> (<year>2022</year>): <fpage>325</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>331</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-022-04593-5</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35418683</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cpr13785-bib-0016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cpr13785-cit-0016">
<string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
<surname>Wang</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
<surname>An</surname>
</string-name>, et&#x000a0;al., &#x0201c;<article-title>Lower Genomic Stability of Induced Pluripotent Stem Cells Reflects Increased Non&#x02010;Homologous End Joining</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Cancer Communications (London)</source>
<volume>38</volume> (<year>2018</year>): <fpage>49</fpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40880-018-0313-0</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cpr13785-bib-0017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cpr13785-cit-0017">
<string-name>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
<surname>Ye</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
<surname>Takemoto</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Ito</surname>
</string-name>, et&#x000a0;al., &#x0201c;<article-title>Reproducible Production and Image&#x02010;Based Quality Evaluation of Retinal Pigment Epithelium Sheets From Human Induced Pluripotent Stem Cells</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Scientific Reports</source>
<volume>10</volume> (<year>2020</year>): <fpage>14387</fpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-70979-y</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32873827</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cpr13785-bib-0018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cpr13785-cit-0018">
<string-name>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
<surname>Li</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
<surname>Li</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
<surname>Kristiansen</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Wang</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>SOAP: Short Oligonucleotide Alignment Program</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>24</volume> (<year>2008</year>): <fpage>713</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>714</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btn025</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18227114</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cpr13785-bib-0019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cpr13785-cit-0019">
<string-name>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
<surname>Li</surname>
</string-name> and <string-name>
<given-names>C. N.</given-names>
<surname>Dewey</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>RSEM: Accurate Transcript Quantification From RNA&#x02010;Seq Data With or Without a Reference Genome</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>12</volume> (<year>2011</year>): <elocation-id>323</elocation-id>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-12-323</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21816040</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cpr13785-bib-0020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="miscellaneous" id="cpr13785-cit-0020">
<string-name>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
<surname>Raivo</surname>
</string-name>, <article-title>&#x0201c;Package &#x02018;pheatmap&#x02019;,&#x0201d; 2019&#x02010;01&#x02010;04 13:50:12 UTC</article-title>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cpr13785-bib-0021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cpr13785-cit-0021">
<string-name>
<given-names>M. I.</given-names>
<surname>Love</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>W.</given-names>
<surname>Huber</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Anders</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>Moderated Estimation of Fold Change and Dispersion for RNA&#x02010;Seq Data With DESeq2</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Genome Biology</source>
<volume>15</volume> (<year>2014</year>): <fpage>550</fpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-014-0550-8</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25516281</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cpr13785-bib-0022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cpr13785-cit-0022">
<string-name>
<given-names>D. A.</given-names>
<surname>Lutz</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
<surname>Guo</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>B. J.</given-names>
<surname>McLaughlin</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>Natural, High&#x02010;Mannose Glycoproteins Inhibit ROS Binding and Ingestion by RPE Cell Cultures</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Experimental Eye Research</source>
<volume>61</volume> (<year>1995</year>): <fpage>487</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>493</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0014-4835(05)80144-7</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8549690</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cpr13785-bib-0023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cpr13785-cit-0023">
<string-name>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
<surname>Lin</surname>
</string-name> and <string-name>
<given-names>D. O.</given-names>
<surname>Clegg</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>Integrin alphavbeta5 Participates in the Binding of Photoreceptor Rod Outer Segments During Phagocytosis by Cultured Human Retinal Pigment Epithelium</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Investigative Ophthalmology &#x00026; Visual Science</source>
<volume>39</volume> (<year>1998</year>): <fpage>1703</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1712</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9699560</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cpr13785-bib-0024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cpr13785-cit-0024">
<string-name>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
<surname>Shyh&#x02010;Chang</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
<surname>Zhu</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
<surname>Yvanka de Soysa</surname>
</string-name>, et&#x000a0;al., &#x0201c;<article-title>Lin28 Enhances Tissue Repair by Reprogramming Cellular Metabolism</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Cell</source>
<volume>155</volume> (<year>2013</year>): <fpage>778</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>792</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2013.09.059</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24209617</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cpr13785-bib-0025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cpr13785-cit-0025">
<string-name>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
<surname>Diacou</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
<surname>Nandigrami</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Fiser</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>W.</given-names>
<surname>Liu</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
<surname>Ashery&#x02010;Padan</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Cvekl</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>Cell Fate Decisions, Transcription Factors and Signaling During Early Retinal Development</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Progress in Retinal and Eye Research</source>
<volume>91</volume> (<year>2022</year>): <elocation-id>101093</elocation-id>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.preteyeres.2022.101093</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35817658</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cpr13785-bib-0026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cpr13785-cit-0026">
<string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Maminishkis</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Chen</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Jalickee</surname>
</string-name>, et&#x000a0;al., &#x0201c;<article-title>Confluent Monolayers of Cultured Human Fetal Retinal Pigment Epithelium Exhibit Morphology and Physiology of Native Tissue</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Investigative Ophthalmology &#x00026; Visual Science</source>
<volume>47</volume> (<year>2006</year>): <fpage>3612</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3624</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1167/iovs.05-1622</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16877436</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cpr13785-bib-0027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cpr13785-cit-0027">
<string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Sonoda</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
<surname>Spee</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
<surname>Barron</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S. J.</given-names>
<surname>Ryan</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
<surname>Kannan</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>D. R.</given-names>
<surname>Hinton</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>A Protocol for the Culture and Differentiation of Highly Polarized Human Retinal Pigment Epithelial Cells</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Nature Protocols</source>
<volume>4</volume> (<year>2009</year>): <fpage>662</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>673</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2009.33</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19373231</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cpr13785-bib-0028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cpr13785-cit-0028">
<string-name>
<given-names>E. K.</given-names>
<surname>Markert</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
<surname>Klein</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
<surname>Viollet</surname>
</string-name>, et&#x000a0;al., &#x0201c;<article-title>Transcriptional Comparison of Adult Human Primary Retinal Pigment Epithelium, Human Pluripotent Stem Cell&#x02010;Derived Retinal Pigment Epithelium, and ARPE19 Cells</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Frontiers in Cell and Development Biology</source>
<volume>10</volume> (<year>2022</year>): <elocation-id>910040</elocation-id>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fcell.2022.910040</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cpr13785-bib-0029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cpr13785-cit-0029">
<string-name>
<given-names>N. V.</given-names>
<surname>Strunnikova</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Maminishkis</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J. J.</given-names>
<surname>Barb</surname>
</string-name>, et&#x000a0;al., &#x0201c;<article-title>Transcriptome Analysis and Molecular Signature of Human Retinal Pigment Epithelium</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Human Molecular Genetics</source>
<volume>19</volume> (<year>2010</year>): <fpage>2468</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2486</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/hmg/ddq129</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20360305</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cpr13785-bib-0030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cpr13785-cit-0030">
<string-name>
<given-names>T. A.</given-names>
<surname>Ferguson</surname>
</string-name> and <string-name>
<given-names>D. R.</given-names>
<surname>Green</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>Autophagy and Phagocytosis Converge for Better Vision</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Autophagy</source>
<volume>10</volume> (<year>2014</year>): <fpage>165</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>167</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4161/auto.26735</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24220227</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cpr13785-bib-0031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cpr13785-cit-0031">
<string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Plaza Reyes</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Petrus&#x02010;Reurer</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Padrell S&#x000e1;nchez</surname>
</string-name>, et&#x000a0;al., &#x0201c;<article-title>Identification of Cell Surface Markers and Establishment of Monolayer Differentiation to Retinal Pigment Epithelial Cells</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Nature Communications</source>
<volume>11</volume> (<year>2020</year>): <fpage>1609</fpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-020-15326-5</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cpr13785-bib-0032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cpr13785-cit-0032">
<string-name>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
<surname>Choudhary</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
<surname>Booth</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Gutteridge</surname>
</string-name>, et&#x000a0;al., &#x0201c;<article-title>Directing Differentiation of Pluripotent Stem Cells Toward Retinal Pigment Epithelium Lineage</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Stem Cells Translational Medicine</source>
<volume>6</volume> (<year>2017</year>): <fpage>490</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>501</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5966/sctm.2016-0088</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28191760</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cpr13785-bib-0033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cpr13785-cit-0033">
<string-name>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
<surname>Kuroda</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Ando</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
<surname>Takeno</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Kishino</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
<surname>Kimura</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>Robust Induction of Retinal Pigment Epithelium Cells From Human Induced Pluripotent Stem Cells by Inhibiting FGF/MAPK Signaling</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Stem Cell Research</source>
<volume>39</volume> (<year>2019</year>): <elocation-id>101514</elocation-id>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scr.2019.101514</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31376722</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cpr13785-bib-0034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cpr13785-cit-0034">
<string-name>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
<surname>Lange</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M. A.</given-names>
<surname>Esteban</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Schambach</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>Back to Pluripotency: Fully Chemically Induced Reboot of Human Somatic Cells</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Signal Transduction and Targeted Therapy</source>
<volume>7</volume> (<year>2022</year>): <fpage>244</fpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41392-022-01109-5</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35853857</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cpr13785-bib-0035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cpr13785-cit-0035">
<string-name>
<given-names>D. E.</given-names>
<surname>Buchholz</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S. T.</given-names>
<surname>Hikita</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>T. J.</given-names>
<surname>Rowland</surname>
</string-name>, et&#x000a0;al., &#x0201c;<article-title>Derivation of Functional Retinal Pigmented Epithelium From Induced Pluripotent Stem Cells</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Stem Cells</source>
<volume>27</volume> (<year>2009</year>): <fpage>2427</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2434</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/stem.189</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19658190</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cpr13785-bib-0036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cpr13785-cit-0036">
<string-name>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Maruotti</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S. R.</given-names>
<surname>Sripathi</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
<surname>Bharti</surname>
</string-name>, et&#x000a0;al., &#x0201c;<article-title>Small&#x02010;Molecule&#x02010;Directed, Efficient Generation of Retinal Pigment Epithelium From Human Pluripotent Stem Cells</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source>
<volume>112</volume>, no. <issue>35</issue> (<year>2015</year>): <fpage>10950</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10955</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1422818112</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26269569</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cpr13785-bib-0037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cpr13785-cit-0037">
<string-name>
<given-names>F. J.</given-names>
<surname>Rouhani</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>X.</given-names>
<surname>Zou</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
<surname>Danecek</surname>
</string-name>, et&#x000a0;al., &#x0201c;<article-title>Substantial Somatic Genomic Variation and Selection for BCOR Mutations in Human Induced Pluripotent Stem Cells</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Nature Genetics</source>
<volume>54</volume> (<year>2022</year>): <fpage>1406</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1416</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41588-022-01147-3</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35953586</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cpr13785-bib-0038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cpr13785-cit-0038">
<string-name>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
<surname>Lezmi</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Jung</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
<surname>Benvenisty</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>High Prevalence of Acquired Cancer&#x02010;Related Mutations in 146 Human Pluripotent Stem Cell Lines and Their Differentiated Derivatives</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Nature Biotechnology</source>
<volume>42</volume> (<year>2024</year>): <fpage>1667</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1671</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41587-023-02090-2</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cpr13785-bib-0039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cpr13785-cit-0039">
<string-name>
<given-names>C. V.</given-names>
<surname>Dang</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>MYC on the Path to Cancer</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Cell</source>
<volume>149</volume> (<year>2012</year>): <fpage>22</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>35</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2012.03.003</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22464321</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cpr13785-bib-0040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cpr13785-cit-0040">
<string-name>
<given-names>Y. J.</given-names>
<surname>Wang</surname>
</string-name> and <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Herlyn</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>The Emerging Roles of Oct4 in Tumor&#x02010;Initiating Cells</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>American Journal of Physiology. Cell Physiology</source>
<volume>309</volume> (<year>2015</year>): <fpage>C709</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>C718</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpcell.00212.2015</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26447206</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cpr13785-bib-0041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cpr13785-cit-0041">
<string-name>
<given-names>L. N.</given-names>
<surname>Ding</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>Y. Y.</given-names>
<surname>Yu</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>C. J.</given-names>
<surname>Ma</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>C. J.</given-names>
<surname>Lei</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>H. B.</given-names>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>SOX2&#x02010;Associated Signaling Pathways Regulate Biological Phenotypes of Cancers</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Biomedicine &#x00026; Pharmacotherapy</source>
<volume>160</volume> (<year>2023</year>): <elocation-id>114336</elocation-id>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopha.2023.114336</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36738502</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cpr13785-bib-0042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cpr13785-cit-0042">
<string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Wang</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
<surname>Du</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
</string-name>, et&#x000a0;al., &#x0201c;<article-title>Transplantation of Chemically Induced Pluripotent Stem&#x02010;Cell&#x02010;Derived Islets Under Abdominal Anterior Rectus Sheath in a Type 1 Diabetes Patient</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Cell</source>
<volume>187</volume> (<year>2024</year>): <fpage>P6152</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>P6164</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2024.09.004</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cpr13785-bib-0043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cpr13785-cit-0043">
<string-name>
<given-names>B. T.</given-names>
<surname>McLelland</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
<surname>Lin</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Mathur</surname>
</string-name>, et&#x000a0;al., &#x0201c;<article-title>Transplanted hESC&#x02010;Derived Retina Organoid Sheets Differentiate, Integrate, and Improve Visual Function in Retinal Degenerate Rats</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Investigative Ophthalmology &#x00026; Visual Science</source>
<volume>59</volume> (<year>2018</year>): <fpage>2586</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2603</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1167/iovs.17-23646</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29847666</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cpr13785-bib-0044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cpr13785-cit-0044">
<string-name>
<given-names>A. O.</given-names>
<surname>Barnea&#x02010;Cramer</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>W.</given-names>
<surname>Wang</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S. J.</given-names>
<surname>Lu</surname>
</string-name>, et&#x000a0;al., &#x0201c;<article-title>Function of Human Pluripotent Stem Cell&#x02010;Derived Photoreceptor Progenitors in Blind Mice</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Scientific Reports</source>
<volume>6</volume> (<year>2016</year>): <elocation-id>29784</elocation-id>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep29784</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27405580</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cpr13785-bib-0045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cpr13785-cit-0045">
<string-name>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
<surname>Hirami</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Mandai</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Sugita</surname>
</string-name>, et&#x000a0;al., &#x0201c;<article-title>Safety and Stable Survival of Stem&#x02010;Cell&#x02010;Derived Retinal Organoid for 2&#x02009;Years in Patients With Retinitis Pigmentosa</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Cell Stem Cell</source>
<volume>30</volume> (<year>2023</year>): <fpage>1585</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1596.e6</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.stem.2023.11.004</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38065067</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>