<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="letter" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Exp Hematol Oncol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Exp Hematol Oncol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Experimental Hematology &#x00026; Oncology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2162-3619</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40001149</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11863397</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">604</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40164-025-00604-z</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Correspondence</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Bridging therapy with histotripsy prior to liver transplantation for hepatocellular carcinoma: a first case report</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Uysal</surname><given-names>Melis</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wehrle</surname><given-names>Chase J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Coppa</surname><given-names>Christopher</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kamath</surname><given-names>Suneel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Krishnamurthi</surname><given-names>Smitha</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>Charles</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hag</surname><given-names>Mohamed El</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Khalil</surname><given-names>Mazhar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fujiki</surname><given-names>Masato</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schlegel</surname><given-names>Andrea</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>Charles</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hashimoto</surname><given-names>Koji</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Aucejo</surname><given-names>Federico</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>David CH</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Jaekeun</given-names></name><address><email>kimj30@ccf.org</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/03xjacd83</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.239578.2</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0675 4725</institution-id><institution>Department of General Surgery, Digestive Disease &#x00026; Surgery Institute, </institution><institution>Cleveland Clinic, </institution></institution-wrap>9500 Euclid Avenue, Cleveland, OH 44195 USA </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/03xjacd83</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.239578.2</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0675 4725</institution-id><institution>Cleveland Clinic, Imaging Institute, </institution></institution-wrap>Cleveland, OH USA </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/03xjacd83</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.239578.2</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0675 4725</institution-id><institution>Department of Oncology, </institution><institution>Cleveland Clinic, Taussig Cancer Institute, </institution></institution-wrap>Cleveland, OH USA </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/03xjacd83</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.239578.2</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0675 4725</institution-id><institution>Diagnostics Institute, Department of Pathology, </institution><institution>Cleveland Clinic, </institution></institution-wrap>Cleveland, OH USA </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/03xjacd83</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.239578.2</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0675 4725</institution-id><institution>Department of Inflammation and Immunity, </institution><institution>Cleveland Clinic, Lerner Research Institute, </institution></institution-wrap>Cleveland, OH USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>25</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>25</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>20</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Histotripsy is a novel, non-invasive, non-ionizing, and non-thermal ablation technique that disrupts tumors using acoustic cavitation. We report the first use of Histotripsy as bridging therapy prior to liver transplant for hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) treated with histotripsy.</p></sec><sec><title>Case presentation</title><p id="Par2">A 59-year-old woman presented with Metabolic-Associated Steatotic Liver Disease (MASLD) cirrhosis (labMELD&#x02009;=&#x02009;14), hepatic encephalopathy, and a single 2&#x000a0;cm OPTN V lesion in the left lateral segment consistent with HCC. The patient underwent histotripsy treatment of the lesion as bridging therapy before receiving liver transplantation. Histopathology analysis of the explanted liver showed total necrosis of the treated area, with no residual viable tissue tumor.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par3">This case demonstrates the potential utility of histotripsy as an effective bridging therapy for patients with combined cirrhosis and hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) awaiting liver transplantation, with complete tumor necrosis on explant pathology demonstrating its therapeutic efficacy.</p></sec><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1186/s40164-025-00604-z.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Histotripsy</kwd><kwd>Liver transplantation</kwd><kwd>Hepatocellular carcinoma</kwd><kwd>Immune response</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; YUMED Inc. and BioMed Central Ltd. 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p id="Par4">To the editor: Liver cancer is a leading cause of cancer-related deaths, with hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) accounting for over 90% of primary liver cancer cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. The five-year survival rate for liver cancer in the U.S. is only 18%, the second lowest among all cancer types [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. HCC typically arises in cirrhotic livers and is often diagnosed at advanced stages, although improved screening has led to earlier tumor detection and more locoregional treatment options.</p><p id="Par5">A liver transplant is a potentially curative treatment for hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC), particularly in patients who meet specific criteria, such as the Milan or UCSF criteria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. These guidelines ensure the cancer is contained within certain size and number limits, optimizing outcomes post-transplant. Bridging treatments (such as transarterial chemoembolization (TACE), radiofrequency ablation (RFA), or microwave ablation) are often employed to control tumor growth and prevent progression while a patient awaits a transplant [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>].</p><p id="Par6">Histotripsy is a novel, non-invasive, non-ionizing, and non-thermal ablation technique that disrupts tumors via controlled acoustic cavitation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Worlikar et al. demonstrated its effectiveness in non-invasive liver tumor ablation, showing it prevents local progression and metastasis in rodent models [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Histotripsy achieves complete ablation, liquefying target tissue into an acellular homogenate that the body absorbs within two months [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. The initial THERESA trial reported 100% acute technical success and a 25% incidence of potential off-target, or &#x0201c;abscopal,&#x0201d; effects [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. The #HOPE4LIVER trial, the largest prospective study on histotripsy to date, included 18 participants, 41% of whom had HCC. Technical success was achieved in 42 out of 44 treated tumors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>].</p><p id="Par7">This case report aims to document the inaugural instance of histotripsy as bridging therapy prior to a liver transplant in a patient with HCC, along with the complete pathologic response of HCC in the explanted liver following histotripsy ablation.</p><sec id="Sec1"><title>Case presentation</title><p id="Par8">We report a case of a 59-year-old Caucasian female with morbid obesity (BMI 55&#x000a0;kg/m&#x000b2;) and cirrhosis from metabolic dysfunction-associated steatotic liver disease (MASLD), complicated by hepatic encephalopathy, thrombocytopenia and portal hypertension. An MRI on 8/14/2023 showed a 2&#x000a0;cm LIRAD-5/OPTN-5b lesion consistent with HCC. The patient had an initial AFP of 12.1 ng/ml. The patient underwent evaluation and listed for liver transplantation and the decision was made to pursue bridging therapy first.</p><p id="Par9">While a 6.5% extrahepatic shunt from the hepatic artery to the lungs does not constitute an absolute contraindication to radioembolization, concerns regarding potential pulmonary complications, particularly in the context of the patient&#x02019;s elevated BMI and planned liver transplantation, warranted careful consideration. Following evaluation by the multidisciplinary tumor board, histotripsy was selected as the optimal therapeutic approach.</p><p id="Par10">The patient underwent liver histotripsy with an ablative margin of 0.5&#x000a0;cm, the patient&#x02019;s pre- and post-histotripsy CT images can be seen in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a. Histotripsy was conducted in an operating room using the HistoSonics Edison System (HistoSonics, Plymouth, MN, USA) under general anesthesia. General anesthesia was necessary to minimize patient movement and ensure controlled respiratory motion during the procedure.</p><p id="Par11">
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Histotripsy for HCC <bold>a</bold>. Pre &#x00026; Post histotripsy CT <bold>b</bold>. Histotripsy simulation <bold>c</bold>. Preop US and operation set up <bold>d</bold>. Timeline</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40164_2025_604_Fig1_HTML" id="d33e346"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par12">One month later, she received an orthotopic liver transplant from a donation after cardiac death donor. The explanted liver demonstrated total necrosis of the area treated with histotripsy. The gross image of the macronodular cirrhotic liver can be seen in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a. There was no evidence of viable tumor cells at the site of the original tumor on H&#x00026;E staining and low magnification view of the region of interest showed a necrotic nodule from the treated HCC (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2c</xref>). High magnification of the explanted liver showed histiocytes and giant cell reaction at the edge of the treated tumor (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>d).</p><p id="Par13">
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Gross and pathology <bold>a</bold>. explanted liver <bold>b</bold>. untreated cirrhotic nodule (low-magnification, 1.25X) <bold>c</bold>. total necrotic nodule histotripsy treated HCC (below arrows, low-magnification, 4X) <bold>d</bold>. edge of treated HCC showing histiocytes and giant cell reaction (high magnification, 40X)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40164_2025_604_Fig2_HTML" id="d33e380"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par14">The patient&#x02019;s postoperative course was complicated by respiratory distress given morbid obesity, fungemia, but she was recovered and discharged to rehab facility postoperative day (POD) 21. Unfortunately, she passed away due to iatrogenic major vascular injury from the rehab facility POD 30.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par15">
This report describes the first use of histotripsy as a bridging therapy prior to liver transplantation for HCC, providing post-trial evidence of complete pathological response. While histotripsy is non-invasive and no histological data is available, liver transplantation revealed complete necrosis of the treated lesion. Although human data is lacking, these results align with animal studies by Worlikar et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>], which demonstrated complete tumor regression with histotripsy.</p><p id="Par16">Patients with HCC face a significant risk of waitlist drop-out during the six-month waiting period due to tumor progression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Locoregional treatments such as RFA, MWA, TACE, and TARE are well-established options for bridging these patients to liver transplantation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. While supported by robust evidence, these modalities have notable limitations, including their invasive nature, significant radiation exposure, limited real-time visualization of therapeutic effects, and inconsistent tumor control. Furthermore, these treatments often necessitate the suspension of systemic therapies, such as chemotherapy or immunotherapy, which can disrupt potential synergistic effects during a critical period. As a result, their use is typically confined to cases with curative intent. In the presented case, conventional bridging methods were not feasible due to hepatic-pulmonary arterial shunting, prompting us to opt for histotripsy ablation. This case highlights the successful use of histotripsy, suggesting it could be a valuable addition to existing HCC treatments, especially given its non-invasive nature and the risks associated with other bridging therapies.</p><p id="Par17">This case report has limitations, including its single-case nature, which may not be representative of broader patient populations. Future research with larger, controlled studies is needed to assess the efficacy of histotripsy in patients with HCC and various liver conditions.</p></sec><sec id="Sec3"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par18">Histotripsy shows potential as a bridging therapy for HCC. Here, we present the first case of complete tumor necrosis in explanted tissue after histotripsy treatment for HCC, demonstrating its initial use as a bridging therapy before transplantation. Further large-scale studies are needed to validate these findings.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.</p><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="40164_2025_604_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><caption><p>Supplementary Material 1</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>The study was conceptualized and conducted under the direction of Dr. David Kwon, Dr. Federico Aucejo and Dr. Jaekeun Kim. Data collection and analysis was performed by MU and CJW. Manuscript drafting was performed by MU and CJW. Critical manuscript review was performed by all authors.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>No funding was received for this study.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>No datasets were generated or analysed during the current study.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par19">Institutional review board (IRB) approval is waived as this is a case report.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par20">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par21">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>HCC</term><def><p id="Par22">Hepatocellular Carcinoma</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LT</term><def><p id="Par23">Liver Transplantation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MWA</term><def><p id="Par24">Microwave Ablation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IRB</term><def><p id="Par25">Institutional Review Board</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MASLD</term><def><p id="Par26">Metabolic dysfunction-Associated Steatotic Liver Disease</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LIRAD</term><def><p id="Par27">Liver Imaging Reporting and Data System</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>OPTN</term><def><p id="Par28">Organ Procurement and Transplantation Network</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>POD</term><def><p id="Par29">Postoperative Day</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Siegel RL, Miller KD, Fuchs HE, Jemal A. Cancer statistics, 2021. CA Cancer J Clin. 2021;71(1):7&#x02013;33.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Llovet</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Villanueva</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Singal</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Pikarsky</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Roayaie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title><source>Nat Rev Dis Primers</source><year>2021</year><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>6</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41572-020-00240-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33479224</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Llovet JM, Kelley RK, Villanueva A, Singal AG, Pikarsky E, Roayaie S, et al. Hepatocellular carcinoma. Nat Rev Dis Primers. 2021;7(1):6.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33479224</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mazzaferro</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Regalia</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Doci</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Andreola</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pulvirenti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bozzetti</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Liver transplantation for the treatment of small hepatocellular carcinomas in patients with cirrhosis</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>1996</year><volume>334</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>693</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJM199603143341104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8594428</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Mazzaferro V, Regalia E, Doci R, Andreola S, Pulvirenti A, Bozzetti F, et al. Liver transplantation for the treatment of small hepatocellular carcinomas in patients with cirrhosis. N Engl J Med. 1996;334(11):693&#x02013;9.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8594428</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crocetti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bozzi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Scalise</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bargellini</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Lorenzoni</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghinolfi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Locoregional treatments for bridging and Downstaging HCC to Liver Transplantation</article-title><source>Cancers (Basel)</source><year>2021</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>21</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/cancers13215558</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Crocetti L, Bozzi E, Scalise P, Bargellini I, Lorenzoni G, Ghinolfi D, et al. Locoregional treatments for bridging and Downstaging HCC to Liver Transplantation. Cancers (Basel). 2021;13:21.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parsons</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Cain</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Abrams</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Fowlkes</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pulsed cavitational ultrasound therapy for controlled tissue homogenization</article-title><source>Ultrasound Med Biol</source><year>2006</year><volume>32</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ultrasmedbio.2005.09.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16364803</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Parsons JE, Cain CA, Abrams GD, Fowlkes JB. Pulsed cavitational ultrasound therapy for controlled tissue homogenization. Ultrasound Med Biol. 2006;32(1):115&#x02013;29.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16364803</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ives</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>JS</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Fowlkes</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Cain</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pulsed cavitational ultrasound: a noninvasive technology for controlled tissue ablation (histotripsy) in the rabbit kidney</article-title><source>J Urol</source><year>2006</year><volume>175</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>734</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0022-5347(05)00141-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16407041</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Roberts WW, Hall TL, Ives K, Wolf JS Jr., Fowlkes JB, Cain CA. Pulsed cavitational ultrasound: a noninvasive technology for controlled tissue ablation (histotripsy) in the rabbit kidney. J Urol. 2006;175(2):734&#x02013;8.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16407041</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Worlikar T, Zhang M, Ganguly A, Hall TL, Shi J, Zhao L et al. Impact of Histotripsy on Development of Intrahepatic Metastases in a Rodent Liver Tumor Model. Cancers (Basel). 2022;14(7).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YN</given-names></name><name><surname>Khokhlova</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Khokhlova</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Histological and biochemical analysis of mechanical and thermal bioeffects in boiling histotripsy lesions induced by high intensity focused ultrasound</article-title><source>Ultrasound Med Biol</source><year>2013</year><volume>39</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>424</fpage><lpage>38</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ultrasmedbio.2012.10.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23312958</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Wang YN, Khokhlova T, Bailey M, Hwang JH, Khokhlova V. Histological and biochemical analysis of mechanical and thermal bioeffects in boiling histotripsy lesions induced by high intensity focused ultrasound. Ultrasound Med Biol. 2013;39(3):424&#x02013;38.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23312958</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Winterroth</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Fowlkes</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Examining and analyzing subcellular morphology of renal tissue treated by histotripsy</article-title><source>Ultrasound Med Biol</source><year>2011</year><volume>37</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>78</fpage><lpage>86</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ultrasmedbio.2010.10.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21144960</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Winterroth F, Xu Z, Wang TY, Wilkinson JE, Fowlkes JB, Roberts WW, et al. Examining and analyzing subcellular morphology of renal tissue treated by histotripsy. Ultrasound Med Biol. 2011;37(1):78&#x02013;86.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21144960</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vidal-Jove</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Serres</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Vlaisavljevich</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Cannata</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Duryea</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>First-in-man histotripsy of hepatic tumors: the THERESA trial, a feasibility study</article-title><source>Int J Hyperth</source><year>2022</year><volume>39</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1115</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/02656736.2022.2112309</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Vidal-Jove J, Serres X, Vlaisavljevich E, Cannata J, Duryea A, Miller R, et al. First-in-man histotripsy of hepatic tumors: the THERESA trial, a feasibility study. Int J Hyperth. 2022;39(1):1115&#x02013;23.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wah</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pech</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Thormann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Serres</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Littler</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Stenberg</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A multi-centre, single Arm, non-randomized, prospective European trial to evaluate the safety and efficacy of the HistoSonics System in the treatment of primary and metastatic liver cancers (#HOPE4LIVER)</article-title><source>Cardiovasc Intervent Radiol</source><year>2023</year><volume>46</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>259</fpage><lpage>67</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00270-022-03309-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36380155</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Wah TM, Pech M, Thormann M, Serres X, Littler P, Stenberg B, et al. A multi-centre, single Arm, non-randomized, prospective European trial to evaluate the safety and efficacy of the HistoSonics System in the treatment of primary and metastatic liver cancers (#HOPE4LIVER). Cardiovasc Intervent Radiol. 2023;46(2):259&#x02013;67.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36380155</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pommergaard</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Rostved</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Adam</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Thygesen</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Salizzoni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x000f3;mez Bravo</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Locoregional treatments before liver transplantation for hepatocellular carcinoma: a study from the European Liver Transplant Registry</article-title><source>Transpl Int</source><year>2018</year><volume>31</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>531</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tri.13123</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29380442</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Pommergaard HC, Rostved AA, Adam R, Thygesen LC, Salizzoni M, G&#x000f3;mez Bravo MA, et al. Locoregional treatments before liver transplantation for hepatocellular carcinoma: a study from the European Liver Transplant Registry. Transpl Int. 2018;31(5):531&#x02013;9.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29380442</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article>