<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Gen Intern Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Gen Intern Med</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of General Internal Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0884-8734</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1525-1497</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer International Publishing</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Cham</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39557754</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11861457</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">9184</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11606-024-09184-w</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Physician Documentation of Social Determinants of Health: Results from Two National Surveys</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9784-0521</contrib-id><name><surname>Iott</surname><given-names>Bradley E.</given-names></name><degrees>PhD, MPH, MS</degrees><address><email>biott@umich.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>Vaishali</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Richwine</surname><given-names>Chelsea</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/00jmfr291</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.214458.e</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000000086837370</institution-id><institution>Division of General Internal Medicine, Department of Internal Medicine, </institution><institution>University of Michigan Medical School, </institution></institution-wrap>Ann Arbor, MI USA </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/05p26gw61</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.428374.e</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0442 7108</institution-id><institution>Office of the Assistant Secretary for Technology Policy, US Department of Health and Human Services, </institution></institution-wrap>Washington, D.C USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>18</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>18</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>2</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>40</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>620</fpage><lpage>628</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>7</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2024</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Objective</title><p id="Par1">We measured physicians&#x02019; (1) perceived importance of having access to social determinants of health (SDOH) data received from external providers in the electronic health record (EHR); (2) internal SDOH documentation practices in the EHR, including whether physicians document SDOH in a structured format that may facilitate use; and (3) use of EHR SDOH data to identify community resources and make referrals on behalf of patients.</p></sec><sec><title>Approach</title><p id="Par2">We conducted a secondary analysis of two national physician surveys.</p></sec><sec><title>Participants</title><p id="Par3">Respondents from the American Board of Family Medicine Recertification Survey (ABFM, <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;4040), a survey of family physicians fielded 2021&#x02013;2022, and the National Physician Health IT Survey (NPHIT, <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3006), a survey of outpatient physicians across specialty areas fielded in 2022.</p></sec><sec><title>Key Results</title><p id="Par4">Under half of physicians felt that SDOH data were very important (ABFM: 44.8%, NPHIT: 30.8%). Although most physicians documented SDOH in the EHR (ABFM: 72%, NPHIT: 63.3%), fewer used structured documentation methods (ABFM: 56.3%, NPHIT: 33.2%). In both surveys, physicians who participated in value-based care initiatives, those for whom&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;10% of their patient population was considered vulnerable, and those who felt that their clinic had the resources to address patients&#x02019; social needs had higher likelihood of documenting SDOH. Sixty-two percent of family physicians reported using SDOH data for identifying resources and making referrals.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par5">In 2022, most physicians documented SDOH data in their EHR, yet fewer used structured methods, limiting data exchange opportunities to address patients&#x02019; social needs. Under half of physicians considered access to external SDOH data to be &#x0201c;very&#x0201d; important, suggesting greater reliance on data collected internally and missed opportunities to identify patients who need support. Variation in perceived importance of SDOH data access and SDOH documentation by physician characteristics indicate opportunities to support adoption of structured documentation tools facilitating SDOH data capture and exchange to improve patient-centered care.</p></sec><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1007/s11606-024-09184-w.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>KEY WORDS</title><kwd>Social determinants of health</kwd><kwd>Electronic health records</kwd><kwd>Documentation</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Society of General Internal Medicine 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p id="Par6">There is growing recognition that social determinants of health (SDOH) and social needs play an important role in shaping health outcomes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup> The shift towards value-based care initiatives and the use of SDOH data to inform population health interventions have motivated healthcare delivery organizations to screen patients and document SDOH data in electronic health record (EHR) systems.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup> EHR SDOH data may be used to facilitate patient care coordination, including tailoring medical care according to patients&#x02019; social situations or offering referrals to community resources to provide more equitable care that enhances patients&#x02019; health and well-being.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup> Beyond supporting patient care, capturing structured SDOH data in the EHR, rather than free-text notes, is critical to supporting downstream uses, such as for community health and population management, and sharing data to connect patients with the resources they need via referrals to community-based organizations.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup></p><p id="Par7">Recently, there has been significant development in data standards for structured SDOH documentation,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup> including LOINC and ICD-10 Z codes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup> Despite efforts to enable more structured, systematic collection of SDOH data, a recent study showed that physicians&#x02019; rates of documenting and reviewing structured SDOH data were lower than rates of documentation and review of other structured medical, behavioral, and family history domains.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup> There are several reasons why physicians may be under-documenting SDOH data, or not capturing the information in a structured format that would facilitate exchange and reuse. Physicians&#x02019; SDOH documentation practices may be affected by systemic, organizational, and attitudinal factors, including training on why and how to screen; having access to and awareness of, appropriate documentation tools, and access to resources to address social needs.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup></p><p id="Par8">Prior work has shown there is variation in physicians&#x02019; awareness of SDOH documentation tools, such as screening instruments or templates available in the EHR, which likely affects documentation practices.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup> How these tools are implemented within organizations may also affect physicians&#x02019; documentation and use of these data, as adding SDOH screening, documentation, and referral tasks to existing workflows may create burden for clinicians, potentially contributing to burnout.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup> Finally, physician SDOH documentation may be moderated by views on the relevancy of SDOH to their clinical practice or patient populations.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup></p><p id="Par9">This study contributes to existing literature on clinicians&#x02019; documentation of SDOH by describing physicians&#x02019; perspectives on the importance of having access to SDOH data received electronically from other providers (&#x0201c;external&#x0201d; data) in the EHR; physicians&#x02019; current SDOH practices, including whether physicians document SDOH in a structured format that would facilitate downstream use; and how these measures vary by clinician and organization characteristics. Finally, we examine whether internal or external EHR SDOH data were used to identify community resources and make referrals on behalf of patients.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>METHODS</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Study Sample</title><p id="Par10">We use two sources of data: (1) the American Board of Family Medicine Recertification Survey (ABFM), a national survey of family physicians, and (2) the National Physician Health IT Survey (NPHIT), a national sample of outpatient physicians across specialty areas.</p><p id="Par11">As further described elsewhere,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup> the American Board of Family Medicine administers a questionnaire during certification, which has a 100% response rate. Family physicians take this web-based survey on a rolling basis every year based on their initial year of certification, offering a nationally representative sample. The specific survey questions used in this study were developed and revised based on cognitive interviews with family physicians. The survey was fielded from December 12, 2021, to October 12, 2022. A total of 4040 family physicians completed the survey. After answering core questions about practice characteristics and technology use, respondents were randomized to complete one of two modules, one of which contained questions about physicians&#x02019; perceived importance of access to SDOH information from other health systems/organizations (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2034) and the other featured questions about how physicians documented SDOH in the EHR (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2006, questions shown in Appendix <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">A</xref>). We observed no significant differences in physician and practice characteristics between respondents who answered each question module. A separate subsample (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;809, 20% of the overall sample) was asked whether they routinely received comprehensive health assessments that include social concerns (e.g., housing and food security, poverty) and whether they used information on patients&#x02019; social concerns to identify needed community resources and make referrals.</p><p id="Par12">The NPHIT was fielded between April and November 2022. Physicians were recruited from a national database (Definitive Healthcare Physician Database). Physicians completed the survey online or via mail (3.6% response rate). Results are weighted for non-response and to generate national estimates. A total of 3006 physicians who provided outpatient care and used an EHR responded to the survey. The same questions about physicians&#x02019; perceived importance of access to SDOH information from other health systems/organizations and how physicians documented SDOH in the EHR from the ABFM survey were given to all NPHIT respondents, allowing us to gain insights into physician SDOH documentation practices from these two samples.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Statistical Analyses</title><p id="Par13">We use logistic regression models to measure associations between physician/practice characteristics and (1) importance of having access to SDOH data in the EHR and (2) use of different SDOH documentation modalities (checkboxes and diagnosis codes) that result in structured data versus free-text clinical notes, and (3) SDOH data utilization among family medicine physicians.</p><p id="Par14">The primary outcome of our first model was a binary variable indicating physician-reported access to external SDOH was very important (1&#x02009;=&#x02009;very important, 0&#x02009;=&#x02009;somewhat or not at all important). The primary outcome of our SDOH documentation modality models was binary variables indicating whether the respondent sometimes or often documented SDOH using any modality (free-text note, click button, or diagnosis code) or using a structured modality (click button or diagnosis code, 1&#x02009;=&#x02009;sometimes or often documented, 0&#x02009;=&#x02009;never, rarely, or did not know if documented). Our SDOH data use models featured two binary outcome variables indicating whether the respondent (1) routinely received comprehensive health assessments that include social concerns (e.g., housing and food security, poverty) and (2) used information on social concerns of the patient population to identify needed community resources and make referrals (1&#x02009;=&#x02009;yes, 0&#x02009;=&#x02009;no or don&#x02019;t know).</p><p id="Par15">Regression models were adjusted for age, gender, region, rural/urban, principal practice site, practice ownership, principal practice site size, proportion of patient population that was a part of a vulnerable group, EHR vendor, and participation in value-based care initiatives. ABFM models included a covariate indicating if the clinic had resources to address patients&#x02019; social needs, while NPHIT models included physician specialty type (primary care, medical, or surgical) and indicators of Medicare and Medicaid/CHIP acceptance. All relationships are reported in terms of predicted probabilities, which offer a useful way to describe the predicted probability of observing outcomes of interest for different values of explanatory variables.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>RESULTS</title><p id="Par16">Nearly half of ABFM respondents (43.7%) and NPHIT respondents (50.1%) practiced in hospital or academic settings (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Nearly a quarter of both survey respondents (ABFM 23.5%, NPHIT 25.0%) reported that&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;50% of their patient population was part of a vulnerable group. Most ABFM physicians (57.7%) felt that their clinic had the resources and tools, such as dedicated staff and linkages to community programs, to address patients&#x02019; social needs. Most NPHIT physicians participated in a value-based payment program (61.1%) and most accepted Medicaid/CHIP (80.8%) and Medicare (82.0%).
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Sample Demographics</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2"><bold>Physician, practice, payment, and EHR characteristics</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="2">ABFM (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;4040)</th><th align="left" colspan="2">NPHIT (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3006)</th></tr><tr><th align="left"># (raw)</th><th align="left">% (raw)</th><th align="left"># (raw)</th><th align="left">% (weighted)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="5">Gender</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Female</td><td align="left">2016</td><td char="." align="char">49.90</td><td align="left">1184</td><td char="." align="char">40.63</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Male</td><td align="left">2024</td><td char="." align="char">50.10</td><td align="left">1822</td><td char="." align="char">59.37</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5">Age</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> &#x0003c;&#x02009;50&#x000a0;years</td><td align="left">2417</td><td char="." align="char">59.83</td><td align="left">892</td><td char="." align="char">28.72</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> 50&#x02009;+&#x02009;years</td><td align="left">1623</td><td char="." align="char">40.17</td><td align="left">2114</td><td char="." align="char">71.28</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5">Specialty mix at principal practice</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Primary care/family medicine</td><td align="left">4040</td><td char="." align="char">100.00</td><td align="left">1282</td><td char="." align="char">42.65</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Medical</td><td align="left">-</td><td char="." align="char">-</td><td align="left">1175</td><td char="." align="char">39.09</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Surgical</td><td align="left">-</td><td char="." align="char">-</td><td align="left">549</td><td char="." align="char">18.26</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5">Principle practice site</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Private practice/urgent care</td><td align="left">1073</td><td char="." align="char">26.56</td><td align="left">866</td><td char="." align="char">33.84</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> FQHC/rural</td><td align="left">415</td><td char="." align="char">10.27</td><td align="left">171</td><td char="." align="char">6.58</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Academic/hospital/ED/HMO/health system</td><td align="left">1766</td><td char="." align="char">43.71</td><td align="left">1736</td><td char="." align="char">50.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Federal</td><td align="left">161</td><td char="." align="char">3.99</td><td align="left">-</td><td char="." align="char">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Other: family planning, workplace clinic</td><td align="left">625</td><td char="." align="char">15.47</td><td align="left">233</td><td char="." align="char">9.51</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5">Role in ownership of principle practice</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> No ownership</td><td align="left">3005</td><td char="." align="char">74.38</td><td align="left">2329</td><td char="." align="char">73.49</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Sole or partial ownership</td><td align="left">1035</td><td char="." align="char">25.62</td><td align="left">580</td><td char="." align="char">23.23</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Contractor/other</td><td align="left">-</td><td char="." align="char">-</td><td align="left">97</td><td char="." align="char">3.27</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5">Principle practice site size</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> 1&#x02013;10 clinicians</td><td align="left">-&#x000a0;</td><td char="." align="char">-</td><td align="left">1282</td><td char="." align="char">42.65</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> &#x0003e;&#x02009;11 clinicians</td><td align="left">-</td><td char="." align="char">-</td><td align="left">1724</td><td char="." align="char">57.35</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5">Principle practice site size</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Solo practice</td><td align="left">358</td><td char="." align="char">8.86</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> 2&#x02013;5 clinicians</td><td align="left">1314</td><td char="." align="char">32.52</td><td align="left">-</td><td char="." align="char">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> 6&#x02013;20 clinicians</td><td align="left">1271</td><td char="." align="char">31.46</td><td align="left">-</td><td char="." align="char">-&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> &#x0003e;&#x02009;20 clinicians</td><td align="left">1097</td><td char="." align="char">27.15</td><td align="left">-</td><td char="." align="char">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5">Percentage of patient population at principal practice site is part of a vulnerable group (i.e., uninsured, Medicaid, homeless, low income, non-English speaking, racial/ethnic minority, or otherwise traditionally underserved group)?</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> &#x0003c;&#x02009;10%</td><td align="left">1360</td><td char="." align="char">33.66</td><td align="left">566</td><td char="." align="char">19.43</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> 10&#x02013;49%</td><td align="left">1730</td><td char="." align="char">42.82</td><td align="left">1448</td><td char="." align="char">47.39</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> &#x0003e;&#x02009;50%</td><td align="left">950</td><td char="." align="char">23.51</td><td align="left">717</td><td char="." align="char">24.96</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Don&#x02019;t know</td><td align="left">-</td><td char="." align="char">-</td><td align="left">275</td><td char="." align="char">8.21</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5">Does your organization participate in one or more value-based care initiative(s), such as a patient-centered medical home, accountable care organization or pay-for-performance arrangement?</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Yes</td><td align="left">2736</td><td char="." align="char">67.72</td><td align="left">1837</td><td char="." align="char">61.14</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> No</td><td align="left">495</td><td char="." align="char">12.25</td><td align="left">508</td><td char="." align="char">19.14</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Don&#x02019;t know</td><td align="left">809</td><td char="." align="char">20.02</td><td align="left">661</td><td char="." align="char">19.72</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5">My clinic has the resources and tools, such as dedicated staff and linkages to community programs, to address patients&#x02019; social needs</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Agree</td><td align="left">2331</td><td char="." align="char">57.70</td><td align="left">-</td><td char="." align="char">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Neutral</td><td align="left">875</td><td char="." align="char">21.66</td><td align="left">-</td><td char="." align="char">-&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Disagree</td><td align="left">834</td><td char="." align="char">20.64</td><td align="left">-</td><td char="." align="char">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Accepts Medicaid/CHIP</td><td align="left">-</td><td char="." align="char">-</td><td align="left">2504</td><td char="." align="char">80.84</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Accepts Medicare</td><td align="left">-</td><td char="." align="char">-</td><td align="left">2520</td><td char="." align="char">81.99</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5">Region</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Northeast</td><td align="left">577</td><td char="." align="char">14.28</td><td align="left">651</td><td char="." align="char">24.26</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Midwest</td><td align="left">965</td><td char="." align="char">23.89</td><td align="left">742</td><td char="." align="char">21.48</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> South</td><td align="left">1408</td><td char="." align="char">34.85</td><td align="left">787</td><td char="." align="char">30.58</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> West</td><td align="left">1090</td><td char="." align="char">26.98</td><td align="left">826</td><td char="." align="char">23.67</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5">Location</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Urban</td><td align="left">3485</td><td char="." align="char">86.26</td><td align="left">-</td><td char="." align="char">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Rural</td><td align="left">555</td><td char="." align="char">13.74</td><td align="left">-</td><td char="." align="char">-</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><sec id="Sec6"><title>Importance of Access to SDOH Information from Other Health Systems/Organizations</title><p id="Par17">Most respondents in both surveys indicated they believed accessing external SDOH information in the EHR to be somewhat or very important (NPHIT&#x02009;=&#x02009;81.7%, ABFM&#x02009;=&#x02009;96.4%, Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). The number of physicians that endorsed these as &#x0201c;very important&#x0201d; dropped to 44.8% among ABFM survey respondents and 30.8% of the NPHIT respondents. Among NPHIT respondents, this varied by specialty, with rates of indicating external SDOH information as very important being lower among surgeons than primary care physicians and medical specialists (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> and Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Importance of accessing external SDOH information in the EHR across samples (ABFM, <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2006 and NPHIT, <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3006).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="11606_2024_9184_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p id="Par18">In a logistic regression model with ABFM respondents, those who believed that their clinic had the resources and tools to address patients&#x02019; social needs had a significantly higher predicted probability of reporting that access to SDOH information was very important (predicted probability&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.48, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.010, Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). In a logistic regression model with NPHIT respondents, the predicted probability of physicians reporting that access to external SDOH information was very important was significantly lower among surgical specialists (PP&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.21, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001) compared to primary care physicians (PP&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.32) and higher among medical specialists (PP&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.35), although the difference was not statistically significant. Additionally, NPHIT respondents for whom 50% or more of their patient population was part of a vulnerable group were more likely to value the importance of SDOH data than those with&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;10% vulnerable patients (PP&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.36, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001).
<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Logistic Regression Models Predicting Whether Access to External SDOH Information Was Believed to Be Very Important (Predicted Probabilities)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left">ABFM (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2034)<sup>^</sup></th><th align="left">NPHIT (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3006)<sup>&#x02020;</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="3">Specialty (Ref: Primary care)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Primary care</td><td char="." align="char">-</td><td char="." align="char">0.32</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Medical</td><td char="." align="char">-</td><td char="." align="char">0.35</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Surgical</td><td char="." align="char">-</td><td char="." align="char">0.21***</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3">Participates in value-based care (Ref: No or I don&#x02019;t know)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> No or I don&#x02019;t know</td><td char="." align="char">0.43</td><td char="." align="char">0.29</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Yes</td><td char="." align="char">0.46</td><td char="." align="char">0.32</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3">% of patient population is a part of a vulnerable group (Ref:&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;10%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> &#x0003c;&#x02009;10%</td><td char="." align="char">0.43</td><td char="." align="char">0.28</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> 10&#x02013;49%</td><td char="." align="char">0.44</td><td char="." align="char">0.30</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> &#x0003e;&#x02009;50%</td><td char="." align="char">0.49</td><td char="." align="char">0.36*</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Don&#x02019;t know</td><td char="." align="char">-</td><td char="." align="char">0.26</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3">Clinic has the resources to address social needs (Ref: Neutral)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Neutral</td><td char="." align="char">0.41</td><td char="." align="char">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Agree</td><td char="." align="char">0.48*</td><td char="." align="char">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Disagree</td><td char="." align="char">0.41</td><td char="." align="char">-</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, **<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, ***<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</p><p><sup>^</sup>Adjusted for practice type, practice ownership, practice size, region, urban/rural setting, EHR, respondent age and gender</p><p><sup>&#x02020;</sup>Adjusted for practice type, Medicare and Medicaid/CHIP acceptance, practice ownership, practice size, region, EHR, respondent age and gender</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Modalities of SDOH Documentation</title><p id="Par19">Seventy-two percent of ABFM respondents and 63.3% of NPHIT respondents reported sometimes or often documenting SDOH using at least one of three methods (clinical notes, checkboxes/buttons, or diagnosis codes) to document SDOH in the EHR (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). While most respondents in both samples documented SDOH via clinical notes, a higher proportion of ABFM physicians (56.3%) than NPHIT physicians (33.2%) used methods that would result in structured data entry (checkboxes/buttons and diagnosis codes) (Appendix <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">B</xref>). Among NPHIT respondents, those who provided primary care were more likely to use structured documentation methods relative to medical care physicians and surgeons (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>SDOH documentation in the EHR across samples (ABFM, <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2006 and NPHIT, <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3006).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="11606_2024_9184_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p><p id="Par20">Physicians who participated in value-based care had significantly higher likelihood of documenting SDOH via any methods (ABFM: PP&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.77, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001; NPHIT: PP&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.67, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001) and structured methods (ABFM: PP&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.61, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001, NPHIT: PP&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.38, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001) compared to those not participating. Additionally, among respondents from both surveys, physicians for whom&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;10% of their patient population was considered vulnerable had significantly higher likelihood of documenting via any method (ABFM: 10&#x02013;49% PP&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.73, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.002;&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;50%: PP&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.81, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001; NPHIT: 10&#x02013;49% PP&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.66, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001;&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;50% PP&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.71, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001, Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). We observed a similar association between patient population vulnerability and use of structured documentation approaches (ABFM: 10&#x02013;49% PP&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.57, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.009;&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;50%: PP&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.65, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001; NPHIT: 10&#x02013;49% PP&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.33, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.019;&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;50% PP&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.40, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001).
</p><p id="Par21">Among ABFM respondents, those who felt that their clinic had the resources to address patients&#x02019; social needs had higher likelihood of documenting via any method (PP&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.76, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.036) or structured methods (PP&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.61, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.027) than those who selected neutral or disagree to that statement. Among NPHIT respondents, medical specialists and surgeons had significantly lower likelihood of using any SDOH documentation methods (PP&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.62, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001 and PP&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.40, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001, respectively, Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>) and structured documentation tools (PP&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.25, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001 and PP&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.16, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001, respectively) relative to primary care physicians. Results for regression models predicting the likelihood of using each type of documentation modality are shown in Appendix <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">C</xref>.
<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Logistic Regression Models Predicting SDOH Documentation (Predicted Probabilities)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2"/><th align="left" colspan="2">ABFM (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2006)</th><th align="left" colspan="2">NPHIT (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3006)</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Documented SDOH using any method<sup>^</sup></th><th align="left">Documented SDOH via structured method (button or diagnosis code)<sup>^</sup></th><th align="left">Documented SDOH using any method<sup>&#x02020;</sup></th><th align="left">Documented SDOH via structured method (button or diagnosis code)<sup>&#x02020;</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="5">Specialty (Ref: Primary care)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Primary care</td><td char="." align="char">-</td><td char="." align="char">-</td><td char="." align="char">0.74</td><td char="." align="char">0.45</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Medical</td><td char="." align="char">-</td><td char="." align="char">-</td><td char="." align="char">0.62***</td><td char="." align="char">0.25***</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Surgical</td><td char="." align="char">-</td><td char="." align="char">-</td><td char="." align="char">0.40***</td><td char="." align="char">0.16***</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5">Participates in value-based care (Ref: No or I don&#x02019;t know)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> No or I Don&#x02019;t Know</td><td char="." align="char">0.61</td><td char="." align="char">0.47</td><td char="." align="char">0.59</td><td char="." align="char">0.25</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Yes</td><td char="." align="char">0.77***</td><td char="." align="char">0.61***</td><td char="." align="char">0.67***</td><td char="." align="char">0.38***</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5">% of patient population is a part of a vulnerable group (Ref:&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;10%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> &#x0003c;&#x02009;10%</td><td char="." align="char">0.65</td><td char="." align="char">0.50</td><td char="." align="char">0.53</td><td char="." align="char">0.27</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> 10&#x02013;49%</td><td char="." align="char">0.73**</td><td char="." align="char">0.57**</td><td char="." align="char">0.66***</td><td char="." align="char">0.33*</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> &#x0003e;&#x02009;50%</td><td char="." align="char">0.81***</td><td char="." align="char">0.65***</td><td char="." align="char">0.71***</td><td char="." align="char">0.40***</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Don&#x02019;t know</td><td char="." align="char">-</td><td char="." align="char">-</td><td char="." align="char">0.56</td><td char="." align="char">0.31</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5">Clinic has the resources to address social needs (Ref: Neutral)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Neutral</td><td char="." align="char">0.61</td><td char="." align="char">0.45</td><td char="." align="char">-</td><td char="." align="char">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Agree</td><td char="." align="char">0.76*</td><td char="." align="char">0.61*</td><td char="." align="char">-</td><td char="." align="char">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Disagree</td><td char="." align="char">0.71**</td><td char="." align="char">0.55**</td><td char="." align="char">-</td><td char="." align="char">-</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, **<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, ***<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</p><p><sup>^</sup>Adjusted for practice type, practice ownership, practice size, region, urban/rural setting, EHR, respondent age and gender</p><p><sup>&#x02020;</sup>Adjusted for practice type, Medicare and Medicaid/CHIP acceptance, practice ownership, practice size, region, EHR, respondent age and gender</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Use of SDOH Data Among Family Medicine Physicians</title><p id="Par22">Approximately 20% of ABFM respondents (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;809) were asked whether they routinely received comprehensive health assessments that include social concerns and whether they used information on patients&#x02019; social concerns to identify resources and make referrals. Most ABFM respondents reported receiving assessments with social concerns (71.0%) and 61.8% used information about patients&#x02019; social needs to make referrals. The share of respondents who used SDOH data to make referrals for patients was higher among those who documented SDOH using structured methods&#x02014;78.45% for those using checkboxes/buttons and 77.24% for those using diagnosis codes&#x02014;compared to respondents using free-text notes (67.45%).</p><p id="Par23">Respondents who believed access to external SDOH information was very important were more likely to use SDOH data to identify resources and make referrals (PP&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.71, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.004). Those who documented SDOH using any method and those who documented SDOH using a structured method were more likely to receive social needs assessments (PP&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.77, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001 and PP&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.83, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001, respectively) and to use SDOH data to identify resources and make referrals (PP&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.66, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001 and PP&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.73, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001, respectively). Respondents who felt that their clinic had the resources to address social needs, and those who participated in value-based care, had higher likelihood of using this information to identify resources and make referrals to social services for patients (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>).
<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Logistic Regression Models Predicting How ABFM Respondents Used SDOH Data (Predicted Probabilities, ABFM Subsample, <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;809)<sup>&#x02020;</sup></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left">Received social needs assessments</th><th align="left">Received social needs assessments</th><th align="left">Received social needs assessments</th><th align="left">Identified resources and made referrals</th><th align="left">Identified resources and made referrals</th><th align="left">Identified resources and made referrals</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="7">Access to external SDOH information was believed to be very important (Ref: No or I don&#x02019;t know)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> No or I don&#x02019;t know</td><td char="." align="char">0.68</td><td char="." align="char">-</td><td char="." align="char">-</td><td char="." align="char">0.58</td><td char="." align="char">-</td><td char="." align="char">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Yes</td><td char="." align="char">0.76</td><td char="." align="char">-</td><td char="." align="char">-</td><td char="." align="char">0.71**</td><td char="." align="char">-</td><td char="." align="char">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7">Documented SDOH using any method (Ref: No)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> No</td><td char="." align="char">-</td><td char="." align="char">0.55</td><td char="." align="char">-</td><td char="." align="char">-</td><td char="." align="char">0.45</td><td char="." align="char">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Yes</td><td char="." align="char">-</td><td char="." align="char">0.77***</td><td char="." align="char">-</td><td char="." align="char">-</td><td char="." align="char">0.66***</td><td char="." align="char">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7">Documented SDOH via structured method (button or diagnosis code) (Ref: No)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> No</td><td char="." align="char">-</td><td char="." align="char">-</td><td char="." align="char">0.58</td><td char="." align="char">-</td><td char="." align="char">-</td><td char="." align="char">0.46</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Yes</td><td char="." align="char">-</td><td char="." align="char">-</td><td char="." align="char">0.83***</td><td char="." align="char">-</td><td char="." align="char">-</td><td char="." align="char">0.73***</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7">Clinic has the resources to address social needs (Ref: Neutral)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Neutral</td><td char="." align="char">0.68</td><td char="." align="char">0.65</td><td char="." align="char">0.67</td><td char="." align="char">0.56</td><td char="." align="char">0.49</td><td char="." align="char">0.51</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Agree</td><td char="." align="char">0.78</td><td char="." align="char">0.76*</td><td char="." align="char">0.76</td><td char="." align="char">0.73**</td><td char="." align="char">0.69***</td><td char="." align="char">0.68**</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Disagree</td><td char="." align="char">0.58</td><td char="." align="char">0.61</td><td char="." align="char">0.61</td><td char="." align="char">0.46</td><td char="." align="char">0.49</td><td char="." align="char">0.49</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7">Participates in value-based care (Ref: No or I don&#x02019;t know)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> No or I don&#x02019;t know</td><td char="." align="char">0.66</td><td char="." align="char">0.61</td><td char="." align="char">0.62</td><td char="." align="char">0.45</td><td char="." align="char">0.47</td><td char="." align="char">0.48</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Yes</td><td char="." align="char">0.74</td><td char="." align="char">0.74**</td><td char="." align="char">0.74**</td><td char="." align="char">0.72***</td><td char="." align="char">0.66**</td><td char="." align="char">0.65**</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7">% of patient population is a part of a vulnerable group (Ref:&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;10%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> &#x0003c;&#x02009;10%</td><td char="." align="char">0.71</td><td char="." align="char">0.70</td><td char="." align="char">0.70</td><td char="." align="char">0.58</td><td char="." align="char">0.63</td><td char="." align="char">0.63</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> 10&#x02013;49%</td><td char="." align="char">0.72</td><td char="." align="char">0.73</td><td char="." align="char">0.73</td><td char="." align="char">0.64</td><td char="." align="char">0.60</td><td char="." align="char">0.59</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> &#x0003e;&#x02009;50%</td><td char="." align="char">0.73</td><td char="." align="char">0.65</td><td char="." align="char">0.66</td><td char="." align="char">0.73*</td><td char="." align="char">0.56</td><td char="." align="char">0.58</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, **<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, ***<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</p><p><sup>&#x02020;</sup>Adjusted for practice type, practice ownership, practice size, region, urban/rural setting, EHR, respondent age and gender</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p id="Par24">In two national surveys, we found that while most physicians&#x02014;particularly primary care physicians&#x02014;indicated that it was somewhat or very important to be able to view external SDOH information in the EHR, fewer physicians felt that having access to SDOH data was very important. The perceived value of SDOH varied by specialty, with fewer surgical specialists rating access to external SDOH data as very important. EHR SDOH documentation rates were relatively high among physicians overall, especially among family medicine physicians. However, rates of documentation using structured methods were lower, with about one-third of physicians and about half of family medicine physicians reporting using structured methods. Those working in medical or surgical specialties were less likely to document overall and using structured methods than primary care physicians.</p><p id="Par25">Variation in the documentation and use of SDOH data by specialty may be due, in part, to differences in perceived importance of accessing external SDOH data in the EHR which suggests there are opportunities to promote structured documentation and use of SDOH data in a variety of clinical settings. For instance, lower perceived importance of external SDOH data among surgeons relative to other types of physicians contrasts with known associations between SDOH and post-operative outcomes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup> While some SDOH screening and referral interventions occur in surgical settings,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup> many current efforts are focused in primary care settings.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup> Given that SDOH may play a role in post-operative outcomes, educating surgeons regarding the value of SDOH data in surgical and specialty settings may be beneficial. Future work should assess capacity for and interest in providing screening and referrals in specialty settings. In interpreting these findings, it should be noted that other members of the healthcare team, including community health workers, nurses, care coordinators, case managers, and social workers, may be more likely to conduct SDOH screening and offering resources to address social needs than physicians.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup> This may be due to workflow design, including having more time with patients or conducting screening during the rooming process. However, physicians play an important role in using SDOH data to adjust medical care decisions to accommodate social circumstances and to offer resources to address social needs.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup></p><p id="Par26">Not surprisingly, physicians who had a higher proportion of vulnerable patients were more likely to indicate that access to external SDOH data was very important. We also show that family medicine physicians who reported having the necessary resources in their clinics to address social needs were more likely to believe that access to external SDOH data was very important. Furthermore, perceptions regarding having the necessary resources to address social needs were also associated with greater collection and use of SDOH data, and identifying resources and making referrals. Having in-clinic resources for screening and referrals, education about the impact of SDOH on health, and training on how to address social needs may be important facilitators of conducting screening and using that information to inform clinical decision-making and to make referrals.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup> Those serving high proportions of marginalized patients may practice in resource-constrained environments, and thus, attention must be paid to ensure that patients have access to screening and referral resources regardless of where they seek care.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup> Physicians who serve vulnerable populations may have limited access to resources to address social needs, which in turn may perpetuate existing inequities.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup></p><p id="Par27">Sharable structured SDOH data helps to ensure physicians have access to the timely and accurate data about patients&#x02019; needs. Recent studies have demonstrated that EHR SDOH documentation may underestimate the prevalence of SDOH.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup> We affirm prior work indicating that documentation of SDOH occurs frequently via free-text notes, while the use of structured data capture tools remains limited.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup> In addition to primary care, those practicing in clinics engaged in value-based care or served a higher proportion of vulnerable groups were more likely to document using a structured method. Variation in SDOH documentation practices suggests the need for outreach to increase SDOH documentation rates among certain physician populations, such as specialists, as SDOH documentation has been shown to be important for care coordination<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup> and to support efforts to assist patients with social needs or adjust medical care decisions based on social circumstances.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup> Additionally, there are several standards in development which will require SDOH screening and referrals to address social needs, which may increase adoption of structured SDOH EHR documentation approaches.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup></p><p id="Par28">Efforts to increase structured SDOH documentation will be important to facilitate exchange and use of SDOH data.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup><sup>(p19)</sup> Value-based payment models and incentives are beginning to encourage the collection and use of these data,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup><sup>(p19)</sup> and starting in 2024, Medicare is requiring screening of all inpatients for food insecurity, housing instability, transportation needs, utility difficulties, and interpersonal safety.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup> As more patients are regularly screened for SDOH, structured SDOH documentation will be important for quality measurement and reporting, and indeed, several SDOH-focused quality measures under development will require reporting on the prevalence of SDOH screening.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup> Additionally, structured SDOH data may be used in clinical decision support algorithms to support tailoring medical decisions based on patients&#x02019; social needs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup> and in community resource referral platforms to facilitate referrals to local resources.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup> The increased prevalence of SDOH screening, and subsequent documentation of SDOH in the EHR, spurred by the new Medicare inpatient screening requirement further underscores the need to support all types of physicians on healthcare teams with resources to best make use of these data to support patients.</p><p id="Par29">Our findings suggest there is opportunity to improve structured data collection and use of SDOH data to address social needs. In recognition of the urgent need to create a more integrated health and social care system that can effectively meet patients&#x02019; needs and improve equitable opportunities for attaining health and well-being, the U.S. Department of Health and Human Services recently released a Call to Action urging clinicians&#x02014;including primary care physicians and specialists&#x02014;to consistently screen and identify patients with social needs using diagnosis codes, and to leverage partnerships with community-based organizations and community care hubs that can help facilitate care coordination and service delivery to address social needs.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup> Further research is necessary to determine how best to support clinicians as reporting on SDOH screening and referrals become increasingly required or strongly encouraged through financial incentives.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup></p><p id="Par30">This study has several limitations that must be considered. First, all included physician documentation measures relied on respondent self-report and may not reflect all documentation efforts in each clinic. Furthermore, these measures do not provide indication of frequency nor volume of EHR SDOH documentation or methods used. While the survey provides insight into the different types of methods used for SDOH documentation, it is unclear how often each of these methods is used for documentation.</p><p id="Par31">We show that while many physicians value having access to SDOH data from outside sources, fewer physicians consider these external data to be &#x0201c;very&#x0201d; important. While most physicians document SDOH data, yet fewer use structured methods, limiting opportunities for exchange or use of these data to connect patients to resources. Physicians&#x02019; perceived value and documentation practices varied by specialty, availability of resources to address social needs, participation in value-based care, and patient population vulnerability, suggesting there are myriad factors potentially affecting the documentation and use of SDOH data. As efforts are underway to develop tools to help inform medical care decisions and provide services to address social needs, it is critical to ensure physicians have access to complete and accurate EHR SDOH data and have the resources they need to effectively use data captured through screening.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="11606_2024_9184_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><caption><p>Supplementary file1 (DOCX 16 KB)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data Availability:</title><p>The data underlying this article cannot be shared publicly in order to protect the privacy of individuals represented in the dataset.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations:</title><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of Interest:</title><p id="Par32">The authors declare that they do not have any conflicts&#x000a0;of interest.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gottlieb</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Fichtenberg</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Alderwick</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Social Determinants of Health: What&#x02019;s a Healthcare System to Do?</article-title><source>J Healthc Manag.</source><year>2019</year><volume>64</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>243</fpage><lpage>257</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/JHM-D-18-00160</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31274816</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal"><bold>Gottlieb L, Fichtenberg C, Alderwick H, Adler N.</bold> Social Determinants of Health: What&#x02019;s a Healthcare System to Do? <italic>J Healthc Manag</italic>. 2019;64(4):243-257. 10.1097/JHM-D-18-00160<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31274816</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Healthcare Intelligence Network. <italic>2019 Healthcare Benchmarks: Social Determinants of Health</italic>. Accessed November 20, 2021. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://hin.3dcartstores.com/2019-Healthcare-Benchmarks-Social-Determinants-of-Health_p_5324.html">https://hin.3dcartstores.com/2019-Healthcare-Benchmarks-Social-Determinants-of-Health_p_5324.html</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">National Academies of Sciences, Medicine. <italic>Integrating Social Care into the Delivery of Health Care: Moving Upstream to Improve the Nation&#x02019;s Health</italic>. The National Academies Press; 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iott</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>Rivas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gottlieb</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Adler-Milstein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pantell</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structured and unstructured social risk factor documentation in the electronic health record underestimates patients&#x02019; self-reported risks</article-title><source>J Am Med Inform Assoc</source><year>2024</year><volume>2024</volume><fpage>ocad261</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jamia/ocad261</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal"><bold>Iott BE, Rivas S, Gottlieb LM, Adler-Milstein J, Pantell MS.</bold> Structured and unstructured social risk factor documentation in the electronic health record underestimates patients&#x02019; self-reported risks. <italic>J Am Med Inform Assoc</italic>. Published online January 12, 2024:ocad261. 10.1093/jamia/ocad261</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><bold>Vest JR, Adler-Milstein J, Gottlieb LM, et al.</bold> Assessment of structured data elements for social risk factors. <italic>Am J Manag Care</italic>. 2022;(1).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vest</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Grannis</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Haut</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Halverson</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Menachemi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Using structured and unstructured data to identify patients&#x02019; need for services that address the social determinants of health</article-title><source>Int J Med Inf.</source><year>2017</year><volume>107</volume><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>106</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijmedinf.2017.09.008</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal"><bold>Vest JR, Grannis SJ, Haut DP, Halverson PK, Menachemi N</bold>. Using structured and unstructured data to identify patients&#x02019; need for services that address the social determinants of health. <italic>Int J Med Inf</italic>. 2017;107:101-106. 10.1016/j.ijmedinf.2017.09.008</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">United States Core Data for Interoperability (USCDI). Accessed February 15, 2024. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.healthit.gov/isa/united-states-core-data-interoperability-uscdi">http://www.healthit.gov/isa/united-states-core-data-interoperability-uscdi</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">LOINC. Social Determinants of Health. Accessed February 15, 2024. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://loinc.org/sdh/">https://loinc.org/sdh/</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Centers for Medicare &#x00026; Medicaid Services. Improving the Collection of Social Determinants of Health (SDOH) data with ICD-10-CM Z Codes. Accessed February 15, 2024. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cms.gov/files/document/cms-2023-omh-z-code-resource.pdf">https://www.cms.gov/files/document/cms-2023-omh-z-code-resource.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iott</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>Adler-Milstein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gottlieb</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Pantell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterizing the Relative Frequency of Clinician Engagement with Structured Social Determinants of Health Data</article-title><source>J Am Med Inform Assoc.</source><year>2022</year><volume>30</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>503</fpage><lpage>510</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jamia/ocac251</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal"><bold>Iott BE, Adler-Milstein J, Gottlieb L, Pantell M.</bold> Characterizing the Relative Frequency of Clinician Engagement with Structured Social Determinants of Health Data. <italic>J Am Med Inform Assoc</italic>. 2022;30(3):503-510. 10.1093/jamia/ocac251</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marchis</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><name><surname>Knox</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hessler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Physician Burnout and Higher Clinic Capacity to Address Patients&#x02019; Social Needs</article-title><source>J Am Board Fam Med.</source><year>2019</year><volume>32</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>78</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3122/jabfm.2019.01.180104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30610144</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal"><bold>Marchis ED, Knox M, Hessler D, et al.</bold> Physician Burnout and Higher Clinic Capacity to Address Patients&#x02019; Social Needs. <italic>J Am Board Fam Med</italic>. 2019;32(1):69-78. 10.3122/jabfm.2019.01.180104<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30610144</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Liveris</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Caruso Brown</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Assessment and Evaluation in Social Determinants of Health Education: a National Survey of US Medical Schools and Physician Assistant Programs</article-title><source>J Gen Intern Med.</source><year>2022</year><volume>37</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>2180</fpage><lpage>2186</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11606-022-07498-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35710668</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal"><bold>Campbell M, Liveris M, Caruso Brown AE, et al.</bold> Assessment and Evaluation in Social Determinants of Health Education: a National Survey of US Medical Schools and Physician Assistant Programs. <italic>J Gen Intern Med</italic>. 2022;37(9):2180-2186. 10.1007/s11606-022-07498-1<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35710668</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iott</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Pantell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Adler-Milstein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gottlieb</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Physician Awareness of Social Determinants of Health Documentation Capability in the Electronic Health Record</article-title><source>J Am Med Inform Assoc.</source><year>2022</year><volume>29</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>2110</fpage><lpage>2116</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jamia/ocac154</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36069887</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal"><bold>Iott B, Pantell M, Adler-Milstein J, Gottlieb L.</bold> Physician Awareness of Social Determinants of Health Documentation Capability in the Electronic Health Record. <italic>J Am Med Inform Assoc</italic>. 2022;29(12):2110-2116. 10.1093/jamia/ocac154<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36069887</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pantell</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Marchis</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><name><surname>Bueno</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gottlieb</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Practice Capacity to Address Patients&#x02019; Social Needs and Physician Satisfaction and Perceived Quality of Care</article-title><source>Ann Fam Med.</source><year>2019</year><volume>17</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>42</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1370/afm.2334</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30670394</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal"><bold>Pantell MS, Marchis ED, Bueno A, Gottlieb LM.</bold> Practice Capacity to Address Patients&#x02019; Social Needs and Physician Satisfaction and Perceived Quality of Care. <italic>Ann Fam Med</italic>. 2019;17(1):42-45. 10.1370/afm.2334<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30670394</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fichtenberg</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Alley</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Mistry</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improving Social Needs Intervention Research: Key Questions for Advancing the Field</article-title><source>Am J Prev Med.</source><year>2019</year><volume>57</volume><issue>6, Supplement 1</issue><fpage>S47</fpage><lpage>S54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amepre.2019.07.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31753279</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal"><bold>Fichtenberg CM, Alley DE, Mistry KB.</bold> Improving Social Needs Intervention Research: Key Questions for Advancing the Field. <italic>Am J Prev Med</italic>. 2019;57(6, Supplement 1):S47-S54. 10.1016/j.amepre.2019.07.018<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31753279</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kostelanetz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pettapiece-Phillips</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Weems</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Health Care Professionals&#x02019; Perspectives on Universal Screening of Social Determinants of Health: A Mixed-Methods Study</article-title><source>Popul Health Manag.</source><year>2022</year><volume>25</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>367</fpage><lpage>374</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/pop.2021.0176</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34698559</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal"><bold>Kostelanetz S, Pettapiece-Phillips M, Weems J, et al.</bold> Health Care Professionals&#x02019; Perspectives on Universal Screening of Social Determinants of Health: A Mixed-Methods Study. <italic>Popul Health Manag</italic>. 2022;25(3):367-374. 10.1089/pop.2021.0176<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34698559</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kung</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Knox</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Capacity to Address Social Needs Affects Primary Care Clinician Burnout</article-title><source>Ann Fam Med.</source><year>2019</year><volume>17</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>487</fpage><lpage>494</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1370/afm.2470</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31712286</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal"><bold>Kung A, Cheung T, Knox M, et al.</bold> Capacity to Address Social Needs Affects Primary Care Clinician Burnout. <italic>Ann Fam Med</italic>. 2019;17(6):487-494. 10.1370/afm.2470<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31712286</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maani</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Galea</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Role of Physicians in Addressing Social Determinants of Health</article-title><source>JAMA.</source><year>2020</year><volume>323</volume><issue>16</issue><fpage>1551</fpage><lpage>1552</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2020.1637</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32242894</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal"><bold>Maani N, Galea S.</bold> The Role of Physicians in Addressing Social Determinants of Health. <italic>JAMA</italic>. 2020;323(16):1551-1552. 10.1001/jama.2020.1637<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32242894</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Everson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hendrix</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Adler-Milstein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bazemore</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Primary Care Physicians&#x02019; Satisfaction With Interoperable Health Information Technology</article-title><source>JAMA Netw Open.</source><year>2024</year><volume>7</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>e243793</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.3793</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38530309</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal"><bold>Everson J, Hendrix N, Phillips RL, Adler-Milstein J, Bazemore A, Patel V.</bold> Primary Care Physicians&#x02019; Satisfaction With Interoperable Health Information Technology. <italic>JAMA Netw Open</italic>. 2024;7(3):e243793. 10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.3793<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38530309</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Norton</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Dowd</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Log Odds and the Interpretation of Logit Models</article-title><source>Health Serv Res.</source><year>2018</year><volume>53</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>859</fpage><lpage>878</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1475-6773.12712</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28560732</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal"><bold>Norton EC, Dowd BE.</bold> Log Odds and the Interpretation of Logit Models. <italic>Health Serv Res</italic>. 2018;53(2):859-878. 10.1111/1475-6773.12712<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28560732</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><bold>Taylor KK, Neiman PU, Bonner S, Ranganathan K, Tipirneni R, Scott JW.</bold> Unmet Social Health Needs as a Driver of Inequitable Outcomes After Surgery: A Cross-Sectional Analysis of the National Health Interview Survey. <italic>Ann Surg</italic>.:10.1097/SLA.0000000000005689. 10.1097/SLA.0000000000005689</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name><surname>Scanlon</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Kisilu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Litzelman</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of community health workers in the surgical cascade: a scoping review</article-title><source>Hum Resour Health.</source><year>2021</year><volume>19</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>122</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12960-021-00659-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34602064</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal"><bold>Li HW, Scanlon ML, Kisilu N, Litzelman DK.</bold> The role of community health workers in the surgical cascade: a scoping review. <italic>Hum Resour Health</italic>. 2021;19(1):122. 10.1186/s12960-021-00659-z<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34602064</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ivers</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Levett</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Winch</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Home to health care to hospital: Evaluation of a cancer care team based in Australian Aboriginal primary care</article-title><source>Aust J Rural Health.</source><year>2019</year><volume>27</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>88</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ajr.12484</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30694000</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal"><bold>Ivers R, Jackson B, Levett T, Wallace K, Winch S.</bold> Home to health care to hospital: Evaluation of a cancer care team based in Australian Aboriginal primary care. <italic>Aust J Rural Health</italic>. 2019;27(1):88-92. 10.1111/ajr.12484<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30694000</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gottlieb</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wing</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A Systematic Review of Interventions on Patients&#x02019; Social and Economic Needs</article-title><source>Am J Prev Med.</source><year>2017</year><volume>53</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>719</fpage><lpage>729</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amepre.2017.05.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28688725</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal"><bold>Gottlieb LM, Wing H, Adler NE.</bold> A Systematic Review of Interventions on Patients&#x02019; Social and Economic Needs. <italic>Am J Prev Med</italic>. 2017;53(5):719-729. 10.1016/j.amepre.2017.05.011<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28688725</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name><surname>Ingram</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dougherty</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Centering the role of community health workers in social risk screening, referral, and follow-up within the primary care setting</article-title><source>BMC Prim Care.</source><year>2024</year><volume>25</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>338</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12875-024-02590-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39271996</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="journal"><bold>Larson EK, Ingram M, Dougherty E, et al.</bold> Centering the role of community health workers in social risk screening, referral, and follow-up within the primary care setting. <italic>BMC Prim Care</italic>. 2024;25(1):338. 10.1186/s12875-024-02590-3<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39271996</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR26" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Luther</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kulesa</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Social Determinants of Health: What Are They and How Do We Screen</article-title><source>Orthop Nurs.</source><year>2022</year><volume>41</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>88</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/NOR.0000000000000829</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35358126</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26" publication-type="journal"><bold>Johnson CB, Luther B, Wallace AS, Kulesa MG.</bold> Social Determinants of Health: What Are They and How Do We Screen. <italic>Orthop Nurs</italic>. 2022;41(2):88. 10.1097/NOR.0000000000000829<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35358126</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR27" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iott</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Anthony</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Provision of Social Care Services by US Hospitals</article-title><source>Milbank Q.</source><year>2023</year><volume>101</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>601</fpage><lpage>635</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1468-0009.12653</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37098719</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27" publication-type="journal"><bold>Iott B, Anthony D.</bold> Provision of Social Care Services by US Hospitals. <italic>Milbank Q</italic>. 2023;101(2):601-635. 10.1111/1468-0009.12653<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37098719</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR28" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harle</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Vest</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Accuracy of Electronic Health Record Food Insecurity, Housing Instability, and Financial Strain Screening in Adult Primary Care</article-title><source>JAMA.</source><year>2023</year><volume>329</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>423</fpage><lpage>424</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2022.23631</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36749341</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28" publication-type="journal"><bold>Harle CA, Wu W, Vest JR.</bold> Accuracy of Electronic Health Record Food Insecurity, Housing Instability, and Financial Strain Screening in Adult Primary Care. <italic>JAMA</italic>. 2023;329(5):423-424. 10.1001/jama.2022.23631<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36749341</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR29" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Porta</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improving patient well-being in the United States through care coordination interventions informed by social determinants of health</article-title><source>Health Soc Care Community.</source><year>2022</year><volume>30</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>2270</fpage><lpage>2281</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/hsc.13776</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35301764</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29" publication-type="journal"><bold>Singer C, Porta C.</bold> Improving patient well-being in the United States through care coordination interventions informed by social determinants of health. <italic>Health Soc Care Community</italic>. 2022;30(6):2270-2281. 10.1111/hsc.13776<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35301764</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR30" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Campagna</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Krsnak</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Addressing Social Determinants of Health: A Care Coordination Approach for Professional Case Managers</article-title><source>Prof Case Manag.</source><year>2022</year><volume>27</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>263</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/NCM.0000000000000590</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36206117</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30" publication-type="journal"><bold>Campagna V, Mitchell E, Krsnak J.</bold> Addressing Social Determinants of Health: A Care Coordination Approach for Professional Case Managers. <italic>Prof Case Manag</italic>. 2022;27(6):263. 10.1097/NCM.0000000000000590<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36206117</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><bold>Gottlieb LM, DeSilvey SC, Fichtenberg C, Bernheim S, Peltz A.</bold> Developing National Social Care Standards. <italic>Health Aff Forefr</italic>. 10.1377/forefront.20230221.857308</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><bold>S. Allen K, Gilliam NJ, Kharrazi H, McPheeters M, Dixon BE.</bold> Chapter 19 - Health information exchange: incorporating social and environmental determinants of health into health information exchange. In: Dixon BE, ed. <italic>Health Information Exchange (Second Edition)</italic>. Academic Press; 2023:423&#x02013;433. 10.1016/B978-0-323-90802-3.00023-X</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><bold>Jackson C, Bullock D, Dunlap V.</bold> Hospital IQR Program Requirementsfor CY 2023 Reporting (FY 2025 Payment Determination) Question and Answer Summary Document. Published online January 24, 2023. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.qualityreportingcenter.com/globalassets/iqr-2023-events/iqr12423/iqr_qa-summary-document_1.24.23_06132023508.pdf">https://www.qualityreportingcenter.com/globalassets/iqr-2023-events/iqr12423/iqr_qa-summary-document_1.24.23_06132023508.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">MIPS Clinical Quality Measures (CQMS) Quality ID #487: Screening for Social Drivers of Health. Published online November 2022. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://qpp.cms.gov/docs/QPP_quality_measure_specifications/CQM-Measures/2023_Measure_487_MIPSCQM.pdf">https://qpp.cms.gov/docs/QPP_quality_measure_specifications/CQM-Measures/2023_Measure_487_MIPSCQM.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><bold>Hayes T.</bold> HEDIS&#x000ae; Public Comment Period Is Now Open. NCQA. February 11, 2022. Accessed July 15, 2022. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncqa.org/blog/hedis-public-comment-period-is-now-open/">https://www.ncqa.org/blog/hedis-public-comment-period-is-now-open/</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">National Committee for Quality Assurance. <italic>Health Equity and Social Determinants of Health in HEDIS: Data for Measurement</italic>.; 2021. Accessed March 23, 2022. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncqa.org/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/20210622_NCQA_Health_Equity_Social_Determinants_of_Health_in_HEDIS.pdf">https://www.ncqa.org/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/20210622_NCQA_Health_Equity_Social_Determinants_of_Health_in_HEDIS.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">PatientEngagementHIT. How NCQA Created Measures on Social Determinants of Health Screenings. PatientEngagementHIT. February 23, 2022. Accessed July 15, 2022. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://patientengagementhit.com/features/how-ncqa-created-measures-on-social-determinants-of-health-screenings">https://patientengagementhit.com/features/how-ncqa-created-measures-on-social-determinants-of-health-screenings</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><bold>Nuzum R, Lewis C, Chang DI.</bold> Measuring What Matters: Social Drivers of Health. The Commonwealth Fund. 10.26099/q0pa-xf79</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">CMS Proposes Policies to Advance Health Equity and Maternal Health, Support Hospitals. Published online April 18, 2022. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cms.gov/newsroom/press-releases/cms-proposes-policies-advance-health-equity-and-maternal-health-support-hospitals">https://www.cms.gov/newsroom/press-releases/cms-proposes-policies-advance-health-equity-and-maternal-health-support-hospitals</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Quick Safety Issue 60: Understanding the needs of diverse populations in your community | The Joint Commission. Accessed July 15, 2022. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.jointcommission.org/resources/news-and-multimedia/newsletters/newsletters/quick-safety/quick-safety-issue-60/">https://www.jointcommission.org/resources/news-and-multimedia/newsletters/newsletters/quick-safety/quick-safety-issue-60/</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR41" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gold</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheppler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hessler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Using Electronic Health Record-Based Clinical Decision Support to Provide Social Risk-Informed Care in Community Health Centers: Protocol for the Design and Assessment of a Clinical Decision Support Tool</article-title><source>JMIR Res Protoc.</source><year>2021</year><volume>10</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>e31733</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/31733</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34623308</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR41" publication-type="journal"><bold>Gold R, Sheppler C, Hessler D, et al.</bold> Using Electronic Health Record&#x02013;Based Clinical Decision Support to Provide Social Risk&#x02013;Informed Care in Community Health Centers: Protocol for the Design and Assessment of a Clinical Decision Support Tool. <italic>JMIR Res Protoc</italic>. 2021;10(10):e31733. 10.2196/31733<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34623308</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><bold>Cartier Y, Fichtenberg C, Gottlieb L.</bold> Community Resource Referral Platforms: A Guide for Health Care Organizations. Accessed March 5, 2020. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://sirenetwork.ucsf.edu/tools-resources/resources/community-resource-referral-platforms-guide-health-care-organizations">https://sirenetwork.ucsf.edu/tools-resources/resources/community-resource-referral-platforms-guide-health-care-organizations</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">U.S. Department of Health and Human Services (HHS). <italic>Call to Action: Addressing Health-Related Social Needs in Communities Across the Nation</italic>.; 2023. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://aspe.hhs.gov/sites/default/files/documents/3e2f6140d0087435cc6832bf8cf32618/hhs-call-to-action-health-related-social-needs.pdf">https://aspe.hhs.gov/sites/default/files/documents/3e2f6140d0087435cc6832bf8cf32618/hhs-call-to-action-health-related-social-needs.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>