<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="discussion"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Oncol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Oncol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Oncol.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Oncology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2234-943X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12098273</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fonc.2025.1494417</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Oncology</subject><subj-group><subject>Opinion</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Breaking the dichotomy of HER2: highlighting the flaws of simplifying variables</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Pozin</surname><given-names>Jacob</given-names></name><xref rid="fn001" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2839794/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/investigation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/methodology/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/resources/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/validation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/visualization/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>Reid</given-names></name><uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2151863/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/investigation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/methodology/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/resources/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/validation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/visualization/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>Jennifer</given-names></name><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/project-administration/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/resources/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/supervision/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<institution>Department of Hematology/Oncology, Loyola University Medical Center</institution>, <addr-line>Maywood, IL</addr-line>, <country>United States</country>
</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Jo Chien, University of California, San Francisco, United States</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Silvana Marcia Bruschi Kelles, NATS UNIMED-BH, Brazil</p></fn><corresp id="fn001">*Correspondence: Jacob Pozin, <email xlink:href="mailto:jacob.pozin@luhs.org">jacob.pozin@luhs.org</email>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>09</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>1494417</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2025 Pozin, Shaw and Weiss</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Pozin, Shaw and Weiss</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><kwd-group><kwd>HER2</kwd><kwd>breast cancer</kwd><kwd>trastuzumab</kwd><kwd>IHC</kwd><kwd>dichotomization</kwd><kwd>mass spectrometry</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><funding-statement>The author(s) declare that no financial support was received for the research and/or publication of this article.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="0"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="27"/><page-count count="3"/><word-count count="1025"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>section-in-acceptance</meta-name><meta-value>Breast Cancer</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Forecasting and modeling is an inherently imprecise practice. However, the goal is to make predictions that are useful and as accurate as possible. Dichotomization, which is common in medicine, is universally considered a poor practice in modeling. Dichotomization leads to the loss of information, loss of effect size and power, spurious statistical significance, potential to overlook non-linear relationships, and loss of measurement reliability. (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>) Despite this, it is perceived to ease interpretability, simplify analysis by reducing complexity, or allow for comparisons between multiple groups. However, few physicians would argue that a hemoglobin A1c of 6.5% is equivalent to 12% &#x02013; despite both values meeting the criteria for diabetes. (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>) When a continuous variable is dichotomized, the information contained in the specific values vanishes. In contrast, an individual with an A1c of 6.4% is unlikely to have significantly different outcomes than that of an individual with an A1c of 6.5%. However, with dichotomization, they are now viewed as distinct entities &#x02013; decreasing the effect size and power. Although clinicians are unlikely to treat these scenarios similarly, problems arise when the dichotomized variable is less well understood and reporting on disease status is not standardized &#x02013; as is the case of HER2-low in breast cancer.</p><p>Amplification of the HER2 gene is present in approximately 15% of early-stage breast cancer and is associated with an aggressive phenotype and increased risk of disease recurrence. Fortunately, there are HER2-targeting agents, such as trastuzumab, a humanized monoclonal antibody that improve overall survival in this patient cohort. (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>) This landmark randomized control trial (RCT) used immunohistochemistry (IHC) to identify patients who may benefit from trastuzumab. (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>) IHC separates HER2 into semi-quantitative categories: positive (3+), equivocal (2+), and negative (1+ and 0). (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>) Although, HER2-positive tumors are most likely to respond to HER2-targeting therapy, the <italic>post-hoc</italic> analysis demonstrated that certain HER2-negative patients derived benefit from trastuzumab &#x02013; opening the door for a new subset of patients termed HER2-low. (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>) HER2-low is defined as IHC 1+ or 2+ with no amplification of HER2 by fluorescent <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization, a costly, but more accurate method of assessing HER2 status. However, when assessed in an RCT, trastuzumab failed to demonstrate a survival benefit in HER2-low breast cancer. (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>) In support of these findings, multiple studies demonstrate that the HER2-low classification is not a reproducibly defined subtype of breast cancer with any distinct prognostic implication. (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>) Despite these contradicting results, the drug-antibody conjugate, trastuzumab deruxtecan, showed improved overall survival in the HER2-low cohort. (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>) It even demonstrated an objective response rate of 30% in HER2-negative (IHC 0) metastatic breast cancer. (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>) Although the debate surrounding HER2-low as a distinct entity continues, the 2023 ASCO-College of American Pathologists encourages the reporting comment of IHC 0 versus 1+ to ensure identification of patients eligible for trastuzumab deruxtecan. These guidelines indicate the differentiation in IHC classification of 0 and 1+ is based on the detection of faint or barely perceptible incomplete membrane staining of amplified HER-2 in less or greater than 10% of tumor cells, respectively. (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>) However, one survey of the College of American Pathologists shows that approximately 20% of cases read by laboratories generate results with less than 70% concordance for IHC HER2 score 0 versus 1+ (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). Despite this discrepancy, DESTINY-Breast06 is currently investigating trastuzumab deruxtecan in HER2-low and HER2-ultralow (IHC&#x000a0;&#x0003e;0 &#x0003c;1+ expression). The results from the DESTINY-Breast06 trial presented at ASCO 2024 revealed that both HER2 low and ultralow cancers had similarly increased PFS and objective response rates (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Although the DESTINY studies utilize a novel IHC assay to assess HER2 status, it is not clear if this test has less discordance than prior assays. To address this problem, quantitative measurements of HER2 are being developed that utilize mass spectrometry. (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>) These methods of multiple reaction monitoring mass-spectrometry, which evaluate formalin-fixed-paraffin-embedded breast cancer tissues, have been found to both offer numerical quantification of HER2 levels that correlates well with established IHC classification, even at low HER2 expression levels (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>), as well as possibly distinguish between HER2-positive and HER2-negative samples with high specificity and sensitivity (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). Mass spectrometry identification of HER2 levels has also been shown to serve as a prognostic method in determining which patients will benefit from trastuzumab treatment. Specifically, higher HER2 levels (threshold &#x0003e;2200 amol/&#x000b5;g) were significantly associated with longer disease-free survival and overall survival in an adjuvant setting, as well longer overall survival in a metastatic setting (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). However, for quantitative HER2 methods to have clinical utility, they would need to be validated in trials studying whether they are predictive of benefit from HER2 targeted therapies in patients with HER2-positive, HER2-low, and HER2-ultralow breast cancer (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). Currently, we do not report ultralow HER2, however with HER2-ultralow showing clinical significance, it likely will change how we report HER2 status. For this reason, we need more standardized procedures, guidelines, and specialized training for pathologists in order to more accurately assess and report HER2-low and ultralow scores (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). Potentially, artificial intelligence IHC quantifier software will be used to consistently and accurately score HER2 expression (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>).</p><p>Although the aim of this essay is not to settle the debate surrounding the legitimacy of HER2-low or HER2-ultralow as distinct biological entities, there are more appropriate and statistically rigorous means of evaluating HER2-targeted therapies. As evidenced by multiple prior studies, the answer is not to arbitrarily bin variables. Rather, HER2 expression should be kept as a continuous variable, with different treatment modalities based on a spectrum of HER2 expression. Treating HER2 as a continuous variable will likely decrease the number of patients needed in a clinical trial. (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>) Furthermore, instead of spurious odds ratios determined by arbitrary cut points, the data may be presented as a simple line graph and confidence bands. (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>) As the landscape continues to develop surrounding the clinical significant of HER2 status, newer, more standardized modalities to accurately evaluate and report its expression are increasingly needed to help individualize patient care and improve outcomes.</p></body><back><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="s1"><title>Author contributions</title><p>JP: Conceptualization, Data curation, Investigation, Methodology, Resources, Validation, Visualization, Writing &#x02013; original draft, Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing. RS: Conceptualization, Data curation, Investigation, Methodology, Resources, Validation, Visualization, Writing &#x02013; original draft, Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing. JW: Project administration, Resources, Supervision, Writing &#x02013; original draft, Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s3"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s4"><title>Publisher&#x02019;s note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>MacCallum</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Preacher</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rucker</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>On the practice of dichotomization of quantitative variables</article-title>. <source>Psychol Methods</source>. (<year>2002</year>) <volume>7</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>19</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>40</lpage>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/1082-989X</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11928888</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Walraven</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Leave &#x02019;em alone - Why continuous variables should be analyzed as such</article-title>. <source>Neuroepidemiology</source>. (<year>2008</year>) <volume>30</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<page-range>138&#x02013;9</page-range>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000126908</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Royston</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauerbrei</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Dichotomizing continuous predictors in multiple regression: A bad idea</article-title>. <source>Stat Med</source>. (<year>2006</year>) <volume>25</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<page-range>127&#x02013;41</page-range>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/sim.2331</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>American Diabetes Association</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Standards of medical care in diabetes-2011</article-title>. <source>Diabetes Care</source>. (<year>2011</year>) <volume>34 Suppl 1</volume>(<issue>Suppl 1</issue>):<page-range>S11&#x02013;61</page-range>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/dc11-S011</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Braybrooke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hills</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Zulian</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Peto</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Trastuzumab for early-stage, HER2-positive breast cancer: a meta-analysis of 13&#x02008;864 women in seven randomised trials</article-title>. <source>Lancet Oncol</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>22</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<page-range>1139&#x02013;50</page-range>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1470-2045(21)00288-6</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Romond</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name><surname>Perez</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bryant</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Suman</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Geyer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Trastuzumab plus Adjuvant Chemotherapy for Operable HER2-Positive Breast Cancer</article-title>. <source>New Engl J Med</source>. (<year>2005</year>) <volume>353</volume>(<issue>16</issue>):<page-range>1673&#x02013;84</page-range>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/nejmoa052122</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wolff</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>McShane</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hammond</surname><given-names>MEH</given-names></name><name><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Mangu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartlett</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Human epidermal growth factor receptor 2 testing in breast cancer: American Society of Clinical Oncology/College of American Pathologists Clinical Practice Guideline Focused Update</article-title>. <source>Arch Pathol Lab Med</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>142</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<page-range>1364&#x02013;82</page-range>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5858/arpa.2018-0902-SA</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perez</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Reinholz</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hillman</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Tenner</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Schroeder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>HER2 and chromosome 17 effect on patient outcome in the N9831 adjuvant trastuzumab trial</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source>. (<year>2010</year>) <volume>28</volume>(<issue>28</issue>):<page-range>4307&#x02013;15</page-range>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/JCO.2009.26.2154</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fehrenbacher</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Cecchini</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Geyer</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Rastogi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Constantino</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Atkins</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>NSABP B-47/NRG oncology phase III randomized trial comparing adjuvant chemotherapy with or without trastuzumab in high-risk invasive breast cancer negative for HER2 by FISH and with IHC 1+ or 2+</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>38</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<page-range>444&#x02013;53</page-range>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/JCO.19.01455</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellizzi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Brock</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fadare</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanley</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Examination of Low ERBB2 Protein Expression in Breast Cancer Tissue</article-title>. <source>JAMA Oncol</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>8</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4</lpage>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamaoncol.2021.7239</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miglietta</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Griguolo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bottosso</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Giarratano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lo Mele</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fassan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Evolution of HER2-low expression from primary to recurrent breast cancer</article-title>. <source>NPJ Breast Cancer</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>7</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>137</fpage>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41523-021-00343-4</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34642348</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tarantino</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Tayob</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeselsohn</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Schnitt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Vincuilla</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Prognostic and Biologic Significance of ERBB2-Low Expression in Early-Stage Breast Cancer</article-title>. <source>JAMA Oncol</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>8</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<page-range>1177&#x02013;83</page-range>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamaoncol.2022.2286</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hein</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartkopf</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Emons</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lux</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Volz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Taran</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Prognostic effect of low-level HER2 expression in patients with clinically negative HER2 status</article-title>. <source>Eur J Cancer</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>155</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12</lpage>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejca.2021.06.033</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34311211</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schettini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Chic</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bras&#x000f3;-Maristany</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Pare</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Pascual</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Conte</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical, pathological, and PAM50 gene expression features of HER2-low breast cancer</article-title>. <source>NPJ Breast Cancer</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>7</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<elocation-id>1</elocation-id>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41523-020-00208-2</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33397968</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Modi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacot</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamashita</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sohn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Vidal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tokunaga</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Trastuzumab Deruxtecan in Previously Treated HER2-Low Advanced Breast Cancer</article-title>. <source>New Eng J Med</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>387</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>9</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20</lpage>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/nejmoa2203690</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35665782</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Di&#x000e9;ras</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Deluche</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lusque</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pistilli</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Bachelot</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Pierga</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Abstract PD8-02: Trastuzumab deruxtecan (T-DXd) for advanced breast cancer patients (ABC), regardless HER2 status: A phase II study with biomarkers analysis (DAISY)</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>82</volume>(<issue>4</issue>). doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/1538-7445.sabcs21-pd8-02</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wolff</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Somer</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Dowsett</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hammond</surname><given-names>MEH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Human Epidermal growth factor receptor 2 testing in breast cancer&#x0202f;: asco &#x02013; college of american pathologists guideline update</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>41</volume>(<issue>22</issue>):<page-range>3867&#x02013;72</page-range>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/JCO.22.02864</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Curigliano</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Dent</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Yonemori</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrios</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Shaughnessy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Trastuzumab deruxtecan (T-DXd) vs physician&#x02019;s choice of chemotherapy (TPC) in patients (pts) with hormone receptor-positive (HR+), human epidermal growth factor receptor 2 (HER2)-low or HER2-ultralow metastatic breast cancer (mBC) with prior endocrine therapy (ET): Primary results from DESTINY-Breast06 (DB-06) [abstract]</article-title>. <source>ASCO</source>. (<year>2024</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moutafi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Robbins</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yaghoobi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez-Morilla</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Xirou</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Quantitative measurement of HER2 expression to subclassify ERBB2 unamplified breast cancer</article-title>. <source>Lab Invest</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>102</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<page-range>1101&#x02013;8</page-range>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41374-022-00804-9</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Whiteaker</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bosch</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lerch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schoenherr</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Quantification of Human Epidermal Growth Factor Receptor 2 by Immunopeptide Enrichment and Targeted Mass Spectrometry in Formalin-Fixed Paraffin-Embedded and Frozen Breast Cancer Tissues</article-title>. <source>Clin Chem</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>67</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<page-range>1008&#x02013;18</page-range>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/clinchem/hvab047</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Do</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeo</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical application of multiple reaction monitoring-mass spectrometry to human epidermal growth factor receptor 2 measurements as a potential diagnostic tool for breast cancer therapy</article-title>. <source>Clin Chem</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>66</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<page-range>1339&#x02013;48</page-range>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/clinchem/hvaa178</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ivanova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Porta</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>D'Ercole</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pescia</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sajjadi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Cursano</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Standardized pathology report for HER2 testing in compliance with 2023 ASCO/CAP updates and 2023 ESMO consensus statements on HER2-low breast cancer</article-title>. <source>Virchows Arch Publsihed Online</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>484</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>3</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14</lpage>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00428-023-03656-w</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nuciforo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Thyparambil</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Aura</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Garrido-Castro</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vilaro</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Peg</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>High HER2 protein levels correlate with increased survival in breast cancer patients treated with anti-HER2 therapy</article-title>. <source>Mol Oncol</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<page-range>138&#x02013;47</page-range>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molonc.2015.09.002</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Parallel Reaction Monitoring-Mass Spectrometry (PRM-MS)-Based Targeted Proteomic Surrogates for Intrinsic Subtypes in Breast Cancer: Comparative Analysis with Immunohistochemical Phenotypes</article-title>. <source>J Proteome Res</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>19</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<page-range>2643&#x02013;53</page-range>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jproteome.9b00490</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frey</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mamilos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Minin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Banisch</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x000fc;nther</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>AI-based HER2-low IHC scoring in breast cancer across multiple sites, clones, and scanners</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>41</volume>(<issue>16_suppl</issue>):<page-range>516&#x02013;6</page-range>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/jco.2023.41.16_suppl.516</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolonel</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Efficiency loss from categorizing quantitative exposures into qualitative exposures in case-control studies</article-title>. <source>Am J Epidemiol</source>. (<year>1992</year>) <volume>136</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<page-range>464&#x02013;74</page-range>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/oxfordjournals.aje.a116520</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Selvin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Statistical Power and Sample Size Calculations</article-title>. <source>Stat Anal Epidemiologic Data</source>. (<year>2004</year>), <fpage>75</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>92</lpage>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/acprof:oso/9780195172805.003.03</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>