<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sensors (Basel)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sensors (Basel)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">sensors</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Sensors (Basel, Switzerland)</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1424-8220</issn><publisher><publisher-name>MDPI</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11679950</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/s24248091</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">sensors-24-08091</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Machine Learning-Based Modeling of pH-Sensitive Silicon Nanowire (SiNW) for Ion Sensitive Field Effect Transistor (ISFET)</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ayadi</surname><given-names>Nabil</given-names></name><role vocab="credit" vocab-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/" vocab-term="Methodology" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/methodology/">Methodology</role><role vocab="credit" vocab-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/" vocab-term="Software" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/software/">Software</role><role vocab="credit" vocab-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/" vocab-term="Data curation" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation/">Data curation</role><role vocab="credit" vocab-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/" vocab-term="Writing &#x02013; original draft" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/">Writing &#x02013; original draft</role><xref rid="af1-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lale</surname><given-names>Ahmet</given-names></name><role vocab="credit" vocab-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/" vocab-term="Methodology" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/methodology/">Methodology</role><role vocab="credit" vocab-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/" vocab-term="Validation" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/validation/">Validation</role><xref rid="af2-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0009-0004-3150-3564</contrib-id><name><surname>Hajji</surname><given-names>Bekkay</given-names></name><role vocab="credit" vocab-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/" vocab-term="Conceptualization" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/">Conceptualization</role><role vocab="credit" vocab-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/" vocab-term="Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/">Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing</role><role vocab="credit" vocab-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/" vocab-term="Visualization" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/visualization/">Visualization</role><xref rid="af1-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Launay</surname><given-names>J&#x000e9;r&#x000f4;me</given-names></name><role vocab="credit" vocab-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/" vocab-term="Conceptualization" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/">Conceptualization</role><role vocab="credit" vocab-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/" vocab-term="Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/">Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing</role><role vocab="credit" vocab-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/" vocab-term="Supervision" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/supervision/">Supervision</role><xref rid="af2-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="af3-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="aff">3</xref><xref rid="c1-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Temple-Boyer</surname><given-names>Pierre</given-names></name><role vocab="credit" vocab-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/" vocab-term="Conceptualization" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/">Conceptualization</role><role vocab="credit" vocab-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/" vocab-term="Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/">Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing</role><role vocab="credit" vocab-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/" vocab-term="Supervision" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/supervision/">Supervision</role><xref rid="af2-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="af3-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Velha</surname><given-names>Philippe</given-names></name><role>Academic Editor</role></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af1-sensors-24-08091"><label>1</label>Laboratory of Energy, Embedded System and Information Processing, National School of Applied Sciences, Mohammed First University, Oujda 60000, Morocco; <email>ayadi.nabil@ump.ac.ma</email> (N.A.); <email>hajji.bekkay@gmail.com</email> (B.H.)</aff><aff id="af2-sensors-24-08091"><label>2</label>CNRS, LAAS, 7 Avenue du Colonel Roche, F-31400 Toulouse, France; <email>ahmet_lale@hotmail.fr</email> (A.L.); <email>temple@laas.fr</email> (P.T.-B.)</aff><aff id="af3-sensors-24-08091"><label>3</label>INSAT, UT3-PS, INPT, University of Toulouse, 118 Route de Narbonne, CEDEX 9, F-31062 Toulouse, France</aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1-sensors-24-08091"><label>*</label>Correspondence: <email>jerome.launay@iut-tlse3.fr</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>18</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>12</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>24</volume><issue>24</issue><elocation-id>8091</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>21</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2024 by the authors.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>Licensee MDPI, Basel, Switzerland. This article is an open access article distributed under the terms and conditions of the Creative Commons Attribution (CC BY) license (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>The development of ion-sensitive field-effect transistor (ISFET) sensors based on silicon nanowires (SiNW) has recently seen significant progress, due to their many advantages such as compact size, low cost, robustness and real-time portability. However, little work has been done to predict the performance of SiNW-ISFET sensors. The present study focuses on predicting the performance of the silicon nanowire (SiNW)-based ISFET sensor using four machine learning techniques, namely multilayer perceptron (MLP), nonlinear regression (NLR), support vector regression (SVR) and extra tree regression (ETR). The proposed ML algorithms are trained and validated using experimental measurements of the SiNW-ISFET sensor. The results obtained show a better predictive ability of extra tree regression (ETR) compared to other techniques, with a low RMSE of 1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup> mA and an R<sup>2</sup> value of 0.9999725. This prediction study corrects the problems associated with SiNW -ISFET sensors.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>silicon nanowire ion-sensitive field effect transistor SiNW-ISFET</kwd><kwd>extra trees regression (ETR)</kwd><kwd>multi-layer perceptron (MLP)</kwd><kwd>nonlinear regression (NLR)</kwd><kwd>support vector regression (SVR)</kwd><kwd>machine learning (ML)</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><funding-statement>This research received no external funding.</funding-statement></funding-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-sensors-24-08091"><title>1. Introduction</title><p>Invented in 1970, the Ion-Sensitive Field-Effect-Transistor (ISFET) is described as a MOSFET device where the sensing layer is in direct contact with an analytic solution [<xref rid="B1-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Thanks to its compatibility with the standard CMOS process [<xref rid="B2-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="B3-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>], ISFET represents itself as a promising candidate in various applications in different fields, such as the food industry [<xref rid="B4-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], the pharmaceutical industry [<xref rid="B5-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="B6-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], the biomedical field, environmental monitoring [<xref rid="B7-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="B8-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="B9-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], agriculture applications [<xref rid="B10-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], etc.</p><p>In spite of the interesting potentialities demonstrated by ISFET, there remain certain challenges limiting its performance, which must be addressed. These limitations include (but are not limited to) the ISFET sensitivity close to the theoretical limit, the Nernstian of 59 mV/pH and the response time, which is relatively high and not suitable for new applications requiring real-time detection.</p><p>To overcome these problems, researchers are exploring the potential of nanomaterials and nanotechnologies to develop small, low-cost, highly efficient and sensitive biosensors with a wide range of applications. Silicon nanowires (SiNW) and carbon nanotubes (CNT) are examples of promising sensing materials [<xref rid="B11-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Their size, comparable to that of biological species, makes silicon nanowires (SiNW) an ideal interface between biological media and physicists&#x02019; tools. Moreover, their high surface-to-volume ratio makes them particularly sensitive to surface charge effects. These unique and unexpected properties of nanoscale materials make them ideal candidates for sensing applications.</p><p>The development of the ISFET sensor based on silicon nanowires (SiNW) appears to be the ideal candidate, offering good sensitivity thanks to a high surface-to-volume ratio [<xref rid="B12-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="B13-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="B14-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="B15-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Moreover, SiNW-ISFET sensors are inexpensive, easy to manufacture and reliable.</p><p>The sensing mechanism of SiNW-ISFET is based on the accumulation of charged molecules on the nanowire surface, which leads to a surface potential shift. The transistor then responds to changes in the surface potential with a threshold voltage shift &#x00394;Vth.</p><p>Metallic alloy nanoparticles possess excellent electronic properties, but their stability is limited due to low resistance to environmental factors, such as temperature, oxygen, and electromagnetic radiation. In contrast, oxide compounds, including complex iron oxides, provide greater stability at temperatures up to 1000 &#x000b0;C, making them promising for practical applications [<xref rid="B16-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>].</p><p>With the recent technological development of the Internet of Things (IoT), the SiNW-ISFET sensors can be also deployed at remote sites for the collection of data which will be transmitted in real time to the supervisor for analysis and decision making [<xref rid="B17-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. One of the fundamental monitoring parameters in these applications is the precise measurement of pH [<xref rid="B18-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="B19-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. The development of accurate models for pH detection is essential to extract reliable information from the data collected.</p><p>Since 1992, several studies have focused on the modeling of the behavior of the ISFET sensor. Sergio Martinoia et al. were the first to develop a macro-model to simulate it under various physico-chemical conditions, including temperature variations [<xref rid="B20-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. This model is based on the site-binding model combined with the MOSFET transistor model. In addition, the ISFET model is developed and implemented in the SPICE simulation program. The detection behavior of Ta<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> ISFET has been studied by Chuan et al., using Mathematica calculation software [<xref rid="B21-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Andrzej Napieralski et al. modeled the behavior of the ISFET sensor using the mixed language VHDL-AMS [<xref rid="B22-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. B. Hajji et al. studied the influence of temperature on the pH-ISFET response using the Orcad PSPICE tool, and the Matlab R2006a software [<xref rid="B23-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. S. E. Naimi et al. presented the modeling of the pH-ChemFET response using the genetic algorithm [<xref rid="B24-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. The simplified version of the EKV model combined with the site binding model was used by S. E. Naimi et al. to describe the behavior of ISFET with respect to temperature and pH change.</p><p>A simplified model based on BSIM was proposed by N. Ayadi et al. to analyze the performance of the SiNW ISFET microsensor [<xref rid="B25-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. The use of the SiNW ISFET-based pH sensors for prolonged duration in various monitoring applications requires a robust ion-sensitive FET (ISFET) model to accurately predict pH values of unknown samples. The application of artificial intelligence (AI) to the SiNW ISFET sensor makes it possible to develop an efficient and precise model. This technique (ML) should be able to learn the patterns from labelled train data and apply these learning over unseen data for correct predictions. Four most popular supervised machine learning techniques are employed to learn the characteristics of the silicon nanowire ISFET sensor based on experimental data: neural networks or Multi-Layer Perceptron (MLP), Nonlinear Regression (NLR), Support Vector Regression (SVR) and Extra Trees Regression (ETR). The first works on modeling and compensation of ISFET temperature drift based on ML were presented by the authors of the papers [<xref rid="B26-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="B27-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="B28-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="B29-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. These studies aimed to compare the performance of different ML models. Sinha et al. proposed the first ISFET temporal drift compensation model using an ML technique called Bayesian inference [<xref rid="B29-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. The use of these (ML) techniques can mitigate the need for complex subsystems reported in the literature for sensor drift compensation tasks. Nevertheless, no existing work has investigated the application of machine learning algorithms for modeling silicon nanowire (SiNW)-based ISFET sensor.</p><p>In this study, we focus on the development of an efficient model of the SiNW-ISFET sensor capable of efficiently predicting measurements of pH values using artificial intelligence (AI) techniques. Four models have been developed in this work and compared with real measurements in order to determine which one best guarantees the performance of the SiNW-ISFET sensor, namely: Multi-Layer Perceptron (MLP), Nonlinear Regression (NLR), Support Vector Regression (SVR), and Extra Trees Regression (ETR).</p><p>This paper is therefore organized in four sections: <xref rid="sec1-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="sec">Section 1</xref>, introduction; <xref rid="sec2-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="sec">Section 2</xref>, Modeling SiNW-ISFET using machine learning (ML) techniques; <xref rid="sec3-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="sec">Section 3</xref>, results and discussion; and <xref rid="sec4-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="sec">Section 4</xref>, conclusions.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-sensors-24-08091"><title>2. Modeling SiNW-ISFET Using Machine Learning (ML) Techniques</title><p>The supervised learning used in this work is the machine learning (ML) task of learning a function that associates an input with an output based on examples of input&#x02013;output pairs. Given a training set of n examples of input&#x02013;output pairs (x1, y1), (x2, y2), &#x02026; (xn, yn), machine learning (ML) generates each new value yj by the mapping function f defined by the following Equation (1). In this work, Y is associated with the current Ids.
<disp-formula id="FD1-sensors-24-08091"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="mm1" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Y</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">X</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>Through this equation, we deduce that ML models are trained using a set of labeled data (80% of the data), where the model learns each data type. Once the training process is complete, the model is tested on the test data (20% of the data) and then predicts the result.</p><p>All the algorithms used in this work are implemented using popular machine learning libraries in Python, such as scikit-learn and TensorFlow. These libraries offer a wide range of tools and features for efficiently creating, training and evaluating machine learning models.</p><p>In this work, we have tried the four most popular supervised machine learning techniques to learn the characteristics of the silicon nanowires ISFET sensor based on experimental data. These techniques are respectively, the Neural Networks or the Multi-Layer Perceptron (MLP), the Nonlinear Regression (NLR), the Support Vector Regression (SVR) and Extra Trees Regression (ETR) (<xref rid="sensors-24-08091-f001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>).</p><p>The aim of examining these different ML algorithms is to select the best algorithm that seems closest to the assigned function, and to choose the right combination of hyperparameters.</p><sec id="sec2dot1-sensors-24-08091"><title>2.1. Multi-Layer Perceptron Neural Networks</title><p>The Artificial Neural Networks are powerful tools for the simulation and prediction of I-V characteristics of ISFETs sensors. In particular, Multilayer Perception (MLP) is considered as the most common Neural Network model (<xref rid="sensors-24-08091-f002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>), consisting of successive linear transformations followed by processing with non-linear activation functions.</p><p>In this work, the developed MLP is a feed forward network including three layers as shown in <xref rid="sensors-24-08091-f002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>The input layer with five neurons; each neuron is associated with a parameter such as the Vgs, the nanowire length, the number of wires, the gate lengths and the pH;</p></list-item><list-item><p>One hidden layer of Multilayer Perception;</p></list-item><list-item><p>An output layer with a single neuron associated with the courant Ids.</p></list-item></list></p><p>A split ratio of 80&#x02013;20% is used to divide the data into training and testing sets. MLP is trained with 80% experimental data using the Levenberg Marquardt (LM) algorithm for faster convergence, and 20% experimental data are used for the test.</p><p>The output of MLP Ids is determined as a nonlinearity activation function, applied to the linear combination of the input vector presented by Equation (1) [<xref rid="B30-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="B31-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>].
<disp-formula id="FD2-sensors-24-08091"><label>(2)</label><mml:math id="mm2" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Y</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo mathsize="75%">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>and</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1,2</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02026;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
where Wij is the weight connecting the jth neuron in the output layer; b is the bias termand; and n is the number of neurons in the output layer.</p><p>The output activation <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm3" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is given by:<disp-formula id="FD3-sensors-24-08091"><label>(3)</label><mml:math id="mm4" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>The hidden and the output layers are processed using a softmax activation function as shown in Equation (4):<disp-formula id="FD4-sensors-24-08091"><label>(4)</label><mml:math id="mm5" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:munderover><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">k</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">k</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm6" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the net input given by:
<disp-formula id="FD5-sensors-24-08091"><label>(5)</label><mml:math id="mm7" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo mathsize="75%">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">q</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>and</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1,2</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02026;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
where s is the number of neurons in the hidden layer; q is the number of neurons in the input layer; b<sub>l</sub> is the bias term; and w is the weighting factor [<xref rid="B31-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. In this work, the main MLP key parameters (Equation (5)) are defined as follows:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><inline-formula><mml:math id="mm8" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the connecting weight;</p></list-item><list-item><p><inline-formula><mml:math id="mm9" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x02032;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02026;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the output from ith neuron of the first hidden layer;</p></list-item><list-item><p><inline-formula><mml:math id="mm10" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">M</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">L</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the output of the only neuron in the output layer.</p></list-item></list>
</p><p>The input layer includes five neurons; each neuron is associated with a parameter such as the V<sub>gs</sub>, the nanowire length (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm11" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">w</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), the number of wires (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm12" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), the gate lengths (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm13" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">L</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) and the pH;
<disp-formula id="FD6-sensors-24-08091"><label>(6)</label><mml:math id="mm14" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>21</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>31</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>41</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>51</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">g</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">w</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">p</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">H</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">L</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">N</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>For the first hidden layer, we replace the input layer in Equation (5):<disp-formula id="FD7-sensors-24-08091"><label>(7)</label><mml:math id="mm15" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mo>&#x022ee;</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>101</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>&#x022ef;</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>51</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mo>&#x022ee;</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>&#x022f1;</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>&#x022ee;</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>110</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>&#x022ef;</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>510</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">g</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">w</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">p</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">H</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">L</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">N</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mo>&#x022ee;</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>The first hidden layer uses a softmax activation function, therefore, it is noted as:<disp-formula id="FD8-sensors-24-08091"><label>(8)</label><mml:math id="mm16" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02032;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mo>&#x022ee;</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>101</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02032;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02026;</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>101</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mo>&#x022ee;</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>101</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02026;</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>101</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>For the output layer, replacing Equation (8) in Equation (2), the new equation is written as follow:<disp-formula id="FD9-sensors-24-08091"><label>(9)</label><mml:math id="mm17" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">M</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">L</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02032;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>21</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>21</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02032;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02026;</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>101</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>101</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02032;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>Finally, to determine the model output, the flowing set up is processed, as noted in the Program flow chart of Multilayer Perception (MLP) (<xref rid="sensors-24-08091-f003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>).
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Calculation of the Error</p></list-item></list>
<disp-formula id="FD10-sensors-24-08091"><label>(10)</label><mml:math id="mm18" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">M</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">L</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p><p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Weight Updating</p></list-item></list><disp-formula id="FD11-sensors-24-08091"><label>(11)</label><mml:math id="mm19" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mo>&#x02206;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mo>&#x02206;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>21</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mo>&#x022ee;</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02206;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>101</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>21</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mo>&#x022ee;</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>101</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
where &#x003b1; is the learning rate.
</p><p>
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>New Weights Calculation</p></list-item></list>
<disp-formula id="FD12-sensors-24-08091">
<label>(12)</label>
<mml:math id="mm20" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">w</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>21</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">w</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mo>&#x022ee;</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>101</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">w</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>21</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mo>&#x022ee;</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>101</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mo>&#x02206;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mo>&#x02206;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>21</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mo>&#x022ee;</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02206;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>101</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
</p><p><xref rid="sensors-24-08091-f003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref> illustrates the functioning of the Multilayer Perceptron (MLP) algorithm. The process begins with downloading the dataset, followed by preparing the input and output variables. Next, the input features are normalized to ensure a uniform scale across the dataset. The model is then defined and trained on 80% of the data, using the backpropagation gradient algorithm for training. Evaluation is based on calculating the error e (the difference between Ids calculated and Ids measured), which should be minimized to assess the model&#x02019;s performance across multiple subsets of the dataset. Once trained, the models are deployed to predict new data instances. Finally, the error indicators R<sup>2</sup>, RMSE, and MAE are used to effectively evaluate the predictive capability of the model.</p></sec><sec id="sec2dot2-sensors-24-08091"><title>2.2. Support Vector Regression</title><p>Support Vector Machines (SVM) are supervised learning models with associated learning algorithms that analyze data used for classification and regression analysis. They are very effective at analyzing input and output parameters because of their global minima. The SVM method is called support vector regression (SVR), when used for prediction (<xref rid="sensors-24-08091-f004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>). In fact, it represents a nonlinear regression algorithm where the data sample inputs are represented in a high-dimensional feature domain for nonlinear matching [<xref rid="B32-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="B33-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="B34-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>].</p><p>The use of the SVR method requires a set of training data determined by <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm21" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">y</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> where xi is the ith element of input vector in <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm22" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> dimensional space and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm23" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">y</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the actual value corresponding to <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm24" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. In the case study, the input vectors are respectively the gate voltage (V<sub>gs</sub>), the nanowire length (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm25" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">w</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), the number of wires (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm26" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), the gate lengths (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm27" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">L</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) and the (pH). While, the output is the source drain current (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm28" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>). Furthermore, the evaluation of the main key parameters is based on the estimation function <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm29" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> shown in Equation (13) [<xref rid="B34-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]:<disp-formula id="FD13-sensors-24-08091"><label>(13)</label><mml:math id="mm30" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">y</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
where f(x) denotes the forecasting values; <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm31" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the mapping function of kernel space for extracting the character from the original space; w is a weight vector; and b is the bias.</p><p>To minimize the structure risk and reduce the model complexity with respect to the training data, a sensitive loss function &#x003b5; is integrated in the SVR as suggested by Vabnik [<xref rid="B35-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Obviously, it is used when the error is not penalized as long as it is less than &#x003b5;. This function is able to transform the regression problem into an optimization one as described by Equation (14):<disp-formula id="FD14-sensors-24-08091"><label>(14)</label><mml:math id="mm32" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">L</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced open="{" close="" separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mfenced open="|" close="|" separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">y</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>&#x02264;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced open="|" close="|" separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">y</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b5;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi>otherwise</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>For more details, the SVR method objective is to find the optimum hyperplane and minimize the error between the training data and &#x003b5;-insensitive loss function. This could be performed by minimizing the overall errors, as follows [<xref rid="B36-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]:<disp-formula id="FD15-sensors-24-08091"><label>(15)</label><mml:math id="mm33" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">w</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:munderover><mml:mo mathsize="140%">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>max</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02061;</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b5;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
where C is the penalty applied over training errors and &#x003b5; is the user-specified positive constant.</p><sec><title>Kernel Function</title><p>The Kernel function is one of the main of SVR function. In fact, the SVR performance is deeply dependent on the selected kernel function parameters. In this work, the Gaussian kernel (RBF Kernel) function G(xi, xj) has been employed to get the best performance and adjust the Key Kernel parameter (&#x003b3;) [<xref rid="B37-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]:<disp-formula id="FD16-sensors-24-08091"><label>(16)</label><mml:math id="mm34" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">G</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>exp</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02061;</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced open="&#x02016;" close="&#x02016;" separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0003e;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
where &#x003b3; is the Kernel parameter.</p><p>Finally, the Support Vector Regression (SVR) function (f(x)) for predicting the new values can be formulated as:<disp-formula id="FD17-sensors-24-08091"><label>(17)</label><mml:math id="mm35" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:munderover><mml:mo mathsize="140%">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b1;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b1;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">G</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
where <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm36" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b1;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm37" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b1;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> are the Lagrange multipliers (i.e., a single weight) subject to <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm38" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02200;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02264;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b1;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b1;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm39" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02200;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b1;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b1;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p><p>Support Vector Regression (SVR) is described using the following steps:</p><p>Step 1: State the training set <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm40" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">y</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</p><p>Step 2: Select the appropriate parameters C, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm41" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, &#x003b5;, where C &#x0003e; 0, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm42" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0003e;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and &#x003b5; &#x0003e; 0</p><p>Step 3: Solving problem (15) and we get the solution (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm43" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, b)</p><p>Step 4: Select the feature set: <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm44" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b1;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm45" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b1;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</p><p>Step 5: Construct the decision formula (17): <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm46" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:munderover><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b1;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b1;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">G</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</p><p><xref rid="sensors-24-08091-f005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref> represents the program flow chart of the Support Vector Regression (SVR) with the set of resolution steps. Initially, the data are integrated as a form of experimental input (the gate voltage (Vgs), the nanowire length (lnw), the number of wires (N), the gate lengths (L) and the (pH)) and output (Ids experimental). Thereafter, the choice of the Kernel function and relaxation factors <italic toggle="yes">C</italic> and &#x003b3; is made. After that, the data training and testing are performed. Finally, the source-drain current (Ids) predicted is assessed.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec2dot3-sensors-24-08091"><title>2.3. Nonlinear Regression</title><p>Nonlinear regression (NLR) is a technique of regression analysis in which observational data are controlled by a specified function. This one is a nonlinear combination of model parameters that depends on one or more independent variables. In fact, the data are adapted by a method based on successive approximations. These data are used in similar cases without additional training [<xref rid="B38-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>].</p><p>The use of the NLR method requires a set of training data determined by <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm47" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">y</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> with a size value of <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm48" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Moreover, the explicit data-driven model can be written as follows [<xref rid="B39-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]:<disp-formula id="FD18-sensors-24-08091"><label>(18)</label><mml:math id="mm49" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">y</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
where <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm50" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">y</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02208;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">I</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the response variable, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm51" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02208;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">I</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> are the explanatory variables and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm52" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02208;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">I</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> are the estimated parameters. Indeed, the <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm53" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> represents the regression function, whose form is known up to some unknown parameters <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm54" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, and error term <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm55" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> with zero mean and variance <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm56" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003c3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Following the approach of the linear model, if <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm57" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is a vector of length <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm58" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, there are <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm59" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> degrees of freedom. Then, the residual error variance is defined as:<disp-formula id="FD19-sensors-24-08091"><label>(19)</label><mml:math id="mm60" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003c3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:munderover><mml:mo mathsize="140%">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>The unknown parameter vector <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm61" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> in the nonlinear regression model is estimated from the data by minimizing the residual sum of square (Equation (20)) [<xref rid="B40-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. This estimation is also known as nonlinear least squares:<disp-formula id="FD20-sensors-24-08091"><label>(20)</label><mml:math id="mm62" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">S</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:munderover><mml:mo mathsize="140%">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>A normal distribution for the error term is given by:<disp-formula id="FD21-sensors-24-08091"><label>(21)</label><mml:math id="mm63" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">y</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b5;</mml:mi><mml:mo>~</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">N</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003c3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>If the errors &#x003b5;i follow a normal distribution N (0, &#x003c3;<sup>2</sup>), then the least squares estimator for &#x003b2; is also the maximum likelihood estimator. Therefore, the likelihood for the nonlinear regression model is expressed as [<xref rid="B41-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]:<disp-formula id="FD22-sensors-24-08091"><label>(22)</label><mml:math id="mm64" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">L</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003c3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003c0;</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003c3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">exp</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02061;</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">S</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003c3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>In this work, the researched parameters are the source drain current (Ids) (output) estimated as a function of the gate voltage (Vgs), the nanowire length (lnw), the number of wires (N), the gate lengths (L) and the (pH) (inputs). From the different formulations for the (NLR) function for the prediction of data, the following formula is developed:<disp-formula id="FD23-sensors-24-08091"><label>(23)</label><mml:math id="mm65" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">y</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">log</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02061;</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">exp</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02061;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>8</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">log</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02061;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">exp</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02061;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>8</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>]</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>The main (NLR) key parameters shown in Equation (25) are defined as follows: Ids (NLR) is the source-drain current (output symbolized by y); the inputs (x1, x2, x3, x4, x5) are respectively the gate voltage Vgs, the nanowire length (lnw), the gate lengths (L), the pH and the number of wires (N):<disp-formula id="FD24-sensors-24-08091"><label>(24)</label><mml:math id="mm66" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">g</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">w</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">L</mml:mi></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi>pH</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>The model output is determined, replacing Equation (24) in Equation (23). Then, the new equation can be written as follows:<disp-formula id="FD25-sensors-24-08091"><label>(25)</label><mml:math id="mm67" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">N</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">L</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">N</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">w</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">L</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">g</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">p</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">H</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">log</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr columnalign="left"><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">exp</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">g</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">p</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">H</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>8</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr columnalign="left"><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">log</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02061;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">exp</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02061;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">g</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">p</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">H</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>8</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>]</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>The developed model set up for the output prediction is also presented in the program flow chart of nonlinear regression (NLR) (<xref rid="sensors-24-08091-f006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>). For the model convergence, the residual error variance (&#x003c3;<sup>2</sup>) is calculated using the following equation:<disp-formula id="FD26-sensors-24-08091"><label>(26)</label><mml:math id="mm68" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003c3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:munderover><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">I</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">p</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">I</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">N</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">L</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p><xref rid="sensors-24-08091-f006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref> shows the program flow chart of the Nonlinear Regression (NLR) with the set of resolution steps. Initially, the data are included as forms of experimental inputs (the gate voltage (Vgs), the nanowire length (lnw), the number of wires (N), the gate lengths (L) and the (pH)) and output (Ids experimental). After that, the (NLR) function, the initial coefficients for the nonlinear model &#x003b2;<sub>0</sub>, are chosen. Next, the data training and testing operation are carried out. Finally, the predicted source-drain current (Ids) is evaluated.</p></sec><sec id="sec2dot4-sensors-24-08091"><title>2.4. Extra Trees Regression</title><p>Extra Trees Regression is an ensemble learning method designed for regression tasks. This algorithm, an extension of the Random Forest Regression model, was proposed by Geurts et al. [<xref rid="B42-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Like Random Forest, Extra Trees constructs a collection of decision trees, but it incorporates additional randomness during the training process. Extra Trees are particularly important within this class of algorithms and have demonstrated state-of-the-art performance on various regression tasks, especially with high-dimensional inputs and outputs [<xref rid="B43-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. They are computationally efficient, offering faster training and working effectively with both categorical and numerical data. Additionally, Extra Trees can manage non-linear relationships between features and target variables.</p><p>Random Forest (RF) is a regression technique that enhances predictive accuracy by combining the outputs of multiple decision tree (DT) algorithms to classify or predict the value of a variable [<xref rid="B44-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,<xref rid="B45-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. When RF receives an input vector (x), consisting of the values of various features evaluated for a specific training set, it constructs K regression trees and averages their outputs. After growing K trees <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm69" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">T</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">K</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, the RF regression predictor is computed as the average of the individual tree predictions, based on the equation:<disp-formula id="FD27-sensors-24-08091"><label>(27)</label><mml:math id="mm70" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">F</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">K</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">K</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:munderover><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">k</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">K</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">T</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>The Extra Trees Regression (ETR) and Random Forest (RF) models differ in two significant ways. First, ETR considers all potential split points and randomly selects from them to divide nodes. Second, it utilizes the entire training dataset to grow the trees, helping to minimize bias [<xref rid="B42-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>].</p><p>In the ETR model, the splitting process is controlled by two key parameters: k and n<sub>min</sub>. k defines the number of features randomly chosen at each node, while n<sub>min</sub> specifies the minimum number of samples required to split a node. These parameters enhance accuracy and reduce the risk of overfitting in the ETR model [<xref rid="B43-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="B46-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>].</p><p>In our study, we trained an Extra Trees regression model with 100 trees to predict the source-drain current (Ids) of the SiNW-ISFET sensor. This approach was implemented using the Python programming language. The developed model for output prediction is also illustrated in the program flowchart for Extra Trees regression (ETR) (<xref rid="sensors-24-08091-f007" ref-type="fig">Figure 7</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec2dot5-sensors-24-08091"><title>2.5. Error Indicators</title><p>In this work, four performance indices, including the coefficient of determination (R<sup>2</sup>), the Mean Absolute Error (MAE) and the Root Mean Square Error (RMSE), were used to assess the accuracy of the forecast results (simulated results). These indices are generally used to evaluate the accuracy of the developed models in comparison with experimental results. The following <xref rid="sensors-24-08091-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> indicates the indices formulas used in this work.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec3-sensors-24-08091"><title>3. Results and Discussion</title><p>In this section, we present the results obtained for the four artificial intelligence methods used for the learning of the silicon nanowire ISFET sensor, namely neural networks or Multi-Layer Perceptron (MLP), Nonlinear Regression (NLR), Support Vector Regression (SVR) and Extra Trees Regression (ETR).</p><p>For the machine learning techniques developed, around 956 datasets were used in the simulation of the SiNW-ISFET sensor in MATLAB R2018a software and the Python language. The minimum and maximum data ranges used for these models are shown in <xref rid="sensors-24-08091-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>.</p><p>For the experimental activities, the Laboratory of Analysis and Architecture of Systems (LAAS-CNRS, Toulouse, France) provided a set of data obtained with N+/P/N+ silicon-nanowire-based ion-sensitive field effect transistors SiNW-ISFET [<xref rid="B15-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. These devices were realized using silicon technologies thanks to a specific reactive ion etching process for the silicon nanowire fabrication, and were finally adapted to liquid phase analysis thanks to the integration of an SU-8 based microfluidic channel by wafer-level packaging (to be published). The Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> detection layer was deposited by ALD. The thickness of this layer is about 3.3 nm for 30 ALD cycles, and about 4.5 nm for 50 ALD cycles. The composition of this layer at the interface evolves very gradually from silicon to alumina Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>; we will call it aluminosilicate AlxSiyOz. The alumina beyond the interface zone is stoichiometric; after calibration of the EDX with two samples, one in sapphire Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> and the other in SiO<sub>2</sub>, the ratio between oxygen and aluminum is indeed 60:40 [<xref rid="B48-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>].</p><p>It has been shown that the refractive index of alumina deposited by ALD increases under the effect of heat treatment. This phenomenon could be explained by crystallization of the films. To demonstrate this, the alumina was characterized using grazing incidence X-ray diffraction (GIXRD). This is a non-destructive technique used to study crystalline structures. The sample is subjected to an X-ray with a wavelength close to the dimensions of the crystal lattice (around 0.1 nm). The crystalline planes then act as a lattice of slits whose spacing is close to the wavelength of the X-rays. Diffraction then occurs at a precise angle that depends on the crystalline structure of the sample being analyzed. If the structure is amorphous, there is no crystalline plane and therefore no diffraction [<xref rid="B49-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>].</p><p>In the case of the developed ML models, the dataset comprising 956 samples was partitioned, with approximately 80% (765 samples) used for training and 20% (191 samples) reserved for testing.</p><p><xref rid="sensors-24-08091-f008" ref-type="fig">Figure 8</xref> illustrates the comparison between the experimental measurements of the SiNW-ISFET sensor (line) and the simulation results for the four machine learning techniques. The lengths of wire used are respectively 20 &#x000b5;m and 4 &#x000b5;m and the drain-source voltage is fixed at 1 (Vds = 1 V).</p><p>From the results, the transfer characteristics Ids(Vgs) show good scalability as a function of the different lengths of nanowire. Obviously, the effect of the wire length is due to parasitic contact resistance (RS1 + RS2). As the wire length increases, the transconductance decreases. A pronounced saturation phenomenon also occurs as the nanowire length increases, leading to a decrease in the on-state current of the transistor. From this figure, a good agreement between the (ML) models and the measurements is observed. Furthermore, the Extra Trees Regression (ETR) technique shows a very good prediction (as shown in <xref rid="sensors-24-08091-f009" ref-type="fig">Figure 9</xref>) of the SiNW-ISFET characteristics, with a coefficient of determination (R<sup>2</sup>) of 0.99998 and root mean square error of (RMSE) of 0.0027 &#x000b5;A.</p><p>The effect of different numbers of nanowires (1, 20 and 100) on the Si-NW-ISFET performance has been studied and presented in <xref rid="sensors-24-08091-f010" ref-type="fig">Figure 10</xref>. The results indicate a monotonic variation in the Ids current with the number of nanowires. This suggests that the series resistance R<sub>S</sub> is negligible compared to the on-resistance R<sub>ON</sub> of the nanowire, as shown by the proportionality of the transconductance with the number of nanowires. From the comparison of the four models, the ML model give accurate results, in good agreement with the experiments. In particular, the Extra Trees Regression (ETR) model proves its effectiveness and good prediction (as shown in <xref rid="sensors-24-08091-f011" ref-type="fig">Figure 11</xref>) for the assessment of the SiNW-ISFET characteristics (R<sup>2</sup> of 0.99997 and RMSE of 0.002 mA).</p><p><xref rid="sensors-24-08091-f012" ref-type="fig">Figure 12</xref> shows a decrease in the drain current of the SiNW-ISFET sensor with an increase of the channel length L (short channel: 0.73 &#x003bc;m and long channel: 3.73 &#x003bc;m) for a fixed source-drain voltage (Vds = 1 V). In fact, this current decreases with the W/L ratio increase in the transistor ON state. This phenomenon is related to the length of the wire. Since the current in the saturation region is theoretically proportional to W/L, this measurement result is consistent with the theoretical prediction.</p><p>For the test accuracy of the four developed models, <xref rid="sensors-24-08091-f013" ref-type="fig">Figure 13</xref> illustrates the varying efficiency of the compared machine learning (ML) techniques. As results, the Extra Trees Regression (ETR) technique seems to conform to the measurement, and gives very accurate results and a correct forecast (as shown in <xref rid="sensors-24-08091-f013" ref-type="fig">Figure 13</xref>) (R<sup>2</sup> of 0.99996 and RMSE of 0.0015 mA).</p><p>In <xref rid="sensors-24-08091-f014" ref-type="fig">Figure 14</xref>, the transfer characteristics Ids (Vds) of SiNW-ISFET with varying pH values are presented. The measured data are described by line and the simulations results with other symbols for the four machine learning techniques. From this figure, it is confirmed that the surface potential at the Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>/SiO<sub>2</sub>/SiNW interface is well modulated by the pH values. The average shift of the threshold voltage Vth by pH was 51.66 mV/pH (<xref rid="sensors-24-08091-f014" ref-type="fig">Figure 14</xref>); in comparison with the Nernst ideal limit (&#x0223c;59.2 mV/pH at 25 &#x000b0;C).</p><p>The results of <xref rid="sensors-24-08091-f015" ref-type="fig">Figure 15</xref> prove that the ML models match perfectly with the measured data. A very low error is noted for the Extra Trees Regression (ETR) model with an R<sup>2</sup> and RMSE about (0.99998, 0.53 &#x000b5;A). For the sensibility (<xref rid="sensors-24-08091-f016" ref-type="fig">Figure 16</xref>), it is noticed that Extra Trees Regression (ETR) provides an accurate sensibility in comparison with the others models.</p><p>For more effective analysis of the four machine learning techniques, a three of uncertainty indices MAE, RMSE and R<sup>2</sup> have been reported in <xref rid="sensors-24-08091-t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>. Moreover, the parameters used for the development of the ML models are presented in <xref rid="sensors-24-08091-t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>. Indeed, it is clear that the results obtained from the four machine learning algorithms are very promising. Furthermore, the Extra Trees Regression (ETR) model allows very accurate results and correct prediction with a mean R&#x000b2; of 0.9999725, MAE of 0.000415 mA and RMSE of 0.001 mA.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec4-sensors-24-08091"><title>4. Conclusions</title><p>In this work, four mathematical models were developed for the silicon nanowire ISFET sensor using MATLAB software and the Python language: Multi-Layer Perceptron (MLP), Nonlinear Regression (NLR), Support Vector Regression (SVR), and Extra Trees Regression (ETR). The objective was to create highly accurate predictive models for the source-drain current (Ids) output of the SiNW-ISFET sensor. The four developed models have been compared with real measurements in order to determine the one that ensures the best performance. From the results, the ML models are found to be efficient. In particular, Extra Trees Regression (ETR) offers the best performance prediction. It presents a good agreement with the experimental results with a lowest RMSE value of about 0.001 mA and R<sup>2</sup> of 0.9999725.</p><p>This model proves to be effective for studying the simulation response of the silicon nanowire ISFET and analyzing various parameters related to its manufacturing process. The use of artificial intelligence techniques is of great importance, as it allows for the prediction and correction of defects before manufacturing. Thereafter, the application of these machine learning methods could be very promising for future studies of CMOS circuits.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Disclaimer/Publisher&#x02019;s Note:</bold> The statements, opinions and data contained in all publications are solely those of the individual author(s) and contributor(s) and not of MDPI and/or the editor(s). MDPI and/or the editor(s) disclaim responsibility for any injury to people or property resulting from any ideas, methods, instructions or products referred to in the content.</p></fn></fn-group><notes><title>Author Contributions</title><p>Conceptualization, B.H., J.L. and P.T.-B.; Methodology, N.A. and A.L.; Software, N.A.; Validation, A.L.; Data curation, N.A.; Writing&#x02014;original draft, N.A.; Writing&#x02014;review &#x00026; editing, B.H., J.L. and P.T.-B.; Visualization, B.H.; Supervision, J.L. and P.T.-B. All authors have read and agreed to the published version of the manuscript.</p></notes><notes><title>Institutional Review Board Statement</title><p>Not applicable.</p></notes><notes><title>Informed Consent Statement</title><p>Informed consent was obtained from all subjects involved in the study.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The original contributions presented in this study are included in the article. Further inquiries can be directed to the corresponding author.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflicts of Interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></notes><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1-sensors-24-08091"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bergveld</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Development of an Ion-Sensitive Solid-State Device for Neurophysiological Measurements</article-title><source>IEEE Trans. Biomed. Eng.</source><year>1970</year><volume>BME-17</volume><fpage>70</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/TBME.1970.4502688</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5441220</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B2-sensors-24-08091"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zekentes</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stambouli</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bano</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Karker</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rogdakis</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Progress in SiC nanowire field-effect-transistors for integrated circuits and sensing applications</article-title><source>Microelectron. Eng.</source><year>2022</year><volume>255</volume><fpage>111704</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mee.2021.111704</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3-sensors-24-08091"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Panteli</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Georgiou</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fobelets</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Performance improvement of commercial ISFET sensors using reactive ion etching</article-title><source>Microelectron. Eng.</source><year>2018</year><volume>192</volume><fpage>61</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mee.2018.02.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4-sensors-24-08091"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Artigas</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jim&#x000e9;nez</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dom&#x000ed;nguez</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>M&#x000ed;nguez</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gonzalo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Development of a multiparametric analyser based on ISFET sensors applied to process control in the wine industry</article-title><source>Sens. Actuators B</source><year>2003</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>199</fpage><lpage>204</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0925-4005(02)00464-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5-sensors-24-08091"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mani</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Devadas</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Direct electrochemistry of glucose oxidase at electrochemically reduced graphene oxide-multiwalled carbon nanotubes hybrid material modified electrode for glucose biosensor</article-title><source>Biosens. Bioelectron.</source><year>2013</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>309</fpage><lpage>315</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bios.2012.08.045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22964382</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B6-sensors-24-08091"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hideshima</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Takeuchi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wustoni</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kuroiwa</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nakanishi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Momma</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Osaka</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Improvement in long-term stability of field effect transistor biosensor in aqueous environments using a combination of silane and reduced graphene oxide coating</article-title><source>Microelectron. Eng.</source><year>2022</year><volume>264</volume><fpage>111859</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mee.2022.111859</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7-sensors-24-08091"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jimenez</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Orozco</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baldi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>ISFET Based Microsensors for Environmental Monitoring</article-title><source>Sensors</source><year>2010</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>61</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/s100100061</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22315527</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B8-sensors-24-08091"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pal&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>F.V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Karam</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Courtois</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hus&#x000e1;k</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>New ISFET sensor interface circuit for biomedical applications</article-title><source>Sens. Actuators B</source><year>1999</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>63</fpage><lpage>68</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0925-4005(99)00136-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9-sensors-24-08091"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kutovaa</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dusheikoa</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Klyuia</surname><given-names>N.I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Skryshevskyd</surname><given-names>V.A.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>C-reactive protein detection based on ISFET structure with gate dielectric SiO<sub>2</sub>-CeO<sub>2</sub></article-title><source>Microelectron. Eng.</source><year>2019</year><volume>215</volume><fpage>110993</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mee.2019.110993</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10-sensors-24-08091"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Joly</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mazenq</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marlet</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Temple-Boyer</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Durieu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Launay</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Multimodal Probe Based on ISFET Electrochemical Microsensors for In-Situ Monitoring of Soil Nutrients in Agriculture</article-title><source>Proceedings</source><year>2017</year><volume>1</volume><elocation-id>420</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/proceedings1040420</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11-sensors-24-08091"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Abreu</surname><given-names>R.F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Saturno</surname><given-names>S.O.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nobrega</surname><given-names>F.A.C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Colares</surname><given-names>D.d.M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>do Nascimento</surname><given-names>J.P.C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vasconcelos</surname><given-names>S.J.T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nogueira</surname><given-names>F.E.A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>de Freitas</surname><given-names>D.B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>do Carmo</surname><given-names>F.F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>Study of electrical properties with temperature variation by complex impedance spectroscopy (CIS) and efects on the Ba<sub>2</sub>TiSi<sub>2</sub>O<sub>8</sub>&#x02013;TiO<sub>2</sub> matrix</article-title><source>Appl. Phys. A</source><year>2024</year><volume>130</volume><fpage>138</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00339-024-07295-z</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12-sensors-24-08091"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lale</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Grappin</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mazenq</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bourrier</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lecestre</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Launay</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Temple-Boyer</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Development of All-Around SiO<sub>2</sub>/Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> Gate, Suspended Silicon Nanowire Chemical Field Effect Transistors Si-nw-ChemFET</article-title><source>Proceedings</source><year>2017</year><volume>1</volume><elocation-id>419</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/proceedings1040419</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13-sensors-24-08091"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jayakumar</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hellstr&#x000f6;m</surname><given-names>P.-E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>&#x000d6;stling</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Utilizing the superior etch stop quality of HfO<sub>2</sub> in the front end of line wafer scale integration of silicon nanowire biosensors</article-title><source>Microelectron. Eng.</source><year>2019</year><volume>212</volume><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mee.2019.03.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14-sensors-24-08091"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Baek</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baek</surname><given-names>C.K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>S.W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yeoh</surname><given-names>Y.Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D.W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>Y.H.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Comparison of Series Resistance and Mobility Degradation Extracted from n- and p-Type Si-Nanowire Field Effect Transistors Using the Y-Function Technique</article-title><source>Jpn. J. Appl. Phys.</source><year>2010</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>04DN06</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1143/JJAP.49.04DN06</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15-sensors-24-08091"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lale</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Grappin</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lecestre</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mazenq</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Launay</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Temple-Boyer</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Top-down integration of suspended N+/P/N+ silicon-nanowire-based ion-sensitive field effect transistors for pH analysis at the submicronic scale</article-title><source>Thin Solid Film.</source><year>2023</year><volume>764</volume><fpage>139609</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tsf.2022.139609</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16-sensors-24-08091"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Trukhanov</surname><given-names>S.V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Trukhanov</surname><given-names>A.V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kostishyn</surname><given-names>V.G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Panina</surname><given-names>L.V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Trukhanov</surname><given-names>A.V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Turchenko</surname><given-names>V.A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tishkevich</surname><given-names>D.I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Trukhanova</surname><given-names>E.L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oleynik</surname><given-names>V.V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yakovenko</surname><given-names>O.S.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>Magnetic, dielectric and microwave properties of the BaFe12-xGaxO19 (x &#x02264; 1.2) solid solutions at room temperature</article-title><source>J. Magn. Magn. Mater.</source><year>2017</year><volume>442</volume><fpage>300</fpage><lpage>310</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jmmm.2017.06.022</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17-sensors-24-08091"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Application of ISFET Microsensors with Mobile Network to Build IoT for Water Environment Monitoring</article-title><source>Proceedings of the 2014 International Conference on Intelligent Environments</source><conf-loc>Shanghai, China</conf-loc><conf-date>30 June&#x02013;1 July 2014</conf-date><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>210</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18-sensors-24-08091"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Margarit-Taul&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;n-Ezquerra</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Escud&#x000e9;-Pujol</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jim&#x000e9;nez-Jorquera</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S.C.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Cross-compensation of FET sensor drift and matrix effects in the industrial continuous monitoring of ion concentrations</article-title><source>Sens. Actuators B Chem.</source><year>2022</year><volume>353</volume><fpage>131123</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.snb.2021.131123</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19-sensors-24-08091"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hajji</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Temple-Boyer</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Launay</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>do Conto</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>pH, pK and pNa detection properties of SiO<sub>2</sub>/Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> ISFET chemical sensors</article-title><source>Microelectron. Reliab.</source><year>2000</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>783</fpage><lpage>786</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0026-2714(99)00285-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20-sensors-24-08091"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Martinoia</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Massobrio</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Grattarola</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>An ISFET model for CAD applications</article-title><source>Sens. Actuators B</source><year>1992</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>261</fpage><lpage>265</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0925-4005(92)85029-V</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21-sensors-24-08091"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Simulation of Ta<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>-gate ISFET temperature characteristics</article-title><source>Sens. Actuators B</source><year>2000</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>76</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0925-4005(00)00611-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22-sensors-24-08091"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Janicki</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Daniel</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Szermer</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Napieralski</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Ion sensitive field effect transistor modelling for multidomain simulation purposes</article-title><source>Microelectron. J.</source><year>2004</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>831</fpage><lpage>840</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mejo.2004.06.015</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23-sensors-24-08091"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hajji</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Naimi</surname><given-names>S.E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Humenyuk</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Launay</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Temple-Boyer</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Behavioral modeling of the pH-ISFET temperature influence</article-title><source>Proceedings of the 2007 14th IEEE International Conference on Electronics, Circuits and Systems</source><conf-loc>Marrakech, Morocco</conf-loc><conf-date>11&#x02013;14 December 2007</conf-date><fpage>419</fpage><lpage>422</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24-sensors-24-08091"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Naimi</surname><given-names>S.E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hajji</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Habbani</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Humenyuk</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Launay</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Temple-Boyer</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Modeling of the pH-ChemFET response and using Genetic Algorithm as extraction parameters method</article-title><source>Proceedings of the 2011 Faible Tension Faible Consommation (FTFC)</source><conf-loc>Marrakech, Morocco</conf-loc><conf-date>30 May&#x02013;1 June 2011</conf-date><fpage>103</fpage><lpage>106</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25-sensors-24-08091"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ayadi</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hajji</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Madani</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lale</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Launay</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Temple-Boyer</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Simulation and performance study of silicon nanowire (SiNW) field-effect transistor (FET) pH microsensor</article-title><source>Proceedings of the 2nd International Conference on Electronic Engineering and Renewable Energy Systems. ICEERE 2020, Saidia, Morocco, 13&#x02013;15 April 2020</source><comment>Lecture Notes in Electrical Engineering</comment><person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Hajji</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mellit</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marco Tina</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rabhi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Launay</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Naimi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Singapore</publisher-loc><year>2021</year><volume>Volume 681</volume></element-citation></ref><ref id="B26-sensors-24-08091"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sahu</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bhardwaj</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mukhiya</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sinha</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Towards development of an isfet-based smart ph sensor: Enabling machine learning for drift compensation in iot applications</article-title><source>IEEE Sens. J.</source><year>2021</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>19013</fpage><lpage>19024</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/JSEN.2021.3087333</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B27-sensors-24-08091"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>W.-E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Y.-H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>C.-T.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>A machine-learning assisted sensor for chemo-physical dual sensing based on ion-sensitive field-effect transistor architecture</article-title><source>IEEE Sens. J.</source><year>2019</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>9983</fpage><lpage>9990</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/JSEN.2019.2927038</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B28-sensors-24-08091"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Isik</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tasyurek</surname><given-names>L.B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Isik</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kilinc</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Synthesis and analysis of TiO<sub>2</sub> nanotubes by electrochemical anodization and machine learning method for hydrogen sensors</article-title><source>Microelectron. Eng.</source><year>2022</year><volume>262</volume><fpage>111834</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mee.2022.111834</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B29-sensors-24-08091"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sinha</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sahu</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bhardwaj</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ahuja</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Srivastava</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Elhence</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chamola</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Machine Learning on FPGA for Robust Si3N4-Gate ISFET pH Sensor in Industrial IoT</article-title><source>IEEE Trans. Ind. Appl.</source><year>2021</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>6700</fpage><lpage>6712</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/TIA.2021.3117233</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B30-sensors-24-08091"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hayati</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rezaei</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Seifi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>CNT-MOSFET modeling based on artificial neural network:Application to simulation of nanoscale circuits</article-title><source>Solid-State Electron.</source><year>2010</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>52</fpage><lpage>57</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sse.2009.09.027</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B31-sensors-24-08091"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Manry</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Narasimha</surname><given-names>P.L.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>An efficient hidden layer training method for the multilayer perceptron</article-title><source>Neurocomputing</source><year>2006</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>525</fpage><lpage>535</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neucom.2005.11.008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B32-sensors-24-08091"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>A fast and manufacture-friendly optical proximity correction based on machine learning</article-title><source>Microelectron. Eng.</source><year>2017</year><volume>168</volume><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mee.2016.10.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B33-sensors-24-08091"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>U.K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tey</surname><given-names>K.S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Seyedmahmoudian</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Idna Idris</surname><given-names>M.Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mekhilef</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Horan</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stojcevski</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>SVR-Based Model to Forecast PV Power Generation under Different Weather Conditions</article-title><source>Energies</source><year>2017</year><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>876</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/en10070876</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B34-sensors-24-08091"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nishi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Global Convergence of SMO Algorithm for Support Vector Regression</article-title><source>IEEE Trans. Neural Netw.</source><year>2008</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>971</fpage><lpage>982</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/TNN.2007.915116</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18541498</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B35-sensors-24-08091"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vapnik</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>The Nature of Statistical Learning Theory</source><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name><publisher-loc>New York, NY, USA</publisher-loc><year>1995</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="B36-sensors-24-08091"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Amutha</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nagar</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C.-C.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>LT-FS-ID: Log-Transformed Feature Learning and Feature-Scaling-Based Machine Learning Algorithms to Predict the k-Barriers for Intrusion Detection Using Wireless Sensor Network</article-title><source>Sensors</source><year>2022</year><volume>22</volume><elocation-id>1070</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/s22031070</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35161815</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B37-sensors-24-08091"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>S.-S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H.-W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Variant of Gaussian kernel and parameter setting method for nonlinear SVM</article-title><source>Neurocomputing</source><year>2009</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>2931</fpage><lpage>2937</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neucom.2008.07.016</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B38-sensors-24-08091"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Watts</surname><given-names>D.G.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Nonlinear Regression Analysis and Its Applications</source><publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name><publisher-loc>New York, NY, USA</publisher-loc><year>1988</year><volume>Volume 2</volume></element-citation></ref><ref id="B39-sensors-24-08091"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Haj Seyed Hadi</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gonzalez-Andujar</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Comparison of fitting weed seedling emergence models with nonlinear regression and genetic algorithm</article-title><source>Comput. Electron. Agric.</source><year>2009</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.compag.2008.07.005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B40-sensors-24-08091"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>G.K.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Nonlinear regression</article-title><source>Encycl. Environmetrics</source><year>2002</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>1405</fpage><lpage>1411</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B41-sensors-24-08091"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Nonlinear Regression and Nonlinear Least Square</article-title><month>January</month><year>2002</year><comment>Available online: <ext-link xlink:href="https://socserv.socsci.mcmaster.ca/jfox/Books/Companion-1E/appendix-nonlinear-regression.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://socserv.socsci.mcmaster.ca/jfox/Books/Companion-1E/appendix-nonlinear-regression.pdf</ext-link></comment><date-in-citation content-type="access-date" iso-8601-date="2024-10-23">(accessed on 23 October 2024)</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="B42-sensors-24-08091"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Geurts</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ernst</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wehenkel</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Extremely randomized trees</article-title><source>Mach. Learn.</source><year>2006</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10994-006-6226-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B43-sensors-24-08091"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>John</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mita</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kidono</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Real-time lane estimation using deep features and extra trees regression</article-title><source>Image and Video Technology: 7th Pacific-Rim Symposium, PSIVT 2015, Auckland, New Zealand, 25&#x02013;27 November 2015, Revised Selected Papers 7</source><publisher-name>Springer International Publishing</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Cham, Switzerland</publisher-loc><year>2016</year><fpage>721</fpage><lpage>733</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B44-sensors-24-08091"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Breiman</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Random forests</article-title><source>Mach. Learn.</source><year>2001</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1010933404324</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B45-sensors-24-08091"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rodriguez-Galiano</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sanchez-Castillo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chica-Olmo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chica-Rivas</surname><given-names>M.J.O.G.R.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Machine learning predictive models for mineral prospectivity: An evaluation of neural networks, random forest, regression trees and support vector machines</article-title><source>Ore Geol. Rev.</source><year>2015</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>804</fpage><lpage>818</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.oregeorev.2015.01.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B46-sensors-24-08091"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hameed</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>AlOmar</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Khaleel</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Al-Ansari</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>An extra tree regression model for discharge coefficient prediction: Novel, practical applications in the hydraulic sector and future research directions</article-title><source>Math. Probl. Eng.</source><year>2021</year><volume>2021</volume><fpage>7001710</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2021/7001710</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B47-sensors-24-08091"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xhafa</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Anomaly detection: Concepts and methods</article-title><source>Anomaly Detection and Complex Event Processing over IoT Data Streams</source><person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xhafa</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
</person-group><publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA, USA</publisher-loc><year>2022</year><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>66</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B48-sensors-24-08091"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Trukhanov</surname><given-names>S.V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Trukhanov</surname><given-names>A.V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vasil</surname><given-names>A.N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maignan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Szymczak</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Critical behavior of La<sub>0.825</sub>Sr<sub>0.175</sub>MnO<sub>2.912</sub> anion-deficient manganite in the magnetic phase transition region</article-title><source>J. Exp. Theor. Phys. Lett.</source><year>2007</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>507</fpage><lpage>512</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1134/S0021364007100086</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B49-sensors-24-08091"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Trukhanov</surname><given-names>S.V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Troyanchuk</surname><given-names>I.O.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fedotova</surname><given-names>V.V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ryzhov</surname><given-names>V.A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maignan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Flahaut</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Szymczak</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Szymczak</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Magnetic properties of the nonstoichiometric Sr-doped manganites</article-title><source>Phys. Stat. Solidi (b)</source><year>2005</year><volume>242</volume><fpage>1123</fpage><lpage>1131</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pssb.200402143</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig position="float" id="sensors-24-08091-f001"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>The (ML) techniques used for the Ids prediction of the silicon nanowires ISFET.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sensors-24-08091-g001" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="sensors-24-08091-f002"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>The Multi-Layer Perception Neural Networks (MLP).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sensors-24-08091-g002" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="sensors-24-08091-f003"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Program flow chart of Multilayer Perception (MLP).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sensors-24-08091-g003" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="sensors-24-08091-f004"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Architecture of Support Vector Regression (SVR).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sensors-24-08091-g004" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="sensors-24-08091-f005"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Program flow chart of the Support Vector Regression (SVR).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sensors-24-08091-g005" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="sensors-24-08091-f006"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Program flow chart of the Nonlinear Regression (NLR).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sensors-24-08091-g006" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="sensors-24-08091-f007"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Program flow chart of the Extra Trees regression (ETR).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sensors-24-08091-g007" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="sensors-24-08091-f008"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Comparison of SiNW-ISFET characteristics with varying wire lengths, obtained through four machine learning techniques and validated by measurements (Vds = 1 V): (<bold>a</bold>) SVR, (<bold>b</bold>) MLP, (<bold>c</bold>) NLR and (<bold>d</bold>) ETR.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sensors-24-08091-g008" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="sensors-24-08091-f009"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p>Prediction accuracy of four machine learning techniques with different lengths of nanowires: (<bold>a</bold>) SVR, (<bold>b</bold>) NLR, (<bold>c</bold>) MLP and (<bold>d</bold>) ETR.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sensors-24-08091-g009" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="sensors-24-08091-f010"><label>Figure 10</label><caption><p>Comparison of the SiNW-ISFET characteristics with different numbers of wires, obtained through four machine learning techniques and validated by measurements (the nanowire length is 2 &#x003bc;m and Vds = 1 V): (<bold>a</bold>) SVR, (<bold>b</bold>) MLP, (<bold>c</bold>) NLR and (<bold>d</bold>) ETR.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sensors-24-08091-g010" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="sensors-24-08091-f011"><label>Figure 11</label><caption><p>Prediction accuracy of four machine learning techniques with different numbers of wires: (<bold>a</bold>) SVR, (<bold>b</bold>) NLR, (<bold>c</bold>) MLP and (<bold>d</bold>) ETR.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sensors-24-08091-g011" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="sensors-24-08091-f012"><label>Figure 12</label><caption><p>Comparison of the SiNW-ISFET characteristics with different gate lengths (0.73 &#x003bc;m and 3.73 &#x003bc;m), obtained through four machine learning techniques and validated by measurements (the nanowire length is 10 &#x003bc;m and Vds = 1 V): (<bold>a</bold>) SVR, (<bold>b</bold>) MLP, (<bold>c</bold>) NLR and (<bold>d</bold>) ETR.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sensors-24-08091-g012" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="sensors-24-08091-f013"><label>Figure 13</label><caption><p>Prediction accuracy of four machine learning techniques with different gate lengths: (<bold>a</bold>) SVR, (<bold>b</bold>) NLR, (<bold>c</bold>) MLP and (<bold>d</bold>) ETR.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sensors-24-08091-g013" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="sensors-24-08091-f014"><label>Figure 14</label><caption><p>Comparison of the SiNW-ISFET characteristics with different pH, obtained through four machine learning techniques and validated by measurements (Vds = 1 V): (<bold>a</bold>) SVR, (<bold>b</bold>) MLP, (<bold>c</bold>) NLR and (<bold>d</bold>) ETR.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sensors-24-08091-g014" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="sensors-24-08091-f015"><label>Figure 15</label><caption><p>Prediction accuracy of four machine learning techniques with different pH values: (<bold>a</bold>) SVR, (<bold>b</bold>) NLR, (<bold>c</bold>) MLP and (<bold>d</bold>) ETR.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sensors-24-08091-g015" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="sensors-24-08091-f016"><label>Figure 16</label><caption><p>Comparison of the sensitivities of SiNW-ISFET sensor, obtained through four machine learning techniques and validated by measurements (Ids = 200 &#x000b5;A and Vds = 1 V): (<bold>a</bold>) SVR, (<bold>b</bold>) MLP, (<bold>c</bold>) NLR and (<bold>d</bold>) ETR.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sensors-24-08091-g016" position="float"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="sensors-24-08091-t001"><object-id pub-id-type="pii">sensors-24-08091-t001_Table 1</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Error indicators.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metric</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Formula</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula>
<mml:math id="mm71" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math>
</inline-formula>
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula>
<mml:math id="mm72" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:munderover><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math>
</inline-formula>
</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula>
<mml:math id="mm73" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">M</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">A</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">E</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math>
</inline-formula>
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula>
<mml:math id="mm74" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:munderover><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced open="|" close="|" separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math>
</inline-formula>
</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula>
<mml:math id="mm75" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">M</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">S</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">E</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math>
</inline-formula>
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula>
<mml:math id="mm76" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:munderover><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math>
</inline-formula>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>where n represents the number of elements of data from the whole test process; <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm77" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm78" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
are the correct and predicted values of target [<xref rid="B47-sensors-24-08091" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>].</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="sensors-24-08091-t002"><object-id pub-id-type="pii">sensors-24-08091-t002_Table 2</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Data ranges used for ML.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Range</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length of Nanowire (&#x000b5;m)</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of Wires</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gate Length (&#x000b5;m)</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vgs (V)</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pH</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ids (mA)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">min</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10<sup>&#x02212;9</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">max</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.73</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Input</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Output</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="sensors-24-08091-t003"><object-id pub-id-type="pii">sensors-24-08091-t003_Table 3</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Comparison the uncertainty indices obtained for the machine learning models.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RMSE (mA)</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MAE (mA)</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R<sup>2</sup> (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MLP</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0053</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00264</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.9725</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NLR</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.095</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.028</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.59</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SVR</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0047</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00156</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.97925</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ETR</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000415</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.99725</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="sensors-24-08091-t004"><object-id pub-id-type="pii">sensors-24-08091-t004_Table 4</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Parameters selected for different machine learning techniques.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameters</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MLP</td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">activation function (&#x003b3;l): &#x0201c;softmax&#x0201d;, alpha: 0.001, batch size: &#x02018;auto&#x02019;, number of hidden layer: 1, hidden layer size (s): 10, learning rate (&#x003b1;): 10<sup>&#x02212;8</sup>, max-iter: 200</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SVR</td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">penalty applied over training errors (C): 10, epsilon: 10<sup>&#x02212;8</sup>, gamma(&#x003b3;): auto, kernel function (G):&#x02018;Gaussian&#x02019;, max-iter: 1, termination tolerance (tol): 10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NLR</td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">fit-intercept: True, <break/>termination tolerance for the function (TolFun): 10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ETR</td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of trees: 100, n<sub>min</sub>: 2, k: 1</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></floats-group></article>