<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="issn">2168-8184</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cureus</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2168-8184</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cureus</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Palo Alto (CA)</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11681291</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7759/cureus.74641</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Emergency Medicine</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Internal Medicine</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Substance Use and Addiction</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Buckwheat-Associated Acute Psychosis: A Case of Anticholinergic Syndrome</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Muacevic</surname><given-names>Alexander</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>John R</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Barbosa Mateus</surname><given-names>Daniela</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Henriques Gomes</surname><given-names>Carolina</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Barbosa Barroso</surname><given-names>Jo&#x000e3;o</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cruz</surname><given-names>Sofia</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff-1">
<label>1</label>
Internal Medicine, Hospital Vila Franca de Xira, Vila Franca de Xira, PRT </aff><aff id="aff-2">
<label>2</label>
Medicine, Hospital Vila Franca de Xira, Vila Franca de Xira, PRT </aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">
Daniela Barbosa Mateus <email>danielabarbosamateus@gmail.com</email>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>27</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic"><month>11</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><issue>11</issue><elocation-id>e74641</elocation-id><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2024, Barbosa Mateus et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Barbosa Mateus et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License CC-BY 4.0., which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="https://www.cureus.com/articles/287194-buckwheat-associated-acute-psychosis-a-case-of-anticholinergic-syndrome">This article is available from https://www.cureus.com/articles/287194-buckwheat-associated-acute-psychosis-a-case-of-anticholinergic-syndrome</self-uri><abstract><p>Buckwheat (<italic>Fagopyrum esculentum</italic>) is a seed increasingly used as a gluten-free alternative, particularly by individuals with gluten-sensitive enteropathy. While rich in vitamins and minerals, it may also contain toxic secondary metabolites.</p><p>The authors present a case of a 49-year-old female patient, admitted to the emergency department with a four-hour history of psychomotor agitation, confusion, and mydriasis. Symptom onset occurred three hours after consuming buckwheat. Clinical examination revealed disorientation, agitation, and visual and auditory hallucinations, with mydriasis and tachycardia. Laboratory and imaging tests were unremarkable. Toxicology screening was negative for common substances of abuse. A diagnosis of acute psychosis secondary to buckwheat ingestion was made. Management included intravenous diazepam, leading to a favorable clinical outcome.</p><p>Buckwheat may contain tropane alkaloids, which can be toxic to humans. Benzodiazepines were effective in managing acute psychosis. This case highlights the potential neuropsychiatric effects of buckwheat ingestion and the importance of considering dietary causes in the differential diagnosis of acute psychosis.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>acute psychosis</kwd><kwd>anticholinergic syndrome</kwd><kwd>buckwheat</kwd><kwd>neuropsychiatric disorders</kwd><kwd>tropane alkaloids</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Buckwheat (<italic>Fagopyrum esculentum</italic>) is a pseudocereal widely consumed as a gluten-free alternative, especially among individuals with gluten-sensitive enteropathy. It is valued for its nutritional profile and is rich in essential vitamins, minerals, and bioactive compounds&#x000a0;[<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>].</p><p>Buckwheat can be contaminated by <italic>Datura </italic>spp, which can contain high concentrations of tropane alkaloids&#x000a0;[<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Certain tropane alkaloids possess pharmacological properties and may function as anticholinergics or stimulants&#x000a0;[<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>].</p><p>Although generally considered safe, there is limited literature on its potential to induce neuropsychiatric symptoms, particularly psychosis characterized by hallucinations and delirium.</p><p>This report presents a rare case of acute psychosis following buckwheat ingestion, emphasizing the need for awareness of the potential toxicological effects associated with this increasingly popular food.</p></sec><sec sec-type="cases"><title>Case presentation</title><p>A 49-year-old female patient with a medical history of hypothyroidism managed with 100 mcg of levothyroxine daily, presented to the Emergency Department with a four-hour history of psychomotor agitation, mental confusion, and mydriasis. The patient reported consuming pancakes made with buckwheat approximately three hours before symptom onset.&#x000a0;There was no prior history of allergies.</p><p>On physical examination, the patient appeared disoriented and agitated, exhibiting visual and auditory hallucinations. Her pupils were bilaterally dilated and reactive to light. She was normotensive, tachycardic (heart rate: 140 beats per minute), afebrile, and without signs of respiratory distress. The Glasgow Coma Scale (GCS) score was 15, indicating full consciousness, with no focal neurological deficits observed.</p><p>Initial laboratory investigations (Table <xref rid="TAB1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) were unremarkable, including a metabolic panel&#x000a0;and thyroid function tests. Urine toxicology screening was negative for amphetamines, benzodiazepines, cannabinoids, cocaine derivatives, opiates, and methamphetamines.&#x000a0;A cranial CT scan was performed&#x000a0;without changes (Figure <xref rid="FIG1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Laboratory findings on the day of admission to the emergency room</title><p>pCO2: partial pressure of carbon dioxide, pO2: partial pressure of oxygen,&#x000a0;HCO3: bicarbonate</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Value</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference range</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Comment</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hemoglobin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13,2 g/dL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12-15 g/dL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">White blood cells</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6300/&#x000b5;L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4000-1000/&#x000b5;L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Platelets</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">248000/&#x000b5;L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">150000-400000/&#x000b5;L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C-reactive protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0,5 mg/dL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c; 1 mg/dL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Creatinine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,70 mg/dL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;0.7-1.3 mg/dL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urea</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 mg/dL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c; 50 mg/dL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sodium</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">137 mmol/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">136-145 mmol/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Potassium</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.24 mmol/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5-5.1 mmol/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total bilirubin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35 mg/dL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1-1.2 mg/dL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alanine transaminase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 U/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c; 59 U/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aspartate transaminase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 U/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c; 50 U/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thyroid-stimulating hormone</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.886 mU/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.350-5.5 mU/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Free T4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.42 ng/dL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8-1.76 ng/dL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Creatine phosphokinase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93U/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26-192 U/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urinary test for drugs</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Negative to amphetamines, benzodiazepines, cannabinoids, cocaine derivatives, opiates, and methamphetamines</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arterial blood gases</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pH</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.47</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.35-7.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Above normal</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pCO2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.2 mmHg</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35-45 mmHg</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pO2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">108.7 mmHg</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e; 65 mmHg</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HCO3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.8 mmHg</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22-26 mmHg</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lactate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.01 mmol/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c; 1.8 mmol/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Above normal</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Cranial CT scan</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0016-00000074641-i01" position="float"/></fig><p>Given the temporal association with buckwheat consumption and the absence of other identifiable causes, a diagnosis of acute psychosis induced by buckwheat toxins was made. The Poison Information Center was consulted, and benzodiazepine administration was recommended, as physostigmine was unavailable. The patient received a total of 9 mg of intravenous diazepam.&#x000a0;</p><p>She was closely monitored in the emergency department, and her symptoms gradually improved. During this period, the patient was re-evaluated, showing continued resolution of her agitation and hallucinations. After 12 hours, she was stable, alert, and oriented, with no further neuropsychiatric symptoms.</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>In recent years, there has been a rise in the inclusion of functional foods with bioactive compounds in consumers' diets. These foods provide both nutritional value and health benefits to consumers&#x000a0;[<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>].&#x000a0;</p><p>Buckwheat is known to contain various bioactive compounds, including flavonoids&#x000a0;and phytosterols, and may have secondary metabolites such as tropane alkaloids, which can be toxic&#x000a0;[<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Plants are also a common source of both accidental and intentional anticholinergic ingestion. Plants containing belladonna alkaloids, such as scopolamine and, more prominently, atropine, may exhibit hallucinogenic properties due to their antimuscarinic effects&#x000a0;[<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. These compounds can cause a range of symptoms, including delirium, confusion, tachycardia, and dilated pupils, and are often misused for their psychoactive effects&#x000a0;[<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Buckwheat can be contaminated by <italic>Datura</italic> spp., which contains high levels of tropane alkaloids, and can contaminate buckwheat crops if they grow nearby or if the seeds come into contact&#x000a0;[<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>].</p><p>Similarly with this case, in 2003, Slovenia witnessed a case of mass poisoning affecting 73 individuals, who exhibited symptoms including dry mouth, flushed skin, blurred vision, tachycardia, urinary retention, ataxia, speech disturbances, disorientation, and visual hallucinations [<xref rid="REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. All individuals, who were affected, had ingested food products made with buckwheat flour in the hours leading up to the appearance of symptoms. A subsequent investigation revealed that the poisoning was caused by the inadvertent contamination of the buckwheat flour with <italic>Datura stramonium</italic> seeds, leading to anticholinergic toxicity&#x000a0;[<xref rid="REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>].</p><p>Management of anticholinergic toxicity typically involves benzodiazepine administration intravenously to control mild to moderate agitation&#x000a0;[<xref rid="REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. In cases of hypotension or suspected rhabdomyolysis, intravenous fluids should be administered. If significant hyperthermia is present, cooling interventions should be initiated. Additionally, activated charcoal may be considered if the ingestion occurred within one hour before the patient&#x02019;s presentation&#x000a0;[<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. In severe cases, cholinesterase inhibitors, such as physostigmine, may be considered. As a reversible acetylcholinesterase inhibitor, physostigmine increases acetylcholine concentration at the synaptic cleft, serving as an antidote for anticholinergic syndrome by effectively reversing toxicity in both the central and peripheral nervous systems&#x000a0;[<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>].</p><p>In this case,&#x000a0;despite the unavailability of physostigmine,&#x000a0;diazepam effectively managed the acute psychotic symptoms, highlighting the importance of timely intervention.&#x000a0;Usually, when anticholinergic toxicity is promptly recognized and proper supportive treatment is provided, the outcome is favorable&#x000a0;[<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].</p><p>This case underscores the importance of considering dietary and environmental factors in the differential diagnosis of acute psychosis, especially in patients without a prior psychiatric history. Although buckwheat is generally considered safe, healthcare providers should know its potential to induce toxic effects.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>This case illustrates a rare but significant neuropsychiatric complication following buckwheat ingestion, emphasizing the need for increased awareness of its potential toxic effects. While buckwheat is typically considered a safe and nutritious pseudocereal, the presence of tropane alkaloids may contribute to adverse reactions such as acute psychosis. Prompt recognition and treatment with benzodiazepines, as demonstrated in this case, can lead to a favorable outcome.&#x000a0;As the consumption of functional foods like buckwheat increases, healthcare providers should remain vigilant for rare but serious toxicological effects.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group content-type="conflict"><title>Disclosures</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Human subjects:</bold> Consent for treatment and open access publication was obtained or waived by all participants in this study.</p><p><bold>Conflicts of interest:</bold> In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following:</p><p><bold>Payment/services info:</bold> All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work.</p><p><bold>Financial relationships:</bold> All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work.</p><p><bold>Other relationships:</bold> All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="other"><title>Author Contributions</title><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Concept and design:</bold>&#x000a0; Daniela Barbosa Mateus, Carolina Henriques Gomes, Jo&#x000e3;o Barbosa Barroso, Sofia Cruz</p><p><bold>Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data:</bold>&#x000a0; Daniela Barbosa Mateus, Carolina Henriques Gomes, Jo&#x000e3;o Barbosa Barroso, Sofia Cruz</p><p><bold>Drafting of the manuscript:</bold>&#x000a0; Daniela Barbosa Mateus</p><p><bold>Critical review of the manuscript for important intellectual content:</bold>&#x000a0; Daniela Barbosa Mateus, Carolina Henriques Gomes, Jo&#x000e3;o Barbosa Barroso, Sofia Cruz</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="REF1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Simultaneous determination of atropine and scopolamine in buckwheat and related products using modified QuEChERS and liquid chromatography tandem mass spectrometry</article-title><source>Food Chem</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mar&#x000ed;n-S&#x000e1;ez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Romero-Gonz&#x000e1;lez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Garrido Frenich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>173</fpage><lpage>180</lpage><volume>218</volume><year>2017</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27719895</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Nutritional and bioactive characteristics of buckwheat, and its potential for developing gluten-free products: an updated overview</article-title><source>Food Sci Nutr</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Sofi</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Farooq</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>2256</fpage><lpage>2276</lpage><volume>11</volume><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37181307</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Occurrence and chemistry of tropane alkaloids in foods, with a focus on sample analysis methods: a review on recent trends and technological advances</article-title><source>Foods</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez-G&#x000f3;mez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morante-Zarcero</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>P&#x000e9;rez-Quintanilla</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sierra</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
</person-group><volume>11</volume><year>2022</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Cereal alkaloids</article-title><source>J Food Health Technol Innov</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Menkovska</surname><given-names>Menkovska</given-names></name>
<name><surname>M</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>134</fpage><lpage>153</lpage><volume>2</volume><year>2019</year><uri xlink:href="https://dergipark.org.tr/en/pub/food/issue/51905/676116">https://dergipark.org.tr/en/pub/food/issue/51905/676116</uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><article-title>Anticholinergic toxicity</article-title><source>StatPearls</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Broderick</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Metheny</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Crosby</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group><publisher-loc>Treasure Island, FL</publisher-loc><publisher-name>StatPearls Publishing</publisher-name><year>2024</year><uri xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK534798/">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK534798/</uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Anticholinergic syndrome induced by toxic plants</article-title><source>World J Emerg Med</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Soulaidopoulos</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sinakos</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dimopoulou</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vettas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cholongitas</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Garyfallos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>297</fpage><lpage>301</lpage><volume>8</volume><year>2017</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29123609</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Risk assessment of buckwheat flour contaminated by thorn-apple (Datura stramonium L.) alkaloids: a case study from Slovenia</article-title><source>Food Addit Contam Part A Chem Anal Control Expo Risk Assess</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Perhari&#x0010d;</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ko&#x0017e;elj</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dru&#x0017e;ina</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stanovnik</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>321</fpage><lpage>330</lpage><volume>30</volume><year>2013</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23244511</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Pharmacological management of anticholinergic delirium - theory, evidence and practice</article-title><source>Br J Clin Pharmacol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Dawson</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Buckley</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>516</fpage><lpage>524</lpage><volume>81</volume><year>2016</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26589572</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>