<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40394095</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12092728</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2161</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-025-02161-1</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><italic>Orobanche aegyptiaca</italic>-chitosan nanocomposite efficacy against the freshwater snail <italic>Biomphalaria alexandrina</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Abdel-Khalek</surname><given-names>Reda Ramadan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Abdel-Ghaffar</surname><given-names>Fathy</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hamdi</surname><given-names>Salwa Abdel-Hamid</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>Amina M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fol</surname><given-names>Mona Fathi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Mostafa</surname><given-names>Nesma Abbas</given-names></name><address><email>nesma_abass@cu.edu.eg</email><email>nesma_abass@yahoo.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/03q21mh05</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.7776.1</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0639 9286</institution-id><institution>Zoology Department, Faculty of Science, </institution><institution>Cairo University, </institution></institution-wrap>Giza, Egypt </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/04d4dr544</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.420091.e</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0165 571X</institution-id><institution>Medical Malacology Department, </institution><institution>Theodor Bilharz Research Institute, </institution></institution-wrap>Giza, Egypt </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>20</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>17553</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>12</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">As one of the neglected tropical diseases, schistosomiasis is responsible for various social and economic issues in numerous developing countries. The intermediate host of <italic>Schistosoma mansoni</italic> is the <italic>Biomphalaria alexandrina</italic> snails. A promising approach to mitigate the transmission of this disease is to use medicinal plants loaded with nanomaterials to control these snails. This research aimed to investigate the molluscicidal activity of <italic>Orobanche aegyptiaca-</italic> chitosan nanocomposite on <italic>B. alexandrina</italic> snails. The phytochemical screening of the tested plant verified its abundance of saponins, tannins, and flavonoids, which may be responsible for its cytotoxic effects. Chitosan nanoparticles were produced using the ionotropic gelation technique, while the <italic>O. aegyptiaca</italic>-chitosan nanocomposite was synthesized using the sonochemical approach. The characterization of the nanocomposite was carried out using TEM, XRD, and Zeta potential. The results demonstrated that the survival, fecundity (eggs/snail/week), and reproductive rates of <italic>B. alexandrina</italic> snails were substantially reduced upon exposure to the sub-lethal concentrations LC10 or LC25 of <italic>O. aegyptiaca</italic>-chitosan nanocomposite. Biochemically, it adversely affected some parameters, where it considerably (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) raised ALT, AST, and ALP levels, while urea, uric acid, and cholesterol were significantly decreased compared to control snails. Furthermore, the antioxidant markers CAT, SOD, and GSH exhibited a substantial (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) reduction, while MDA and NO levels increased at both sublethal concentrations. Histopathological examinations of the digestive gland of the treated <italic>B. alexandrina</italic> revealed a decrease in the size of the tubules, and the digestive and secretory cells degenerated. The hermaphrodite glands exhibited substantial damage in the reproductive tubules, with extensive damage to the gonadal cells, resulting in the loss of ova and sperm shapes. Also, the comet analysis showed a genotoxic effect of the nanocomposite, evidenced by significant changes in crucial comet assay parameters: tail length (TL), tail DNA percentage (TD), tail moment (TM), and olive tail moment (OTM). Conclusively, these findings confirmed the potential activity of <italic>O. aegyptiaca-</italic> chitosan nanocomposite as a molluscicidal agent against <italic>B. alexandrina</italic> to decrease schistosomiasis transmission.</p></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Chitosan</kwd><kwd><italic>Orobanche aegyptiaca</italic></kwd><kwd><italic>Biomphalaria Alexandrina</italic></kwd><kwd>Oxidative stress</kwd><kwd>Histopathological</kwd><kwd>Comet assay</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Biochemistry</kwd><kwd>Biological techniques</kwd><kwd>Biotechnology</kwd><kwd>Zoology</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Cairo University</institution></funding-source></award-group><open-access><p>Open access funding provided by The Science, Technology &#x00026; Innovation Funding Authority (STDF) in cooperation with The Egyptian Knowledge Bank (EKB).</p></open-access></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Springer Nature Limited 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Schistosomiasis ranks second most frequently overlooked parasitic infection after malaria<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. <italic>B. alexandrina</italic> snails serve as the intermediate host for <italic>S. mansoni</italic>, which is extensively spread over various regions of Africa, the Middle East, and South America<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>, resulting in considerable mortality and morbidity on a global scale<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. To remove this disease, it is necessary to disrupt the snail&#x02019;s life cycle<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. This can be achieved through chemical control or natural molluscicides<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. Although chemical controlling of the intermediate host of schistosomiasis effectively decreases transmission<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>, their significant cost and potential risks to non-target organisms have prompted the utilization of natural molluscicides<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. Furthermore, chemical molluscicide applications are expensive and require substantial financial resources, and they must be repeated annually to prevent snails from returning to water systems<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>. Recently, Egypt has implemented plant molluscicides as part of its schistosome, which requires substantial financial resources and a management program<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. Medicinal plants have emerged as the primary source of molluscicide agents due to their cost-effectiveness and few adverse effects compared to chemical medications<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. The plants possess several bioactive constituents exerting antibacterial, fungicidal, herbicidal, molluscicidal, and pesticidal effects<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. Plants rich in saponins, flavonoids, and terpenoids exhibit significant potential for managing schistosomiasis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. The Egyptian broomrape or <italic>Orobanche</italic> is a chlorophyll-deficient, obligate root-holoparasitic plant that parasitizes vegetable and field crops associated with Solanaceae, Leguminaceae, and Brassicaceae<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>. A broomrape infestation causes oxidative stress and leads to the generation of reactive oxygen species (ROS) which can damage proteins, carbohydrates, DNA and RNA, lipids, and can result in cell death<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. Medicinal plants growing in regions with endemic schistosomiasis could serve as valuable supplementary agents, either molluscicides or chemotherapeutics, to manage this disease. Over the last few decades, nano-enhanced approaches have been extensively evaluated for controlling parasitic infections with promising outcomes, although many challenges limit their broad implementation. Numerous researchers attempted to exploit the distinctive characteristics of nano-based delivery systems to enhance treatment<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>, develop new prophylactics<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>, and reduce the prevalence of parasitic diseases in snail hosts, resulting in significant morbidity in poor and developing nations worldwide<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. The reduction in particle size can change materials&#x02019; physical, chemical, and structural properties, which might give rise to novel and unexpected biological effects<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. Chitosan is an amino polysaccharide produced by partially deacetylating chitin, primarily derived from crustaceans or fungal species<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. Its beneficial characteristics, such as low molecular weight, high water solubility, and diverse biological activities, including antibacterial, anti-inflammatory, antioxidant, and anti-diabetic properties, have received more attention<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>. Therefore, the current study aims to investigate the molluscicidal activity of <italic>O. aegyptiaca</italic>- chitosan nanocomposite on <italic>B. alexandrina</italic> snails via assessing the biological, biochemical, histopathological changes, and genotoxic effect of snail tissues.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par3">The current study followed guidelines approved by the Cairo University Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee (CU-IACUC).</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Experimental snails</title><p id="Par4"><italic>Biomphalaria alexandrina</italic> snails ranging from (9&#x02013;11&#x000a0;mm) were acquired from the Medical Malacology Laboratory at the Theodor Bilharz Research Institute (TBRI) in Giza, Egypt. The snails were subsequently cultivated in a plastic aquarium measuring 15&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;24&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10&#x000a0;cm at a temperature of 25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C and a light-dark cycle of 12&#x000a0;h: 12&#x000a0;h for 4 weeks before the beginning of the experiments. Each aquarium contained dechlorinated tap water (50 snails/ aquarium) and was provided with blue-green algae (<italic>Nostoc muscorum</italic>) and oven-dry lettuce leaves for feeding. The aquaria water was changed once a week on<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Plant materials</title><p id="Par5">The Egyptian broomrape <italic>Orobanche aegyptiaca</italic> Pers. leaves were collected from the Giza Governorate, Egypt. They were identified by Dr. Hasnaa Hosney, a Professor of Botany, Faculty of Science, Cairo University. Using an electronic grinder, the leaves were dried and finely powdered. Voucher specimens of the tested plant were deposited at the Herbarium of the Faculty of Science, Cairo University (deposition number: Cai. 97. 465. 1373. 38). A stock solution of 5% (5&#x000a0;g of leaf powder in 100&#x000a0;ml of distilled water) was soaked at room temperature for 24&#x000a0;h; then it was filtered and kept till being used.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Phytochemical tests</title><p id="Par6">To ascertain the presence or absence of different phytoconstituents, such as alkaloids in Mayer&#x02019;s and Draggendorff&#x02019;s tests<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>, flavonoids (Shinoda test, aluminium chloride, and potassium hydroxide tests), steroids and terpenoids (Salkowski and Liebermann-Burchard&#x02019;s tests), and tannins (ferric chloride and gelatin tests) according to Harborne<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>, qualitative phytochemical screening tests were conducted. Saponins were estimated to use foaming and haemolytic tests<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>, anthraquinones by Borntrager&#x02019;s test, carbohydrates via Molisch&#x02019;s and Barfoed&#x02019;s tests, and coumarins with the Sodium hydroxide test, as per Gul et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. The outcomes were assessed through visual observation for alterations in colour or precipitation.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Synthesis of chitosan nanoparticles</title><p id="Par7">The ionotropic gelation method, as described by Calvo et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>, was employed to synthesize chitosan nanoparticles. This method involves electrostatic interaction between the amine group of chitosan and tripolyphosphate. Nevertheless, 3&#x000a0;g of chitosan, which had been dissolved in diluted glacial acetic acid (4&#x000a0;ml glacial acetic acid to 296&#x000a0;ml doubled deionized water), was added to 2&#x000a0;g of sodium tripolyphosphate in 200&#x000a0;ml doubled deionized water. The mixture was agitated for 4&#x000a0;h and placed at 40 &#x000ba;C for 24&#x000a0;h until a white gel formed. Finally, the sample was desiccated in an oven at 40 &#x000ba;C for 24&#x000a0;h.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Preparation of <italic>Orobanche aegyptiaca</italic>-chitosan nanocomposite</title><p id="Par8">The <italic>O. aegyptiaca</italic>-chitosan nanocomposite was synthesized via the sonochemical approach, where the production and collapse of microbubbles induced by ultrasonic effects generated extreme conditions that facilitated the incorporation of <italic>O. aegyptiaca</italic> nanoparticles into the chitosan matrix. First, 0.1&#x000a0;g of <italic>O. aegyptiaca</italic> powder was incorporated into 100&#x000a0;ml of double-distilled water and agitated at 1200&#x000a0;rpm at 45 &#x000ba;C using a magnetic stirrer for 30&#x000a0;min. Subsequently, 0.1&#x000a0;g of chitosan nanoparticles were incorporated, and stirring was prolonged for 30&#x000a0;min. Then, the mixture was placed in an ultrasonic device for nanocomposite synthesis under the specified conditions: Pulsate every 2&#x000a0;s at 85% amplitude power for 6&#x000a0;h.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Characterization <italic>Orobanche aegyptiaca</italic>-chitosan nanocomposite</title><sec id="Sec10"><title>Transmission electron microscopy (TEM)</title><p id="Par9">The morphology and particle size of the <italic>O. aegyptiaca</italic>-chitosan nanocomposite were analyzed using TEM (EM-2100 High-Resolution-Japan) at a magnification of 20X and an accelerating voltage of 200&#x000a0;kV to evaluate the two-dimensional shape and size. A droplet from a dilute sample solution was placed on an amorphous carbon-coated copper grid and allowed to dry at ambient temperature. The resultant monolayer of particles was examined with the Image J software, and many TEM pictures were captured<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>(XRD) X-ray diffraction analysis</title><p id="Par10">The XRD pattern of the <italic>O. aegyptiaca</italic>- chitosan nanocomposite was examined using a Bruker D8 Discover XRD analyzer. The light source utilized was Cu K&#x003b1; radiation, operating at a current of 35&#x000a0;mA and a voltage of 40&#x000a0;kV. The 2&#x003b8; angles ranged from 5&#x000b0; to 80&#x000b0;, with a scanning rate of 0.3&#x000b0; perz minute. The mean crystal size was determined using the Scherrer formula:</p><p id="Par11">
<inline-formula id="IEq1"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e438">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\text{D}}\,=\,0.{\text{89}}\uplambda /\beta {\text{cos}}\upphi$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_2161_Article_IEq1.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</p><p id="Par12">where D represents the mean crystal size, &#x003bb; is the x-ray wavelength, 0.89 is the shape factor, &#x003b2; indicates the line broadening at half maximum intensity (FWHM) in radians, and &#x003b8; is the Bragg angle.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Zeta potential analysis</title><p id="Par13">The zeta potential of <italic>O. aegyptiaca-</italic> chitosan nanocomposite was determined using a zeta potential analyzer (Zetasizer Nano ZS Malvern).</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>UV spectrum</title><p id="Par14">
<disp-quote><p id="Par15">UV&#x02013;vis absorption spectrum was obtained using a spectrophotometer (Thermo Scientific, Helios gamma) at a wavelength range of 200&#x02013;900&#x000a0;nm.</p></disp-quote>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Toxicity assessment of <italic>O. aegyptiaca</italic>-chitosan nanocomposite</title><p id="Par16">To investigate the lethality of <italic>O. aegyptiaca-</italic>chitosan nanocomposite against adult <italic>B. alexandrina</italic> snails, 1000&#x000a0;mg/L a stock solution was prepared. Serial concentrations (70, 60, 50, 40,30, 20, and 10&#x000a0;mg/l) in 100&#x000a0;ml distilled water were set in transparent glass beakers. Three replicates of ten adult snails were exposed to 24&#x000a0;h for each concentration at 25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C and pH 7.4. Control snails were sustained under the same testing conditions in dechlorinated water. Subsequently, they were extracted and meticulously rinsed with dechlorinated tap water before being placed in containers with freshly dechlorinated tap water for 24&#x000a0;h of recuperation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. The observed mortality percentages of snails were documented, and the sub-lethal concentrations were established by probit analysis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. The statistical application SPSS was utilized to estimate the LC<sub>0</sub> at one-tenth of the LC<sub>50</sub> value<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Effect of <italic>O. aegyptiaca-</italic>chitosan nanocomposite on the survival rate, and egg laying capacity, reproductive rate of <italic>B. alexandrina</italic> snails</title><p id="Par17">Snails (9&#x02013;11&#x000a0;mm) were subjected to (LC<sub>10</sub> 32.3&#x000a0;mg/l and LC<sub>25</sub> 37.7&#x000a0;mg/l) concentrations of the <italic>O. aegyptiaca-</italic> chitosan nanocomposite for 24&#x000a0;h/ week, followed by 7 days of recovery in dechlorinated water for four weeks. Three replicates of 10 snails/L were saved for each concentration, with an additional set of snails serving as a control in clean, dechlorinated tap water. The water was changed twice every week. Dead snails were collected daily, and the survival rate was estimated according to Frank<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup> using the following equation:<disp-formula id="Equa"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e514">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:Survival\:rate=\frac{\text{N}\text{u}\text{m}\text{b}\text{e}\text{r}\:\text{o}\text{f}\:\text{s}\text{u}\text{r}\text{v}\text{i}\text{v}\text{e}\text{d}\:\text{s}\text{n}\text{a}\text{i}\text{l}\text{s}\:}{\:Total\:number\:of\:exposed\:snails}\:\:\times\:100$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_2161_Article_Equa.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par18">The egg mass was collected daily by placing small pieces of polyethylene film over the aquaria, as reported by Pellegrino et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>. The eggs were then preserved in small jars until they hatched. The egg-laying capacity is denoted as (Mx), representing the weekly number of eggs per snail. The reproductive rate (R0) is calculated as the summation of LxMx over the experimental duration<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Determination of biochemical indicators</title><sec id="Sec17"><title>Tissue homogenization</title><p id="Par19">Control and treated snails&#x02019; soft tissues were weighed and homogenized (10%wt/vol) in an ice-cold (0.1&#x000a0;M Tris HCl buffer, pH 7.4) using a glass Dounce homogenizer (Swedesboro, USA). The homogenates were centrifuged for 15&#x000a0;min at 3000&#x000a0;rpm at 4<sup>o</sup>C. The resulting supernatant was kept at &#x02212;&#x02009;80<sup>o</sup>C.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Hepatic and renal markers</title><p id="Par20">The obtained supernatants were utilized to assess renal function indicators (creatinine, urea, uric acid, and albumin) and hepatic markers (alanine aminotransferase (ALT), aspartate aminotransferase (AST), alkaline phosphatase (ALP), and total protein), as well as total cholesterol (TC) and triglycerides (TG) employing Bio Diagnostic kits from Egypt.</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Oxidative stress markers</title><p id="Par21">Lipid peroxidation process was assessed through the generation of malondialdehyde (MDA)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. The stress-induced synthesis of nitric oxide (NO) was examined as outlined by Montgomery and Dymock<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>. Reduced glutathione (GSH) is the primary intracellular thiol utilized by cells for signaling antioxidant defense<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>. Catalase activity (CAT) serves as a defense mechanism against H2O2-induced stress<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>, whereas superoxide dismutase (SOD) was assessed according to the method of Nishikimi et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup> using Bio Diagnostic kits in Egypt.</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Histopathological studies</title><p id="Par22">Soft parts of both the control and treated snails were gently extracted from the shells. The hermaphrodite and digestive glands of each snail were rigorously isolated and preserved in Bouin&#x02019;s solution, subsequently embedded in paraffin wax, sectioned, and stained with hematoxylin and eosin. Sections were inspected with a Zeiss microscope (Carl Zeiss Micrography GmbH 07.745 Jena, Germany) at magnifications of 200x and 400x.</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Comet assay</title><p id="Par23">Snails (9&#x02013;11&#x000a0;mm) were subjected to LC10 or LC25 of <italic>O. aegyptiaca</italic>- chitosan nanocomposite, and then DNA damage was measured by single cell gel assay according to Grazeffe et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup> as shown: The tissues were weighed and homogenized in ice-cold phosphate buffer at a 1:10 (w/v) ratio using a glass homogenizer for 5&#x000a0;min. The homogenized samples were centrifuged at 1,700&#x000a0;g for 15&#x000a0;min at 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. After centrifugation, the resulting suspension was stirred for 5&#x000a0;min and filtered. After that, A 100&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l aliquot of the cell suspension was combined with 600&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l of 0.8% low-melting-point agarose prepared in PBS. Subsequently, 100&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l of this agarose-cell mixture was evenly spread onto pre-coated microscope slides. The slides were immersed in a lysis buffer solution (0.045&#x000a0;M Tris-borate-EDTA (TBE), pH 8.4, with 2.5% sodium dodecyl sulfate (SDS) for 15&#x000a0;min to facilitate cell lysis. After lysis, the slides were transferred to an electrophoresis chamber containing TBE buffer (without SDS). Electrophoresis was conducted under specific conditions: slides were exposed to 2&#x000a0;V/cm for 2&#x000a0;min at a current of 100&#x000a0;mA. Following electrophoresis, the slides were stained with ethidium bromide (20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml) and stored at 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C until analysis. The slides were examined using a fluorescence microscope equipped with an excitation filter of 420&#x02013;490&#x000a0;nm and an emission filter at 510&#x000a0;nm. DNA migration patterns were evaluated in 100 cells, where comet tail lengths were measured from the nucleus&#x02019;s center to the tail&#x02019;s end at 40x. Each slide was stained with 100&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l of 1X ethidium bromide to enhance visualization. Slides were examined under an epifluorescence microscope (Zeiss, 400x magnification) with an image analysis system. Images of 50 randomly selected comets per slide were captured and analyzed for comet tail length, percentage of DNA in the tail, and tail moment, using Comet Assay V.20 software to quantify DNA damage parameters accurately.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par24">Statistical Processor Systems Support (SPSS) software, version 20, was employed to conduct a One-Way ANOVA on the data, followed by a Duncan post-hoc test to compare the means of the groups. The data were presented as the mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;standard error of the mean (SEM). Statistical significance was determined at <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec24"><title>Phytochemical screening analysis of <italic>O. aegyptiaca</italic> leaves aqueous extract</title><p id="Par25">The aqueous extract of <italic>O. aegyptiaca</italic> leaves is rich in various phytochemical components such as alkaloids, flavonoids, saponin, tannins, carbohydrates, phenols, steroids, and terpenoids (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Also, the total phenolic content and the antioxidant capacity were 320.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.1 and 245.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.9, respectively (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p><p id="Par26">
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Phytochemical screening analysis of <italic>Orobanche aegyptiaca</italic> leaves aqueous extract.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Secondary metabolites</th><th align="left">Phytochemical test</th><th align="left">Aqueous extract of O. aegyptiaca</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Flavonoids</td><td align="left">i. Shinoda</td><td align="left">+++</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ii. AlCl<sub>3</sub></td><td align="left">+++</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Saponins</td><td align="left">i. Frothing</td><td align="left">+++</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Alkaloids</td><td align="left">i. Dragendorff&#x02019;s</td><td align="left">+++</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ii. Meyer&#x02019;s</td><td align="left">++</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Tannins</td><td align="left">i. FeCl<sub>3</sub></td><td align="left">++</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Terpenoids &#x00026; Steroids</td><td align="left">i. Salkowski</td><td align="left">++</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ii. Libarman-Burchard&#x02019;s</td><td align="left">++</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Anthraquinones</td><td align="left">i. Borntrager&#x02019;s</td><td align="left">++</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Carbohydrates</td><td align="left">i. Molisch&#x02019;s</td><td align="left">++</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ii. Barfoed&#x02019;s</td><td align="left">++</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Coumarins</td><td align="left">i. NaOH</td><td align="left">-</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>-: not detected, +: low concentration, ++: moderate, +++: high concentration.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par27">
<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Total phenolic content (TPC) and total antioxidant capacity (TAC) of <italic>O. aegyptiaca</italic> leaves aqueous extract.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Parameter</th><th align="left"><italic>O. aegyptiaca</italic> leaves aqueous extract</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">TPC (mg gallic acid equivalent/ g extract)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">320.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">TAC (mg AAE/g dry sample)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">245.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.9</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Data was expressed as (means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;S.E.)</p><p>TPC (total phenolic content) values are expressed as mg gallic acid equivalent/g extract (mg GAE/g ext.).</p><p>AAE: Ascorbic acid equivalent.</p><p>Total antioxidant capacity (TAC) values are expressed as mg AAE/g dry sample.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec25"><title>Characterization of <italic>O. aegyptiaca-</italic>chitosan nanocomposite</title><p id="Par28">The TEM images of <italic>O. aegyptiaca-</italic> chitosan nanocomposite confirmed a spherical shape forming chain-like aggregates with particle size diameters ranging from 27.1 to 83.4&#x000a0;nm (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). The XRD pattern illustrates the presence of five characteristic peaks at 2&#x003b8;&#x02009;=&#x02009;20.61&#x000b0;, 21.74&#x000b0;, 23.79&#x000b0; 26.36&#x000b0; and 29.69&#x000b0;. Other additional faint peaks appeared at 36.09&#x000b0;, 39.06&#x000b0;, 42.01&#x000b0;, 44.73&#x000b0;, 45.40&#x000b0; and 49.65&#x000b0; are probably residual chitin peaks because of the incomplete deacetylation (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Also, the zeta potential analysis shown in (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>) revealed a positive value of +&#x02009;5.51 mV, indicating the minimal stability of <italic>O. aegyptiaca-</italic> chitosan nanocomposite<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>. The UV&#x02013;vis spectrum of chitosan nanoparticles is shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>. Broad absorption bands observed at 273 and 294&#x000a0;nm could be related to the CO group<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par29">
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>TEM image of <italic>O. aegyptiaca-</italic>chitosan nanocomposite.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_2161_Fig1_HTML" id="d33e804"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par30">
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>XRD pattern of <italic>O. aegyptiaca-</italic>chitosan nanocomposite.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_2161_Fig2_HTML" id="d33e818"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par31">
<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Zeta potential analysis of <italic>O. aegyptiaca-</italic>chitosan nanocomposite.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_2161_Fig3_HTML" id="d33e832"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par32">
<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>UV/Vis spectrum of concentrations of <italic>O. aegyptiaca-</italic>chitosan nanocomposite.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_2161_Fig4_HTML" id="d33e846"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec26"><title>Toxicity findings of <italic>O. aegyptiaca</italic>-chitosan nanocomposite on <italic>Biomphalaria alexandrina</italic></title><p id="Par33">The molluscicide properties of the nanocomposite against adult <italic>B. alexandrina</italic> snails were determined after 24&#x000a0;h of exposure, followed by 24&#x000a0;h of recovery. As shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>, The obtained results revealed that the value of the median lethal concentration (LC<sub>50</sub>) that <italic>O. aegyptiaca</italic>- chitosan nanocomposite is highly toxic against <italic>B. alexandrina</italic> at the concentration (43.7&#x000a0;mg/l) and other lethal concentrations were LC<sub>0</sub> (4.3&#x000a0;mg/l), LC<sub>10</sub> (32.3&#x000a0;mg/l), LC<sub>25</sub> (37. 7&#x000a0;mg/l), and LC<sub>90</sub> (55.1&#x000a0;mg/l).</p><p id="Par34">
<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Mortality rate (%) of adult <italic>Biomphalaria alexandrina</italic> after 24&#x000a0;h exposure to various concentrations of <italic>O. aegyptiaca-</italic>chitosan nanocomposite against adult <italic>Biomphalaria alexandrina</italic> by probit analysis.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_2161_Fig5_HTML" id="d33e899"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec27"><title>Effect of <italic>O. aegyptiaca-</italic>chitosan nanocomposite on survival rate (L<sub>x</sub>), fecundity (M<sub>x</sub>), and reproductive rate of adult <italic>B. alexandrina</italic> snails</title><p id="Par35">The findings revealed that the survival rate (Lx) of snails exposed to LC0 (4.3&#x000a0;mg/l) was barely reduced, reaching 0.75 by the fourth week of exposure. After four weeks of recuperation, the snails survived until the end of the experiment, with L<sub>X</sub> values of 0.50 in the eighth week, compared to 0.92 in the control group. Furthermore, exposure of snails to LC10 (32.3&#x000a0;mg/l) significantly reduced their survival rate (Lx) to 0.35 in the fourth week of exposure, compared to 0.98 in the control group. This group perished during their seventh week of recovery. Raising the concentration to LC25 (37.7&#x000a0;mg/l) produced a speedy and severe death among treated snails through the first 4 weeks of the experiment because their L<sub>X</sub> was 0.05, then the surviving snails could not withstand this treatment and perished by the fifth week of the experiment (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>).</p><p id="Par36">Additionally, snails&#x02019; fecundity (Mx) was adversely affected at the LC<sub>0</sub> (4.3&#x000a0;mg/l) of <italic>O. aegyptiaca-</italic> chitosan nanocomposite, decreasing the number of laid eggs/snails/weeks throughout the experiment. During the 4th and 8th weeks, treated snails laid 3.20 and 1.96 eggs/snail/week compared to 5.22 and 4.11 eggs/control snail/week, respectively. At LC<sub>10</sub> (32.3&#x000a0;mg/l), the snail&#x02019;s fecundity was highly suppressed in the 4th week to be 1.55 eggs/snail/ week, compared to 5.22 eggs/control snail/week. Moreover, the surviving snails stopped egg-laying in the 7th week till they died in the 8th week. Increasing the concentration to LC10 (37.7&#x000a0;mg/l) significantly diminished the snails&#x02019; fertility in the 4th week to 2.1 eggs per snail per week, in contrast to 5.22 eggs per control snail per week. The snails ceased in oviposition in the 5th week. They perished in the 6th week (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>). The reproductive rate (R<sub>O</sub>) of exposed snails revealed that it was significantly suppressed (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001) by snails&#x02019; exposure to the tested concentrations than the control group. At LC<sub>0</sub>, the reproductive rate (R<sub>o</sub>) was 18.54, with a percentage of 46.4% reduction in comparison with the control group (34.59). The R<sub>o</sub> values of snails exposed to LC<sub>10</sub> and LC<sub>25</sub> were 9.71 and 7.72, respectively, compared to 34.59 for control ones, and the reduced rates under these conditions were 71.9% and 77.6%, respectively (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>).</p><p id="Par37">
<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Survival rate (Lx) and fecundity (Mx) of adult <italic>B. alexandrina</italic> snails exposed for 24&#x000a0;h/ week to sub-lethal concentrations of <italic>O. aegyptiaca-</italic>chitosan nanocomposite for 4 successive weeks followed by 4 weeks of recovery.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Weeks</th><th align="left" colspan="3">Control</th><th align="left" colspan="3">LC<sub>0</sub> (4.3&#x000a0;mg/l)</th><th align="left" colspan="3">LC<sub>10</sub> (32.3&#x000a0;mg/l)</th><th align="left" colspan="3">LC<sub>25</sub> (37.7&#x000a0;mg/l)</th></tr><tr><th align="left">L<sub>x</sub></th><th align="left">M<sub>x</sub></th><th align="left">L<sub>x</sub>M<sub>x</sub></th><th align="left">L<sub>x</sub></th><th align="left">M<sub>x</sub></th><th align="left">L<sub>x</sub>M<sub>x</sub></th><th align="left">L<sub>x</sub></th><th align="left">M<sub>x</sub></th><th align="left">L<sub>x</sub>M<sub>x</sub></th><th align="left">L<sub>x</sub></th><th align="left">M<sub>x</sub></th><th align="left">L<sub>x</sub>M<sub>x</sub></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">1.00</td><td align="left">3.96</td><td align="left">3.96</td><td align="left">1.00</td><td align="left">3.96</td><td align="left">3.96</td><td align="left">1.00</td><td align="left">3.96</td><td align="left">3.96</td><td align="left">1.00</td><td align="left">3.96</td><td align="left">3.96</td></tr><tr><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1.00</td><td align="left">4.23</td><td align="left">4.23</td><td align="left">0.95</td><td align="left">3.99</td><td align="left">3.79</td><td align="left">0.85</td><td align="left">4.91</td><td align="left">4.17</td><td align="left">0.75</td><td align="left">5.96</td><td align="left">4.47</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">1.00</td><td align="left">4.59</td><td align="left">4.59</td><td align="left">0.90</td><td align="left">4.51</td><td align="left">4.05</td><td align="left">0.70</td><td align="left">4.6</td><td align="left">3.22</td><td align="left">0.50</td><td align="left">5.4</td><td align="left">2.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">0.99</td><td align="left">4.85</td><td align="left">4.54</td><td align="left">0.80</td><td align="left">4.12</td><td align="left">3.29</td><td align="left">0.50</td><td align="left">2.18</td><td align="left">1.09</td><td align="left">0.10</td><td align="left">4.59</td><td align="left">0.45</td></tr><tr><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">0.98</td><td align="left">5.22</td><td align="left">5.11</td><td align="left">0.75</td><td align="left">3.20</td><td align="left">2.4</td><td align="left">0.35</td><td align="left">1.55</td><td align="left">0.54</td><td align="left">0.05</td><td align="left">2.1</td><td align="left">0.10</td></tr><tr><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">0.98</td><td align="left">4.61</td><td align="left">4.51</td><td align="left">0.70</td><td align="left">2.3</td><td align="left">1.61</td><td align="left">0.15</td><td align="left">1.32</td><td align="left">0.19</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">6</td><td align="left">0.96</td><td align="left">3.98</td><td align="left">3.82</td><td align="left">0.60</td><td align="left">2.3</td><td align="left">1.38</td><td align="left">0.50</td><td align="left">1.01</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">7</td><td align="left">0.95</td><td align="left">4.23</td><td align="left">4.01</td><td align="left">0.50</td><td align="left">1.89</td><td align="left">0.94</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">0.92</td><td align="left">4.11</td><td align="left">3.78</td><td align="left">0.50</td><td align="left">1.96</td><td align="left">1.078</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">R<sub>O =</sub> &#x003a3;Lx Mx</td><td align="left" colspan="2">34.59</td><td align="left" colspan="3">**18.54</td><td align="left" colspan="3">***9.71</td><td align="left" colspan="3">***7.72</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">Reduction %</td><td align="left" colspan="2"/><td align="left" colspan="3">46.4</td><td align="left" colspan="3">71.9</td><td align="left" colspan="3">77.6</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par38">***Highly significant from control at <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001, compared to control.</p><p id="Par39">
<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Histogram shows the survival rate (Lx) of adult <italic>B. alexandrina</italic> snails exposed to sub-lethal concentrations of <italic>O. aegyptiaca-</italic> chitosan nanocomposite for 24&#x000a0;h/ week for 4 weeks followed by 4 weeks of recovery.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_2161_Fig6_HTML" id="d33e1352"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par40">
<fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Histogram shows the fecundity (Mx) of <italic>B. alexandrina</italic> snails exposed to sub-lethal concentrations of <italic>O. aegyptiaca -</italic>chitosan nanocomposite for 24&#x000a0;h/ week for 4 weeks, followed by 4 weeks of recovery.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_2161_Fig7_HTML" id="d33e1369"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par41">
<fig id="Fig8"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>Histogram shows the reproductive rate (R<sub>0</sub>) of adult <italic>B. alexandrina</italic> snails exposed to sub-lethal concentrations of <italic>O. aegyptiaca-</italic>chitosan nanocomposite for 24&#x000a0;h/ week for 4 weeks followed by four weeks of recovery.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_2161_Fig8_HTML" id="d33e1388"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec28"><title>Biochemical parameters</title><p id="Par42">Compared with the control snails, the sublethal concentrations LC<sub>10</sub> (32.3&#x000a0;mg/l) and LC<sub>25</sub> (37.78&#x000a0;mg/l) of <italic>O. aegyptiaca</italic><bold><italic>-</italic></bold> chitosan nanocomposite showed a high significant (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) increase in AST, ALT and ALP activities in snails&#x02019; tissue after exposure for 24&#x000a0;h as demonstrated in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>. However, albumin total and protein did not affect significantly (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) with the sublethal concentrations LC<sub>10</sub> (32.3&#x000a0;mg/l) and LC<sub>25</sub> (37.78&#x000a0;mg/l) of <italic>O. aegyptiaca</italic><bold><italic>-</italic></bold> chitosan nanocomposite. Also, it was observed that urea, uric acid, and cholesterol concentrations significantly (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) dropped while creatinine and triglyceride appeared normal. In addition, lipid profile, cholesterol.</p><p id="Par43">
<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Effect of <italic>O. aegyptiaca-</italic>chitosan nanocomposite on biochemical parameters.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Groups</th><th align="left">Control</th><th align="left">LC<sub>10</sub> (32.3&#x000a0;mg/l)</th><th align="left">LC<sub>25</sub> (37.7&#x000a0;mg/l)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">AST (U/ml)</td><td align="left">10.75&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.3<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">53.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.58<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">46.17&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;10.7<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">ALT (U/ml)</td><td align="left">1.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.35<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">60.22&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.15<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">72.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.69<sup>c</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">ALP (U/L)</td><td align="left">18.49&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.0<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">39.67&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.93<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">68.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.99<sup>c</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Total protein (g/dl)</td><td align="left">1.81&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.06<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">1.74&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.26<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">1.79&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.117<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Albumin (g/dl)</td><td align="left">1.18&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.07<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">1.40&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.089<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">1.59&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.018<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Urea (mg/dl)</td><td align="left">11.86&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.37<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">6.55&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.25<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">7.28&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.367<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Uric acid (mg/dl)</td><td align="left">2.11&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.26<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">1.80&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.88<sup>a, b</sup></td><td align="left">1.84&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.19 <sup>a, b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Creatinine (mg/dl)</td><td align="left">0.33&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.10<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">0.402&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.156<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">0.736&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.13<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Triglycerides (mg/dl)</td><td align="left">176.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;18.73<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">177.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;14.46<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">187.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;12.17<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Total cholesterol (mg/dl)</td><td align="left">137.09&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;45.7<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">52.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.06<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">48.02&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.63<sup>b</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Data represented as mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SEM, values with different superscript letters are considered significant (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05).</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec29"><title>Oxidative stress state</title><p id="Par44">The results showed a decline in antioxidant markers, including GSH content and catalase and superoxide dismutase of snail tissue after exposure to LC<sub>10</sub> (32.3&#x000a0;mg\l) and LC<sub>25</sub> (37.78&#x000a0;mg\l) of <italic>O. aegyptiaca</italic>- chitosan nanocomposite. These sub-lethal concentrations caused a substantial increase in MDA and NO levels relative to controlling snails in a concentration-dependent manner, as shown in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>.</p><p id="Par45">
<table-wrap id="Tab5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Effect of <italic>O. aegyptiaca-</italic>chitosan nanocomposite on oxidative stress markers.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Groups</th><th align="left">Control</th><th align="left">LC<sub>10</sub> (32.3&#x000a0;mg/l)</th><th align="left">LC<sub>25</sub> (37.7&#x000a0;mg/l)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Catalase (CAT) (U/g.tissue)</td><td align="left">38.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.129<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">25.09&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.344<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">14.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.186 <sup>c</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Glutathione (GSH), (mg/g.tissue)</td><td align="left">320.75&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;7.16<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">216.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.17<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">155.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;9.66<sup>c</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Superoxide dismutase (SOD), (U/g. tissue)</td><td align="left">14315.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1288.8<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">9672.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2990.56 <sup>a, b</sup></td><td align="left">3980.38&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1506.05<sup>c</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">MDA, (&#x000b5;mol/g.tissue)</td><td align="left">53.91&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.18<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">103.62&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.87<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">175.89&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;9.16<sup>c</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Nitric oxide (nmol/g.tissue)</td><td align="left">13.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.51<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">14.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.42<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">18.11&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.35<sup>b</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Data represented as mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SEM, values with different superscript letters are considered significant (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05).</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec30"><title>Histopathological studies</title><sec id="Sec31"><title>Digestive gland</title><p id="Par46">The digestive gland of control <italic>B. alexandrina</italic> comprises two unequal lobes interconnected by loose connective tissue and consists of tubular glands of varying sizes. Each tubule is lined by columnar digestive cells with rounded apices and pyramid-shaped secretory cells (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>a). The inter-tubular space between the digestive tubules increased because of the deterioration of connective tissue and the shrinkage following exposure to LC<sub>10</sub> (32.3&#x000a0;mg/l) of <italic>O. aegyptiaca</italic>- chitosan nanocomposite. Additionally, the lumen of each tubule was expanded, and some digestive and secretory cells degenerated and became vacuolated (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>b). The most devastating effect was seen at LC<sub>25</sub>, which included extensive degradation of the digestive tubules with expanded lumen. The secretory and digestive cells are severely damaged in most of the tubules. Additionally, epithelial cells deteriorated, resulting in the loss of cell boundaries. Digestive cells demonstrated apoptosis (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>c).</p><p id="Par47">
<fig id="Fig9"><label>Fig. 9</label><caption><p>Photomicrograph of the digestive gland of <italic>B. alexandrina</italic>, (<bold>a</bold>) Control snails showed digestive tubules surrounded by connective tissue and consist of digestive and secretory cells and a lumen in the center. (<bold>b</bold>) Snails exposed to LC<sub>10</sub> of <italic>O. aegyptiaca</italic>- chitosan nanocomposite showed degeneration of the connective tissue and shrinkage of some tubules with expanded lumen and some digestive and secretory cells became vacuolated. (<bold>c</bold>) Snails exposed to LC<sub>25</sub> showed rupture of some tubules and an increase in the lumen with severe damage in the digestive and secretory cells, and epithelial cells deteriorated, resulting in the loss of cell boundaries. Connective tissue CT, Digestive cells DC, Degenerated Digestive Cell DDC, Degenerated intestinal villi DIV, Degenerated Secretory Cells DSC, Digestive tubules DT, Inter tubular space IT, Lumen L, Secretory cells SC, vacuolated V, Vacuolated Digestive Cell VDC.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_2161_Fig9_HTML" id="d33e1799"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec32"><title>Hermaphrodite gland</title><p id="Par48"><bold>T</bold>he hermaphrodite gland of control <italic>B. alexandrina</italic> snails consists of cuboidal acini linked by connective tissue. The male gametes were categorized into primary and secondary spermatocytes, with fully matured spermatozoa identified in the lumen. The female oogenic cells populated the acinar lumen with primary and secondary oocytes and mature ova encased in a follicular membrane (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>a). Sections of snails&#x02019; hermaphrodite gland subjected to LC<sub>10</sub> of <italic>O. aegyptiaca-</italic> chitosan nanocomposite showed marked damage in some of the reproductive tubules with shrinkage, destruction, and degenerations of both male and female gonadal cells; ova and sperms with the absence of the developmental stages of spermatocytes and oocytes (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>b). At the higher concentration, LC<sub>25,</sub> the gonadal cells were severely damaged, where ova and sperms vanished their shapes and distingrated. The epithelial cells of the tubules deteriorated, resulting in cell boundary loss and nuclear pyknosis (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>c).</p><p id="Par49">
<fig id="Fig10"><label>Fig. 10</label><caption><p>Photomicrograph of the hermaphrodite gland of <italic>B. alexandrina</italic> snails. (<bold>a</bold>) Normal snails displaying cup-shaped acini with primary and secondary oocytes, mature ovum bounded by a follicular membrane with a large nucleus appeared, the male reproductive cells were distinguished into clusters of primary and secondary spermatocytes, and fully developed spermatozoa in the lumen. (<bold>b</bold>) Snails exposed to LC<sub>10</sub> of <italic>O. aegyptiaca-</italic> chitosan nanocomposite revealed marked shrinkage of the reproductive tubules with degenerations in oocytes, ova, and spermatocytes. (<bold>c</bold>) At LC<sub>25</sub> of <italic>O. aegyptiaca-</italic> chitosan nanocomposite, severe damage was represented by shrinkage of the acini and compacted tubules, female gonadal cells deteriorated, the lumen of the male acini concentrated with degenerated spermatozoa. Acini A, Degenerated ovum DO, Degenerated Oocyte DOC, Degenerated spermatocytes DSPC, Follicular cavity FC, Follicular membrane FM, Mature ovum O, nucleus N, Oocytes OC, Spermatids SP, Spermatocytes SPC, Vacuole V.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_2161_Fig10_HTML" id="d33e1859"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec33"><title>Comet analysis</title><p id="Par50">The results of the comet assay summarized in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref>; Figure <xref rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig">11</xref> revealed significant genotoxic effects of the sublethal concentrations LC10 and LC25 of <italic>O. aegyptiaca</italic>- chitosan nanocomposite, with specific metrics such as tail length (TL), tail DNA percentage (TD), tail moment (TM), and olive tail moment (OTM)&#x02014;highlighting the extent of DNA fragmentation and cellular impairment.</p><p id="Par51">Tail Length (TL), indicative of cellular malformation and DNA strand breaks, demonstrated a substantial increase in treated snails compared to controls. The control group exhibited a mean TL of 2.960&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.046 px, serving as a baseline for DNA integrity. In contrast, exposure to the LC10 concentration of <italic>O. aegyptiaca</italic>- chitosan nanocomposite led to a significant (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) increase in TL to 4.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.046 px. This increase was further amplified at the LC25 concentration, where TL rose sharply to 6.35&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.33 px, underscoring the high degree of DNA damage induced at elevated exposure levels. Tail DNA percentage (TD) represents the proportion of DNA migrating from the head of the comet. In the control group, TD was measured at 13.08&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.090%, reflecting limited DNA fragmentation. However, following LC10 exposure, there was a marked increase (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) to 20.27&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.79%, suggesting heightened DNA fragmentation at this concentration. The LC25 exposure group displayed an even more pronounced rise in TD to 21.49&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.60% (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05), indicating that higher concentrations of the nanocomposite substantially exacerbate DNA damage. Tail Moment (TM), a parameter that integrates tail length and the percentage of DNA in the tail, is a sensitive marker for DNA migration and the extent of damage. TM in the control group was recorded at 0.652&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.005, demonstrating baseline DNA stability. However, in the LC10 group, TM showed a notable increase (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) to 1.51&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.06, nearly doubling the control value and reflecting significant DNA migration and cellular genotoxic stress. The LC25 group exhibited an even more substantial rise in TM to 3.45&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.288 (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05), signifying severe genotoxicity in response to higher nanocomposite concentration. Olive Tail Moment (OTM), which indicates the extent of DNA fragmentation, exhibited a similar trend of significant increases in treated groups. The control group showed an OTM of 1.49&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.033, indicating low baseline DNA fragmentation. Exposure to LC10 resulted in a statistically significant (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) increase in OTM to 2.45&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.092, denoting moderate DNA damage. At the highest concentration, LC25, OTM increased sharply to 3.59&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.171 (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05), underscoring the high degree of DNA fragmentation induced by the nanocomposite treatment.</p><p id="Par52">
<table-wrap id="Tab6"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>DNA damage parameters of <italic>Biomphalaria alexandrina</italic> after exposure to <italic>O. aegyptiaca</italic>-chitosan nanocomposite.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Groups</th><th align="left">Control</th><th align="left">LC10 (32.3&#x000a0;mg/l)</th><th align="left">LC25 (37.7&#x000a0;mg/l)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Tail length (px)</td><td align="left">2.960&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.046<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">4.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.046 <sup>a, b</sup></td><td align="left">6.35&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.33<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">% DNA in tail</td><td align="left">13.08&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.090<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">20.27&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.79<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">21.49&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.60<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Tail moment (Unit)</td><td align="left">0.652&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.005<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">1.51&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.06<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">3.45&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.288<sup>c</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Olive tail moment (OTM)</td><td align="left">1.49&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.033<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">2.45&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.092<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">3.59&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.171<sup>c</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Groups with similar superscript letters indicate no significant differences, whereas different letters denote significant differences (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). All values are presented as mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SEM.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par53">
<fig id="Fig11"><label>Fig. 11</label><caption><p>DNA damage in <italic>B. alexandrina</italic> snails exposed to <italic>O.aegyptiaca</italic>-chitosan nanocomposite, visualized by comet assay. (<bold>A</bold>) The control group showed minimal DNA migration, with largely intact nuclei and short comet tails (indicated by arrows). (<bold>B</bold>) Snails exposed to LC<sub>10</sub> (32.3&#x000a0;mg/L) of <italic>O. aegyptiaca</italic>- chitosan nanocomposite showed increased DNA migration and longer comet tails, indicative of moderate DNA damage (arrows). (<bold>C</bold>) Snails exposed to LC<sub>25</sub> (37.78&#x000a0;mg/L) of <italic>O. aegyptiaca</italic>- chitosan nanocomposite exhibited extensive DNA migration with pronounced comet tails, suggesting substantial DNA fragmentation (arrows). The comet tails represent DNA strand breaks, with tail length correlating to the degree of DNA damage.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_2161_Fig11_HTML" id="d33e2033"/></fig>
</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="Sec34"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par54">The results showed that <italic>O. aegyptiaca-</italic> chitosan nanocomposite TEM images revealed nanomaterial size. The XRD pattern illustrates the presence of five characteristic peaks at 2&#x003b8;&#x02009;=&#x02009;20.61&#x000b0;, 21.74&#x000b0;, 23.79&#x000b0; 26.36&#x000b0; and 29.69&#x000b0;. Similar peaks were observed in Chitosan structures<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>. Also, the zeta potential analysis revealed a positive value of +&#x02009;5.51 mV, indicating the stability of <italic>O. aegyptiaca-</italic> chitosan nanocomposite. In a similar line, previous studies reported that the zeta potential values for chitosan nanoparticles usually vary from +&#x02009;22 to +&#x02009;88 mV, and this positive value provides better activity toward negatively charged and readily adsorbed at the cell biological membranes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par55">Several studies indicated that using natural materials, including botanical and marine extracts, as molluscicides has received significant interest owing to the rising resistance to chemical molluscicides<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>. The present results found that the aqueous extract of <italic>O. aegyptiaca</italic> leaves is rich in various phytochemical components such as alkaloids, flavonoids, saponin, tannins, carbohydrates, phenols, steroids, and terpenoids. These secondary metabolites may possess potent molluscicidal properties as suggested by Augusto and de Mello-Silva<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par56">The current findings showed a significant effect of <italic>O. aegyptica</italic>- chitosan nanocomposite on the survival rate of <italic>B. alexandrina</italic> compared to the control group. After exposure to the sub-lethal concentrations, LC<sub>10</sub> (32.3&#x000a0;mg/l) and LC<sub>25</sub> (37.7&#x000a0;mg/l), the survival rate (Lx) considerably reduced to 0.35 and 0.05, respectively, in the fourth week compared to 0.98 for the control group. The LC<sub>10</sub> group died in the seventh week of the experiment, while the LC<sub>25</sub> group deceased in the fifth week. The results demonstrated a marked reduction in the survival and life span of snails correlating with increased concentration and duration of exposure. This decline in the survival rate of snails may result from metabolic disorders due to the toxic effects of the chemical components of flavonoids, alkaloids, and saponins, that precipitate on cell membrane proteins after penetration<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>. Moreover, these compounds can establish hydrogen bonds with nitrogen-free and multi-hydroxyl groups, inhibiting some enzymes critical to the organism<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>. Similarly, this investigation is consistent with the findings of Ibrahim and Abdalla<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup> who observed a decline in the survival rates of adult <italic>B. alexandrina</italic> post-exposure to sub-lethal concentrations of the aqueous seed extract of <italic>Moringa oleifera.</italic></p><p id="Par57">Transaminases enzymes, AST and ALT are critical enzymes and sensitive indicators for assessing hepatocellular damage in snails under stressful circumstances. Alkaline phosphatase benefits gastropod secretory functions and protein synthesis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. Concerning the biochemical changes in the tissues of <italic>B. alexandrina</italic> subjected to sub-lethal concentrations LC<sub>10</sub> or LC<sub>25</sub> of <italic>O. aegyptica</italic>- chitosan nanocomposite, a significant (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) elevation in the activities of AST, ALT, and ALP was observed in the body tissues. Our results match those of Ibrahim and Abdalla<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup> who revealed that the aqueous seed extract of <italic>Moringa oleifera</italic> negatively affected some biochemical aspects, where it increased the levels of transaminases (ALT and AST). Al-Sayed et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup> reported a comparable outcome, indicating that ALP activity was considerably elevated in the hemolymph of <italic>B. alexandrina</italic> subjected to the sub-lethal amounts of the methanol extract of <italic>Eucalyptus globulus</italic> and <italic>Melaleuca styphelioides</italic>. These alterations resulted from animal trials to restore the amino acid equilibrium in various bodily tissues and degradation of snail cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup>. Furthermore, Tunholi et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup> indicated that the increase in AST, ALT, and ALP activities was associated with changes in phospholipid metabolism and the elevated energy requirements of the snail. This mirrors the impact inflicted by this nanocomposite on physiological state, aligning with the findings of Abdel et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup> who documented significant impairment in these essential enzymes due to exposure to synthetic and natural molluscicides.</p><p id="Par58">Also, the present findings indicated a reduction in uric acid and creatinine levels following exposure to the sub-lethal concentration of the nanocomposite. In agreement with Ibrahim et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref></sup> who demonstrated an increase in uric acid and creatinine activities of <italic>B. alexandrina</italic> snails following exposure to chitosan-capped gold nanocomposite,</p><p id="Par59">The antioxidant system was established to counteract the detrimental effects of free radicals, including the oxidation of proteins, lipids, and DNA, which may result in cell mortality and tissue malfunction<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref></sup>. In this study, the antioxidant balance was assessed in snail tissue by determining the levels of GSH, CAT, SOD, NO, and MDA. The data exhibited that antioxidants levels GSH, CAT and SOD activities substantially (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) decreased following exposure to the sub-lethal concentration of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>aegyptica</italic>- chitosan nanocomposite while the NO, and MDA levels were raised. These findings are consistent with those of Ibrahim et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref></sup>, who observed a decline in SOD and CAT activities of exposed snails while increased MDA levels after treating <italic>B. alexandrina</italic> snails with sub-lethal concentrations of chitosan-capped gold nanocomposite. Also, Ibrahim et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref></sup> discovered that treating <italic>B. truncatus</italic> with saponin increased NO activity.</p><p id="Par60">The current investigation demonstrated that the sub-lethal concentration of nanocomposite of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>aegyptica-</italic>chitosan induced histopathological alterations in the digestive gland of <italic>B</italic>. <italic>alexandrina</italic> snails, including shrinkage of the digestive tubules and the broken down of the connective tissue, causing an increase in inter-tubular space. Also, some digestive cells became vacuolated, and the secretory cells deteriorated. The observations align with those of Abdel-Wareth et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref></sup>, who illustrated that the exposure of <italic>B. alexandrina</italic> snails to acetone extracts of <italic>Beauveria bassiana</italic> and <italic>Paecilomyces lilacinus</italic> led to vacuolation of the digestive cells and degeneration of the secretory cells. Similarly, Ibrahim et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup> recorded digestive cells rupture and degeneration of the connective tissue between tubules and deformation in the secretory cells after treatment of <italic>B. alexandrina</italic> with the sub-lethal concentration of the methanolic extract of <italic>Nerium oleander</italic> and <italic>Tecoma stans.</italic></p><p id="Par61">The hermaphrodite gland is one of the target tissues used to test the molluscicidal potency<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup>. Herein, the histological investigation of the treated hermaphrodite gland revealed shrinkage, destruction, and degeneration of both male and female gonadal cells. At the higher concentration, LC<sub>25,</sub> the gonadal cells were severely damaged, and the cell boundary loss and nuclear pyknosis were observed. Mossalem et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup> observed the destruction of gametogenic cells and severe injury to hermaphrodite gland tissues by subjecting <italic>B. alexandrina</italic> snails to the anthelmintic plant derivative (artemether). Also, Hassan et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup> identified histological alterations in the hermaphrodite gland of <italic>B. alexandrina</italic> snails exposed to the ethanolic extract of <italic>Euphorbia aphylla</italic>, <italic>Ziziphus spina</italic>-<italic>christi</italic>, and <italic>Enterolobium contortisiliquum</italic>.</p><p id="Par62">The comet assay is widely recognized as a rapid and sensitive technique for detecting DNA damage, particularly single-strand breaks, at the individual cell level<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref></sup>. As one of the most reliable genotoxic biomarkers, the comet assay requires only a minimal number of cells to yield significant insights, making it a valuable tool in studying the effects of novel compounds and nanoparticles on DNA integrity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref></sup>. The results demonstrated that the sub-lethal concentration of <italic>O. aegyptiaca</italic>-chitosan nanocomposite induced significant DNA damage in <italic>B. alexandrina</italic> snails, as reflected in crucial comet assay parameters: tail length (TL), tail DNA percentage (TD), tail moment (TM), and olive tail moment (OTM). The highest level of genotoxicity was observed at the LC<sub>25</sub> concentration, with a substantial increase in DNA fragmentation and migration across all measured parameters compared to the control group. The increase in OTM observed in nanocomposite-treated snails aligns with findings by Ibrahim and Ghoname<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>, who reported significantly elevated OTM values in <italic>B. alexandrina</italic> exposed to plant-derived extracts. Similarly, Sharaf El-Din et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref></sup> demonstrated that snails treated with other nanoparticle formulations showed increased DNA migration. Our results show that exposure to <italic>O. aegyptiaca</italic>- chitosan nanocomposite increases tail length and DNA fragmentation in <italic>B. alexandrina</italic>, suggesting a substantial impact on DNA integrity. The potential toxicity of chitosan nanoparticles is mainly mediated by generating reactive oxygen species which attack cellular components, leading to oxidative stress and DNA fragmentation. causing cytotoxicity.</p></sec><sec id="Sec340"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par64">The nanocomposite of <italic>O. aegyptica</italic>-chitosan was proposed in the current investigation as a potential molluscicide against the intermediate host of schistosomiasis, <italic>B</italic>. <italic>alexandrina</italic> snails. This is demonstrated by a decline in survival, fecundity, and reproduction rates. In addition, the levels of biochemical parameters, including ALT, AST, and ALP were elevated, while urea, uric acid, and cholesterol were decreased. The antioxidant markers, CAT, SOD, and GSH demonstrated a significant decrease, while MDA and NO levels increased, as well as alterations in hermaphrodite and digestive glands were observed. Also, the comet analysis exhibited a genotoxic effect of the nanocomposite. Further studies are required to confirm the effectiveness of the nanocomposite, its application, and its biotoxicity on other aquatic organisms to evaluate its target specificity and potential ecological impacts in natural water bodies.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The Faculty of Science, Cairo University, Egypt, supports this work. The authors thank members of the Zoology Department for their assistance.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>F. G. and S.H. guided the idea&#x02019;s development. N.M. and R.R. prepared the O. aegyptica- chitosan nanocomposite. A.I.,&#x000a0;N.M., R.R. and M.F. did the experimental design, statistical analysis and interpretation of data. A.I. prepared and examined the histological sections. All authors wrote the first version and then revised and edited the final version.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>Open access funding provided by The Science, Technology &#x00026; Innovation Funding Authority (STDF) in cooperation with The Egyptian Knowledge Bank (EKB).</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>Data is available upon request from the corresponding author.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par65">All laboratory animal techniques used in this work agreed with the Ethics of Research Committee regulations at the Faculty of Science, Cairo University.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par66">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nyarko</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Torpey</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ankomah</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Schistosoma haematobium, plasmodium falciparum infection and anaemia in children in Accra, Ghana</article-title><source>Trop. Dis. Travel Med. Vaccines</source><year>2018</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40794-018-0063-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29507748</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Nyarko, R., Torpey, K. &#x00026; Ankomah, A. Schistosoma haematobium, plasmodium falciparum infection and anaemia in children in Accra, Ghana. <italic>Trop. Dis. Travel Med. Vaccines</italic>. <bold>4</bold>, 1&#x02013;6 (2018).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29507748</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohamed</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Quraishy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdel-Baki</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdel-Tawab</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Green synthesis of cerium oxide / <italic>Moringa oleifera</italic> seed extract nano-composite and its molluscicidsal activities against <italic>Biomophalaria alexanderina</italic></article-title><source>J. King Saud Univ. Sci.</source><year>2021</year><volume>33</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>101368</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jksus.2021.101368</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Ibrahim, A. M., Mohamed, F., Al-Quraishy, S., Abdel-Baki, A. S. &#x00026; Abdel-Tawab, H. Green synthesis of cerium oxide / <italic>Moringa oleifera</italic> seed extract nano-composite and its molluscicidsal activities against <italic>Biomophalaria alexanderina</italic>. <italic>J. King Saud Univ. Sci.</italic><bold>33</bold>(3), 101368. 10.1016/j.jksus.2021.101368 (2021).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">WHO (World Health Organization). <italic>Schistosomiasis Weekly Epidemiological Record</italic> (WHO, 2017).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Omobhude</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Morenikeji</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name><name><surname>Oyeyemi</surname><given-names>OT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molluscicidal activities of curcumin-nisin polylactic acid nanoparticle on <italic>Biomphalaria pfeifferi</italic> (SW Attwood</article-title><source>Ed.) PLoS Negl. Trop. Dis.</source><year>2017</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>e0005855</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0005855</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Omobhude, M. E., Morenikeji, O. A. &#x00026; Oyeyemi, O. T. Molluscicidal activities of curcumin-nisin polylactic acid nanoparticle on <italic>Biomphalaria pfeifferi</italic> (SW Attwood. <italic>Ed.) PLoS Negl. Trop. Dis.</italic><bold>11</bold>, e0005855 (2017).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hamdi</surname><given-names>S.A.H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The impact of three herbicides on biological and histological aspects of<italic> Biomphalaria alexandrina</italic>, intermediate host of<italic> Schistosoma mansoni</italic></article-title><source>Malacologia</source><year>2025</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10499-025-01956-3</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Hamdi, S. A. H. et al. Biological, biochemical, hormonal effect, and histological perturbations of <italic>Procambarus</italic><italic>clarkii </italic>(Crustacea: Cambaridae) hemolymph on <italic>Biomphalaria alexandrina</italic> snails. <italic>Aquacult. Int.</italic>&#x000a0;<bold>33</bold>(5), 1&#x02013;16. 10.1007/s10499-025-01956-3 (2025).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Morad</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamdi</surname><given-names>SAH</given-names></name><name><surname>Fol</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biocontrol potential of Chitosan extracted from <italic>Procambarus clarkii</italic> (<italic>Crustacea: Cambaridae</italic>) against <italic>Eobania vermiculata</italic> snails (Muller 1774) in Egypt</article-title><source>Egypt. J. Biol. Pest Control</source><year>2022</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>32</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s41938-022-00521-x</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Ibrahim, A. M., Morad, M. Y., Hamdi, S. A. H. &#x00026; Fol, M. F. Biocontrol potential of Chitosan extracted from <italic>Procambarus clarkii</italic> (<italic>Crustacea: Cambaridae</italic>) against <italic>Eobania vermiculata</italic> snails (Muller 1774) in Egypt. <italic>Egypt. J. Biol. Pest Control</italic>. <bold>32</bold>, 32. 10.1186/s41938-022-00521-x (2022).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fol</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdel-Ghaffar</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hassan</surname><given-names>HAM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oxidative stress, histopathological and genotoxicity of copper oxide nanoparticles in <italic>Biomphalaria alexandrina</italic> snail</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2024</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>25187</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-024-74439-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39448690</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Fol, M. F., Abdel-Ghaffar, F. A., Hassan, H. A. M. &#x00026; Ibrahim, A. M. Oxidative stress, histopathological and genotoxicity of copper oxide nanoparticles in <italic>Biomphalaria alexandrina</italic> snail. <italic>Sci. Rep.</italic><bold>14</bold>, 25187. 10.1038/s41598-024-74439-9 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39448690</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghoname</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molluscicidal impacts of <italic>Anagallis arvensis</italic> aqueous extract on biological, hormonal, histological and molecular aspects of <italic>Biomphalaria alexandrina</italic> snails</article-title><source>Exp. Parasit.</source><year>2018</year><volume>192</volume><fpage>36</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.exppara.2018.07.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30040958</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Ibrahim, A. M. &#x00026; Ghoname, S. I. Molluscicidal impacts of <italic>Anagallis arvensis</italic> aqueous extract on biological, hormonal, histological and molecular aspects of <italic>Biomphalaria alexandrina</italic> snails. <italic>Exp. Parasit.</italic><bold>192</bold>, 36&#x02013;41. 10.1016/j.exppara.2018.07.014 (2018).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30040958</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ayad</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The use of molluscicides in Egypt</article-title><source>Bull. World Health Organ.</source><year>1961</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>712</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13863477</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Ayad, N. The use of molluscicides in Egypt. <italic>Bull. World Health Organ.</italic><bold>25</bold>, 712 (1961). PMID: 13863477.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13863477</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elmal</surname><given-names>N.Y.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdel-Ghaffar</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamdi</surname><given-names>S.A.H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fol</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mostafa</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immunotoxical, neurotoxical, histopathological and immunohistopathological alterations of<italic> Nerium oleander</italic> and<italic> Tecoma stans</italic></article-title><source>Acta Trop.</source><year>2025</year><volume>230</volume><fpage>106405</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.actatropica.2022.106405</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Elmal, N. Y. B. et al. Biocontrol potential of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana&#x000a0;</italic>against <italic>Biomphalaria glabrata</italic>, the intermediate host of <italic>Schistosoma mansoni</italic>, focusing on biological, physiological, histopathological, and genotoxic impacts. <italic>Parasite Epidemiol. Control.</italic> e00428. 10.1016/j.parepi.2025.e00428 (2025)</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ibrahim, A. M. &#x00026; Ghareeb, M. Preliminary phytochemical screening, total phenolic content, in vitro antioxidant and molluscicidal activities of the methanolic extract of five medicinal plants on <italic>Biomphalaria alexandrina</italic> snails. <italic>Int. J. Geogr. Inf. Syst.</italic><bold>26</bold>. 10.1080/10496475.2019.1666769 (2020).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zulfiqar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Abidi</surname><given-names>ALI</given-names></name><name><surname>Shakir</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preliminary screening of some plants of Punjab</article-title><source>Pak Phytochemicals</source><year>2017</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>179</fpage><lpage>191</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Zulfiqar, S., Abidi, A. L. I., Shakir, H. A. &#x00026; Ali, S. S. Preliminary screening of some plants of Punjab. <italic>Pak Phytochemicals</italic>. <bold>63</bold>, 179&#x02013;191 (2017).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saidi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antifungal, molluscicidal and larvicidal assessment of Anemonin and <italic>Clematis flammula</italic> L. extracts against mollusk <italic>Galba truncatula</italic>, intermediate host of <italic>Fasciola hepatica</italic> in Tunisia. As</article-title><source>Pac. J. Trop. Med.</source><year>2017</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>967</fpage><lpage>973</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apjtm.2017.09.008</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Saidi, R. et al. Antifungal, molluscicidal and larvicidal assessment of Anemonin and <italic>Clematis flammula</italic> L. extracts against mollusk <italic>Galba truncatula</italic>, intermediate host of <italic>Fasciola hepatica</italic> in Tunisia. As. <italic>Pac. J. Trop. Med.</italic><bold>10</bold>, 967&#x02013;973 (2017).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sheoran</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Punia</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Orobanche</italic> weed management in mustard: opportunities, possibilities and limitations</article-title><source>J. Oilseed Brassica</source><year>2014</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>96</fpage><lpage>101</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Sheoran, P., Punia, S. S., Singh, S. &#x00026; Singh, D. <italic>Orobanche</italic> weed management in mustard: opportunities, possibilities and limitations. <italic>J. Oilseed Brassica</italic>. <bold>5</bold>, 96&#x02013;101 (2014).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Demirbas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Acar</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Superoxide dismutase and peroxidase activities from antioxidative enzymes in <italic>Helianthus annuus</italic> L. roots during <italic>Orobanche cumana</italic> Wallr</article-title><source>Penetration Fresenius Environ. Bull.</source><year>2008</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1038</fpage><lpage>1044</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Demirbas, S. &#x00026; Acar, O. Superoxide dismutase and peroxidase activities from antioxidative enzymes in <italic>Helianthus annuus</italic> L. roots during <italic>Orobanche cumana</italic> Wallr. <italic>Penetration Fresenius Environ. Bull.</italic><bold>17</bold>, 1038&#x02013;1044 (2008).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dauda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Poly-D, L-lactic-co-glycolic acid-based artesunate nanoparticles, formulation, antimalarial and toxicity assessments</article-title><source>J. Zheijang Univ. Sci. B - Biomed. Biotechnol.</source><year>2017</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>977</fpage><lpage>985</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Dauda, K. et al. Poly-D, L-lactic-co-glycolic acid-based artesunate nanoparticles, formulation, antimalarial and toxicity assessments. <italic>J. Zheijang Univ. Sci. B - Biomed. Biotechnol.</italic><bold>18</bold>, 977&#x02013;985 (2017).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bakshi</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Long-acting injectable atovaquone nanomedicines for malaria prophylaxis</article-title><source>Nat. Commun.</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>315</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-017-02603-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29358624</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Bakshi, R. P. et al. Long-acting injectable atovaquone nanomedicines for malaria prophylaxis. <italic>Nat. Commun.</italic><bold>9</bold>, 315 (2018).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29358624</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moustafa</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mossalem</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarhan</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdel-Rahman</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hassan</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The potential effects of silver and gold nanoparticles as molluscicides and cercaricides on <italic>Schistosoma mansoni</italic></article-title><source>Parasitol. Res.</source><year>2018</year><volume>117</volume><fpage>3867</fpage><lpage>3880</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00436-018-6093-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30280220</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Moustafa, M. A., Mossalem, H. S., Sarhan, R. M., Abdel-Rahman, A. A. &#x00026; Hassan, E. M. The potential effects of silver and gold nanoparticles as molluscicides and cercaricides on <italic>Schistosoma mansoni</italic>. <italic>Parasitol. Res.</italic><bold>117</bold>, 3867&#x02013;3880 (2018).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30280220</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mona</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The protective effect of crawfish chitosan on the reproductive performance of obese male rats</article-title><source>Food Bioscience</source><year>2024</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>103463</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fbio.2023.103463</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Mona, F. F. et al. The protective effect of crawfish chitosan on the reproductive performance of obese male rats. <italic>Food Bioscience</italic>. <bold>57</bold>, 103463 (2024).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sharif, R. et al. The multifunctional role of chitosan in horticultural crops; A review. <italic>Molecules</italic>. <bold>23</bold>, 872 (2018).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Liang, Y. S., Bruce, J. I. &#x00026; Boyd, D. A. Laboratory cultivation of schistosome vector snails and maintenance of schistosome life cycles. In <italic>Proceeding of the 1st Sino-American Symposium</italic>. vol. 1, 4&#x02013;48 (1987).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Waldi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Stahl</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spray reagents for thin-layer chromatography</article-title><source>Thin-Layer Chromatography</source><year>1965</year><publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name><fpage>483</fpage><lpage>502</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="book">Waldi, D. Spray reagents for thin-layer chromatography. In <italic>Thin-Layer Chromatography</italic> (ed Stahl, E.). 483&#x02013;502 (Springer, 1965).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harborne</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phytochemical methods</article-title><source>Kew. Bull.</source><year>1974</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>736</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/4108146</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Harborne, J. B. Phytochemical methods. <italic>Kew. Bull.</italic><bold>29</bold>, 736 (1974).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elumalai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Dhanasekaran</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Krishnappa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Larvicidal activity of saponin isolated from Gymnema sylvestre R. Br. (Asclepiadaceae) against Japanese encephalitis vector, Culex Tritaeniorhynchus Giles (Diptera: Culicidae)</article-title><source>Eur. Rev. Med. Pharmacol. Sci.</source><year>2013</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1404</fpage><lpage>1410</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23740457</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">Elumalai, K., Dhanasekaran, S. &#x00026; Krishnappa, K. Larvicidal activity of saponin isolated from Gymnema sylvestre R. Br. (Asclepiadaceae) against Japanese encephalitis vector, Culex Tritaeniorhynchus Giles (Diptera: Culicidae). <italic>Eur. Rev. Med. Pharmacol. Sci.</italic><bold>17</bold>, 1404&#x02013;1410 (2013).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23740457</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gul, R., Jan, S. U., Faridullah, S., Sherani, S. &#x00026; Jahan, N. Preliminary phytochemical screening, quantitative analysis of alkaloids, and antioxidant activity of crude plant extracts from Ephedra intermedia Indigenous to Balochistan. <italic>Sci. World</italic> 1&#x02013;8 (2017).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR26" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Calvo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Remunanae-Lopez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Vila-Jato</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Novel hydrophilic chitosan polyethylene oxide nanoparticles as protein carriers</article-title><source>J. Appl. Polym. Sci.</source><year>1997</year><volume>63</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>132</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1097-4628(19970103)63:1&#x0003c;125::AID-APP13&#x0003e;3.0.CO;2-4</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26" publication-type="journal">Calvo, P., Remunanae-Lopez, C., Vila-Jato, J. L. &#x00026; Alonso, M. J. Novel hydrophilic chitosan polyethylene oxide nanoparticles as protein carriers. <italic>J. Appl. Polym. Sci.</italic><bold>63</bold>(1), 125&#x02013;132 (1997).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ross, L. E. &#x00026; Dykstra, M. <italic>Biological Electron Microscopy: Theory, Techniques and Troubleshooting</italic> (Springer, 2003).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">WHO Molluscicide screening and evaluation. <italic>BullWHO</italic><bold>33</bold>, 567&#x02013;581 (1965).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Finney, D. J. <italic>Probit Analysis</italic> (Cambridge University Press. J Pharma Sciences., 1971).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR30" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>El-Gindy</surname><given-names>HI</given-names></name><name><surname>Rawi</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdel-Kader</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ebeid</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative effect of different pesticides on the transaminases activities in haemolymph of <italic>Biomphalaria alexandrina</italic> snails</article-title><source>J. Egypt. Ger. Soc. Zool.</source><year>1991</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>138</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30" publication-type="journal">El-Gindy, H. I., Rawi, S. M., Abdel-Kader, A. &#x00026; Ebeid, F. A. Comparative effect of different pesticides on the transaminases activities in haemolymph of <italic>Biomphalaria alexandrina</italic> snails. <italic>J. Egypt. Ger. Soc. Zool.</italic><bold>6</bold>, 131&#x02013;138 (1991).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR31" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Some factors affecting the fecundity of Biomphalaria Pfeifferi (krauss)</article-title><source>Bull. World Health Organ.</source><year>1963</year><volume>29</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>531</fpage><lpage>537</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14099678</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR31" publication-type="journal">Frank, G. H. Some factors affecting the fecundity of Biomphalaria Pfeifferi (krauss). <italic>Bull. World Health Organ.</italic><bold>29</bold>(4), 531&#x02013;537 (1963). [Pubmed].<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14099678</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR32" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pellegrino</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Da Gloria</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Goncalves</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Simple method for collecting egg clutches of <italic>Biomphalaria glabrata</italic> (<italic>Australorbis glabratus</italic>) and for rearing newly hatched snails</article-title><source>J. Parasitol.</source><year>1965</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>1014</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/3275898</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5892123</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32" publication-type="journal">Pellegrino, J., Da Gloria, R. &#x00026; Goncalves, M. A. Simple method for collecting egg clutches of <italic>Biomphalaria glabrata</italic> (<italic>Australorbis glabratus</italic>) and for rearing newly hatched snails. <italic>J. Parasitol.</italic><bold>51</bold>, 1014. 10.2307/3275898 (1965).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5892123</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">El-Gindy, M. S. et al. Effect of low concentrations of sodium pentachlorophenate on the fecundity and egg viability of <italic>Bulinus truncatus</italic> from central Iraq bull. <italic>Endem Dis. (Baghdad</italic>) (1965).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR34" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buege</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Aust</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microsomal lipid per- oxidation</article-title><source>Methods Enzymol.</source><year>1978</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>302</fpage><lpage>310</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0076-6879(78)52032-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">672633</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR34" publication-type="journal">Buege, J. A. &#x00026; Aust, S. D. Microsomal lipid per- oxidation. <italic>Methods Enzymol.</italic><bold>52</bold>, 302&#x02013;310 (1978).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">672633</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR35" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Montgomery</surname><given-names>HAC</given-names></name><name><surname>Dymock</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The determination of nitrite in water</article-title><source>Analyst</source><year>1961</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>414</fpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR35" publication-type="journal">Montgomery, H. A. C. &#x00026; Dymock, J. F. The determination of nitrite in water. <italic>Analyst</italic><bold>86</bold>, 414 (1961).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR36" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beutler</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Duron</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improved method for the determination of blood glutathione</article-title><source>J. Lab. Clin. Med.</source><year>1963</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>882</fpage><lpage>888</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13967893</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR36" publication-type="journal">Beutler, E., Duron, O. &#x00026; Kelly, M. B. Improved method for the determination of blood glutathione. <italic>J. Lab. Clin. Med.</italic><bold>61</bold>, 882&#x02013;888 (1963).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13967893</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR37" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aebi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><source>Methods Enzymol.</source><year>1984</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>121</fpage><lpage>126</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0076-6879(84)05016-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6727660</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR37" publication-type="journal">Aebi, H. <italic>Methods Enzymol.</italic><bold>105</bold>, 121&#x02013;126 (1984).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6727660</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR38" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nishikimi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Roa</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Yogi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><source>Biochem. Bioph Res. Common.</source><year>1972</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>849</fpage><lpage>854</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-291X(72)80218-3</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR38" publication-type="journal">Nishikimi, M., Roa, N. A. &#x00026; Yogi, K. <italic>Biochem. Bioph Res. Common.</italic><bold>46</bold>, 849&#x02013;854 (1972).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR39" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grazeffe</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Establishment of the comet assay in the freshwater snail Biomphalaria glabrata (Say, 1818)</article-title><source>Mutat. Res.</source><year>2008</year><volume>654</volume><fpage>58</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mrgentox.2008.05.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18579435</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR39" publication-type="journal">Grazeffe, V. S. et al. Establishment of the comet assay in the freshwater snail Biomphalaria glabrata (Say, 1818). <italic>Mutat. Res.</italic><bold>654</bold>, 58&#x02013;63 (2008).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18579435</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR40" publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Varma</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Baul</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chhabra</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gulati</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Gulati</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Introduction to chitosan and chitosan-based nanocomposites</article-title><source>Chitosan-Based Nanocomposite Materials</source><year>2022</year><publisher-loc>Singapore</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR40" publication-type="book">Varma, R. S., Baul, A., Chhabra, L. &#x00026; Gulati, S. Introduction to chitosan and chitosan-based nanocomposites. In <italic>Chitosan-Based Nanocomposite Materials</italic> (ed Gulati, S.) 10.1007/978-981-19-5338-5_1 (Springer, 2022).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR41" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>QY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Carbohydr. Polym.</source><year>2010</year><volume>79</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>783</fpage><lpage>785</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.carbpol.2009.08.022</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR41" publication-type="journal">Cai, Q. Y. et al. <italic>Carbohydr. Polym.</italic><bold>79</bold>,(3), 783&#x02013;785 (2010).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR42" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fol</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The protective effect of crawfish chitosan on the reproductive performance of obese male rats</article-title><source>Food Biosci.</source><year>2024</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>103463</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fbio.2023.103463</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR42" publication-type="journal">Fol, M. F. et al. The protective effect of crawfish chitosan on the reproductive performance of obese male rats. <italic>Food Biosci.</italic><bold>57</bold>, 103463. 10.1016/j.fbio.2023.103463 (2024).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR43" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saharan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Synthesis and in vitro antifungal efficacy of Cu-chitosan nanoparticles against pathogenic fungi of tomato</article-title><source>Int. J. Biol. Macromol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>346</fpage><lpage>353</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2015.01.027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25617841</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR43" publication-type="journal">Saharan, V. et al. Synthesis and in vitro antifungal efficacy of Cu-chitosan nanoparticles against pathogenic fungi of tomato. <italic>Int. J. Biol. Macromol.</italic><bold>75</bold>, 346&#x02013;353 (2015).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25617841</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR44" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molluscicidal effectiveness of Luo-Wei, a novel plant-derived molluscicide, against <italic>Oncomelania hupensis</italic>, <italic>Biomphalaria alexandrina</italic> and <italic>Bulinus truncatus</italic></article-title><source>Infect. Dis. Poverty</source><year>2019</year><volume>27</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40249-019-0535-7</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR44" publication-type="journal">Jia, T. et al. Molluscicidal effectiveness of Luo-Wei, a novel plant-derived molluscicide, against <italic>Oncomelania hupensis</italic>, <italic>Biomphalaria alexandrina</italic> and <italic>Bulinus truncatus</italic>. <italic>Infect. Dis. Poverty</italic>. <bold>27</bold>(8), 1&#x02013;10. 10.1186/s40249-019-0535-7 (2019).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR45" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Augusto</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>de Mello-Silva</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phytochemical molluscicides and schistosomiasis: what we know and what we still need to learn vet</article-title><source>Sci</source><year>2018</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>94</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/vetsci5040094</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR45" publication-type="journal">Augusto, R. &#x00026; de Mello-Silva, C. Phytochemical molluscicides and schistosomiasis: what we know and what we still need to learn vet. <italic>Sci</italic><bold>5</bold>, 94. 10.3390/vetsci5040094 (2018).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR46" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jarallah</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of some plant extracts as a molluscicides against the snail <italic>Lymnaea auricularia</italic> L. in Basrah</article-title><source>Baby J. Res. Sci.</source><year>2012</year><volume>20</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>556</fpage><lpage>561</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR46" publication-type="journal">Jarallah, H. M. Effect of some plant extracts as a molluscicides against the snail <italic>Lymnaea auricularia</italic> L. in Basrah. <italic>Baby J. Res. Sci.</italic><bold>20</bold>(2), 556&#x02013;561 (2012).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR47" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdalla</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of <italic>Moringa oleifera</italic> seed aqueous extract on some biological, biochemical, and histological aspects of <italic>Biomphalaria Alexandrina</italic> snails</article-title><source>Environ. Sci. Pollut Re S</source><year>2017</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>28072</fpage><lpage>28078</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11356-017-0397-0</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR47" publication-type="journal">Ibrahim, A. M. &#x00026; Abdalla, A. M. Impact of <italic>Moringa oleifera</italic> seed aqueous extract on some biological, biochemical, and histological aspects of <italic>Biomphalaria Alexandrina</italic> snails. <italic>Environ. Sci. Pollut Re S</italic>. <bold>24</bold>, 28072&#x02013;28078. 10.1007/s11356-017-0397-0 (2017).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR48" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Al-Sayed</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamid</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>El Abu</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molluscicidal and antischistosomal activities of methanol extracts and isolated compounds from <italic>Eucalyptus globulus</italic> and <italic>Melaleuca styphelioides</italic></article-title><source>Pharmal Biology</source><year>2014</year><volume>(52)</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>698</fpage><lpage>705</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/13880209.2013.865240</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR48" publication-type="journal">Al-Sayed, E., Hamid, H. A. &#x00026; El Abu, H. M. Molluscicidal and antischistosomal activities of methanol extracts and isolated compounds from <italic>Eucalyptus globulus</italic> and <italic>Melaleuca styphelioides</italic>. <italic>Pharmal Biology</italic>. <bold>(52)</bold>(6), 698&#x02013;705 (2014).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR49" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mohamed</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact profenophos (pesticide) on infectivity of <italic>Biomphalaria alexandrina</italic> snails with <italic>Schistosoma mansoni</italic> miracidia and on their physiological parameters</article-title><source>Open. J. Ecol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>47</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4236/oje.2011.12005</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR49" publication-type="journal">Mohamed, R. Impact profenophos (pesticide) on infectivity of <italic>Biomphalaria alexandrina</italic> snails with <italic>Schistosoma mansoni</italic> miracidia and on their physiological parameters. <italic>Open. J. Ecol.</italic><bold>1</bold>, 2: 41&#x02013;47. 10.4236/oje.2011.12005 (2011).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR50" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tunholi</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A. Biochemical profile of <italic>Biomphalaria glabrata</italic> (Mollusca: Gastropoda) after infection by <italic>Echinostoma paraensei</italic> (Trematoda: Echinostomatidae)</article-title><source>Parasitol. Res.</source><year>2011</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>885</fpage><lpage>891</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00436-011-2330-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21537991</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR50" publication-type="journal">Tunholi, V. M. et al. A. Biochemical profile of <italic>Biomphalaria glabrata</italic> (Mollusca: Gastropoda) after infection by <italic>Echinostoma paraensei</italic> (Trematoda: Echinostomatidae). <italic>Parasitol. Res.</italic><bold>109</bold>, 885&#x02013;891. 10.1007/s00436-011-2330-7 (2011).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21537991</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR51" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abdel</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramzy</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Tantawy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of the molluscicidal and in vitro schistosomicidal activity of butanol extract of the plant Agave filifera</article-title><source>Egypt. J. Biomed. Sci.</source><year>2004</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>67</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR51" publication-type="journal">Abdel, K. A., Ramzy, M. T. &#x00026; Tantawy, A. Evaluation of the molluscicidal and in vitro schistosomicidal activity of butanol extract of the plant Agave filifera. <italic>Egypt. J. Biomed. Sci.</italic><bold>16</bold>, 53&#x02013;67 (2004).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ibrahim, A. M., Bekhit, M., Sokary, R., Hammam, O. &#x00026; Atta, S. Toxicological, hepato-renal, endocrine disruption, oxidative stress and immunohistopathological responses of Chitosan capped gold nanocomposite on Biomphalaria Alexandrina snails. <italic>Pesticide Biochem. Physiol.</italic><bold>195</bold>, 105559 10.1016/j.pestbp.2023.105559 (2023).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR53" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Omar</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Biointerfrence between zinc oxide/alginate nanocomposites and freshwater bivalve</article-title><source>Biointerface Res. Appl. Chem.</source><year>2023</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>3277</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.33263/BRIAC133</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR53" publication-type="journal">Omar, T. Y. et al. Biointerfrence between zinc oxide/alginate nanocomposites and freshwater bivalve. <italic>Biointerface Res. Appl. Chem.</italic><bold>13</bold>, 3277. 10.33263/BRIAC133 (2023).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR54" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>El-karim</surname><given-names>RMG</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Nasr</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Toxicological effects of saponin on the free larval stages of Schistosoma mansoni, infection rate, some biochemical and molecular parameters of Biomphalaria Alexandrina snails</article-title><source>Pestic Biochem. Physiol.</source><year>2023</year><volume>191</volume><fpage>105357</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pestbp.2023.105357</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36963932</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR54" publication-type="journal">Ibrahim, A. M., El-karim, R. M. G., Ali, E. &#x00026; Nasr, S. M. Toxicological effects of saponin on the free larval stages of Schistosoma mansoni, infection rate, some biochemical and molecular parameters of Biomphalaria Alexandrina snails. <italic>Pestic Biochem. Physiol.</italic><bold>191</bold>, 105357. 10.1016/j.pestbp.2023.105357 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36963932</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR55" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abdel-Wareth</surname><given-names>MTA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghareeb</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdel-Aziz</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>El- Hagrassi</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Snailicidal, antimicrobial, antioxidant and anticancer activities of <italic>Beauveria bassiana, Metarhizium anisopliae</italic> and <italic>Paecilomyces lilacinus</italic> fungal extracts</article-title><source>Egy J. Aqu Biol. Fish.</source><year>2019</year><volume>23</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21608/ejabf.2019.30550</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR55" publication-type="journal">Abdel-Wareth, M. T. A., Ghareeb, M. A., Abdel-Aziz, M. S. &#x00026; El- Hagrassi, A. M. Snailicidal, antimicrobial, antioxidant and anticancer activities of <italic>Beauveria bassiana, Metarhizium anisopliae</italic> and <italic>Paecilomyces lilacinus</italic> fungal extracts. <italic>Egy J. Aqu Biol. Fish.</italic><bold>23</bold>(2), 195&#x02013;212 (2019).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR56" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bode</surname><given-names>AU</given-names></name><name><surname>Adewunmi</surname><given-names>CO</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x000f6;rfler</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effects of extracts from <italic>Tetrapleura tetraptera</italic> (Taub.) and Bayluscide on cells and tissue structures of <italic>Biomphalaria glabrata</italic> (Say)</article-title><source>J. Ethnopharmacol.</source><year>1996</year><volume>50</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>103</fpage><lpage>113</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0378-8741</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8866731</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR56" publication-type="journal">Bode, A. U., Adewunmi, C. O., D&#x000f6;rfler, G. &#x00026; Becker, W. The effects of extracts from <italic>Tetrapleura tetraptera</italic> (Taub.) and Bayluscide on cells and tissue structures of <italic>Biomphalaria glabrata</italic> (Say). <italic>J. Ethnopharmacol.</italic><bold>50</bold>(2), 103&#x02013;113. 10.1016/0378-8741 (1996).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8866731</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR57" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mossalem</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdel-Hamid</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Shinnawy</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of artemether on some histological and histochemical parameters in <italic>Biomphalaria alexandrina</italic></article-title><source>Afr. J. Pharm. Pharmacol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>2220</fpage><lpage>2230</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5897/AJPP2013.3762</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR57" publication-type="journal">Mossalem, H. S., Abdel-Hamid, H. &#x00026; El-Shinnawy, N. A. Impact of artemether on some histological and histochemical parameters in <italic>Biomphalaria alexandrina</italic>. <italic>Afr. J. Pharm. Pharmacol.</italic><bold>7</bold>, 2220&#x02013;2230 (2013).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hassan, A. A., Mahmoud, A. E., Attia, R. A. H. &#x00026; Huseein, E. A. M. Evaluation of the ethanolic extracts of three plants for their molluscicidal activities against snails intermediate hosts of <italic>Schistosoma mansoni</italic> and <italic>Fasciola</italic>. <italic>IJBasic Appl. Sci.</italic><bold>3</bold>(1), 235&#x02013;249 (2012).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ibrahim, A. M., Ahmed, A. K., Bakry, F. A. &#x00026; Abdel-Ghaffar, F. Hematological, physiological and genotoxicological effects of match 5% EC insecticide on <italic>Biomphalaria Alexandrina</italic> snails. <italic>Ecotoxicol. Environ. Saf.</italic><bold>147</bold>10.1016/j.ecoenv.2017.09.059 (2018).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR60" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bolognesi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Cirillo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genotoxicity biomarkers in aquatic bioindicators</article-title><source>Curr. Zool.</source><year>2014</year><volume>60</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>273</fpage><lpage>284</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/czoolo/60.2.273</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR60" publication-type="journal">Bolognesi, C. &#x00026; Cirillo, S. Genotoxicity biomarkers in aquatic bioindicators. <italic>Curr. Zool.</italic><bold>60</bold>(2), 273&#x02013;284 (2014).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR61" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharaf El-Din</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Abu-Senna</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaldoum</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zayed</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Azzam</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biomphalaria Alexandrina snails as a bio-monitor for water pollution using genotoxic&#x02019;s effect of cuprous oxide nanoparticles and copper sulphate</article-title><source>Middle East. J. Appl. Sci.</source><year>2016</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>189</fpage><lpage>197</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR61" publication-type="journal">Sharaf El-Din, A. T., Abu-Senna, F. M., Shaldoum, F. M., Zayed, K. M. &#x00026; Azzam, A. M. Biomphalaria Alexandrina snails as a bio-monitor for water pollution using genotoxic&#x02019;s effect of cuprous oxide nanoparticles and copper sulphate. <italic>Middle East. J. Appl. Sci.</italic><bold>6</bold>, 189&#x02013;197 (2016).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article>