<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLOS One</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40397893</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12094759</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0324287</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-25-02625</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Earth Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Geography</subject><subj-group><subject>Geographic Areas</subject><subj-group><subject>Rural Areas</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Health Care</subject><subj-group><subject>Health Education and Awareness</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Physiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Physiological Processes</subject><subj-group><subject>Sleep</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Health Care</subject><subj-group><subject>Socioeconomic Aspects of Health</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Public and Occupational Health</subject><subj-group><subject>Socioeconomic Aspects of Health</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Earth Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Geography</subject><subj-group><subject>Human Geography</subject><subj-group><subject>Urban Geography</subject><subj-group><subject>Urban Areas</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Social Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Human Geography</subject><subj-group><subject>Urban Geography</subject><subj-group><subject>Urban Areas</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Earth Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Geography</subject><subj-group><subject>Geographic Areas</subject><subj-group><subject>Urban Areas</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Public and Occupational Health</subject><subj-group><subject>Physical Activity</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Engineering and Technology</subject><subj-group><subject>Management Engineering</subject><subj-group><subject>Risk Management</subject><subj-group><subject>Insurance</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Social Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Sociology</subject><subj-group><subject>Education</subject><subj-group><subject>Schools</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Chronic diseases and self-rated health disparity between urban and rural residents in China</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Chronic diseases and health disparity in China</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Yu</given-names></name><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation/">Data curation</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/formal-analysis/">Formal analysis</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/investigation/">Investigation</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/methodology/">Methodology</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/">Writing &#x02013; original draft</role><xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0009-0007-3902-4180</contrib-id><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Li</given-names></name><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/">Conceptualization</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/funding-acquisition/">Funding acquisition</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/supervision/">Supervision</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/">Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing</role><xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff001"><label>1</label>
<addr-line>College of Public Health, Chongqing Medical University, Chongqing, China</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff002"><label>2</label>
<addr-line>Yongchuan Hospital of Chongqing Medical University, Chongqing, China</addr-line></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Bhandari</surname><given-names>Buna</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref rid="edit1" ref-type="aff"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>Tribhuvan University Institute of Medicine, NEPAL</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="coi001"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>liuli@cqmu.edu.cn</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>20</volume><issue>5</issue><elocation-id>e0324287</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2025 Wang, Liu</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Wang, Liu</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="pone.0324287.pdf">
</self-uri><abstract><p>This study investigates the significant disparities between urban and rural areas in China, particularly in terms of health status, which are driven by economic inequality and the uneven distribution of healthcare resources. Chronic diseases are a major threat to the health of Chinese residents, and this study explores how these diseases contribute to the disparity in self-rated health between urban and rural populations. Using data from the 2021 Chinese General Social Survey, various data analysis methods, including descriptive, regression, and decomposition analyses, were employed. The results reveal substantial disparities in self-rated health between urban and rural residents, with chronic diseases playing a significant role in explaining these disparities. Approximately 39% of the urban-rural disparity in self-rated health can be explained by differences in chronic disease prevalence, with additional factors such as age, socio-economic status, social participation, and sleep quality also contributing. This study identified the correlation between chronic diseases and the disparity in self-rated health, and limitations may arise from the use of self-reported health and the complexity of urban-rural health disparities. The findings suggest that the urban-rural disparity in chronic diseases is the primary driver of the health disparity, and that policymakers should focus on improving health education, promoting chronic disease prevention and management, and emphasizing preventive healthcare in rural areas.</p></abstract><funding-group><award-group id="award001"><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="funder-id">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100017501</institution-id><institution>Science-Health Joint Medical Scientific Research Project of Chongqing</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source><award-id>2023MSXM165</award-id><principal-award-recipient>
<contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0009-0007-3902-4180</contrib-id>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Li</given-names></name>
</principal-award-recipient></award-group><funding-statement>Author receiving the funding: LL Grant number: 2023MSXM165 Funder's full name: Chongqing Science-Health Joint Medical Scientific Research Project Funder's website URL: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.cq.gov.cn/health" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cq.gov.cn/health</ext-link> The funder played no role in the study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="3"/><page-count count="12"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>All data files are available from the CGSS database (<ext-link xlink:href="http://www.cnsda.org/index.php?r=projects/view&#x00026;id=65635422" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.cnsda.org/index.php?r=projects/view&#x00026;id=65635422</ext-link>).</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><title>Data Availability</title><p>All data files are available from the CGSS database (<ext-link xlink:href="http://www.cnsda.org/index.php?r=projects/view&#x00026;id=65635422" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.cnsda.org/index.php?r=projects/view&#x00026;id=65635422</ext-link>).</p></notes></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001"><title>Introduction</title><p>Health is related to quality of life, national security and social stability, and is the basis for human survival and development. It plays an important role in national economic development and is a basic condition for economic and social development [<xref rid="pone.0324287.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. In recent years, with social development and improved living standards, the health status of Chinese residents has significantly improved [<xref rid="pone.0324287.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0324287.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>], and the average life expectancy has continued to increase. However, the longstanding urban-rural dual structure has led to disparities in opportunities for accumulating health-related human capital. According to the results of the National Health and Wellness Commission&#x02019;s Health Literacy Monitoring Points for Residents in 2023, the health literacy level of urban residents nationwide was 33.25% in 2023, and that of rural residents was 26.23% [<xref rid="pone.0324287.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. The development of health literacy remains uneven between urban and rural areas. The issue of health disparities among different population groups has attracted widespread attention in both developed and developing countries. Health disparities are defined as systematic disparities in health outcomes between different population groups [<xref rid="pone.0324287.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0324287.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. In this study, we used the Self-Rated Health (SRH) as an indicator of the health status of the population. The SRH not only reflects the health status of an individual, but also integrates subjective and objective aspects of health status [<xref rid="pone.0324287.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>].</p><p>Most studies have found that urban residents have better health than rural residents. It has been found that rural Americans are more likely to report risk factors associated with poorer health [<xref rid="pone.0324287.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0324287.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], and residents living in rural areas typically have poorer health than their urban counterparts [<xref rid="pone.0324287.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. In Brazil, although rural residents have better mortality indicators, urban residents report better self-rated health [<xref rid="pone.0324287.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Kaczmarek&#x02019;s study found that middle-aged women in urban areas have a higher quality of life than those in rural areas [<xref rid="pone.0324287.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. In fact, rural communities around the world are not only in poorer health than their urban counterparts, but also have more problems accessing health care [<xref rid="pone.0324287.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. The mechanisms that contributed to the urban-rural health disparity were multifactorial and complex. The management of multiple chronic diseases requires more health-care interactions, and the lack of access to health-care services in rural areas creates significant barriers to the management of chronic diseases [<xref rid="pone.0324287.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. In this study, urban areas refer to provincial capitals, prefecture-level cities, and their subordinate urban districts, while rural areas refer to townships and the villages under their jurisdiction.</p><p>In conclusion, with the transition of diseases, chronic diseases have been recognized as major threats to human health [<xref rid="pone.0324287.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. In 2016, non-communicable diseases caused 41 million deaths globally, accounting for 71% of global mortality. Studies have shown that chronic diseases are closely related to poor SRH [<xref rid="pone.0324287.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], with some researchers finding that patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) perceive their health status more negatively [<xref rid="pone.0324287.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. As age increases, the incidence of chronic diseases rises, and the prevalence of multimorbidity also increases, a trend that is expected to continue [<xref rid="pone.0324287.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0324287.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. In China, studies show that chronic diseases have become a major threat to residents&#x02019; health, accounting for about 70% of the total disease burden [<xref rid="pone.0324287.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], and have a significant negative impact on health-related quality of life [<xref rid="pone.0324287.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>].</p><p>However, although studies generally suggest that chronic diseases affect individuals&#x02019; SRH, the relationship between chronic diseases and SRH varies across different regions, cultures, and socioeconomic backgrounds. Few studies have specifically explored whether the disparities in chronic diseases between urban and rural residents are associated with SRH disparities, and to what extent chronic diseases contribute to the urban-rural SRH disparity. Some studies have indicated that chronic diseases affect SRH through physical symptoms, psychological distress, and functional limitations, and these factors may be exacerbated by differences in healthcare accessibility and social determinants of health [<xref rid="pone.0324287.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. To extend the current knowledge in explaining the urban&#x02013;rural disparity in SRH among residents in China from the perspective of chronic diseases, this study aimed to address three questions: (1) to measure the disparities in SRH between urban and rural residents; (2) to examine the association between chronic diseases and residents&#x02019; SRH, and (3) to explore the extent to which the disparities in SRH between urban and rural residents can be explained by chronic disease disparities. Through these explorations, the aim is to gain a deeper understanding of the impact of chronic diseases on urban-rural health disparities, providing new insights for public health interventions to reduce inequalities.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec002"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="sec003"><title>Data</title><p>The data used in this study came from the China General Social Survey (CGSS) conducted by the China Survey and Data Centre (NSRC) of Renmin University of China in 2021. The CGSS, which began in 2003, is China&#x02019;s earliest nationwide, comprehensive, and continuous academic survey project. The survey adopts a multistage stratified sampling method, with Chinese citizens aged 18 and above as the target respondents, and a face-to-face interview model to conduct a continuous cross-section survey of information at multiple levels of society, community, household, and individual, with a total of 100 counties plus 5 major metropolitan cities, which is a good representation of the country. CGSS2021 is the latest publicly available data covering 320 communities in 19 provinces, with a valid sample of 8,148 (56.14% from towns and cities, 45.16% male, mean age 51.60 years, mean years of education 9.20 years, 73.87% married) [<xref rid="pone.0324287.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. After data cleaning, this study ultimately obtained 2,514 valid samples. The database counted the basic information of the residents in the years they covered, and the variables related to the study of this paper broadly included: age, gender, hukou registration status (China&#x02019;s household registration system, which classifies individuals into urban and rural hukou based on their place of residence), socio-economic status, education level, marital status, health status, chronic disease status, physical activity and so on.</p></sec><sec id="sec004"><title>Variables</title><sec id="sec005"><title>Dependent variables.</title><p>The dependent variable in this study is the SRH indicator. SRH was popularized in the 1950s through social surveys, and was theoretically developed by researchers like Edward A. Suchman in 1958, who argued that it provides a comprehensive picture of the body&#x02019;s subjective perceptions and objective bodily functions to obtain an individual&#x02019;s health status [<xref rid="pone.0324287.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. It refers to the respondents&#x02019; overall evaluation of their own health status based on the comprehensive situation of their physical, psychological and social functions. Domestic and foreign studies believe that SRH is a comprehensive indicator reflecting the objective health status and subjective psychological expectations of the population, which can not only reflect the objective physical condition of an individual in a certain period of time, but also reflect the subjective evaluation of the individual&#x02019;s own health expectations, the accessibility of health care in the living environment, etc. It is an individual&#x02019;s evaluation of his or her own objective health status based on self-feelings, and compared with the traditional health indicators, it is able to more effectively reflect the health status of the population [<xref rid="pone.0324287.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. In the 2021 CGSS survey, there was a question related to SRH, &#x0201c;What is your current health status?&#x0201d; with responses categorised as very unhealthy, relatively unhealthy, average, relatively healthy, and very healthy. Research has shown that the binary classification of self-rated health (SRH) can better reflect an individual&#x02019;s overall health status, and it can more clearly reveal health disparities, improve data reliability, reduce subjective bias, and enhance the stability of statistical modeling [<xref rid="pone.0324287.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0324287.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0324287.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Therefore, we assigned a value of 1 to the answer &#x0201c;relatively healthy&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;very healthy&#x0201d;, which means that the health condition is good. Responses of &#x0201c;very unhealthy&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;relatively unhealthy&#x0201d;, and &#x0201c;average&#x0201d; were assigned a value of 0, representing poor health.</p></sec><sec id="sec006"><title>Independent variables.</title><p>In this study, chronic disease was the independent variable. In the CGSS, respondents were asked to answer whether they had a chronic disease or had a long-term health problem, and their responses were categorised as &#x0201c;yes&#x0201d;&#x02009;=&#x02009;1 and &#x0201c;no&#x0201d;&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.</p></sec><sec id="sec007"><title>Covariates.</title><p>A large body of evidence suggests that disparities in SRH among different residents are related to factors such as gender, age, marital status, socioeconomic status, educational level, insurance status, lifestyle, and related factors [<xref rid="pone.0324287.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0324287.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Therefore, three types of covariates related to SRH were selected for this study. The first type of covariate describes the demographic characteristics of the population, including age (continuous variable), sex (1&#x02009;=&#x02009;male; 0&#x02009;=&#x02009;female), household registration status (1&#x02009;=&#x02009;urban; 0&#x02009;=&#x02009;rural), and marital status (1&#x02009;=&#x02009;married; 0&#x02009;=&#x02009;other). The second type of covariate describes residents&#x02019; socioeconomic status (continuous variable), educational status (1&#x02009;=&#x02009;high school and above; 0&#x02009;=&#x02009;middle school and below), and insurance status (1&#x02009;=&#x02009;yes; 0&#x02009;=&#x02009;no). The third type of covariate describes the health-related behaviours of the population, including smoking (1&#x02009;=&#x02009;yes; 0&#x02009;=&#x02009;no), drinking (1&#x02009;=&#x02009;yes; 0&#x02009;=&#x02009;no), physical activity (1&#x02009;=&#x02009;yes; 0&#x02009;=&#x02009;no), sleep duration (1&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02265;7, &#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;9; 0 =&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;7, &#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;9), and sleep quality (1&#x02009;=&#x02009;good; 0&#x02009;=&#x02009;poor).</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec008"><title>Statistical analyses</title><p>Multiple data analysis methods were performed to address each of our research questions. Descriptive analyses were used to describe the mean and distribution of the variables. Two-sample t-tests were used for continuous variables and chi-square tests for categorical variables to test for disparities between urban and rural groups, and the results are displayed in <xref rid="pone.0324287.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. In addition, listwise deletion was used to handle missing data, which involves excluding all observations with missing data, ensuring the simplicity and accuracy of the analysis results. This method is suitable for cases where the missing data is missing completely at random (MCAR) [<xref rid="pone.0324287.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0324287.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. In order to investigate whether and to what extent chronic diseases are associated with the SRH of the residents, <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/topics/nursing-and-health-professions/logistic-regression-analysis" ext-link-type="uri">logistic regression</ext-link> for binary SRH were employed, the Linear coefficients and SRH odds ratios (OR) with 95% confidence intervals were reported. The model is as follows:</p><table-wrap position="float" id="pone.0324287.t001"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0324287.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Descriptive and bivariate analyses of dependent and independent variables.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0324287.t001" id="pone.0324287.t001g" position="float"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urban (N&#x02009;=&#x02009;760)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rural <break/>(N&#x02009;=&#x02009;1754)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All <break/>(N&#x02009;=&#x02009;2514)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T-test/Chi-square Test</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-rates health (<italic toggle="yes">%</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.08<bold>***</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.82</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.40</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.94</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poor</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.18</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.60</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.06</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chronic diseases (<italic toggle="yes">%</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.27<bold>***</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.89</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.97</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.83</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.03</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age [mean (sd)]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.81 (18.24)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.77 (16.88)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.18 (17.32)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.60<bold>**</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">socio-economic status [mean (sd)]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.50 (0.86)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.20 (0.89)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.29 (0.89)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-7.59<bold>***</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender (<italic toggle="yes">%</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.63</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.42</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.54</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.58</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.70</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.46</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Marital status (<italic toggle="yes">%</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.31<bold>**</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Married</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.37</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.71</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.09</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Else</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.63</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.29</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.91</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Education (<italic toggle="yes">%</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">182.74<bold>***</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Junior high school and below</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.92</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.26</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.39</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High school and above</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.08</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.74</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.61</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">physical activity (<italic toggle="yes">%</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">117.60<bold>***</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.58</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.40</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.87</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.42</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.60</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking (<italic toggle="yes">%</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.92</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.66</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.77</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.83</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.34</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.23</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drinking (%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.48<bold>***</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.32</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.23</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.58</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.68</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.77</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.42</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep duration (%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.64<bold>*</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;7, &#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.37</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.88</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.24</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;7, &#x0003e;9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.63</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.76</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep quality (%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.41<bold>*</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.58</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.47</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poor</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.42</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.88</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.53</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medical insurance (<italic toggle="yes">%</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.28<bold>*</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.71</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.58</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.23</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.29</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.42</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.77</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pension insurance (%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.69<bold>***</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.84</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.55</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.66</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.16</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.45</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.34</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t001fn001"><p>Note: 1. Mean or percentage were presented. 2.Standard deviation in parentheses.</p></fn><fn id="t001fn002"><p><bold>*</bold> p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, <bold>**</bold> p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, <bold>***</bold> p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><disp-formula id="pone.0324287.e001">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0324287.e001.jpg" id="pone.0324287.e001g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M1" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable columnspacing="" displaystyle="true" rowspacing="3pt"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mi>;</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo fence="true" form="prefix" stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo fence="true" form="postfix" stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives>
<label>(1)</label>
</disp-formula><p>Finally, the contribution of chronic disease was further explored by applying Fairlie&#x02019;s non-linear decomposition (for urban-rural disparities in SRH) [<xref rid="pone.0324287.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. The model is as follows:</p><disp-formula id="pone.0324287.e002">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0324287.e002.jpg" id="pone.0324287.e002g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M2" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo accent="true">&#x02015;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo accent="true">&#x02015;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo fence="true" form="prefix" stretchy="true">[</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo fence="true" form="prefix" stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo fence="true" form="postfix" stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:munderover><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo fence="true" form="prefix" stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo fence="true" form="postfix" stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo fence="true" form="postfix" stretchy="true">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo fence="true" form="prefix" stretchy="true">[</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo fence="true" form="prefix" stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo fence="true" form="postfix" stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:munderover><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo fence="true" form="prefix" stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo fence="true" form="postfix" stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo fence="true" form="postfix" stretchy="true">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives>
<label>(2)</label>
</disp-formula><p>Some studies have shown that the Fairlie decomposition based on logistic regression model can solve the probability decomposition problem of the binary choice model, and can clearly portray the contribution of each factor to the urban-rural disparities in residents&#x02019; SRH [<xref rid="pone.0324287.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Fairlie decomposition can be done by analysing the factors influencing the disparities in SRH between urban and rural residents and decomposing the disparities into explainable and unexplainable components. The explainable part is mainly caused by disparities in the characteristics of urban and rural residents, also known as the characteristics effect; the unexplainable part is mainly caused by unobservable factors, i.e., disparities due to urban-rural attributes when all explanatory variables are the same in urban and rural areas, also known as coefficient effects [<xref rid="pone.0324287.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. P&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 was used to identify significant data in the analysis results. All statistical analyses were conducted using STATA 18.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec009"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec010"><title>Descriptive statistical analysis</title><p><xref rid="pone.0324287.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> showed descriptive statistics for all variables. There are disparities in the SRH of urban and rural inhabitants, 58.82%, 50.40% and 52.49% of urban, rural and all inhabitants, respectively, had a good SRH. This indicated that the overall SRH of rural residents was worse compared to urban residents. In addition, there was a significant disparity between the chronic disease status of urban and rural residents (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001), with rural residents suffering from a higher incidence of chronic disease than urban residents. The results of the t-test showed that there was a significant disparity between the socio-economic status of urban and rural residents (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001), and the mean value of urban residents was higher than that of rural residents, which indicated that the socio-economic status of urban residents was higher than that of rural residents. The results of the chi-square test showed that rural residents were more likely to have less education, with 60.26% of rural residents having junior high school or less education, almost twice as much as urban residents (30.92%). Physical activity was higher among urban residents than rural residents (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001). In addition, there were significant disparities between urban and rural residents for all variables except gender and smoking status.</p></sec><sec id="sec011"><title>Regression analysis</title><p>Regression analyses examined independent associations between chronic diseases and residents&#x02019; SRH, and the results were shown in <xref rid="pone.0324287.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="pone.0324287.t002"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0324287.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Logistic regression analysis of the relationship between chronic diseases and self-rated health.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0324287.t002" id="pone.0324287.t002g" position="float"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</th><th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Self-rated health (Odds Ratios)</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urban (N&#x02009;=&#x02009;760)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rural (N&#x02009;=&#x02009;1754)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All (N&#x02009;=&#x02009;2514)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chronic disease</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.205<bold>***</bold><break/>[0.140,0.300]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.167<bold>***</bold><break/>[0.130,0.215]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.179<bold>***</bold><break/>[0.145,0.220]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.978<bold>***</bold><break/>[0.966,0.989]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.976<bold>***</bold><break/>[0.968,0.984]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.976<bold>***</bold><break/>[0.970,0.983]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.128<break/>[0.757,1.679]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.257<break/>[0.953,1.659]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.209<break/>[0.964,1.516]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Marital status</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.629<bold>*</bold><break/>[0.419,0.945]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.917<break/>[0.688,1.223]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.802<break/>[0.636,1.011]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Education</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.913<break/>[0.620,1.345]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.019<break/>[0.801,1.297]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.976<break/>[0.797,1.195]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Socio-economic status</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.462<bold>***</bold><break/>[1.193,1.791]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.467<bold>***</bold><break/>[1.288,1.671]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.467<bold>***</bold><break/>[1.315,1.636]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">physical activity</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.662<bold>*</bold><break/>[1.088,2.538]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.154<break/>[0.912,1.460]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.260<bold>*</bold><break/>[1.028,1.545]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.786<break/>[0.493,1.255]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.058<break/>[0.778,1.439]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.980<break/>[0.758,1.267]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drinking</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.154<break/>[0.793,1.680]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.948<break/>[0.726,1.238]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.996<break/>[0.801,1.239]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep duration</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.047<break/>[0.713,1.537]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.161<break/>[0.915,1.475]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.120<break/>[0.915,1.369]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep quality</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.915<bold>***</bold><break/>[1.287,2.850]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.106<bold>***</bold><break/>[1.623,2.734]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.034<bold>***</bold><break/>[1.639,2.525]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medical insurance</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.445<break/>[0.532,3.925]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.812<break/>[0.495,1.331]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.889<break/>[0.570,1.386]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pension insurance</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.911<break/>[0.563,1.473]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.993<break/>[0.760,1.298]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.986<break/>[0.782,1.243]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Constant</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.305<break/>[0.358,4.761]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.790<break/>[0.839,3.818]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.809<break/>[0.953,3.433]</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t002fn001"><p>Note: Confidence intervals are in square brackets.</p></fn><fn id="t002fn002"><p><bold>*</bold> p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, <bold>**</bold> p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, <bold>***</bold> p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>In the regression results, the OR values for chronic diseases were significantly less than 1 for both urban (OR=0.205) and rural (OR=0.167) residents, suggesting that increased chronic disease conditions were largely significantly associated with lower odds of improving SRH (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001). In addition, age (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001), marital status (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05), socio-economic status (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001), physical activity (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05), and sleep quality (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001) were significantly associated with SRH among urban residents. Age (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001), socio-economic status (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001), sleep quality (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001) were significantly associated with SRH among rural residents. In contrast, the regression results showed that there is no statistical significance for urban residents in terms of gender, education, smoking, drinking, sleep duration, and insurance status. Rural residents were not statistically significant in terms of gender, marital status, education, physical activity, smoking, drinking, sleep duration, and insurance status.</p></sec><sec id="sec012"><title>Decomposition analyses</title><p>Through decomposition, this study further revealed the contribution of different factors to the disparities in SRH between urban and rural residents. The results of Fairlie&#x02019;s decomposition were presented in <xref rid="pone.0324287.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="pone.0324287.t003"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0324287.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Fairlie decomposition analysis of disparity in self-rated healt between urban and rural residents.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0324287.t003" id="pone.0324287.t003g" position="float"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fairlie decomposition for each variable</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coefficient (95% CI)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Robust standard error</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Contribution (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chronic disease</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.029<bold>***</bold><break/>[-0.032, -0.025]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.915</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.007<bold>***</bold><break/>[-0.010, -0.005]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.026</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.001<break/>[-0.003, 0.000]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.817</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Marital status</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.001<break/>[-0.002, 0.000]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.298</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Education</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001<break/>[-0.010, 0.011]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.708</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Socio-economic status</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.021<bold>***</bold><break/>[-0.027, -0.015]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.280</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">physical activity</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.010<bold>*</bold><break/>[-0.018, -0.001]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.277</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.000<break/>[-0.001, 0.001]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.139</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drinking</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.000<break/>[-0.005, 0.004]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.035</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep duration</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.001<break/>[-0.002, 0.001]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.146</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep quality</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.004<bold>***</bold><break/>[-0.006, -0.003]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.915</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medical insurance</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001<break/>[-0.002, 0.003]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.719</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pension insurance</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000<break/>[-0.004, 0.005]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.175</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Explained</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.074</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.851</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unexplained</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.011</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.149</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Difference</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.084</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t003fn001"><p>Note: The ordering of variables was randomized in Fairlie decomposition.</p></fn><fn id="t003fn002"><p><bold>*</bold> p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, <bold>**</bold> p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, *** p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The results of the Fairlie decomposition showed that the proportion of the explainable part of the total disparities were 87.851% and the proportion of the unexplainable part were 12.149%, i.e., 87.851% of the urban-rural disparities in the SRH of the Chinese residents were due to the observable factors, and the other 12.149% were related to the unexplainable part (coefficient effect). The results of the decomposition of the factors showed that the disparity between chronic diseases on the SRH of urban and rural residents was statistically significant (&#x003b2;&#x02009;=&#x02009;-0.029, p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001), which contributed the most, accounting for 38.915% of the total; In addition, age (&#x003b2;&#x02009;=&#x02009;-0.007, p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001), socioeconomic status (&#x003b2;&#x02009;=&#x02009;-0.021, p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001), physical activity (&#x003b2;&#x02009;=&#x02009;-0.010, p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05), and sleep quality (&#x003b2;&#x02009;=&#x02009;-0.004, p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001) were statistically significant in the disparity between the SRH of the urban and rural residents, with a contribution of 10.026%, 28.280%, 13.277%, and 5.915%; all other factors were not statistically significant (p&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.05).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec013"><title>Discussion</title><p>This study used data from the CGSS 2021, focused on the disparities in SRH between urban and rural residents in China, and quantified the extent to which chronic diseases explained the disparities in SRH between urban and rural residents in China. The results of descriptive, regression analyses confirmed that the SRH rate of urban residents (58.82%) was higher than that of rural residents (50.40%), which is consistent with the findings of Liu Yehong et al. [<xref rid="pone.0324287.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>] and Wang Yijie et al. [<xref rid="pone.0324287.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>], indicating that the SRH of urban residents was better than that of rural residents. Urban residents were less likely to suffer from chronic diseases (32.89%) than rural residents (39.97%), and an increase in the prevalence of chronic diseases was largely significantly associated with a decrease in the odds of improving SRH. With this in mind, we turned our attention to explaining the urban-rural disparities in SRH by conducting decomposition analyses.</p><p>The results of the study showed that 87.851% of the disparity in SRH rates between urban and rural residents was due to observed influencing factors, including chronic diseases, age, socio-economic status, physical activity and sleep quality. Among them, the disparity in the SRH rate of urban and rural residents due to chronic diseases is statistically significant (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001), and the disparity in the SRH of urban and rural residents with a contribution rate of 38.915% could be explained by the urban-rural disparity in chronic diseases, i.e., the disparity in the SRH rate between urban and rural areas decreases by 38.915% when the urban and rural areas are equally probable to suffer from the same condition of chronic diseases, indicating that the chronic disease disparity was the most important factor influencing the disparity in SRH between urban and rural residents. This phenomenon reflected the rural population&#x02019;s lack of awareness of chronic diseases and their weak self-management capacity, which is consistent with the findings of scholars such as Lu Jiehua and Sun Yang [<xref rid="pone.0324287.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>].</p><p>Specifically, the problem of low accessibility to basic health services in rural areas may lie behind this discrepancy. The relative scarcity of medical resources and the limited level of medical services in rural areas have led to poorer management and control of chronic diseases in rural areas compared to urban areas, which is consistent with the findings of scholars such as Vicky et al [<xref rid="pone.0324287.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Some scholars have pointed out that the primary healthcare management of non-communicable diseases in rural areas largely relies on grassroots doctors, who have received limited medical education and training [<xref rid="pone.0324287.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. In 2012, 84% of rural doctors in China did not hold a university degree, compared to 60% in urban areas [<xref rid="pone.0324287.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. At the same time, there was also a disparity between urban and rural residents in terms of health awareness, health literacy, and medical behavior. The rural residents have insufficient awareness of healthy lifestyles and behaviors, and their failure to develop good habits and healthy lifestyles not only increased their risk of illness, but also reduced their SRH [<xref rid="pone.0324287.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. On the contrary, urban residents were better able to manage chronic diseases due to more abundant healthcare resources and greater health awareness, thus improving their SRH. In addition, previous studies had shown that people with different health levels have different needs for healthcare [<xref rid="pone.0324287.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. According to some scholars&#x02019; research, the results of the study that most of the urban residents had significantly higher levels of health knowledge, attitude holding and behaviour than the rural residents also corroborated the findings of this study [<xref rid="pone.0324287.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0324287.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. Therefore, reducing the health disparity between urban and rural residents required attention to the impact of chronic diseases. Through the implementation of chronic disease prevention and treatment, it was possible to enhance rural residents&#x02019; knowledge of chronic diseases, improve their ability to self-manage chronic diseases, advocate for rural residents to change unhealthy lifestyles and reduce health disparities between urban and rural residents, thereby promoting health equity between urban and rural residents.</p><p>Firstly, the construction of basic health services in rural areas has been strengthened, and the quality of medical services has been upgraded by raising the level of medical resource allocation in rural areas and improving the conditions of medical services. At the same time, rural health education and publicity have been strengthened to raise rural residents&#x02019; health literacy and awareness of chronic disease prevention and treatment. Secondly, chronic disease prevention and treatment have been promoted, and the early detection and treatment rates of chronic diseases have been increased through the establishment and improvement of chronic disease prevention and treatment systems and the strengthening of chronic disease monitoring and screening. At the same time, health management and follow-up work for chronic disease patients has been strengthened to enhance their self-management capabilities. Thirdly, healthy lifestyles are being promoted, and urban and rural residents (especially in rural areas) are being encouraged to take an active part in health activities by stepping up publicity and promotion of healthy lifestyles. Furthermore, to narrow the disparity between urban and rural areas, measures such as promoting telemedicine services, providing subsidies for chronic disease management to alleviate the financial burden on rural residents, improving their health security, and dispatching community health workers to underserved areas can help reduce disparities in medical resources, economic conditions, and social support. The standard of living and health protection of rural residents has been raised, thereby narrowing the disparity between urban and rural residents in terms of chronic diseases and SRH status.</p><p>Urban-rural disparities in age, socio-economic status, physical activity, and sleep quality were also important factors associated with urban-rural disparities in the SRH of the residents. Disparities in the socio-economic status of urban and rural residents are associated with 28.280% of the disparity in SRH between urban and rural areas. It indicates that the higher the socio-economic status of Chinese residents, the more positive their SRH tends to be. This was because higher socio-economic status leads to increased spending on diet and health, which in turn improves one&#x02019;s health. There were great disparities in socioeconomic status and health service utilization between urban and rural residents in China [<xref rid="pone.0324287.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. For example, the elderly living in living in rural areas often do not afford medical care and were less likely to use hospitalization services [<xref rid="pone.0324287.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>].</p><p>This study had several limitations. First, our choice of SRH as a measure of health status, although widely validated, still had the disadvantage of subjectivity, which may pose a threat to the accuracy of health status. Second, this study only established a association, not a causal relationship, between chronic diseases and disparities in SRH between urban and rural residents. Due to the use of cross-sectional data in this study, it is not possible to rule out the influence of potential confounding factors and reverse causality. Therefore, although our study shows that chronic disease differences play an important role in the urban-rural disparity in SRH, we cannot conclude that chronic diseases directly cause these disparities. Third, Unobservable cultural factors may have an impact on the results of the analyses in this study and the generalizability of the results. Due to the unobservability of cultural factors and the inherent complexity of urban-rural health disparities, the use of cross-sectional data may not capture all relevant factors. In the future, research should collect more data for further validation, while rigorous clinical diagnostic techniques, well-designed longitudinal surveys, and experimental analyses under ethical approval will help address these limitations.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec014"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Based on the results of regression and decomposition analyses, rural residents have poorer SRH and a higher prevalence of chronic diseases compared to urban residents. The increase in chronic diseases significantly reduces the likelihood of improved SRH, making the rural-urban disparity in chronic diseases a primary factor in explaining SRH disparities. Additionally, age, socioeconomic status, social participation, and sleep quality also contribute to these disparities. It is recommended to strengthen health education, emphasize disease prevention and health behavior guidance, and focus on low-education populations, labor force groups, and underdeveloped regions. Furthermore, 12.149% of the SRH disparity remains unexplained, likely due to inherent rural-urban disparities. Therefore, breaking the urban-rural divide is crucial for narrowing health disparities.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>We would like to thank all individuals and organizations who provided assistance and support throughout this research. Special thanks to colleagues for their valuable feedback and to all staff members involved in the study, as well as to the institutions that provided resources for the research.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0324287.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fei</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Building a healthy China: The development process and experience of China&#x02019;s medical and health services under the leadership of the CPC</article-title>. <source>Manag World</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>26</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>40</lpage>. <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.19744/j.cnki.11-1235/f.2021.0169</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>. <article-title>Effects of the government&#x02019;s health expenditure on the health of rural residents in China</article-title>. <source>Soc Sci China</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>41</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>60</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>The current situation, problems and countermeasures of healthy village construction in the context of rural revitalization</article-title>. <source>Rural Econ</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>119</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>26</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>National Health Commission (NHC)</collab>. Monitoring of Health Literacy Among Chinese Residents in 2023. <year>2024</year> Available from: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.gov.cn/lianbo/bumen/202404/content6947232.htm" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.gov.cn/lianbo/bumen/202404/content6947232.htm</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Downey</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>DiBenedetto</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Health disparity concept analysis</article-title>. <source>Diversity Equal Health Care</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>224</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>31</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>McCartney</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Popham</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McMaster</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cumbers</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Defining health and health inequalities</article-title>. <source>Public Health</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>172</volume>:<fpage>22</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>30</lpage>. <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.puhe.2019.03.023</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31154234</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Idler</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Benyamini</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>. <article-title>Self-rated health and mortality: a review of twenty-seven community studies</article-title>. <source>J Health Soc Behav</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>21</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>37</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9097506</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Doogan</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kurti</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Redner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gaalema</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stanton</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Rural tobacco use across the United States: How rural and urban areas differ, broken down by census regions and divisions</article-title>. <source>Health Place</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>153</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.healthplace.2016.04.001</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27107746</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>GCK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Quinn</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Connor</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Weier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Rural and Urban Differences in Adolescent Alcohol Use, Alcohol Supply, and Parental Drinking</article-title>. <source>J Rural Health</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>280</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>. <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jrh.12151</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26450773</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Saman</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lipsky</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lutfiyya</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name>. <article-title>A cross-sectional study on health differences between rural and non-rural U.S. counties using the County Health Rankings</article-title>. <source>BMC Health Serv Res</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>441</fpage>. <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12913-015-1053-3</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26423746</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Arruda</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maia</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Inequality in access to health services between urban and rural areas in Brazil: a disaggregation of factors from 1998 to 2008</article-title>. <source>Cad Saude Publica</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):e00213816. <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/0102-311X00213816</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29947662</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kaczmarek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pacholska-Bogalska</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kwa&#x0015b;niewski</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kotarski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Halerz-Nowakowska</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Go&#x0017a;dzicka-J&#x000f3;zefiak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>The association between socioeconomic status and health-related quality of life among Polish postmenopausal women from urban and rural communities</article-title>. <source>Homo</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>68</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>42</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>50</lpage>. <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jchb.2016.11.004</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28024658</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ryan-Nicholls</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name>. <article-title>Health and sustainability of rural communities</article-title>. <source>Rural Remote Health</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>242</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15882108</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bonnell</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Clifton</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Waddell</surname><given-names>EN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Littenberg</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>. <article-title>Urban-Rural Differences in Mental and Physical Health among Primary Care Patients with Multiple Chronic Conditions: A Secondary Analysis from a Randomized Clinical Trial</article-title>. <source>Int J Environ Res Public Health</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>23</issue>):<fpage>15580</fpage>. <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph192315580</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36497657</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Westaway</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>. <article-title>The impact of chronic diseases on the health and well-being of South Africans in early and later old age</article-title>. <source>Arch Gerontol Geriatr</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>50</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>213</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>21</lpage>. <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.archger.2009.03.012</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19398135</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Molarius</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Janson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Self-rated health, chronic diseases, and symptoms among middle-aged and elderly men and women</article-title>. <source>J Clin Epidemiol</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>55</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>364</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>70</lpage>. <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0895-4356(01)00491-7</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11927204</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Barreto</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Figueiredo RC</surname><given-names>de</given-names></name>. <article-title>Chronic diseases, self-perceived health status and health risk behaviors: gender differences</article-title>. <source>Rev Saude Publica</source>. <year>2009</year>;43 Suppl 2:<fpage>38</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>47</lpage>. <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/s0034-89102009000900006</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19936497</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wolff</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Starfield</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>. <article-title>Prevalence, expenditures, and complications of multiple chronic conditions in the elderly</article-title>. <source>Arch Intern Med</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>162</volume>(<issue>20</issue>):<fpage>2269</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>76</lpage>. <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archinte.162.20.2269</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12418941</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>Y-J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Trends in the prevalence of multiple chronic conditions in Taiwan from 2000 to 2010: a population-based study</article-title>. <source>Prev Chronic Dis</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>11</volume>:E187. <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5888/pcd11.140205</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25340359</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>General Office of the State Council</collab>. Circular of the General Office of the State Council on the Issuance of the Medium- and Long-Term Plan for thePrevention and Treatment of Chronic Diseases in China (2017-2025). <year>2017</year>. Available from: <ext-link xlink:href="http://www.gov.cn/zhengce/content/2017-02/14/content_5167886.Htm" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.gov.cn/zhengce/content/2017-02/14/content_5167886.Htm</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sui</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>The impact of chronic diseases on the health-related quality of life of middle-aged and older adults: the role of physical activity and degree of digitization</article-title>. <source>BMC Public Health</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>2335</fpage>. <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-024-19833-8</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39198736</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name>. Construction and validation of the middle-range theory of chronic disease adaptation. <publisher-name>Zhejiang University</publisher-name>; <year>2020</year>. <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.27461/d.cnki.gzjdx.2020.002292</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Impact of internet use on physical and mental health of rural residents: empirical analysis based on CGSS2021 data</article-title>. <source>J Sichuan Agr Univ</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>689</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>97</lpage>. <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.16036/j.issn.1000-2650.202402361</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jylh&#x000e4;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>What is self-rated health and why does it predict mortality? Towards a unified conceptual model</article-title>. <source>Soc Sci Med</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>69</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>307</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>16</lpage>. <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.socscimed.2009.05.013</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19520474</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Miilunpalo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vuori</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oja</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pasanen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Urponen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Self-rated health status as a health measure: the predictive value of self-reported health status on the use of physician services and on mortality in the working-age population</article-title>. <source>J Clin Epidemiol</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>50</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>517</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>28</lpage>. <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0895-4356(97)00045-0</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9180644</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zajacova</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dowd</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>. <article-title>Reliability of self-rated health in US adults</article-title>. <source>Am J Epidemiol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>174</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>977</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>83</lpage>. <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aje/kwr204</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21890836</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Association of adverse childhood experiences with self-rated health among Chinese elderly people</article-title>. <source>Chin Gen Pract</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>25</issue>):<fpage>3101</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>. <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12114/j.issn.1007-9572.2022.0379</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>. <article-title>The impact of self-rated health and self-care ability and their interaction on depression symptoms in the elderly</article-title>. <source>Mod Prev Med</source>. <year>2025</year>;<volume>52</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>497</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>502</lpage>. <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.20043/j.cnki.MPM.202408051</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Olshansky</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ault</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>. <article-title>The fourth stage of the epidemiologic transition: the age of delayed degenerative diseases</article-title>. <source>Milbank Q</source>. <year>1986</year>;<volume>64</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>355</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>91</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3762504</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fuhrer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stansfeld</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>. <article-title>How gender affects patterns of social relations and their impact on health: a comparison of one or multiple sources of support from &#x0201c;close persons&#x0201d;</article-title>. <source>Soc Sci Med</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>54</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>811</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>25</lpage>. <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0277-9536(01)00111-3</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11999495</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Kawachi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Berkman</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name>. <article-title>Social Cohesion, Social Capital, and Health.</article-title> In: <source>Social Epidemiology</source>. <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>. <year>2000</year>. p. <fpage>174</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>190</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Lowry</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>. <source>Socioeconomic Status and Health Differentials in China: Convergence or Divergence at Old Ages</source>. <publisher-name>Population Studies Center, University of Michigan</publisher-name>. <year>2009</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yip</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>M-C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>H-S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S-D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>Y-L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>The effects of Taiwan&#x02019;s National Health Insurance on access and health status of the elderly</article-title>. <source>Health Econ</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>223</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>42</lpage>. <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hec.1160</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16929478</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chelak</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chakole</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>The Role of Social Determinants of Health in Promoting Health Equality: A Narrative Review</article-title>. <source>Cureus</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):e33425. <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7759/cureus.33425</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36751221</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Boffetta</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hashibe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Alcohol and cancer</article-title>. <source>Lancet Oncol</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>149</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>56</lpage>. <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1470-2045(06)70577-0</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16455479</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>H-R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nam</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C-H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Impact of Smoking and Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease on All-Cause, Respiratory, and Cardio-Cerebrovascular Mortality</article-title>. <source>Int J Chron Obstruct Pulmon Dis</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>1261</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>72</lpage>. <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/COPD.S458356</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38863653</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Warburton</surname><given-names>DER</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nicol</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bredin</surname><given-names>SSD</given-names></name>. <article-title>Health benefits of physical activity: the evidence</article-title>. <source>CMAJ</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>174</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>801</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1503/cmaj.051351</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16534088</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Weighall</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kellar</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>. <article-title>Sleep and memory consolidation in healthy, neurotypical children, and adults: a summary of systematic reviews and meta-analyses</article-title>. <source>Emerg Top Life Sci</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>513</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>24</lpage>. <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/ETLS20230110</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39288097</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Little</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name>. <source>Statistical Analysis with Missing Data</source>. <edition>2nd ed.</edition>
<publisher-loc>Hoboken, New Jersey</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Inc</publisher-name>; <year>2002</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Enders</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name>. <source>Applied Missing Data Analysis</source>. <publisher-name>Guilford Press</publisher-name>; <year>2010</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>. <article-title>Missing data analysis: making it work in the real world</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Psychol</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>60</volume>:<fpage>549</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>76</lpage>. <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.psych.58.110405.085530</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18652544</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fairlie</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name>. <article-title>An extension of the Blinder-Oaxaca decomposition technique to logit and probit models</article-title>. <source>J Econ Soc Meas</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>305</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>16</lpage>. <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3233/JEM-2005-0259</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>. <article-title>Research on urban-rural difference of higher education opportunities: empirical results through O-B decomposition of binary choice</article-title>. <source>Statist Inf Forum</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>87</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>93</lpage>. <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3969/j.issn.1007-3116.2012.04.015</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>. <article-title>Analysis of regional differences in health in China</article-title>. <source>J Shanxi Finance Econ Univ</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>11</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>24</lpage>. <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.13781/j.cnki.1007-9556.2011.08.004</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>XJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Measurement and trend analysis of health opportunity inequality among urban and rural residents in China</article-title>. <source>Popul Dev</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>72</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>87</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>Different influence of socioeconomic status on urban and rural residents&#x02019; health</article-title>. <source>J Northwest A &#x00026; F Univ (Soc Sci Ed)</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>117</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>23</lpage>. <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.13968/j.cnki.1009-9107.2015.06.017</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>. <article-title>Elderly health in rural China: characteristics, causes and responding strategies</article-title>. <source>J China Agric Univ (Soc Sci)</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>49</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>67</lpage>. <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.13240/j.cnki.caujsse.2024.02.005</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref048"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McPake</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Raban</surname><given-names>MZ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cowling</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alshamsan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chia</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Rural and urban differences in health system performance among older Chinese adults: cross-sectional analysis of a national sample</article-title>. <source>BMC Health Serv Res</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>372</fpage>. <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12913-020-05194-6</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32366235</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref049"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>The Effects of Chronic Disease Management in Primary Health Care: Evidence from Rural China</article-title>. <source>J Health Econ</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>80</volume>:<fpage>102539</fpage>. <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhealeco.2021.102539</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34740053</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref050"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>. <source>People&#x02019;s Republic of China health system review</source>. <publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name>. <year>2015</year>. Available from: <ext-link xlink:href="https://apo.who.int/publications/i/item/9789290617280" ext-link-type="uri">https://apo.who.int/publications/i/item/9789290617280</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref051"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mei</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ping</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>. <article-title>The Urban-Rural Disparity in the Status and Risk Factors of Health Literacy: A Cross-Sectional Survey in Central China</article-title>. <source>Int J Environ Res Public Health</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>3848</fpage>. <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph17113848</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32485790</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref052"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Asmus-Szepesi</surname><given-names>KJE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>de Vreede</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Flinterman</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nieboer</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bakker</surname><given-names>TJEM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Borsboom</surname><given-names>GJJM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Prognosis of hospitalised older people with different levels of functioning: a prospective cohort study</article-title>. <source>Age Ageing</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>803</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ageing/aft126</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23974209</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref053"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>. <article-title>Efficacy of China healthy lifestyle for all among urban and rural residents in Liaoning province</article-title>. <source>Chin J Public Health</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1693</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>. <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.11847/zgggws2017-33-12-05</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref054"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>. <article-title>Analysis on influence factors and countermeasures of old people&#x02019;s health in Siping city of Jilin province</article-title>. <source>Popul J</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>28</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>34</lpage>. <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3969/j.issn.1004-129X.2010.02.005</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref055"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>Comparison of health services use by Chinese urban and rural older adults in Yunnan province</article-title>. <source>Geriatr Gerontol</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>260</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1447-0594.2006.00358.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0324287.ref056"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>Health care in China: a rural-urban comparison after the socioeconomic reforms</article-title>. <source>Bull World Health Organ</source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>71</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>723</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>36</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8313490</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>