<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="issn">2168-8184</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cureus</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2168-8184</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cureus</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Palo Alto (CA)</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11681191</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7759/cureus.74635</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Dermatology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Facial Contouring Through Jaw Exercises: A Report of Two Cases Examining Efficacy and Consumer Expectations</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Muacevic</surname><given-names>Alexander</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>John R</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>Kritin K</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>Ryan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gidwani</surname><given-names>Karan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Walterscheid</surname><given-names>Brooke</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Friedmann</surname><given-names>Daniel P</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-5" ref-type="aff">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Parekh</surname><given-names>Palak</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-6" ref-type="aff">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tarbox</surname><given-names>Michelle</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff-1">
<label>1</label>
School of Medicine, Texas Tech University Health Sciences Center, Lubbock, USA </aff><aff id="aff-2">
<label>2</label>
School of Medicine, Texas A&#x00026;M University, College Station, USA </aff><aff id="aff-3">
<label>3</label>
Osteopathic Medicine, Touro University Nevada, Henderson, USA </aff><aff id="aff-4">
<label>4</label>
Dermatology, Texas Tech University Health Sciences Center, Lubbock, USA </aff><aff id="aff-5">
<label>5</label>
Dermatology, Westlake Dermatology Clinical Research Center, Westlake Dermatology and Cosmetic Surgery, Austin, USA </aff><aff id="aff-6">
<label>6</label>
Dermatology, Baylor Scott and White Medical Center, Temple, USA </aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">
Kritin K. Verma <email>kritin.k.verma@ttuhsc.edu</email>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>27</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic"><month>11</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><issue>11</issue><elocation-id>e74635</elocation-id><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2024, Verma et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Verma et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License CC-BY 4.0., which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="https://www.cureus.com/articles/296857-facial-contouring-through-jaw-exercises-a-report-of-two-cases-examining-efficacy-and-consumer-expectations">This article is available from https://www.cureus.com/articles/296857-facial-contouring-through-jaw-exercises-a-report-of-two-cases-examining-efficacy-and-consumer-expectations</self-uri><abstract><p>This study examines the efficacy of jaw exercising products for facial contouring. The two individuals used a commercially available jaw exerciser for approximately three months, following the provided instructions. Neither case reported noticeable changes in jaw appearance based on subjective measurements. In this study, a&#x000a0;review of scientific literature found limited evidence supporting these devices' ability to reduce double chins, enhance jawlines, or tighten facial skin. The mastication muscles targeted by these exercises do not directly affect submental fat or skin elasticity. While some studies show potential benefits for facial rejuvenation with specific devices, the overall evidence for jaw exercisers remains inconclusive. The results from the cases highlight&#x000a0;concerns about potentially misleading marketing claims and emphasize the need for larger, more objective studies to definitively assess these products' effectiveness. Limitations include the small sample size and the potential for bias. The findings suggest that jaw exercising products may have limited efficacy in achieving advertised results for facial contouring.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>consumer products</kwd><kwd>deceptive advertising</kwd><kwd>efficacy</kwd><kwd>facial contouring</kwd><kwd>jaw exercises</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>The growing popularity of jaw exercising products, which are frequently advertised on venues, such as Amazon and social media, has sparked tremendous consumer interest in their potential advantages for facial contouring. These products promise to improve face appearance through jaw exercises.</p><p>Despite these advertising claims, there is limited scientific data to support the ability of these devices to reduce double chins, enhance jawline structure, or result in face and neck tightening. Previous studies on facial workouts produced conflicting outcomes.&#x000a0;For example, a control group study evaluating the effectiveness of facial workouts for reducing wrinkles and sagging discovered no significant differences between the experimental and control groups, implying that facial exercises may not be useful for face rejuvenation [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Furthermore, a systematic assessment of exercise therapy for temporomandibular disorders (TMDs) found that while some exercises can increase jaw mobility and reduce discomfort, their effect on face contouring is unknown [<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>].</p><p>We analyzed the efficacy of jaw exercise tools through a report of two cases. Additionally, a literature review was done on the masticatory muscles involved, including the temporalis, masseter, medial pterygoid, and lateral pterygoid [<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. The findings will add to the continuing debate over the efficacy of these products and their potential for deceptive advertising.</p></sec><sec sec-type="cases"><title>Case presentation</title><p>The two cases in this report individually experimented with a set of jaw-exercising products at independent times at their leisure, due to interest in enhancing their jawline as advertised online.&#x000a0;The jaw-exercising products, which were obtained online for around $10 each by the individuals in this report, were used according to the instructions provided with the product at the time of purchase for approximately 10 minutes, one to three times per week. The participants used the product for roughly three months. These patients individually documented the course of their&#x000a0;jaw-exercising treatment by taking images before and after.</p><p>Case 1 involved a&#x000a0;27-year-old male with a BMI of 30.0 who used the product two to three times per week for three months. The patient's&#x000a0;diet and exercise were noted to be the same during this period as before the initiation of the jaw products. Exact details on exercise frequency and diet were not obtained. Before and after pictures were taken of the patient&#x02019;s face (Figures <xref rid="FIG1" ref-type="fig">1A</xref>-<xref rid="FIG1" ref-type="fig">1F</xref>). The participant reported no statistically significant&#x000a0;change in jaw appearance and facial contouring.</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Before (A-C) and after (D-F) pictures of the patient in Case 1.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0016-00000074635-i01" position="float"/></fig><p>Case 2 was a 24-year-old male with a BMI of 24 who used the product one to two times per week for three months. The patient reported being active three to four times a week before and during the use of the jaw exerciser. The patient noted no vast change in diet intake during the use of the product and stated that it was the same as before the initiation of the exerciser. Before and after pictures were taken of the patient&#x02019;s face (Figures <xref rid="FIG2" ref-type="fig">2A</xref>-<xref rid="FIG2" ref-type="fig">2F</xref>). The second patient had vitiligo, which may make it harder to evaluate facial contouring; however, did not impact the findings from the analysis, which indicated no statistically significant change in observable facial contouring.</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Before (A-C) and after (D-F) pictures of the patient in Case 2.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0016-00000074635-i02" position="float"/></fig><p>Various criteria were evaluated including facial contouring changes and overall satisfaction between patients (Table <xref rid="TAB1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The decision for documented facial contouring was a unanimous decision between the participants themselves and all the authors of this paper. The results for overall satisfaction were the self-documented experience with the product themselves and were reported as either very dissatisfied, slightly dissatisfied, neutral, slightly satisfied, and very satisfied. Neither case saw any change in the reduction of the double chin line, jawline enhancement, as well as face and neck tightening.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Evaluation of device and results from participants.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">
Evaluated criteria
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Case 1
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Case 2
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">
Documented facial contouring changes
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Double chin reduction
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
No change
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
No change
</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Jawline enhancement
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
No change
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
No change
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Face and neck tightening&#x000a0;
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
No change
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
No change
</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="6" colspan="1">
Overall satisfaction
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Ease of use
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Neutral
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Slightly satisfied
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Easy to clean
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Neutral
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Slightly dissatisfied
</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Suctioning problem
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Very dissatisfied
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Slightly dissatisfied
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Gagging
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Slightly dissatisfied
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Very dissatisfied
</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Unstable in mouth
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Slightly dissatisfied
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Neutral
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Rubbery feeling
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Slightly dissatisfied
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Slightly dissatisfied
</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Jaw exercisers typically target the mastication muscles, which control chewing movements [<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. These muscles - temporalis, masseter, medial pterygoid, and lateral pterygoid - have no direct effect on submental double chin fat reduction, jawline enhancement, or skin tightening based on the three cases we reported in this study [<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. This understanding is supported by scientific literature. For example, a study on face exercises discovered no significant increase in facial rejuvenation, implying that activities aimed at facial muscles may not successfully eliminate wrinkles or sagging skin [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Similarly, assessments of exercise therapy for TMDs found that while exercises can increase jaw mobility and reduce discomfort, they have no meaningful effect on face contours [<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].</p><p>One study concluded that facial muscle exercises could lead to beneficial effects on facial rejuvenation [<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. However, the device used in this study had a vastly different mechanism than the one used in the present study [<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. The Pao device (Nagoya, Japan: MTG Co., Ltd), which is held in the mouth and moves in an oscillating motion by nodding the head, was used for 30 s&#x000a0;twice a day for a total of eight weeks [<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. The researchers found that the exercises led to changes in facial surface distances, surface areas, and volumes resulting in decreased facial wrinkles and jawline sagging [<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>].&#x000a0;The Pao device targets facial muscles differently than the static resistance provided by jaw exercisers in our cases [<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. This distinction in the mechanism of action could explain the disparity in outcomes.</p><p>Weight gain, genetics, and aging are common causes of double chin reduction that cannot be treated with muscle exercises alone [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. There is no strong scientific data to support the effectiveness of jaw workouts in reducing submental fat. While workouts can improve jaw muscle strength, they do not affect the underlying bone structure or facial shapes. Non-surgical procedures such as fillers and botulinum toxin (Botox) injections have shown greater potential in improving facial esthetics [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Skin tightening is influenced by skin elasticity and fat distribution. Exercises that target the jaw muscles may not have any meaningful effect on these parameters [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Furthermore, recent advancements in non-invasive facial contouring techniques, such as high-intensity focused ultrasound (HIFU) and radiofrequency therapy, offer alternative approaches that may be more effective than exercise-based methods for addressing issues like submental fat reduction and skin tightening and should be considered for any patients considering facial contouring [<xref rid="REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].</p><p>The fundamental limitation of this study is the subjectivity of the presented results. Quantifiable methods to measure facial contouring&#x000a0;(e.g.,&#x000a0;using 3D imaging technology or facial scans yielding facial fat percentage) would have more precisely analyzed the efficacy of the product. Another limitation was that the BMIs for before and after product use were not obtained. Blinding patients in future studies may&#x000a0;help eliminate bias in identifying the efficacy of jaw exercisers. Additionally, participants, who are also the authors, may have biases that influence their findings. Furthermore, the small sample size and absence of objective measurements make the findings qualitative&#x000a0;and&#x000a0;potentially biased. The marketing promises, which may be typically seen in online products, for these jaw exercisers need to be more supported by scientific research [<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. The products do not treat the underlying reasons for double chins or skin laxity; hence, they do not produce the expected outcomes. This raises issues regarding deceptive advertising, and customers should use caution when considering such products.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>According to the findings of this report of two cases, jaw exercising items have limited efficacy in terms of double chin reduction, jawline enhancement, and face and neck tightening. The findings indicate that these products may not achieve the stated results, and their benefits are mostly subjective and minor. More studies with larger sample sizes and objective metrics are required to verify their efficacy definitively.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group content-type="conflict"><title>Disclosures</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Human subjects:</bold> Consent for treatment and open access publication was obtained or waived by all participants in this study.</p><p><bold>Conflicts of interest:</bold> In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following:</p><p><bold>Payment/services info:</bold> All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work.</p><p><bold>Financial relationships:</bold> All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work.</p><p><bold>Other relationships:</bold> All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="other"><title>Author Contributions</title><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Concept and design:</bold>&#x000a0; Kritin K. Verma, Ryan Koch, Daniel P. Friedmann, Michelle Tarbox</p><p><bold>Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data:</bold>&#x000a0; Kritin K. Verma, Karan Gidwani, Brooke Walterscheid, Daniel P. Friedmann, Palak Parekh, Michelle Tarbox</p><p><bold>Drafting of the manuscript:</bold>&#x000a0; Kritin K. Verma, Ryan Koch, Karan Gidwani, Brooke Walterscheid</p><p><bold>Supervision:</bold>&#x000a0; Kritin K. Verma, Michelle Tarbox</p><p><bold>Critical review of the manuscript for important intellectual content:</bold>&#x000a0; Brooke Walterscheid, Daniel P. Friedmann, Palak Parekh, Michelle Tarbox</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="REF1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Facial exercises for facial rejuvenation: a control group study</article-title><source>Folia Phoniatr Logop</source><person-group>
<name><surname>De Vos</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Van den Brande</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Boone</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Van Borsel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>117</fpage><lpage>122</lpage><volume>65</volume><year>2013</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24296342</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Jaw exercises in the treatment of temporomandibular disorders - an international modified Delphi study</article-title><source>J Oral Facial Pain Headache</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Lindfors</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Arima</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baad-Hansen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>389</fpage><lpage>398</lpage><volume>33</volume><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31247061</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><article-title>Anatomy, head and neck, mastication muscles</article-title><source>StatPearls [Internet]</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Basit</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tariq</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Siccardi</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
</person-group><publisher-loc>Treasure Island, FL</publisher-loc><publisher-name>StatPearls Publishing</publisher-name><year>2024</year><uri xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/31082071/">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/31082071/</uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Effects of jaw-opening exercises with/without pain for temporomandibular disorders: a pilot randomized controlled trial</article-title><source>Int J Environ Res Public Health</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Tobe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ishiyama</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nishiyama</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Miyazono</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fueki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group><volume>19</volume><year>2022</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Effectiveness of exercise therapy on pain relief and jaw mobility in patients with pain-related temporomandibular disorders: a systematic review</article-title><source>Front Oral Health</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Shimada</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ogawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sammour</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><volume>4</volume><year>2023</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Effect of a facial muscle exercise device on facial rejuvenation</article-title><source>Aesthet Surg J</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>UJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>OY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gwak</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>463</fpage><lpage>476</lpage><volume>38</volume><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29365050</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Three-dimensional analysis of lifting effects after high-intensity focused ultrasound (Ultraformer-MPT) across seven facial aesthetic units considering sonoanatomy</article-title><source>Plast Reconstr Surg Glob Open</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>
</person-group><volume>12</volume><year>2024</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Facial rejuvenation and contouring with radiofrequency-assisted procedures in Asians</article-title><source>Clin Plast Surg</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>49</lpage><volume>50</volume><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36396260</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Uncovering shortcomings in advertising strategies for over-the-counter minoxidil products on Amazon</article-title><source>Cureus</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Friedmann</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tarbox</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><volume>16</volume><year>2024</year></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>