<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Pain Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Pain Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="coden">PAIREP</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Painreports</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Pain Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2471-2531</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Wolters Kluwer</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Philadelphia, PA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40012559</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11864306</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PAINREPORTS-D-24-0152</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/PR9.0000000000001246</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="art-access-id">00012</article-id><article-version vocab="JAV" vocab-identifier="http://www.niso.org/publications/rp/RP-8-2008.pdf" article-version-type="Version of Record">3</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>12</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>General Section</subject><subject>Research Paper</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Difficulties with prescribed opioids: a cross-sectional survey of primary care patients in England, United Kingdom</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4200-1074</contrib-id><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>Louise E.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1646-8321</contrib-id><name><surname>Knaggs</surname><given-names>Roger D.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><email>roger.knaggs@nottingham.ac.uk</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7591-4438</contrib-id><name><surname>Avery</surname><given-names>Anthony J.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><email>anthony.avery@nottingham.ac.uk</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9276-052X</contrib-id><name><surname>Thornley</surname><given-names>Tracey</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><email>tracey.thornley1@nottingham.ac.uk</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>Jos&#x000e9;</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref><email>jose.moss@boots.co.uk</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3775-5346</contrib-id><name><surname>Baamer</surname><given-names>Reham M.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref><email>reham.baamer2@nottingham.ac.uk</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2997-5090</contrib-id><name><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>Matthew J.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><email>matthew.boyd@nottingham.ac.uk</email></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Division of Pharmacy Practice and Policy, School of Pharmacy, University of Nottingham, Nottingham, <country>United Kingdom</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Centre for Academic Primary Care, School of Medicine, University of Nottingham, Nottingham, <country>United Kingdom</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Boots UK, Nottingham, <country>United Kingdom</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>Department of Pharmacy Practice, Faculty of Pharmacy, King Abdulaziz University, Jeddah, <country>Saudi Arabia</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Corresponding author. Address: Division of Pharmacy Practice and Policy, School of Pharmacy, Pharmacy School Building, University of Nottingham, Nottingham, NG7 2RD, England, United Kingdom. Tel.: +44 (0) 115 823 2271. E-mail address: <email>louise.wilson1@nottingham.ac.uk</email> (L. E. Wilson).</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>4</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>25</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue>2</issue><elocation-id>e1246</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>6</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>19</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>01</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2025 The Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. on behalf of the International Association for the Study of Pain.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License 4.0 (CCBY)</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="painreports-10-e1246.pdf"/><abstract abstract-type="toc"><p>Supplemental Digital Content is Available in the Text.</p></abstract><abstract><title>Abstract</title><sec><title>Introduction:</title><p>Knowledge of the potential for harm and adverse effects from long-term opioid medicines has led to reduced prescribing in recent years. However, the number of patients receiving opioid prescriptions from primary care in England remains substantial and understanding the difficulties patients experience with these medicines is important for the provision of care.</p></sec><sec><title>Objective:</title><p>To understand the difficulties experienced by patients prescribed opioids for noncancer pain in primary care.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods:</title><p>A cross-sectional postal survey of adults prescribed an opioid medicine for noncancer pain over a period of &#x02265;3 months from 10 general practices (n = 3077) in the East Midlands was conducted using self-completed questionnaires. Sociodemographic, pain, and opioid use information was gathered to characterise the study population. An adapted version of the 15-item Prescribed Opioids Difficulties Scale was used to assess the problems and concerns attributed to using prescribed opioids, from the time opioids were first prescribed.</p></sec><sec><title>Results:</title><p>Questionnaires were received from 619 respondents (response rate = 20.1%), of whom 59.8% were female, and the median age was 64 years. Four in 5 (79.8%) had experienced at least one opioid problem or concern from the Prescribed Opioids Difficulties Scale, and one in 5 (22.8%) had experienced 8 or more. The most frequently reported difficulty was needing to increase the dose of opioids to get the same effect (46.0%). Chi-square analysis with odds ratio found respondents were 2.6 times more likely to report &#x02265;4 difficulties if they had higher pain intensity and interference (95% CI: 1.85&#x02013;3.77, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion:</title><p>Opioid difficulties were common in this population and this study provides evidence for regular monitoring of problems after prescribing.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><title>Keywords:</title><kwd>Opioids</kwd><kwd>Pain</kwd><kwd>Primary care</kwd><kwd>Cross-sectional survey</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="award1"><funding-source xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.13039/501100000272">National Institute for Health and Care Research</funding-source><award-id>NF-SI-0617-10076</award-id><principal-award-recipient>Anthony J Avery</principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="award2"><funding-source>Boots UK</funding-source><award-id>N/A</award-id><principal-award-recipient>Louise E Wilson</principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="award3"><funding-source xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.13039/501100000837">University of Nottingham</funding-source><award-id>N/A</award-id><principal-award-recipient>Louise E Wilson</principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name><meta-value>TRUE</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>SDC</meta-name><meta-value>T</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>1. Introduction</title><p>Knowledge about the potential for harm and adverse effects from long-term use of opioid medicines, alongside limited benefits in the treatment of chronic noncancer pain (CNCP), has advanced over the past 20 years.<sup><xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup> Side effects such as constipation, nausea, dizziness, sedation, vomiting, and pruritus are known to occur frequently.<sup><xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> Harm from problems related to opioid tolerance, dependence, and addiction is well documented, but the extent of these problems is less certain, particularly in the case of dependence.<sup><xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> Reported levels of prescription opioid use disorder have been found to be very low in the United Kingdom, but are likely to be an underestimate because of a lack of diagnosis and documentation in patient records.<sup><xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> This measure also fails to identify problems that fall below the threshold for opioid use disorder.</p><p>In recent years, countries with high levels of opioid prescribing have updated clinical guidelines to avoid or limit the use of opioids in many painful conditions, especially in CNCP.<sup><xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,<xref rid="R51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref></sup> This change is reflected within guidance for health care practitioners in England, United Kingdom, produced by the National Institute for Health and Care Excellence (NICE).<sup><xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="R43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></sup> The United Kingdom National Health Service (NHS) requires patient registration with one general practice physician and uses a shared patient record system.<sup><xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> This structure may have limited increases in opioid use in comparison with countries where patients have access to any medical practice, such as in the United States. Despite this, the United Kingdom has still experienced historical increases in opioid prescribing,<sup><xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup> followed by a period of gradual decline from 2016.<sup><xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="R50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></sup> In the absence of alternative medicines, the use of opioids for many types of pain remains substantial, with prescriptions for codeine accounting for the largest proportion of opioid prescribing in primary care.<sup><xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup> Several national initiatives and clinical interventions have been developed in the United Kingdom in recent years to support opioid dose reductions and/or discontinuation in CNCP.<sup><xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,<xref rid="R48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></sup> However, it is likely that many patients will continue to be prescribed some form of opioid medicine for the foreseeable future, and therefore require support to manage side effects and problems. Understanding the experiences of patients using these medicines, therefore, continues to be important for the provision of associated care.</p><p>The Prescribed Opioids Difficulties Scale (PODS) is a survey tool developed to assess recent issues associated with long-term opioid use for CNCP from the patient's perspective.<sup><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> Scale items examine problems and concerns attributed to opioids, including issues related to tolerance, dependence, and addiction. The survey has potential for wider use to assess opioid-related difficulties across the entire time opioids are prescribed. The Prescribed Opioids Difficulties Scale has been used in several studies in different countries<sup><xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup>; however, to our knowledge, it has not previously been used in the United Kingdom. The main aim of this research was to assess the pain, opioid use, and difficulties experienced by patients prescribed opioids for noncancer pain, in a real-world setting, using an adapted version of the PODS.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>2. Methods</title><p>The study design was a cross-sectional postal survey of adults prescribed an opioid medicine for noncancer pain by their general practice. Ethical approval was given by the United Kingdom Health Research Authority (ref 21/SC/0105).</p><sec id="s2-1"><title>2.1. Study population</title><p>Ten primary care general practices were recruited via the East Midlands Clinical Research Network, England, United Kingdom.<sup><xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> The sampling frame included all adults aged 18 years and older, prescribed any opioid or opioid/paracetamol combination analgesic for noncancer pain over a period of &#x02265;3 months (defined as &#x02265;2 opioid prescriptions issued in the previous 3 months with a minimum of one opioid prescription in month 1, and one opioid prescription in month 3). Eligible patients were identified through an electronic search of the practice clinical system, followed by GP screening to check for exclusions. Patients with a terminal illness, unable to understand English, or vulnerable and deemed inappropriate to contact were excluded. Questionnaires were mailed, via CFH Docmail,<sup><xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> with a letter from the practice, a letter from the research team, a participant information sheet, and a freepost returns envelope. A text message reminder to complete the questionnaire was sent 2 weeks after mailing to all eligible patients where the practice held a mobile telephone number. Questionnaires were mailed from the first practice in October 2021 and from the last practice in June 2022. Questionnaire returns were accepted until 31st July 2022.</p><p>Recruitment via general practices was considered the most appropriate method for identifying a sample of patients recently prescribed an opioid pain medicine. The majority of opioid prescriptions are issued from this setting, with 5.6 million adults in England (13% of the population) dispensed an opioid prescription for noncancer pain in 2017/18.<sup><xref rid="R50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></sup> The duration of opioid prescribing was chosen to give an adequate period of use on which participants could report their experience, not to determine long-term use. In this study, general practices completed all recruitment processes and the clinical information of eligible patients was not accessible to the research team. A sample size target of 600 patients was set to achieve a 4% margin of error, with a 95% confidence level, in descriptive statistics and detect any associations between categorical variables. A conservative 20% response estimate was used to recruit a sufficient number of practices from which 3000 eligible patients could be identified.</p></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>2.2. Experiences of prescribed opioids questionnaire</title><p>The survey collected information relating to prescribed opioids including participant sociodemographics, pain and opioid use, and difficulties experienced with opioid medicines (Supplemental Appendix 1, <ext-link xlink:href="http://links.lww.com/PR9/A283" ext-link-type="uri">http://links.lww.com/PR9/A283</ext-link>). Survey questions used preexisting scales and nonscaled items developed from the literature and expertise within the research team. The survey was pretested with a PPI representative.</p><sec id="s2-2-1"><title>2.2.1. Sociodemographic information</title><p>Data were collected for age, sex, ethnic group, and current employment status. Each participant was also assigned to an Index of Multiple Deprivation (IMD) quintile, determined by the profile of patients registered at the general practice from which they were recruited to the study.<sup><xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup></p></sec><sec id="s2-2-2"><title>2.2.2. Pain and prescribed opioid use</title><p>Participants were asked to complete a brief pain assessment using the Pain, Enjoyment of life, and General activity (PEG) scale.<sup><xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup> The PEG scale is composed of 3 numerical rating scales (range 0&#x02013;10), assessing pain intensity and interference. Participants were also asked how long they had been using prescribed opioids for pain, on how many days they had used an opioid in the past 2 weeks, how helpful opioids have been in relieving pain over the past month, and whether opioids had relieved their pain as much as expected.</p></sec><sec id="s2-2-3"><title>2.2.3. Difficulties with opioid pain medicines</title><p>An adapted version of the PODS was used to assess the difficulties participants attributed to using prescribed opioids. The Prescribed Opioids Difficulties Scale is a validated scale, developed in the United States, composed of 8 items relating to psychosocial problems and 7 items relating to control concerns.<sup><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> The original version of the scale assesses current or recent difficulties to determine a problems and concerns score. We wanted to assess difficulties over the entire time opioids were prescribed; therefore, PODS scale items were not time-limited and, with the exception of one item, response options were presented as a 5-point agreement Likert scale.<sup><xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup></p></sec></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title>2.3. Data analysis</title><p>Responses were entered manually with an accuracy check on 10% of entries by a second member of the research team. IBM SPSS version 27 software program was used to conduct subsequent statistical analyses.</p><p>Pain, Enjoyment of life, and General activity scores were determined for each respondent by calculating the average score of the 3 scale items and grouping the results into low (0&#x02013;3), medium (4&#x02013;6), or high (7&#x02013;10) scores, following the common categorisation of the Numerical Pain Rating Scale (NRPS).<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> Days of opioid use in the past 2 weeks were grouped into less than 7, 7 to 13, and 14 (daily use). Values greater than 14 were treated as missing data.</p><p>Problems and concerns scores were calculated for each respondent by dichotomising each PODS item response into agreement/nonagreement. All questions scored 1 for agreement and 0 for nonagreement. One item, which asked about the impact of side effects, did not use a Likert agreement scale. For this the responses &#x0201c;no side effects&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;a little bothersome&#x0201d; scored 0, and &#x0201c;moderately&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;very,&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;extremely bothersome&#x0201d; scored 1. Total scores were subsequently grouped into &#x0201c;low&#x0201d; (0&#x02013;3), &#x0201c;medium&#x0201d; (4&#x02013;7), and &#x0201c;high&#x0201d; (8&#x02013;15). Scoring and grouping reflected the original scoring of the scale as far as possible.<sup><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup></p><p>Chi-square tests for independence were conducted to determine associations between respondent characteristics and how helpful they found opioids in relieving pain over the past month.<sup><xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> Further chi-square tests were conducted between respondent characteristics and the problems and concerns score generated from the PODS questions. Odds ratios (OR) with 95% confidence intervals (CIs) were calculated for significant associations between dichotomous variables to give an indication of the strength of the association. A Bonferroni adjustment was made to the significance value to account for the multiple tests performed.<sup><xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup></p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>3. Results</title><sec id="s3-1"><title>3.1. Demographics</title><p>General practices in the study had a combined list size of 101,774 patients (as reported on the date of electronic search), from which 3077 (3.0%) potential participants were identified as eligible to take part. A total of 619 questionnaires were received by the study team, giving a response rate of 20.1%. Demographic characteristics of respondents are presented in Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, with 59.8% categorised female and a median (IQR) age of 64 years (55&#x02013;74 years). Just over half (50.7%) were retired and 59.9% were registered at a practice with a patient population within the 2 most deprived IMD quintiles.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Demographic characteristics of respondents.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristic</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Classification</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex (n = 610)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">365</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">241</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (y) (n = 611)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18&#x02013;29</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30&#x02013;39</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40&#x02013;49</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50&#x02013;59</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">130</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60&#x02013;69</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">179</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70&#x02013;79</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">148</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80+</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">73</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethnic background (n = 601)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asian/Asian British</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Black/African/Caribbean/Black British</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed/multiple ethnic groups</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">White</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">567</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Employment status<xref rid="tblfn1" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref> (n = 603)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Employed</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">126</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A student</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retired</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">306</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A homemaker</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unable to work</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">163</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Out of work and seeking</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Opportunities</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IMD quintile of participant GP practice<xref rid="tblfn2" ref-type="table-fn">&#x02020;</xref> (n = 619)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (most deprived)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">226</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">145</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">116</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">74</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (least deprived)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.4</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other" id="tblfn1"><label>*</label><p>In some instances, respondents selected more than one answer.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="tblfn2"><label>&#x02020;</label><p>Respondents assigned to IMD quintile of GP Practice population on date of database search as published at <ext-link xlink:href="https://fingertips.phe.org.uk/profile/general-practice" ext-link-type="uri">https://fingertips.phe.org.uk/profile/general-practice</ext-link>.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>IMD, Index of Multiple Deprivation.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3-2"><title>3.2. Pain and prescribed opioid use</title><p>Pain intensity and interference (PEG) scores are shown in Table <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref>. Two-thirds of respondents (67.5%) had a calculated PEG score of between 7 and 10, indicating high pain intensity and interference. The proportion of high, medium, and low scores were similar within each of the 3 domains.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>PEG 3-item pain scale scores.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Scale component (range 0&#x02013;10)</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Low score (0&#x02013;3)</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Medium score (4&#x02013;6)</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">High score (7&#x02013;10)</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pain intensity (P) (n = 618)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">188</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.4</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">403</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Interference with enjoyment of life (E) (n = 616)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.4</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">130</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.1</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">428</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Interference with general activity (G) (n = 616)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.4</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">149</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.2</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">415</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average (PEG) (n = 613)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">163</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.6</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">414</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.5</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Table <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">3</xref> summarises the reported use of prescribed opioids by respondents. Nearly two-thirds (63.6%) had used prescribed opioid pain medicines for more than 3 years, with 82.5% reporting daily use in the past 2 weeks. Just over two-fifths (41.0%) found opioids very or extremely helpful in relieving their pain over the past month, with half (51.2%) reporting that opioids had probably or definitely relieved pain as much as they expected over the same time.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Prescribed opioid use.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristic</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Classification</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration of opioid use (n = 615)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3&#x02013;6 mo</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7&#x02013;12 mo</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02013;2 y</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2&#x02013;3 y</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">81</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;3 y</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">391</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Opioid use in past 2 wk (n = 601)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;7 d</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7&#x02013;13 d</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">74</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 d</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">496</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">How helpful found opioids in relieving pain over the past month ? (n = 615)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not at all helpful</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A little helpful</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">83</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderately helpful</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">267</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Very helpful</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">188</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Extremely helpful</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Have opioids relieved pain as much as expected over the past month ? (n = 615)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Definitely not</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Probably not</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">134</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Might or might not</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">119</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Probably yes</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">217</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Definitely yes</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">98</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.9</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3-3"><title>3.3. Prescribed Opioids Difficulties Scale</title><p>Percentage responses to PODS items are shown in Table <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">4</xref> (psychosocial problems) and Table <xref rid="T5" ref-type="table">5</xref> (control concerns). Problems with the highest levels of agreement from respondents were feeling slowed down, sluggish, or sedated (45.2%), and feeling sleepy or less alert when doing something where they needed to be alert (38.2%). One in 8 respondents (12.3%) considered any side effects of opioid pain medicines to be very or extremely bothersome.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Percentage response for opioid problems.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Strongly disagree</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Disagree</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Neutral</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Agree</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Strongly agree</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">There have been times when opioid pain medicines have caused me to lose interest in my usual activities (n = 610)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">88</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.4</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">188</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.8</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">139</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.8</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">150</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.6</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">There have been times when opioid pain medicines have caused me to have trouble concentrating or remembering (n = 612)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">78</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.7</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">195</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.9</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">142</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.2</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">155</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.3</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">There have been times when opioid pain medicines have caused me to feel slowed down, sluggish, or sedated (n = 613)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.6</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">153</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">124</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.2</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">221</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.1</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">There have been times when opioid pain medicines have caused me to feel depressed, down, or anxious (n = 612)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">108</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.6</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">191</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.2</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">147</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">123</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.1</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">There have been times when the side effects of opioid pain medicines have interfered with my work, family, or social responsibilities (n = 612)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">106</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.3</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">180</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.4</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">142</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.2</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">141</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">There have been times when opioid pain medicines have made it hard for me to think clearly (n = 606)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">94</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.5</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">209</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.5</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">139</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.9</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">137</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.6</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">There have been times when opioid pain medicines have made me sleepy or less alert when I was doing something where I needed to be alert (n = 604)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">73</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.1</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">169</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">131</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.7</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">187</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.3</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">No side effects</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">A little bothersome</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Moderately bothersome</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Very bothersome</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Extremely bothersome</th></tr><tr><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">n</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">n</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">n</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">n</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">n</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Considering any side effects of opioid pain medicines you may have experienced, how bothersome were these side effects ? (n = 602)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">218</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">176</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">134</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Percentage response for opioid concerns.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Strongly disagree</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Disagree</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Neutral</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Agree</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Strongly agree</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">There have been times when I have been preoccupied with or thought constantly about my opioid pain medicines (n = 602)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">163</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.1</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">211</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">119</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.8</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">87</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.5</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">There have been times when I have felt that I could not control how much or how often I needed opioid pain medicines (n = 605)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">173</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.6</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">216</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.7</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">98</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.2</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.9</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">There have been times when I have needed to increase the dose of my opioid pain medicines to get the same effect (n = 605)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">93</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.4</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">133</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">101</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.7</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">230</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">There have been times when I have worried that I might be dependent on or addicted to opioid pain medicines (n = 611)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">119</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.5</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">172</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.2</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">102</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.7</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">167</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.3</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">There have been times when I have wanted to stop my opioid pain medicines or to cut down on the amount that I use (n = 607)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">88</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.5</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">195</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.1</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">135</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.2</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">148</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.4</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">There have been times when opioid pain medicines have caused me to have problems with family, friends, or coworkers (n = 606)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">233</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.4</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">243</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.1</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">78</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.9</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.8</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">There have been times when family or friends have thought that I may be dependent on or addicted to opioid pain medicines (n = 608)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">232</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.2</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">203</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.4</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">85</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">73</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Concerns with the highest levels of agreement from respondents included needing to increase the dose to get the same effect (46.0%) and being worried that they might be dependent on or addicted to opioid pain medicines (35.7%). The level of agreement with other concerns was more variable, but notably, 31.1% of respondents had wanted to stop or cut down the amount used, and one in 12 (8.6%) reported opioid pain medicines had caused problems with family, friends, or coworkers.</p><p>The distribution of problems and concerns scores is presented in Figure <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. Four in 5 respondents (79.8%) had experienced at least one problem or concern attributed to opioid pain medicines, with almost half (48.1%) experiencing 4 or more. More than one in 5 respondents (22.8%) reported difficulties resulting in a high score (&#x02265;8 problems or concerns).</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Distribution of problems and concerns scores.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="painreports-10-e1246-g001" position="float"/></fig><p>Associations between respondent characteristics and how helpful they found opioids in relieving pain over the past month are shown in Table <xref rid="T6" ref-type="table">6</xref>. No significant associations were seen with sex, age, duration of opioid use, or daily opioid use. A significant association was seen with PEG score where those who reported high pain intensity and interference (high PEG score) found opioids less helpful than those with a lower score (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T6"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Associations between respondent characteristics and how helpful they found opioids in relieving pain over the past month.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Characteristic</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Not at all/A little/Moderately helpful</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Very/Extremely helpful</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
<xref rid="tblfn4" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>
</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chi-square</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex (n = 602)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Female</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">214</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.1</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">148</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.9</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.996</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Male</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">141</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.8</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">99</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (n = 607)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x0003c;50 y</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.3</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02265;50 y</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">310</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.9</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">216</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.1</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration of opioid use (n = 613)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02264;3 y</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">130</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.3</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">93</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.7</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.888</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x0003e;3 y</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">231</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.2</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">159</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Daily opioid use (n = 599)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Yes</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">298</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.1</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">198</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.9</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.252</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;No</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.4</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PEG score (n = 610)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Low (0&#x02013;3)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.2</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.8</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003<xref rid="tblfn3" ref-type="table-fn">&#x02020;</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Medium (4&#x02013;6)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">81</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.7</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">82</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;High (7&#x02013;10)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">261</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.5</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">150</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other" id="tblfn3"><label>&#x02020;</label><p>Significance reduced to <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01 via Bonferroni adjustment.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="tblfn4"><label>*</label><p>With Yates' continuity correction for all 2 &#x000d7; 2 tables.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>PEG, pain intensity, interference with enjoyment, and interference with general activity.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Associations between respondent characteristics and problems and concerns score are shown in Table <xref rid="T7" ref-type="table">7</xref>. No significant associations were seen with sex or duration of opioid use. Significant associations were seen with age, PEG score, and how helpful respondents found opioids in relieving pain over the past month (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01). The odds of a respondent reporting a medium to high problems and concerns score were 2.03 times higher when aged younger than 50 years, 2.18 times higher when they found opioids less helpful in relieving pain, and 2.64 times higher when they had a high PEG score. Approximately one-third of respondents had experienced &#x02265;4 problems or concerns attributed to opioid pain medicines, while also reporting limited pain relief and/or high pain intensity and interference.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T7"><label>Table 7</label><caption><p>Associations between respondent characteristics and problems and concerns score.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="3" colspan="1">Characteristic</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Problems and concerns</th><th rowspan="3" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic><xref rid="tblfn5" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref><break/>Chi-square</th><th rowspan="3" colspan="1">OR</th><th rowspan="3" colspan="1">95% CI</th></tr><tr><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Med-high score (4&#x02013;15)</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Low score (0&#x02013;3)</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex (n = 605)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Female</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">161</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.1</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">204</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.9</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.032</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Male</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.3</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">123</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (n = 610)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x0003c;50 y</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005<xref rid="tblfn6" ref-type="table-fn">&#x02020;</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25&#x02013;3.29</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02265;50 y</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">241</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.6</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">288</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration of opioid use (n = 614)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02264;3 y</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">102</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.5</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">122</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.5</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.357</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x0003e;3 y</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">194</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.7</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">196</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PEG score (n = 612)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;High (7&#x02013;10)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">232</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.2</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">181</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.8</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001<xref rid="tblfn6" ref-type="table-fn">&#x02020;</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.85&#x02013;3.77</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Low to medium (0&#x02013;6)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">65</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.7</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">134</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">How helpful found opioids in relieving pain ? (n = 614)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Not at all/a little/moderately</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">203</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.1</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">159</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.9</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001<xref rid="tblfn6" ref-type="table-fn">&#x02020;</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.57&#x02013;3.04</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Very/extremely</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">93</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.9</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">159</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other" id="tblfn5"><label>*</label><p>With Yates' continuity correction.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="tblfn6"><label>&#x02020;</label><p>Reduced to <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01 via Bonferroni adjustment.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>PEG, pain intensity, interference with enjoyment, and interference with general activity.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><title>4. Discussion</title><p>In this population of primary care patients, almost 80 percent reported at least one problem or concern attributed to prescribed opioids and over 20 percent reported 8 or more, highlighting the frequent occurrence of difficulties. Almost all reported opioids were helpful in relieving pain to some extent, but more than half reported they were only moderately, or a little helpful, and only half reported opioids had definitely or probably relieved pain as much as they expected in the past month. To our knowledge, this is the first study to assess opioid difficulties using the PODS for the entire duration of prescribing, providing valuable new insights into the problems and concerns of patients from their perspective.</p><p>Problems related to drowsiness or sedation were the most frequently reported, experienced by approximately 45% of respondents. This finding was consistent with other literature indicating these side effects are observed in 20% to 60% of patients using opioids.<sup><xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> The impact of these side effects on daily life was highlighted by a similar proportion of respondents reporting drowsiness affecting their ability to be alert at times when they needed to be. Approximately 30% of respondents also reported opioids affecting concentration and memory, or the ability to think clearly, demonstrating further impact on daily activities and function. However, the proportion of respondents reporting side effects as very or extremely bothersome was lower at 12.3%, offering an insight into patient perceptions of these issues.</p><p>Opioid concerns relating to tolerance, dependence, or addiction were the most frequently reported. Almost half (46.0%) reported needing to increase the dose to get the same effect. This is interesting when considered in relation to current NICE guidance for medicines associated with dependence, published during the data collection period of this study.<sup><xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup> Guidance recommends prescribers should avoid automatically increasing the dose if the response is not sustained because reduced benefit is rarely due to pharmacological tolerance and the risk of harmful prescribing is increased. Nearly a third (31.1%) reported times when they wanted to stop or cut down the amount of opioid used. More respondents were worried they might be dependent on, or addicted to, opioids (35.7%) than reported not being able to control how much or how often they needed them (19.5%) or had been preoccupied with or thought constantly about them (18.1%). A previous survey in the United Kingdom and Ireland of people using codeine identified 17.1% of respondents as dependent using the Severity of Dependence Scale,<sup><xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup> a similar proportion to the dependence-related behaviours observed in this research. The levels of agreement we identified were higher than those reported in previous research using the PODS but followed a similar pattern of frequency across questions.<sup><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="R52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref></sup> This difference may be in part because difficulties were reported for the entire time opioids were prescribed.</p><p>Four in 5 respondents had used opioids every day for the past 2 weeks. Guidance on opioid use from the United Kingdom advises some patients may experience good pain relief when opioids are used intermittently.<sup><xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> However, in this study, we did not find an association between nondaily use and how helpful respondents found opioids in relieving pain. A significant association was identified between pain intensity and interference (PEG score) and how helpful respondents found opioids in relieving their pain. High PEG scores were associated with finding opioids less helpful compared with low and medium PEG scores. Further analysis of the individual PEG domains (Supplemental Fig. 1, <ext-link xlink:href="http://links.lww.com/PR9/A284" ext-link-type="uri">http://links.lww.com/PR9/A284</ext-link>) revealed the strongest association occurred between pain intensity and helpfulness. This study did not measure respondents experience of pain both with and without opioids. Therefore, we were unable to determine if patients with a high PEG score are less likely to respond to opioids, or if PEG scores remain high because opioids are not effective in treating pain in some patients. Approximately one in 6 respondents who found opioids very or extremely helpful reported a low to medium PEG score. However, more than a third of respondents with a high PEG score reported opioids were very or extremely useful in relieving their pain. This finding may be helpful in understanding why it can be difficult for patients to agree to opioid reductions even when the effect on pain intensity is limited. Previous studies in the United States have found no relationship between perceived helpfulness and pain severity or physical function scores, although these involved specific patient groups or conditions where opioids were expected to be less useful.<sup><xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> Systematic reviews of opioid use have reported short-term efficacy in some patient groups and weak evidence for clinically significant pain relief in long-term use, with lower certainty for strong opioids.<sup><xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,<xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></sup> Many studies within these reviews also show a significant proportion of people taking opioids report high pain intensity. However, as highlighted above, there remains a gap in understanding the experience of pain when treated with opioids. The large level of reported helpfulness observed in this study was perhaps unexpected but may be explained by several factors. This study did not directly assess reductions in pain intensity, only patient perceptions of how helpful they found opioids in relieving pain over the past month. Patient perceptions of helpfulness may therefore have included very small changes in pain or improvements in issues associated with pain, such as sleep. Patients may also have had concerns about their opioid prescription being withdrawn, and worsening pain, if they reported opioids as less helpful. Where patients describe opioids as helpful, understanding the components of this is important to guide monitoring and support for these medicines.</p><p>Several studies have shown opioids are prescribed more frequently to female patients and this was observed in the respondent demographics of this research.<sup><xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup> However, we did not identify any further association between sex and the experience of opioid difficulties. Younger respondents, those who found opioids less helpful in relieving pain, and those reporting higher pain intensity and interference were associated with a greater number of problems and concerns. Previous research conducted in the United Kingdom has shown an association between younger age and opioid dependence,<sup><xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup> and our study indicates this association may be extended to other opioid difficulties.</p><sec id="s4-1"><title>4.1. Strengths and limitations</title><p>Although primary care practices recruited to this study were located within one geographical region, the sample is representative of people prescribed opioids for noncancer pain in England, over a period of at least 3 months, with respect to age, sex, and ethnicity.<sup><xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="R50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></sup> The study design enabled all eligible patients prescribed opioids at each participating practice to be identified and invited to take part, and a range of practices were recruited to the study with respect to socioeconomic factors. The survey response rate was modest at 20.1% but was consistent with the conservative estimate used in the study design and within the typical range for postal surveys.<sup><xref rid="R49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></sup> Nonresponse to individual questions was low, ranging from 0.2% to 2.9%, with no systematic omissions.</p><p>We were unable to determine if the sample characteristics of responders differed from nonresponders because of the ethical requirement for practice-held information about eligible patients to remain confidential. For the same reason, data on the type of opioid prescribed to participants were not available to the research team, and participants were not asked to provide this information. We recognise that having a general idea about the type of opioid prescribed could have been useful as harms are known to increase with higher morphine equivalent dose.<sup><xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> Our aim was to assess the extent of difficulties in a real-world population, and it would have been difficult to accurately associate the opioid type and amount used with the point at which difficulties occurred. The proportion of respondents prescribed opioids for more than 3 years in the sample was larger than reported figures for England.<sup><xref rid="R50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></sup> There was potential for recruitment bias towards patients who had experienced difficulties with opioids and for whom pain had a greater impact on daily life. Recall bias may also have occurred because of the length of time some respondents had been prescribed opioids. It is also possible that the cause of difficulties experienced may not always have been opioids or solely because of opioids. Considering study strengths and limitations, we believe the results may be cautiously generalised.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s5"><title>5. Conclusion</title><p>This research identified opioid difficulties were frequently experienced by patients prescribed opioid pain medicines and regular monitoring of problems after prescribing may be needed. These findings can be used to inform future work to identify pain diagnoses, comorbidities, and prescribing indicators associated with opioid difficulties. Our findings also highlight opportunities and challenges for reducing opioid prescribing. We identified a substantial proportion of patients who have wanted to stop or cut down their opioid use and/or experienced multiple difficulties with little perceived benefit. These patients may respond more positively towards opioid reductions. However, a considerable proportion of patients in this study reported opioids were helpful in relieving pain, irrespective of the extent of difficulties experienced or the current intensity of pain. Persuading patients to reduce opioid use in these circumstances is more challenging. A person-centred approach to pain management is essential as individual experiences, expectations, and perceived benefits of using opioid medicines can vary significantly.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Disclosures</title><p>A. J. Avery is National Clinical Director for Prescribing for NHS England. The remaining authors have no conflict of interest to declare.</p></sec><sec><title>Appendix A. Supplemental digital content</title><supplementary-material position="float" content-type="local-data"><p>Supplemental digital content associated with this article can be found online at <ext-link xlink:href="http://links.lww.com/PR9/A283" ext-link-type="uri">http://links.lww.com/PR9/A283</ext-link>, and <ext-link xlink:href="http://links.lww.com/PR9/A284" ext-link-type="uri">http://links.lww.com/PR9/A284</ext-link>.</p></supplementary-material></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="SD1" position="float" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIAL</title></caption><media xlink:href="painreports-10-e1246-s001.pdf" id="d67e2038" position="anchor"/><media xlink:href="painreports-10-e1246-s002.pdf" id="d67e2039" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>The authors thank the primary care practices who supported the recruitment of participants for this research during the COVID-19 pandemic, and all respondents for completing the questionnaire. The authors acknowledge the input of NIHR Clinical Research Network East Midlands for practice recruitment support, Antony Chuter as PPI representative, and Pamela Pepper for administrative support. This work was supported by a doctoral studentship held by L.E.W. (cofunded by the University of Nottingham and Boots United Kingdom) and a National Institute for Health Research (NIHR) Senior Investigator Award held by A.J.A. (NF-SI-0617-10076). The views expressed are those of the authors and not necessarily those of the National Health Service, NIHR, or Boots United Kingdom. The data set generated in this research can be made available upon request.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>Sponsorships or competing interests that may be relevant to content are disclosed at the end of this article.</p></fn><fn fn-type="supplementary-material"><p>Supplemental digital content is available for this article. Direct URL citations appear in the printed text and are provided in the HTML and PDF versions of this article on the journal's Web site (<ext-link xlink:href="http://journals.lww.com/painrpts/pages/default.aspx" ext-link-type="uri">www.painrpts.com</ext-link>).</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>[1]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>British Pain Society, Faculty of Pain Medicine</collab>. <source>Outcome measures</source>, <year>2019</year>. Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.britishpainsociety.org/static/uploads/resources/files/Outcome_Measures_January_2019.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.britishpainsociety.org/static/uploads/resources/files/Outcome_Measures_January_2019.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed January 05, 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>[2]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><source>CFH Docmail ltd</source>. Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.cfh.com/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cfh.com/</ext-link>. Accessed March 31, 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>[3]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>East Midlands Academic Health Science Network</collab>. <source>Medicines safety improvement programme (MedSIP)</source>. Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://emahsn.org.uk/our-work/patient-safety/medicines-safety-improvement-programme/1247-medicines-safety-improvement-programme" ext-link-type="uri">https://emahsn.org.uk/our-work/patient-safety/medicines-safety-improvement-programme/1247-medicines-safety-improvement-programme</ext-link>. Accessed April 04, 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>[4]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><source>The NHS constitution for England</source>. Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-nhs-constitution-for-england/the-nhs-constitution-for-england" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-nhs-constitution-for-england/the-nhs-constitution-for-england</ext-link>. Accessed November 07, 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>[5]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>NHS England</collab>. <source>Optimising personalised care for adults prescribed medicines associated with dependence or withdrawal symptoms: framework for action for integrated care boards (ICBs) and primary care</source>, <year>2023</year>. Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.england.nhs.uk/long-read/optimising-personalised-care-for-adults-prescribed-medicines-associated-with-dependence-or-withdrawal-symptoms/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.england.nhs.uk/long-read/optimising-personalised-care-for-adults-prescribed-medicines-associated-with-dependence-or-withdrawal-symptoms/</ext-link>. Accessed January 12, 2024.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>[6]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>NIHR</surname><given-names>CRN</given-names></name></person-group> East Midlands, <volume>2023</volume>. <comment>Available at:</comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://local.nihr.ac.uk/lcrn/east-midlands/[Accessed31/03/2023]" ext-link-type="uri">https://local.nihr.ac.uk/lcrn/east-midlands/[Accessed 31/03/2023]</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>[7]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>Office for Health Improvement and Disparities</collab>. <source>National general practice profiles</source>. Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://fingertips.phe.org.uk/profile/general-practice" ext-link-type="uri">https://fingertips.phe.org.uk/profile/general-practice</ext-link>. Accessed October, 2021 to June, 2022.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>[8]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>PROMPPT</collab>. <source>Proactive clinical review of patients taking opioid medicines for persistent pain led by clinical pharmacists in primary care teams</source>. Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.promppt.co.uk/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.promppt.co.uk/</ext-link>. Accessed April 04, 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>[9]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>When to use the Bonferroni correction</article-title>. <source>Ophthalmic Physiol Opt</source>
<year>2014</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>502</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24697967</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>[10]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rosser</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nanda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Martucci</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Contributions of pain interference and affect to patient-reported opioid benefit in chronic pain management</article-title>. <source>medRxiv preprint</source>
<year>2022</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>[11]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Banta-Green</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Von Korff</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Merrill</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Doyle</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Saunders</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The prescribed opioids difficulties scale: a patient-centered assessment of problems and concerns</article-title>. <source>Clin J Pain</source>
<year>2010</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>489</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20551723</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>[12]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bedson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ashworth</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hayward</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Risk of adverse events in patients prescribed long-term opioids: a cohort study in the UK Clinical Practice Research Datalink</article-title>. <source>Eur J Pain</source>
<year>2019</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>908</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>22</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30620116</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>[13]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Busse</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Craigie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Juurlink</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Buckley</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Couban</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Agoritsas</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Akl</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carrasco-Labra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cull</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Da Costa</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Iorio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Persaud</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tugwell</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vandvik</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guyatt</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Guideline for opioid therapy and chronic noncancer pain</article-title>. <source>CMAJ</source>
<year>2017</year>;<volume>189</volume>:<fpage>E659</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>E666</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28483845</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>[14]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Noghrehchi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Clare</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bruno</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lintzeris</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Blyth</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Larance</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hungerford</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dobbins</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Farrell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Degenhardt</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Risk factors for indicators of opioid-related harms amongst people living with chronic non-cancer pain: findings from a 5-year prospective cohort study</article-title>. <source>EClinicalMedicine</source>
<year>2020</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>100592</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33294810</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>[15]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chaparro</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Furlan</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Deshpande</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mailis-Gagnon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Atlas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Turk</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Opioids compared with placebo or other treatments for chronic low back pain: an update of the cochrane review</article-title>. <source>Spine (Phila PA 1976)</source>
<year>2014</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>556</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>63</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24480962</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>[16]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cherny</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ripamonti</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fallon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McQuay</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mercadante</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pasternak</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ventafridda</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Strategies to manage the adverse effects of oral morphine: an evidence-based report</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source>
<year>2001</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>2542</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>54</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11331334</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>[17]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Devine</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Blazina</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dana</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bougatsos</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Deyo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The effectiveness and risks of long-term opioid therapy for chronic pain: a systematic review for a national institutes of health pathways to prevention workshop</article-title>. <source>Ann Intern Med</source>
<year>2015</year>;<volume>162</volume>:<fpage>276</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25581257</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>[18]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Willis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fuller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Benecke</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Leighton-Scott</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Andersohn</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Knaggs</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence and incidence trends for diagnosed prescription opioid use disorders in the United Kingdom</article-title>. <source>Pain Ther</source>
<year>2017</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>73</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>84</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28451867</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>[19]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Curtis</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Croker</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Quinlan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goldacre</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Opioid prescribing trends and geographical variation in England, 1998&#x02013;2018: a retrospective database study</article-title>. <source>Lancet Psychiatry</source>
<year>2019</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>140</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>50</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30580987</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>[20]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Degenhardt</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Grebely</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hickman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vickerman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>BDL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bruneau</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Altice</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rahimi-Movaghar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Larney</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Global patterns of opioid use and dependence: harms to populations, interventions, and future action</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>
<year>2019</year>;<volume>394</volume>:<fpage>1560</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>79</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31657732</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>[21]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dowell</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ragan</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>CDC clinical practice guideline for prescribing opioids for pain&#x02014;United States, 2022</article-title>. <source>MMWR Recomm Rep</source>
<year>2022</year>;<volume>71</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>95</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>[22]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Els</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kunyk</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lappi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sonnenberg</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hagtvedt</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kolandooz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Straube</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Adverse events associated with medium- and long-term use of opioids for chronic non-cancer pain: an overview of Cochrane Reviews</article-title>. <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source>
<year>2017</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>10</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>[23]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Discovering statistics using IBM SPSS statistics</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>, <year>2018</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>[24]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>FPM</collab>. <article-title>Opioids Aware: a resource for patients and healthcare professionals to support prescribing of opioid medicines for pain</article-title>. Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://fpm.ac.uk/opioids-aware:FacultyofPainMedicineoftheRoyalCollegeofAnaesthetists" ext-link-type="uri">https://fpm.ac.uk/opioids-aware:FacultyofPainMedicineoftheRoyalCollegeofAnaesthetists</ext-link>. Accessed January 19, 2024.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>[25]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Furlan</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sandoval</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mailis-Gagnon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tunks</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Opioids for chronic noncancer pain: a meta-analysis of effectiveness and side effects</article-title>. <source>CMAJ</source>
<year>2006</year>;<volume>174</volume>:<fpage>1589</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>94</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16717269</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>[26]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goesling</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moser</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hassett</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wasserman</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brummett</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Discrepancies between perceived benefit of opioids and self-reported patient outcomes</article-title>. <source>Pain Med</source>
<year>2018</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>297</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>306</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28034978</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>[27]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>H&#x000e4;user</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bock</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Engeser</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>T&#x000f6;lle</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Willweber-Strumpfe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Petzke</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Long-term opioid use in non-cancer pain</article-title>. <source>Dtsch Arztebl Int</source>
<year>2014</year>;<volume>111</volume>:<fpage>732</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>40</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25404530</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>[28]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Howe</surname><given-names>CQ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Saunders</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Merrill</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Banta-Green</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weisner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Von Korff</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Depression and ambivalence toward chronic opioid therapy for chronic noncancer pain</article-title>. <source>Clin J Pain</source>
<year>2012</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>561</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22699127</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>[29]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Birlie Yimer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sheppard</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lunt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Time trends and prescribing patterns of opioid drugs in UK primary care patients with non-cancer pain: a retrospective cohort study</article-title>. <source>PLoS Med</source>
<year>2020</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>e1003270</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33057368</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>[30]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kardell</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hilmer</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Crane</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>MacPherson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gnjidic</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Investigation of opioid prescribing in the postoperative setting among opioid-na&#x000ef;ve surgical patients: a 6-month observational study</article-title>. <source>J Pharm Pract Res</source>
<year>2019</year>;<volume>49</volume>:<fpage>58</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>61</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>[31]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kimerg&#x000e5;rd</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Foley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Davey</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dunne</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Drummond</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Deluca</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Codeine use, dependence and help-seeking behaviour in the UK and Ireland: an online cross-sectional survey</article-title>. <source>QJM</source>
<year>2017</year>;<volume>110</volume>:<fpage>559</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>64</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28379496</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>[32]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krebs</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lorenz</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bair</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Damush</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sutherland</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Asch</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kroenke</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Development and initial validation of the PEG, a three-item scale assessing pain intensity and interference</article-title>. <source>J Gen Intern Med</source>
<year>2009</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>733</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19418100</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>[33]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Larance</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bruno</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lintzeris</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mattick</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>O'Donnell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Degenhardt</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Concerns and help-seeking among patients using opioids for management of chronic noncancer pain</article-title>. <source>Pain Med</source>
<year>2019</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>758</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>69</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29762767</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>[34]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Likert</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A technique for the measurement of attitudes</article-title>. <source>Arch Psychol</source>
<year>1932</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>55</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>[35]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Macfarlane</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Beasley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stannard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The epidemiology of regular opioid use and its association with mortality: prospective cohort study of 466 486 UK biobank participants</article-title>. <source>EClinicalMedicine</source>
<year>2020</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>10</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>[36]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Merrill</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Von Korff</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Banta-Green</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Saunders</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weisner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prescribed opioid difficulties, depression and opioid dose among chronic opioid therapy patients</article-title>. <source>Gen Hosp Psychiatry</source>
<year>2012</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>581</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>87</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22959422</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>[37]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>NICE</collab>. <source>CG150 headaches in over 12s: Diagnosis and management</source>; <year>2012</year>. Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/cg150" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/cg150</ext-link>. Accessed January 19, 2024.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>[38]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>NICE</collab>. <source>CG173 neuropathic pain in adults: Pharmacological management in non-specialist settings</source>; <year>2013</year>. Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/cg173" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/cg173</ext-link>. Accessed January 19, 2024.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>[39]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>NICE</collab>. <source>NG59 low back pain and sciatica in over 16s: Assessment and management</source>, <year>2016</year>. Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/ng59" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/ng59</ext-link>. Accessed January 19, 2024.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>[40]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>NICE</collab>. <source>NG180 Perioperative care in adults</source>; <year>2020</year>. Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/ng180" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/ng180</ext-link>. Accessed January 19, 2024.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>[41]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>NICE</collab>. <source>NG193 chronic pain (primary and secondary) in over 16s: Assessment of all chronic pain and management of chronic primary pain</source>, <year>2021</year>. Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/ng193" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/ng193</ext-link>. Accessed January 19, 2024.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>[42]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>NICE</collab>. <source>NG215 medicines associated with dependence or withdrawal symptoms: Safe prescribing and withdrawal management for adults</source>, <year>2022</year>. Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/ng215" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/ng215</ext-link>. Accessed May, 07 2024.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>[43]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>NICE</collab>. <source>NG226 osteoarthritis in over 16s: diagnosis and management</source>, <year>2022</year>. Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/ng226" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/ng226</ext-link>. Accessed January 19, 2024.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><label>[44]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Noble</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Treadwell</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tregear</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Coates</surname><given-names>VH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wiffen</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Akafomo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schoelles</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Erskine</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Long-term opioid management for chronic noncancer pain</article-title>. <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source>
<year>2010</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>232</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><label>[45]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nury</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schmucker</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nagavci</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Motschall</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nitschke</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schulte</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wegwarth</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Meerpohl</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Efficacy and safety of strong opioids for chronic noncancer pain and chronic low back pain: a systematic review and meta-analyses</article-title>. <source>PAIN</source>
<year>2022</year>;<volume>163</volume>:<fpage>610</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>36</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34326292</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><label>[46]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petzke</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bock</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hueppe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nothacker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Norda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Radbruch</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schiltenwolf</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schuler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Toelle</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Viniol</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hauser</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Long-term opioid therapy for chronic noncancer pain: second update of the German guidelines</article-title>. <source>Pain Rep</source>
<year>2020</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>e840</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32904018</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><label>[47]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sandhu</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Booth</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Furlan</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carnes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>SJC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alleyne</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Balasubramanian</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Betteley</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Haywood</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Iglesias-Urrutia</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Krishnan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lall</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Manca</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mistry</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Newton</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Noyes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Padfield</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Seers</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>NKY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tysall</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eldabe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Underwood</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Reducing opioid use for chronic pain with a group-based intervention: a randomized clinical trial</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>
<year>2023</year>;<volume>329</volume>:<fpage>1745</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>56</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37219554</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><label>[48]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kesten</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bache</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hickman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pickering</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Redwood</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of a primary care-based opioid and pain review service: a mixed-methods evaluation in two GP practices in England</article-title>. <source>Br J Gen Pract</source>
<year>2020</year>;<volume>70</volume>:<fpage>e111</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>e119</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31791939</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><label>[49]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stedman</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Connelly</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Heberlein</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Decker</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Allred</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The end of the (research) world as we know it? Understanding and coping with declining response rates to mail surveys</article-title>. <source>Soc Nat Resour</source>
<year>2019</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>1139</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>54</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><label>[50]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Annand</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Burkinshaw</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Greaves</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kelleher</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Perkins</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>White</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marsden</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Dependence and withdrawal associated with some prescribed medicines</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Public Health England</publisher-name>, <year>2019</year>. Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://assets.publishing.service.gov.uk/media/5fc658398fa8f5474c800149/PHE_PMR_report_Dec2020.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://assets.publishing.service.gov.uk/media/5fc658398fa8f5474c800149/PHE_PMR_report_Dec2020.pdf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><label>[51]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>TGA</collab>. <article-title>Prescription opioids: information for health professionals</article-title>; <year>2021</year>. Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.tga.gov.au/resources/resource/guidance/prescription-opioids-information-health-professionals" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.tga.gov.au/resources/resource/guidance/prescription-opioids-information-health-professionals</ext-link>. Accessed June 15, 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R52"><label>[52]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thielke</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shortreed</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Saunders</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Leresche</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weisner</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Korff</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Do patient-perceived pros and cons of opioids predict sustained higher-dose use?</article-title>
<source>Clin J Pain</source>
<year>2014</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>93</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>101</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23535150</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>