<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Res Rep Urol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Res Rep Urol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">rru</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Research and Reports in Urology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2253-2447</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11681773</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">487854</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/RRU.S487854</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Knowledge of Male Infertility and Acceptance of Medical Assistance Reproductive Technology Among Fertile and Infertile Senegalese Men</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Gaye et al</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Gaye et al</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8873-9560</contrib-id><name><surname>Gaye</surname><given-names>Oumar</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ba</surname><given-names>Khadidiatou</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Diallo</surname><given-names>Mouhamed</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Niasse</surname><given-names>Awa</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Counta</surname><given-names>Amdy Laye</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ndiaye</surname><given-names>Modou</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gning</surname><given-names>Moustapha</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gueye</surname><given-names>Ablaye</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fall</surname><given-names>Papa Ahmed</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Urology Department of Dalal Jamm Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Dakar</addr-line>, <country>Senegal</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Oumar Gaye, <institution>Urology Department of Dalal Jamm Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Dakar</addr-line>, <addr-line>21346</addr-line>, <country>Senegal</country>, <phone content-type="general">Tel +221776190954</phone>, Email oumargaye-uro@outlook.fr</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>24</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><fpage>343</fpage><lpage>355</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>7</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2024 Gaye et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Gaye et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is published by Dove Medical Press Limited, and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution License. The full terms of the License are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The license permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Purpose</title><p>The objective of our study was to examine the knowledge of male infertility and the acceptance of assisted reproductive technology (ART) methods.</p></sec><sec><title>Patients and Methods</title><p>We conducted a descriptive, comparative, cross-sectional study from April 2023 to August 2023 in a center in Dakar. Included in the study were male patients aged 18 and older followed for male infertility (group 1) and fertile patients of the same age as those in group 1 (group 2). We designed a questionnaire assessing the sociodemographic characteristics of the respondents, their knowledge of male infertility, knowledge of ART, its acceptability, and the source of information about male infertility.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Our sample size consisted of 119 respondents for each group. The average age of respondents in both groups was 41.24 &#x000b1; 8.42 years. Fifty-eight percent of respondents in group 1 were referred by their wife&#x02019;s gynecologist. Fifty-four percent of respondents in group 1&#x000a0;had a good knowledge of male infertility, and 42.86% had average knowledge of male infertility. The majority of respondents in group 1 (42.9%) and group 2 (40.3%) did not know the duration that defines infertility. Fifty-seven percent of respondents in Group 1 and 81.5% of respondents in Group 2 did not know what assisted reproductive technology meant. Eighty-six percent of respondents in Group 1 agreed to use ART for procreation. The majority of respondents in Group 1 (54.6%) and Group 2 (58.8%) attributed a success rate of between 35% and 75% to ART.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Infertile men had better knowledge of male fertility than fertile men. Respondents in both groups, as well as the advanced age of men did not know the duration defining infertility. Poor knowledge of ART was also observed among respondents in both groups, and a better acceptance of ART methods was noted among infertile men.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>knowledge</kwd><kwd>male infertility</kwd><kwd>assisted reproductive technology</kwd><kwd>awareness</kwd><kwd>Senegal</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>no funding to report</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>There is no funding to report.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="4"/><table-count count="5"/><ref-count count="30"/><page-count count="13"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001"><title>Introduction</title><p>Infertility is defined as the inability to conceive a child after a year of regular, unprotected sexual intercourse. The prevalence of infertility is approximately 15% among couples,<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> with a male factor identified in about 60% of cases. However, socio-cultural considerations of masculinity create psychosocial barriers to seeking professional health care.<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> In Africa, women are often held responsible for infertility,<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> despite best practice guidelines recommending that the initial assessment of a couple&#x02019;s infertility be conducted simultaneously in both men and women.<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> Moreover, infertility, recognized as a disease by the WHO,<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> continues to be viewed within several African societies as the consequence of supernatural manifestations, such as evil spirits, witchcraft, or divine punishment.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></p><p>Lifestyle factors such as obesity, diet, smoking, excessive alcohol consumption, and environmental chemical exposures<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> can impair male fertility. Thus, education on fertility issues is essential to avoid delays in seeking care and/or behaviors that impair fertility.<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> This underpins the emphasis on lifestyle modifications in the new approaches to managing male infertility, thereby reducing the reliance on Assisted Reproductive Technology (ART).<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> However, studies evaluating men&#x02019;s knowledge of fertility are scarce, with most fertility knowledge studies conducted among women.</p><p>Despite the effectiveness of lifestyle changes in managing male infertility, ART remains a significant therapeutic means, enabling many couples to conceive.<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> Nonetheless, access to and acceptability of ART are influenced by religious, cultural, political, and economic factors. The perspectives of different religions or cultures on ART vary greatly, affecting its acceptability. Additionally, its high cost, in a context of no social coverage or insurance, renders it inaccessible for most patients living in Africa.<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></p><p>Given the importance of understanding male infertility factors for the preservation or restoration of male fertility, and since the acceptance of ART depends on factors such as religion or cost, it is necessary to evaluate these in Senegal, especially since this topic has been little studied in men in the literature.</p><p>Thus, our study aimed to assess the knowledge of male infertility and the acceptance of ART methods among fertile and infertile Senegalese men.</p></sec><sec id="s0002"><title>Patients and Methods</title><sec id="s0002-s2001"><title>Type and Period of Study</title><p>This was a descriptive, comparative, and cross-sectional study aimed at evaluating the knowledge of male infertility and the acceptability of Assisted Reproductive Technologies (ART) among fertile and infertile patients followed at a university hospital in Dakar from April 2023 to August 2023.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2002"><title>Population</title><p>The included patients were those followed for male infertility, aged 18 years and older, at the urology service of a university hospital in Dakar from January 2019 to December 2022 (Group 1). The control group (Group 2) consisted of patients or companions of fertile patients without chronic pathology of the same age as the patients in Group 1, followed in outpatient consultation. Patients who did not have the faculties allowing them to understand and/or respond to the questionnaire were not included in the study. Among the 180 patients followed for male infertility in the urology-andrology service, 148 patients could be contacted. Among them, 139 patients had agreed to respond to the questionnaire, and the data from the first 20 respondents were used to evaluate the understanding of the questionnaire (<xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). In total, 119 infertile patients were included (Group 1) and compared to 119 control respondents of the same age (Group 2).
<fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Distribution diagram of infertile respondents included in the study.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="RRU-16-343-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2003"><title>Questionnaire</title><p>We designed a questionnaire based on previously published works on male infertility.<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13&#x02013;15</xref> This questionnaire was written in French and translated into Wolof (the national language of Senegal). The terms used were meticulously chosen according to the national dictionary to facilitate understanding of the questions. The questionnaire included 4 parts:
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p>The first part of the questionnaire consisted of questions specifying the sociodemographic characteristics of the respondents (age of respondents, age of their wives, marital status, duration of marriage, type of infertility, educational level, religion, culture, occupation&#x02026;).</p></list-item><list-item><p>The second part of the questionnaire consisted of questions assessing the knowledge of modifiable factors promoting male infertility (tobacco use, drug, and alcohol consumption, pathologies favoring male infertility such as diabetes, obesity, and genetic disease.)., the duration defining infertility, the period of female fertility, the perception of infertility as a disease (or due to a curse or a djinn). Responses were scored a 1 if the respondents had given the correct answer and 0 when an incorrect answer was given. For the 18 questions, a total score ranging from 0 to 18 could be assigned to each respondent. This total score allowed us to individualize 3 classes: poor knowledge (0 to 6), average knowledge (7 to 12), and good knowledge (13 to 18).</p></list-item><list-item><p>The third part of the questionnaire consisted of questions assessing the knowledge of ART (definition, cost, availability, accessibility, legal framework of ART with gamete donation in Senegal.), and its acceptability (with their gametes, with gamete donation, sperm or embryo conservation) or that of child adoption in case of failure or refusal of the latter.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The fourth part of the questionnaire specified the source of information of the respondents on male infertility (internet, doctor, family, friends).</p></list-item></list></p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2004"><title>Definitions</title><sec id="s0002-s2004-s3001"><title>Educational Level</title><p>Primary (Preschool&#x02014;Elementary school), Secondary (College and high school), Tertiary (University or other post-secondary education)</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2004-s3002"><title>Ethnicity</title><p>Senegal has multiple ethnic groups, the biggest ones being the Wolofs, the Fulanis, the Sereers and the Joolas.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2004-s3003"><title>Currency</title><p>The West African French franc (XOF) was the currency used to report the monthly salary of respondents.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2004-s3004"><title>Obedience</title><p>Religious brotherhoods or denominations in Senegal [Muslim (Tidianes, Mourides, Khadr&#x02026;) and Christians (Catholics et Protestants)].</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2004-s3005"><title>Djinns</title><p>Supernatural beings in African culture thought to be responsible for curses and misfortunes.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0002-s2005"><title>Application of the Questionnaire to Respondents</title><p>Two investigators (Ms. K Ba and Mr. A Counta) were trained to reduce the bias of understanding the questions by the respondents. The two investigators applied the questionnaire to each participant interviewed for about 20&#x000a0;minutes.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2006"><title>Data Collection</title><p>Data from the questionnaire applied to respondents were collected on an online platform named &#x0201c;Kobotoolbox.&#x0201d;</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2007"><title>Statistical Analyses</title><p>The software SPSS version 2.0 was used for analyses. Associations were evaluated using the chi-squared test. A p-value of &#x02264; 0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2008"><title>Ethical Considerations</title><p>Informed consent was obtained from all participants before the interview. Participants had the right to withdraw from the study without explaining to the research team. Confidentiality of the obtained data was guaranteed.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0003"><title>Results</title><sec id="s0003-s2001"><title>Sociodemographic Characteristics of Respondents (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>)</title><p>The average age of respondents in both groups was 41.24 &#x000b1; 8.42 years (ranging from 24 to 61 years). Age groups between 30 to 40 years and 40 to 50 years were predominant, respectively, in 37% and 37.8% of cases. The average age of the wives of Group 1 respondents was 31.79 &#x000b1; 7.5 (ranging from 18 to 55 years), and for Group 2 respondents, it was 32.82 &#x000b1; 7.52 (ranging from 20 to 55 years). Eighty-four percent of Group 1 respondents and 85.7% of Group 2 respondents were married under monogamous arrangements. Infertility was primary in 79% of the cases for Group 1 respondents. Their wife&#x02019;s gynecologist referred Fifty-eight percent of Group 1 respondents.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Comparison of Sociodemographic Characteristics of the Two Groups</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Group</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">P</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group 1 n (%)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group 2 n (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Age of respondents (years)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="6" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (7.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (7.6)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[30&#x02013;40]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44 (37.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44 (37.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[40&#x02013;50]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 (37.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 (37.8)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[50&#x02013;60]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (16.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (16.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (1.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (1.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Age of spouses (years)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="6" colspan="1">0.489</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c; 20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (2.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[20&#x02013;30]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 (37.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 (34.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[30&#x02013;40]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56 (42.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55 (46.2)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[40&#x02013;50]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (16.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (16.8)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (1.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (2.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Type of marriage</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.855</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Monogamous</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">101 (84.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">102 (85.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Polygamous</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (15.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (14.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Duration of marriage (years)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">0.041</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c; 5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (29.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (19.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[5&#x02013;10]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 (41.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47 (39.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e; 10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (29.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 (41.2)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Type of infertility</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primary infertility</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">94 (79.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Secondary infertility</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (21.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Education level</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">0.22</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primary</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (14.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (16.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Secondary</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81 (68.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69 (58.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tertiary</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (17.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (26.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Religion</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="7" colspan="1">0.115</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Muslim</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">110 (92.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">115 (96.6)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Khadre</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (4.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (11.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mouride</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (41.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 (42.6)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tidiane</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53 (48.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 (34.8)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Others</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (5.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (11.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Christian</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (7.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (4.4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Catholics</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (100)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (75.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protestants</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (25.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Ethnicity</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="6" colspan="1">0.036*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wolof</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (38.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (30.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peul</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (21.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (21.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">S&#x000e9;r&#x000e8;re</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (11.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (7.6)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diolas</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (4.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.8)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Autres</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (23.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 (40.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Occupation</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.025*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unemployed</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (5.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (13.4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Employed</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">113 (95.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">103 (86.6)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Monthly income (FCFA)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="5" colspan="1">0.58</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;100,000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 (42.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (35.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100,000&#x02013;300,000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (11.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (11.8)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">300,000&#x02013;500,000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52 (41.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 (40.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;500,000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (2.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (12.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Health insurance</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.06</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99 (83.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">87 (73.1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (16.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 (26.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Reason for consultation</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Referred by wife&#x02019;s gynecologist</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69 (58)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spontaneously</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 (42)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: P-value found using a Chi2 test. *Significant statistical difference was found.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2002"><title>Assessment of Male Infertility Knowledge (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>)</title><p>Group 1 respondents had an average total knowledge score of male infertility of 12.49 &#x000b1; 3.42, and Group 2 respondents had an average total score of 10.97 &#x000b1; 4.41. Fifty-four percent of Group 1 respondents had good knowledge of male infertility (total score between 13 and 18), and 42.86% of Group 1 respondents had average knowledge of male infertility (total score between 7 and 12) (<xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>). Unlike Group 1 respondents, the majority of Group 2 respondents did not know that tobacco, drug use, and excessive alcohol consumption could impair male fertility. The majority of respondents from both groups knew that the use of anabolic steroids, exposure to certain toxic products, or taking certain medications could compromise male fertility. Most respondents from both groups did not recognize advanced age as a factor favoring male infertility. The majority of Group 1 respondents (42.9%) and Group 2 (40.3%) did not know that infertility is discussed after 12 months of unprotected sexual intercourse without conceiving.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Distribution of Respondents in the Two Groups According to Their Knowledge of Male Fertility</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group 1 n(%)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group 2 n(%)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Smoking</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84 (70.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 (37.8)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (29.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74 (62.2)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Drug use</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83 (69.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (38.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (30.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73 (61.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Excessive alcohol consumption</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">82 (68.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52 (43.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (31.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67 (56.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Advanced age of the man</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.141</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39 (32.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 (42.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80 (67.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69 (58.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Genital infection</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100 (84.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66 (55.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (16.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53 (44.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Genital malformation</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.122</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">103 (86.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">94 (79.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (13.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (21.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Obesity</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.76</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">92 (77.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90 (75.6)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (22.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (24.4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Genetic disease</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.275</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">96 (80.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">89 (74.8)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (19.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (25.2)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Heat exposure (job exposing to heat, tight underwear)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.075</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85 (71.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72 (60.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 (28.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47 (39.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Anabolic steroid use</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.458</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">91 (76.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86 (72.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (23.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (27.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Exposure to certain toxic products</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.07</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">88 (73.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75 (63.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (26.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44 (37.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Duration defining infertility</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.429</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (38.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52 (43.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73 (61.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67 (56.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Exposure to certain toxic products</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.685</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78 (65.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75 (63.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 (34.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44 (37.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Diabete</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.341</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oui</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81 (68.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74 (62.2)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (31.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 (37.8)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Period of fertility</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">0.367</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2&#x02013;3 days every month</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85 (71.43)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76 (63.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 days every month</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (26.05)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (35.29)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">All of the month</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (2.52)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.84)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Duration defining infertility</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="5" colspan="1">0.22</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (22.69)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 (33.61)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (18.49)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (15.97)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51 (42.86)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 (40.34)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (16.97)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (10.08)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Infertility is</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">0.219</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Due to djinns</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.84)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">116 (97.48)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">119 (100.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Due to a curse</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (1.68)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Infertility is curable</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.122</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">87 (73.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97 (81.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not sure</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 (26.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (18.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: P-value found using a Chi2 test. *Significant statistical difference was found.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Distribution of respondents in groups 1 and 2 according to their knowledge of infertility.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="RRU-16-343-g0002" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2003"><title>Assessment of Assisted Reproductive Technologies (ART) Knowledge</title><p>Fifty-seven percent of Group 1 respondents and 81.5% of Group 2 respondents did not know what Assisted Reproductive Technology (ART) meant (<xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). After explaining ART and its various methods, 65% of Group 2 respondents did not consider ART as a natural method (<xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). The majority of Group 1 (54.6%) and Group 2 (58.8%) respondents attributed an ART success rate between]35&#x02013;75%].<table-wrap position="float" id="t0003"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Distribution of Respondents in the Two Groups According to Their Acceptance of Assisted Reproductive Technology (ART) Methods</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group 1 n(%)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group 2 n(%)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Knowledge of ART</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51 (42.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (18.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c; 0.001*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68 (57.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97 (81.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Do you think that ART with egg/sperm donation is legal in Senegal?</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (14.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (4.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 (34.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68 (57.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c; 0.001*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uncertain</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61 (51.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (38.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Do you think that ART is a natural means?</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61 (51.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (10.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (17.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78 (65.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c; 0.001*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uncertain</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (31.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (24.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Is ART disponible in S&#x000e9;n&#x000e9;gal ?</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47 (39.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (20.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c; 0.001*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (7.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (21.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uncertain</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63 (52.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69 (58.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Do you think that ART is accessible to those who want it?</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 (45.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (14.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c; 0.001*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (4.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (20.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uncertain</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60 (50.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78 (65.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Does the advanced age of the man influence the success rate of ART?</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (22.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (12.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.047*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71 (59.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71 (59.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uncertain</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (17.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (27.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>What do you think of the cost of ART?</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cost</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58(48.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45(37.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uncertain</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59 (49.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74(62.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not cost</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2(1.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0(0.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Would you agree to carry out ART there?</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">103(86.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1(0.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16(13.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">118(99.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Would you do ART with sperm donation?</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24(20.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0(0.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81(68.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">101(84.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uncertain</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14(11.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18(15.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Would you do ART with egg donation?</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24(20.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1(0.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81(68.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100(84.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uncertain</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14(11.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18(15.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Would you do ART with your own sperm and your wife&#x02019;s egg?</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97(81.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1(0.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19(16.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99(83.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uncertain</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3(2.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19(16.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Would you preserve your sperm for possible future use?</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61(51.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1(0.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45(37.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">101(84.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uncertain</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13(10.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17(14.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>In case of multiple fertilization during ART, would you keep the eggs (embryos)?</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84(70.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1(0.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21(17.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">111(93.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uncertain</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14(11.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7(5.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: P-value found using a Chi2 test. *Significant statistical difference was found.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2004"><title>Assessment of Acceptance of ART Methods (<xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>)</title><p>Eighty-six percent of Group 1 respondents were willing to use ART methods for conception. Conversely, only 0.8% of Group 2 respondents agreed to use them. Twenty percent of Group 1 respondents were agreeable to undergoing ART with gamete donation. Fifty-one percent and 70.6% of Group 1 respondents were respectively agreeable to sperm conservation and embryo conservation in cases of multiple fertilized egg formation.</p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2005"><title>Assessment of Child Adoption Acceptance</title><p>Only 31.9% of Group 1 respondents and 25% of Group 2 respondents would agree to adopt a child as an alternative (<xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>).
<fig position="float" id="f0003" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Distribution of Group 1 and 2 respondents according to their acceptance of adoption of children.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="RRU-16-343-g0003" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2006"><title>Factors Favoring Knowledge of Male Infertility, ART, and Its Acceptance</title><p>The educational level of respondents from Group 1 influenced their level of knowledge of ART (p=0.018) (<xref rid="t0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). The educational level of respondents from Group 2 affected their knowledge of both infertility and ART (p=0.002 and p&#x0003c;0.001) (<xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>). However, religion, culture, or marriage duration did not influence the acceptance of ART and child adoption among respondents from both groups.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0004"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Factors Influencing Knowledge of Infertility and Acceptance of ART Methods Among Group 1 Respondents</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Religion</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Obedience</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethnicity</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Educational level</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patient age</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration of marriage</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Knowledge of infertility</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.793</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.841</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.175</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.018*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.861</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ART knowledge</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.169</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.044*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.519</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.088</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.331</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ART acceptance</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.347</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.255</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.854</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.391</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.452</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acceptance of sperm donation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.522</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.669</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.242</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.667</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.556</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acceptance of egg donation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.552</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.302</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.669</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.242</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.667</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.556</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adoption acceptance</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.311</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.725</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.462</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.778</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0004"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: P-value found using a Chi2 test. *Significant statistical difference was found. Obedience: Religious brotherhoods or denominations in Senegal [Muslim (Tidianes, Mourides, Khadr&#x02026;) and Christians (Catholics et Protestants)].</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<table-wrap position="float" id="t0005"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Factors Influencing Knowledge of Infertility and Acceptance of ART Methods Among Group 2 Respondents</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Religion</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Obedience</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethnicity</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Educational level</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patient age</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration of marriage</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Knowledge of infertility</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.603</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.219</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.353</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.561</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ART knowledge</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.314</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.979</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.348</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ART acceptance</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.966</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.595</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.015*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.694</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.751</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.462</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acceptance of sperm donation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acceptance of egg donation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adoption acceptance</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.098</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.282</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.417</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.328</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.757</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.757</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0005"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: P-value found using a Chi2 test. *Significant statistical difference was found Obedience: Religious brotherhoods or denominations in Senegal [Muslim (Tidianes, Mourides, Khadr&#x02026;) and Christians (Catholics et Protestants)].</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2007"><title>Evaluation of the Source of Information on Male Infertility Among Respondents</title><p>The internet was the most reported source of information on male infertility and ART by 62.7% and 68.2% of respondents from Groups 1 and 2, respectively (<xref rid="f0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>).
<fig position="float" id="f0004" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Distribution of respondents in groups 1 and 2 according to their source of information regarding male infertility.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="RRU-16-343-g0004" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="s0004"><title>Discussion</title><p>We interviewed 119 infertile men and 119 fertile men of the same age to compare their knowledge of male infertility and Assisted Reproductive Technology (ART). Few studies have focused on men&#x02019;s knowledge of their fertility. We found that infertile men had better knowledge of male fertility than fertile men did. Despite a relatively good understanding of most modifiable factors of male infertility by respondents from both groups, the duration defining infertility and advanced male age as a factor favoring male infertility were not known to the respondents. Additionally, a poor understanding of ART was observed among respondents from both groups, with a better acceptance of ART methods among infertile men (Group 1).</p><p>Their wife&#x02019;s gynecologist referred 58% of respondents from Group 1. Indeed, when a couple faces infertility, it is often the woman who is blamed, and men feel less concerned by infertility.<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> The partner&#x02019;s gynecologist asks the man to perform a semen analysis and refers him to andrology in case of abnormalities. We might be tempted to believe that this is a phenomenon observed only in Africa, but, unfortunately, the same observation has also been made in developed countries with respondents having a supposedly higher level of community health. This is due to male infertility affecting a man&#x02019;s virility, giving him a sense of reduced masculinity, leading to a complex and difficulty in seeking medical help.<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></p><p>Monogamy was the most observed type of marriage among respondents from both groups. However, one might have been tempted to think that polygamy would be more observed among respondents from Group 1 than those from Group 2 because one of the attitudes of men in the event of couple infertility in Africa is to seek another wife or to divorce.<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></p><p>Respondents from Group 1&#x000a0;had a better knowledge of infertility factors than those from Group 2. This is probably because patients from Group 1 informed themselves more about infertility and had the opportunity to meet a doctor, as evidenced by the question about their source of information concerning infertility.</p><p>Only about 40% of respondents knew that couple infertility is discussed after 12 months of regular, unprotected sexual intercourse. This lack of knowledge contributes to a delay in consultation, as evidenced by numerous African series where this delay often exceeds 5 years.<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> This delay in consultation reduces the chances of conceiving because the older a man gets, the more his chances of procreating are reduced.<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></p><p>Unlike respondents from Group 1, respondents from Group 2 did not know that tobacco, drug use, and excessive alcohol consumption affect male fertility. It is important for men to know these modifiable factors of infertility because stopping these substances often leads to an improvement in the number and quality of spermatozoa. Respondents in both groups correctly identified psychoactive drug consumption, diabetes, obesity and use of anabolic steroids as factors affecting male fertility.</p><p>As in many studies, the majority of respondents from both groups did not recognize advanced male age as a factor favoring infertility.<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> However, the quantity and quality of sperm decrease with age, and men should be sensitized to this. Indeed, men, like women, tend to form couples later in life nowadays, wishing to acquire certain financial stability before committing to a relationship and/or and having children.</p><p>Two respondents from Group 1 claimed that infertility was due to a curse, and one respondent attributed it to djinns. This perception of infertility as a curse or a spell cast on them has been observed in respondents from several African series.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> This perception often leads men to first seek or concurrently use traditional medicine.<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> Respondents from other series believed that infertility was due to divine will and that over time and with prayers, their dream of procreating could become a reality if God so decided. This attitude also delays seeking care from a healthcare provider.</p><p>Like in our study, respondents from Canadian studies knew most of the modifiable factors of male infertility such as smoking, excessive alcohol consumption, or sexually transmitted infections.<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> Most respondents were uncertain about the availability, accessibility, and cost of ART in Senegal. This could be explained by the fact that there was only one center performing ART in Senegal, and it was private, even though a public center would soon open in a hospital in Dakar. Currently, the cost of ART per oocyte retrieval is about 2,500,000 CFA francs, and it is not covered by Senegalese insurance. This economic aspect should be considered in setting the rates in this new center when it opens. Indeed, one of the major problems of ART in southern countries is the high cost.<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> A study showed that the direct medical costs paid by patients living in low and middle-income countries for ART are often higher than the Gross Domestic Product (GDP) per capita, making it inaccessible to most patients.<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></p><p>Moreover, we noticed that respondents from both groups overestimated the success rate of ART by oocyte retrieval. This observation has been made in several studies conducted in different countries.<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> However, the chances of success per oocyte retrieval are about 25 to 30%.<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></p><p>Eighty-six percent of respondents from Group 1 were willing to undergo ART compared to 8% of respondents from Group 2. This significant difference between the respondents of the two groups could be explained by a lesser knowledge of ART by respondents from Group 2 but also by the fact that they were not infertile and thus did not appreciate the opportunity that ART could offer them for procreation.</p><p>Nonetheless, no relationship between religion and the acceptance of ART was observed. This could be explained by an uneven distribution of our population, predominantly Muslim. However, the views of the Catholic Church and Islam differ on this issue. Indeed, the Vatican categorically opposes any ART technique because it believes that the dignity of the embryo must be respected as a person and that procreation must take place within marriage and in conjugal love presented as a reciprocal self-giving key to the relationship between spouses and to the relationship with God.<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> Islam permits Assisted Reproductive Technology (ART) exclusively for married couples.</p><p>Despite a significant rate of acceptance of ART among respondents from Group 1, only 20.2% of respondents were open to undergoing ART with gamete donation. Our findings contrast with a study conducted in Nigeria, where 59% of respondents<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> were favorable to gamete donation.</p><p>The alternative of child adoption in the event of refusal or failure of ART was only considered by respectively 31.9% and 25% of respondents from groups 1 and 2. These results are similar to the studies by Ezugwu<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> conducted in Nigeria and by Bokaie in Iran,<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> where respectively 59% and 82% of respondents were hesitant to adopt a child.</p><p>The internet was the primary source of information for respondents from both groups regarding their knowledge of male infertility and its management. Indeed, the internet has significantly changed how individuals obtain information about their health, and male infertility is no exception, as infertile men increasingly turn to social media for information, advice, or to share experiences.<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> However, some information available on the internet may be inaccurate or misleading, as confirmed by studies evaluating the quality of information on male infertility available online.<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> This contributes to the misinformation of patients with significant repercussions, such as in advertisements that overestimate the results of ART or dietary supplements that improve sperm quality. Therefore, it&#x02019;s crucial for practitioners managing male infertility to communicate more through the internet, as it has become the preferred source of information for patients.</p><p>The sample was not representative of the general Senegalese population therefore these results cannot be generalized to the entire country. However the present study brings important information on a topic that has not been studied much in Subsaharan Africa. Methodologically, we chose to perform semi-structured interviews to inquire about our patients&#x02019; knowledge on male infertility and their acceptance of MAR. This format can stop respondents from fully expressing their perceptions during the interview particularly regarding current marital status and their perception of infertility as a disease.Although minimized by the training sessions and a structured interview, interviewer bias can still be present.</p></sec><sec id="s0005"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Infertile men had a better understanding of male fertility than fertile men. Despite a relatively good knowledge of most modifiable factors of male infertility by respondents from both groups, the duration defining infertility, the respondents did not know advanced male age, and consanguinity as factors favoring male infertility. Additionally, a poor understanding of ART was observed among respondents from both groups, with a better acceptance of ART methods among infertile men. Awareness of male fertility among Senegalese men and its management options, such as lifestyle modifications or ART, needs to be raised. However, this awareness should be achieved using internet, as it is the primary source of information on infertility for Senegalese men.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>Special thanks to Urology Department of Dalal Jamm Hospital, Dakar (Senegal).</p></ack><sec id="s0006"><title>Ethics Statement</title><p>Institutional review Board of Dalal Jamm Hospital approved this study. Our study complies with the Declaration of Helsinki.</p></sec><sec id="s0007"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>All authors made a significant contribution to the work reported, whether that is in the conception, study design, execution, acquisition of data, analysis and interpretation, or in all these areas; took part in drafting, revising or critically reviewing the article; gave final approval of the version to be published; have agreed on the journal to which the article has been submitted; and agree to be accountable for all aspects of the work.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0008"><title>Disclosure</title><p>The authors have nothing to disclose.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="cit0001"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Borght</surname>
<given-names>MV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wyns</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Fertility and infertility: definition and epidemiology</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Biochem</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>62</volume>:<fpage>2</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clinbiochem.2018.03.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29555319</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0002"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Quallich</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Male factor infertility: an area of health disparity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Nurse Practit</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>e235</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>e6</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nurpra.2016.01.020</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0003"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Abebe</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Afework</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abaynew</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Primary and secondary infertility in Africa: systematic review with meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Fertil Res Pract</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>20</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40738-020-00090-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33292584</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0004"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Schlegel</surname>
<given-names>PN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sigman</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Collura</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Diagnosis and treatment of infertility in men: AUA/ASRM guideline part I</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Fertil Steril</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>115</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>54</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>61</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fertnstert.2020.11.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33309062</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0005"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zegers-Hochschild</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Adamson</surname>
<given-names>GD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dyer</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The International Glossary on Infertility and Fertility Care, 2017</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hum Reprod</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1786</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/humrep/dex234</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29117321</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0006"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mabasa</surname>
<given-names>LF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sociocultural aspects of infertility in a Black South African community</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Psychol Afr</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>65</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>79</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0007"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Phillips</surname>
<given-names>KP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tanphaichitr</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Human exposure to endocrine disrupters and semen quality</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Toxicol Environ Health</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>3&#x02013;4</issue>):<fpage>188</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>220</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10937400701873472</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0008"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Phillips</surname>
<given-names>KP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tanphaichitr</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Mechanisms of obesity-induced male infertility</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Expert Rev Endocrinol Metab</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>229</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>251</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1586/eem.09.65</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30764048</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0009"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bunting</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boivin</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Decision-making about seeking medical advice in an internet sample of women trying to get pregnant</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hum Reprod</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1662</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1668</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/humrep/dem057</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17416917</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0010"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gnoth</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Godehardt</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Frank-Herrmann</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Friol</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tigges</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Freundl</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Definition and prevalence of subfertility and infertility</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hum Reprod</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1144</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1147</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/humrep/deh870</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15802321</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0011"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bitler</surname>
<given-names>MP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schmidt</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Utilization of Infertility Treatments: the Effects of Insurance Mandates</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Demography</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>49</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>125</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13524-011-0078-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22167581</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0012"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Njagi</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Groot</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Arsenijevic</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dyer</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mburu</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kiarie</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Financial costs of assisted reproductive technology for patients in low- and middle-income countries: a systematic review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hum Reprod Open</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>2023</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>hoad007</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/hropen/hoad007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36959890</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0013"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zaila</surname>
<given-names>KE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Osadchiy</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shahinyan</surname>
<given-names>RH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mills</surname>
<given-names>JN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eleswarapu</surname>
<given-names>SV</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Social Media Sensationalism in the Male Infertility Space: a Mixed Methodology Analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">World J Mens Health</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>591</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>598</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5534/wjmh.200009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32378368</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0014"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Daumler</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chan</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lo</surname>
<given-names>KC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Takefman</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zelkowitz</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Men&#x02019;s knowledge of their own fertility: a population-based survey examining the awareness of factors that are associated with male infertility</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hum Reprod</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>2781</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2790</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/humrep/dew265</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27816924</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0015"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Daniluk</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Koert</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The other side of the fertility coin: a comparison of childless men&#x02019;s and women&#x02019;s knowledge of fertility and assisted reproductive technology</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Fertil Steril</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>99</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>839</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>846</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fertnstert.2012.10.033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23148926</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0016"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Xie</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ren</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Niu</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zheng</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The impact of stigma on mental health and quality of life of infertile women: a systematic review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Frontiers in Psychology</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>1093459</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2022.1093459</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36698573</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0017"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fisher</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hammarberg</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Psychological and social aspects of infertility in men: an overview of the evidence and implications for psychologically informed clinical care and future research</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Asian j Androl</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>121</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/aja.2011.72</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22179515</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0018"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Naab</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lawali</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Donkor</surname>
<given-names>ES</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bartels</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>&#x0201c;My mother in-law forced my husband to divorce me&#x0201d;: experiences of women with infertility in Zamfara State of Nigeria</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>e0225149</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0225149</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31856167</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0019"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dierickx</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Balen</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Longman</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>We are always desperate and will try anything to conceive&#x02019;: the convoluted and dynamic process of health seeking among women with infertility in the West Coast Region of The Gambia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>e0211634</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0211634</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30703136</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0020"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Boulegue</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Janny</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pouly</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boucher</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hermabessiere</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Fertilit&#x000e9; de l&#x02019;homme en fonction de l&#x02019;&#x000e2;ge</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Andrologie</italic></source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>28</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>41</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0021"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hammarberg</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Setter</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Norman</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Holden</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Michelmore</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Johnson</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Knowledge about factors that influence fertility among Australians of reproductive age: a population-based survey</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Fertil Steril</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>99</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>502</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>507</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fertnstert.2012.10.031</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23158832</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0022"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Faye</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Quand les tradith&#x000e9;rapeutes ouest-africains soignent l&#x02019;infertilit&#x000e9; conjugale &#x000e0; Dakar (S&#x000e9;n&#x000e9;gal): recompositions et dynamiques entrepreneuriales</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Anth Sant&#x000e9; Revue Int Francophone D&#x02019;anthropologie de la Sant&#x000e9;</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>3</volume>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0023"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Roberts</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Metcalfe</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jack</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tough</surname>
<given-names>SC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Factors that influence the childbearing intentions of Canadian men</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hum Reprod</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1202</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1208</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/humrep/der007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21339195</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0024"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dyer</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Archary</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>de Mouzon</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fiadjoe</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ashiru</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Network</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Assisted reproductive technologies in Africa: first results from the African Network and Registry for Assisted Reproductive Technology, 2013</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Reproductive BioMedicine Online</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>216</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>224</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rbmo.2018.11.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30553656</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0025"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nargund</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fauser</surname>
<given-names>BCJM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Macklon</surname>
<given-names>NS</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The ISMAAR proposal on terminology for ovarian stimulation for IVF</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hum Reprod</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>2801</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2804</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/humrep/dem285</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17855409</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0026"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Djimadjibaye</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jacquemin</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <part-title>Procr&#x000e9;ation m&#x000e9;dicalement assist&#x000e9;e: enjeux &#x000e9;thiques et th&#x000e9;ologiques</part-title>. In: <source><italic toggle="yes">M&#x000e9;moire</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>Louvain</publisher-loc>:<publisher-name>Universit&#x000e9; Catholique de Louvain</publisher-name>. <year>2017</year></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0027"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Abieyuwa</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>James</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Michael</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Orhue</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Gamete donation: knowledge, attitude and perception of infertile couple in a public hospital in Nigeria</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Trop J Obstetrics Gyn</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>129</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>133</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0028"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ezugwu</surname>
<given-names>FO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Obi</surname>
<given-names>SN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Onah</surname>
<given-names>HE</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The knowledge, attitude and practice of child adoption among infertile Nigerian women</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Obstetrics Gynaecol</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>211</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>216</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/01443610120113463</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0029"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bokaie</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Farajkhoda</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Enjezab</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Heidari</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zarchi</surname>
<given-names>MK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Barriers of child adoption in infertile couples: iranian&#x02019;s views</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Iran J Reprod Med</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>429</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25246908</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0030"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Satir</surname>
<given-names>DG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kavlak</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Use of the internet related to infertility by infertile women and men in Turkey</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pakistan J Med Scie</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>265</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12669/pjms.332.12620</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>