<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Bioinformation</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Bioinformation</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Bioinformation</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Bioinformation</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0973-8894</issn><issn pub-type="epub">0973-2063</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Biomedical Informatics</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40401286</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12093259</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">973206300200234</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.6026/973206300200234</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Fluoride exposure among children with different blood groups at Kolar district, Karnataka, India</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shashidhar</surname><given-names>Kurpad Nagaraj</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="COR1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hemalatha</surname><given-names>Anantharamaiah</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="COR3" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Munilakshmi</surname><given-names>Uppalamethi</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="COR4" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sharon Rose</surname><given-names>Paramaturi</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="COR5" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Meghanath</surname><given-names>Muthyala</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="COR2" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Biochemistry, Sri Devaraj Urs Medical College, Kolar, Karnataka, India</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="COR1"><label>1</label>Kurpad Nagaraj Shashidhar <email>drshashikn1971@yahoo.co.in</email></corresp><corresp id="COR2"><label>2</label>Muthyala Meghanath <email>gh.meghanath777@gmail.com</email></corresp><corresp id="COR3"><label>3</label>Anantharamaiah Hemalatha <email>drhemashashi@gmail.com</email></corresp><corresp id="COR4"><label>4</label>Uppalamethi Munilakshmi <email>lakshmisundharsj@gmail.com</email></corresp><corresp id="COR5"><label>5</label>Paramaturi Sharon Rose <email>sharonhoney06@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>3</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>20</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>234</fpage><lpage>237</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>1</day><month>3</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>31</day><month>3</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>31</day><month>3</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2024 Biomedical Informatics</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited. This is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Fluoride is present naturally in water at &#x0003c; 1.5 ppm and it is considered to be essential for dental and bone enamel mineralization
forming fluorapatite. Chronic exposure (&#x0003e; 2ppm) is considered to be toxic and it leads to fluorosis. Fluoride in minor quantities is
excreted through sweat, saliva and feaces. Kidneys are the major route of excretion of fluoride and are thus it is the primary organ to
be affected. Therefore, it is of interest to assess urinary fluoride among school children with different blood groups at Kolar district,
Karnataka, India. Study was conducted in 155 subjects, aged 16-17 years. Data shows that blood group B has high risk of effecting by
fluorosis (mean value of urine fluoride = 1.11). However, subjects with negative blood groups are least affected by fluorosis (mean
value of urine fluoride =0.30). However, a larger population study is required for validation.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Fluoride exposure</kwd><kwd>children</kwd><kwd>blood groups</kwd><kwd>Kolar district</kwd><kwd>Karnataka</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Background:</title><p>Fluoride is derived from Fluorine, the 13th most abundant element on earth's crust [<xref rid="R01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>].
It is present in majority of foods and beverages including water [<xref rid="R02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Fluoride levels vary among
the population [<xref rid="R03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Fluoride accumulation of ground water varies according to the source of
water, geological formulation of the area and quantum of rain fall [<xref rid="R03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Fluoride in permissible
limits protects against dental caries in children [<xref rid="R04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Excess intake of fluoride results in
adverse events and health hazards [<xref rid="R05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Direct resultants of chronic fluoride exposure are Dental
Fluorosis, Skeletal Fluorosis and Non-Skeletal fluorosis [<xref rid="R06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Further excessive intake of
fluoride indirectly impairs the Cognitive, Renal and other physiological functions [<xref rid="R07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
<xref rid="R08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>-<xref rid="R09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Kolar district of Karnataka is a fluoride endemic
area [<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Underground drinking water of this area is rich in Fluoride. Healthy range of fluoride
in drinking water is upto 1.5ppm [<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Studies and population surveys suggest the mean value of
fluoride levels of Kolar district is around 3.06ppm, substantiating the adverse events of high fluorosis exposure [<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].
Therefore, it is of interest to assess the effect of fluoride exposure among school children with different blood groups in India.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods:</title><p>This is an observational study conducted in a school health education camp at Kolar district. A total of 155 subjects of were
enrolled with age group of 16-17 years. Anthropometric measurements, Blood pressure, Urine fluoride and blood group categorization was
done to the study subjects. Around 25 ml of urine was collected from each subject. Urine Fluoride was determined using Thermo Scientific
Ion selective electrode and Total Ionic Strength Adjustment Buffer (TISAB) II buffer. TISAB was used to provide a constant background
ionic strength that de-complexes fluoride ion and adjusts the pH of the sample. Chemicals and reagents used were of analytical grade.
Blood Grouping was done through ABO typing. Selected subjects were categorized by gender and blood group. Mean values of anthropometric
measurements, Systolic blood pressure SBP, Diastolic blood pressure DBP and urine fluoride were measured and statistically analyzed.</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Results and Discussion:</title><p>Kolar district is an endemic area for fluoride with scanty rainfall and has affected at large [<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].
Local population including agriculture, Floriculture, Horticulture, Livestock and various other agricultural dependencies are also not
spared. Correlation of Urine fluoride with anthropometric measurements including BMI calculation and BP measurements was carried out.
Pearson's correlation depicted a notable correlation of urine fluoride with systolic blood pressure (SBP) with p value of -0.007
(<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). There is no significance observed among the correlation of urine fluoride and blood
groups (Figure 3 - see PDF). Gender based comparison of urine fluoride between males and females with a total number of 155 study
subjects were analyzed (Figure 1 - (see PDF) and Figure 2 - (see PDF)). The same was tabulated in <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>.
We could observe a positive correlation with urine fluoride, SBP and DBP. However, the BMI and urine fluoride did not show any
statistical significance. Correlation of urine fluoride with blood groups showed predominantly 24 male with B+ blood group and 22 with
O+ blood group; females we could observe equal distribution of 14 in both B positive and O positive, respectively
(Figure 1 - (see PDF) and Figure 2 - (see PDF)). The other blood groups viz O-, A+, A-, B-, AB+ and AB- were less in number compared to
B+ and O+ respectively (<xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). It has been documented that Genetics play a critical role in
determination of blood groups [<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. However the impact
of fluoride on alleles needs to be determined, as studies conducted by Marganwar <italic>et al.</italic> observed that high fluoride
concentration may disturb the anion channel of erythrocytes membrane, which in turn leads to haemolysis and swelling of cells. This
causes toxic effect on RBC's and their metabolomics and Epigenetics [<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Scattered diagram with
comparison of urine fluoride versus blood group as R value of 0.02 indicated a non-significance of fluoride on blood groups. However a
large population studies with Epigenetic studies impart the predetermined effects of fluoride on the blood group and RH and also blood
homeostasis. We could observe &#x0003e;1ppm in the blood groups B, O, A and AB with highest to lowest of 18, 16, 12 and 2
(<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). In a cross-sectional study conducted by Ali Al Ghamdi, concluded that people with
Blood group B are at higher risk of developing severe forms of Periodontitis [<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Our study
strengthens his point as we observed more number of subjects having urine fluoride value of &#x0003e;1ppm in blood group B. However, within
the blood group RH positive and negative determined 16/16 of O+, 11 of 12 in A+, 17 out of 18 in B+ and 2 on 2 of AB+ indicating the
negative blood groups are comparatively protective against fluorosis and its role (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).
Earlier studies of Mazumdar <italic>et al.</italic> excluding negative blood groups, concluded with no statistical significance
[<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. We included Rh-ve groups and a larger population than those and submitting an output that
negative blood groups are better protected against fluorosis. Haematological studies concluded that red blood cell antigens are
inherited traits; they are usually not altered throughout the life of an individual. There have been occasional case reports of ABO
blood group antigen change in malignant conditions [<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].</p><p>Awareness programs on fluorosis and its impact prevents the adverse events of highly exposed population [<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>].
Despite use of RO filters, the filtered out effluent of the water with a high fluoride content discharged onto the ground gets recharged
and further concentrates the fluoride in soil leading to further high fluoride of soil and grass [<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>].
Consumption of the same by poultry and livestock with a resultant consumption of poultry products and milk by humans leads to indirect
worsening of the fluorosis in highly fluoridated areas [<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].
Studies conducted by Helen G Jarvis and his team suggests providing safe and clean piped water, we too recommend the Government agencies
and statutory bodies to take appropriate measures to reduce the salinity of water and soil [<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>].
Safe disposal of filtered out fluoridated water is to be considered as a Biohazard. We also recommend that RO filters also filters out
in addition to fluoride various other essential minerals which are required for enzyme activities and metabolomics, leading to a direct
or indirect effect on the Epigenetics and metabolism of fluoride [<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Conclusion:</title><p>Data shows that blood group B has high risk of effecting by fluorosis. However, subjects with negative blood groups are least
affected by fluorosis in this sample size.</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Limitations of our study:</title><p>This study is conducted in a fluoride endemic area with a small sample size so to know the impact in correlation with urine fluoride
among children with different blood groups. The same is required with a large sample size among different age groups along with serum
fluoride.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn id="FN" fn-type="other"><p>
<bold>Edited by Peter N Pushparaj</bold>
</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group><fn id="FN1" fn-type="other"><p><bold>Citation: </bold>Shashidhar <italic>et al.</italic> Bioinformation 20(3):234-237(2024)</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group><fn id="FN3" fn-type="other"><p><bold>Declaration on Publication Ethics:</bold> The author's state that they adhere with COPE guidelines on publishing ethics as described elsewhere at https://publicationethics.org/.
The authors also undertake that they are not associated with any other third party (governmental or non-governmental agencies) linking with any form of unethical issues connecting to this publication. The authors also declare
that they are not withholding any information that is misleading to the publisher in regard to this article.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group><fn id="FN4" fn-type="other"><p><bold>Declaration on official E-mail: </bold> The corresponding author declares that official e-mail from their institution is not available for all authors.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group><fn id="FN5" fn-type="other"><p><bold>License statement: </bold> This is an Open Access article which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly
credited. This is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group><fn id="FN6" fn-type="other"><p><bold>Comments from readers: </bold> Articles published in BIOINFORMATION are open for relevant post publication comments and criticisms, which will be published immediately linking to
the original article without open access charges. Comments should be concise, coherent and critical in less than 1000 words.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group><fn id="FN7" fn-type="other"><p><bold>Bioinformation Impact Factor:</bold>Impact Factor (Clarivate Inc 2023 release) for BIOINFORMATION is 1.9 with 2,198 citations from 2020 to 2022 taken for IF calculations.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group><fn id="FN8" fn-type="other"><p><bold>Disclaimer:</bold>The views and opinions expressed are those of the author(s) and do not reflect the views or opinions of Bioinformation and (or) its publisher Biomedical Informatics. Biomedical Informatics
remains neutral and allows authors to specify their address and affiliation details including territory where required. Bioinformation provides a platform for scholarly communication of data and information to create knowledge in the Biological/Biomedical
domain.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R01"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haritash</surname><given-names>A.K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Appl. Water. Sci. </source><year>2018</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>52</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13201-018-0691-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R02"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/23115811/" ext-link-type="uri">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/23115811/</ext-link>
</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R03"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://nap.nationalacademies.org/catalog/11571/fluoride-in-drinking-water-a-scientific-review-of-epas-standards" ext-link-type="uri">https://nap.nationalacademies.org/catalog/11571/fluoride-in-drinking-water-a-scientific-review-of-epas-standards</ext-link>
</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R04"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>G.E</given-names></name></person-group><source>Soc. Sci. Med. </source><year>1988</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>451</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3283946</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R05"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rizwan</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Iran. J. Basic. Med. Sci. </source><year>2017</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>841</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29085574</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R06"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Everett</surname><given-names>E.T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>J. Dent. Res. </source><year>2011</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>552</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20929720</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R07"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gopu</surname><given-names>B.P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Int. J. Environ. Res. Public Health. </source><year>2022</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>22</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36612346</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R08"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Godebo</surname><given-names>T.R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Neurotoxicol. Teratol. </source><year>2023</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>107293</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37690675</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R09"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Mondal</surname><given-names>N.K</given-names></name></person-group><source>Environ. Monit. Assess. </source><year>2016</year><volume>188</volume><fpage>218</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26960765</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Environ. Health. Prev. Med. </source><year>2017</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>17</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29165120</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prasad</surname><given-names>U.V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Front. Public Health. </source><year>2023</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1110777</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37006577</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Narayanamurthy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Navale</surname><given-names>A.S</given-names></name></person-group><source>J. Orofac. Sci. </source><year>2013</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>105</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0975-8844.124253</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shruthi</surname><given-names>M.N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Indian. J. Public Health. </source><year>2016</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>203</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27561399</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Groot</surname><given-names>H.E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Arterioscler Thromb Vasc. Biol. </source><year>2020</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>830</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31969017</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marganwar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Dhurvey</surname><given-names>V.T</given-names></name></person-group><source>Int. J. Zool. Investig. </source><year>2021</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>456</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.33745/ijzi.2021.v07i02.020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghamdi</surname><given-names>A.A</given-names></name></person-group><source>Med. Sci. </source><year>2009</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>31</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mazumdar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Int. J. Adv. Res. </source><year>2018</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>832</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21474/IJAR01/6737</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nambiar</surname><given-names>R.K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Proc (Bayl. Univ. Med. Cent). </source><year>2017</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>74</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28127141</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Srivastava</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Flora</surname><given-names>S.J.S</given-names></name></person-group><source>Curr. Environ. Health Report. </source><year>2020</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>140</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32207100</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yadav</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Int. J. Curr. Microbiol. App. Sci. </source><year>2018</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>713</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.20546/ijcmas.2018.708.078</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shahab</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><source>Fluoride. </source><year>2017</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>393</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kessabi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Sci. Total .Environ. </source><year>1984</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>63</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6523125</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jarvis</surname><given-names>H.G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Trop. Med. Int. Health. </source><year>2013</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>222</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23198699</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khairnar</surname><given-names>M.R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>J. Indian. Assoc. Public Health. Dent. </source><year>2018</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>165</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/jiaphd.</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prabhakar</surname><given-names>A.R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>J. Indian. Soc. Pedod. Prev. Dent. </source><year>2008</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>6</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18408264</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Correlation of Urine Fluoride (UF) with Anthropometric measurements and Physiological variables</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>R value</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Age</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Gender</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Blood Group</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>SBP (mm/hg)</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>DBP (mm/hg)</bold>
</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">UF</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.075</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.056</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.043</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.047</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.007*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.031</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.351</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.486</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.653</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.573</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.935</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.719</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SBP: Systolic blood pressure; DBP: Diastolic blood pressure;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">*p-value &#x02264; 0.05 is considered as statistically significant.</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Gender based comparison of Urine fluoride: (Male: 91; Female: 64)</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Variables</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Groups</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Mean &#x000b1; SD</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Std. Error Mean</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>P Value</bold>
</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (in years)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.6 &#x000b1;0.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.70 &#x000b1; 0.46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blood</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.52 &#x000b1; 2.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.05 &#x000b1; 1.92</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.02 &#x000b1; 4.69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.20 &#x000b1; 4.31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SBP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">113.45 &#x000b1; 13.39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(mm/hg)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">111.37&#x000b1;11.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DBP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.85 &#x000b1; 10.44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(mm/hg)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.61 &#x000b1; 9.36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urine Fluoride</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14 &#x000b1; 0.41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(ppm)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09 &#x000b1; 0.43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Study subjects (155) were categorized into two groups based on Urine Fluoride value (&#x0003c;1ppm and &#x0003e;1ppm). With this categorization, UF values are correlated with BMI, SBP, DBP and blood groups to find out the p value</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>UF</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>O</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>O+ve</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>O-ve</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>A</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>A+ve</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>A-ve</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>B</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>B+ve</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>B-ve</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>AB</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>AB+ve</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>AB-ve</bold>
</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;1 ppm N = 65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;1 ppm N = 90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Correlation of Urine fluoride with Blood groups</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Chi-square value</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>BMI</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>SBP</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>DBP</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>O+ve</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>A+ve</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>B+ve</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>O (+ &#x00026; -)</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>A (+ &#x00026; -)</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>B (+ &#x00026; -)</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>AB (+ &#x00026; -)</bold>
</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.125</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.62</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.37</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>p-value</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00836*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.723</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.056*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.123</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">We have considered the significance with p-value &#x02264; 0.05,</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">significance of Urine-fluoride is observed only with BMI and blood group O.</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></floats-group></article>