<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="abstract"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Eur Psychiatry</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Eur Psychiatry</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">EPA</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>European Psychiatry</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0924-9338</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1778-3585</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11862469</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1192/j.eurpsy.2024.645</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="other">EPP0518</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S092493382400645X</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Abstract</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="section"><subject>e-Poster Presentation</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Association between social distancing and incident microvascular events among individuals with diabetes mellitus: a population-based cohort study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Y. Y.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1504" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor0506" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1504" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1504"><sup>1</sup>Center for Sleep and Circadian Medicine, <institution>The Affiliated Brain Hospital of Guangzhou Medical University</institution>, <city>Guangzhou</city>, <country>
China</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor0506"><label>*</label>Corresponding author.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="collection" iso-8601-date="2024-04"><month>4</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>67</volume><issue seq="620">Suppl 1</issue><issue-title content-type="special_issue">Abstracts of the 32nd European Congress of Psychiatry</issue-title><fpage>S310</fpage><lpage>S310</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2024</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Author(s)</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article, distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution licence (<uri xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</uri>), which permits unrestricted re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="S092493382400645Xa.pdf"/><abstract><sec id="sec3040"><title>Introduction</title><p>Social isolation and loneliness have been rising social determinants of cardiometabolic health.</p></sec><sec id="sec3041"><title>Objectives</title><p>To investigate the associations of social isolation and loneliness with diabetic microvascular complications (DMC) among individuals with type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM) and assess the extent to which intermediate risk factors explained the associations.</p></sec><sec id="sec3042"><title>Methods</title><p>Data for individuals with T2DM (n=24,297, 62.2% male; mean age=60.0 years) were taken from the UK Biobank. Social isolation and loneliness were assessed using self-reported questionnaires. DMC, mainly including diabetic kidney disease, diabetic retinopathy, and diabetic neuropathy, were identified by linking hospital records and death registries.</p></sec><sec id="sec3043"><title>Results</title><p>In the multivariate-adjusted model, social isolation was associated with an increased risk for incidence of any DMC (most vs. least: HR: 1.13; 95% CI: 1.05-1.22), especially diabetic kidney disease and neuropathy; loneliness was also associated with any DMC (yes vs. no: HR: 1.12; 95% CI: 1.02-1.23) and diabetic kidney disease. Social isolation and loneliness ranked similarly in relative strength for predicting DMC as other conventional risk factors, such as smoking, high blood pressure, and physical activity. The association between social isolation and DMC was mainly attributed to health behaviors, while the association between loneliness and DMC was primarily explained by health behaviors, psychological factors, and diabetes-related factors.</p></sec><sec id="sec3044"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Social isolation and loneliness were independently associated with a higher risk for incident DMC among individuals with T2DM, which were largely explained by subsequent unhealthy lifestyles, psychosocial stress, and diabetes-related factors. These findings underscore social isolation and loneliness as novel modifiable risk factors for predicting DMC.</p></sec><sec id="sec3045"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This research has been conducted using the UK Biobank Resource under Application Number 58082.</p></sec><sec id="sec3046"><title>Funding Support</title><p>This work was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (grant number 32100880), Guangzhou Municipal Key Discipline in Medicine (2021-2023), Guangzhou High-level Clinical Key Specialty, and Guangzhou Research-oriented Hospital. The funders had no role in the design and conduct of the study; collection, management, analysis, and interpretation of the data; preparation, review, or approval of the manuscript; and decision to submit the manuscript for publication.</p></sec><sec id="sec3047"><title>Disclosure of Interest</title><p>None Declared</p></sec></abstract><counts><page-count count="1"/></counts></article-meta></front></article>