<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="abstract"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Eur Psychiatry</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Eur Psychiatry</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">EPA</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>European Psychiatry</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0924-9338</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1778-3585</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11862036</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1192/j.eurpsy.2024.1236</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="other">EPV0558</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S0924933824012367</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Abstract</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="section"><subject>e-Poster Viewing</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Perception of Violence by Psychiatric Nurses: Behind the scenes</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hamzaoui</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2769" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mahfoudh</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2769" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Walha</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2769" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mezri</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2769" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ouertani</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2769" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ouali</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2769" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Aissa</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2769" ref-type="aff"/><xref rid="cor1090" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jomli</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2769" ref-type="aff"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff2769">Psychiatry A, <institution>Razi Hospital</institution>, <city>Manouba</city>, <country>Tunisia</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1090"><label>*</label>Corresponding author.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="collection" iso-8601-date="2024-04"><month>4</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>67</volume><issue seq="1211">Suppl 1</issue><issue-title content-type="special_issue">Abstracts of the 32nd European Congress of Psychiatry</issue-title><fpage>S594</fpage><lpage>S594</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2024</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Author(s)</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article, distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution licence (<uri xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</uri>), which permits unrestricted re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="S0924933824012367a.pdf"/><abstract><sec id="sec6552"><title>Introduction</title><p>Violence in psychiatric settings poses significant challenges for healthcare professionals, particularly nurses. This study examines psychiatric nurses&#x02019; perceptions of violence and its impact on the quality of care they provide.</p></sec><sec id="sec6553"><title>Objectives</title><p>The primary objective is to assess the influence of violence on the quality of care in psychiatric settings, with a focus on the experiences and perspectives of nurses.</p></sec><sec id="sec6554"><title>Methods</title><p>We employed a questionnaire-based survey administered to 30 psychiatric nurses working in both inpatient and outpatient psychiatric units&#x000a0;of the Razi hospital Manouba. The survey gathered information on the prevalence of violence, types of violence encountered, and the impact on nursing practice.</p></sec><sec id="sec6555"><title>Results</title><p>Of the 30 respondents, 75% identified as female and 25% identified as male.&#x000a0;Most of them had more than five years of experience.&#x000a0;The primary results revealed that all the psychiatric nurses reported experiencing at least one incident of violence during their psychiatric nursing careers.&#x000a0;Regarding exposure to verbal violence, the results indicated that 52% encountered it sometimes, 22% often, 17% very often.&#x000a0;Regarding physical violence, 30% experienced it rarely, 26% sometimes, 13% often, and 13% very often.&#x000a0;For sexual violence, 56% reported never experiencing it, 8% rarely, 26% sometimes, and 8% very often.&#x000a0;These incidents had varying effects on nurses&#x02019; emotional well-being, job satisfaction, and the quality of care they were able to provide.&#x000a0;53% of nurses reported experiencing emotional distress and feelings of anxiety as a result of violence, 13% felt anger and frustration. One nurse declared he was not affected emotionally. Most of the respondents (75%) indicated that their job satisfaction had been negatively affected by violent incidents. 40% of respondents stated that violence has a negative impact on their relationship with patients, but they make efforts to maintain care quality. Whereas, 20% found ways to strengthen connections despite challenging experiences.The most commonly endorsed strategies to cope with violence included attempting to master their emotions by remaining calm and patient (78% of respondents), seeking assistance or the presence of other healthcare team members (65%), and maintaining a safe distance from patients (69%). Fewer participants reported raising their voice and adopting a position of authority (30%), while a minority indicated engaging in additional training on the management of violent situations (20%). These results illustrate the diverse range of personal coping strategies.</p></sec><sec id="sec6556"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Violence in psychiatric settings has a multifaceted impact on psychiatric nurses, affecting both their emotional well-being and the quality of care they provide. Strategies for managing and preventing violence, as well as supporting nurses in coping with these challenges, are essential for maintaining high-quality psychiatric care.</p></sec><sec id="sec6557"><title>Disclosure of Interest</title><p>None Declared</p></sec></abstract><counts><page-count count="1"/></counts></article-meta></front></article>