<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Heliyon</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Heliyon</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Heliyon</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2405-8440</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11681852</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2405-8440(24)16972-1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e40941</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e40941</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Association between the use of herbal medicines during pregnancy and adverse fetal outcomes among mothers in eastern Ethiopia, 2023</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name><surname>Getachew</surname><given-names>Tamirat</given-names></name><email>tamirget@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name><surname>Tura</surname><given-names>Abera Kenay</given-names></name><email>daberaf@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name><surname>Dheresa</surname><given-names>Merga</given-names></name><email>mderesa@yahoo.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4"><name><surname>Niguse</surname><given-names>Shamble</given-names></name><email>shambelpharm02@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5"><name><surname>Balis</surname><given-names>Bikila</given-names></name><email>bik.balis2008@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au6"><name><surname>Regassa</surname><given-names>Lemma Demissie</given-names></name><email>esraeldemiss@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au7"><name><surname>Eyeberu</surname><given-names>Addis</given-names></name><email>addiseyeberu@gmailm.co</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#x0204e;</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>School of Nursing and Midwifery, College of Health and Medical Sciences, Haramaya University, Harar, Ethiopia</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>School of Pharmacy, College of Health and Medical Sciences, Haramaya University, Harar, Ethiopia</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>School of Public Health, College of Health and Medical Sciences, Haramaya University, Harar, Ethiopia</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x0204e;</label>Corresponding author. School of Nursing and Midwifery, College of Health and Medical Sciences, Haramaya University P.O. BOX 138 Dire Dawa, Ethiopia. <email>addiseyeberu@gmailm.co</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>06</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>30</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>06</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue>24</issue><elocation-id>e40941</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>3</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>3</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>3</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2024 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="abs0010"><sec><title>Background</title><p>Nowadays, pregnant women around the world use herbal remedies extensively. Evidence illustrated that the association between the use of herbal medicines and unfavorable fetal outcomes is not well established. Furthermore, much of the existing research is conducted within medical facilities, which may result in excluding mothers who do not receive antenatal follow-up care. Therefore, this study aimed to explore the association between the use of herbal medicine and adverse fetal outcomes in eastern Ethiopia.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>A community-based cross-sectional study was conducted among 882 randomly selected mothers from February 1, 2023 to November 1, 2023. Data were collected through face-to-face interviews using structured questionnaires adapted from previous literature. The dataset was analyzed using Stata version 18, and a modified Poisson regression model was applied. Adjusted prevalence ratios (APR) with 95&#x000a0;% confidence intervals were estimated.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>The prevalence of herbal medicines use among pregnant women in eastern Ethiopia was 43.2&#x000a0;% (95&#x000a0;% CI: 39.9, 46.5). The most commonly used herbal medicines were <italic>Ocimum lamiifolium</italic> 109 (29.1&#x000a0;%), <italic>pumpkin fruit</italic> 68 (18.2&#x000a0;%) and <italic>Rutachalepensis</italic> 61(16.3&#x000a0;%). Factors such as rural residency [APR&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1.27, 95%CI (1.01,1.59)], having obstetric complications in recent pregnancy [APR&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1.42, 95&#x000a0;% CI: (1.14,1.78)], and experiencing adverse fetal outcomes [APR&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1.59, 95%CI: (1.05,2.2)] were significantly associated with the use of herbal medicine.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>More than two out of five mothers used herbal remedies during their recent pregnancy. The study identified a significant association between the use of herbal medicines and various sociodemographic and obstetric factors. Consequently, it is essential to establish the safety and effectiveness of herbal medications before their use during pregnancy. To address the diverse health needs of pregnant women and mitigate the risks associated with the indiscriminate use of herbal remedies, a collaborative strategy should be developed involving herbalists, communities with strong beliefs in herbal medicine, and healthcare professionals.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Integrative medicine</kwd><kwd>Traditional african medicine</kwd><kwd>Herbal medicines</kwd><kwd>Pregnant women</kwd><kwd>Adverse fetal outcomes</kwd><kwd>Ethiopia</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0010">Globally, pregnant women are increasingly turning to herbal drugs. Most pregnant women use herbal medicine to treat diseases and improve their health before, during, and after giving birth [<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Numerous studies have indicated that the use of herbal remedies during pregnancy is quite common. Studies from the UK (56&#x000a0;%) [<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>], Italy (48&#x000a0;%) [<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>], and Norway (36&#x000a0;%) [<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] have shown that herbal remedies are commonly used to treat acute illnesses and pregnancy-related issues. In the Western world, pregnant women most frequently use herbs to treat conditions such as echinacea (common cold), cranberry (urinary tract irritation), ginger (nausea), and raspberry leaf (as a uterotonic) [<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>].</p><p id="p0015">The prevalence of herbal medicine use varies from place to place. A systematic review study revealed that the worldwide prevalence of herbal use was 32.4&#x000a0;% [<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. The prevalence of use of herbal medicine during pregnancy in Saudi Arabia, and Palestine was 33&#x000a0;% and 40&#x000a0;% respectively [<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. In sub-Saharan Africa, the prevalence of herbal medicine use among pregnant women varies. The prevalence of use of herbal medicine in Uganda [<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], Kenya [<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], Sierra Leone [<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], and eastern Kenya [<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], was 20&#x000a0;%, 12&#x000a0;%, 62.7&#x000a0;%, and 100&#x000a0;% respectively.</p><p id="p0020">There are regional variations in the prevalence of herbal use among pregnant women in Ethiopia. The prevalence of herbal medicine use was 22.6&#x000a0;% in Woldiya, Ethiopia [<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], 36.3&#x000a0;% in Debre tabor, Ethiopia [<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], 73.1&#x000a0;% in southern Ethiopia [<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], 48.6&#x000a0;% in Gondar, Ethiopia [<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], and 504.% in western Ethiopia [<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. According to a systematic review and meta-analysis study, the common herbal medicines used by pregnant women in Ethiopia were <italic>ginger, damakasse, garlic, tenaadam, and eucalyptus</italic> [<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>].</p><p id="p0025">Evidence showed that the most common reasons for the use of herbal medicines were for the treatment of gastrointestinal disorders and common cold symptoms [<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. In addition to deep-rooted beliefs, customs, and rational attitudes, lack of knowledge and ignorance of the effects of practices help maintain the use of herbal medicines [<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Several studies showed that educational status, occupational status, residency, history of herbal use, and maternal illness during pregnancy were significantly associated with the use of herbal medicine use among pregnant women [<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].</p><p id="p0030">In Ethiopia, certain practices involve the use of herbal medicine aimed at protecting mothers and newborns from perceived dangers and adverse effects [<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. However, these traditional embedded practices have an impact on the health of mothers and their newborns. Some evidence illustrated that the use of herbal medicines is not associated with adverse maternal and fetal outcomes [<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] and others showed that herbal medicines are associated with adverse fetal outcomes such as abortion, congenital malformations, and fetal death [<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. This indicated that the association between the use of herbal medicines and adverse maternal outcomes is not well established and requires further investigation. Furthermore, the majority of studies in Ethiopia were conducted in health facilities that possibly excluded women who did not have antenatal care visits and there is limited research on these issues in community settings [<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Therefore, the purpose of this study is to explore the association between the use of herbal medicines during pregnancy and adverse fetal outcomes among mothers in eastern Ethiopia.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><label>2</label><title>Methods</title><sec id="sec2.1"><label>2.1</label><title>Study setting and period</title><p id="p0035">This study was carried out at the Health and Demographic Surveillance Sites (HDSS) in the eastern Ethiopian regions of Haramaya, Harar, and Kersa. The capital of the Harari Regional State is Harar, which contains 19 kebeles, or subdistricts. Twelve of these kebeles are part of the urban HDSS, which was started in 2011. Founded in 2007, Kersa HDSS is located in Kersa district in eastern Hararghe, Oromia region, Eastern Ethiopia. This site includes 24 representative kebeles (of 38 in the district) under health and demographic surveillance [<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], but representativeness beyond the district level cannot be assumed. Four kebeles from Harar, Haramaya, and Kersa were used for this investigation. Basic sociodemographic information, Global Positioning System (GPS) locations, and comprehensive home characteristics are included in the database for each HDSS site. The Haramaya HDSS catchment area includes 12 of the 34 rural kebeles in Haramaya district. The total number of households in the HDSS was 17&#x000a0;461. The total baseline population was 99&#x000a0;898 (51&#x000a0;259 men and 48&#x000a0;639 women), of whom 23.86&#x000a0;% were women of reproductive age [<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. The study was carried out from February 2023 to November 2023.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><label>2.2</label><title>Study design and population</title><p id="p0040">A community-based cross-sectional study design was conducted among 882 randomly selected mothers. All selected mothers who gave birth in the past six months prior to the study and currently resided in Kersa, Haramaya, and Harar HDSS, eastern Ethiopia, were the study populations. All postnatal mothers who were unable to respond to the survey questionnaire during the data collection period due to severe illness, and unable to communicate verbally and mentally were excluded from the study.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><label>2.3</label><title>Sampling size determination and sampling procedure</title><p id="p0045">The sample size was calculated using a single population proportion formula with confidence level assumptions at 95&#x000a0;%&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1.96, a margin of error (d)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.03, and a reasonable proportion of herbal medicine use (P&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.226) from a previous study conducted in Amhara region [<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] and by adding 2&#x000a0;% design effect and a non-response rate of 5&#x000a0;%, the final sample size became 882.</p><p id="p0050">A simple random sampling method was used to select mothers. There are 24 rural kebeles (Kersa and Haramaya) and 12 urban kebeles (Harar) in HDSS; two kebeles were chosen at random from each location. The distribution of the sample size among the six kebeles was based on the size of their respective populations. Lastly, using a simple random sampling method (lottery method) based on the sampling frame retrieved from HDSS (N&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;8330) (N&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;2,784, 1908 and 3621 for Kersa, Haramaya, and Harar respectively), study participants who were included in the study from each kebele were selected. A total of 295 samples were assigned to Kersa HDSS, 202 samples to Haramaya HDSS, and 384 samples to Harar HDSS.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><label>2.4</label><title>Data collection methods and quality assurance</title><p id="p0055">Data were collected using a structured questionnaire administered by interviewers, along with a review of records from the Health and Demographic Surveillance System (HDSS) sites in Kersa, Haramaya, and Harar. The questionnaire was adapted from established instruments with proven validity and reliability in similar populations [<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>, <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>]. The instrument was initially developed in English and subsequently translated into Amharic and Afaan Oromo to ensure accessibility for participants in the study area. To maintain accuracy and consistency, the translation process involved back-translation into English. The tool contains four sections such as; socio-demographic characteristics related to factors such as age, residency, educational status, marital status, and monthly income level; obstetric-related factors such as Antenatal care (ANC) follow-up visit, gravidity, complication during recent pregnancy, history of fetal loss, place of delivery and mode of delivery; herbal use such as type of use of herbal medicine, reason for use, route of administration, and side effects of herbal use.</p><p id="p0060">To ensure validity, the questionnaires were pre-tested on 5&#x000a0;% of the sample of respondents before the actual data collection in Dre Dawa city. This pretest helped refine the questions for clarity, appropriateness, and cultural relevance, ensuring that the instrument accurately measured what it was intended to. To assess reliability, the structured questionnaire was administered consistently across all participants, and interviewers were trained to follow a standard protocol, minimizing interviewer bias and ensuring uniformity in the data collection process. Data were collected by well-trained 10 BSc midwives and supervised by 4 supervisors for data quality.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.5"><label>2.5</label><title>Operational definitions</title><p id="p0065"><bold>Herbal use:</bold> is the use of parts of active ingredients of plants, other plant materials, or their combinations as part of traditional or conventional medicine and are not fully integrated into the dominant health care system [<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>].</p><p id="p0070"><bold>Adverse fetal outcomes</bold>: The presence of at least one of the following (stillbirth, low birth weight, preterm, and congenital anomaly) [<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec2.6"><label>2.6</label><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="p0075">The data were exported to Stata version 18 for analysis. Data were compiled using a descriptive statistical analysis. Frequencies, tables, and figures were used in the data presentation.</p><p id="p0080">To explore the relationship between the independent variables and the use of herbal medicine, we employed a Poisson regression analysis model with robust variance estimation. This generalized linear model is specifically designed to directly estimate prevalence ratios in cross-sectional studies. Notably, when applied to binomial data, the Poisson regression with robust variance avoids convergence issues. Furthermore, in cases where the outcome variable is common, particularly with a prevalence exceeding 10&#x000a0;%, the odds ratio may overestimate the prevalence ratio, making the Poisson model a more appropriate choice for our analysis. Variables with p-values less than 0.25 in the bivariable analysis were included in the multivariable analysis. To find out if there was multicollinearity between the independent variables, the variance inflation factor (VIFs) and the correlation matrix for the regression coefficients were utilized. The VIF values were all below 2, suggesting that multicollinearity is not a significant concern. Additionally, the matrix indicated that the correlations were generally low. The Bayesian information criterion and Akaike's criteria were used to choose the final model. Pearson's Chi-square and the Hosmer-Lemeshow goodness-of-fit test were used to evaluate the model's fitness. To report the data, adjusted prevalence ratios (APRs) with a 95&#x000a0;% confidence interval were used. A P value less than 0.05 was designated as the statistically significant level.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><label>3</label><title>Result</title><sec id="sec3.1"><label>3.1</label><title>Socio-demographic characteristics</title><p id="p0085">Of the total of 882 sampled mothers, 866 mothers participated in the study with a response rate of 98.2&#x000a0;%. Of these, 596 (68.8&#x000a0;%), and 567 (65.47&#x000a0;%), of the mothers were under 35 years of age and came from urban areas respectively. About 754(87.1&#x000a0;%) of mothers were married. Regarding the educational status of mothers, 432 (49.88&#x000a0;%) of the mothers completed the secondary education level. Four hundred and sixty-one (53.2&#x000a0;%) mothers had a middle economic status. Almost three-fourths, 641 (74.02&#x000a0;%), of mothers have health insurance. Regarding the time to reach the hospital, 408 mothers responded that less than 30&#x000a0;min is required to reach the hospital (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Sociodemographic characteristics of mothers in eastern Ethiopia, Ethiopia, 2023 (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;866).</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0015">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Variable</th><th>Frequency</th><th>Percentage</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="3" align="left">Age mothers</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x0003c;35 years</td><td align="left">596</td><td align="left">68.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x02265;35 years</td><td align="left">270</td><td align="left">31.2</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left">Residency</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Urban</td><td align="left">567</td><td align="left">65.47</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Rural</td><td align="left">299</td><td align="left">34.53</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left">Educational status of mothers</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Illiterate</td><td align="left">82</td><td align="left">9.47</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Primary education</td><td align="left">102</td><td align="left">11.78</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Secondary education</td><td align="left">432</td><td align="left">49.88</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Collage and above</td><td align="left">250</td><td align="left">28.87</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left">Marital status</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Not married</td><td align="left">112</td><td align="left">12.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Married</td><td align="left">754</td><td align="left">87.1</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left">Income status</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Low</td><td align="left">364</td><td align="left">42.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Medium</td><td align="left">461</td><td align="left">53.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;High</td><td align="left">41</td><td align="left">4.7</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left">Occupational status of mothers</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Housewife</td><td align="left">198</td><td align="left">22.86</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Merchant</td><td align="left">212</td><td align="left">24.48</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Government/private employee</td><td align="left">424</td><td align="left">48.96</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Farmer</td><td align="left">32</td><td align="left">3.7</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left">Have health insurance</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Yes</td><td align="left">641</td><td align="left">74.02</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;No</td><td align="left">225</td><td align="left">25.98</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left">Time to reach a health facility</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Below 30&#x000a0;min</td><td align="left">408</td><td align="left">47.11</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;30&#x02013;60&#x000a0;min</td><td align="left">298</td><td align="left">34.41</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Above 1&#x000a0;h</td><td align="left">160</td><td align="left">18.48</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><label>3.2</label><title>Obstetrics-related characteristics</title><p id="p0090">Of the total of participants, 605 (69.86&#x000a0;%) of the mothers were multigravida. More than three-fourths (79.21&#x000a0;%) of the mothers had ANC follow-up. There were 86 (9.93&#x000a0;%) mothers with a history of neonatal loss. More than a third (27.02&#x000a0;%) of mothers experienced obstetric complications in the last pregnancy. There were 800 (92.38&#x000a0;%) mothers with a single pregnancy. There were 41 (4.73&#x000a0;%) home deliveries. Of the total of the respondents, 61 (7.04&#x000a0;%) of the mothers experienced adverse fetal outcomes in recent pregnancy (<xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Obstetrics-related characteristics of the mothers in eastern Ethiopia, 2023 (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;866).</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0020">Table 2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Variables</th><th>Frequency</th><th>Percentage</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="3" align="left">ANC follow-up</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Yes</td><td align="left">686</td><td align="left">79.21</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;No</td><td align="left">180</td><td align="left">20.79</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left">Gravidity</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Primigravida</td><td align="left">261</td><td align="left">30.14</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Multigravida</td><td align="left">605</td><td align="left">69.86</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left">History of neonatal loss</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Yes</td><td align="left">86</td><td align="left">9.93</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;No</td><td align="left">780</td><td align="left">90.07</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left">Presence of pregnancy complications</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Yes</td><td align="left">234</td><td align="left">27.02</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;No</td><td align="left">632</td><td align="left">72.98</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left">No fetus in the last pregnancy</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Single</td><td align="left">800</td><td align="left">92.38</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Multiple</td><td align="left">66</td><td align="left">7.62</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left">Place of delivery</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Home</td><td align="left">41</td><td align="left">4.73</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Health facility</td><td align="left">825</td><td align="left">95.27</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left">Experience adverse fetal outcome in recent pregnancy</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;No</td><td align="left">805</td><td align="left">92.96</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Yes</td><td align="left">61</td><td align="left">7.04</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>ANC&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;Antenatal Care.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec3.3"><label>3.3</label><title>Herbal medicine use</title><p id="p0095">The prevalence of the use of herbal medicine among pregnant women in eastern Ethiopia was 43.2&#x000a0;% (95&#x000a0;% CI 39.9,46.5). The most commonly used herbal medicine were <italic>Ocimum lamiifolium</italic> 109 (12.6&#x000a0;%), <italic>Pumpkin fruit</italic> 68(7.9&#x000a0;%), <italic>Rutachalepensis</italic> (tenadam) 61(7&#x000a0;%), <italic>Feto</italic> 45(5.2&#x000a0;%), and <italic>Ginger</italic> 41(4.7&#x000a0;%). The most common indications for the use of herbal medicines were Vomiting 76(20.3&#x000a0;%), Fever 76(20.3&#x000a0;%), Taeniases 64(17.1&#x000a0;%), Nausea 54(14.4&#x000a0;%), and Abdominal pain 36 (9.6&#x000a0;%). Of the mothers who used herbal medicine in the recent pregnancy, 79 (21.1&#x000a0;%) experienced unwanted side effects. The most common reason for the use of herbal Medicine was maternal illness during pregnancy 151 (40.4&#x000a0;%) and perceiving its safety during pregnancy147 (39.3&#x000a0;%) (<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Herbal medicine use and related characteristics of mothers in eastern Ethiopia, Ethiopia, 2023 (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;866).</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0025">Table 3</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Variable</th><th>Frequency</th><th>Percentage</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="3" align="left">Herbal Medicine Uses during Recent Pregnancy</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Yes</td><td align="left">374</td><td align="left">43.19</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;No</td><td align="left">492</td><td align="left">56.81</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left">Type of Herbal Medicine Used by mothers (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;374)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<italic>Zingiber officinale</italic> (<italic>Ginger)</italic></td><td align="left">41</td><td align="left">10.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<italic>Allium sativum (Garlic)</italic></td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">1.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<italic>Eucalyptus</italic> spp. <italic>(Eucalyptus)</italic></td><td align="left">26</td><td align="left">6.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<italic>Leonotis nepetifolia (Tenaadam)</italic></td><td align="left">61</td><td align="left">16.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<italic>Ocimum lamiifolium (Damakese)</italic></td><td align="left">109</td><td align="left">29.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<italic>Ficus thonningii (Feto)</italic></td><td align="left">45</td><td align="left">12</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<italic>Cucurbita pepo (Pumpkin fruit orDuba fire)</italic></td><td align="left">68</td><td align="left">18.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<italic>Linum usitatissimum (Telba)</italic></td><td align="left">20</td><td align="left">5.3</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left">Indication for Herbal Medicine Use (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;374)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Nausea</td><td align="left">54</td><td align="left">14.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Vomiting</td><td align="left">76</td><td align="left">20.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Abdominal pain</td><td align="left">36</td><td align="left">9.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Cold</td><td align="left">15</td><td align="left">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Amebiasis</td><td align="left">11</td><td align="left">2.94</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Fever</td><td align="left">76</td><td align="left">20.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Taeniases</td><td align="left">64</td><td align="left">17.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Typhoid fever</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0.27</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Tonsilitis</td><td align="left">32</td><td align="left">8.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Diarrhea</td><td align="left">9</td><td align="left">2.4</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left">Route of medicine administration (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;374)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Oral</td><td align="left">315</td><td align="left">84.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Topical</td><td align="left">40</td><td align="left">10.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Intra vaginal</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Intra nasal</td><td align="left">18</td><td align="left">4.8</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left">Gestational age where medication administered (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;374)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;At specific gestation</td><td align="left">137</td><td align="left">36.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Throughout pregnancy</td><td align="left">237</td><td align="left">63.3</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left">Experience unwanted side effects of medicine (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;374)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Yes</td><td align="left">79</td><td align="left">21.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;No</td><td align="left">295</td><td align="left">78.9</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left">Common reported side effects (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;79)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Burning sensation</td><td align="left">51</td><td align="left">64.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Vomiting</td><td align="left">17</td><td align="left">21.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Diarrhea</td><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">6.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Abdominal pain</td><td align="left">6</td><td align="left">7.6</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left">Reason for herbal use (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;374)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Safe in pregnancy</td><td align="left">147</td><td align="left">39.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Believes in the effectiveness of herbal medicines</td><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">1.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Part of our culture to use it</td><td align="left">71</td><td align="left">19</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Maternal illness during pregnancy</td><td align="left">151</td><td align="left">40.4</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left">Source of information for herbal use (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;374)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Traditional medicine healers</td><td align="left">72</td><td align="left">19.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Self-preparation</td><td align="left">25</td><td align="left">6.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Family members</td><td align="left">273</td><td align="left">73</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Media</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">1.07</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec3.4"><label>3.4</label><title>Distribution of herbal medicine use among different type of adverse fetal outcomes</title><p id="p0100"><italic>Leonotis nepetifolia (Tenaadam)</italic> use was high among mothers who experienced stillbirth compared to other adverse fetal outcomes. <italic>Ocimum lamiifolium (Damakese)</italic> use was high among mothers who experienced preterm birth compared to other adverse fetal outcomes (<xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Distribution of herbal medicine use among different types of adverse fetal outcomes in eastern Ethiopia, 2023.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0030">Table 4</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Herbal Medicines</th><th colspan="2">Stillbirth<hr/></th><th colspan="2">LBW<hr/></th><th colspan="2">Preterm<hr/></th><th colspan="2">Congenital anomaly<hr/></th></tr><tr><th>Yes</th><th>No</th><th>Yes</th><th>No</th><th>Yes</th><th>No</th><th>Yes</th><th>No</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><italic>Ginger</italic></td><td align="left">6</td><td align="left">35</td><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">36</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">39</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">41</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Garlic</italic></td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Eucalyptus</italic></td><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">21</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">26</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">23</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">26</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Tenaadam</italic></td><td align="left">14</td><td align="left">47</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">46</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">61</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">58</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Ocimum lamiifolium (Damakese)</italic></td><td align="left">9</td><td align="left">100</td><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">104</td><td align="left">11</td><td align="left">98</td><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">104</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Feto</italic></td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">41</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">44</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">42</td><td align="left">6</td><td align="left">39</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Pumpkin fruit (Duba fire)</italic></td><td align="left">6</td><td align="left">62</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">68</td><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">63</td><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">63</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Linen (Telba)</italic></td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">20</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">18</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">20</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">20</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>LBW&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;Low Birth Weight.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec3.5"><label>3.5</label><title>Factors associated with the use of herbal medicine</title><p id="p0105">Rural residency, history of neonatal loss, presence of complications of obstetrics during recent pregnancy, lack of ANC follow-up, multigravida, and adverse fetal outcomes were significantly associated with the use of herbal medicines in the bivariate Poisson regression model. After controlling for possible confounders in the multivariate Poisson regression model, variables such as rural residency, presence of obstetric complications during recent pregnancy, and having adverse fetal outcomes were significantly associated with the use of herbal medicines.</p><p id="p0110">The prevalence of herbal medicine use among rural residents was 1.27 times [APR&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1.27, 95%CI (1.01,1.59)] higher than urban residents. The prevalence of herbal medicine use among mothers who had obstetric complications in recent pregnancy increased by 42&#x000a0;% compared to mothers without the condition [APR&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1.42, 95%CI: (1.14,1.78)]. The prevalence of herbal use among mothers who experienced adverse fetal outcomes was 1.59 times that of mothers who did not have the conditions [APR&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1.59, 95%CI: (1.05,2.2)] <xref rid="tbl5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Factors associated with herbal Medicine Use among pregnant women in eastern Ethiopia, Ethiopia, 2023.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0035">Table 5</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="2" rowspan="2">Variables</th><th colspan="2">Herbal Use<hr/></th><th rowspan="2">CPR (95&#x000a0;% CI)</th><th rowspan="2">APR (95%CI)</th></tr><tr><th>No</th><th>Yes</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left">Residency</td><td align="left">Urban</td><td align="left">353</td><td align="left">214</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Rural</td><td align="left">139</td><td align="left">160</td><td align="left">1.42(1.16,1.74)<xref rid="tbl5fnb" ref-type="table-fn">b</xref></td><td align="left">1.27(1.01,1.59)<xref rid="tbl5fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left">Age</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;35 years</td><td align="left">352</td><td align="left">244</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02265;35 years</td><td align="left">140</td><td align="left">130</td><td align="left">1.18(0.95,1.45)</td><td align="left">0.98(0.77,1.25)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left">History of neonatal loss</td><td align="left">Yes</td><td align="left">29</td><td align="left">57</td><td align="left">1.63(1.23,2.16) &#x02217;&#x02217;</td><td align="left">1.14(0.82,1.61)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">No</td><td align="left">463</td><td align="left">317</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left">ANC follow-up</td><td align="left">Yes</td><td align="left">405</td><td align="left">281</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">No</td><td align="left">87</td><td align="left">93</td><td align="left">1.26(1,1.59)<xref rid="tbl5fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left">0.93(0.69,1.25)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left">Presence of complications during pregnancy</td><td align="left">Yes</td><td align="left">98</td><td align="left">136</td><td align="left">1.54(1.25,1.91)<xref rid="tbl5fnb" ref-type="table-fn">b</xref></td><td align="left">1.42(1.14,1.78)<xref rid="tbl5fnb" ref-type="table-fn">b</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">No</td><td align="left">394</td><td align="left">238</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left">Place of delivery</td><td align="left">Health facility</td><td align="left">476</td><td align="left">349</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Home</td><td align="left">16</td><td align="left">25</td><td align="left">1.44 (0.96,2.16)</td><td align="left">1.22(0.77,1.91)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left">Gravidity</td><td align="left">Primigravida</td><td align="left">166</td><td align="left">95</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Multigravida</td><td align="left">326</td><td align="left">279</td><td align="left">1.27(1.01,1.60)<xref rid="tbl5fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left">1.12(0.86,1.45)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left">Experience of adverse fetal outcomes</td><td align="left">No</td><td align="left">478</td><td align="left">327</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Yes</td><td align="left">14</td><td align="left">47</td><td align="left">1.90(1.40,2.58)<xref rid="tbl5fnb" ref-type="table-fn">b</xref></td><td align="left">1.52(1.05,2.2)<xref rid="tbl5fnb" ref-type="table-fn">b</xref></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl5fna"><label>a</label><p id="ntpara0010">Significant with P&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05 and.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl5fnb"><label>b</label><p id="ntpara0015">Significant with P&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001, CI= Confidence Interval, CPR= Crude Prevalence Ratio, APR&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;Adjusted Prevalence ratio.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec4"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0115">This study found that 43.2&#x000a0;% of pregnant women in Eastern Ethiopia used herbal medicines, with the most commonly used being <italic>Ocimum lamiifolium</italic> (29.1&#x000a0;%), <italic>pumpkin fruit</italic> (18.2&#x000a0;%), and <italic>Rutachaleensis</italic> (16.3&#x000a0;%). The use of herbal medicines was significantly associated with factors such as rural residency, obstetric complications in recent pregnancies, and adverse fetal outcomes. The study found that the prevalence of herbal medicine use among pregnant women in eastern Ethiopia was found to be 43.2&#x000a0;% (95&#x000a0;% CI:39.9,46.5). The finding of this study is in harmony with a study done in Palestine (40&#x000a0;%) [<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. The possible justification may be the similarity in socioeconomic status of the participants.</p><p id="p0120">The finding of this study is higher than studies done in Woldiya, Ethiopia 22.6&#x000a0;% [<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], Debre tabor, Ethiopia (36.3&#x000a0;%) [<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], Uganda (20&#x000a0;%) [<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], Kenya (12&#x000a0;%) [<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], and Saudi Arabia (33&#x000a0;%) [<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. This finding is also lower than studies done in southern Ethiopia (73.1&#x000a0;%) [<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], Gondar, Ethiopia (48.6&#x000a0;%) [<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], western Ethiopia (50.4&#x000a0;%) [<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], Dessie, Ethiopia (51.2&#x000a0;%) [<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], and Sierra Leone (62.7&#x000a0;%) [<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. A possible justification could be the difference in sample sizes; the sample size of the current study is larger than studies conducted in Ethiopia and other African countries,. The other potential discrepancy is the study setting; the studies were conducted in health institutions. The current study is conducted in a community setting, which can include women who miss ANC follow-up. A systematic review and meta-analysis conducted in Ethiopia highlighted that the effects of available herbal medications on the fetus have not been thoroughly studied, making it difficult to rule out potential adverse maternal and fetal outcomes. Therefore, traditional healers and medical professionals need to collaborate in disseminating critical information about these medications to mitigate any negative effects [<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. To address safety concerns and negative effects, more research is necessary, as this study suggests that herbal medications are commonly used in eastern Ethiopia. Additionally, healthcare professionals should be educated about the potential risks associated with herbal medicine use among pregnant women. In this study, rural residency was significantly associated with the use of herbal medicines. The prevalence of herbal medicine use among rural residents was 1.27 times [APR&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1.27, 95%CI (1.01,1.59)] higher than urban residents. This finding is consistent with previous studies conducted in Ethiopia and Nigeria [<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. This might be due to mothers living in rural areas being more prone to experience problems with the accessibility and affordability of contemporary medicine, leading them to turn to herbal remedies. The high prevalence of herbal medicines use among rural residents may also be due to the lack of information available on the risks associated with the use of herbal medicines, as well as the fact that pregnant women in rural areas have less access to health facilities than those in urban areas [<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].</p><p id="p0125">We found that experiencing obstetric complications during a recent pregnancy was significantly associated with the use of herbal medicines. The prevalence of herbal medicine uses among mothers who had obstetric complications in recent pregnancy was 1.42 times higher compared to mothers without the condition. This finding is in line with studies done in Ethiopia [<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. This may be due to the fact that most women in this study accessed herbalist information and may be convinced to use medicines to treat the complications. The other possible reason may be the previous experience of using medication to treat health problems [<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Furthermore, in this study, nearly half of mothers who used herbal medicines believed that herbal medicines are safe to use during pregnancy.</p><p id="p0130">In this study, the experience of adverse fetal outcomes in recent pregnancy was significantly associated with the use of herbal medicines. The prevalence of herbal medicine uses among mothers who experienced adverse fetal outcomes was 1.59 times that of mothers who did not have the condition [APR&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1.59, 95%CI: (1.05,2.2)]. This finding is in agreement with studies done in China [<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>] and Malaysia [<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. However, the finding is in contrast with a study done in Sweden [<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. This may be attributed to prior experience with using medications to address health issues. Consequently, it is crucial to evaluate both the risks and benefits of herbal medicines by conducting further safety investigations and clinical trials with larger sample sizes to confirm their safety during pregnancy [<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>].</p><sec id="sec4.1"><label>4.1</label><title>Clinical implications</title><p id="p0135">The clinical implications of this study are significant and multifaceted, particularly in the context of complementary and alternative medicine (CAM), including herbal products. With the increasing global interest in CAM, healthcare providers need to recognize both the potential benefits and risks associated with herbal medicine use [<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>, <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>, <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>, <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>]. Herbal medicines, often perceived as natural and safe, are widely used by pregnant women, but their effects on maternal and fetal health are not always well understood. This study highlights the importance of incorporating herbal medicine use into routine prenatal care assessments. Healthcare providers should provide appropriate counseling to pregnant women about the potential risks and benefits of herbal products, ensuring that they are informed and supported in their choices. Pregnant women who report using herbal medicines should undergo a thorough risk assessment and be monitored throughout their pregnancy. The findings of this study can help inform the development of evidence-based guidelines or protocols tailored to the local context, which take into account cultural practices and beliefs surrounding herbal medicine use. Overall, this study underscores the growing relevance of integrating knowledge about herbal medicine use into contemporary healthcare practices. As the use of CAM continues to rise, it is crucial to develop comprehensive strategies that promote informed decision-making and ensure the safety and well-being of both pregnant women and their unborn babies in Eastern Ethiopia.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.2"><label>4.2</label><title>Research implications</title><p id="p0140">The study highlights the need for further research to better understand the mechanisms underlying the association between herbal medicine use during pregnancy and adverse fetal outcomes. Collaborative efforts between healthcare providers, researchers, traditional healers, and community members can help identify effective interventions and strategies to mitigate risks and improve maternal and child health outcomes in Eastern Ethiopia.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.3"><label>4.3</label><title>Strengths and limitations</title><p id="p0145">The strength of the study is that study was conducted in multiple areas of eastern Ethiopia. The limitation of this study was that it might not indicate a cause-effect relationship due to the nature of the study. There may be recall bias in the listing of the herbs. Furthermore, the study was conducted in eastern Ethiopia, which may limit the generalizability of the findings to other areas with different demographic, cultural, or healthcare contexts.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec5"><label>5</label><title>Conclusion</title><p id="p0150">The study found that more than two out of five mothers used herbal medicines during their recent pregnancies. It identified significant associations between herbal medicine use and factors such as rural residency, obstetric complications during the current pregnancy, and adverse fetal outcomes. Therefore, it is crucial to verify the efficacy and safety of herbal medicines before they are used during pregnancy. A collaborative strategy involving herbalists, communities with strong beliefs in herbal remedies, and healthcare professionals should be developed to mitigate the risks associated with indiscriminate herbal medicine use and to address the diverse health needs of pregnant women.</p></sec><sec id="sec7"><title>CRediT authorship contribution statement</title><p id="p0160"><bold>Tamirat Getachew:</bold> Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing, Writing &#x02013; original draft, Visualization, Validation, Supervision, Investigation, Formal analysis, Conceptualization. <bold>Abera Kenay Tura:</bold> Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing, Writing &#x02013; original draft, Visualization, Validation, Supervision, Methodology, Conceptualization. <bold>Merga Dheresa:</bold> Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing, Writing &#x02013; original draft, Visualization, Validation, Software, Methodology, Formal analysis, Data curation. <bold>Shamble Niguse:</bold> Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing, Writing &#x02013; original draft, Visualization, Validation, Investigation, Funding acquisition, Conceptualization. <bold>Bikila Balis:</bold> Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing, Writing &#x02013; original draft, Visualization, Project administration, Methodology, Funding acquisition, Formal analysis. <bold>Lemma Demissie Regassa:</bold> Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing, Writing &#x02013; original draft, Supervision, Resources, Methodology, Investigation, Formal analysis. <bold>Addis Eyeberu:</bold> Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing, Writing &#x02013; original draft, Visualization, Validation, Supervision, Methodology, Investigation, Formal analysis, Conceptualization.</p></sec><sec id="sec8"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="p0165">Ethical clearance was obtained from Haramaya University, the Faculty of Health and Medical Sciences, Institutional Health Research Ethics Review Committee (IHRERC). The ethical approval ref.no was IHRERC/225/2021. Informed, voluntary, written, and signed consent was obtained from study participants before data collection. The study was carried out in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki.</p></sec><sec id="sec9"><title>Consent to publication</title><p id="p0170">Non-applicable.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="sec10"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p id="p0175">All necessary data are included in the manuscript. However, additional data are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></sec><sec id="sec11"><title>Funding</title><p id="p0180">This work was supported by <funding-source id="gs1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100004845</institution-id><institution>Haramaya University</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> [grant number HURG_2021_02_04_71].</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Declaration of competing interest</title><p id="p0185">The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khadivzadeh</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghabel</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Complementary and alternative medicine use in pregnancy in Mashhad, Iran, 2007-8</article-title><source>Iran. J. Nurs. Midwifery Res.</source><volume>17</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>263</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23833624</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holst</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The use and the user of herbal remedies during pregnancy</article-title><source>J. Alternative Compl. Med.</source><volume>15</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>787</fpage><lpage>792</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lapi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Use, attitudes and knowledge of complementary and alternative drugs (CADs) among pregnant women: a preliminary survey in Tuscany</article-title><source>Evid. base Compl. Alternative Med.</source><volume>7</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>477</fpage><lpage>486</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nordeng</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Havnen</surname><given-names>G.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of herbal drugs in pregnancy: a survey among 400 Norwegian women</article-title><source>Pharmacoepidemiol. Drug Saf.</source><volume>13</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2004</year><fpage>371</fpage><lpage>380</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15170766</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maats</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Crowther</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Patterns of vitamin, mineral and herbal supplement use prior to and during pregnancy</article-title><source>Aust. N. Z. J. Obstet. Gynaecol.</source><volume>42</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2002</year><fpage>494</fpage><lpage>496</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12495093</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hepner</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Herbal medicine use in parturients</article-title><source>Anesth. Analg.</source><volume>94</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2002</year><fpage>690</fpage><lpage>693</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11867399</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heydarpour</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of medicinal herbs use during pregnancy in the world: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Journal of Chemical Health Risks</source><volume>12</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>183</fpage><lpage>196</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aljofan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alkhamaiseh</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence, and factors influencing the use of herbal medicines during pregnancy in Hail, Saudi Arabia: a cross-sectional study</article-title><source>Sultan Qaboos University Medical Journal</source><volume>20</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>e71</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32190372</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jaradat</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adawi</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of herbal medicines during pregnancy in a group of Palestinian women</article-title><source>J. Ethnopharmacol.</source><volume>150</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>79</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23933314</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nyeko</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tumwesigye</surname><given-names>N.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Halage</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence and factors associated with the use of herbal medicines during pregnancy among women attending postnatal clinics in Gulu district, Northern Uganda</article-title><source>BMC Pregnancy Childbirth</source><volume>16</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26728010</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mothupi</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of herbal medicine during pregnancy among women with access to public healthcare in Nairobi, Kenya: a cross-sectional survey</article-title><source>BMC Compl. Alternative Med.</source><volume>14</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>432</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>James</surname><given-names>P.B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Herbal medicines use during pregnancy in Sierra Leone: an exploratory cross-sectional study</article-title><source>Women Birth</source><volume>31</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>e302</fpage><lpage>e309</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29254852</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaingu</surname><given-names>C.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oduma</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanui</surname><given-names>T.I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Practices of traditional birth attendants in Machakos District, Kenya</article-title><source>J. Ethnopharmacol.</source><volume>137</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>495</fpage><lpage>502</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21679761</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Girmaw</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Herbal medicine use among pregnant women at antenatal clinic in Ethiopia</article-title><source>Heliyon</source><volume>9</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2023</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e18408</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Addis</surname><given-names>G.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Workneh</surname><given-names>B.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kahissay</surname><given-names>M.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Herbal medicines use and associated factors among pregnant women in Debre Tabor town, north West Ethiopia: a mixed method approach</article-title><source>BMC complementary medicine and therapies</source><volume>21</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33386071</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laelago</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yohannes</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemango</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of herbal medicine use and associated factors among pregnant women attending antenatal care at public health facilities in Hossana Town, Southern Ethiopia: facility based cross-sectional study</article-title><source>Arch. Publ. Health</source><volume>74</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mekuria</surname><given-names>A.B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prevalence and associated factors of herbal medicine use among pregnant women on antenatal care follow-up at the University of Gondar referral and teaching hospital, Ethiopia: a cross-sectional study</article-title><source>BMC Compl. Alternative Med.</source><volume>17</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>7</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bayisa</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tatiparthi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mulisa</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of herbal medicine among pregnant women on antenatal care at Nekemte Hospital, Western Ethiopia</article-title><source>Jundishapur J. Nat. Pharm. Prod.</source><volume>9</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2014</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adane</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Herbal medicine use and predictors among pregnant women attending antenatal care in Ethiopia: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>BMC Pregnancy Childbirth</source><volume>20</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>John</surname><given-names>L.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shantakumari</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Herbal medicines use during pregnancy: a review from the Middle East</article-title><source>Oman Med. J.</source><volume>30</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>229</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26366255</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tola</surname><given-names>T.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tadesse</surname><given-names>A.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cultural malpractices during pregnancy, childbirth and postnatal period among women of childbearing age in Limmu Genet town, southwest Ethiopia</article-title><source>Sci J Public Health</source><volume>3</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>752</fpage><lpage>756</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Belayneh</surname><given-names>Y.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoseph</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A cross-sectional study of herbal medicine use and contributing factors among pregnant women on antenatal care follow-up at Dessie Referral Hospital, Northeast Ethiopia</article-title><source>BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies</source><volume>22</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34980092</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Diamond-Smith</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Delivery and postpartum practices among new mothers in Laputta, Myanmar: intersecting traditional and modern practices and beliefs</article-title><source>Cult. Health Sex.</source><volume>18</volume><issue>9</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>1054</fpage><lpage>1066</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27212423</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref24"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Withers</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kharazmi</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Traditional beliefs and practices in pregnancy, childbirth and postpartum: a review of the evidence from Asian countries</article-title><source>Midwifery</source><volume>56</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>158</fpage><lpage>170</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29132060</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holst</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nordeng</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haavik</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of herbal drugs during early pregnancy in relation to maternal characteristics and pregnancy outcome</article-title><source>Pharmacoepidemiol. Drug Saf.</source><volume>17</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2008</year><fpage>151</fpage><lpage>159</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17992658</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref26"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balarastaghi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Potential benefits versus hazards of herbal therapy during pregnancy; a systematic review of available literature</article-title><source>Phytother Res.</source><volume>36</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>824</fpage><lpage>841</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35023227</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref27"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Assefa</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>HDSS profile: the kersa health and demographic surveillance system</article-title><source>Int. J. Epidemiol.</source><volume>45</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>94</fpage><lpage>101</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26510420</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref28"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Girma Gudata</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cohort Profile: the Haramaya health and demographic surveillance system (Haramaya HDSS)</article-title><source>Int. J. Epidemiol.</source><volume>51</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>e46</fpage><lpage>e54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34738113</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref29"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Organization</surname><given-names>W.H.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>WHO Global Report on Traditional and Complementary Medicine 2019</part-title><year>2019</year><publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gedefaw</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alemnew</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Demis</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adverse fetal outcomes and its associated factors in Ethiopia: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>BMC Pediatr.</source><volume>20</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31900152</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref33"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fakeye</surname><given-names>T.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adisa</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Musa</surname><given-names>I.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Attitude and use of herbal medicines among pregnant women in Nigeria</article-title><source>BMC Compl. Alternative Med.</source><volume>9</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>7</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref34"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C.C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pregnancy outcomes, embryonic and fetal development in maternal exposure to Chinese medicines</article-title><source>Birth Defects Res. Part C Embryo Today - Rev.</source><volume>99</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>275</fpage><lpage>291</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref35"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yusof</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahdy</surname><given-names>Z.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Noor</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of complementary and alternative medicine in pregnancy and its impact on obstetric outcome</article-title><source>Compl. Ther. Clin. Pract.</source><volume>25</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>163</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref36"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghorat</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of complementary and alternative medicine use and its associated factors among Iranian diabetic patients: a cross-sectional study</article-title><source>Curr. Ther. Res.</source><volume>100</volume><year>2024</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100746</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref37"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharifi</surname><given-names>M.H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Utilization of complementary and alternative medicine among patients with cardiovascular disease in Iran: a cross-sectional study</article-title><source>Traditional and Integrative Medicine</source><year>2024</year><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>23</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref38"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chijan</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The I-CAM-IR: Persian translation, cross-cultural adaptation and revised version of the I-CAM-Q</article-title><source>Tradit. Integr. Med.</source><volume>7</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2022</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref39"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Darani</surname><given-names>N.S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Oxymel: a review of preclinical and clinical studies</article-title><source>Heliyon</source><year>2023</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e22649</object-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="appsec1" sec-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><title>Supplementary data</title><p id="p0195">The following is the Supplementary data to this article:<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc1"><caption><title>Multimedia component 1</title></caption><media xlink:href="mmc1.docx"><alt-text>Multimedia component 1</alt-text></media></supplementary-material></p></sec><ack id="ack0010"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p id="p0190">The authors thank <funding-source id="gs2"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100004845</institution-id><institution>Haramaya University</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source>, College of Health and Medical Sciences (CHMS), for giving us the opportunity and support to perform this research.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="appsec2" fn-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><p id="p0200">Supplementary data to this article can be found online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e40941" id="intref0010">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e40941</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>