<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="EN" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">ACS Appl Bio Mater</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">ACS Appl Bio Mater</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">mt</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="coden">aabmcb</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>ACS Applied Bio Materials</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2576-6422</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Chemical Society</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40273314</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12093361</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acsabm.5c00307</article-id><article-categories><subj-group><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Virus Detection by
CRISPR-Cas9-Mediated Strand Displacement
in a Lateral Flow Assay</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath1"><name><surname>Montagud-Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>Roser</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">&#x02020;</xref><xref rid="notes-1" ref-type="notes">#</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath2"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9956-0873</contrib-id><name><surname>M&#x000e1;rquez-Costa</surname><given-names>Rosa</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">&#x02020;</xref><xref rid="notes-1" ref-type="notes">#</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath3"><name><surname>Ruiz</surname><given-names>Ra&#x000fa;l</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath4"><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez-Avi&#x000f1;&#x000f3;</surname><given-names>Adri&#x000e0;</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">&#x02021;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath5"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8364-114X</contrib-id><name><surname>Ballesteros-Garrido</surname><given-names>Rafael</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">&#x000a7;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath6"><name><surname>Navarro</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">&#x02225;</xref><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">&#x022a5;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath7"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0980-8298</contrib-id><name><surname>Campins-Falc&#x000f3;</surname><given-names>Pilar</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">&#x02021;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="ath8"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1871-9617</contrib-id><name><surname>Rodrigo</surname><given-names>Guillermo</given-names></name><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="other">*</xref><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>&#x02020;</label>Institute
for Integrative Systems Biology (I2SysBio), <institution>CSIC &#x02013; University of Valencia</institution>, 46980 Paterna, <country>Spain</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>&#x02021;</label>Department
of Analytical Chemistry, School of Chemistry, <institution>University of Valencia</institution>, 46100 Burjassot, <country>Spain</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>&#x000a7;</label>Department
of Organic Chemistry, School of Pharmacy, <institution>University of Valencia</institution>, 46100 Burjassot, <country>Spain</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><label>&#x02225;</label>Microbiology
Service, Clinic University Hospital, <institution>INCLIVA
Biomedical Research Institute</institution>, 46010 Valencia, <country>Spain</country></aff><aff id="aff5"><label>&#x022a5;</label>Department
of Microbiology, School of Medicine, <institution>University
of Valencia</institution>, 46010 Valencia, <country>Spain</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Email: <email>guillermo.rodrigo@csic.es</email>.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>24</day><month>04</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>19</day><month>05</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>4221</fpage><lpage>4229</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>02</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>04</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>10</day><month>04</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2025 The Authors. Published by American Chemical Society</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Authors</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>Permits the broadest form of re-use including for commercial purposes, provided that author attribution and integrity are maintained (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p content-type="toc-graphic"><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mt5c00307_0006" id="ab-tgr1"/></p><p>In public health
emergencies or in resource-constrained settings,
laboratory-based diagnostic methods, such as RT-qPCR, need to be complemented
with accurate, rapid, and accessible approaches to increase testing
capacity, as this will translate into better outcomes in disease prevention
and management. Here, we develop an original nucleic acid detection
platform by leveraging CRISPR-Cas9 and lateral flow immunochromatography
technologies. In combination with an isothermal amplification that
runs with a biotinylated primer, the system exploits the interaction
between the CRISPR-Cas9 R-loop formed upon targeting a specific nucleic
acid and a fluorescein-labeled probe to generate a visual readout
on a lateral flow device. Our method enables rapid, sensitive detection
of nucleic acids, achieving a limit of 1&#x02013;10 copies/&#x003bc;L
in 1 h at a low temperature. We validated the efficacy of the method
by using clinical samples of patients infected with SARS-CoV-2. Compared
with other assays, it operates with more accessible molecular elements
and showcases a robust signal-to-noise ratio. Moreover, multiplexed
detection was demonstrated using primers labeled with biotin and digoxigenin,
achieving the simultaneous identification of target genes on lateral
flow devices with two test lines. We successfully detected SARS-CoV-2
and Influenza A (H1N1) in spiked samples, highlighting the potential
of the method for multiplexed diagnostics of respiratory viruses.
All in all, this represents a versatile and manageable platform for
point-of-care testing, thereby supporting better patient outcomes
and enhanced pandemic preparedness.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>bioanalytics</kwd><kwd>CRISPR diagnostics</kwd><kwd>DNA nanotechnology</kwd><kwd>lateral flow immunochromatography</kwd><kwd>synthetic biology</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Banco Santander</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100010784</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>NA</award-id></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Generalitat Valenciana</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100003359</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>SEJI/2020/011</award-id></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Generalitat Valenciana</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100003359</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>GVA-COVID19/2021/036</award-id></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Generalitat Valenciana</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100003359</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>CIPROM/2023/46</award-id></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Generalitat Valenciana</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100003359</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>CIPROM/2022/21</award-id></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>NextGenerationEU</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100031478</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>NA</award-id></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Ministerio de Ciencia, Innovaci&#x000c3;&#x000b3;n y Universidades</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100014440</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>PRE2019-088531</award-id></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Ministerio de Ciencia, Innovaci&#x000c3;&#x000b3;n y Universidades</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100014440</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>PDC2022-133941-I00</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>document-id-old-9</meta-name><meta-value>mt5c00307</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>document-id-new-14</meta-name><meta-value>mt5c00307</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>ccc-price</meta-name><meta-value/></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Nucleic acid detection has become a standard
approach for precise
disease diagnosis thanks to the rapid advancement of genetic and genomic
sequencing technologies.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref></sup> For infectious
diseases, accurately identifying the causative pathogen is essential
for implementing the correct treatment and containment strategies,
requiring in most cases multiplexed reactions.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref></sup> In the case of nontransmissible diseases, detecting key genetic
variations and biomarkers can enable early intervention before symptoms
appear and the condition worsens.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref></sup> Apart
from clinical diagnostics, nucleic acid detection with high specificity
and sensitivity is vital for applications in epidemiological surveillance,
agricultural biosecurity, environmental monitoring, and biodefense.</p><p>Polymerase chain reaction (PCR) methods are the cornerstone of
diagnostics across various fields.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref></sup> However,
the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref></sup> has underscored the need for diagnostic tools beyond PCR,
ones that do not require expensive equipment or specialized training,
hence facilitating large-scale screening programs. According to the
World Health Organization, these new tools should be affordable, sensitive,
specific, user-friendly, rapid, equipment-free, and deliverable (ASSURED).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref></sup> These characteristics make them ideal for point-of-care
(POC) testing and for use in low-resource settings. Notably, by increasing
testing capacity through a combination of complementary methods, better
outcomes in disease prevention and community-level mitigation could
be achieved.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref></sup></p><p>In recent times, systems
based on clustered regularly interspaced
short palindromic repeats (CRISPR) have found innovative applications
in the realm of specific and sensitive nucleic acid detection.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref></sup> These ribonucleoprotein-based systems are archetypes
because of their programmable sequence specificity, diverse binding
and cleavage mechanisms, and compatibility with advanced nanobiotechnological
developments. Pioneering work disclosed the <italic>trans</italic>-cleavage activity of the nucleases Cas12a and Cas13a (on single-stranded
DNA and RNA, respectively),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref></sup> which was exploited
to produce a suitable readout upon target recognition in combination
with an isothermal preamplification step. Recombinase polymerase amplification
(RPA)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref></sup> is particularly favored for its
simplicity in design and execution, though other amplification methods
could also be employed.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref></sup> The resulting
CRISPR-based approach allows detections with single-nucleotide specificity
and attomolar sensitivity and even the use of lateral flow immunochromatographic
assays (LFAs) for their resolution. However, in these applications
with commercially available strips, the control line is used as the
test line and <italic>vice versa</italic>, which greatly reduces the
sensitivity of the technique and favors the occurrence of false positives.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref></sup></p><p>The CRISPR-Cas9 system can also be repurposed
for nucleic acid
detection. CASLFA (CRISPR-Cas9-mediated lateral flow nucleic acid
assay),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref></sup> FELUDA (<italic>Francisella novicida</italic> Cas9 editor linked uniform detection assay),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref></sup> Bio-SCAN (biotin-coupled specific CRISPR-based assay for
nucleic acid detection),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref></sup> and Vigilant
(VirD2-dCas9 guided and LFA-coupled nucleic acid test)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref></sup> are methods that have been developed to exploit
LFA kits, relying on RPA and CRISPR-Cas9. These techniques depend
on the formation of a suitable CRISPR-dCas9-DNA complex (with dCas9
being a catalytically inactive nuclease) carrying biotin and fluorescein
labels. In particular, CASLFA utilizes a biotinylated primer and a
gold nanoparticle-linked oligonucleotide probe, FELUDA uses a biotinylated
primer and fluorescein-labeled single-guide RNA (sgRNA), Bio-SCAN
employs a fluorescein-labeled primer and a biotinylated dCas9, and
Vigilant combines a biotinylated primer with a dCas9-relaxase fusion
attached to a fluorescein-labeled oligonucleotide.</p><p>In the aforementioned
diagnostic schemes, the test line, which
is more sensitive than the control line, provided the readout. They
have demonstrated limits of detection ranging from attomolar to femtomolar
within approximately 1 h and are capable of discriminating small genetic
variations. Of note, they have been effectively applied to detect
pathogens such as severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2
(SARS-CoV-2), African swine fever virus (ASFV), and <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic>. However, these methods require
the modification of either sgRNA or nuclease, which prevents widespread
and cost-effective application. In addition, despite some efforts
have been made with CASLFA,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref></sup> the multiplexed
detection of different species in the same reaction with the CRISPR-Cas9
system to then be resolved in an LFA needs to be investigated (e.g.,
to discriminate infections produced by different viruses).</p><p>Recently,
we developed a novel nucleic acid detection method based
on CRISPR-Cas9-mediated strand displacement, which we called COLUMBO
(CRISPR-Cas9 R-loop usage for molecular beacon opening).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19">19</xref></sup> This method allowed a multiplexed detection
in a single tube and demonstrated biocomputing capabilities,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">20</xref></sup> thereby complementing the existing CRISPR-based
diagnostic techniques. Nonetheless, it relies on the generation of
a fluorescence signal upon nucleic acid recognition, which precludes
its pervasive application in POC settings. In this work, we report
the modification of COLUMBO that aims to exploit LFAs to resolve the
detection. To this end, we employed biotin- and digoxigenin-labeled
primers for the preamplification step and fluorescein-labeled probes
for the CRISPR-Cas9-mediated strand displacement reactions. Our results
show that a rapid and streamline procedure implemented with attainable
reagents allows the multiplexed detection of different species and
displays ASSURED diagnostic potential.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>Results and Discussion</title><sec id="sec2.1"><title>Molecular
Mechanism and Functional Characterization</title><p>We previously showed
that a CRISPR-Cas9 ribonucleoprotein appropriately
programmed to target a given DNA molecule, typically obtained by a
preamplification step, generates an R-loop that can be exploited to
interact with a molecular beacon supplied in <italic>trans</italic> by means of a toehold-mediated strand displacement reaction, thereby
producing a fluorescence readout.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19">19</xref></sup> Yet,
the detection could also be resolved in an LFA with subtle adaptations.
In typical commercial paper-based devices, gold nanoparticles functionalized
with antifluorescein antibodies are used to detect the presence of
a specific analyte by observing a color change in a test line that
is coated with streptavidin.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref></sup> Here, we
envisioned the use of a biotin-labeled primer to generate DNA amplicons
that can be recognized by streptavidin and the use of a fluorescein-labeled
probe that can interact with the displaced strand of the R-loop in
the protospacer adjacent motif (PAM)-proximal region to be recognized
by the antifluorescein antibody. Thus, the formation of the quaternary
complex upon DNA targeting by the CRISPR-Cas9 ribonucleoprotein and
subsequent interaction with the probe would lead to a color change
in the test line (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref></xref>). The intensity of such a band can then be quantified for
an accurate result. Nothing prevents using a fluorescein-labeled primer
and a biotin-labeled probe to obtain a similar visual output. However,
to implement a multiplexed detection, it would be convenient to have
biotin- and digoxigenin-labeled primers together with fluorescein-labeled
probes to exploit commercial lateral flow strips (LFSs).</p><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Schematic overview
of iCOLUMBO. The method can be applied to detect
any nucleic acid (DNA or RNA), including viral genomes. The iCOLUMBO
assay can be completed in less than 1 h from the collected patient
sample to the LFS with the result. (Top) Illustration of the procedure
and molecular mechanism of iCOLUMBO. It uses RT-RPA to implement a
preamplification step with a biotin-labeled primer (recognized by
streptavidin) and then a programmed sgRNA and a fluorescein-labeled
probe (recognized by the antifluorescein antibody) for the specific
CRISPR-Cas9-based detection of the resulting DNA amplicon. (Bottom)
Illustrative scheme of the functioning of the LFS. The formation of
the quaternary complex upon specific DNA detection by the CRISPR-Cas9
ribonucleoprotein and subsequent probe binding leads to a color change
in the test line. B7, biotin. FAM, fluorescein.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mt5c00307_0001" id="gr1" position="float"/></fig><p>To prove the functionality of the system, we considered
the RNA
genome of SARS-CoV-2 as the nucleic acid of interest. Using DNA amplicons
from the N and E genes generated with custom primers by reverse transcription
PCR (RT-PCR), we showed good detection resolution in the LFA with
appropriately programmed ribonucleoproteins (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref></xref>A). In the absence of sgRNA or Cas9, the
test line did not reveal a noticeable signal, stressing that the detection
was mediated by the CRISPR-Cas9 complex. A quantification of the band
intensity in the test line for increasing concentrations of input
DNA revealed a monotonous response and a sensitivity of 5&#x02013;10
nM (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref></xref>B; see
replicates in <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsabm.5c00307/suppl_file/mt5c00307_si_001.pdf">Figure S1</ext-link>). Using dilutions
of the RNA genome and RT-RPA for the preamplification step, we found
a limit of detection for the whole technique of 1&#x02013;10 copies/&#x003bc;L
(<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsabm.5c00307/suppl_file/mt5c00307_si_001.pdf">Figure S2</ext-link>). Importantly, this limit of
detection is comparable to that of quantitative RT-PCR (RT-qPCR).
In addition, we examined the impact of the catalytic activity of Cas9
on the performance of the assay. We used four different versions of
Cas9 to this end, <italic>viz</italic>., the wild-type nuclease (from <italic>Streptococcus pyogenes</italic>), the Cas9 H840A nickase (Cas9n),
which only cleaves the nontargeted strand, the catalytically dead
Cas9 protein (dCas9), which does not produce any cleavage, and an
engineered version of Cas9 with reduced off-target effects (Cas9HF).
All nucleases were able to perform proper detection (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref></xref>C). However, we observed that
the use of Cas9n produced less visual signal in the test line. These
results demonstrate the suitability of this new method, dubbed iCOLUMBO
(immunochromatographic COLUMBO), to perform POC testing.</p><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Detection of
DNA with iCOLUMBO. (A) Image of representative LFSs
in the detection of the DNA amplicons from the N and E genes of SARS-CoV-2.
(i) N gene amplicon. (ii) E gene amplicon. (B) Image of representative
LFSs (right) and quantified intensity of the test line band (left)
for increasing concentrations of DNA (from 0 to 40 nM). (C) Image
of representative LFSs in the detection of DNA for different versions
of Cas9. Represented data in the bar plots correspond to mean &#x000b1;
standard deviation (<italic>n</italic> = 3). Statistical significance
assessed by the Welch&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic>-test, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05. *Statistically significant change, <sup>ns</sup>nonsignificant
change (comparisons against 0). AU, arbitrary units.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mt5c00307_0002" id="gr2" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><title>Mutant Discrimination, Multiplexed Detection, and Comparative
Performance</title><p>The ability to detect mutations with a CRISPR-based
system may be important to discriminate between strains or variants
of an infectious agent, without requiring sequencing, thereby providing
rapid and cost-effective insights about the transmission dynamics.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">21</xref></sup> We introduced artificial mutations in the E
gene amplicon and assessed the ability of iCOLUMBO to detect them.
The system was responsive to a mutation in the PAM, but not to a mutation
in the protospacer (in the PAM-proximal region; <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref></xref>A). The use of Cas9HF neither resulted effective
to detect the mutation in the protospacer, despite we previously found
that this engineered nuclease was instrumental to do so with COLUMBO.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19">19</xref></sup> Arguably, even a slight proportion of quaternary
complexes formed are relevant because of the higher sensitivity of
the LFA. With Bio-SCAN, for instance, the mutations that were detected
also affected the PAM or were deletions of more than one nucleotide.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref></sup> Further work is required to engineer systems
that are suitable to detect arbitrary mutations. In addition, the
simultaneous detection of two different regions of the pathogen genome
may be instrumental in maximizing the accuracy of the detection by
surmounting scenarios at the edge of the signal-to-noise limit. For
that, we employed LFSs with two test lines, one coated with streptavidin
and another with an antidigoxigenin antibody. We performed the multiplexed
detection of the N and E gene amplicons, showing a proper detection
resolution in the LFA (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref></xref>B; see also procedure in <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsabm.5c00307/suppl_file/mt5c00307_si_002.mpg">Video S1</ext-link>).</p><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Detection of mutations and multiple genes with iCOLUMBO. (A) Image
of representative LFSs (right) and quantified intensity of the test
line band (left) in the detection of DNA (E gene of SARS-CoV-2) with
different mutations, which are shown in red in the inset. (B) Image
of representative two-test-line LFSs, together with an illustrative
scheme of the functioning, in the multiplexed detection of DNA (N
and E genes of SARS-CoV-2). (C) Comparative performance assessment.
Scheme of the CRISPR-based detection and image of LFSs in the detection
of DNA (N gene of SARS-CoV-2). (i) CRISPR-Cas9. (ii) CRISPR-Cas12a.
Represented data in the bar plot correspond to means &#x000b1; standard
deviations (<italic>n</italic> = 3). Statistical significance assessed
by the Welch&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic>-test, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c;
0.05. *Statistically significant change, <sup>ns</sup>nonsignificant
change (comparisons against WT). B7, biotin. DIG, digoxigenin. FAM,
fluorescein. AU, arbitrary units.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mt5c00307_0003" id="gr3" position="float"/></fig><p>To realize the nucleic acid detection potential
of iCOLUMBO, we
aimed to compare its performance with that of DETECTR (DNA endonuclease-targeted
CRISPR <italic>trans</italic> reporter).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref></sup> This latter method is based on the CRISPR-Cas12a system and has
been widely applied in recent times, such as to detect SARS-CoV-2<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref22">22</xref></sup> or monkeypox virus.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref23">23</xref></sup> To perform the CRISPR-Cas12a reaction here, we used the nuclease
from <italic>Lachnospiraceae bacterium</italic> and
a probe labeled with fluorescein and biotin. We focused on the detection
of the SARS-CoV-2 N gene amplicon. With CRISPR-Cas9, the test line
was almost clean to the naked eye in the absence of target DNA and
the control line was always colored. By contrast, with CRISPR-Cas12a,
a faint band was observed in the test line in the absence of target
DNA and the band in the control line changed according to the input
(<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref></xref>C). This stresses
the distinctive usage of the commercial LFSs with both systems. It
is important to note that while the <italic>trans</italic>-cleavage
activity of Cas12a serves to obtain a higher dynamic range in a fluorescence-based
assay, the visual signal obtained in an LFA upon Cas9-mediated assembly
is more differential (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsabm.5c00307/suppl_file/mt5c00307_si_001.pdf">Figure S3</ext-link>).</p><p>Notwithstanding, it has been reported that a <italic>trans</italic>-cleavage activity of Cas9 when using a poly(T) probe.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref24">24</xref></sup> This activity appears to be increased if the
ribonucleoprotein is formed with a CRISPR RNA (crRNA) and a <italic>trans</italic>-activating crRNA (tracrRNA), i.e., the natural form.
Using a crRNA targeting the E gene amplicon and the universal tracrRNA,
we did not find any degradation effect on the specific fluorescein-labeled
probe (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsabm.5c00307/suppl_file/mt5c00307_si_001.pdf">Figure S4</ext-link>), suggesting that the
eventual collateral activity of Cas9 is irrelevant within the iCOLUMBO
setup as a result of working with ordinary nonpoly(T) sequences.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><title>Validation with Clinical Samples</title><p>To illustrate the
applicability of the technology, we collected clinical samples from
patients showing symptoms compatible with COVID-19 in order to perform
virus detection assays. Initially, we confirmed the presence of SARS-CoV-2
in the samples by RT-qPCR using the Centers for Disease Control and
Prevention (CDC) N1 primers (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsabm.5c00307/suppl_file/mt5c00307_si_001.pdf">Figure S5</ext-link>).
Infected patient samples showed cycle threshold (C<sub>T</sub>) values
lower than 30. Subsequently, we ran CRISPR-Cas9-based reactions. We
found that the iCOLUMBO assay, targeting both the N and E genes, gave
marked differential readouts in the LFSs that were useful to discriminate
the presence of the virus (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref></xref>A). We used custom primers targeting the N and E genes
of SARS-CoV-2 and RT-RPA (without RNA extraction) for the preamplification
step.</p><fig id="fig4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Detection of SARS-CoV-2 in clinical samples with iCOLUMBO. (A)
Image of representative LFSs (right) and quantified intensity of the
test line band (left) in the detection of the RNA genome of SARS-CoV-2.
(i) N gene amplicon. (ii) E gene amplicon (preamplification by RT-RPA).
(B) Image of representative two-test-line LFSs (bottom) and quantified
intensities of the test line bands (top) in the multiplexed detection
of SARS-CoV-2. Represented data in the bar plots correspond to means
&#x000b1; standard deviations (<italic>n</italic> = 3). Statistical significance
assessed by the Welch&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic>-test, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05. *Statistically significant change, <sup>ns</sup>nonsignificant
change (comparisons against P2). B7, biotin. DIG, digoxigenin. FAM,
fluorescein. AU, arbitrary units.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mt5c00307_0004" id="gr4" position="float"/></fig><p>In addition, we performed multiplexed detection
of the N and E
genes, also obtaining marked differential readouts in the LFSs with
two test lines (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref></xref>B). In this case, RT-RPA was regularly performed with two pairs of
primers, one of them targeting the N gene labeled with biotin and
another targeting the E gene labeled with digoxigenin. This set of
primers showed good compatibility for the multiplexed amplification.
Next, CRISPR-Cas9-based reactions with two different ribonucleoproteins
and probes were carried out. Compared to the single detection, we
noticed more variability between replicates in the results. We also
observed that the system performance could be fine-tuned by optimizing
the relative concentrations of primers and probes used in the reactions.</p><p>These results demonstrate the potential of iCOLUMBO to perform <italic>in vitro</italic> clinical diagnostics in a simple and effective
way. A number of considerations can be drawn. First, RNA extraction
and concentration (e.g., through magnetic beads) are considered as
rate-limiting steps and potential sources for contamination. Our approach
does not involve such steps and allows one to work directly with the
collected sample. Still, further work is required to combine the RT-RPA
and CRISPR-Cas9 reactions, resulting in a one-pot detection procedure.
Second, reactions are implemented with highly attainable molecular
and instrumental elements. Specific nucleic acids can be redesigned
and are easily resynthesized. In the clinic, a computational method
could be used to automate such a design, given the full sequence(s)
of interest. Third, iCOLUMBO has the potential to target a wide range
of infectious agents including viruses and bacteria. Besides, the
assay could be exploited to recognize nucleic acids beyond pathogen
genomes, such as specific genetic markers associated with noncommunicable
diseases (e.g., cancer), providing a powerful tool for early detection
and management.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><title>Multiplexed Detection of Clinically Relevant
Respiratory Viruses</title><p>Infections caused by different respiratory
viruses usually cause
similar symptoms. Therefore, it is important to have methods that
are specific enough to identify the causing agent and adopt the appropriate
treatment. These viruses can even coinfect the host organism.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25">25</xref></sup> Mixed infections are less frequent but lead
to more severe outcomes for the patient, especially in children. In
this regard, we assessed the ability to detect two different viruses
simultaneously in the sample with iCOLUMBO. We focused on SARS-CoV-2
and Influenza A (H1N1). While SARS-CoV-2 has caused the recent COVID-19
pandemic, the evolution and transmission of Influenza has increased
with time, so there is also an elevated risk for public health associated
with this virus.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref26">26</xref></sup> In addition, correctly
identifying infections caused by viruses rather than bacteria in the
respiratory tract is crucial for mitigating the overuse of antibiotics.
Viral infections, such as those caused by SARS-CoV-2 or Influenza,
do not respond to these compounds. Yet, misusing antibiotics for viral
infections contributes to the emergence and evolution of multidrug-resistant
bacteria, which is a growing global health challenge.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref27">27</xref></sup></p><p>Thus, artificial samples spiked with the RNA genomes
of these viruses in a combinatorial manner were prepared. A concentration
of &#x0223c;10<sup>3</sup> copies/&#x003bc;L was considered, as it is
comparable to those found in clinical samples. We designed primers
to amplify the M gene of Influenza A (H1N1) and a new sgRNA and probe
to detect the resulting DNA amplicon with CRISPR-Cas9. One of these
new primers was labeled with biotin to be used in combination with
those targeting the E gene of SARS-CoV-2 (labeled with digoxigenin)
in the multiplexed RT-RPA and subsequent detection step. Multiplexed
amplifications are always critical and may require screening various
sets of primers; the primers here considered showed adequate compatibility
(<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsabm.5c00307/suppl_file/mt5c00307_si_001.pdf">Figure S6</ext-link>). In first place, we verified
that the single detection of Influenza A (H1N1) was possible with
the designed elements (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsabm.5c00307/suppl_file/mt5c00307_si_001.pdf">Figure S7</ext-link>). Then,
we found that iCOLUMBO allowed multiplexed detection of the case study
respiratory viruses employing the LFSs with two test lines (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref></xref>). The method distinguished
between samples containing either SARS-CoV-2, Influenza A (H1N1),
or both, without noteworthy cross-reactivity. Yet, we noticed that
the band intensity in the first test line was lower, suggesting that
the designed elements to detect Influenza A (H1N1) were less efficient
than those to detect SARS-CoV-2, especially the amplification primers.
Further screening in terms of amplification and detection might be
performed to obtain more efficient nucleic acids. These findings demonstrate
that the challenge of coinfection diagnostics can be addressed with
CRISPR systems. Ultimately, our development is aligned with ensuring
better patient care and strengthening pandemic preparedness efforts.</p><fig id="fig5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Multiplexed
detection of SARS-CoV-2 and Influenza A (H1N1) with
iCOLUMBO. Image of representative two-test-line LFSs (right) and quantified
intensities of the test line bands (left) in the multiplexed detection
of the RNA genomes of SARS-CoV-2 and Influenza A (H1N1) (preamplification
by RT-RPA). Represented data in the bar plot correspond to means &#x000b1;
standard deviations (<italic>n</italic> = 3). Statistical significance
assessed by the Welch&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic>-test, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05. *Statistically significant change, <sup>ns</sup>nonsignificant
change (comparisons against &#x02300;). SARS2, and SARS-CoV-2. InfA,
Influenza A (H1N1). B7, biotin. DIG, digoxigenin. AU, arbitrary units.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mt5c00307_0005" id="gr5" position="float"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>Conclusions</title><p>This study sought to
develop a nucleic acid detection method applicable
to virus detection that effectively balanced the specificity, sensitivity,
and POC potential. To this end, we relied on the CRISPR-Cas9 system
for the detection, with a preamplification step of RT-RPA, and the
LFA technology to produce a visual output. The proposed method does
not rely on <italic>trans</italic>-cleavage but on logic nucleic acid
intermolecular interactions, and it uses commercial LFSs for a simple
and cost-effective detection. The iCOLUMBO assay is completed in less
than 1 h with high specificity and sensitivity, hence providing rapid,
visual, and precise results. It does not require an initial step of
RNA extraction or concentration, shows an attomolar limit of detection
(i.e., &#x0003c; 100 copies/&#x003bc;L in the collected sample), and allows
a multiplexed detection of different nucleic acid species. It operates
at a low constant temperature (37&#x02013;42 &#x000b0;C), eliminating
the need for temperature cycling. By employing CRISPR-Cas9 complexes
for posterior recognition, the method effectively reduces the false
positives generated by spurious amplifications, then enhancing specificity,
in addition to provide a way to identify mutations, especially those
that affect a PAM (with the aim to genotype a pathogen). Importantly,
the evaluation of various clinical nasopharyngeal swab samples revealed
that iCOLUMBO displayed the required specificity and sensitivity to
obtain reliable diagnoses in the clinic, hence being a potential complement
to the gold-standard RT-qPCR technique. It was applied to detect the
RNA genomes of SARS-CoV-2 and Influenza A (H1N1). Furthermore, this
assay may be accessible in low-income countries to monitor and control
the spread of infectious diseases, which cause millions of deaths
every year (especially those that affect the respiratory tract).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref28">28</xref></sup> With an in-house production system of purified
enzymes and strips, the unit cost of the assay may be drastically
reduced and be competitive in the market. In sum, this advance for
nucleic acid detection by leveraging the CRISPR-Cas9 system may significantly
contribute toward the effective deployment of ASSURED diagnostic techniques
in POC settings. We envision exciting applications of iCOLUMBO in
the near future.</p></sec><sec id="sec4"><title>Methods</title><sec id="sec4.1"><title>Clinical Samples</title><p>Nasopharyngeal swab samples from patients
infected with SARS-CoV-2 and noninfected patients were gathered in
the Clinic University Hospital of Valencia (Spain). Samples were treated
with proteinase K followed by a heat shock (5 min at 60 &#x000b0;C) before
proceeding. No RNA extraction was performed. The ethics committee
of the Clinic University Hospital approved this study (order #2020/221).</p></sec><sec id="sec4.2"><title>Spiked Samples</title><p>Samples of total RNA from human embryonic
kidney (HEK293T) cells at 5 ng/&#x003bc;L, extracted using RNAzol RT
(Merck), were spiked with the complete and purified RNA genomes of
SARS-CoV-2 and Influenza A (H1N1) (Vircell) in a combinatorial way
at the final concentration of 5&#x000b7;10<sup>3</sup> copies/&#x003bc;L
each. These samples were used to perform multiplexed detection of
different respiratory viruses.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.3"><title>Purified DNA Amplicons</title><p>From the complete RNA genome
of SARS-CoV-2 (Vircell), RT-PCRs were performed to generate suitable
DNA amplicons of the N and E genes. The TaqPath 1-step RT-qPCR master
mix, CG (Applied) was used, with 52 copies/&#x003bc;L RNA genome and
250 nM custom primers. The reverse primer was labeled with biotin
or digoxigenin in its 5&#x02032; end. The protocol consisted of an
initial step at 25 &#x000b0;C for 2 min for uracil-N-glycosylation and
50 &#x000b0;C for 15 min for RT, then an inactivation step at 95 &#x000b0;C
for 2 min, followed by 40 cycles of amplification at 95 &#x000b0;C for
15 s and 60 &#x000b0;C for 60 s. RT-PCR products were purified using
the DNA clean and concentrator column (Zymo) and quantified in a spectrophotometer
(NanoDrop, Thermo). Besides, E gene amplicons with different single-base
mutations were chemically synthesized (IDT), and then amplified by
PCR to label with biotin.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.4"><title>CRISPR Elements</title><p>Four versions of <italic>S.
pyogenes</italic> Cas9 (IDT) were used: the wild-type nuclease
(Cas9), the Cas9 H840A nickase (Cas9n), the catalytically dead Cas9
protein (dCas9),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref29">29</xref></sup> and a high-fidelity
nuclease with similar on-target potency to the wild-type but significantly
reduced off-target effects (Cas9HF). The <italic>L. bacterium</italic> Cas12a (NEB) was used to implement the CRISPR-Cas12a reactions.
In addition, sgRNAs were produced by <italic>in vitro</italic> transcription
with the TranscriptAid T7 high yield transcription kit (Thermo) from
DNA templates (sequences are provided in <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsabm.5c00307/suppl_file/mt5c00307_si_001.pdf">Table S1</ext-link>). They were purified using the RNA clean and concentrator
column (Zymo) and quantified in a spectrophotometer (NanoDrop, Thermo).</p></sec><sec id="sec4.5"><title>Nucleic Acid Detection by RT-qPCR</title><p>The TaqPath 1-step
RT-qPCR master mix, CG (Applied) was used. In a microplate (Applied),
2 &#x003bc;L of clinical sample, 500 nM CDC N1 primers, 125 nM probe
(SARS-CoV-2 RUO kit, IDT), and RT-qPCR mix were combined for a total
volume of 20 &#x003bc;L. The microplate was loaded into a real-time
PCR system (QuantStudio 3, Applied) for fluorescence measurement,
and the following protocol was employed: an initial step of 25 &#x000b0;C
for 2 min for uracil-N-glycosylation, then a step of 53 &#x000b0;C for
10 min for RT, 95 &#x000b0;C for 2 min for RT inactivation, followed
by 40 cycles of 95 &#x000b0;C for 3 s for denaturation and 60 &#x000b0;C
for 30 s for annealing and extension. Samples with C<sub>T</sub> values
lower than 40 were considered positive for SARS-CoV-2 infection.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.6"><title>Nucleic Acid Amplification by RT-RPA</title><p>The TwistAmp basic
kit (TwistDX) was used. 500 U RevertAid (Thermo), 50 U RNase inhibitor
(Thermo), and 480 nM custom forward and reverse primers were added
to 29.5 &#x003bc;L rehydration buffer. Primers targeting the N and E
genes of SARS-CoV-2 and the M gene of Influenza A (H1N1) were used
(sequences are provided in <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsabm.5c00307/suppl_file/mt5c00307_si_001.pdf">Table S1</ext-link>). The
reverse primer was labeled with biotin or digoxigenin in its 5&#x02032;
end. In the case of multiplexed amplifications, 360 nM primers were
used. The TwistAmp basic reaction pellet was resuspended, then splitting
into two the resulting volume. To start the reaction, 1 &#x003bc;L patient
or spiked sample and 7 mM magnesium acetate were added. Reactions
were incubated at 42 &#x000b0;C for 30 min in a thermomixer (Eppendorf).</p></sec><sec id="sec4.7"><title>Nucleic Acid Detection with CRISPR-Cas9</title><p>CRISPR reactions
were performed in 1&#x000d7; Tris/Acetate/EDTA (TAE) buffer pH 8.5 (Invitrogen),
0.05% Tween 20, and 12.5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub> at a final volume of
20 &#x003bc;L. In the case of DNA amplicon detection (from the E and
N genes of SARS-CoV-2), 100 nM CRISPR-Cas9 ribonucleoprotein, previously
assembled at room temperature for 30 min, was mixed with 40 nM amplified
DNA (unless otherwise specified) and 100 nM ssDNA probe (labeled with
fluorescein). For the SARS-CoV-2 RNA genome detection in clinical
samples, 2 &#x003bc;L RT-RPA product was used rather than a definite
DNA amount. For the multiplexed detection of the SARS-CoV-2 E and
N genes, the probe interacting with the E amplicon was added at 50
nM, while the concentration of all other species remained unaltered.
For the multiplexed detection of the SARS-CoV-2 and Influenza A (H1N1)
RNA genomes in spiked samples, 1 &#x003bc;L RT-RPA product and 100 nM
of each of the probes were used. Reactions were incubated at 37 &#x000b0;C
for 20 min in a thermomixer (Eppendorf).</p></sec><sec id="sec4.8"><title>Nucleic Acid Detection
with CRISPR-Cas12a</title><p>Reactions
were performed in NEBuffer 2.1 (10 mM Tris-HCl pH 7.9, 50 mM NaCl,
10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, and 100 &#x003bc;g/mL bovine serum albumin;
NEB). 50 nM CRISPR-Cas12a ribonucleoprotein, previously assembled
at room temperature for 30 min, was mixed with 40 nM amplified DNA
and 100 nM ssDNA probe (labeled with fluorescein and biotin) to make
a total volume of 20 &#x003bc;L. Reactions were incubated at 37 &#x000b0;C
for 20 min in a thermomixer (Eppendorf).</p></sec><sec id="sec4.9"><title>Lateral Flow Assay</title><p>After completing the CRISPR reactions,
80 &#x003bc;L of GenLine Dipstick buffer (Milenia) was carefully added
for a 1:5 dilution. The LFS (HybriDetect, Milenia) was soaked into
the reaction tube for 4 min, and images were captured with a gel documentation
system (Uvidoc HD6, Uvitec). Quantification of the band intensity
in the test line was done with Fiji.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref30">30</xref></sup> Moreover,
to perform a quantitative characterization of the strip, different
mixtures of fluorescein, biotin, and ssDNA probe labeled with both
fluorescein and biotin were prepared, maintaining the total level
of biotin at 0.1 or 25 nM. The band intensities in the test and control
lines were monitored by measuring absorbance with a conventional spectrophotometer
(UV&#x02013;vis diffuse reflectance spectroscopy; <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsabm.5c00307/suppl_file/mt5c00307_si_001.pdf">Figures S8 and S9</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="sec4.10"><title>Gel Electrophoresis</title><p>Nucleic acid
amplifications by
PCR or RPA were confirmed by agarose gel electrophoresis. For that,
2 &#x003bc;L of amplified product was used. Samples were loaded on a
3% agarose gel prepared with 0.5&#x000d7; Tris/Borate/EDTA (TBE) buffer,
which was run for 45 min at room temperature (110 V). Gels were stained
using GreenSafe (NZYtech). The GeneRuler ultralow range DNA ladder
(10&#x02013;300 bp, Thermo) was used as a marker.</p></sec></sec></body><back><notes id="notes-2" notes-type="si"><title>Supporting Information Available</title><p>The Supporting Information
is available free of charge at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/10.1021/acsabm.5c00307?goto=supporting-info">https://pubs.acs.org/doi/10.1021/acsabm.5c00307</ext-link>.<list id="silist" list-type="simple"><list-item><p>Additional experimental
results of nucleic acid detection
(Figures S1&#x02013;S9) and nucleotide sequences of the elements used
in this work (Table S1) (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsabm.5c00307/suppl_file/mt5c00307_si_001.pdf">PDF</ext-link>)</p></list-item><list-item><p>Representative multiplexed detection (Video S1) (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsabm.5c00307/suppl_file/mt5c00307_si_002.mpg">MPG</ext-link>)</p></list-item></list></p></notes><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sifile1"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mt5c00307_si_001.pdf"><caption><p>mt5c00307_si_001.pdf</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sifile2"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mt5c00307_si_002.mpg"><caption><p>mt5c00307_si_002.mpg</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><notes notes-type="" id="notes-1"><title>Author Contributions</title><p><sup>#</sup> R.M.-M. and R.M.-C. contributed equally.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement" id="notes-3"><p>The authors
declare the following competing financial interest(s): R.M.-M., R.M.-C.,
R.R., and G.R. declare that they have filled a patent on the use of
the CRISPR-Cas9 R-loop for molecular beacon opening.</p></notes><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>This
work was supported by CRUE and Banco Santander (Fondo
Supera Covid-19), CSIC PTI+ Global Health (NextGenerationEU/PRTR),
Spanish Ministry of Science and Innovation and AEI/10.13039/501100011033
(PDC2022-133941-I00 and PRE2019-088531, cofinanced by NextGenerationEU/PRTR),
and Regional Government of Valencia (SEJI/2020/011, GVA-COVID19/2021/036,
CIPROM/2022/21, and CIPROM/2023/46).</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit1"><name><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Diagnostic
applications of high-throughput DNA sequencing</article-title>. <source>Annu. Rev. Pathol.</source>
<year>2013</year>, <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>381</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>410</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-pathol-020712-164026</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23121054</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit2"><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Nucleic
acid amplification tests for detection of respiratory viruses</article-title>. <source>J. Clin. Virol.</source>
<year>2007</year>, <volume>40</volume>, <fpage>S15</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>S23</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1386-6532(07)70005-7</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18162249</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit3"><name><surname>Gilboa</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Garden</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Single-molecule analysis
of nucleic
acid biomarkers &#x02013; A review</article-title>. <source>Anal. Chim.
Acta</source>
<year>2020</year>, <volume>1115</volume>, <fpage>61</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>85</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aca.2020.03.001</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32370870</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit4"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Rothman</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name>
<article-title>PCR-based
diagnostics for infectious diseases: uses,
limitations, and future applications in acute-care settings</article-title>. <source>Lancet Infect. Dis.</source>
<year>2004</year>, <volume>4</volume>, <fpage>337</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>348</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(04)01044-8</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15172342</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit5"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kaur</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>; et al. <article-title>Wuhan to world: the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title>. <source>Front.
Cell Infect. Microbiol.</source>
<year>2021</year>, <volume>11</volume>, <elocation-id>596201</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fcimb.2021.596201</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33859951</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit6"><name><surname>Mabey</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Peeling</surname><given-names>R. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ustianowski</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Perkins</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Diagnostics for
the developing world</article-title>. <source>Nat. Rev. Microbiol.</source>
<year>2004</year>, <volume>2</volume>, <fpage>231</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>240</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro841</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15083158</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit7"><name><surname>Larremore</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wilder</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lester</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Shehata</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hay</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tambe</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mina</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Test sensitivity
is secondary to frequency and turnaround time for COVID-19 screening</article-title>. <source>Sci. Adv.</source>
<year>2021</year>, <volume>7</volume>, <elocation-id>eabd5393</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/sciadv.abd5393</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33219112</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit8"><name><surname>Kaminski</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Abudayyeh</surname><given-names>O. O.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gootenberg</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name>
<article-title>CRISPR-based
diagnostics</article-title>. <source>Nat. Biomed. Eng.</source>
<year>2021</year>, <volume>5</volume>, <fpage>643</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>656</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41551-021-00760-7</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34272525</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit9"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Harrington</surname><given-names>L. B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Da Costa</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>; et al. <article-title>CRISPR-Cas12a target
binding unleashes indiscriminate single-stranded
DNase activity</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<year>2018</year>, <volume>360</volume>, <fpage>436</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>439</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aar6245</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29449511</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit10"><name><surname>Gootenberg</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Abudayyeh</surname><given-names>O. O.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Essletzbichler</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Dy</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name>; et al. <article-title>Nucleic
acid detection with CRISPR-Cas13a/C2c2</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<year>2017</year>, <volume>356</volume>, <fpage>438</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>442</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aam9321</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28408723</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit11"><name><surname>Piepenburg</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>C. H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Stemple</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Armes</surname><given-names>N. A.</given-names></name>
<article-title>DNA detection using
recombination proteins</article-title>. <source>PLoS Biol.</source>
<year>2006</year>, <volume>4</volume>, <fpage>e204</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.0040204</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16756388</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit12"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Isothermal
amplification of nucleic acids</article-title>. <source>Chem. Rev.</source>
<year>2015</year>, <volume>115</volume>, <fpage>12491</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12545</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.chemrev.5b00428</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26551336</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit13"><name><surname>Posthuma-Trumpie</surname><given-names>G. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Korf</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>van Amerongen</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Lateral flow
(immuno) assay: its
strengths, weaknesses, opportunities and threats. A literature survey</article-title>. <source>Anal. Bioanal. Chem.</source>
<year>2009</year>, <volume>393</volume>, <fpage>569</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>582</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00216-008-2287-2</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18696055</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit14"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Clustered
regularly interspaced short palindromic repeats/Cas9-mediated lateral
flow nucleic acid assay</article-title>. <source>ACS Nano</source>
<year>2020</year>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>2497</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2508</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acsnano.0c00022</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32045522</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit15"><name><surname>Azhar</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Phutela</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ansari</surname><given-names>A. H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Rauthan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; et al. <article-title>Rapid and accurate nucleobase
detection using FnCas9 and its application
in COVID-19 diagnosis</article-title>. <source>Biosens. Bioelectron.</source>
<year>2021</year>, <volume>183</volume>, <elocation-id>113207</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bios.2021.113207</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33866136</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit16"><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>S&#x000e1;nchez</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tehseen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mahas</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Marsic</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; et al. <article-title>Bio-SCAN:
A CRISPR/dCas9-based lateral flow assay for rapid, specific,
and sensitive detection of SARS-CoV-2</article-title>. <source>ACS Synth.
Biol.</source>
<year>2022</year>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>406</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>419</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acssynbio.1c00499</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34939798</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit17"><name><surname>Marsic</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tehseen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mahas</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hamdan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mahfouz</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Vigilant:
an engineered VirD2-Cas9 complex for lateral flow assay-based detection
of SARS-CoV2</article-title>. <source>Nano Lett.</source>
<year>2021</year>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>3596</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3603</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.nanolett.1c00612</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33844549</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit18"><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Yue</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; et al. <article-title>Simultaneous dual-gene diagnosis of SARS-CoV-2
based on CRISPR/Cas9-mediated
lateral flow assay</article-title>. <source>Angew. Chem., Int. Ed.</source>
<year>2021</year>, <volume>60</volume>, <fpage>5307</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5315</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/anie.202014506</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit19"><name><surname>M&#x000e1;rquez-Costa</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Montagud-Martinez</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Marques</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Albert</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Navarro</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Daros</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ruiz</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Rodrigo</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Multiplexable and biocomputational
virus detection by CRISPR-Cas9-mediated strand displacement</article-title>. <source>Anal. Chem.</source>
<year>2023</year>, <volume>95</volume>, <fpage>9564</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9574</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.analchem.3c01041</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37204239</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit20"><name><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Biocomputing
based
on DNA strand displacement reactions</article-title>. <source>ChemPhysChem</source>
<year>2021</year>, <volume>22</volume>, <fpage>1151</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1166</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cphc.202100140</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33871136</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit21"><name><surname>Alpert</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Brito</surname><given-names>A. F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lasek-Nesselquist</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Rothman</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Valesano</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name>; et al. <article-title>Early introductions
and transmission of SARS-CoV-2 variant B.1.1.7
in the United States</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<year>2021</year>, <volume>184</volume>, <fpage>2595</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2604</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2021.03.061</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33891875</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit22"><name><surname>Broughton</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Fasching</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Servellita</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>; et al. <article-title>CRISPR-Cas12-based detection
of SARS-CoV-2</article-title>. <source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source>
<year>2020</year>, <volume>38</volume>, <fpage>870</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>874</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41587-020-0513-4</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32300245</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit23"><name><surname>Low</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>O&#x02019;Neill</surname><given-names>M. T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kerry</surname><given-names>W. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Krysiak</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Papadakis</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; et al. <article-title>Rapid detection of monkeypox virus using a CRISPR-Cas12a mediated
assay: a laboratory validation and evaluation study</article-title>. <source>Lancet Microbe</source>
<year>2023</year>, <volume>4</volume>, <fpage>e800</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>e810</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2666-5247(23)00148-9</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37722405</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit24"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Trans-nuclease activity
of Cas9 activated
by DNA or RNA target binding</article-title>. <source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source>
<year>2025</year>, <volume>43</volume>, <fpage>558</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41587-024-02255-7</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38811761</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit25"><name><surname>Paranhos-Baccal&#x000e0;</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Komurian-Pradel</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Richard</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Vernet</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lina</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Floret</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Mixed respiratory
virus infections</article-title>. <source>J. Clin. Virol.</source>
<year>2008</year>, <volume>43</volume>, <fpage>407</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>410</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jcv.2008.08.010</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18829380</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit26"><name><surname>Harrington</surname><given-names>W. N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kackos</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Webby</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>
<article-title>The evolution
and future of influenza
pandemic preparedness</article-title>. <source>Exp. Mol. Med.</source>
<year>2021</year>, <volume>53</volume>, <fpage>737</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>749</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s12276-021-00603-0</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33953324</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit27"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; et al. <article-title>Assessment of global health risk of antibiotic
resistance genes</article-title>. <source>Nat. Commun.</source>
<year>2022</year>, <volume>13</volume>, <elocation-id>1553</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-022-29283-8</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35322038</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit28"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>B. G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gouws</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Boschi-Pinto</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Bryce</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Dye</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Estimates
of world-wide distribution of child deaths from acute respiratory
infections</article-title>. <source>Lancet Infect. Dis.</source>
<year>2002</year>, <volume>2</volume>, <fpage>25</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>32</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(01)00170-0</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11892493</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit29"><name><surname>Jinek</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Chylinski</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Fonfara</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hauer</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Doudna</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Charpentier</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<article-title>A programmable
dual-RNA-guided DNA endonuclease in
adaptive bacterial immunity</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<year>2012</year>, <volume>337</volume>, <fpage>816</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>821</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1225829</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22745249</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit30"><name><surname>Schindelin</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Arganda-Carreras</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Frise</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kaynig</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Longair</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; et al. <article-title>Fiji:
an open-source platform for biological-image analysis</article-title>. <source>Nat. Methods</source>
<year>2012</year>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>676</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>682</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.2019</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22743772</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>