<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="abstract"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Eur Psychiatry</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Eur Psychiatry</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">EPA</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>European Psychiatry</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0924-9338</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1778-3585</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11862549</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1192/j.eurpsy.2024.735</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="other">EPP0633</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S0924933824007351</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Abstract</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="section"><subject>e-Poster Presentation</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Acute obsessive symptoms: case report of a PANDAS-like syndrome in an adult patient.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>de Vicente Blanco</surname><given-names>&#x000c1;.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1750" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor0596" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Orgaz &#x000c1;lvarez</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1750" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ib&#x000e1;&#x000f1;ez Mendoza</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1750" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Velasco Santos</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1750" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1750"><sup>1</sup><institution>Hospital Universitario La Paz</institution>, <city>Madrid</city>, <country>Spain</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor0596"><label>*</label>Corresponding author.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="collection" iso-8601-date="2024-04"><month>4</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>67</volume><issue seq="710">Suppl 1</issue><issue-title content-type="special_issue">Abstracts of the 32nd European Congress of Psychiatry</issue-title><fpage>S356</fpage><lpage>S357</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2024</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Author(s)</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article, distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution licence (<uri xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</uri>), which permits unrestricted re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="S0924933824007351a.pdf"/><abstract><sec id="sec3582"><title>Introduction</title><p>Neuropsychiatric disorders can develop following a group A &#x003b2;-hemolytic streptococcal infection, through autoimmune inflammation of the nervous system. Sydenham&#x02019;s chorea and PANDAS (Pediatric Autoimmune Neuropsychiatric Disorders Associated with Streptococcal Infection) are the two most well-known syndromes, primarily affecting children but rarely observed in adults.</p></sec><sec id="sec3583"><title>Objectives</title><p>Our aims are to contribute to the scientific understanding of adult PANDAS-like syndrome and provide a comprehensive literature review on the subject.</p></sec><sec id="sec3584"><title>Methods</title><p>Case report using clinical records and a non-systematic literature review.</p></sec><sec id="sec3585"><title>Results</title><p>
A 24-year-old female presented to the emergency department with profound emotional distress triggered by intrusive thoughts of existential dread, accompanied by compulsive praying. She reported that these symptoms had commenced five days earlier. Two days prior to the onset of her obsessions, she had experienced a high fever, odynophagia, cough, and chills and received an empirical diagnosis of tonsillitis following a physical examination. She was prescribed antibiotics with good response. She revealed that she had experienced two prior episodes of similar anxiety and obsessions when she was approximately seven years old.</p><p>She developed acute obsessive thoughts, including doubts about the meaning of her life, and engaged in compulsive prayer and seeking reassurance from relatives. Notably, there were no signs of affective, dissociative, or psychotic disorders during her admission to the ED or in the preceding months. She reported suffering from anxiety, insomnia, and loss of appetite in the past five days but did not express any suicidal ideation.</p><p>Physical examination indicated mild laryngeal erythema, and laboratory tests showed non-specific signs of infection with no further significant findings. Symptoms were alleviated within a week, aided by treatment with benzodiazepines (lorazepam 1 mg/8h), and she did not require further psychiatric counselling.</p></sec><sec id="sec3586"><title>Conclusions</title><p>
It is worth noting that adult patients can experience a PANDAS-like reaction after a streptococcal infection and may also undergo symptom relapse following new immunological challenges upon reinfection. The existence of a PANDAS spectrum has been postulated, encompassing various manifestations. Thus, when presented with acute obsessive symptoms, healthcare providers should consider this diagnosis, inquire about previous episodes, and conduct a comprehensive medical history and etiological assessment.</p></sec><sec id="sec3587"><title>Disclosure of Interest</title><p>None Declared</p></sec></abstract><counts><page-count count="2"/></counts></article-meta></front></article>