<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" id="deo270011" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">DEN Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">DEN Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.1002/(ISSN)2692-4609</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">DEO2</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>DEN Open</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2692-4609</issn><publisher><publisher-name>John Wiley and Sons Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Hoboken</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39253626</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11382536</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/deo2.70011</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">DEO270011</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Recurrence rates and risk factors in obscure gastrointestinal bleeding</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="left-running-head">ONISHI <sc>et al</sc>.</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="deo270011-cr-0001" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Onishi</surname><given-names>Sachiyo</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8633-1019</contrib-id><xref rid="deo270011-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="deo270011-cr-0002" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Iwashita</surname><given-names>Takuji</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4978-1787</contrib-id><xref rid="deo270011-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><address><email>takuji@w7.dion.ne.jp</email></address></contrib><contrib id="deo270011-cr-0003" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tezuka</surname><given-names>Yukari</given-names></name><xref rid="deo270011-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="deo270011-cr-0004" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kojima</surname><given-names>Kentaro</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9000-2426</contrib-id><xref rid="deo270011-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="deo270011-cr-0005" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Takada</surname><given-names>Jun</given-names></name><xref rid="deo270011-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="deo270011-cr-0006" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kubota</surname><given-names>Masaya</given-names></name><xref rid="deo270011-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="deo270011-cr-0007" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ibuka</surname><given-names>Takashi</given-names></name><xref rid="deo270011-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="deo270011-cr-0008" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>Masahito</given-names></name><xref rid="deo270011-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="deo270011-aff-0001">
<label>
<sup>1</sup>
</label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">First Department of Internal Medicine</named-content>
<institution>Gifu University Hospital</institution>
<city>Gifu</city>
<country country="JP">Japan</country>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="correspondenceTo">
<label>*</label>
<bold>Correspondance</bold>
<break/>Takuji Iwashita, First Department of Internal Medicine, Gifu University Hospital, 1&#x02010;1 Yanagido, Gifu, 501&#x02013;1194, Japan.<break/> Email: <email>takuji@w7.dion.ne.jp</email>
<break/>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>09</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>4</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue seq="89">1</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/deo2.v5.1</issue-id><elocation-id>e70011</elocation-id><history>
<date date-type="rev-recd"><day>22</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></date>
<date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>7</month><year>2024</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>26</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></date>
</history><permissions><!--&#x000a9; 2025 John Wiley & Sons Ltd.--><copyright-statement content-type="article-copyright">&#x000a9; 2024 The Author(s). <italic toggle="yes">DEN Open</italic> published by John Wiley &#x00026; Sons Australia, Ltd on behalf of Japan Gastroenterological Endoscopy Society.</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link> License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="file:DEO2-5-e70011.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><p>Obscure gastrointestinal bleeding (OGIB), defined in 2010, involves bleeding from the GI tract that remains unexplained after standard diagnostic procedures. OGIB, which accounts for about 5% of all GI bleeds, poses diagnostic and management challenges, particularly due to the anatomical features of the small intestine. Advances in capsule endoscopy (CE) and balloon&#x02010;assisted endoscopy have improved the diagnostic and therapeutic landscape for small intestinal lesions.</p><sec id="deo270011-sec-0020"><title>Objective</title><p>To determine the recurrence rate and identify risk factors for recurrence following diagnostic and therapeutic interventions using CE and balloon&#x02010;assisted endoscopy&#x000a0;in patients with OGIB.</p></sec><sec id="deo270011-sec-0030"><title>Methods</title><p>A retrospective cohort study at Gifu University Hospital analyzed CE procedures for patients with OGIB from 2008 to 2022. Patients underwent CE with subsequent treatments based on the findings. Statistical analyses, including Kaplan&#x02010;Meier and Cox proportional hazards models, were used to estimate cumulative recurrence rates and identify recurrence risk factors.</p></sec><sec id="deo270011-sec-0040"><title>Results</title><p>Out of 417 patients, 65.2% had positive CE findings, leading to therapeutic interventions in 16.3% of cases. The cumulative recurrence rates at 12, 24, and 36 months were 4.3%, 9.0%, and 13.9%, respectively. Liver cirrhosis (hazard rate: 4.15, 95% confidence interval 1.88&#x02013;9.18, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01) was identified as a significant risk factor for recurrence.</p></sec><sec id="deo270011-sec-0050"><title>Conclusions</title><p>A significant recurrence rate in OGIB patients, with liver cirrhosis being a major risk factor. Despite diagnostic and therapeutic advances, a comprehensive approach including careful follow&#x02010;up and consideration of risk factors is essential for management.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-generated"><kwd id="deo270011-kwd-0001">balloon endoscopy</kwd><kwd id="deo270011-kwd-0002">capsule endoscopy</kwd><kwd id="deo270011-kwd-0003">obscure gastrointestinal bleeding</kwd><kwd id="deo270011-kwd-0004">recurrence</kwd><kwd id="deo270011-kwd-0005">small intestine</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="funding-0001"><funding-source>None</funding-source></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="2"/><table-count count="6"/><page-count count="8"/><word-count count="4554"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>source-schema-version-number</meta-name><meta-value>2.0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>April 2025</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>details-of-publishers-convertor</meta-name><meta-value>Converter:WILEY_ML3GV2_TO_JATSPMC version:6.5.4 mode:remove_FC converted:27.02.2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="deo270011-sec-0060"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Obscure gastrointestinal bleeding (OGIB) was delineated in 2010 as a condition involving bleeding from the GI tract that persists or recurs, with no identifiable cause upon esophagogastroduodenoscopy (EGD) and colonoscopy (CS). OGIB is classified into overt and occult categories. The overt OGIB is marked by continuous or prior instances of melena or hematochezia, while occult OGIB is characterized by repeated or enduring anemia due to iron deficiency, and a positive fecal occult blood test result. OGIB accounts for approximately 5% of all GI bleeding incidents<xref rid="deo270011-bib-0001" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>,<xref rid="deo270011-bib-0002" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref> with an estimated 75% of these cases stemming from the small intestine<xref rid="deo270011-bib-0003" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>. Given its significant prevalence, the examination of the small intestine is important in the diagnosis and management of OGIB. Nonetheless, the extensive length of the small intestine and its minimal attachment to adjacent structures pose substantial challenges for endoscopic examination. Recent advancements in capsule endoscopy (CE) and balloon&#x02010;assisted endoscopy (BAE) have significantly enhanced the diagnostic and therapeutic capabilities of small intestinal lesions.</p><p>The diagnostic efficacy of CE and BAE in identifying the source of bleeding in cases of OGIB has been reported to be 62% for CE and 56% for BAE.<xref rid="deo270011-bib-0004" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref> The diagnosis of small intestinal lesions and the implementation of appropriate treatment have been associated with favorable clinical outcomes.<xref rid="deo270011-bib-0005" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref> Treatment modalities include endoscopic interventions using BAE, intravascular radiology (IVR), surgical procedures, and conservative management. The success rate of clinical treatments varies from 40% to 73% with endoscopic interventions<xref rid="deo270011-bib-0006" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="deo270011-bib-0007" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="deo270011-bib-0008" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>8</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="deo270011-bib-0009" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>9</sup>
</xref> and reaches 71% for IVR,<xref rid="deo270011-bib-0010" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>10</sup>
</xref> indicating significant effectiveness. However, approximately 10% of OGIB cases experience rebleeding or recurrence of symptoms, necessitating rehospitalization, blood transfusions, and further diagnostic and therapeutic interventions.<xref rid="deo270011-bib-0011" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>11</sup>
</xref> Identifying risk factors for rebleeding and recurrence of symptoms could facilitate strategies such as meticulous follow&#x02010;up and the initiation of early or intensified treatment. Previous studies typically have limited sample sizes. In this study, we analyzed a relatively larger cohort size. Therefore, this study aims to determine the recurrence rate and identify risk factors for recurrence following diagnostic and therapeutic interventions using CE and BAE in OGIB cases.</p></sec><sec id="deo270011-sec-0070"><title>PATIENTS AND METHODS</title><sec id="deo270011-sec-0080"><title>Study design and participants</title><p>This retrospective cohort study was conducted at Gifu University Hospital, analyzing a database including all CE procedures from November 2008 to December 2022. Inclusion criteria were patients who underwent an initial CE for OGIB. Exclusion criteria were as follows: 1) patients in whom the capsule did not progress beyond the upper intestine, preventing small intestine observation, and 2) patients in whom CE procedure was hindered by factors such as food residue, rendering CE visualization difficult.</p></sec><sec id="deo270011-sec-0090"><title>CE procedure and treatment strategy</title><p>Prior to CE, all patients were required to fast for 8 h. On the test day, patients were equipped with the necessary devices at the hospital, consumed an adequate volume of water, and swallowed a capsule endoscope (PillCam SB or SB2 Plus; Medtronic). Water intake resumed 2 h post&#x02010;ingestion, followed by light meals after 4 h, concluding the test approximately 8 h later. Patients were then questioned to check for capsule excretion; in cases of uncertainty, a plain abdominal X&#x02010;ray was conducted to confirm excretion. CE image interpretation was performed independently by two board&#x02010;certified gastroenterologists, both experts in analyzing CE findings, to ensure accuracy and determine the necessity for further examinations or treatments. These considerations were discussed during weekly board meetings attended by the CE instructor. Subsequent to CE, the indications for additional diagnostics or treatment were essentially determined based on guidelines,<xref rid="deo270011-bib-0012" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>12</sup>
</xref> but in cases where treatment strategies are unclear, decisions are made at conferences based on the advice of a CE Instructor Certified by the Japanese Association for Capsule Endoscopy. Treatment decisions were made case basis by the attending physicians. BAE was typically offered for bleeding from mucosal defects, such as erosions, or polyps within the small intestine. Lesions deemed unsuitable for endoscopic intervention were surgically treated at a later date. Patients who underwent hemostasis procedures were typically followed up with CE within 3 to 6 months.</p></sec><sec id="deo270011-sec-0100"><title>Study definitions and evaluation criteria</title><p>Recurrence was defined as patients who, following the initial CE and clinical successful management, experienced overt bleeding or in cases where there is a progression of severe anemia necessitating further small bowel examination. Overt bleeding encompassed bloody stools, melena, or hematemesis, while significant anemia was quantified by a reduction of at least 2 g/dL from baseline hemoglobin (Hb) levels. Positive CE findings were defined as follows: 1) tumors potentially causing bleeding, 2) in the absence of tumors, mucosal defects (such as erosions or ulcers) or vascular lesions implicated in anemia, and 3) visible blood without identifiable sources.</p><p>Bleeding from areas other than the small intestine<xref rid="deo270011-bib-0001" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>: CE showed bleeding from the esophagus, stomach, and duodenum<xref rid="deo270011-bib-0002" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>; CE showed no abnormal findings, and colonoscopy revealed the source of the bleeding.</p><p>Assessments covered patient demographics, including age, gender, comorbidities, medication use, laboratory data, CE timing, findings, and hemostatic interventions. Noted comorbidities included hypertension, dyslipidemia, diabetes under oral management, ischemic heart disease (with a history of myocardial infarction or angina), cerebrovascular disease (including stroke or cerebral hemorrhage history), chronic heart failure, chronic kidney disease, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, and liver cirrhosis. Medication evaluations included the use of prednisolone, nonsteroidal anti&#x02010;inflammatory drugs, low&#x02010;dose aspirin, antiplatelet drugs, and anticoagulants, defined as oral administration initiated at least one month before OGIB symptom onset.</p></sec><sec id="deo270011-sec-0110"><title>Study outcomes and statistical evaluation</title><p>The primary outcome was the cumulative recurrence rate of bleeding, with secondary outcomes including the success rate of hemostasis in treating OGIB and identifying recurrence risk factors. We have defined success as the absence of recurrence, which includes no new episodes of bleeding or progression of severe anemia.</p><p>Data were presented as mean &#x000b1; standard deviation (SD) for continuous variables and as numbers and percentages for categorical variables. The Mann&#x02010;Whitney U test compared continuous variables, while Fisher's exact test compared categorical variables. Cumulative rebleeding rates were estimated using the Kaplan&#x02010;Meier method. Risk factors for rebleeding were evaluated through univariate and multivariate analyses using Cox proportional hazards models, with adjusted hazard ratios (HRs) and 95% confidence intervals. <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02010;Values of &#x0003c;0.05 were considered statistically significant. Statistical analyses were conducted using JMP Pro for Windows software (version 13).</p></sec></sec><sec id="deo270011-sec-0120"><title>RESULT</title><sec id="deo270011-sec-0130"><title>Patient background</title><p>A total of 417 patients with an average age of 65.2 years including 238 males (57.1%) were included in this analysis. The mean minimum Hb value was 8.9 g/dL. The type of OGIB was overt in 155 cases (37.2%) and occult in 262 cases (62.8%; Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="deo270011-tbl-0001" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="deo270011-tbl-0002" ref-type="table">2</xref> lists the underlying diseases. Regarding oral medication use, 73 patients (17.5%) were on antiplatelet drugs, 63 (15.1%) on anticoagulants, 109 (26.1%) on NSAIDs, and 53 (12.7%) on prednisolone.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="deo270011-tbl-0001" content-type="TABLE"><label>TABLE 1</label><caption><p>Patient baseline clinical characteristics.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" char="(" span="1"/><thead><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, years, mean (SD)</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.2 (15.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">238 (57.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">179 (42.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI, kg/m<sup>2</sup>, mean (SD)</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.6 (9.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minimum hemoglobin level, g/dL, mean (SD)</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.9 (2.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Albumin, g/dL, mean (SD)</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2 (0.68)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Obscure GI bleeding type, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overt</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">155 (37.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Occult</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">262 (62.8)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="deo270011-tbl1-note-0001"><p>Abbreviations: BMI, body mass index; GI, gastrointestinal; SD, standard deviation.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd.</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="deo270011-tbl-0002" content-type="TABLE"><label>TABLE 2</label><caption><p>Patients' underlying diseases and oral medications at baseline.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" char="(" span="1"/><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<bold>Underlying disease, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>History of myocardial infarction</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>51 (12.2)</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Congestive heart failure</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52 (12.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cerebrovascular accident</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (8.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (4.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chronic hepatitis</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (4.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Liver cirrhosis</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 (9.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diabetes mellitus</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 (8.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chronic kidney failure</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52 (12.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lymphoma</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (7.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Malignant tumor</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (10.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">Medication, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antiplatelets</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73 (17.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anticoagulants</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63 (15.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NSAIDs</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">109 (26.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prednisolone</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53 (12.7)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="deo270011-tbl2-note-0001"><p>Results are described with <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%).</p></fn><fn id="deo270011-tbl2-note-0002"><p>The cohort of patients with liver cirrhosis included 23 patients classified as Child&#x02010;Pugh class A, 16 patients as class B, and 1 patient as class C. The mean Child&#x02010;Pugh score was 6.4.</p></fn><fn id="deo270011-tbl2-note-0003"><p>Abbreviation: NSAIDs, non&#x02010;steroidal anti&#x02010;inflammatory drugs.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd.</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap></sec><sec id="deo270011-sec-0140"><title>Initial CE and treatment results</title><p>Whole small intestine observation was possible in 94%.&#x03000;CE revealed findings in 272 cases (65.2%). Of these, 97 patients (35.7%) had mucosal breaks, vascular lesions in 79 patients (29%), tumors or submucosal tumors (SMTs) in 22 patients (8.1%), and sources of bleeding outside the small intestine in 34 patients (12.5%). In contrast, 145 patients (34.7%) exhibited no significant findings (CE negative; Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="deo270011-tbl-0003" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Among the patients with CE&#x02010;positive findings, BAE was conducted in 136 patients (50%). The therapeutic intervention was carried out in 52 patients, including 34 instances of endoscopic hemostasis (32 of clipping and two of endoscopic mucosal resection), 11 patients of surgical treatment (seven for tumor bleeding, two for Meckel's diverticulum, two for multiple vascular lesions that are difficult to treat endoscopically), and medication adjustments in seven patients (three for analgesic discontinuation and four for mucosal protectants). Eventually, in 52 patients (38.2%) where BAE was performed, treatment was administered. However, in 84 patients, although BAE was conducted, the lesions identified by CE could not be found, and no hemostatic treatment was applied. Conversely, in 136 patients with positive CE findings, BAE was not performed; however, in 16 patients, therapeutic intervention was performed with other than BAE: Argon plasma coagulation (APC) for vascular lesions in the terminal ileum with colonoscopy in one patient, surgical treatment for jejunal cancer in one patient, and oral medication adjustment in 14 patients. The success rate was found to be 88.2% (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="deo270011-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="deo270011-tbl-0003" content-type="TABLE"><label>TABLE 3</label><caption><p>Capsule endoscopy findings.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" char="(" span="1"/><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Negative, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)</bold>
</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">145 (34.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Positive, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)</bold>
</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">272 (65.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mucosal break</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97 (35.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vascular lesion</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79 (29.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tumor</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (8.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other findings</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (1.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Only blood</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (13.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other organs<xref rid="deo270011-tbl3-note-0002" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 (12.5)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="deo270011-tbl3-note-0001"><p>Abbreviations: Negative, negative capsule endoscopy findings.; Positive, positive capsule endoscopy findings.</p></fn><fn id="deo270011-tbl3-note-0002"><label>*</label><p>Other organs include the following:&#x03000;Stomach: eight cases, Duodenum: 13 cases, Colon: 13 cases.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd.</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap><fig position="float" fig-type="FIGURE" id="deo270011-fig-0001"><label>FIGURE 1</label><caption><p>Patient flowchart. BAE, balloon&#x02010;assisted endoscopy; CE, capsule endoscopy.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="DEO2-5-e70011-g001" position="anchor" id="jats-graphic-1"/></fig></sec><sec id="deo270011-sec-0150"><title>Long&#x02010;term course and recurrence predictors</title><p>The median follow&#x02010;up period was 8.46 months (range 1.19&#x02013;50.3 months), with 35 patients (8.4%) experiencing a recurrence. The cumulative recurrence rates at 12, 24, and 36 months were 4.3%, 9.0%, and 13.9%, respectively (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="deo270011-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Of the recurrence cases, 30 patients had initial CE&#x02010;positive findings, and five had CE&#x02010;negative findings. The specifics of the 29 patients with positive initial CE findings related to bleeding are depicted in Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="deo270011-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. At the time of recurrence, symptoms included hematochezia or melena in 13 patients and progressive anemia in 22 patients. Recurrence risk factors were analyzed using Cox proportional hazards analysis. We included the following specific criteria: age, sex, OGIB type, current comorbidities such as liver cirrhosis and chronic kidney disease, use of the antithrombotic drug, an anticoagulant drug, and endoscopic findings of mucosal break, vascular lesion, and negative findings. In the univariate analysis, factors such as liver cirrhosis (HR: 4.34, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01), vascular lesions (HR: 3.14, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01), and negative CE findings (HR: 2.79, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.03) were identified. Multivariate analysis revealed that only liver cirrhosis (HR: 4.15, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01) was a significant predictive factor. Gender, age, oral medication use and therapeutic interventions were not significant predictors of recurrence (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="deo270011-tbl-0004" ref-type="table">4</xref>).</p><fig position="float" fig-type="FIGURE" id="deo270011-fig-0002"><label>FIGURE 2</label><caption><p>The Kaplan&#x02010;Meier analysis regarding the cumulative relapse rate.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="DEO2-5-e70011-g002" position="anchor" id="jats-graphic-3"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="deo270011-tbl-0004" content-type="TABLE"><label>TABLE 4</label><caption><p>Predictive factors of relapse.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="2" style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" rowspan="1">Univariate</th><th align="left" colspan="2" style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" rowspan="1">Multivariate</th></tr><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HR (95% CI)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02010;value</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HR (95% CI)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02010;value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;60</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.35 (0.66&#x02013;2.74)</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.69 (0.78&#x02013;3.65)</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;60</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.11 (0.56&#x02013;2.17)</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20 (0.59&#x02013;2.43)</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OGIB type</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overt</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.31 (0.66&#x02013;2.59)</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10 (0.53&#x02013;2.27)</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Occult</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Present</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.34 (2.21&#x02013;8.55)</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.15 (1.88&#x02013;9.18)</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absent</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CKD</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Present</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.15 (0.47&#x02013;2.78)</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05 (0.41&#x02013;2.56)</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absent</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anticoagulant use</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28 (0.56&#x02013;2.95)</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.27 (0.52&#x02013;3.10)</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antiplatelet use</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03 (0.43&#x02013;2.49)</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.83 (0.71&#x02013;4.66)</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mucosal break</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Present</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07 (0.43&#x02013;1.99)</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05 (0.36&#x02013;3.08)</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absent</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vascular lesion</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Present</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.14 (1.6&#x02013;6.14)</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.82 (0.66&#x02013;5.02)</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absent</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative findings of CE</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.79 (1.08&#x02010;7.21)</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.05 (0.58&#x02013;7.17)</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="deo270011-tbl4-note-0001"><p>Abbreviations: CI, confidence interval; CKD, chronic kidney disease; HR, hazard rate; LC, liver cirrhosis; OGIB, obscure gastrointestinal bleeding.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd.</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap><p>Out of 40 patients with LC, 31 cases had positive CE (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="deo270011-tbl-0005" ref-type="table">5</xref>). Among them, 14 cases had a recurrence, and 13 cases had positive CE (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="deo270011-tbl-0006" ref-type="table">6</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="deo270011-tbl-0005" content-type="TABLE"><label>TABLE 5</label><caption><p>Capsule endoscopy findings in liver cirrhosis.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><thead><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Child&#x02013;Pugh A</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Child&#x02013;Pugh B</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Child&#x02013;Pugh C</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> (specific treatment)</bold>
</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>40</bold>
</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>23</bold>
<xref rid="deo270011-bib-0005" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>16 (0)</bold>
</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1 (0)</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Negative (specific treatment), <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>
</bold>
</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>9 (0)</bold>
</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>5 (0)</bold>
</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>4 (0)</bold>
</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0 (0)</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Positive (specific treatment), <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>
</bold>
</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>31</bold>
<xref rid="deo270011-bib-0005" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>18</bold>
<xref rid="deo270011-bib-0005" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>12 (0)</bold>
</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1 (0)</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mucosal break</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8<xref rid="deo270011-bib-0001" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5<xref rid="deo270011-bib-0001" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (0)</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vascular lesion</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18<xref rid="deo270011-bib-0003" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10<xref rid="deo270011-bib-0003" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (0)</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Only blood</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2<xref rid="deo270011-bib-0001" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2<xref rid="deo270011-bib-0001" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other organs<xref rid="deo270011-tbl5-note-0001" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (0)</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0)</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (0)</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="deo270011-tbl5-note-0001"><label>*</label><p>Other organs include the following:&#x03000;Stomach: three cases.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd.</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="deo270011-tbl-0006" content-type="TABLE"><label>TABLE 6</label><caption><p>Recurrence rate in liver cirrhosis.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><thead><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Child&#x02013;Pugh A</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Child&#x02013;Pugh B</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Child&#x02013;Pugh C</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> (specific treatment)</bold>
</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>14</bold>
<xref rid="deo270011-bib-0002" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>10</bold>
<xref rid="deo270011-bib-0002" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>4 (0)</bold>
</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0 (0)</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Negative (specific treatment), <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>
</bold>
</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1 (0)</bold>
</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1 (0)</bold>
</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0 (0)</bold>
</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0 (0)</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Positive (specific treatment), <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>
</bold>
</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>13</bold>
<xref rid="deo270011-bib-0002" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>9</bold>
<xref rid="deo270011-bib-0002" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>4 (0)</bold>
</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0 (0)</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mucosal break</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (0)</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (0)</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0)</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vascular lesion</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8<xref rid="deo270011-bib-0002" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6<xref rid="deo270011-bib-0002" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (0)</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Only blood</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0)</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0)</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other organs<xref rid="deo270011-tbl6-note-0001" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0)</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0)</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="deo270011-tbl6-note-0001"><label>*</label><p>Other organs include the following: Stomach: three cases.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd.</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec id="deo270011-sec-0160"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>In this study, we focused on the cumulative recurrence rate and risk factors associated with recurrence following the initial CE in patients with OGIB. Evaluating the recurrence rate of OGIB is critical for enhancing clinical management strategies. Our findings indicate that 16.3% of the patients exhibited positive CE results, enabling therapeutic intervention. Moreover, the overall recurrence rate of OGIB was determined to be 8.2%, with liver cirrhosis identified as a particularly significant risk factor for recurrence. Based on the results presented in Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="deo270011-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, we believe that careful follow&#x02010;up for at least 48 months is necessary to adequately monitor for recurrence.</p><p>Several studies have investigated the rebleeding rates of OGIB, yielding diverse outcomes. Niikura et&#x000a0;al.<xref rid="deo270011-bib-0013" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>13</sup>
</xref> conducted a retrospective analysis of 320 patients undergoing CE for OGIB, reporting a mean patient age of 65 years. Among these, 46% had overt OGIB, and 29% demonstrated positive CE findings, such as erosions, ulcers, tumors, and telangiectasias, with 7.5% undergoing therapeutic intervention post&#x02010;CE. The study reported a rebleeding rate of 13.4% over an average follow&#x02010;up of 18.3 months, with cumulative rebleeding rates of 11% at 12 months and 18.5% at 36 months. Conversely, Panu et&#x000a0;al.<xref rid="deo270011-bib-0014" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>14</sup>
</xref> assessed 173 patients with OGIB via CE, finding a mean patient age of 65.4 years, with 60.4% presenting with overt OGIB and 42.1% showing positive CE findings. Therapeutic intervention was performed in 26.3% of patients. The study observed a rebleeding rate of 26.3% during an average 26&#x02010;month observation period. In our study, we observed that the relapse rates for patients who did not receive specific treatment after BAE and those who received specific treatment were nearly identical. However, it is crucial to recognize that our analysis focuses on short&#x02010;term outcomes. The potential benefits of specific treatment for small bowel lesions may become more apparent over a longer period.</p><p>A comprehensive analysis of these findings, alongside our study results, suggests an approximate recurrence rate of 10&#x02013;30%. The variable recurrence rates can be attributed to the broad range of OGIB causes, complicating accurate diagnosis and treatment. Study design, patient demographics, and follow&#x02010;up duration also contribute to these variations.</p><p>Furthermore, several studies have identified various risk factors for rebleeding, with cirrhosis consistently reported as a significant risk factor.<xref rid="deo270011-bib-0014" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>14</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="deo270011-bib-0015" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>15</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="deo270011-bib-0016" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>16</sup>
</xref> The increased recurrence risk in liver cirrhosis patients is attributed to venous system stasis in the small intestine due to elevated portal pressure and reduced blood clotting capabilities stemming from lowered platelet counts and impaired liver function. If gastrointestinal bleeding occurs, these conditions can exacerbate bleeding or cause portal hypertensive gastroenteropathy, further compromising blood vessel integrity throughout the gastrointestinal tract.<xref rid="deo270011-bib-0017" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>17</sup>
</xref> Additional reported risk factors for rebleeding include vascular lesions,<xref rid="deo270011-bib-0018" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>18</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="deo270011-bib-0019" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>19</sup>
</xref> overt OGIB,<xref rid="deo270011-bib-0015" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>15</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="deo270011-bib-0019" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>19</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="deo270011-bib-0020" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>20</sup>
</xref> duration of OGIB<xref rid="deo270011-bib-0021" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>21</sup>
</xref> older age,<xref rid="deo270011-bib-0022" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>22</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="deo270011-bib-0023" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>23</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="deo270011-bib-0024" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>24</sup>
</xref> bleeding from the jejunum,<xref rid="deo270011-bib-0022" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>22</sup>
</xref> and a history of blood transfusions,<xref rid="deo270011-bib-0020" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>20</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="deo270011-bib-0024" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>24</sup>
</xref> although these factors were not significant in our study. Tojo et&#x000a0;al.<xref rid="deo270011-bib-0025" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>25</sup>
</xref> have reported a potential association between Saurin classification P2 and rebleeding. The study found that P2 findings on CE were more frequent in patients taking antiplatelet drugs. Among the studies that have proposed models for predicting rebleeding in OGIB<xref rid="deo270011-bib-0026" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>26</sup>
</xref>, the RHEMITT score,<xref rid="deo270011-bib-0027" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>27</sup>
</xref> which has been validated and has been shown to be reliable, is the most used model. This score is calculated from seven variables: renal disease, heart failure, endoscopic capsule lesion, major bleeding, incomplete capsule, tobacco, and treatment by endoscopy. The score is calculated from the following seven variables However, the RHEMITT score does not include cirrhosis, which was a risk factor for rebleeding in this study and in other predicting models for rebleeding.<xref rid="deo270011-bib-0013" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>13</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="deo270011-bib-0028" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>28</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="deo270011-bib-0029" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>29</sup>
</xref> The inclusion of additional risk factors may further improve the accuracy of the predicting model for rebleeding. High&#x02010;risk patients require cautious management to mitigate the likelihood of recurrence.</p><p>While accurate diagnosis and treatment of OGIB are fundamentally crucial for reducing recurrence risk, advancements in OGIB diagnosis have outpaced treatment research.<xref rid="deo270011-bib-0030" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>30</sup>
</xref> Currently, endoscopic treatment, surgical interventions, and radiotherapy are the common treatment modalities for OGIB. In surgical treatment, it shows excellent results in individual lesions such as tumors and localized arteriovascular malformations. However, lesions that are used more extensively, such as multifocal angioectasia as in our case, are usually treated endoscopically at the time of surgery. Although rebleeding rates are expected to be similar between surgical treatment and endoscopic hemostasis, long&#x02010;term follow&#x02010;up data are not available.<xref rid="deo270011-bib-0006" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref> In radiotherapy, the advantage of angiography is that if the source of bleeding is identified during diagnosis using angiography, it can be treated with embolization, and unlike endoscopy, there is no difficulty in obtaining a visual field due to bleeding. Therefore, angiography is considered to be indicated when endoscopic hemostasis is difficult due to active bleeding. However, in our study, there were no cases in which endoscopic hemostasis was difficult and the patient underwent angiography.<xref rid="deo270011-bib-0006" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref> Endoscopic options include clipping for hemostasis, APC, and endoscopic band ligation, with treatment selection based on lesion location, bleeding severity, and patient comorbidities. Despite the absence of large&#x02010;scale prospective studies comparing treatment efficacy, various treatments have been explored, including hormonal therapies, somatostatin analogs, thalidomide, erythropoietin, and Von Willebrand factor. However, these pharmacological treatments have yet to demonstrate definitive efficacy and are primarily considered for patients who continue to bleed post&#x02010;endoscopic treatment or those ineligible for surgical intervention.<xref rid="deo270011-bib-0031" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>31</sup>
</xref> However, supportive therapy with oral or intravenous iron is said to be the only primary means of treatment for minor small bowel bleeding.<xref rid="deo270011-bib-0032" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>32</sup>
</xref> Given the challenges in managing portal hypertension and its sequelae in liver cirrhosis, regular monitoring and early detection of recurrence signs are important in patients with comorbidity of liver cirrhosis, including other risk factors elevating the risk of OGIB recurrence as mentioned above. Future efforts should focus on refining treatment and management strategies for OGIB.</p><p>This study has some limitations. A retrospective nature and reliance on data from a single academic center potentially have introduced selection bias. In addition, the criteria for additional examinations or treatments after CE could vary based on historical background. Dependence on medical records and external referrals for patient follow&#x02010;up may overlook certain recurrence instances, possibly underestimating the recurrence rate. Further research is needed to evaluate the long&#x02010;term efficacy and impact of specific treatments on recurrence rates. Saurin classification should normally be used for vascular lesions, but this was not done in this case because there were old cases and there was insufficient information to classify them.</p><p>In conclusion, this study reports an OGIB recurrence rate of 8.2%, with a 3&#x02010;year cumulative recurrence rate of approximately 14%, and underscores liver cirrhosis as a risk factor for recurrence. Despite the challenges in diagnosing and treating OGIB, diligent follow&#x02010;up is essential, particularly for patients with liver cirrhosis. Future research should be conducted with large&#x02010;scale prospective studies to further understand and address OGIB management.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="deo270011-sec-0180"><title>CONFLICT OF INTEREST STATEMENT</title><p>None.</p></sec><sec id="deo270011-sec-0190"><title>ETHICS STATEMENT</title><p>This study was conducted according to the ethical guidelines of the Declaration of Helsinki and was approved by the Institutional Review Board of Gifu University Hospital. Registry and the Registration&#x03000;N/A. Animal Studies. N/A.</p></sec><sec id="deo270011-sec-0200"><title>PATIENT CONSENT STATEMENT</title><p>The opt&#x02010;out method was used to obtain consent from study participants.</p></sec></body><back><ack id="deo270011-sec-0170"><title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title><p>We would like to extend our heartfelt thanks to Gifu University School of Medicine Graduate School of Medicine for their invaluable support and contributions, which significantly enriched our research and made its success possible.</p></ack><ref-list id="deo270011-bibl-0001"><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="deo270011-bib-0001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270011-cit-0001">
<string-name>
<surname>Briley</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names>
</string-name> Jr., <string-name>
<surname>Jackson</surname>
<given-names>DC</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Johnsrude</surname>
<given-names>IS</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Mills</surname>
<given-names>SR</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Acute gastrointestinal hemorrhage of small&#x02010;bowel origin</article-title>. <source>Radiology</source>
<year>1980</year>; <volume>136</volume>: <fpage>317</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>319</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6967614</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270011-bib-0002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270011-cit-0002">
<string-name>
<surname>Rockey</surname>
<given-names>DC</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Occult and obscure gastrointestinal bleeding: Causes and clinical management</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Gastroenterol Hepatol</source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>265</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>279</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20351759</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270011-bib-0003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270011-cit-0003">
<string-name>
<surname>Raju</surname>
<given-names>GS</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Gerson</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Das</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Lewis</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>American Gastroenterological Association (AGA) Institute technical review on obscure gastrointestinal bleeding</article-title>. <source>Gastroenterology</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>133</volume>: <fpage>1697</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1717</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17983812</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270011-bib-0004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270011-cit-0004">
<string-name>
<surname>Teshima</surname>
<given-names>CW</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Kuipers</surname>
<given-names>EJ</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>van Zanten</surname>
<given-names>SV</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Mensink</surname>
<given-names>PB</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Double balloon enteroscopy and capsule endoscopy for obscure gastrointestinal bleeding: An updated meta&#x02010;analysis</article-title>. <source>J Gastroenterol Hepatol</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>796</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>801</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21155884</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270011-bib-0005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270011-cit-0005">
<string-name>
<surname>Shishido</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Oka</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Tanaka</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>
<italic toggle="yes">et&#x000a0;al.</italic>
<article-title>Outcome of patients who have undergone total enteroscopy for obscure gastrointestinal bleeding</article-title>. <source>World J Gastroenterol</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>666</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>672</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22363138</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270011-bib-0006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270011-cit-0006">
<string-name>
<surname>Gerson</surname>
<given-names>LB</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Fidler</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Cave</surname>
<given-names>DR</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Leighton</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>ACG clinical guideline: Diagnosis and management of small bowel bleeding</article-title>. <source>Am J Gastroenterol</source>
<year>2015</year>; <volume>110</volume>: <fpage>1265</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1287</lpage>; quiz 88.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26303132</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270011-bib-0007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270011-cit-0007">
<string-name>
<surname>May</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Nachbar</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ell</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Double&#x02010;balloon enteroscopy (push&#x02010;and&#x02010;pull enteroscopy) of the small bowel: Feasibility and diagnostic and therapeutic yield in patients with suspected small bowel disease</article-title>. <source>Gastrointest Endosc</source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>62</volume> :<fpage>62</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>70</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15990821</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270011-bib-0008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270011-cit-0008">
<string-name>
<surname>Yamamoto</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Kita</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Sunada</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</string-name>
<italic toggle="yes">et&#x000a0;al.</italic>
<article-title>Clinical outcomes of double&#x02010;balloon endoscopy for the diagnosis and treatment of small&#x02010;intestinal diseases</article-title>. <source>Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol</source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>1010</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1016</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15551254</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270011-bib-0009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270011-cit-0009">
<string-name>
<surname>Gross</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Stark</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Initial experience with double&#x02010;balloon enteroscopy at a U.S. center</article-title>. <source>Gastrointest Endosc</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>67</volume>: <fpage>890</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>897</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18178204</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270011-bib-0010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270011-cit-0010">
<string-name>
<surname>Hongsakul</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Pakdeejit</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Tanutit</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Outcome and predictive factors of successful transarterial embolization for the treatment of acute gastrointestinal hemorrhage</article-title>. <source>Acta Radiol</source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>55</volume>: <fpage>186</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>194</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23904090</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270011-bib-0011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270011-cit-0011">
<string-name>
<surname>Pasha</surname>
<given-names>SF</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Hara</surname>
<given-names>AK</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Leighton</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Diagnostic evaluation and management of obscure gastrointestinal bleeding: A changing paradigm</article-title>. <source>Gastroenterol Hepatol</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>839</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>850</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270011-bib-0012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270011-cit-0012">
<string-name>
<surname>Yamamoto</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ogata</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Matsumoto</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</string-name>
<italic toggle="yes">et&#x000a0;al.</italic>
<article-title>Clinical practice guideline for enteroscopy</article-title>. <source>Dig Endosc</source>
<year>2017</year>; <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>519</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>546</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28370422</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270011-bib-0013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270011-cit-0013">
<string-name>
<surname>Niikura</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Yamada</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Nagata</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</string-name>
<italic toggle="yes">et&#x000a0;al.</italic>
<article-title>New predictive model of rebleeding during follow&#x02010;up of patients with obscure gastrointestinal bleeding: A multicenter cohort study</article-title>. <source>J Gastroenterol Hepatol</source>
<year>2016</year>; <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>752</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>760</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26487158</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270011-bib-0014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270011-cit-0014">
<string-name>
<surname>Wetwittayakhlang</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Wonglhow</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Netinatsunton</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Chamroonkul</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Piratvisuth</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Re&#x02010;bleeding and its predictors after capsule endoscopy in patients with obscure gastrointestinal bleeding in long&#x02010;term follow&#x02010;up</article-title>. <source>BMC Gastroenterol</source>
<year>2019</year>; <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>216</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31842770</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270011-bib-0015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270011-cit-0015">
<string-name>
<surname>Nishiwaki</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Noma</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Kunitomo</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</string-name>
<italic toggle="yes">et&#x000a0;al.</italic>
<article-title>Neoadjuvant chemotherapy for locally advanced esophageal cancer comparing cisplatin and 5&#x02010;fluorouracil versus docetaxel plus cisplatin and 5&#x02010;fluorouracil: A propensity score matching analysis</article-title>. <source>Esophagus</source>
<year>2022</year>; <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>626</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>638</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35792947</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270011-bib-0016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270011-cit-0016">
<string-name>
<surname>Otani</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Shimada</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Watanabe</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</string-name>
<italic toggle="yes">et&#x000a0;al.</italic>
<article-title>Long&#x02010;term rebleeding rate and predictive factors of rebleeding after capsule endoscopy in patients with obscure GI bleeding</article-title>. <source>Gastrointest Endosc</source>
<year>2022</year>; <volume>96</volume>: <fpage>956</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>969</lpage>.e3.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35850171</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270011-bib-0017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270011-cit-0017">
<string-name>
<surname>De Palma</surname>
<given-names>GD</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Rega</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Masone</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>
<italic toggle="yes">et&#x000a0;al.</italic>
<article-title>Mucosal abnormalities of the small bowel in patients with cirrhosis and portal hypertension: A capsule endoscopy study</article-title>. <source>Gastrointest Endosc</source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>529</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>534</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16185966</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270011-bib-0018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270011-cit-0018">
<string-name>
<surname>Hirata</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Tsuboi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Matsubara</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</string-name>
<italic toggle="yes">et&#x000a0;al.</italic>
<article-title>Long&#x02010;term outcomes of patients with obscure gastrointestinal bleeding after negative capsule endoscopy</article-title>. <source>J Gastroenterol Hepatol</source>
<year>2024</year>; <volume>39</volume>: 165&#x02013;171.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270011-bib-0019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270011-cit-0019">
<string-name>
<surname>Baba</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Kawano</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Kono</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</string-name>
<italic toggle="yes">et&#x000a0;al.</italic>
<article-title>Clinical characteristics and risk factors for rebleeding in patients with obscure gastrointestinal bleeding</article-title>. <source>Intern Med</source>
<year>2020</year>; <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>1345</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1350</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32023585</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270011-bib-0020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270011-cit-0020">
<string-name>
<surname>Ribeiro</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Pinho</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Rodrigues</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>
<italic toggle="yes">et&#x000a0;al.</italic>
<article-title>What is the long&#x02010;term outcome of a negative capsule endoscopy in patients with obscure gastrointestinal bleeding?</article-title>
<source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig</source>
<year>2015</year>; <volume>107</volume>: <fpage>753</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>758</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26671588</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270011-bib-0021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270011-cit-0021">
<string-name>
<surname>Min</surname>
<given-names>YW</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Jeon</surname>
<given-names>SW</given-names>
</string-name>
<italic toggle="yes">et&#x000a0;al.</italic>
<article-title>Long&#x02010;term outcome of capsule endoscopy in obscure gastrointestinal bleeding: A nationwide analysis</article-title>. <source>Endoscopy</source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>59</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>65</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24254387</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270011-bib-0022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270011-cit-0022">
<string-name>
<surname>Fan</surname>
<given-names>GW</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>TH</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>WP</given-names>
</string-name>
<italic toggle="yes">et&#x000a0;al.</italic>
<article-title>Angiodysplasia and bleeding in the small intestine treated by balloon&#x02010;assisted enteroscopy</article-title>. <source>J Dig Dis</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>113</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>116</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23216888</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270011-bib-0023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270011-cit-0023">
<string-name>
<surname>Rahmi</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Samaha</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Vahedi</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</string-name>
<italic toggle="yes">et&#x000a0;al.</italic>
<article-title>Long&#x02010;term follow&#x02010;up of patients undergoing capsule and double&#x02010;balloon enteroscopy for identification and treatment of small&#x02010;bowel vascular lesions: A prospective, multicenter study</article-title>. <source>Endoscopy</source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>591</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>597</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24830401</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270011-bib-0024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270011-cit-0024">
<string-name>
<surname>Arakawa</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ohmiya</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Nakamura</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>
<italic toggle="yes">et&#x000a0;al.</italic>
<article-title>Outcome after enteroscopy for patients with obscure GI bleeding: Diagnostic comparison between double&#x02010;balloon endoscopy and videocapsule endoscopy</article-title>. <source>Gastrointest Endosc</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>69</volume>: <fpage>866</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>874</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19136098</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270011-bib-0025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270011-cit-0025">
<string-name>
<surname>Tojo</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Sujino</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Hayashi</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</string-name>
<italic toggle="yes">et&#x000a0;al.</italic>
<article-title>Video capsule endoscopy in overt and occult obscure gastrointestinal bleeding: Insights from a single&#x02010;center, observational study in Japan</article-title>. <source>DEN Open</source>
<year>2024</year>; <volume>4</volume>: e354.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270011-bib-0026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270011-cit-0026">
<string-name>
<surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Nam</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Prediction models for recurrence in patients with small bowel bleeding</article-title>. <source>World J Clin Cases</source>
<year>2023</year>; <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>3949</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3957</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37388787</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270011-bib-0027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270011-cit-0027">
<string-name>
<surname>de Sousa Magalh&#x000e3;es</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>C&#x000fa;rdia Gon&#x000e7;alves</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Rosa</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Moreira</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Sousa&#x02010;Pinto</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Cotter</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</string-name>
<article-title>RHEMITT Score: Predicting the risk of rebleeding for patients with mid&#x02010;gastrointestinal bleeding submitted to small bowel capsule endoscopy</article-title>. <source>Dig Dis</source>
<year>2020</year>; <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>299</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>309</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31743910</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270011-bib-0028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270011-cit-0028">
<string-name>
<surname>Uchida</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Hirooka</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Nakamura</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>
<italic toggle="yes">et&#x000a0;al.</italic>
<article-title>Nomogram&#x02010;based prediction of rebleeding in small bowel bleeding patients: The &#x02018;PRSBB&#x02019; score</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep</source>
<year>2018</year>; <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>6378</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29686230</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270011-bib-0029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270011-cit-0029">
<string-name>
<surname>Ohmiya</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Nakamura</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Osaki</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</string-name>
<italic toggle="yes">et&#x000a0;al.</italic>
<article-title>Development of a comorbidity index to identify patients with small bowel bleeding at risk for rebleeding and small bowel vascular diseases</article-title>. <source>Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol</source>
<year>2019</year>; <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>896</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>904</lpage>.e4.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30130626</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270011-bib-0030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270011-cit-0030">
<string-name>
<surname>Baptista</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Marya</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Singh</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Rupawala</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Gondal</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Cave</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Continuing challenges in the diagnosis and management of obscure gastrointestinal bleeding</article-title>. <source>World J Gastrointest Pathophysiol</source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>523</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>533</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25400996</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270011-bib-0031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270011-cit-0031">
<string-name>
<surname>Kochhar</surname>
<given-names>GS</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Sanaka</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Vargo</surname>
<given-names>JJ</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Therapeutic management options for patients with obscure gastrointestinal bleeding</article-title>. <source>Ther Adv Gastroenterol</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>71</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>81</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270011-bib-0032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270011-cit-0032">
<string-name>
<surname>Goddard</surname>
<given-names>AF</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>James</surname>
<given-names>MW</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>McIntyre</surname>
<given-names>AS</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Scott</surname>
<given-names>BB</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Guidelines for the management of iron deficiency anaemia</article-title>. <source>Gut</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>60</volume>: <fpage>1309</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1316</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21561874</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>