<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Neuroeng Rehabil</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Neuroeng Rehabil</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of NeuroEngineering and Rehabilitation</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1743-0003</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11681763</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1531</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12984-024-01531-6</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Compensating elastic faults in a torque-assisted knee exoskeleton: functional evaluation and user perception study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Velasco-Guillen</surname><given-names>Rodrigo J.</given-names></name><address><email>rodrigo.velasco@fau.de</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bliek</surname><given-names>Adna</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Font-Llagunes</surname><given-names>Josep M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vanderborght</surname><given-names>Bram</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Beckerle</surname><given-names>Philipp</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/00f7hpc57</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5330.5</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2107 3311</institution-id><institution>Chair of Autonomous Systems and Mechatronics, </institution><institution>Friedrich-Alexander University Erlangen-N&#x000fc;rnberg, </institution></institution-wrap>Erlangen, Germany </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/03mb6wj31</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.6835.8</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1937 028X</institution-id><institution>Biomechanical Engineering Lab, Department of Mechanical Engineering and Research Centre for Biomedical Engineering, </institution><institution>Universitat Polit&#x000e8;cnica de Catalunya, </institution></institution-wrap>Barcelona, Spain </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/00gy2ar74</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 9332 2809</institution-id><institution>Health Technologies and Innovation, </institution><institution>Institut de Recerca Sant Joan de D&#x000e9;u, </institution></institution-wrap>Esplugues de Llobregat, Spain </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/006e5kg04</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.8767.e</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2290 8069</institution-id><institution>Robotics and MultiBody Mechanics Research Group, </institution><institution>Vrije Universiteit Brussel, </institution></institution-wrap>Brussels, Belgium </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/02kcbn207</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.15762.37</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2215 0390</institution-id><institution>Interuniversity Microelectronics Centre (imec), </institution></institution-wrap>Leuven, Belgium </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/00f7hpc57</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5330.5</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2107 3311</institution-id><institution>Department Artificial Intelligence in Biomedical Engineering (AIBE), </institution><institution>Friedrich-Alexander University Erlangen-N&#x000fc;rnberg, </institution></institution-wrap>Erlangen, Germany </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>28</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>21</volume><elocation-id>230</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>5</day><month>7</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>12</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2024</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Wearable robots are often powered by elastic actuators, which can mimic the intrinsic compliance observed in human joints, contributing to safe and seamless interaction. However, due to their increased complexity, when compared to direct drives, elastic actuators are susceptible to faults, which pose significant challenges, potentially compromising user experience and safety during interaction. In this article, we developed a fault-tolerant control strategy for torque assistance in a knee exoskeleton and investigated user experience during a walking task while emulating faults. We implemented and evaluated the torque control scheme, based on impedance control, for a mechanically adjustable compliance actuator with nonlinear torque-deflection characteristics. Conducted functional evaluation experiments showed that the control strategy is capable of providing support during gait based on a torque profile. A user study was conducted to evaluate the impact of fault severity and compensation on the perception of support, stiffness, comfort, and trust while walking with the exoskeleton. Results from the user study revealed significant differences in participants&#x02019; responses when comparing support and stiffness levels without fault compensation. In contrast, no significant differences were found when faults were compensated, indicating that fault tolerance can be achieved in practice. Meanwhile, comfort and trust measurements do not seem to depend directly on torque support levels, pointing to other influencing factors that could be considered in future research.</p></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Adaptive control</kwd><kwd>Elastic actuation</kwd><kwd>Fault tolerance</kwd><kwd>Human-robot interaction</kwd><kwd>Impedance control</kwd><kwd>Wearable robotics</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100001659</institution-id><institution>Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>BE 5729/1</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Beckerle</surname><given-names>Philipp</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Friedrich-Alexander-Universit&#x000e4;t Erlangen-N&#x000fc;rnberg (1041)</institution></funding-source></award-group><open-access><p>Open Access funding enabled and organized by Projekt DEAL.</p></open-access></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; BioMed Central Ltd., part of Springer Nature 2024</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">The field of wearable robotics has witnessed significant advancements in recent years. In particular, powered exoskeletons have garnered attention for their potential to augment or restore human joint function [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Elastically actuated systems present a viable solution by mimicking the intrinsic compliance observed in natural human joints, contributing to a seamless interaction between the wearer and the exoskeleton. The Series Elastic Actuator (SEA), in which input and output are coupled in series by an elastic element, is a popular topology choice for wearable robots due to the added safety through intrinsic output backdrivability, its energy efficiency capabilities, and its intrinsically low output impedance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. In SEAs, the relationship between torque and deflection effectively turns the torque control problem into a position control problem. In other words, a controller may be used to adjust the input position to attain a desired output torque, which can improve force accuracy since controlling position accurately in geared motors is generally easier than force [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. This method of indirect force control in SEAs is common in literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>], but it generally requires accurate knowledge of the series elasticity properties. The Parallel Elastic Actuator (PEA) topology, in which an elastic element is connected in parallel to the input, is a less popular choice, but it has shown advantages such as torque-control performance and energy efficiency in task specific scenarios [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Elastic actuators can also be designed with fixed or variable stiffness characteristics. Variable Stiffness Actuators (VSAs) are devices capable of adjusting their stiffness through mechanisms that alter elastic properties [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>] and are also often used in wearable robots due to their adaptable mechanical properties [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>].</p><p id="Par3">However, the mechanical complexity of elastic actuators increases compared to direct drives, e.g., due to the inclusion of elastic and kinematic elements. Through that, the chance of fault occurrence, in general, increases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. The reliability of robotic systems strongly depends on their capability to maintain nominal operation in the presence of unexpected conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Internal faults, such as abrupt changes of internal properties, can lead the system to undesired or unsafe configurations. From a technical perspective, the ideal case would be to design a system which is inherently fault-free. However, this is practically unachievable, and fault tolerance is a concept which aims at incorporating redundancy concepts and/or control reconfiguration to avoid these internal faults from causing service failure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. The study in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>] highlighted the practical relevance of faults in elastic actuators. While stiffness degradation in elastic elements might occur due to cyclic loading or excessive forces, faults in kinematic components such as linkages and cables, may be more frequent in elastically actuated systems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. This is particularly critical for VSAs which introduce kinematic elements in their stiffness adjusting mechanisms. Elastic faults are then defined as internal changes that may alter the elastic behavior of the actuator and thus its effective stiffness and output torque. Before they could severely impact the system functionality, a fault-tolerant control strategy can be implemented to detect and compensate for such faults [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. In literature, adaptive control methods are an alternative to achieve fault-tolerance in the face of uncertain parameters in elastic actuators by applying robust methods such as disturbance observers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>] or parameter estimation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>].</p><p id="Par4">The main research question tackled in this paper is how users experience and react to the impact of elastic faults on physical human-robot interaction (pHRI). As such, we investigate the torque support performance and user perception during walking with an elastically powered knee exoskeleton, while emulating elastic faults. This serves as a scenario of close physical interaction and allows to evaluate whether fault tolerance can be achieved in practice through fault compensation and to gain insight in the influencing human factors through psychometric experiments. One critical aspect of exoskeleton control is providing appropriate support to the user. Support refers to the assistance or resistance provided by the exoskeleton&#x02019;s actuators to help the user perform tasks more effectively or safely, which can significantly impact the user&#x02019;s experience while using the exoskeleton. Research shows that exoskeleton support can improve user performance and decrease task difficulty and fatigue [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. However, faulty conditions might degrade the provided support and affect the user experience in the interaction. Investigating user experience with exoskeletons allows to understand how users might experience and interact with the forces applied by the exoskeleton during movement tasks. Fault tolerance in exoskeletons is important to ensure that users experience consistent support and are not disturbed by potential faults. Properly compensating for faults should result in users perceiving no changes in the exoskeleton&#x02019;s performance, maintaining seamless assistance during use. At the same time, users may not immediately notice minor variations in forces or torques, so understanding what degree of fault severity is noticeable is also important. This knowledge helps in designing exoskeletons that can maintain high performance and reliability even in the presence of faults, thereby enhancing user safety and confidence. A compliant control method, such as impedance control, is a suitable solution for providing the required support while allowing for adaptability in the pHRI behavior [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>].</p><p id="Par5">This article extends previous research on fault-tolerant pHRI in elastic actuators [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>], where a trajectory tracking control strategy based on an established passivity-based impedance controller from [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>] was implemented. The control strategy was capable of adapting a desired interaction impedance behavior by detecting and compensating faults in elastic elements using online stiffness estimation. Specifically, we contribute by adapting the strategy to providing torque support, and investigate the impact of compensated and uncompensated faults on user perception when interacting with a SEA-powered knee exoskeleton. We explore the theoretical foundations and experimental validation of the proposed control method for providing a gait torque support profile to users through the knee exoskeleton, and present a user study to evaluate how users experience changes in gait support due to faults. The study investigated the impact on the perceived support level, stiffness, comfort, and trust of several users while physically interacting with the knee exoskeleton in locomotion under different fault conditions. The main contributions of the paper are summarized in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>.</p><p id="Par6">
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Main contributions of the paper. The primary research question, methods, and results are summarized. Results from the user study conducted showed that, when faults are compensated, participants did not distinguish faulty conditions in terms of support and stiffness, suggesting that fault tolerance is achieved. Meanwhile, for uncompensated faults, participants clearly distinguished mid and high faulty conditions</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par7">The rest of the article is organized as follows. Section&#x000a0;"<xref rid="Sec2" ref-type="sec">Fault-tolerant torque control</xref>" details the torque control strategy. Section&#x000a0;"<xref rid="Sec7" ref-type="sec">Materials and methods</xref>" describes the hardware setup, experimental evaluation, and user study design. Section&#x000a0;"<xref rid="Sec13" ref-type="sec">User study results</xref>" presents the results of the user study. Findings are discussed in Sect.&#x000a0;"<xref rid="Sec14" ref-type="sec">Discussion</xref>". Finally, conclusions are presented in Sect.&#x000a0;"<xref rid="Sec15" ref-type="sec">Conclusions</xref>".</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Fault-tolerant torque control</title><p id="Par8">Consider that, in a general case, a rotary series elastic actuator (SEA), shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, has an input position <inline-formula id="IEq1"><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\varphi _i$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M2"><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq1.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and output position <inline-formula id="IEq2"><alternatives><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\varphi _o$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M4"><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq2.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, and its output torque <inline-formula id="IEq3"><alternatives><tex-math id="M5">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\tau _o$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M6"><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq3.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> completely defined by a nonlinear elastic torque function which depends on its deflection <inline-formula id="IEq4"><alternatives><tex-math id="M7">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\alpha =\varphi _i-\varphi _o$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M8"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq4.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. The actuator dynamics can then be defined by<disp-formula id="Equ1"><label>1</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M9">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} J_i\ddot{\varphi }_i&#x00026;=\tau _i-\tau _o-\tau _\text {fric}-\tau _\text {dist}\,, \\ \text {with } \tau _{o}&#x00026;= \text {f}(\alpha )\,,\nonumber \end{aligned}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M10" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000a8;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mtext>fric</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mtext>dist</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow/><mml:mtext>with</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.333333em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mtext>f</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_Equ1.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <inline-formula id="IEq5"><alternatives><tex-math id="M11">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$J_i$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M12"><mml:msub><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq5.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is the input-side inertia, <inline-formula id="IEq6"><alternatives><tex-math id="M13">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\tau _i$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M14"><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq6.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is the input torque provided by the motor, <inline-formula id="IEq7"><alternatives><tex-math id="M15">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\tau _\text {fric}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M16"><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mtext>fric</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq7.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is the friction torque, and <inline-formula id="IEq8"><alternatives><tex-math id="M17">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\tau _\text {dist}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M18"><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mtext>dist</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq8.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> represents torque caused by disturbances.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Diagram of a general SEA with the output torque <inline-formula id="IEq9"><alternatives><tex-math id="M19">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\tau _o$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M20"><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq9.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> as a nonlinear torque function of its deflection</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p><p id="Par9">Given the relationship between torque and deflection in SEAs, torque control can be implemented indirectly by controlling the motor position. A desired torque reference <inline-formula id="IEq10"><alternatives><tex-math id="M21">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\tau _{o,d}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M22"><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq10.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> can be obtained by computing a reference input position <inline-formula id="IEq11"><alternatives><tex-math id="M23">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\varphi _{i,d}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M24"><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq11.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> such that<disp-formula id="Equ2"><label>2</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M25">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} \tau _{o,d}=\text {f}(\alpha _d), \quad \varphi _{i,d}=\alpha _d+\varphi _{o}\,. \end{aligned}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M26" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mtext>f</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_Equ2.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par10">The block diagram of the torque control strategy is shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>. The desired torque <inline-formula id="IEq15"><alternatives><tex-math id="M27">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\tau _{o,d}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M28"><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq15.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is transformed into a reference deflection <inline-formula id="IEq16"><alternatives><tex-math id="M29">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\alpha _d$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M30"><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq16.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> by utilizing the inverse torque function <inline-formula id="IEq17"><alternatives><tex-math id="M31">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\text{f}_\text {inv}(\tau _{o,d})=\alpha _d$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M32"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>f</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>inv</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq17.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. However, since it might not be possible to describe the inverse of nonlinear function analytically, one can resort to finding the root of the auxiliary function <inline-formula id="IEq18"><alternatives><tex-math id="M33">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\text {h}(\alpha ) = \text {f}(\alpha )-\tau _{o,d}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M34"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>h</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mtext>f</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq18.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> at each time step using the Newton&#x02013;Raphson method iteratively at discrete instances <inline-formula id="IEq19"><alternatives><tex-math id="M35">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$i=0,1,2,\dots$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M36"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x022ef;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq19.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>:<disp-formula id="Equ3"><label>3</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M37">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} \alpha _{i+1} = \alpha _i + \frac{\text {h}(\alpha _i)}{\text {h}'(\alpha _i)}\,, \end{aligned}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M38" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>h</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mtext>h</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x02032;</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_Equ3.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <inline-formula id="IEq20"><alternatives><tex-math id="M39">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\text {h}'(\alpha )=\frac{\partial \text {f}(\alpha )}{\partial \alpha }$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M40"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mtext>h</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x02032;</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02202;</mml:mi><mml:mtext>f</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02202;</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq20.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. The process is repeated until the root is found (when the absolute value of <inline-formula id="IEq21"><alternatives><tex-math id="M41">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\text {h}(\alpha _i)$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M42"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>h</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq21.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is below a threshold) or a maximum number of iterations is reached. The value of the last iteration then corresponds to <inline-formula id="IEq22"><alternatives><tex-math id="M43">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\alpha _d$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M44"><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq22.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and the reference input position <inline-formula id="IEq23"><alternatives><tex-math id="M45">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\varphi _{i,d}=\alpha _d+\varphi _o$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M46"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq23.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is tracked by an impedance controller. <fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Torque assistive control strategy for the nonlinear series elastic actuator that drives the knee exoskeleton. A desired torque <inline-formula id="IEq12"><alternatives><tex-math id="M47">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\tau _{o,d}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M48"><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq12.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is tracked by transforming the torque reference into a desired deflection <inline-formula id="IEq13"><alternatives><tex-math id="M49">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\alpha _d$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M50"><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq13.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and to a desired actuator trajectory <inline-formula id="IEq14"><alternatives><tex-math id="M51">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\varphi _{i,d}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M52"><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq14.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. A passivity-based impedance controller is then used to track the reference and attain the desired torque. A parameter estimation algorithm is used to observe the spring pretension parameter <italic>P</italic> which is modulated to emulate faults</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p><sec id="Sec3"><title>Impedance controller</title><p id="Par11">Now consider the following control law, adapted from [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>], of a passivity-based impedance controller for trajectory tracking with inertia shaping and friction compensation:<disp-formula id="Equ4"><label>4</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M53">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} \tau _i = \frac{J_i}{J_{i,d}}u+\left( 1-\frac{J_i}{J_{i,d}}\right) \tau _o+\tau _\text {fric}\,, \end{aligned}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M54" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mtext>fric</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_Equ4.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where<disp-formula id="Equ5"><label>5</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M55">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} u = J_{i,d}\ddot{\varphi }_{i,d}+ \tau _{o,d}+k_c(\varphi _{i,d}-\varphi _i)+d_c(\dot{\varphi }_{i,d}-\dot{\varphi }_i)\,. \end{aligned}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M56" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000a8;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_Equ5.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>Note that the first and second terms of the control variable in eq. (<xref rid="Equ5" ref-type="disp-formula">5</xref>) perform feedforward inertial and elastic torque compensation, respectively; while the third and fourth terms function as a proportional-derivative controller with the proportional value <inline-formula id="IEq24"><alternatives><tex-math id="M57">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$k_c$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M58"><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq24.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> acting as a virtual spring with equilibrium position at <inline-formula id="IEq25"><alternatives><tex-math id="M59">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\varphi _{i,d}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M60"><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq25.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, and the derivative value <inline-formula id="IEq26"><alternatives><tex-math id="M61">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$d_c$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M62"><mml:msub><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq26.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> acting as a virtual damper with equilibrium position at <inline-formula id="IEq27"><alternatives><tex-math id="M63">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\dot{\varphi }_{i,d}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M64"><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq27.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Closed-loop dynamics</title><p id="Par12">Applying the control law in eq. (<xref rid="Equ4" ref-type="disp-formula">4</xref>) to the actuator dynamics in eq. (<xref rid="Equ1" ref-type="disp-formula">1</xref>) attains the following closed-loop dynamics:<disp-formula id="Equ6"><label>6</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M65">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} J_{i,d}\ddot{\tilde{\varphi }}_i+d_c \dot{\tilde{\varphi }}_i+k_c \tilde{\varphi }_i&#x00026;=-\tilde{\tau }_o + \frac{J_{i,d}}{J_i}\tau _\text {dist}\,, \end{aligned}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M66" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">~</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>&#x000a8;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">~</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">~</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">~</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>o</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mtext>dist</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_Equ6.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <inline-formula id="IEq28"><alternatives><tex-math id="M67">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\tilde{\varphi }_i=\varphi _{i,d}-\varphi _i$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M68"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">~</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq28.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq29"><alternatives><tex-math id="M69">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\tilde{\tau }_o = \tau _{o,d}-\tau _o$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M70"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">~</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>o</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq29.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. In order to relate the equation to only <inline-formula id="IEq30"><alternatives><tex-math id="M71">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\tilde{\varphi }_i$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M72"><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">~</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq30.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> or <inline-formula id="IEq31"><alternatives><tex-math id="M73">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\tilde{\tau _o}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M74"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">~</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq31.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, we should consider the linearized case: <inline-formula id="IEq32"><alternatives><tex-math id="M75">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\tilde{\tau }_o \approx k_s \tilde{\varphi }_i$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M76"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">~</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>o</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">~</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq32.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula id="IEq33"><alternatives><tex-math id="M77">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$k_s$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M78"><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq33.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> corresponds to the instantaneous stiffness constant:<disp-formula id="Equ7"><label>7</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M79">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} k_s=\frac{\partial \text {f}(\alpha )}{\partial \alpha }\,. \end{aligned}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M80" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02202;</mml:mi><mml:mtext>f</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02202;</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_Equ7.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>The closed-loop dynamics can now be expressed as<disp-formula id="Equ8"><label>8</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M81">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} J_{i,d}\ddot{\tilde{\varphi }}_i+d_c \dot{\tilde{\varphi }}_i+(k_c+k_s)\tilde{\varphi }_i= \frac{J_{i,d}}{J_i}\tau _\text {dist}\,, \end{aligned}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M82" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">~</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>&#x000a8;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">~</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">~</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mtext>dist</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_Equ8.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>or<disp-formula id="Equ9"><label>9</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M83">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} \frac{J_{i,d}}{k_s}\ddot{\tilde{\tau }}_o+\frac{d_c}{k_s}\dot{\tilde{\tau }}_o+\left( \frac{k_c}{k_s}+1\right) \tilde{\tau }_o=\frac{J_{i,d}}{J_i}\tau _\text {dist}\,. \end{aligned}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M84" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">~</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>&#x000a8;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>o</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">~</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>o</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mfenced><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">~</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>o</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mtext>dist</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_Equ9.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>Notice that for the non-disturbed case, i.e., <inline-formula id="IEq34"><alternatives><tex-math id="M85">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\tau _\text {dist}=0$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M86"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mtext>dist</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq34.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, the closed-loop dynamics for both position and torque are described by a second order homogeneous linear differential equation with natural frequency <inline-formula id="IEq35"><alternatives><tex-math id="M87">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\omega _0$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M88"><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c9;</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq35.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and damping ratio <inline-formula id="IEq36"><alternatives><tex-math id="M89">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\delta$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M90"><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq36.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>:<disp-formula id="Equ10"><label>10</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M91">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} \omega _0 = \sqrt{\frac{k_c+k_s}{J_{i,d}}}\,,\quad \delta = \frac{d_c}{2\omega _0 J_{i,d}}\,. \end{aligned}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M92" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c9;</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mfrac></mml:msqrt><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c9;</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_Equ10.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>The proposed approach is based on the trajectory tracking control strategy from our previous research [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>], which utilizes the same impedance control algorithm but the input reference is computed based on the reference output trajectory. In this work, the strategy is adapted for torque control, which is a very common approach for lower limb assistive robotic devices [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>], by computing an input reference based on the output feedback and a reference torque that is ideally tracked regardless of the selected virtual impedance components. The control parameters <inline-formula id="IEq37"><alternatives><tex-math id="M93">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$J_{i,d}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M94"><mml:msub><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq37.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="IEq38"><alternatives><tex-math id="M95">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$d_c$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M96"><mml:msub><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq38.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula id="IEq39"><alternatives><tex-math id="M97">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$k_c$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M98"><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq39.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> can be, in principle, tuned to obtain a critically damped response.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Disturbance rejection</title><p id="Par13">Analyzing the disturbance rejection, the transfer function of the linearized dynamics in eq. (<xref rid="Equ9" ref-type="disp-formula">9</xref>) is the following:<disp-formula id="Equ11"><label>11</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M99">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} D(s)=\frac{\tilde{\tau }_o(s)}{\tau _\text {dist}(s)}=\frac{J_{i,d}}{J_i}\left( \frac{k_s}{J_{i,d}s^2+d_cs+k_c+k_s}\right) \,. \end{aligned}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M100" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">~</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>o</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mtext>dist</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_Equ11.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>Note that for a low operating frequency<disp-formula id="Equ12"><label>12</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M101">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} \lim _{s\rightarrow 0} D(s)= \frac{J_{i,d}}{J_i}\left( \frac{k_s}{k_c+k_s}\right) \,. \end{aligned}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M102" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:munder><mml:mo movablelimits="true">lim</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02192;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_Equ12.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>From this we can notice that the disturbance rejection is lower for a stiffer system, but it also improves by selecting a high virtual stiffness <inline-formula id="IEq40"><alternatives><tex-math id="M103">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$k_c$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M104"><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq40.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>.</p><p id="Par14">The control law in eq. (<xref rid="Equ4" ref-type="disp-formula">4</xref>) allows to virtually shape a desired inertia <inline-formula id="IEq41"><alternatives><tex-math id="M105">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$J_{i,d}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M106"><mml:msub><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq41.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. Inertia shaping is effectively engaged in instances where <inline-formula id="IEq42"><alternatives><tex-math id="M107">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$J_{i,d}\ne J_i$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M108"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02260;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq42.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. Typically, a reduction in inertia, i.e, <inline-formula id="IEq43"><alternatives><tex-math id="M109">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$J_{i,d}\le J_i$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M110"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02264;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq43.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is advantageous. Diminishing inertia results in an elevated multiplier for the control input, thereby enhancing the system&#x02019;s responsiveness. Our prior research demonstrated that opting for a lower desired inertia yields favorable outcomes in haptic perception [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. It is important to observe that this reduction in inertia concurrently diminishes disturbance rejection by a commensurate factor, thereby augmenting the system&#x02019;s resilience to unmodeled or disruptive behaviors.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Fault compensation</title><p id="Par15">The adaptability of the proposed model-based approach allows to accommodate faults as uncertain parameters. As mentioned in Sect.&#x000a0;"<xref rid="Sec1" ref-type="sec">Introduction</xref>", elastic faults are conceptualized as changes in the anticipated behavior of the elastic torque function <inline-formula id="IEq44"><alternatives><tex-math id="M111">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\text {f}(\alpha )$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M112"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>f</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq44.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> caused by changes in the internal parameters which depend on the actuator design (e.g., spring pretension). Accurate fault detection, in this case, requires to identify and observe relevant uncertain parameters.</p><p id="Par16">In this work, an online parameter estimation method, adapted from [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>], is applied, where an unscented Kalman filter (UKF) is used to estimate the spring pretension <italic>P</italic> in a SEA with a nonlinear torque-deflection relationship, described in Sect.&#x000a0;"<xref rid="Sec8" ref-type="sec">Knee exoskeleton</xref>". Changes in pretension emulate stiffness degradation due to the deformation of the spring, and/or faults in the kinematic elements that comprise the tensing mechanism that adds pretension to the linear spring, e.g., the deformation of the connecting cable. In practice, the method can be applied to estimate any internal parameter that alters the elastic torque function and is subject to changes due to faults. The online estimation method is applied at discrete time instances <inline-formula id="IEq45"><alternatives><tex-math id="M113">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$n=0,1,2\dots$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M114"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x022ef;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq45.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and requires that the output torque at a particular time instance <inline-formula id="IEq46"><alternatives><tex-math id="M115">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\tau _{o,n}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M116"><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq46.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is known or measured. The estimation is then performed considering that the elastic torque function depends on both the deflection and the internal parameter, in this case the pretension: <inline-formula id="IEq47"><alternatives><tex-math id="M117">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\tau _{o,n}=\text {f}(\alpha _n,P_n)$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M118"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mtext>f</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq47.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>.</p><p id="Par17">Our filter was designed with the pretension as the state value <inline-formula id="IEq48"><alternatives><tex-math id="M119">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$x_n=P_n$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M120"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq48.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, the deflection as input <inline-formula id="IEq49"><alternatives><tex-math id="M121">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$u_n=\alpha _n$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M122"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq49.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, and the elastic torque as the measured output <inline-formula id="IEq50"><alternatives><tex-math id="M123">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$y_n=\tau _{o,n}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M124"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq50.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. The UKF algorithm considering additive (zero mean) noise from [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>] was then used to find the estimated state <inline-formula id="IEq51"><alternatives><tex-math id="M125">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\hat{x}_n=\hat{P}_n$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M126"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq51.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, considering the state and measurement functions <inline-formula id="IEq52"><alternatives><tex-math id="M127">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\text {F}(x_n,u_n)=P_n$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M128"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>F</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq52.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq53"><alternatives><tex-math id="M129">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\text {H}(x_n,u_n)=\text {f}(\alpha _n,P_n)$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M130"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>H</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mtext>f</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq53.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, respectively.</p><p id="Par18">During experimentation with active fault detection, to avoid delays in the convergence of the estimated pretension to the reference value, the UKF algorithm is restarted after each pretension change, with the expected pretension as the initial value. The UKF algorithm was internally parameterized based on the recommendations from [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. The measurement noise covariance was set to <inline-formula id="IEq54"><alternatives><tex-math id="M131">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$R=0.7$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M132"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.7</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq54.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, while the process noise covariance was tuned for smooth and slow dynamics to <inline-formula id="IEq55"><alternatives><tex-math id="M133">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$Q= {1e-12}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M134"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq55.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>.</p><p id="Par19">A fault is <italic>compensated</italic> when the parameter estimation algorithm is active and the precise values of the uncertain parameter is known and considered in control calculations, while the fault is <italic>uncompensated</italic> when the parameter is set at a constant baseline value (no fault detection), which makes the determination of the reference input position <inline-formula id="IEq56"><alternatives><tex-math id="M135">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\varphi _{i,d}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M136"><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq56.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and the control&#x000a0;law prone to inaccuracy, potentially leading to a deviation from the desired system behavior.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Materials and methods</title><p id="Par20">This section details the material and methods utilized to evaluate the control strategy presented in Sect.&#x000a0;"<xref rid="Sec2" ref-type="sec">Fault-tolerant torque control</xref>" to achieve fault tolerance in a knee exoskeleton as a scenario of tight pHRI interaction. The knee exoskeleton is presented, followed by an experimental functional evaluation with a single user, and finally a user study design to evaluate fault tolerance and user interaction with multiple participants.</p><sec id="Sec8"><title>Knee exoskeleton</title><p id="Par21">Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> shows the design of the knee exoskeleton for experimentation on a treadmill. Powered by the SMARCOS actuator [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>], a mechanically adjustable compliance and controllable equilibrium position actuator (MACCEPA), the exoskeleton attaches to the leg segments using braces 3D-printed with technical flexible filament (Flexfill TPU) and secured with Velcro straps. Adjustable plates and alignment screws allow to customize the brace positions in the proximal/distal and medial/lateral directions to ensure that the axis of rotation of the actuator aligns with that of the knee of the user. A shoulder strap supports the weight of the device (4.05&#x000a0;kg) during walking. Finally, the elastic properties of the actuator can be modulated by altering the pretension of a linear spring using a servomotor, effectively emulating elastic faults.</p><p id="Par22">
<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Knee exoskeleton experimental setup. The elastic actuator, which drives the exoskeleton, is equipped with a pretension altering mechanism to emulate faults by changing the elastic behavior of the actuator. The exoskeleton is attached to the user using braces with Velcro straps and adjustable plates with alignment screws to customize the brace positions in the proximal/distal and medial/lateral directions. A shoulder strap is included to support the weight of the device. An instrumented insole, embedded with a force-sensing resistor, is used to detect heel strike</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par23">The actuator configuration, shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>, consists of an input link between points <italic>A</italic> and <italic>R</italic>, an output link between points <italic>C</italic> and <italic>R</italic>, and a lever arm between points <italic>B</italic>, <italic>R</italic>, and <italic>D</italic>, all rotating around point <italic>R</italic>. The input link and the lever arm are rigidly coupled through a motorized screw drive between points <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic>. Moreover, a linear spring with stiffness <italic>k</italic> is connected between points <italic>C</italic> and <italic>D</italic>. The positions of the lever arm <inline-formula id="IEq57"><alternatives><tex-math id="M137">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\varphi _i$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M138"><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq57.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and output link <inline-formula id="IEq58"><alternatives><tex-math id="M139">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\varphi _o$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M140"><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq58.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> are measured with magnetic encoders, their speeds are computed with filtered numerical derivation, and the elastic torque <inline-formula id="IEq59"><alternatives><tex-math id="M141">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\tau _o$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M142"><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq59.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is indirectly computed from force measurement at the base of the motor.</p><p id="Par24">The output torque <inline-formula id="IEq60"><alternatives><tex-math id="M143">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\tau _o$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M144"><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq60.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> created by the spring due to the deformation <inline-formula id="IEq61"><alternatives><tex-math id="M145">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\alpha = \varphi _i-\varphi _o$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M146"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq61.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> can be computed based on the geometric properties of the actuator [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]:<disp-formula id="Equ13"><label>13</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M147">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} \tau _o = \text {f}(\alpha ) = kL_CL_D\sin {\alpha }\left( 1+\frac{P-\left| L_D-L_C\right| }{L_{CD}}\right) ,\\ \text {with } L_{CD}=\left( L_C^2+L_D^2-2L_CL_D\cos {\alpha }\right) ^{1/2}\,,\nonumber \end{aligned}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M148" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mtext>f</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>sin</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close="|" open="|"><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CD</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow/><mml:mtext>with</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.333333em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CD</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>cos</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi></mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_Equ13.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <inline-formula id="IEq62"><alternatives><tex-math id="M149">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$L_C$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M150"><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq62.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is the length between points <italic>C</italic> and <italic>R</italic>, <inline-formula id="IEq63"><alternatives><tex-math id="M151">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$L_D$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M152"><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq63.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is the length between points <italic>D</italic> and <italic>R</italic>, and <italic>P</italic> corresponds to the pretension length of the spring. The solution of eq. (<xref rid="Equ13" ref-type="disp-formula">13</xref>) for <inline-formula id="IEq64"><alternatives><tex-math id="M153">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\alpha$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M154"><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq64.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is not analytically possible. Therefore, the Newton&#x02013;Raphson iterative method, described in Sect.&#x000a0;"<xref rid="Sec2" ref-type="sec">Fault-tolerant torque control</xref>", is used to find a numerical solution.</p><p id="Par25">The behavior of the MACCEPA is that of a SEA with a nonlinear torque function. At a given deflection, the apparent stiffness of the actuator can be computed based on eq. (<xref rid="Equ7" ref-type="disp-formula">7</xref>) as<disp-formula id="Equ14"><label>14</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M155">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} k_{s} = kL_CL_D\cos {\alpha }\left( 1+\frac{P-\left| L_D-L_C\right| }{L_{CD}}\right) -kL^2_CL^2_D\sin ^2{\alpha }\left( \frac{P-\left| L_D-L_C\right| }{L_{CD}^3}\right) . \end{aligned}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M156" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>cos</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close="|" open="|"><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CD</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:msup><mml:mo>sin</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close="|" open="|"><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CD</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msubsup></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_Equ14.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>Modifying the pretension <italic>P</italic> alters the behavior of <inline-formula id="IEq65"><alternatives><tex-math id="M157">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\text {f}(\alpha )$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M158"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>f</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq65.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq66"><alternatives><tex-math id="M159">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$k_s$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M160"><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq66.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and thus emulates elastic faults as they might be caused by plastic deformations in the spring or cables in the coupling mechanism.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Kinematic model of the MACCEPA-based actuator</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Functional evaluation experiments</title><p id="Par26">We tested the performance of the exoskeleton while walking on a treadmill at a fixed speed in two different conditions: In <italic>zero-torque mode</italic>, the provided support is zero, i.e., the user can walk freely, ideally without resistance; and in <italic>support mode</italic>, a torque profile is provided in synchronism with the gait cycle. Experiments were carried out with one experienced user (male, 177&#x000a0;cm, 90&#x000a0;kg) walking on a treadmill at 0.58m/s. The synchronization of gait cycle was triggered by a force-sensing resistor (FSR) embedded in an instrumented insole, which detects heel strike as the beginning of the gait cycle. For simplicity, and to avoid introducing noisy signal derivatives to the control law, we assume that the position reference <inline-formula id="IEq67"><alternatives><tex-math id="M161">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\varphi _{i,d}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M162"><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq67.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is static, i.e., <inline-formula id="IEq68"><alternatives><tex-math id="M163">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\dot{\varphi }_{i,d}=0$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M164"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq68.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq69"><alternatives><tex-math id="M165">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\ddot{\varphi }_{i,d}=0$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M166"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000a8;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq69.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>&#x000a0;.</p><p id="Par27">The friction is modeled combining dry (Coulomb) and viscous components [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]:<disp-formula id="Equ15"><label>15</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M167">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} \tau _\text {fric} = c_{c}{{\,\textrm{sign}\,}}{\dot{\varphi }} + c_v\dot{\varphi }\,, \end{aligned}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M168" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mtext>fric</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mtext>sign</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/></mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_Equ15.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <inline-formula id="IEq70"><alternatives><tex-math id="M169">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$c_c$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M170"><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq70.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq71"><alternatives><tex-math id="M171">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$c_v$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M172"><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq71.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> are the Coulomb and viscous friction coefficients, respectively. The parameters of the actuator, extracted from [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>] and [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>], and the control parameters used in the experimentation are detailed in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>.
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Parameters of the MACCEPA-based actuator</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Description</th><th align="left"/><th align="left">Value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Input-side inertia</td><td align="left">
<inline-formula id="IEq72"><alternatives><tex-math id="M173">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$J_i$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M174"><mml:msub><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq72.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left">
<inline-formula id="IEq73"><alternatives><tex-math id="M175">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$1.90\times 10^{-4}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M176"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.90</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq73.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> kg m<inline-formula id="IEq74"><alternatives><tex-math id="M177">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$^{2}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M178"><mml:mmultiscripts><mml:mrow/><mml:mrow/><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mmultiscripts></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq74.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Spring stiffness</td><td align="left"><italic>k</italic></td><td align="left">
<inline-formula id="IEq75"><alternatives><tex-math id="M179">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$118.30\times 10^{3}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M180"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>118.30</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq75.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> N/m </td></tr><tr><td align="left">Lever arm length C</td><td align="left">
<inline-formula id="IEq76"><alternatives><tex-math id="M181">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$L_C$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M182"><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq76.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left">0.056 m</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Output link length</td><td align="left">
<inline-formula id="IEq77"><alternatives><tex-math id="M183">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$L_D$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M184"><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq77.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left">0.0645 m</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Input viscous fric. coefficient</td><td align="left">
<inline-formula id="IEq78"><alternatives><tex-math id="M185">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$c_{v}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M186"><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq78.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left">0.262</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Input Coulomb fric. coefficient</td><td align="left">
<inline-formula id="IEq79"><alternatives><tex-math id="M187">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$c_{c}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M188"><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq79.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left">0.145 N</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Desired input-side inertia</td><td align="left">
<inline-formula id="IEq80"><alternatives><tex-math id="M189">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$J_{i,d}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M190"><mml:msub><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq80.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left">
<inline-formula id="IEq81"><alternatives><tex-math id="M191">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$3.80\times 10^{-5}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M192"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3.80</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq81.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> kg m<inline-formula id="IEq82"><alternatives><tex-math id="M193">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$^{2}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M194"><mml:mmultiscripts><mml:mrow/><mml:mrow/><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mmultiscripts></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq82.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Virtual stiffness</td><td align="left">
<inline-formula id="IEq83"><alternatives><tex-math id="M195">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$k_c$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M196"><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq83.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left">100 N m/rad</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Virtual damping</td><td align="left">
<inline-formula id="IEq84"><alternatives><tex-math id="M197">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$d_c$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M198"><mml:msub><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq84.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left">1 N m s/rad</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><sec id="Sec10"><title>Zero-torque mode</title><p id="Par28">Considering the strategy presented in Sect.&#x000a0;"<xref rid="Sec2" ref-type="sec">Fault-tolerant torque control</xref>", a fixed zero-torque support <inline-formula id="IEq85"><alternatives><tex-math id="M199">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\tau _{o,d}=0$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M200"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq85.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is obtained when <inline-formula id="IEq86"><alternatives><tex-math id="M201">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\varphi _{i,d}=\varphi _o$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M202"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq86.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. This should be achievable in dynamic conditions with a fast enough response from the motor. However, in practice, the motor is limited both in maximum speed and acceleration, which might lead to deviations from the desired zero-torque reference. Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref> shows the residual torque measurements and motor shaft speed (before transmission) throughout 60 gait cycles of the user walking with the exoskeleton in zero-torque mode with two different pretension values (mean and SD shown as line and shaded area, respectively). It is obvious that the residual torque is higher during swing, where the output position has a faster motion. With a pretension value of <inline-formula id="IEq87"><alternatives><tex-math id="M203">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$P={4}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M204"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq87.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>&#x000a0;mm, the root mean square (RMS) of the residual torque measurements was 0.30&#x000a0;N m; and for a pretension value of <inline-formula id="IEq88"><alternatives><tex-math id="M205">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$P={1}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M206"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq88.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>&#x000a0;mm, the obtained RMS was 0.10&#x000a0;N m. A lower pretension value attains a lower residual torque, which is to be expected since the system becomes inherently softer. This, in turn, might affect user perception as a softer configuration might lead to a more transparent interaction in zero-torque control. From the motor shaft speed measurements, it is noticeable that the higher torque deviations occur at points where direction changes and when the motor saturates at its no-load speed. This showcases the limitations of the motor in terms of acceleration and speed. Higher walking speeds could then increase the residual torque during swing, and seriously affect user perception.</p><p id="Par29">
<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Torque and motor shaft speed measurements throughout 60 gait cycles of a user walking on a treadmill at 0.58m/s wearing the knee exoskeleton in zero-torque mode with two pretension configurations: P=4mm (shown in blue) and P=1mm (shown in yellow). Mean and SD are shown as line and shaded area, respectively. Torque is computed from eq. (<xref rid="Equ13" ref-type="disp-formula">13</xref>) with measured deflection and known pretension value. Data RMS: 0.30&#x000a0;N m for P = 4&#x000a0;mm and 0.10&#x000a0;N m for P = 1&#x000a0;mm. The lower pretension configuration attains a lower residual torque which might affect user perception. Motor shaft speed measurements showcase the limitation of the motor in terms of acceleration and speed to maintain the desired zero torque during swing</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Support mode</title><p id="Par30">Biomechanical joint torque data from walking experiments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>] showed that the knee presents a peak of extension torque during early stance, followed by a peak of flexion torque during late stance. Accordingly, the torque profile used in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>] for knee exoskeleton support was implemented in this work. The applied torque profile is shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>. It is characterized by timing parameters <inline-formula id="IEq89"><alternatives><tex-math id="M207">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$t_1$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M208"><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq89.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="IEq90"><alternatives><tex-math id="M209">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$t_2$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M210"><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq90.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula id="IEq91"><alternatives><tex-math id="M211">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$t_3$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M212"><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq91.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, and a support level <inline-formula id="IEq92"><alternatives><tex-math id="M213">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\tau _\text {max}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M214"><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mtext>max</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq92.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, which corresponds to the peak of extension torque. To reduce the number of parameters, the peak of flexion torque is kept at half of the support level, i.e., <inline-formula id="IEq93"><alternatives><tex-math id="M215">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\frac{1}{2}\tau _\text {max}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M216"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mtext>max</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq93.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. The curve is generated using a Piecewise Cubic Hermite Interpolating Polynomial (PCHIP) with waypoints at <inline-formula id="IEq94"><alternatives><tex-math id="M217">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$(0,0),(t_1,0),(\frac{t_2+t_1}{2},-\tau _\text {max}),(t_2,0),(\frac{t_3+t_2}{2},\frac{1}{2}\tau _\text {max}),(100,0)$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M218"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mtext>max</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mtext>max</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq94.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. It is important to mention that the provided torque profile does not necessarily correspond to a biomechanically optimal trajectory for an intended purpose, e.g., metabolic cost reduction or rehabilitation, nor was the intention of this work to determine an optimal torque profile. Instead, it serves as a scenario of close interaction to test fault tolerance and user experience.<fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Torque profile for walking support (top) compared to characteristic sagittal plane knee joint angles during a single gait cycle (bottom), reproduced from [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. Extension support with a peak torque of <inline-formula id="IEq95"><alternatives><tex-math id="M219">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\tau _\text {max}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M220"><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mtext>max</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq95.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is provided during early stance and flexion support with a peak torque of <inline-formula id="IEq96"><alternatives><tex-math id="M221">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\frac{1}{2}\tau _\text {max}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M222"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mtext>max</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq96.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is provided during late stance. No support is provided during swing. The profile is characterized by timing parameters <inline-formula id="IEq97"><alternatives><tex-math id="M223">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$t_1$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M224"><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq97.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="IEq98"><alternatives><tex-math id="M225">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$t_2$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M226"><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq98.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula id="IEq99"><alternatives><tex-math id="M227">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$t_3$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M228"><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq99.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. The curve is generated using a Piecewise Cubic Hermite Interpolating Polynomial (PCHIP) with waypoints marked with yellow circles</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Fig7_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig></p><p id="Par31">During experimentation, faults are emulated by lowering the pretension value <italic>P</italic> from its initial value of 4&#x000a0;mm (<inline-formula id="IEq100"><alternatives><tex-math id="M229">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$P=100\%$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M230"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mo>%</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq100.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>) to different fault levels: Low Fault (<inline-formula id="IEq101"><alternatives><tex-math id="M231">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$P=75\%$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M232"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>75</mml:mn><mml:mo>%</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq101.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>), Mid Fault (<inline-formula id="IEq102"><alternatives><tex-math id="M233">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$P=50\%$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M234"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>50</mml:mn><mml:mo>%</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq102.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>), and High Fault (<inline-formula id="IEq103"><alternatives><tex-math id="M235">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$P=25\%$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M236"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>25</mml:mn><mml:mo>%</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq103.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>). Furthermore a <italic>compensated fault</italic> condition was set when the control strategy utilizes the actual value of <italic>P</italic> for calculations, and an uncompensated fault condition was set by utilizing the initial pretension (<inline-formula id="IEq104"><alternatives><tex-math id="M237">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$P=100\%$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M238"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mo>%</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq104.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>) for calculations.</p><p id="Par32">Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref> shows the results of the torque tracking with all different fault conditions throughout 60 gait cycles (mean and SD shown as line and shaded area, respectively). From the plots, it can be seen that for uncompensated faults, the obtained deflection remains similar throughout all fault conditions. Due to the lower stiffness when faults are emulated, the obtained output torque deviates from the reference, with the deviation increasing as the fault becomes more severe. In other words, uncompensated elastic faults lower the torque support level with respect to the fault severity. When faults are compensated, the obtained deflection increases in order to attain the torque reference. That means that higher fault severity requires higher deflection in order to maintain the desired torque level. This might also be a limiting factor, particularly for higher walking speeds, as the saturation of the motor speed might not allow to track the reference torque accurately. Special care should also be taken to avoid damaging the actuator if mechanical limits in position are reached. Yet, it is clear that the torque assistive control strategy is capable of maintaining the torque support level in the presence of faults, effectively achieving fault tolerance.<fig id="Fig8"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>Torque and deflection measurements throughout 60 gait cycles of a user walking on a treadmill at 0.58&#x000a0;m/s wearing the knee exoskeleton providing a torque support profile in four configurations: (<bold>a</bold>) no fault, (<bold>b</bold>) low fault, (<bold>c</bold>) mid fault, and (<bold>d</bold>) high fault. Mean and SD shown as line and shaded area, respectively. Torque is computed from Eq. (<xref rid="Equ13" ref-type="disp-formula">13</xref>) with measured deflection and known pretension value. Measurements with uncompensated faults (in yellow) show that deflection remains similar throughout all conditions, while the torque level degrades as the fault increases in severity. Measurements with compensated faults (in blue) show that torque levels are maintained close to the reference by increasing deflection, achieving fault tolerance</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Fig8_HTML" id="MO8"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>User study design</title><p id="Par33">A user study was conducted using the knee exoskeleton on healthy participants during walking on a treadmill. The objective of the study was to investigate how user experience changes in torque levels due to elastic faults during physical interaction with the exoskeleton. The study was conducted with 10 participants (5 women, 5 men) with an average age of <inline-formula id="IEq105"><alternatives><tex-math id="M239">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${26.70 \pm 2.06}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M240"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>26.70</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b1;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2.06</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq105.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>&#x000a0;years and an average weight of <inline-formula id="IEq106"><alternatives><tex-math id="M241">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${68.20 \pm 16.47}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M242"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>68.20</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b1;</mml:mo><mml:mn>16.47</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq106.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> kg. Informed consent was obtained from all participants involved in the study. The experimentation was conducted in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki 2008 and a vote from the Ethics Commission at TU Darmstadt (EK 18/2017). A technician from Sanit&#x000e4;tshaus OrthoPoint supervised the orthopedic soundness of the knee exoskeleton and provided suggestions and guidelines for the adjustment of the knee exoskeleton. Accordingly, the leg attachments were individually fitted for each participant.</p><p id="Par34">The experimental setup is the same as described in Sect. "<xref rid="Sec9" ref-type="sec">Functional evaluation experiments</xref>" and represented in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>. The torque profile shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref> was utilized as torque reference for the control strategy implemented in the knee exoskeleton, while an instrumented insole was used to detect heel strike and synchronize the beginning of each gait cycle. The walking speed was kept fixed at 0.58m/s for all participants to avoid introducing high residual torque during swing, as discussed in Sect.&#x000a0;"<xref rid="Sec10" ref-type="sec">Zero-torque mode</xref>". A repeated-measures experiment was devised with two independent variables (IV). The first IV is the fault severity, which is defined by the value of the pretension <italic>P</italic> with respect to its baseline value: Low Fault (<inline-formula id="IEq107"><alternatives><tex-math id="M243">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$P=75\%$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M244"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>75</mml:mn><mml:mo>%</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq107.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>), Mid Fault (<inline-formula id="IEq108"><alternatives><tex-math id="M245">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$P=50\%$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M246"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>50</mml:mn><mml:mo>%</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq108.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>), and High Fault (<inline-formula id="IEq109"><alternatives><tex-math id="M247">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$P=25\%$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M248"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>25</mml:mn><mml:mo>%</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq109.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>). The second IV is the fault compensation, which is either <italic>compensated</italic> or <italic>uncompensated</italic>. To investigate the effects of both IVs, we implemented a 3x2 repeated-measures design, such that participants experienced 6 different walking conditions in a random order. The dependent variables are the levels of support, stiffness, comfort, and trust perceived by the users at each condition. The configuration where no fault occurs (<inline-formula id="IEq110"><alternatives><tex-math id="M249">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$P=100\%$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M250"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mo>%</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq110.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>) is considered the <italic>baseline walking condition</italic> and serves as a comparison condition for each of the 6 faulty walking conditions. <fig id="Fig9"><label>Fig. 9</label><caption><p>Schematic of experimental setup for the user study on user perception. A controller commands a torque profile based on the user&#x02019;s gait (synchronized by heel strike). Elastic faults are emulated by altering the spring pretension of the actuator. Faults are compensated when the controller knows the precise altered pretension value, and the torque is corrected</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Fig9_HTML" id="MO9"/></fig></p><p id="Par35">When the torque profile is applied, participants should be able to distinguish the torque support level depending on the maximum effective torque provided. At the same time, the perception of stiffness, which is expected to be closely related to force perception [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>], and walking comfort might also depend on the support level. Furthermore, trust is also an important aspect to measure in the presence of faults, as it allows to understand which aspects contribute to understanding user experience. The hypotheses of the repeated-measures study were:</p><p id="Par36"><italic>Hypothesis 1a: </italic>Participants will perceive changes in support level when faults are uncompensated but not when they are compensated.</p><p id="Par37"><italic>Hypothesis 1b: </italic>Participants will perceive changes in stiffness when faults are uncompensated but not when they are compensated.</p><p id="Par38"><italic>Hypothesis 1c: </italic>Participants will perceive changes in comfort when faults are uncompensated but not when they are compensated.</p><p id="Par39"><italic>Hypothesis 2: </italic>Trust is scored higher for compensated faults than for the uncompensated conditions.</p><p id="Par40">Hypotheses 1a, 1b, and 1c required that participants compared each condition with the baseline condition, while hypothesis 2 required that participants evaluated their perceived trust after each condition. To achieve this in the repeated-measures study, participants walked with the baseline walking condition for 30&#x000a0;s, followed by 30&#x000a0;s of the faulty condition. To safeguard the mechanical soundness of the pretension altering mechanism, 10&#x000a0;s were left between both walking conditions where the participant stopped walking and the pretension was altered. After each repeated measure, the participant filled out the comparison questionnaire, shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>, which evaluates the perceived level of support, stiffness, and comfort between the baseline and the new condition using a Likert scale of comparison: 1&#x000a0;: <italic>a lot lower</italic>, <inline-formula id="IEq111"><alternatives><tex-math id="M251">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$2 \!=\!$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M252"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="-0.166667em"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="-0.166667em"/></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq111.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
<italic>lower</italic>, <inline-formula id="IEq112"><alternatives><tex-math id="M253">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$3 \!=\!$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M254"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="-0.166667em"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="-0.166667em"/></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq112.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
<italic>slightly lower</italic>, <inline-formula id="IEq113"><alternatives><tex-math id="M255">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$4 \!=\!$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M256"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="-0.166667em"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="-0.166667em"/></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq113.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
<italic>the same</italic>, <inline-formula id="IEq114"><alternatives><tex-math id="M257">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$5 \!=\!$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M258"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>5</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="-0.166667em"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="-0.166667em"/></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq114.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
<italic>slightly higher</italic>, <inline-formula id="IEq115"><alternatives><tex-math id="M259">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$6 \!=\!$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M260"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>6</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="-0.166667em"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="-0.166667em"/></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq115.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
<italic>higher</italic>, <inline-formula id="IEq116"><alternatives><tex-math id="M261">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$7 \!=\!$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M262"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>7</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="-0.166667em"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="-0.166667em"/></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq116.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
<italic>a lot higher</italic>; and the trust questionnaire, shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig">11</xref>, extracted from Jian et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>], which evaluates trust in terms of confidence, security, and dependability with a Likert scale of agreement: <inline-formula id="IEq117"><alternatives><tex-math id="M263">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$1 \!=\!$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M264"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="-0.166667em"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="-0.166667em"/></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq117.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
<italic>strongly disagree</italic>, <inline-formula id="IEq118"><alternatives><tex-math id="M265">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$2 \!=\!$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M266"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="-0.166667em"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="-0.166667em"/></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq118.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
<italic>disagree</italic>, <inline-formula id="IEq119"><alternatives><tex-math id="M267">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$3 \!=\!$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M268"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="-0.166667em"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="-0.166667em"/></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq119.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
<italic>slightly disagree</italic>, <inline-formula id="IEq120"><alternatives><tex-math id="M269">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$4 \!=\!$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M270"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="-0.166667em"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="-0.166667em"/></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq120.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
<italic>neutral</italic>, <inline-formula id="IEq121"><alternatives><tex-math id="M271">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$5 \!=\!$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M272"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>5</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="-0.166667em"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="-0.166667em"/></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq121.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
<italic>slightly agree</italic>, <inline-formula id="IEq122"><alternatives><tex-math id="M273">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$6 \!=\!$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M274"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>6</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="-0.166667em"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="-0.166667em"/></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq122.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
<italic>agree</italic>, <inline-formula id="IEq123"><alternatives><tex-math id="M275">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$7 \!=\!$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M276"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>7</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="-0.166667em"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="-0.166667em"/></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq123.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
<italic>strongly agree</italic>.<fig id="Fig10"><label>Fig. 10</label><caption><p>Comparison questionnaire. Compares levels of support, stiffness, and comfort</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Fig10_HTML" id="MO10"/></fig><fig id="Fig11"><label>Fig. 11</label><caption><p>Trust questionnaire. Evaluates confidence, security, and dependability. Extracted from [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Fig11_HTML" id="MO11"/></fig></p><p id="Par41">At the beginning of the study, participants received initial instructions and were requested to don the instrumented heel insole and the knee exoskeleton. Adjustments to the leg attachments were made to ensure that the knee exoskeleton was fitted to the individual body geometry. The participant was asked to walk on the treadmill with the zero-torque mode at a slow walking speed of 0.58m/s. A low torque support profile with <inline-formula id="IEq124"><alternatives><tex-math id="M277">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\tau _\text {max}={0.05}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M278"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mtext>max</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.05</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq124.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>&#x000a0;N&#x000a0;m/kg (normalized to the user weight) was provided to the participant. Timing parameters <inline-formula id="IEq125"><alternatives><tex-math id="M279">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$t_1$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M280"><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq125.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="IEq126"><alternatives><tex-math id="M281">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$t_2$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M282"><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq126.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula id="IEq127"><alternatives><tex-math id="M283">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$t_3$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M284"><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq127.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> were initially set to <inline-formula id="IEq128"><alternatives><tex-math id="M285">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$t_1=10\%$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M286"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mo>%</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq128.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="IEq129"><alternatives><tex-math id="M287">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$t_2=40\%$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M288"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>40</mml:mn><mml:mo>%</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq129.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula id="IEq130"><alternatives><tex-math id="M289">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$t_3=60\%$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M290"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>60</mml:mn><mml:mo>%</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq130.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and subsequently minimally adjusted in a range of <inline-formula id="IEq131"><alternatives><tex-math id="M291">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\pm 10\%$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M292"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000b1;</mml:mo><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mo>%</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq131.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> based on verbal response from the participant and observed gait pattern measurements, such that the profile did not greatly disturb the natural gait of the participant. This adjustment was not meant to optimize the timing parameters, instead, it was applied to find a good compromise for each participant to conduct the study effectively.</p><p id="Par42">Moreover, a <italic>method of adjustment</italic> experiment was conducted where participants were able to manually adjust the support level by increasing or decreasing <inline-formula id="IEq132"><alternatives><tex-math id="M293">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\tau _\text {max}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M294"><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mtext>max</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq132.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> using a provided touchpad. Participants were told to reach a support level that was <italic>noticeable but comfortable</italic>. The method of adjustment was performed three times, starting from three different support levels in a random order: 0.10&#x000a0;N&#x000a0;m/kg, 0.20&#x000a0;N&#x000a0;m/kg, and 0.30&#x000a0;N&#x000a0;m/kg. Participants were not able to see the actual torque level, only to increase or decrease the level through buttons in the touchscreen. The average of the three adjustments was used as the <italic>baseline walking condition</italic>. The method of adjustment served two purposes: it gave an insight of the average support level with which users are comfortable at the selected speed of 0.58m/s, while at the same time allowing participants to familiarize with the perception of different support levels such that they can better distinguish them in the subsequent study.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>User study results</title><p id="Par43">The results of the method of adjustment experiments averaged <inline-formula id="IEq133"><alternatives><tex-math id="M295">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${0.13 \pm 0.04}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M296"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.13</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b1;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.04</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq133.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>&#x000a0;N&#x000a0;m/kg. The selected support levels, which correspond to the peak extension torques, are comparable to the peak extension torque from biological joint data reported by [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>] for a similarly low speed (0.5&#x000a0;m/s).</p><p id="Par44">The obtained results for the repeated-measures study are summarized in Tables <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> and <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>. Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig12" ref-type="fig">12</xref> shows the boxplots of the level comparison for support, stiffness, and comfort; while Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig13" ref-type="fig">13</xref> shows the boxplots of questions evaluating trust. The normality assumption for all 36 data groups was checked with a Shapiro-Wilk test which showed that 8 out of the 36 groups did not distribute normally (<inline-formula id="IEq134"><alternatives><tex-math id="M297">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$p&#x0003c;0.046$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M298"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.046</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq134.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>). For that reason, the differences between the means of the groups for each dependent variable were analyzed with the non-parametric Kruskal-Wallis test [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. For pairwise comparisons, the Dunn&#x02019;s test [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>] with the Benjamini-Hochberg procedure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>] for the correction of the <italic>p</italic> values was used to determine significant differences between groups that share an independent variable.
<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Effect of the IVs on the perception of support, stiffness and comfort when comparing each condition and the baseline</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="3"/><th align="left" colspan="2">Fault compensation</th><th align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>Kruskal-Wallis test</italic></th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="3"/><th align="left">Compensated</th><th align="left">Uncompens.</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3"> Support</td><td align="left" rowspan="3">Fault severity</td><td align="left">Low</td><td align="left">
<inline-formula id="IEq135"><alternatives><tex-math id="M299">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$4.70\pm 0.95$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M300"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4.70</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b1;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.95</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq135.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left">
<inline-formula id="IEq136"><alternatives><tex-math id="M301">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$3.90\pm 1.29$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M302"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3.90</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b1;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.29</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq136.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="3">
<inline-formula id="IEq137"><alternatives><tex-math id="M303">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$p&#x0003c;0.001$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M304"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.001</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq137.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mid</td><td align="left">
<inline-formula id="IEq138"><alternatives><tex-math id="M305">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$4.40\pm 0.84$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M306"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4.40</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b1;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.84</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq138.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left">
<inline-formula id="IEq139"><alternatives><tex-math id="M307">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$3.00\pm 0.94$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M308"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3.00</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b1;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.94</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq139.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">High</td><td align="left">
<inline-formula id="IEq140"><alternatives><tex-math id="M309">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$4.20\pm 0.92$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M310"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4.20</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b1;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.92</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq140.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left">
<inline-formula id="IEq141"><alternatives><tex-math id="M311">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$2.20\pm 1.03$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M312"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2.20</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b1;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.03</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq141.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">Stiffness</td><td align="left" rowspan="3">Fault severity</td><td align="left">Low</td><td align="left">
<inline-formula id="IEq142"><alternatives><tex-math id="M313">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$4.30\pm 1.34$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M314"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4.30</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b1;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.34</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq142.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left">
<inline-formula id="IEq143"><alternatives><tex-math id="M315">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$4.30\pm 0.95$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M316"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4.30</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b1;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.95</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq143.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="3">
<inline-formula id="IEq144"><alternatives><tex-math id="M317">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$p=0.0022$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M318"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.0022</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq144.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mid</td><td align="left">
<inline-formula id="IEq145"><alternatives><tex-math id="M319">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$4.70\pm 0.95$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M320"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4.70</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b1;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.95</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq145.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left">
<inline-formula id="IEq146"><alternatives><tex-math id="M321">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$2.80\pm 1.40$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M322"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2.80</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b1;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.40</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq146.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">High</td><td align="left">
<inline-formula id="IEq147"><alternatives><tex-math id="M323">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$3.70\pm 1.25$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M324"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3.70</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b1;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.25</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq147.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left">
<inline-formula id="IEq148"><alternatives><tex-math id="M325">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$2.60\pm 1.51$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M326"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2.60</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b1;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.51</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq148.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">Comfort</td><td align="left" rowspan="3">Fault severity</td><td align="left">Low</td><td align="left">
<inline-formula id="IEq149"><alternatives><tex-math id="M327">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$4.20\pm 1.23$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M328"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4.20</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b1;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.23</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq149.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left">
<inline-formula id="IEq150"><alternatives><tex-math id="M329">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$4.00\pm 0.94$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M330"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4.00</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b1;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.94</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq150.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="3">
<inline-formula id="IEq151"><alternatives><tex-math id="M331">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$p=0.34$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M332"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.34</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq151.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mid</td><td align="left">
<inline-formula id="IEq152"><alternatives><tex-math id="M333">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$3.60\pm 1.17$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M334"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3.60</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b1;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.17</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq152.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left">
<inline-formula id="IEq153"><alternatives><tex-math id="M335">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$4.70\pm 1.16$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M336"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4.70</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b1;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.16</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq153.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">High</td><td align="left">
<inline-formula id="IEq154"><alternatives><tex-math id="M337">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$4.60\pm 1.17$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M338"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4.60</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b1;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.17</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq154.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left">
<inline-formula id="IEq155"><alternatives><tex-math id="M339">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$3.90\pm 1.52$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M340"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3.90</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b1;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.52</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq155.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Scale: <inline-formula id="IEq156"><alternatives><tex-math id="M341">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$1 =$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M342"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq156.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
<italic>a lot lower</italic>, <inline-formula id="IEq157"><alternatives><tex-math id="M343">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$2 =$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M344"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq157.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
<italic>lower</italic>, <inline-formula id="IEq158"><alternatives><tex-math id="M345">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$3 =$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M346"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq158.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
<italic>slightly lower</italic>, <inline-formula id="IEq159"><alternatives><tex-math id="M347">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$4 =$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M348"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq159.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
<italic>the same</italic>, <inline-formula id="IEq160"><alternatives><tex-math id="M349">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$5 =$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M350"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>5</mml:mn><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq160.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
<italic>slightly higher</italic>, <inline-formula id="IEq161"><alternatives><tex-math id="M351">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$6 =$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M352"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>6</mml:mn><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq161.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
<italic>higher</italic>, <inline-formula id="IEq162"><alternatives><tex-math id="M353">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$7 =$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M354"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>7</mml:mn><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq162.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
<italic>a lot higher</italic>. Scores presented as MEAN &#x000b1; SD</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Effect of the IVs on the perception of trust metrics after each condition</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="3"/><th align="left" colspan="2">Fault Compensation</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">
<italic>Kruskal-Wallis test</italic></th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="3"/><th align="left">Compensated</th><th align="left">Uncompens.</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">Confidence</td><td align="left" rowspan="3">Fault severity</td><td align="left">Low</td><td align="left">
<inline-formula id="IEq163"><alternatives><tex-math id="M355">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$4.50\pm 1.35$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M356"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4.50</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b1;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.35</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq163.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left">
<inline-formula id="IEq164"><alternatives><tex-math id="M357">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$4.50\pm 1.35$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M358"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4.50</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b1;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.35</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq164.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="3">
<inline-formula id="IEq165"><alternatives><tex-math id="M359">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$p=0.52$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M360"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.52</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq165.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mid</td><td align="left">
<inline-formula id="IEq166"><alternatives><tex-math id="M361">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$4.40\pm 1.84$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M362"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4.40</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b1;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.84</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq166.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left">
<inline-formula id="IEq167"><alternatives><tex-math id="M363">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$5.30\pm 1.34$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M364"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>5.30</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b1;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.34</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq167.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">High</td><td align="left">
<inline-formula id="IEq168"><alternatives><tex-math id="M365">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$5.10\pm 0.88$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M366"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>5.10</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b1;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.88</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq168.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left">
<inline-formula id="IEq169"><alternatives><tex-math id="M367">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$4.00\pm 1.89$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M368"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4.00</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b1;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.89</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq169.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3"> Security</td><td align="left" rowspan="3">Fault severity</td><td align="left">Low</td><td align="left">
<inline-formula id="IEq170"><alternatives><tex-math id="M369">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$4.40\pm 1.43$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M370"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4.40</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b1;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.43</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq170.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left">
<inline-formula id="IEq171"><alternatives><tex-math id="M371">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$4.30\pm 1.49$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M372"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4.30</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b1;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.49</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq171.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="3">
<inline-formula id="IEq172"><alternatives><tex-math id="M373">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$p=0.30$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M374"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.30</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq172.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mid</td><td align="left">
<inline-formula id="IEq173"><alternatives><tex-math id="M375">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$4.70\pm 1.84$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M376"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4.70</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b1;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.84</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq173.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left">
<inline-formula id="IEq174"><alternatives><tex-math id="M377">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$4.70\pm 1.34$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M378"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4.70</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b1;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.34</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq174.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">High</td><td align="left">
<inline-formula id="IEq175"><alternatives><tex-math id="M379">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$4.80\pm 1.32$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M380"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4.80</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b1;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.32</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq175.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left">
<inline-formula id="IEq176"><alternatives><tex-math id="M381">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$3.60\pm 1.43$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M382"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3.60</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b1;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.43</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq176.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">Dependability</td><td align="left" rowspan="3">Fault severity</td><td align="left">Low</td><td align="left">
<inline-formula id="IEq177"><alternatives><tex-math id="M383">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$4.40\pm 1.17$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M384"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4.40</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b1;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.17</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq177.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left">
<inline-formula id="IEq178"><alternatives><tex-math id="M385">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$4.40\pm 1.51$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M386"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4.40</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b1;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.51</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq178.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="3">
<inline-formula id="IEq179"><alternatives><tex-math id="M387">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$p=0.51$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M388"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.51</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq179.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mid</td><td align="left">
<inline-formula id="IEq180"><alternatives><tex-math id="M389">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$4.70\pm 1.49$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M390"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4.70</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b1;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.49</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq180.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left">
<inline-formula id="IEq181"><alternatives><tex-math id="M391">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$4.50\pm 1.51$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M392"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4.50</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b1;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.51</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq181.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">High</td><td align="left">
<inline-formula id="IEq182"><alternatives><tex-math id="M393">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$5.00\pm 1.05$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M394"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>5.00</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b1;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.05</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq182.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left">
<inline-formula id="IEq183"><alternatives><tex-math id="M395">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$3.80\pm 1.75$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M396"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3.80</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b1;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.75</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq183.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Scale: <inline-formula id="IEq184"><alternatives><tex-math id="M397">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$1 =$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M398"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq184.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
<italic>strongly disagree</italic>, <inline-formula id="IEq185"><alternatives><tex-math id="M399">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$2 =$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M400"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq185.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
<italic>disagree</italic>, <inline-formula id="IEq186"><alternatives><tex-math id="M401">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$3 =$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M402"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq186.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
<italic>slightly disagree</italic>, <inline-formula id="IEq187"><alternatives><tex-math id="M403">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$4 =$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M404"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq187.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
<italic>neutral</italic>, <inline-formula id="IEq188"><alternatives><tex-math id="M405">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$5 =$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M406"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>5</mml:mn><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq188.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
<italic>slightly agree</italic>, <inline-formula id="IEq189"><alternatives><tex-math id="M407">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$6 =$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M408"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>6</mml:mn><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq189.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
<italic>agree</italic>, <inline-formula id="IEq190"><alternatives><tex-math id="M409">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$7 =$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M410"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>7</mml:mn><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq190.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>
<italic>strongly agree</italic>. Scores presented as MEAN &#x000b1; SD</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par45">
<fig id="Fig12"><label>Fig. 12</label><caption><p>Boxplots of the obtained responses from participants for (<bold>a</bold>)&#x000a0;support, (<bold>b</bold>)&#x000a0;stiffness, and (<bold>c</bold>)&#x000a0;comfort, across combinations of fault severity (low, mid, high) and compensation (compensated or uncompensated), compared to the baseline (no fault). The median is denoted by a thick line, the box edges represent the 25th and 75th percentile, data points are shown as circles, and the average as a cross. Lines above the boxplots indicate significant differences between groups that share an independent variable (Dunn&#x02019;s test): <inline-formula id="IEq191"><alternatives><tex-math id="M411">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$***= p\le 0.01$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M412"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>&#x02217;</mml:mo><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>&#x02217;</mml:mo><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>&#x02217;</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02264;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.01</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq191.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="IEq192"><alternatives><tex-math id="M413">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$**= p\le 0.05$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M414"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>&#x02217;</mml:mo><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>&#x02217;</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02264;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.05</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq192.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. Non-significant differences are omitted. We found significant differences in support levels between compensated and uncompensated faults at mid and high severities, as well as between low and high uncompensated fault conditions. This suggests fault compensation helps maintain consistent support levels. Significant differences in stiffness were also found between compensated and uncompensated faults at mid severity, and across all severities in the uncompensated condition, indicating compensation helps maintain expected stiffness levels. Comfort responses showed no significant differences</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Fig12_HTML" id="MO12"/></fig>
<fig id="Fig13"><label>Fig. 13</label><caption><p>Boxplot of the obtained responses from participants for (<bold>a</bold>)&#x000a0;confidence, (<bold>b</bold>)&#x000a0;security, and (<bold>c</bold>)&#x000a0;dependability, when asked about their agreement after each condition of the repeated-measures study: a combination of fault severity (low, mid, high) and fault compensation (compensated or uncompensated). The median is denoted by a thick line, the box edges represent the 25th and 75th percentile, data points are shown as circles, and the average as a cross. No significant differences were found in the data</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Fig13_HTML" id="MO13"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par46">When comparing support, the average results for compensated faults present similar average values across all fault severities. For uncompensated faults, meanwhile, the average results showed a decreasing pattern with respect to an increase in fault severity. The Kruskal-Wallis test showed that there are significant differences between the averages among all 6 conditions (<inline-formula id="IEq193"><alternatives><tex-math id="M415">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$p&#x0003c;0.001$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M416"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.001</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq193.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>). The significance levels between groups, obtained with the Dunn&#x02019;s test and detailed in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig12" ref-type="fig">12</xref>a, showed that there were no significant differences between fault severities within the compensated conditions, while uncompensated conditions showed significant differences between low and high severities. Moreover, the significance levels between compensated and uncompensated fault conditions show that responses for mid and high severities were significantly different, with uncompensated faults scoring lower.</p><p id="Par47">When comparing stiffness, the Kruskal-Wallis test showed that there are significant differences between the averages among all 6 conditions (<inline-formula id="IEq194"><alternatives><tex-math id="M417">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$p=0.0022$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M418"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.0022</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq194.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>). The significance levels between groups, obtained with the Dunn&#x02019;s test and detailed in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig12" ref-type="fig">12</xref>b, showed that there are no significant differences between fault severities within the compensated conditions, while uncompensated faults showed a decreasing average pattern with respect to fault severity, with significant differences between high-mid and high-low severities. Moreover, there was a significant difference for the mid fault severity when comparing the compensated and uncompensated conditions, with the uncompensated fault scoring lower.</p><p id="Par48">When comparing comfort, there were no discernible patterns in the obtained responses. The Kruskal-Wallis test confirmed this assertion by showing no significant differences among the 6 data groups (<inline-formula id="IEq195"><alternatives><tex-math id="M419">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$p=0.34$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M420"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.34</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq195.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>).</p><p id="Par49">When evaluating trust in terms of confidence, security, and dependability, the average results for the uncompensated high fault generally showed lower scores. Yet, the Kruskal-Wallis tests showed no significant differences among the 6 conditions for each dependent variable (<inline-formula id="IEq196"><alternatives><tex-math id="M421">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$p=0.52$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M422"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.52</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq196.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> for confidence, <inline-formula id="IEq197"><alternatives><tex-math id="M423">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$p=0.30$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M424"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.30</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq197.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> for security, and <inline-formula id="IEq198"><alternatives><tex-math id="M425">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$p=0.51$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M426"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.51</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12984_2024_1531_Article_IEq198.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> for dependability).</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par50">The functional evaluation in Sect.&#x000a0;"<xref rid="Sec9" ref-type="sec">Functional evaluation experiments</xref>" showed that fault tolerance can be achieved by the proposed control strategy, by compensating for faults such that a torque support level is maintained throughout several gait cycles despite changes in the spring pretension of the nonlinear elastic actuator that powers a knee exoskeleton.</p><p id="Par51">The user experience study, whose results are presented in Sect.&#x000a0;"<xref rid="Sec13" ref-type="sec">User study results</xref>", explored the impact of elastic faults on user perception when physically interacting with the knee exoskeleton. The results showed significant differences in participant responses when comparing support levels between baseline (no fault) and the different faulty conditions. The comparison of response averages revealed that faulty conditions clearly affected the perception of support levels. While there were no differences in responses for compensated faults, the severity of uncompensated faults led to a decline in perceived support. When comparing responses considering fault compensation, scores were significantly lower for mid and high uncompensated faults. Responses for low severity did not show a significant difference between compensated and uncompensated conditions, suggesting that the difference in torque support caused by the low fault is close to or below the just noticeable difference threshold. Yet, the average and median of responses for the uncompensated fault condition are lower than for the compensated one. These results confirm <italic>Hypothesis 1a</italic>, implying that fault compensation helps maintain the support at comparably similar levels.</p><p id="Par52">The results obtained also presented significant differences when comparing stiffness between baseline (no fault) and the different faulty conditions. However, the impact of fault severity in regards to stiffness, as perceived by the user, is not as distinct as for support. Average responses considering fault severity presented no significant differences for compensated faults, and a decreasing pattern for uncompensated faults. When comparing responses considering fault compensation, scores were significantly lower for the uncompensated mid fault condition. Similar as for support, responses for low severity did not show a significant difference, suggesting that the difference in stiffness caused by the low fault is close to or below the just noticeable difference threshold. Responses for high severity also did not show a significant difference, which suggests that participants were able to distinguish when the system was considerably softer, even when the fault was compensated, likely due to the lower residual torque during swing, as observed in Sect.&#x000a0;"<xref rid="Sec10" ref-type="sec">Zero-torque mode</xref>". This might reflect a limitation of the study, as the residual torque occurring from motor speed saturation seems to influence the perception of stiffness on the participants and confound the results, particularly, for the high fault severity. Yet, the average and median of responses for the uncompensated high fault severity are lower than for the compensated one, which suggests that there was some improvement when faults were compensated, helping to adjust the system to keep stiffness levels closer to what we expected. These results align with <italic>Hypothesis 1b</italic>, and support the argument made by Fu et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>] that, in haptic applications, the perception of stiffness is closely related to force perception. The topic of stiffness perception could still be further explored by extending the methods to consider stiffness control profiles [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>] or a combination of stiffness and torque segments&#x000a0;[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>], which could exploit the adaptable virtual stiffness and virtual equilibrium position introduced from impedance control. Furthermore, evaluating the impact of changes in stiffness on the users&#x02019; gait, particularly considering the motor limitations described in Sect.&#x000a0;"<xref rid="Sec10" ref-type="sec">Zero-torque mode</xref>", could also be explored in a long exposure user study similar to the one in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>].</p><p id="Par53">Results also showed no significant difference when comparing comfort levels between baseline and faulty conditions. This rejects <italic>Hypothesis 1c</italic> and implies that the perception of comfort is not solely dependent on the torque level. In literature, comfort in exoskeletons can be related to the reduction of muscle fatigue through support [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. However, this is generally perceived only after an extended use of the device and might be affected by discomfort in the interface between the exoskeleton and the body, or limitations of movement [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. Moreover, comfort might also be affected by design factors such as the weight of the device [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>], or the timing of the support pattern [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>].</p><p id="Par54">Finally, results showed no significant difference for the three categories of trust: dependability, security, and confidence. This rejects <italic>Hypothesis 2</italic> and underlines that trust is a complex multi-dimensional concept that is not directly related to the support level in the selected scenario. From a functional perspective, trust is related to the perception of reliability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. Faults, as considered in this study, do not severely affect the functioning of the exoskeleton, nor do they hinder the walking performance of an able-bodied person, and thus might not have a severe impact on the perceived reliability. The study of trust in human-robot interaction frequently encounters methodological confounds that undermine the robustness of the findings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. In the presented study, the low impact of faults on the task at hand might have contributed to a limited influence on participants&#x02019; trust perception. Future research could adopt different pHRI scenarios that provide deeper insights into the interaction between trust and faulty conditions.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par55">This article proposes a fault-tolerant torque assistive control strategy based on an established impedance control method and presents a user experience study that investigated the user perception of support, stiffness, comfort, and trust during physical human-robot interaction while walking with a knee exoskeleton under different faulty conditions. A functional evaluation demonstrated the feasibility of using analytical methods to compensate for elastic faults, ensuring a desired torque support profile. The user experience study, conducted with 10 participants, showed that fault tolerance can be achieved in practice by compensating for faults and maintaining comparable levels of perceived torque support and stiffness. Meanwhile, results from the user study showed that comfort and trust measures seem not to be directly affected by torque levels.</p><p id="Par56">The findings of this study are important for understanding the role of human perception for the control of wearable robots. They indicate that participants are able to perceive changes in torque levels caused by internal faults, which can be mitigated through fault compensation. Yet, the overall user perception is also influenced by other factors such as ergonomics, timing, and motor performance.</p><p id="Par57">Future work could expand this research by introducing human-in-the-loop optimization methods [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>] in combination with user preference and biomechanical data to optimize the torque profile based on a performance metric, and evaluate walking comfort. Moreover, future research could also consider short term faults or walking disturbances to evaluate the ability of the control method to recover operation. Finally, we expect that the methods and findings outlined in this article will serve to improve user satisfaction and dependability of wearable robots.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors thank Sanit&#x000e4;tshaus OrthoPoint (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.orthopoint.de/">orthopoint.de</ext-link>) for their support in supervising the orthopedic soundness of the knee exoskeleton.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>RJV conceptualized and developed software and methods, and conducted functional experiments. The user study protocol was designed by RJV and AB, with supervision from PB. RJV recruited the participants and conducted the study. RJV and AB analyzed the data. RJV drafted and wrote the manuscript. AB was actively involved in the writing process. JMF, BV and PB provided supervision and proofread the paper. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>Open Access funding enabled and organized by Projekt DEAL. This work was supported by a Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (DFG) Research Grant (no. BE 5729/1).</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>The datasets generated during the current study are not publicly available due to privacy restrictions. Access to the software is available from the corresponding author upon request.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par58">Informed consent was obtained from all participants involved in the study. The experimentation was conducted in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki 2008 and a vote from the Ethics Commission at TU Darmstadt (EK 18/2017).</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par59">The consent of all participants was obtained before publication.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par60">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferris</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>State of the art and future directions for lower limb robotic exoskeletons</article-title><source>IEEE Trans Neural Syst Rehabil Eng</source><year>2016</year><volume>25</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>182</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/TNSRE.2016.2521160</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26829794</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Young AJ, Ferris DP. State of the art and future directions for lower limb robotic exoskeletons. IEEE Trans Neural Syst Rehabil Eng. 2016;25(2):171&#x02013;82. 10.1109/TNSRE.2016.2521160.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26829794</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beckerle</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Verstraten</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathijssen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Furnemont</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanderborght</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lefeber</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Series and parallel elastic actuation: influence of operating positions on design and control</article-title><source>IEEE/ASME Trans Mechatron</source><year>2017</year><volume>22</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>521</fpage><lpage>529</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/TMECH.2016.2621062</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Beckerle P, Verstraten T, Mathijssen G, Furnemont R, Vanderborght B, Lefeber D. Series and parallel elastic actuation: influence of operating positions on design and control. IEEE/ASME Trans Mechatron. 2017;22(1):521&#x02013;9. 10.1109/TMECH.2016.2621062.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aguirre-Ollinger</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lower-limb exoskeleton with variable-structure series elastic actuators: phase-synchronized force control for gait asymmetry correction</article-title><source>IEEE Trans Robot</source><year>2021</year><volume>37</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>763</fpage><lpage>779</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/TRO.2020.3034017</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Aguirre-Ollinger G, Yu H. Lower-limb exoskeleton with variable-structure series elastic actuators: phase-synchronized force control for gait asymmetry correction. IEEE Trans Robot. 2021;37(3):763&#x02013;79. 10.1109/TRO.2020.3034017.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carney</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Shu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Stolyarov</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Duval</surname><given-names>J-F</given-names></name><name><surname>Herr</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Design and preliminary results of a reaction force series elastic actuator for bionic knee and ankle prostheses</article-title><source>IEEE Trans Med Robot Bionics</source><year>2021</year><volume>3</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>542</fpage><lpage>553</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/TMRB.2021.3098921</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Carney ME, Shu T, Stolyarov R, Duval J-F, Herr HM. Design and preliminary results of a reaction force series elastic actuator for bionic knee and ankle prostheses. IEEE Trans Med Robot Bionics. 2021;3(3):542&#x02013;53. 10.1109/TMRB.2021.3098921.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ning</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Design and validation of a lightweight hip exoskeleton driven by series elastic actuator with two-motor variable speed transmission</article-title><source>IEEE Trans Neural Syst Rehabil Eng</source><year>2022</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>2456</fpage><lpage>2466</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/TNSRE.2022.3201383</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36001514</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Zhang T, Ning C, Li Y, Wang M. Design and validation of a lightweight hip exoskeleton driven by series elastic actuator with two-motor variable speed transmission. IEEE Trans Neural Syst Rehabil Eng. 2022;30:2456&#x02013;66. 10.1109/TNSRE.2022.3201383.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36001514</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Pratt GA, Williamson MM, Series elastic actuators. In: Proceedings of the 1995 IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems. IEEE; 1995; vol. 1, p. 399-406. 10.1109/IROS.1995.525827.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Losey</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Erwin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Sergi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Malley</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A time-domain approach to control of series elastic actuators: adaptive torque and passivity-based impedance control</article-title><source>IEEE/ASME Trans Mechatron</source><year>2016</year><volume>21</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>2085</fpage><lpage>2096</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/TMECH.2016.2557727</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Losey DP, Erwin A, McDonald CG, Sergi F, O&#x02019;Malley MK. A time-domain approach to control of series elastic actuators: adaptive torque and passivity-based impedance control. IEEE/ASME Trans Mechatron. 2016;21(4):2085&#x02013;96. 10.1109/TMECH.2016.2557727.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomizuka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Control of rotary series elastic actuator for ideal force-mode actuation in human-robot interaction applications</article-title><source>IEEE/ASME Trans Mechatron</source><year>2009</year><volume>14</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>105</fpage><lpage>118</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/TMECH.2008.2004561</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Kong K, Bae J, Tomizuka M. Control of rotary series elastic actuator for ideal force-mode actuation in human-robot interaction applications. IEEE/ASME Trans Mechatron. 2009;14(1):105&#x02013;18. 10.1109/TMECH.2008.2004561.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vantilt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanghe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Afschrift</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruijnes</surname><given-names>AKBD</given-names></name><name><surname>Junius</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Geeroms</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Aertbeli&#x000eb;n</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Groote</surname><given-names>FD</given-names></name><name><surname>Lefeber</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Jonkers</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Schutter</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Model-based control for exoskeletons with series elastic actuators evaluated on sit-to-stand movements</article-title><source>J NeuroEng Rehabil</source><year>2019</year><volume>16</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>65</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12984-019-0526-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31159874</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Vantilt J, Tanghe K, Afschrift M, Bruijnes AKBD, Junius K, Geeroms J, Aertbeli&#x000eb;n E, Groote FD, Lefeber D, Jonkers I, Schutter JD. Model-based control for exoskeletons with series elastic actuators evaluated on sit-to-stand movements. J NeuroEng Rehabil. 2019;16(1):65. 10.1186/s12984-019-0526-8.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31159874</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Plooij</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wisse</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vallery</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reducing the energy consumption of robots using the bidirectional clutched parallel elastic actuator</article-title><source>IEEE Trans Robot</source><year>2016</year><volume>32</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1512</fpage><lpage>1523</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/TRO.2016.2604496</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Plooij M, Wisse M, Vallery H. Reducing the energy consumption of robots using the bidirectional clutched parallel elastic actuator. IEEE Trans Robot. 2016;32(6):1512&#x02013;23. 10.1109/TRO.2016.2604496.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Toxiri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Calanca</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ortiz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fiorini</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Caldwell</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A parallel-elastic actuator for a torque-controlled back-support exoskeleton</article-title><source>IEEE Robot Autom Lett</source><year>2017</year><volume>3</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>492</fpage><lpage>499</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/LRA.2017.2768120</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Toxiri S, Calanca A, Ortiz J, Fiorini P, Caldwell DG. A parallel-elastic actuator for a torque-controlled back-support exoskeleton. IEEE Robot Autom Lett. 2017;3(1):492&#x02013;9. 10.1109/LRA.2017.2768120.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Penzlin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergmann</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Leonhardt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ngo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Design and first operation of an active lower limb exoskeleton with parallel elastic actuation</article-title><source>Actuators</source><year>2021</year><volume>10</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>75</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/act10040075</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Penzlin B, Bergmann L, Li Y, Ji L, Leonhardt S, Ngo C. Design and first operation of an active lower limb exoskeleton with parallel elastic actuation. Actuators. 2021;10(4):75. 10.3390/act10040075.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vanderborght</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Albu-Schaeffer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bicchi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Burdet</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Caldwell</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Carloni</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Catalano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Eiberger</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Friedl</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Ganesh</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Garabini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Grebenstein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Grioli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Haddadin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoppner</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Jafari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Laffranchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lefeber</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Petit</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Stramigioli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsagarakis</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Damme</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Ham</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name><name><surname>Visser</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Variable impedance actuators: a review</article-title><source>Robot Autonomous Syst</source><year>2013</year><volume>61</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1601</fpage><lpage>1614</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.robot.2013.06.009</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Vanderborght B, Albu-Schaeffer A, Bicchi A, Burdet E, Caldwell DG, Carloni R, Catalano M, Eiberger O, Friedl W, Ganesh G, Garabini M, Grebenstein M, Grioli G, Haddadin S, Hoppner H, Jafari A, Laffranchi M, Lefeber D, Petit F, Stramigioli S, Tsagarakis N, Damme MV, Ham RV, Visser LC, Wolf S. Variable impedance actuators: a review. Robot Autonomous Syst. 2013;61(12):1601&#x02013;14. 10.1016/j.robot.2013.06.009.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>D-Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Firouzeh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>Y-L</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>K-J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A positive pressure jamming based variable stiffness structure and its application on wearable robots</article-title><source>IEEE Robot Autom Lett</source><year>2021</year><volume>6</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>8078</fpage><lpage>8085</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/LRA.2021.3097255</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Liu T, Xia H, Lee D-Y, Firouzeh A, Park Y-L, Cho K-J. A positive pressure jamming based variable stiffness structure and its application on wearable robots. IEEE Robot Autom Lett. 2021;6(4):8078&#x02013;85. 10.1109/LRA.2021.3097255.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheng</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Sivan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z-Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>G-Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>SQ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A lightweight series elastic actuator with variable stiffness: design, modeling, and evaluation</article-title><source>IEEE/ASME Trans Mechatron</source><year>2023</year><volume>28</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>3110</fpage><lpage>3119</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/TMECH.2023.3254813</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Wang C, Sheng B, Li Z, Sivan M, Zhang Z-Q, Li G-Q, Xie SQ. A lightweight series elastic actuator with variable stiffness: design, modeling, and evaluation. IEEE/ASME Trans Mechatron. 2023;28(6):3110&#x02013;9. 10.1109/TMECH.2023.3254813.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beckerle</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Practical relevance of faults, diagnosis methods, and tolerance measures in elastically actuated robots</article-title><source>Control Eng Pract</source><year>2016</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.conengprac.2016.02.006</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Beckerle P. Practical relevance of faults, diagnosis methods, and tolerance measures in elastically actuated robots. Control Eng Pract. 2016;50:95&#x02013;100. 10.1016/j.conengprac.2016.02.006.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Santis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Siciliano</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>De Luca</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bicchi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An atlas of physical human-robot interaction</article-title><source>Mechan Mach Theory</source><year>2008</year><volume>43</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>253</fpage><lpage>270</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mechmachtheory.2007.03.003</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">De Santis A, Siciliano B, De Luca A, Bicchi A. An atlas of physical human-robot interaction. Mechan Mach Theory. 2008;43(3):253&#x02013;70. 10.1016/j.mechmachtheory.2007.03.003.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blanke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kinnaert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lunze</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Staroswiecki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><source>Diagnosis and fault-tolerant control</source><year>2016</year><edition>3</edition><publisher-loc>Heidelberg</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="book">Blanke M, Kinnaert M, Lunze J, Staroswiecki M. Diagnosis and fault-tolerant control. 3rd ed. Heidelberg: Springer; 2016.&#x000a0;10.1007/978-3-662-47943-8.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High-precision robust force control of a series elastic actuator</article-title><source>IEEE/ASME Trans Mechatron</source><year>2017</year><volume>22</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>80</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/TMECH.2016.2614503</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Oh S, Kong K. High-precision robust force control of a series elastic actuator. IEEE/ASME Trans Mechatron. 2017;22(1):71&#x02013;80. 10.1109/TMECH.2016.2614503.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Asignacion</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Haninger</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High-stiffness control of series elastic actuators using a noise reduction disturbance observer</article-title><source>IEEE Trans Ind Electron</source><year>2022</year><volume>69</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>8212</fpage><lpage>8219</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/TIE.2021.3106016</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">Asignacion A, Haninger K, Oh S, Lee H. High-stiffness control of series elastic actuators using a noise reduction disturbance observer. IEEE Trans Ind Electron. 2022;69(8):8212&#x02013;9. 10.1109/TIE.2021.3106016.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Narayan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Abbas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dwivedy</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Robust adaptive backstepping control for a lower-limb exoskeleton system with model uncertainties and external disturbances</article-title><source>Automatika</source><year>2022</year><volume>64</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>145</fpage><lpage>161</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00051144.2022.2119498</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Narayan J, Abbas M, Dwivedy SK. Robust adaptive backstepping control for a lower-limb exoskeleton system with model uncertainties and external disturbances. Automatika. 2022;64(1):145&#x02013;61. 10.1080/00051144.2022.2119498.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kermavnar</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>de Vries</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>de Looze</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Sullivan</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of industrial back-support exoskeletons on body loading and user experience: an updated systematic review</article-title><source>Ergonomics</source><year>2021</year><volume>64</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>685</fpage><lpage>711</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00140139.2020.1870162</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33369518</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">Kermavnar T, de Vries AW, de Looze MP, O&#x02019;Sullivan LW. Effects of industrial back-support exoskeletons on body loading and user experience: an updated systematic review. Ergonomics. 2021;64(6):685&#x02013;711. 10.1080/00140139.2020.1870162.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33369518</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez-Fern&#x000e1;ndez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lobo-Prat</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Font-Llagunes</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Systematic review on wearable lower-limb exoskeletons for gait training in neuromuscular impairments</article-title><source>J Neuroeng Rehabil</source><year>2021</year><volume>18</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>22</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12984-021-00815-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33526065</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Rodr&#x000ed;guez-Fern&#x000e1;ndez A, Lobo-Prat J, Font-Llagunes JM. Systematic review on wearable lower-limb exoskeletons for gait training in neuromuscular impairments. J Neuroeng Rehabil. 2021;18(1):22. 10.1186/s12984-021-00815-5.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33526065</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Miguel-Fern&#x000e1;ndez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lobo-Prat</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Prinsen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Font-Llagunes</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Marchal-Crespo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Control strategies used in lower limb exoskeletons for gait rehabilitation after brain injury: a systematic review and analysis of clinical effectiveness</article-title><source>J Neuroeng Rehabil</source><year>2023</year><volume>20</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>23</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12984-023-01144-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36805777</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">de Miguel-Fern&#x000e1;ndez J, Lobo-Prat J, Prinsen E, Font-Llagunes JM, Marchal-Crespo L. Control strategies used in lower limb exoskeletons for gait rehabilitation after brain injury: a systematic review and analysis of clinical effectiveness. J Neuroeng Rehabil. 2023;20(1):23. 10.1186/s12984-023-01144-5.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36805777</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Stuhlenmiller F, Velasco-Guillen RJ, Rinderknecht S, Beckerle P. Fault-tolerant physical human-robot interaction via stiffness adaptation of elastic actuators. In: Human-Friendly Robotics 2019: 12th International Workshop. Springer; 2020. p. 73&#x02013;87. 10.1007/978-3-030-42026-0_6.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Velasco-Guillen RJ, Grosu V, Vanderborght B, Font-Llagunes JM, Beckerle P. Experimental evaluation of a stiffness-fault-tolerant control strategy on an elastic actuator for wearable robotics. In: 2022 9th IEEE RAS/EMBS International Conference for Biomedical Robotics and Biomechatronics (BioRob). IEEE; 2022. p. 1&#x02013;6. 10.1109/BioRob52689.2022.9925448.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Velasco-Guillen RJ, Furn&#x000e9;mont R, Verstraten T, Beckerle P. A stiffness-fault-tolerant control strategy for a redundant elastic actuator. In: 2022 IEEE/ASME International Conference on Advanced Intelligent Mechatronics (AIM). IEEE; 2022. p. 1360&#x02013;5. 10.1109/AIM52237.2022.9863361.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR28" publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ott</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><source>Cartesian impedance control of redundant and flexible-joint robots</source><year>2008</year><publisher-loc>Heidelberg</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28" publication-type="book">Ott C. Cartesian impedance control of redundant and flexible-joint robots. Heidelberg: Springer; 2008.&#x000a0;10.1007/978-3-540-69255-3.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR29" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>D&#x000ed;az</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Vo&#x000df;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dillen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tassignon</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Flynn</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Geeroms</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Meeusen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Verstraten</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Babi&#x0010d;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Beckerle</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>De Pauw</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Human-in-the-loop optimization of wearable robotic devices to improve human-robot interaction: a systematic review</article-title><source>IEEE Trans Cyber</source><year>2023</year><volume>53</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>7483</fpage><lpage>7496</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/TCYB.2022.3224895</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29" publication-type="journal">D&#x000ed;az MA, Vo&#x000df; M, Dillen A, Tassignon B, Flynn L, Geeroms J, Meeusen R, Verstraten T, Babi&#x0010d; J, Beckerle P, De Pauw K. Human-in-the-loop optimization of wearable robotic devices to improve human-robot interaction: a systematic review. IEEE Trans Cyber. 2023;53(12):7483&#x02013;96. 10.1109/TCYB.2022.3224895.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Velasco-Guillen RJ, Schofer F, Bliek A, Beckerle P. Exploring the just noticeable interaction stiffness differences of an impedance-controlled series elastic actuator. Actuators. 2023;12(10):378. 10.3390/act12100378.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Velasco-Guillen RJ, Grosu V, Carmona-Ortiz VA, Vanderborght B, Lefeber D, Font-Llagunes JM, Beckerle P. A stiffness-fault-tolerant control strategy for an elastically actuated powered knee orthosis. In: 2020 8th IEEE RAS/EMBS International Conference for Biomedical Robotics and Biomechatronics (BioRob). IEEE; 2020. p. 660&#x02013;5. 10.1109/BioRob49111.2020.9224403.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR32" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Der Merwe</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The unscented kalman filter</article-title><source>Kalman Filter Neural Netw</source><year>2001</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/0471221546.ch7</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32" publication-type="journal">Wan EA, Van Der Merwe R. The unscented kalman filter. Kalman Filter Neural Netw. 2001. 10.1002/0471221546.ch7.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ducastel V, Langlois K, Rossini M, Grosu V, Vanderborght B, Lefeber D, Verstraten T, Geeroms J. SMARCOS: off-the-shelf smart compliant actuators for human-robot applications. Actuators. 2021;10(11):289. 10.3390/act10110289.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Van Ham R, Vanderborght B, Van Damme M, Verrelst B, Lefeber D. MACCEPA: the mechanically adjustable compliance and controllable equilibrium position actuator for 'controlled passive walking'. In: Proceedings 2006 IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA). 2006. p. 2195&#x02013;200. 10.1109/ROBOT.2006.1642029.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR35" publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Isermann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><source>Mechatronic systems: fundamentals</source><year>2005</year><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR35" publication-type="book">Isermann R. Mechatronic systems: fundamentals. London: Springer; 2005. 10.1007/1-84628-259-4.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Grimmer M, Eslamy M, Seyfarth A. Energetic and peak power advantages of series elastic actuators in an actuated prosthetic leg for walking and running. Actuators. 2014;3(1):1&#x02013;19. 10.3390/act3010001.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR37" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bryan</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Franks</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Voloshina</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Reyes</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Donovan</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Gregorczyk</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Optimized hip-knee-ankle exoskeleton assistance at a range of walking speeds</article-title><source>J Neuroeng Rehabil</source><year>2021</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>152</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12984-021-00943-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34663372</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR37" publication-type="journal">Bryan GM, Franks PW, Song S, Voloshina AS, Reyes R, O&#x02019;Donovan MP, Gregorczyk KN, Collins SH. Optimized hip-knee-ankle exoskeleton assistance at a range of walking speeds. J Neuroeng Rehabil. 2021;18:152. 10.1186/s12984-021-00943-y.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34663372</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR38" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bryan</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Franks</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Peuchen</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A hip-knee-ankle exoskeleton emulator for studying gait assistance</article-title><source>Int J Robot Res</source><year>2021</year><volume>40</volume><issue>4&#x02013;5</issue><fpage>722</fpage><lpage>746</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0278364920961452</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR38" publication-type="journal">Bryan GM, Franks PW, Klein SC, Peuchen RJ, Collins SH. A hip-knee-ankle exoskeleton emulator for studying gait assistance. Int J Robot Res. 2021;40(4&#x02013;5):722&#x02013;46. 10.1177/0278364920961452.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR39" publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whittle</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group><source>Gait analysis: an introduction</source><year>2007</year><edition>4</edition><publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Elsevier Butterworth-Heinemann</publisher-name></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR39" publication-type="book">Whittle MW. Gait analysis: an introduction. 4th ed. Oxford: Elsevier Butterworth-Heinemann; 2007.&#x000a0;10.1016/B978-0-7506-8883-3.X5001-6.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR40" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jian</surname><given-names>J-Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Bisantz</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Drury</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Foundations for an empirically determined scale of trust in automated systems</article-title><source>Int J Cogn Ergon</source><year>2000</year><volume>4</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1207/S15327566IJCE0401_04</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR40" publication-type="journal">Jian J-Y, Bisantz AM, Drury CG. Foundations for an empirically determined scale of trust in automated systems. Int J Cogn Ergon. 2000;4(1):53&#x02013;71. 10.1207/S15327566IJCE0401_04.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR41" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kruskal</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallis</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of ranks in one-criterion variance analysis</article-title><source>J Am Stat Assoc</source><year>1952</year><volume>47</volume><issue>260</issue><fpage>583</fpage><lpage>621</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/01621459.1952.10483441</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR41" publication-type="journal">Kruskal WH, Wallis WA. Use of ranks in one-criterion variance analysis. J Am Stat Assoc. 1952;47(260):583&#x02013;621. 10.1080/01621459.1952.10483441.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR42" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>OJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiple comparisons among means</article-title><source>J Am Stat Assoc</source><year>1961</year><volume>56</volume><issue>293</issue><fpage>52</fpage><lpage>64</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/01621459.1961.10482090</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR42" publication-type="journal">Dunn OJ. Multiple comparisons among means. J Am Stat Assoc. 1961;56(293):52&#x02013;64. 10.1080/01621459.1961.10482090.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR43" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benjamini</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hochberg</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Controlling the false discovery rate: a practical and powerful approach to multiple testing</article-title><source>J Royal Stat Soc: Ser B</source><year>1995</year><volume>57</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>289</fpage><lpage>300</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.2517-6161.1995.tb02031.x</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR43" publication-type="journal">Benjamini Y, Hochberg Y. Controlling the false discovery rate: a practical and powerful approach to multiple testing. J Royal Stat Soc: Ser B. 1995;57(1):289&#x02013;300. 10.1111/j.2517-6161.1995.tb02031.x.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Fu, W., Van Paassen, M., Mulder, M.: On the relationship between the force JND and the stiffness JND in haptic perception. In: Proceedings of the ACM Symposium on Applied Perception. 2017. vol. 11, p. 1-8. 10.1145/3119881.3119882.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR45" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Vashista</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>External dynamics dependent human gait adaptation using a cable-driven exoskeleton</article-title><source>IEEE Robot Autom Lett</source><year>2023</year><volume>8</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>6036</fpage><lpage>6043</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/LRA.2023.3302189</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR45" publication-type="journal">Nakka S, Vashista V. External dynamics dependent human gait adaptation using a cable-driven exoskeleton. IEEE Robot Autom Lett. 2023;8(9):6036&#x02013;43. 10.1109/LRA.2023.3302189.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR46" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwak</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>McLain</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of assistance during early stance phase using a robotic knee orthosis on energetics, muscle activity, and joint mechanics during incline and decline walking</article-title><source>IEEE Trans Neural Syst Rehabil Eng</source><year>2020</year><volume>28</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>914</fpage><lpage>923</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/TNSRE.2020.2972323</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32054583</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR46" publication-type="journal">Lee D, Kwak EC, McLain BJ, Kang I, Young AJ. Effects of assistance during early stance phase using a robotic knee orthosis on energetics, muscle activity, and joint mechanics during incline and decline walking. IEEE Trans Neural Syst Rehabil Eng. 2020;28(4):914&#x02013;23. 10.1109/TNSRE.2020.2972323.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32054583</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR47" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baldassarre</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lulli</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name><surname>Cavallo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Fiorini</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Mariniello</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mucci</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Arcangeli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Industrial exoskeletons from bench to field: human-machine interface and user experience in occupational settings and tasks</article-title><source>Front Public Health</source><year>2022</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>1039680</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2022.1039680</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36478728</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR47" publication-type="journal">Baldassarre A, Lulli LG, Cavallo F, Fiorini L, Mariniello A, Mucci N, Arcangeli G. Industrial exoskeletons from bench to field: human-machine interface and user experience in occupational settings and tasks. Front Public Health. 2022;10:1039680. 10.3389/fpubh.2022.1039680.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36478728</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR48" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>T-H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Carriero</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Oh-Park</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comfort-centered design of a lightweight and backdrivable knee exoskeleton</article-title><source>IEEE Robot Autom Lett</source><year>2018</year><volume>3</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>4265</fpage><lpage>4272</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/LRA.2018.2864352</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR48" publication-type="journal">Wang J, Li X, Huang T-H, Yu S, Li Y, Chen T, Carriero A, Oh-Park M, Su H. Comfort-centered design of a lightweight and backdrivable knee exoskeleton. IEEE Robot Autom Lett. 2018;3(4):4265&#x02013;72. 10.1109/LRA.2018.2864352.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR49" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Acosta-Sojo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Stirling</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Actuation timing perception of a powered ankle exoskeleton and its associated ankle angle changes during walking</article-title><source>IEEE Trans Neural Syst Rehabil Eng</source><year>2022</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>869</fpage><lpage>877</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/TNSRE.2022.3162213</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35333715</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR49" publication-type="journal">Peng X, Acosta-Sojo Y, Wu MI, Stirling L. Actuation timing perception of a powered ankle exoskeleton and its associated ankle angle changes during walking. IEEE Trans Neural Syst Rehabil Eng. 2022;30:869&#x02013;77. 10.1109/TNSRE.2022.3162213.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35333715</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR50" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hopko</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Human factors considerations and metrics in shared space human-robot collaboration: a systematic review</article-title><source>Front Robot AI.</source><year>2022</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>799522</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/frobt.2022.799522</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35187093</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR50" publication-type="journal">Hopko S, Wang J, Mehta R. Human factors considerations and metrics in shared space human-robot collaboration: a systematic review. Front Robot AI. 2022;9:799522. 10.3389/frobt.2022.799522.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35187093</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR51" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Flook</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Shrinah</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wijnen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Eder</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Melhuish</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemaignan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>On the impact of different types of errors on trust in human-robot interaction: are laboratory-based HRI experiments trustworthy?</article-title><source>Interact Stud</source><year>2019</year><volume>20</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>455</fpage><lpage>486</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1075/is.18067.flo</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR51" publication-type="journal">Flook R, Shrinah A, Wijnen L, Eder K, Melhuish C, Lemaignan S. On the impact of different types of errors on trust in human-robot interaction: are laboratory-based HRI experiments trustworthy? Interact Stud. 2019;20(3):455&#x02013;86. 10.1075/is.18067.flo.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article>