<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Commun</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Commun</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature Communications</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2041-1723</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40393986</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12092714</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">59463</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-025-59463-1</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Human mitochondrial ferritin exhibits highly unusual iron-O<sub>2</sub> chemistry distinct from that of cytosolic ferritins</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-1635-4455</contrib-id><name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>Justin M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bugg</surname><given-names>Zinnia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pullin</surname><given-names>Jacob</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>Geoffrey R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Svistunenko</surname><given-names>Dimitri A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9780-4061</contrib-id><name><surname>Le Brun</surname><given-names>Nick E.</given-names></name><address><email>n.le-brun@uea.ac.uk</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/026k5mg93</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.8273.e</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 1092 7967</institution-id><institution>Centre for Molecular and Structural Biochemistry, School of Chemistry, Pharmacy and Pharmacology, </institution><institution>University of East Anglia, </institution></institution-wrap>Norwich, UK </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/02nkf1q06</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.8356.8</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0942 6946</institution-id><institution>School of Life Sciences, </institution><institution>University of Essex, </institution></institution-wrap>Colchester, UK </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/055zmrh94</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.14830.3e</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2175 7246</institution-id><institution>Present Address: The John Innes Centre, </institution></institution-wrap>Norwich, UK </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>20</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><elocation-id>4695</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>3</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Ferritins are ubiquitous proteins that function in iron storage/detoxification by catalyzing the oxidation of Fe<sup>2+</sup> ions and solubilizing the resulting Fe<sup>3+</sup>-oxo mineral. Mammalian tissues that are metabolically highly active contain, in addition to the widespread cytosolic ferritin, a ferritin that is localized to mitochondria. Mitochondrial ferritin (FtMt) protects against oxidative stress and is found at higher levels in diseases associated with abnormal iron accumulation, including Alzheimer&#x02019;s and Parkinson&#x02019;s. Here we demonstrate that, despite 80% sequence identity with cytosolic human H-chain ferritin, Fe<sup>2+</sup> oxidation at the catalytic diiron ferroxidase center of FtMt proceeds via a distinct mechanism. This involves a mixed-valent ferroxidase center (MVFC) that is readily detected under the O<sub>2</sub>-limiting conditions typical of mitochondria, and formation of a radical on a strictly conserved Tyr residue (Tyr34) that is key for the activation of O<sub>2</sub> and stability of the MVFC. The possible origin of the mechanistic differences exhibited by the highly-related human mitochondrial and cytosolic H-chain ferritins is explored.</p></abstract><abstract id="Abs2" abstract-type="web-summary"><p id="Par2">Human mitochondrial ferritin protects against oxidative stress by detoxifying iron. Here, highly unusual iron-oxygen chemistry, involving formation of a mixed valent diiron site and a tyrosine radical, is uncovered.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Metalloproteins</kwd><kwd>Iron</kwd><kwd>Enzyme mechanisms</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/501100000268</institution-id><institution>RCUK | Biotechnology and Biological Sciences Research Council (BBSRC)</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>BB/R002363/1</award-id><award-id>BB/R003203/1</award-id><award-id>BB/T01802X/1</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Le Brun</surname><given-names>Nick E.</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Springer Nature Limited 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par3">Iron is an essential micronutrient and is contained in many enzymes that catalyze important biological functions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. However, in the presence of O<sub>2</sub>, iron is readily oxidized to the Fe<sup>3+</sup> oxidation state, forming insoluble ferric (oxy)hydroxide minerals at pH&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;3<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. Furthermore, inter-conversion between the Fe<sup>2+</sup> and Fe<sup>3+</sup> oxidation states catalyzes the formation of the highly toxic hydroxyl radical from superoxide and peroxide anions generated as by-products of aerobic respiration<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>. Therefore, oxygenation of the atmosphere during the Paleoproterozoic era presented the dual challenges of poor bioavailability and potential toxicity for the utilization of iron in biological systems. In most organisms, members of the ferritin superfamily are important in overcoming these challenges<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par4">Ferritins were first identified over 85 years ago<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup> and all examples identified in eukaryotes consist of 24 protein subunits assembled into a rhombic dodecahedral cage surrounding an 80&#x02009;&#x000c5; diameter interior cavity. Central to ferritin activity is a diiron catalytic site termed the ferroxidase center (FC)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>, which is key for the detoxification/storage of iron as an insoluble ferric mineral in the protein&#x02019;s internal cavity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. This activity limits the intracellular concentration of the potentially toxic Fe<sup>2+</sup> to low micromolar levels<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>, required to ensure correct metallation of iron-containing proteins<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. Iron stored within the mineral core may be mobilized under conditions of iron limitation in order to maintain the concentration of the labile iron pool<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par5">Ferritins isolated from the cytosol or the serum of animals are heteropolymers of isostructural H-chains, which contain an FC, and L-chains that do not<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. Proportions of H- and L-chains vary depending on the tissue of origin. For example, ferritin isolated from the liver is rich in L-chain, while that isolated from the heart is rich in H-chain. This variation in composition is believed to be linked to function, where H-chains promote rapid Fe<sup>2+</sup> oxidation, resulting in detoxification, and L-chains promote mineral core nucleation, facilitating iron storage<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par6">H- and L-chains were thought to be the only ferritins expressed by mammals until the report in 2001 of an intronless gene, located on human chromosome 5q23.1, which encodes a ferritin with an N-terminal mitochondrial targeting sequence<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>. Expression of this homopolymer mitochondrial ferritin (FtMt) is not uniform throughout all tissues and, unlike the cytosolic proteins, is not under the control of an Iron Responsive Element in the ferritin mRNA<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. Consistent with this, the expression levels of mouse FtMt were found to correlate with mitochondrial density rather than iron levels<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>. FtMt is only detected in the cells of tissues with high metabolic activity, such as the testis, heart, brain, and kidney, and the protein is not expressed in the liver or splenocytes, where cytosolic ferritins are highly expressed for iron storage<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. Despite this, the protein has attracted increasing attention, as its misregulation is associated with many disease states, particularly neurological disorders<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. While a high-resolution X-ray structure<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup> and some initial studies of iron mineralization<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup> were published shortly after the protein&#x02019;s discovery, the focus of most studies has been the physiological consequences of misregulation of FtMt expression. Thus, the biochemical and biophysical properties of the protein and the mechanism of Fe<sup>2+</sup> oxidation/mineralization remain relatively poorly characterized.</p><p id="Par7">Following cleavage of the mitochondrial targeting sequence, FtMt has 80% sequence identity to the H-chain of the cytosolic protein (HuHF), including conservation of all residues that act as ligands to the FC. Despite this, marked differences have been reported in the iron-binding and oxidation properties of the two proteins<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. The mechanism of HuHF is well established: following the binding of two Fe<sup>2+</sup> ions to the FC of the iron-free (apo-) protein, reaction with O<sub>2</sub> generates a di-Fe<sup>3+</sup> peroxo (DFP) species<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup> that is hydrolyzed to yield a metastable di-Fe<sup>3+</sup> oxo form of the FC. Displacement of Fe<sup>3+</sup> by further equivalents of Fe<sup>2+</sup> both initiates mineral core formation and regenerates the di-Fe<sup>2+</sup> form of the FC, allowing multiple turnovers of the site and nucleation/growth of the iron mineral (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>Mechanism of Fe<sup>2+</sup> oxidation at cytosolic ferritin ferroxidase centers (FCs).</title><p>Starting at the top, two equivalents of Fe<sup>2+</sup> bind at the vacant (apo) FC to give di-Fe<sup>2+</sup> FC (right). Transfer of a single electron from each onto O<sub>2</sub> results in the formation of a di-Fe<sup>3+</sup> peroxo intermediate (bottom) that is hydrolyzed to give a metastable di-Fe<sup>3+</sup> oxo species and peroxide (left). In pathway (i) Fe<sup>3+</sup> is then displaced by incoming Fe<sup>2+</sup> substrate, regenerating the di-Fe<sup>2+</sup> form of the FC and leading to the accumulation of a ferrihydrite-like mineral in the interior of the protein. In the absence of further Fe<sup>2+</sup> substrate (pathway (ii)), the apo form of the FC is regenerated by the slower loss of Fe<sup>3+</sup>, into the interior of the protein, where it also contributes to the accumulation of a mineral core. Fe<sup>2+</sup> ions are indicated in cyan, Fe<sup>3+</sup> ions are in brown, and the DFP is in royal blue.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2025_59463_Fig1_HTML" id="d33e422"/></fig></p><p id="Par8">Displacement of the oxidized product of the HuHF FC reaction is slow in comparison to binding and oxidation of Fe<sup>2+</sup>, meaning that initial turnover of the FC is kinetically distinct from the formation of the mineral core<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. The former process in FtMt, characterized by aerobic titration of Fe<sup>2+</sup> up to the point of saturating binding at FC sites, revealed unexpected features, including discontinuities at a ratio of 24 Fe<sup>2+</sup>/FtMt (i.e. 50% of that required to saturate FC binding) in parameters indicative of binding and/or oxidation of Fe<sup>2+</sup> to FCs. Equivalent data for HuHF showed no evidence of such discontinuities, and the reported rate of the subsequent iron core mineralization process in FtMt was approximately 50% of that for HuHF. These observations led to the proposal that only half of the catalytic FCs of FtMt are active.</p><p id="Par9">The majority of the amino acid residues that differ between HuHF and the mature FtMt peptide sequences are located at the N and C termini, or the outer surface of the protein cage<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. A notable exception is residue Ser144 (FtMt numbering, post-maturation), the equivalent residue in HuHF being alanine. In fact, the sequences of animal H-chain ferritins display considerable variation at this position, whilst this residue is invariably Ser in their mitochondrial equivalents (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). FtMt variant S144A was reported to have greater FC activity and faster iron mineralization kinetics than the wild-type protein, leading to the suggestion that negative cooperativity of Fe<sup>2+</sup>-binding to FtMt FCs, in part mediated by Ser144, is responsible for its unusual iron-binding and oxidation properties<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par10">Recently, SynFtn, a ferritin from a coastal-dwelling cyanobacterium that also contains Ser at the position equivalent to Ser144 in FtMt, was characterized<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. This residue was identified as an important factor in directing the mechanism of iron oxidation in SynFtn via an unprecedented pathway, involving a tyrosyl radical and an unusual mixed-valent Fe<sup>2+</sup>/Fe<sup>3+</sup> intermediate form of the FC (MVFC)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>. The site of tyrosyl radical formation was identified as Tyr40 (SynFtn numbering), a residue that is conserved in FtMt (Tyr34). Formation of the MVFC involved oxidation of only 50% of the Fe<sup>2+</sup> at FC sites, potentially linking the behavior of SynFtn and the early reports of FtMt activity. Therefore, we sought to characterize the intermediates formed during the oxidation of Fe<sup>2+</sup> catalyzed by FtMt.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Wild-type FtMt-catalyzed oxidation of Fe<sup>2+</sup> under air-saturated conditions results in a protein-based radical, but no MVFC</title><p id="Par11">Addition of Fe<sup>2+</sup> ions to apo FtMt in air-saturated buffer resulted in a rapid initial reaction, corresponding to the oxidation of two Fe<sup>2+</sup> ions at each FC, followed by a slower reaction due to the subsequent formation of a mineral core. The oxo-coordinated Fe<sup>3+</sup>-containing species generated at the FC and the ferrihydrite-like mineral core both give rise to broad absorbance features centered at 340&#x02009;nm with extinction coefficients of approximately 2000&#x02009;<sc>m</sc><sup>&#x02212;</sup><sup>1</sup>&#x02009;cm<sup>&#x02212;</sup><sup>1</sup> at this wavelength<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>. Thus, the rate of increase in 340&#x02009;nm absorbance is proportional to the rate of Fe<sup>2+</sup> oxidation and hence protein activity. Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref> shows the increase in 340&#x02009;nm absorbance following the addition of 400 equivalents of Fe<sup>2+</sup> to wild-type FtMt. Two clear phases were observed, the slower phase representing mineral core formation following an initial jump due to turnover of the FC.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><title>Iron oxidation and mineralization by FtMt.</title><p><bold>a</bold> The increase in 340&#x02009;nm absorbance as a function of time following the aerobic mixing of wild-type (black trace) and variant Y34F (red trace) FtMt with 400 equivalents of Fe<sup>2+</sup>. <bold>b</bold> The increase in 340&#x02009;nm absorbance as a function of time following the aerobic mixing of wild-type FtMt with equal volumes of solutions containing 6&#x02013;96 equivalents of Fe<sup>2+</sup>. Data are shown as gray circles; red traces represent fits to either mono- or bi-exponential functions. <bold>c</bold> The amplitude of the increase in 340&#x02009;nm absorbance during the rapid phase of Fe<sup>2+</sup> oxidation by wild-type (black) and variant Y34F (red) FtMt as a function of the concentration of added Fe<sup>2+</sup>. <bold>d</bold> The dependence of the apparent first-order rate constant for Fe<sup>2+</sup> oxidation as a function of initial Fe<sup>2+</sup> concentration for wild-type (black) and variant Y34F (red) FtMt. The black line represents the best fit through the origin to the data for the wild-type protein. <bold>e</bold> The change in 650&#x02009;nm absorbance as a function of time following the aerobic mixing of wild-type (black trace) and variant Y34F (red trace) FtMt with 48 equivalents of Fe<sup>2+</sup>, reporting the formation and subsequent decay of the di-Fe<sup>3+</sup> peroxo intermediate. <bold>f</bold> as (<bold>b</bold>) but for variant Y34F FtMt. Source data are provided as a Source Data file.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2025_59463_Fig2_HTML" id="d33e553"/></fig></p><p id="Par12">Stopped-flow absorbance measurements at 340&#x02009;nm following the addition of increasing amounts of Fe<sup>2+</sup> (up to 96 per 24mer) to apo FtMt (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>) revealed the FC reaction in full. A single phase was observed at lower Fe<sup>2+</sup> loading, saturating at ~48 Fe<sup>2+</sup> per cage, and with a &#x00394;A<sub>340 nm</sub> amplitude consistent with oxidation of all Fe<sup>2+</sup> to Fe<sup>3+</sup> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2c</xref>). This was unexpected given the earlier report of activity in only half of the FtMt FCs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. At higher loadings, a biphasic response was observed, with the amplitude of the slower phase increasing in proportion to the amount of Fe<sup>2+</sup> added beyond that needed to saturate the initial rapid phase. Fitting of the data to one or two exponential functions (as needed) yielded effective first-order rate constants for these processes, that for the rapid phase are plotted as a function of Fe<sup>2+</sup> concentration in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2d</xref>. The dependence was approximately linear, indicating that Fe<sup>2+</sup> binding to the FC is rate-limiting under the conditions employed and allowing the calculation of a second order rate constant of 1.8&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup>&#x02009;<sc>m</sc><sup>&#x02212;</sup><sup>1</sup>&#x02009;s<sup>&#x02212;</sup><sup>1</sup> for this process, approximately 50% of the value of 3.8&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup>&#x02009;<sc>m</sc><sup>&#x02212;</sup><sup>1</sup> s<sup>&#x02212;</sup><sup>1</sup> determined for HuHF (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. Parameters describing the rapid oxidation of Fe<sup>2+</sup> by FtMt FCs extracted from these data are listed in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>.</p><p id="Par13">In contrast to early studies of FtMt conducted at pH 7.0<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>, the above data indicated the rapid oxidation of 48 equivalents of Fe<sup>2+</sup> per protein cage. Since this represents the total number of iron-binding sites located within the FCs of the protein, we expected to find that wild-type FtMt directly forms the commonly observed diferric-peroxo (DFP) intermediate species during O<sub>2</sub>-driven activity. DFP species have a characteristic absorbance between 600 and 650&#x02009;nm with an extinction coefficient that varies with the coordination geometry of the peroxide relative to the iron<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>. Stopped-flow measurements at 650&#x02009;nm confirmed that a DFP intermediate formed in FtMt (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2e</xref>), and that it subsequently decayed, most likely to a metastable &#x000b5;-oxo bridged diferric species, as observed for all eukaryotic H-chain ferritins studied to date<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par14">The absorbance data above imply that there is no accumulation of a MVFC intermediate in FtMt. Electron paramagnetic resonance (EPR) spectroscopy was used to further investigate this. Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a</xref> shows the EPR spectrum of wild-type FtMt frozen approximately 10&#x02009;s after mixing with 72 equivalents of Fe<sup>2+</sup> in air-saturated buffer. The spectrum contained a signal at <italic>g</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;4.3, which is commonly observed during ferritin-catalyzed Fe<sup>2+</sup> oxidation, indicating the presence of high-spin Fe<sup>3+</sup> in a low symmetry environment. A second signal was observed at approximately <italic>g</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2, typical of a protein-based radical located on an oxidized tyrosine residue. This is shown over a narrower field range in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3b</xref>. Very low intensity signals below <italic>g</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2 suggested the possible presence of a minor amount of MVFC (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3c</xref>), though this was variable from sample to sample and never amounted to more than approximately 1% of protein monomer concentration.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><title>EPR spectra of the paramagnetic species formed during Fe<sup>2+</sup> oxidation by FtMt.</title><p><bold>a</bold> Spectra recorded at microwave power of 3.19&#x02009;mW over the field range 600&#x02013;4200 Gauss for 4.2&#x02009;&#x003bc;<sc>m</sc> wild-type (black trace) and variant Y34F (red trace) FtMt frozen approximately 10&#x02009;s following aerobic mixing with 72 equivalents of Fe<sup>2+</sup>. <bold>b</bold> as in (<bold>a</bold>) but spectra recorded over the field range 3300&#x02013;3500 Gauss at microwave power 0.05&#x02009;mW. <bold>c</bold> as (<bold>a</bold>) but spectra recorded over the field range 3200&#x02013;4150 Gauss. <bold>d</bold> as (<bold>c</bold>) but with freezing times for the wild-type protein of 45&#x02009;ms (blue), 125&#x02009;ms (yellow), 245&#x02009;ms (brown), 445&#x02009;ms (heavy black trace with maximum radical intensity), or 10&#x02009;s (gray) and freezing times for variant Y34F of 45&#x02009;ms (blue), 245&#x02009;ms (yellow), 445&#x02009;ms (brown), 3&#x02009;s (heavy red trace with maximum mixed-valent ferroxidase center intensity) or 10&#x02009;s (gray). Source data are provided as a Source Data file.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2025_59463_Fig3_HTML" id="d33e718"/></fig></p><p id="Par15">The above data provide no indication of the accumulation of significant amounts of a MVFC. Nevertheless, rapid freeze quench (RFQ) was used to assess freezing times between 50&#x02009;ms and 10&#x02009;s to rule out the possibility that observable quantities of a MVFC species form and decay in wild-type FtMt during the first several seconds of the reaction. The intensity of the protein-based radical signal increased with freezing time up to 445&#x02009;ms and then remained constant over the following 10&#x02009;s. Again, the spectra showed no evidence of significant MVFC formation (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3d</xref>). Thus, the data indicate that a Tyr protein radical species is formed during Fe<sup>2+</sup> oxidation at the FC, but significant amounts of a MVFC are not.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Tyr34 is the site of radical formation on FtMt and plays an important role in initial Fe<sup>2+</sup> oxidation, but not mineralization</title><p id="Par16">All H-chain type ferritins contain a strictly conserved Tyr residue lying close to the FC, which has been shown in several cases to play an important role in Fe<sup>2+</sup> oxidation/mineralization<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>. In FtMt, this is Tyr34, and so the effect of a Y34F substitution on FtMt activity was investigated by measuring the rate of increase in absorbance at 340 or 650&#x02009;nm following aerobic addition of Fe<sup>2+</sup> compared with equivalent data for the wild-type protein. Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref> shows the increase in 340&#x02009;nm absorbance due to the formation of the mineral core following the addition of 400 equivalents of Fe<sup>2+</sup> to Y34F FtMt was almost identical to that of the wild-type protein, indicating that substitution of Tyr34 had no significant effect on the rate at which FtMt can mineralize iron. We note that the equivalent substitution in HuHF resulted in an approximately 50% decrease in mineralization activity (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2a</xref>).</p><p id="Par17">In contrast to mineral core formation, the initial Fe<sup>2+</sup> oxidation reaction was very different for the Y34F variant compared to wild-type FtMt, see Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2f</xref>. Not only was the rate of the rapid oxidation phase reduced in the variant, but the amplitude of this phase for Y34F FtMt saturated at ~30% of that for wild-type FtMt (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2c</xref>). Furthermore, the rate constant associated with the rapid phase observed for Y34F was independent of Fe<sup>2+</sup> concentration below 24&#x02009;&#x003bc;<sc>m</sc> (48 Fe per cage), at which point it began to increase linearly (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2d</xref>), demonstrating that, at low Fe<sup>2+</sup> concentration, iron binding to Y34F is not the rate-limiting step of the FC-catalyzed oxidation reaction. Equivalent data for the Y34F variant of HuHF demonstrated that rapid oxidation is abolished by this substitution (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>).</p><p id="Par18">The rate of formation of the DFP intermediate by the FtMt Y34F variant, indicative of the rate of Fe<sup>2+</sup> oxidation at the FC, was only 65% of that observed for the wild-type FtMt, with apparent first-order rate constants of 70&#x02009;s<sup>&#x02212;</sup><sup>1</sup> and 110&#x02009;s<sup>&#x02212;</sup><sup>1</sup>, respectively, when mixing protein and Fe<sup>2+</sup> under aerobic conditions (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2e</xref>). The rate of FC-catalyzed Fe<sup>2+</sup> oxidation was also monitored using a different experimental arrangement in which equal volumes of aerobic buffer and FtMt anaerobically pre-incubated with 48 Fe<sup>2+</sup> per cage were mixed (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>). This mixing protocol eliminated any effect due to different rates of Fe<sup>2+</sup> binding to the FC of wild-type and variant Y34F, demonstrating that the intrinsic rate of Fe<sup>2+</sup> oxidation is 35-fold slower in the variant protein. Consistent with this, the rate of DFP formation is severely impaired in the variant protein, such that detectable quantities of this intermediate only accumulate at &#x02265;30&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. Even under conditions of aerobic mixing, the maximum increase in A<sub>650 nm</sub> observed for variant Y34F was only approximately 50% of that of the wild-type FtMt. This suggests either a change in the absorbance properties of the DFP due to a different binding mode of peroxide, or that the substitution impacted the extent to which this intermediate was generated (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2e</xref>). Given the reduction in 340&#x02009;nm absorbance amplitude associated with the rapid phase of the FC reaction (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>), this was most likely a consequence of impaired DFP formation. EPR spectroscopy was employed to determine whether this was due to the formation of a MVFC species in competition with the DFP intermediate.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Formation of a MVFC in Y34F FtMt during aerobic Fe<sup>2+</sup> oxidation</title><p id="Par19">The spectrum of Y34F FtMt frozen approximately 10&#x02009;s after mixing with 72 equivalents of Fe<sup>2+</sup> in air-saturated buffer contained the <italic>g</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;4.3 Fe<sup>3+</sup> feature observed for the wild-type protein, but at lower intensity (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a</xref>). The signal in the <italic>g</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2 region was unlike that observed for the wild-type protein, in that the tyrosyl radical signal was replaced by a signal typical of oxidative damage due to peroxidation of amino acid sidechains (ROO<sup>&#x02022;</sup>), see Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3b</xref> for a narrower field range.</p><p id="Par20">In addition to the signals described above, the spectrum of variant Y34F also contained a rhombic signal with all g-values below 2 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a, c</xref>), characteristic of previously reported MVFCs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>. Integration of the MVFC envelope indicated a concentration of this species of approximately 30&#x02009;&#x003bc;<sc>m</sc> (equating to ~30% of subunit concentration). The kinetics of MVFC formation were investigated using RFQ EPR, where freezing times between 50&#x02009;ms and 10&#x02009;s were accessed (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3d</xref>). The data revealed the formation of a MVFC, together with ROO<sup>&#x02022;</sup> species, over the first 3&#x02009;s of the reaction, with the majority formed in the first 500&#x02009;ms. This is similar to the kinetics of DFP formation detected by stopped-flow absorbance, suggesting that in this variant the two species form by competing direct oxidation pathways. The ROO<sup>&#x02022;</sup> species decayed over the following 7&#x02009;s, whilst the MVFC signal remained stable with a maximum observed concentration of approximately 40&#x02009;&#x003bc;<sc>m</sc> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3d</xref>).</p><p id="Par21">Thus, the combination of absorbance and EPR kinetic data demonstrated that the Y34F variant of FtMt forms a MVFC species directly during its reaction with excess O<sub>2</sub>, but an equivalent species is not readily detected in the wild-type protein. Importantly, the EPR spectrum of a sample of Y34F HuHF frozen approximately 10&#x02009;s after mixing with 72 equivalents of Fe<sup>2+</sup> in air-saturated buffer contained no evidence of MVFC formation (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>), indicating that the observation of a MVFC following substitution of Tyr34 by Phe is unique to FtMt and not common to H-chain ferritins.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Formation of a MVFC in wild-type FtMt under limiting O<sub>2</sub></title><p id="Par22">Assays of ferritin activity are usually conducted under conditions of excess oxidant, typically O<sub>2</sub>, such that the reaction terminates when all added Fe<sup>2+</sup> has been oxidized to Fe<sup>3+</sup>. To further probe the FtMt-catalyzed reaction between Fe<sup>2+</sup> and O<sub>2</sub>, samples were prepared with insufficient O<sub>2</sub> to oxidize all the added Fe<sup>2+</sup>. According to the reaction scheme of Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, the predicted result would be ferritin cages containing a mixture of di-Fe<sup>3+</sup>-oxo and unreacted di-Fe<sup>2+</sup> FCs. Indeed, the EPR spectrum of a control sample of HuHF treated in this way was entirely consistent with this outcome (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>), with only trace amounts of MVFC present, most likely formed via displacement of Fe<sup>3+</sup> from di-Fe<sup>3+</sup> centers by trace unreacted Fe<sup>2+</sup> remaining in solution<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. However, the EPR spectrum of wild-type FtMt clearly contained the features associated with formation of a MVFC, with approximately 5% of protein monomers containing an FC in this oxidation state, too great to plausibly be formed by trace unreacted Fe<sup>2+</sup> remaining in solution via the same mechanism as for HuHF (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a</xref>). Several possibilities exist for how this oxidation state of the FtMt FC forms, including: direct oxidation to a MVFC intermediate that is trapped when there is insufficient O<sub>2</sub> to drive further oxidation to the di-Fe<sup>3+</sup> form, protein-mediated electron transfer between unreacted FCs and di-Fe<sup>3+</sup> FCs to yield 2 equivalents of the MVFC form<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>, or dissociation of unreacted Fe<sup>2+</sup> from di-Fe<sup>2+</sup> FCs and subsequent displacement of Fe<sup>3+</sup> from a di-Fe<sup>3+</sup> FC.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><title>O<sub>2</sub>-limited reaction of FtMt.</title><p><bold>a</bold> The EPR spectrum of 4.17&#x02009;&#x003bc;<sc>m</sc> wild-type FtMt anaerobically incubated with 200&#x02009;&#x003bc;<sc>m</sc> Fe<sup>2+</sup> then frozen 10&#x02009;s after mixing with aerobic buffer, resulting in an O<sub>2</sub> concentration of 50&#x02009;&#x003bc;<sc>m</sc> post-mixing (black trace). The red trace shows the MVFC formed by variant Y34F when O<sub>2</sub> is present in excess, and the gray trace shows the spectrum of wild-type protein when O<sub>2</sub> is present in excess for comparison. <bold>b</bold> Accumulation of the MVFC intermediate with increasing freezing time following the mixing of 20.8&#x02009;&#x003bc;<sc>m</sc> wild-type FtMt with 1&#x02009;m<sc>m</sc> Fe<sup>2+</sup> under aerobic conditions. Samples frozen 0.125 (black), 0.250 (red), 1 (blue), 3 (dark green), 6 (magenta) and 10 (dark yellow) s after mixing. <bold>c</bold> Comparison of the relative intensity of the MVFC of the samples from (b) (black circles, left axis) with the change in 650&#x02009;nm absorbance as a function of time after mixing of an equivalent sample (blue trace, right axis). Source data are provided as a Source Data file.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2025_59463_Fig4_HTML" id="d33e999"/></fig></p><p id="Par23">Further EPR experiments were performed in which partial occupancy of FCs or increased concentration of unbound Fe<sup>2+</sup> in solution were deliberately introduced in the wild-type protein. The goal was to probe whether a lower Fe<sup>2+</sup> binding affinity of Y34F FtMt caused the observation of a MVFC in this protein. The data showed that this was not the case, see Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref> for further details. Thus, we conclude that under excess O<sub>2</sub>, any MVFC intermediate, generated by either electron transfer from partially occupied to fully oxidized FCs, or displacement of Fe<sup>3+</sup> by Fe<sup>2+</sup>, does not accumulate. This suggested that the MVFC form of wild-type FtMt catalytic centers is only stable in the absence of O<sub>2</sub> and, unlike the equivalent MVFC form of SynFtn, reacts rapidly with O<sub>2</sub> to generate di-Fe<sup>3+</sup> sites. Absorbance-monitored stopped-flow mixing data support this conclusion. Wild-type FtMt was prepared in the MVFC state using higher protein and Fe<sup>2+</sup> concentrations of 20.8&#x02009;&#x003bc;<sc>m</sc> and 1&#x02009;m<sc>m</sc>, respectively, such that the typical ambient dissolved O<sub>2</sub> concentration (250&#x02009;&#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>) was sufficient to oxidize only 50% of FC sites. A sample prepared in this way within a gas-tight syringe showed no increase in absorbance on mixing with anaerobic buffer, whilst mixing with buffer containing 250&#x02009;&#x003bc;<sc>m</sc> dissolved O<sub>2</sub> resulted in an increase of 0.3 absorbance units within the deadtime of the instrument (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S6</xref>).</p><p id="Par24">Increased protein and Fe<sup>2+</sup> concentrations were also exploited to probe the relative rates of DFP and MVFC formation in wild-type FtMt under O<sub>2</sub>-limited conditions. Slow-freeze experiments (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S7</xref>) performed with equal volume mixing of protein and iron solutions (for equivalence with later RFQ experiments) demonstrated that significant MVFC formation occurred under these conditions. However, the time dependence of MVFC formation (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4b, c</xref>) measured by RFQ experiments showed that it did not begin to accumulate in detectable concentration until after hydrolysis of the DFP formed by reaction with O<sub>2</sub>, as indicated by decay of the transient 650&#x02009;nm absorbance prior to detection of the MVFC by EPR. The MVFC species accumulated rapidly between 0.25 and 1.0&#x02009;s post-mixing, with a maximum observed concentration of ~70&#x02009;&#x003bc;<sc>m</sc> (15% of protein monomers). We therefore conclude that the MVFC that is stabilized under limiting O<sub>2</sub> conditions results from a disproportionation of di-Fe<sup>2+</sup> and di-Fe<sup>3+</sup> FCs. It is not generated by direct O<sub>2</sub>-driven oxidation of the di-Fe<sup>2+</sup> form because that intermediate is consumed by reaction with O<sub>2</sub> far more rapidly than remaining unreacted di-Fe<sup>2+</sup> centers.</p><p id="Par25">Formation of the MVFC post-hydrolysis of the DFP species raises the possibility that the MVFC is produced by the reaction of remaining di-Fe<sup>2+</sup> sites with the peroxide released during decay of the DFP form of the FC. However, control measurements (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S8</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S10</xref>) confirmed that the reaction of di-Fe<sup>2+</sup> FtMt FCs with peroxide is too slow to account for the observed rate of MVFC formation. Furthermore, reaction with peroxide only generates the MVFC on the wild-type protein when Fe<sup>2+</sup> is present in excess, whilst the O<sub>2</sub>-driven reactions above would generate 250&#x02009;&#x003bc;<sc>m</sc> peroxide together with 500&#x02009;&#x003bc;<sc>m</sc> unreacted Fe<sup>2+</sup>.</p><p id="Par26">The impact of Ser at position 144 on the formation of MVFCs by FtMt under limiting O<sub>2</sub> was probed by using FtMt variant S144A and HuHF variant A144S. Whilst the S144A substitution resulted in the previously reported<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup> increase in rate of iron oxidation and mineralization (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S7</xref>), the corresponding A144S substitution in HuHF had a negligible effect on both processes (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S7</xref>). Slow-freeze EPR revealed that, whilst the S144A substitution in FtMt led to a decrease in MVFC intensity of approximately 50%, no detectable MVFC was formed by HuHF variant A144S (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S7</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Products of O<sub>2</sub> reduction</title><p id="Par27">Oxidation of di-Fe<sup>2+</sup> FCs to the mixed-valent form liberates a single electron that might be expected to cause the reduction of O<sub>2</sub> to superoxide. In the wild-type protein, Tyr34 has the potential to deliver a second reducing equivalent to O<sub>2</sub>, or this could be derived from a second Fe<sup>2+</sup> ion at a remote FC, leading to the formation of peroxide in either scenario. Consistent with this, previous studies of the stoichiometry of the iron-O<sub>2</sub> chemistry catalyzed by the FC of FtMt indicated that two equivalents of Fe<sup>2+</sup> were oxidized per O<sub>2</sub> reduced<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par28">In the case of variant Y34F, there is no oxidizable residue at position 34. However, a significant proportion of FCs in the mixed-valent state were observed following reaction with O<sub>2</sub>, including when it was in excess. Thus, if FtMt FCs carry out their oxido-reductase chemistry in isolation from one another, this variant, which has no obvious source of a second reducing equivalent for O<sub>2</sub>, would be expected to produce a higher proportion of superoxide as the product of O<sub>2</sub> reduction than the wild-type protein.</p><p id="Par29">Production of peroxide during FtMt activity was assessed using the Amplex Red assay. Control experiments indicated that FtMt interferes with H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> detection, either by direct reaction or reaction with Complex I of horse radish peroxidase, preventing oxidation of the Amplex Red dye. Nevertheless, for wild-type and Y34F proteins, approximately 25% of the O<sub>2</sub> reduced was detected as H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> in the Amplex Red assay, suggesting that the Y34F substitution had no effect on the product of O<sub>2</sub> reduction.</p><p id="Par30">In the case of variant Y34F, peroxide formation would necessitate either electron transfer between FCs, since each can provide only a single electron, or diffusion of superoxide between centers in order to acquire a second reducing equivalent. The latter would be expected to result in the observation of the superoxide adduct of the spin-trapping reagent DMPO. Ambient temperature EPR spectra of DMPO following incubation with wild-type or Y34F FtMt and 72 equivalents of Fe<sup>2+</sup> showed no evidence of superoxide formation (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S11</xref>). Thus, we conclude that, in variant Y34F, and by extension in wild-type FtMt also, electron transfer from a remote FC provides a second reducing equivalent to FC-bound O<sub>2</sub>, leading to peroxide as the product of O<sub>2</sub> reduction.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par31">Both FtMt and the recently characterized cyanobacterial ferritin SynFtn contain a serine residue in a structurally equivalent position approximately 5&#x02009;&#x000c5; from the nearest iron (termed Fe2) of the FC. Iron oxidation catalyzed by SynFtn has been shown to proceed via an atypical Fe<sup>2+</sup>/Fe<sup>3+</sup> MVFC intermediate in which only 50% of FC-bound iron is oxidized<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. We therefore hypothesized that the presence of a similar intermediate in the catalytic cycle of FtMt may account for the previously reported unusual iron-binding and oxidation characteristics of this protein<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. In fact, we were unable to reproduce the earlier reported behavior of FtMt, which led to the conclusion that only half of the FCs were active<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>: in our hands, all of the FCs of FtMt were active, consistent with the recent structure-focused study of FtMt<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>. Despite this, our data do show that a MVFC intermediate accumulates on wild-type FtMt, but only under O<sub>2</sub>-limiting conditions (of the type likely to occur in mitochondria), and that this is the result of disproportionation of di-Fe<sup>2+</sup> and di-Fe<sup>3+</sup> sites.</p><p id="Par32">A recent computational study offered greater insight into the mechanism of SynFtn, suggesting that the role of the near-FC Ser residue in this protein was to stabilize superoxide bound to Fe2 following the one-electron reduction of O<sub>2</sub><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>. The mechanism also required population of a nearby cation binding site, whilst the generation of peroxide and 2 MVFCs as the product of O<sub>2</sub> reduction implied the presence of an inter-FC electron transfer route. The conserved tyrosine (Tyr34 in FtMt numbering) was essential to lower the activation energy for the reduction of O<sub>2</sub> bound to the di-Fe<sup>2+</sup> FC. FtMt also harbors a cation binding site that is not conserved in HuHF, around 10&#x02009;&#x000c5; from the FC<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>. Generation of peroxide as the product of O<sub>2</sub> reduction by FtMt variant Y34F and electron redistribution in the wild-type protein post-hydrolysis of the DFP species under limiting O<sub>2</sub> both imply the presence of an as yet unidentified inter-FC electron transfer route in FtMt that is absent in HuHF. We therefore propose that the catalytic cycle of FtMt, detailed in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>, is very similar to that of SynFtn but with a MVFC that is far more reactive toward O<sub>2</sub> than the di-Fe<sup>2+</sup> form. However, oxidation of the MVFC involves activation of O<sub>2</sub> by Tyr34 such that a significant proportion of variant Y34F becomes trapped in a metastable MVFC state. While direct oxidation to the DFP state undoubtedly occurs in this variant, formation is slower than in the wild-type protein. We hypothesize that this is due to the energy required to form the DFP via a transient MVFC intermediate being raised by the substitution of Tyr34, to the extent that direct DFP formation becomes a competing reaction pathway. The major role of Ser144 is the stabilization of superoxide bound to Fe2 during the oxidative formation of the MVFC. The 50% reduction in observed MVFC upon substitution of Ser144 with Ala also showed that Ser at position 144 in FtMt favors disproportionation of di-Fe<sup>2+</sup> and di-Fe<sup>3+</sup> sites to generate MVFCs under O<sub>2</sub> limitation. Variant A144S of HuHF is unable to relax to the same MVFC state, presumably because the inter-FC electron transfer route required for FtMt function is missing or much less efficient in HuHF.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><title>Proposed mechanistic cycle of Fe<sup>2+</sup> oxidation by FtMt.</title><p>Following binding of two Fe<sup>2+</sup> ions to the apo FC (top of the main cycle), O<sub>2</sub> binds and is activated by transfer of a single electron from Tyr34 to yield a tyrosyl radical and a superoxo adduct of the di-Fe<sup>2+</sup> FC. The radical is quenched by electron transfer from a remote FC, and electron transfer from Fe<sup>2+</sup> at the site with superoxide bound yields the peroxide product of O<sub>2</sub> reduction and the MVFC intermediate. Binding of O<sub>2</sub> and its activation by the MVFC is rapid in comparison to that occurring at the di-Fe<sup>2+</sup> FC form, and hence, the MVFC intermediate does not accumulate under continuous turnover. This reaction results in the DFP intermediate, which is hydrolyzed to the metastable di-Fe<sup>3+</sup> form. In the presence of excess O<sub>2</sub>, the metastable di-Fe<sup>3+</sup> FC breaks down to release Fe<sup>3+</sup> ions to the FtMt cavity, and the reaction cycle begins again (marked as (i)). Under limiting O<sub>2</sub>, where both di-Fe<sup>2+</sup> and di-Fe<sup>3+</sup> FCs are present, a disproportionation reaction occurs via long-range electron transfer, resulting in two MVFCs (marked as (ii) on the smaller left-hand cycle). When O<sub>2</sub> is available again, these are oxidized to the di-Fe<sup>3+</sup> form (marked as (iii)). The overall stoichiometry of the reaction is identical to that catalyzed by cytosolic ferritins, with each center coupling the oxidation of two equivalents of Fe<sup>2+</sup> to Fe<sup>3+</sup> with the reduction of O<sub>2</sub> to peroxide. Fe<sup>2+</sup> ions are indicated in cyan, Fe<sup>3+</sup> are in brown, and the DFP is in royal blue.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2025_59463_Fig5_HTML" id="d33e1304"/></fig></p><p id="Par33">FtMt is implicated in oxidative stress response, but it seems unlikely that the role of the protein is reactive oxygen species (ROS) detoxification via a direct reaction. Peroxide reduction by FtMt is sluggish, results in damage to the protein, and it is known that the vast majority of peroxide detoxification in mitochondria is performed by other enzymes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>. Similarly, superoxide detoxification is carried out by superoxide dismutase (SOD). Consumption of O<sub>2</sub> by the respiratory chain enzymes within the mitochondrial membrane means that O<sub>2</sub> concentration within the matrix is very low<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>. However, around 1% of the O<sub>2</sub> consumed during respiration is estimated to be converted to superoxide<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>. The action of SOD within the mitochondrial matrix will therefore result in a low but constantly replenished supply of O<sub>2</sub>, the presumed substrate of FtMt. The physiological importance of the unusual iron oxidation mechanism of FtMt remains unclear, but one possibility is that the typical conditions within the mitochondrial matrix, low O<sub>2</sub> concentration combined with high iron flux, serve to poise the protein in the MVFC state. This form of the protein is highly reactive towards O<sub>2</sub> and may serve as a buffer against higher iron and fluctuating O<sub>2</sub> concentrations within the microaerobic environment of the mitochondrial matrix.</p><p id="Par34">Strict conservation among mitochondrial ferritins of Ser at the position equivalent to Ser144 in the human protein (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>) supports the importance of this residue for their function within the mitochondrial matrix. Whilst cytosolic H-chain ferritins from some animals also contain Ser at the position equivalent to 144 in HuHF, these proteins exhibit considerable variation at this position, and our data suggest that the presence of Ser144 alone is not sufficient to influence FC mechanism<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>. However, even if it were to do so, the higher O<sub>2</sub> concentration and lower iron flux within the cytosol mean that accumulation of cytosolic H-chain in the MVFC state is unlikely to occur in vivo, and so the unusual mechanistic features of FtMt evolved specifically in the low O<sub>2</sub> environment of the mitochondrial matrix.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec10"><title>Protein expression and purification</title><p id="Par35">Plasmids based on the pET21a expression vector and encoding FtMt, HuHF and Y34F (FtMt and HuHF), S144A (FtMt), and A144S (HuHF) variants were purchased from Genscript (UK). All FtMt constructs lacked the predicted mitochondrial targeting sequence and the first 9 amino acid residues at the N terminus of the mature protein<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. Proteins were expressed from the <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> strain BL21 DE3. All cultures in liquid media were grown at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, 200&#x02009;rpm shaking, and contained 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;g&#x02009;mL<sup>&#x02212;</sup><sup>1</sup> ampicillin unless otherwise stated. Single colonies from LB agar plates containing 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;g&#x02009;mL<sup>&#x02212;</sup><sup>1</sup> ampicillin, grown overnight at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, were picked into 5&#x02009;mL liquid media (LB) and cultures were grown throughout the day. 400&#x02009;&#x003bc;L of the resulting cell culture was used to inoculate 80&#x02009;mL of LB, which was grown to saturation overnight. 50&#x02009;mL of the saturated culture was diluted 1 part in 100 into 5&#x02009;L of LB and grown until the optical density at 600&#x02009;nm was in the range 0.6&#x02013;0.8. Protein expression was induced by adding isopropyl &#x003b2;&#x02013;d-1 thiogalactopyranoside (IPTG) to a final concentration of 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>. Cultures were grown on for a further 20&#x02009;h at 30&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, 90&#x02009;rpm shaking prior to harvesting by centrifugation.</p><p id="Par36">Pellets were resuspended in 20&#x02009;m<sc>m</sc> HEPES, 100&#x02009;m<sc>m</sc> KCl, 0.1&#x02009;m<sc>m</sc> EDTA, pH 7.8 (buffer A), and the cells disrupted by sonication. Debris was removed by centrifugation at 40,000&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;<italic>g</italic>, 1&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 45&#x02009;min. Thermally unstable proteins were precipitated from the supernatant by heating to 65&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 15&#x02009;min and removed by a further round of centrifugation as above. Ferritin was precipitated from the supernatant by the addition of ammonium sulfate to a concentration of 0.55&#x02009;g&#x02009;mL<sup>&#x02212;</sup><sup>1</sup>. Precipitated protein was pelleted by a further round of centrifugation before redissolving in a minimum volume of buffer A and dialyzing against 1&#x02009;L of identical buffer for a minimum of 12&#x02009;h. Contaminating proteins were removed by size exclusion chromatography (HiPrep 26/60 Sephacryl S300HR, Cytiva) and contaminating DNA by anion exchange chromatography (HiTrap Q FF, Cytiva). For the latter, protein solutions were loaded in buffer A and eluted by stepping to 30% buffer B (20&#x02009;m<sc>m</sc> HEPES, 100&#x02009;m<sc>m</sc> KCl, 1&#x02009;<sc>m</sc> NaCl, 0.1&#x02009;m<sc>m</sc> EDTA, pH 7.8).</p><p id="Par37">Protein as isolated contained small quantities of iron that was removed using the method of Bauminger et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>. Following iron removal, protein was exchanged into 100&#x02009;m<sc>m</sc> MES pH 6.5 by centrifugation over a 10&#x02009;kDa molecular weight cut-off cellulose membrane (Millipore). The absence of contaminating proteins was confirmed using SDS-PAGE, and ferritin was judged free from DNA contamination once the ratio of absorbance at 280&#x02009;nm to 260&#x02009;nm reached 1.5. Protein concentration was determined by absorbance, assuming &#x003b5;<sub>280 nm</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;4.08&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup>&#x02009;<sc>m</sc><sup>&#x02212;</sup><sup>1</sup> cm<sup>&#x02212;</sup><sup>1</sup> for the 24meric protein cage<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par38">In general, kinetic absorbance experiments were performed in triplicate for each of two independently prepared protein samples, which gave very similar results; representative data are shown. EPR slow-freeze experiments were repeated in duplicate, and a standard 10&#x02009;s freeze spectrum following the addition of 72 Fe<sup>2+</sup> per protein was recorded at the beginning of each EPR experiment to ensure reproducibility between different protein preparations. For freeze-quench EPR, experiments were performed with a single protein preparation at increasing time points, resulting in a self-consistent set of spectra.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Absorbance-monitored kinetic studies</title><p id="Par39">Protein activity was monitored via the increase in absorbance at 340&#x02009;nm resulting from the oxidation of Fe<sup>2+</sup> to Fe<sup>3+</sup>, or by monitoring the transient absorbance at 650&#x02009;nm resulting from the formation of a di-Fe<sup>3+</sup> peroxo (DFP) intermediate. The rate of mineral core formation was determined from the increase in 340&#x02009;nm absorbance using a Hitachi U2900 spectrophotometer with the sample chamber maintained at 25&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. Ferrous ammonium sulfate dissolved in 1&#x02009;mm HCl was added to a final concentration of 200&#x02009;&#x003bc;<sc>m</sc> to a 0.5&#x02009;&#x003bc;<sc>m</sc> solution of FtMt in 100&#x02009;m<sc>m</sc> MES, pH 6.5, in a 1&#x02009;cm pathlength cuvette. The extinction coefficient of the mineral core was deduced from the net absorbance change once iron oxidation was complete. Iron oxidation at the FC was monitored by using an Applied Photophysics Bio-Sequential DX.17MV spectrophotometer with a 1&#x02009;cm pathlength observation cell to mix equal volumes of 1&#x02009;&#x003bc;<sc>m</sc> apo protein in 100&#x02009;m<sc>m</sc> MES pH 6.5 and solutions of 6, 12, 18, 24, 30, 36, 42, 48, 60, 72 or 96&#x02009;&#x003bc;<sc>m</sc> ferrous ammonium sulfate in 1&#x02009;m<sc>m</sc> HCl. Data were collected using ProData SX software (Applied Photophysics). The time dependence of absorbance increases at 340&#x02009;nm was fitted to the sum of two exponential processes, encompassing rapid (r) and slow (s) components, using OriginPro 8 (OriginLab):<disp-formula id="Equ1"><label>1</label><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e1465">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\Delta {{{\rm{A}}}}_{340}\left(t\right)=\Delta {{{\rm{A}}}}_{340}^{({{\rm{tot}}})}-\Delta {{{\rm{A}}}}_{340}^{{{\rm{r}}}}{{{\rm{e}}}}^{-{k}_{{{\rm{r}}}}t}-\Delta {{{\rm{A}}}}_{340}^{{{\rm{s}}}}{{{\rm{e}}}}^{-{k}_{{{\rm{s}}}}t}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="d33e1471"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x00394;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>340</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x00394;</mml:mi><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>340</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">tot</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x00394;</mml:mi><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>340</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x00394;</mml:mi><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>340</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41467_2025_59463_Article_Equ1.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par40">Formation of the DFP intermediate was also detected using the Applied Photophysics Bio-Sequential DX.17MV spectrophotometer with ProData SX, but required an increase in protein concentration to 8&#x02009;&#x003bc;M (192&#x02009;&#x003bc;M in monomer) prior to mixing with 384&#x02009;&#x003bc;M Fe<sup>2+</sup> (2 Fe<sup>2+</sup> per FC). The rate of increase and subsequent decrease in 650&#x02009;nm absorbance was used to deduce the rate of formation and decay of the DFP intermediate, whilst the increase in absorbance at 340&#x02009;nm was used to deduce the overall rate of Fe<sup>2+</sup> oxidation.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Electron paramagnetic resonance</title><p id="Par41">EPR spectra were recorded using Bruker EMX and Bruker E500 EPR spectrometers (both X-band) with WinEPR/XEPR software (Bruker BioSpin). The low-temperature EPR spectra were measured at 10&#x02009;K using Oxford Instruments liquid helium systems. Instrument parameters for low-temperature EPR measurements were as follows: microwave frequency <italic>&#x003bd;</italic><sub>MW</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;9.467&#x02009;GHz, modulation frequency <italic>&#x003bd;</italic><sub>M</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;100&#x02009;kHz, time constant &#x003c4;&#x02009;=&#x02009;82&#x02009;ms, microwave power = 3.19&#x02009;mW or 0.05&#x02009;mW, modulation amplitude <italic>A</italic><sub>M</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;5&#x02009;G or 3&#x02009;G (for narrower field range), scan rate <italic>&#x003bd;</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;22.6 Gs<sup>&#x02212;</sup><sup>1</sup> or 6.0 Gs<sup>&#x02212;</sup><sup>1</sup> (for narrower field range). Wilmad SQ EPR tubes (Wilmad Glass, Buena, NJ) with OD&#x02009;=&#x02009;4.05&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.07&#x02009;mm and ID&#x02009;=&#x02009;3.12&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.04&#x02009;mm (mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;range) were used for low-temperature measurements. Two methods of sample freezing were used.</p><p id="Par42">Protein samples in EPR tubes were mixed with the appropriate volume of a 25&#x02009;m<sc>m</sc> stock Fe<sup>2+</sup> solution and frozen 10&#x02009;s thereafter by plunging the tubes into methanol cooled with solid CO<sub>2</sub> (slow freezing method). To produce samples sub-stoichiometric in O<sub>2</sub>, protein solutions were rendered anaerobic by stirring under an argon atmosphere for 30&#x02009;min prior to incubation with Fe<sup>2+</sup>. Reactivity was then initiated by mixing with buffer containing 250&#x02009;&#x003bc;<sc>m</sc> dissolved O<sub>2</sub> prior to freezing as described above. The addition of an appropriate volume of a 50&#x02009;m<sc>m</sc> stock H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> solution in place of oxygenated buffer to equivalent samples was used to generate samples with H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-driven oxidation of Fe<sup>2+</sup>.</p><p id="Par43">Samples frozen at times &#x0003c;10&#x02009;s (the Rapid Freeze-Quench technique, RFQ) were prepared by mixing equal volumes of an 8.33&#x02009;&#x000b5;<sc>m</sc> protein solution (200&#x02009;&#x000b5;<sc>m</sc> in subunit monomer) and a 0.6&#x02009;m<sc>m</sc> Fe<sup>2+</sup> solution in a set-up combining an Update Instrument Syringe Ram Controller (Madison, WI) and a home-built apparatus for freezing the ejected mixtures on the surface of a rotating aluminum disk kept at liquid nitrogen temperature, as described elsewhere<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup>. Final protein concentration was 4.17&#x02009;&#x000b5;<sc>m</sc> (100&#x02009;&#x000b5;<sc>m</sc> in monomer). Proteins were in 100&#x02009;m<sc>m</sc> MES, pH 6.5, and Fe<sup>2+</sup> solutions in 50&#x02009;m<sc>m</sc> HCl (slow freezing) or 1&#x02009;m<sc>m</sc> HCl (RFQ). The concentration of the MVFC species in various samples was determined by comparison of the integrated intensity of the associated EPR signal with that of a 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;<sc>m</sc> CuEDTA standard.</p><p id="Par44">The ambient temperature EPR experiments on radical trapping with the spin trap reagent 5,5-dimethyl-1-pyrroline-N-oxide (DMPO) were performed with the use of a Bruker AquaX system for liquid sample measurements. To minimize the dead volume of AquaX, the inlet tubing was shortened to 1&#x02009;cm. 200&#x02009;&#x003bc;L samples were prepared in 100&#x02009;mM MES pH 6.5 with the following final concentrations: 80&#x02009;m<sc>m</sc> DMPO, 12&#x02009;&#x003bc;<sc>m</sc> FtMt, and 288&#x02009;&#x003bc;<sc>m</sc> Fe<sup>2+</sup> and immediately loaded by syringe into the AquaX capillaries system. Spectra were acquired using the following parameters: microwave frequency <italic>&#x003bd;</italic><sub>MW</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;9.84&#x02009;GHz, modulation frequency <italic>&#x003bd;</italic><sub>M</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;100&#x02009;kHz, time constant &#x003c4;&#x02009;=&#x02009;51&#x02009;ms, microwave power = 0.63&#x02009;m<sc>W</sc>, modulation amplitude <italic>A</italic><sub>M</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1&#x02009;G, scan rate <italic>&#x003bd;</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.9&#x02009;Gs<sup>&#x02212;</sup><sup>1</sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Fluorescence emission spectroscopy</title><p id="Par45">Spectra were recorded on an Edinburgh Instruments FS5 spectrofluorometer equipped with a 96-well plate reader. Hydrogen peroxide was detected using an Amplex Red kit (Thermo Fisher) with excitation at &#x003bb;&#x02009;=&#x02009;530&#x02009;nm and emission scans across the range 550&#x02013;650&#x02009;nm. Fluorescence intensity at 590&#x02009;nm following the aerobic oxidation of 9.6&#x02009;&#x003bc;<sc>m</sc> Fe<sup>2+</sup> by 0.2, 0.4, 0.6, 0.8 or 1.0&#x02009;&#x003bc;<sc>m</sc> wild-type or Y34F FtMt was used to quantify released H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> by comparison to a plot generated from standard peroxide solutions of 1&#x02013;5&#x02009;&#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Reporting summary</title><p id="Par46">Further information on research design is available in the&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">Nature Portfolio Reporting Summary</xref> linked to this article.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec15" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary information</title><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41467_2025_59463_MOESM1_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Supplementary Information</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="41467_2025_59463_MOESM2_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Reporting Summary</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3"><media xlink:href="41467_2025_59463_MOESM3_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Transparent Peer Review file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec16" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Source data</title><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM4"><media xlink:href="41467_2025_59463_MOESM4_ESM.xlsx"><caption><p>Source Data</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Supplementary information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1038/s41467-025-59463-1.</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors wish to thank Dr Andrew Gates (UEA) for access to the stopped-flow instrument. This work was supported by the UK&#x02019;s Biotechnology and Biological Sciences Research Council through grants BB/R002363/1 (J.M.B. and N.L.B.), BB/R003203/1 (D.A.S.) and BB/T01802X/1 (D.A.S.) and by UEA.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>J.M.B. and N.L.B. conceived the study. J.M.B., Z.B., J.P. and D.A.S. performed the experiments. J.M.B., Z.B. and D.A.S. analyzed the data. J.M.B., D.A.S., G.R.M., and N.L.B. wrote the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="peer-review"><title>Peer review</title><sec id="FPar1"><title>Peer review information</title><p id="Par47"><italic>Nature Communications</italic> thanks Keisuke Hino, and the other, anonymous, reviewer(s) for their contribution to the peer review of this work. A peer review file is available.</p></sec></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>All data supporting the findings of this study are available within the paper and its Supplementary Information. Source data are provided with this paper. Expression constructs are available upon request from Nick Le Brun (n.le-brun@uea.ac.uk).&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="sec" rid="Sec16">Source data</xref> are provided with this paper.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par48">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beinert</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Holm</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Munck</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Iron-sulfur clusters: Nature&#x02019;s modular, multipurpose structures</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1997</year><volume>277</volume><fpage>653</fpage><lpage>659</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.277.5326.653</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9235882</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Beinert, H., Holm, R. H. &#x00026; Munck, E. Iron-sulfur clusters: Nature&#x02019;s modular, multipurpose structures. <italic>Science</italic><bold>277</bold>, 653&#x02013;659 (1997).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9235882</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gamba</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Codola</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Lloret-Fillol</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Costas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Making and breaking of the O-O bond at iron complexes</article-title><source>Coord. Chem. Rev.</source><year>2017</year><volume>334</volume><fpage>2</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ccr.2016.11.007</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Gamba, I., Codola, Z., Lloret-Fillol, J. &#x00026; Costas, M. Making and breaking of the O-O bond at iron complexes. <italic>Coord. Chem. Rev.</italic><bold>334</bold>, 2&#x02013;24 (2017).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Poulos</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Heme enzyme structure and function</article-title><source>Chem. Rev.</source><year>2014</year><volume>114</volume><fpage>3919</fpage><lpage>3962</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/cr400415k</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24400737</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Poulos, T. L. Heme enzyme structure and function. <italic>Chem. Rev.</italic><bold>114</bold>, 3919&#x02013;3962 (2014).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24400737</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gayer</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wootner</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The hydrolysis of ferrous chloride at 25 degrees</article-title><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source><year>1956</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>3944</fpage><lpage>3946</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ja01597a021</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Gayer, K. H. &#x00026; Wootner, L. The hydrolysis of ferrous chloride at 25 degrees. <italic>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</italic><bold>78</bold>, 3944&#x02013;3946 (1956).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Imlay</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The molecular mechanisms and physiological consequences of oxidative stress: lessons from a model bacterium</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Microbiol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>443</fpage><lpage>454</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro3032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23712352</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Imlay, J. A. The molecular mechanisms and physiological consequences of oxidative stress: lessons from a model bacterium. <italic>Nat. Rev. Microbiol.</italic><bold>11</bold>, 443&#x02013;454 (2013).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23712352</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Theil</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Matzapetakis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>XF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ferritins: iron/oxygen biominerals in protein nanocages</article-title><source>J. Biol. Inorg. Chem.</source><year>2006</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>803</fpage><lpage>810</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00775-006-0125-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16868744</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Theil, E. C., Matzapetakis, M. &#x00026; Liu, X. F. Ferritins: iron/oxygen biominerals in protein nanocages. <italic>J. Biol. Inorg. Chem.</italic><bold>11</bold>, 803&#x02013;810 (2006).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16868744</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laufberger</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crystallization of ferritn</article-title><source>Bull. Soc. Chim. Biol.</source><year>1937</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1575</fpage><lpage>1582</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Laufberger, V. Crystallization of ferritn. <italic>Bull. Soc. Chim. Biol.</italic><bold>19</bold>, 1575&#x02013;1582 (1937).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lawson</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identification of the ferroxidase center in ferritin</article-title><source>FEBS Lett.</source><year>1989</year><volume>254</volume><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>210</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0014-5793(89)81040-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2776883</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Lawson, D. M. et al. Identification of the ferroxidase center in ferritin. <italic>FEBS Lett.</italic><bold>254</bold>, 207&#x02013;210 (1989).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2776883</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>XF</given-names></name><name><surname>Theil</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ferritin reactions: direct identification of the site for the diferric peroxide reaction intermediate</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2004</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>8557</fpage><lpage>8562</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0401146101</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15166287</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Liu, X. F. &#x00026; Theil, E. C. Ferritin reactions: direct identification of the site for the diferric peroxide reaction intermediate. <italic>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</italic><bold>101</bold>, 8557&#x02013;8562 (2004).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15166287</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Le Brun</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Kinetic and structural characterization of an intermediate in the biomineralization of bacterioferritin</article-title><source>FEBS Lett.</source><year>1993</year><volume>333</volume><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>202</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0014-5793(93)80404-I</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8224163</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Le Brun, N. E. et al. Kinetic and structural characterization of an intermediate in the biomineralization of bacterioferritin. <italic>FEBS Lett.</italic><bold>333</bold>, 197&#x02013;202 (1993).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8224163</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bou-Abdallah</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayne</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name><surname>Arosio</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Chasteen</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Origin of the unusual kinetics of iron deposition in human H-chain ferritin</article-title><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source><year>2005</year><volume>127</volume><fpage>3885</fpage><lpage>3893</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ja044355k</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15771525</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Bou-Abdallah, F., Zhao, G. H., Mayne, H. R., Arosio, P. &#x00026; Chasteen, N. D. Origin of the unusual kinetics of iron deposition in human H-chain ferritin. <italic>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</italic><bold>127</bold>, 3885&#x02013;3893 (2005).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15771525</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ebrahimi</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Bill</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Hagedoorn</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hagen</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The catalytic center of ferritin regulates iron storage via Fe(II)-Fe(III) displacement</article-title><source>Nat. Chem. Biol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>941</fpage><lpage>948</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nchembio.1071</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23001032</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Ebrahimi, K. H., Bill, E., Hagedoorn, P. L. &#x00026; Hagen, W. R. The catalytic center of ferritin regulates iron storage via Fe(II)-Fe(III) displacement. <italic>Nat. Chem. Biol.</italic><bold>8</bold>, 941&#x02013;948 (2012).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23001032</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beauchene</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>O<sub>2</sub> availability impacts iron homeostasis in Escherichia coli</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2017</year><volume>114</volume><fpage>12261</fpage><lpage>12266</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1707189114</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29087312</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Beauchene, N. A. et al. O<sub>2</sub> availability impacts iron homeostasis in Escherichia coli. <italic>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</italic><bold>114</bold>, 12261&#x02013;12266 (2017).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29087312</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jacques</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>RyhB small RNA modulates the free intracellular iron pool and is essential for normal growth during iron limitation in Escherichia coli</article-title><source>Mol. Microbiol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>1181</fpage><lpage>1190</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2006.05439.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17078818</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Jacques, J. F. et al. RyhB small RNA modulates the free intracellular iron pool and is essential for normal growth during iron limitation in Escherichia coli. <italic>Mol. Microbiol.</italic><bold>62</bold>, 1181&#x02013;1190 (2006).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17078818</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keyer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Imlay</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Superoxide accelerates DNA damage by elevating free-iron levels</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>1996</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>13635</fpage><lpage>13640</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.93.24.13635</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8942986</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Keyer, K. &#x00026; Imlay, J. A. Superoxide accelerates DNA damage by elevating free-iron levels. <italic>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</italic><bold>93</bold>, 13635&#x02013;13640 (1996).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8942986</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>RJP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Free manganese(II) and iron(II) cations can act as intracellular cell controls</article-title><source>FEBS Lett.</source><year>1982</year><volume>140</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0014-5793(82)80508-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7084455</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Williams, R. J. P. Free manganese(II) and iron(II) cations can act as intracellular cell controls. <italic>FEBS Lett.</italic><bold>140</bold>, 3&#x02013;10 (1982).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7084455</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Brun</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ferritins: furnishing proteins with iron</article-title><source>J. Biol. Inorg. Chem.</source><year>2016</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>28</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00775-016-1336-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26825805</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Bradley, J. M., Le Brun, N. E. &#x00026; Moore, G. R. Ferritins: furnishing proteins with iron. <italic>J. Biol. Inorg. Chem.</italic><bold>21</bold>, 13&#x02013;28 (2016).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26825805</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Theil</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Behera</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Tosha</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ferritins for chemistry and for life</article-title><source>Coord. Chem. Rev.</source><year>2013</year><volume>257</volume><fpage>579</fpage><lpage>586</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ccr.2012.05.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23470857</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Theil, E. C., Behera, R. K. &#x00026; Tosha, T. Ferritins for chemistry and for life. <italic>Coord. Chem. Rev.</italic><bold>257</bold>, 579&#x02013;586 (2013).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23470857</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arosio</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Adelman</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name><surname>Drysdale</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ferritin heterogeniety - further evidence for heteropolymers</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>1978</year><volume>253</volume><fpage>4451</fpage><lpage>4458</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0021-9258(17)34741-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">659425</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Arosio, P., Adelman, T. G. &#x00026; Drysdale, J. W. Ferritin heterogeniety - further evidence for heteropolymers. <italic>J. Biol. Chem.</italic><bold>253</bold>, 4451&#x02013;4458 (1978).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">659425</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Levi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A human mitochondrial ferritin encoded by an intronless gene</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2001</year><volume>276</volume><fpage>24437</fpage><lpage>24440</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.C100141200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11323407</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">Levi, S. et al. A human mitochondrial ferritin encoded by an intronless gene. <italic>J. Biol. Chem.</italic><bold>276</bold>, 24437&#x02013;24440 (2001).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11323407</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Guaraldo, M. et al. Characterization of human mitochondrial ferritin promoter: identification of transcription factors and evidences of epigenetic control. <italic>Sci. Rep.</italic>10.1038/srep33432 (2016).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>d&#x02019;Estaintot</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Crystal structure and biochemical properties of the human mitochondrial ferritin and its mutant Ser144Ala</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol.</source><year>2004</year><volume>340</volume><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>293</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jmb.2004.04.036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15201052</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">d&#x02019;Estaintot, B. L. et al. Crystal structure and biochemical properties of the human mitochondrial ferritin and its mutant Ser144Ala. <italic>J. Mol. Biol.</italic><bold>340</bold>, 277&#x02013;293 (2004).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15201052</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Neely</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name><surname>Levi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Arosio</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Connor</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regional and cellular distribution of mitochondrial ferritin in the mouse brain</article-title><source>J. Neurosci. Res.</source><year>2010</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>3133</fpage><lpage>3143</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jnr.22462</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20722075</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Snyder, A. M., Neely, E. B., Levi, S., Arosio, P. &#x00026; Connor, J. R. Regional and cellular distribution of mitochondrial ferritin in the mouse brain. <italic>J. Neurosci. Res.</italic><bold>88</bold>, 3133&#x02013;3143 (2010).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20722075</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Santambrogio</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mitochondrial ferritin expression in adult mouse tissues</article-title><source>J. Histochem. Cytochem.</source><year>2007</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>1129</fpage><lpage>1137</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1369/jhc.7A7273.2007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17625226</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">Santambrogio, P. et al. Mitochondrial ferritin expression in adult mouse tissues. <italic>J. Histochem. Cytochem.</italic><bold>55</bold>, 1129&#x02013;1137 (2007).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17625226</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gao, G. F. &#x00026; Chang, Y. Z. Mitochondrial ferritin in the regulation of brain iron homeostasis and neurodegenerative diseases. <italic>Front. Pharmacol.</italic>10.3389/fphar.2014.00019 (2014).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mendsaikhan, A., Takeuchi, S., Walker, D. G. &#x00026; Tooyama, I. Differences in gene expression profiles and phenotypes of differentiated SH-SY5Y neurons stably overexpressing mitochondrial ferritin. <italic>Front. Mol. Neurosci.</italic>10.3389/fnmol.2018.00470 (2019).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR27" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Popescu</surname><given-names>BFG</given-names></name><name><surname>Pickering</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name><name><surname>George</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><name><surname>Nichol</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The chemical form of mitochondrial iron in Friedreich&#x02019;s ataxia</article-title><source>J. Inorg. Biochem.</source><year>2007</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>957</fpage><lpage>966</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jinorgbio.2007.03.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17475338</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27" publication-type="journal">Popescu, B. F. G., Pickering, I. J., George, G. N. &#x00026; Nichol, H. The chemical form of mitochondrial iron in Friedreich&#x02019;s ataxia. <italic>J. Inorg. Biochem.</italic><bold>101</bold>, 957&#x02013;966 (2007).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17475338</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR28" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bou-Abdallah</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Santambrogio</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Levi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Arosio</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Chasteen</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Unique iron binding and oxidation properties of human mitochondrial ferritin: A comparative analysis with human H-chain ferritin</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol.</source><year>2005</year><volume>347</volume><fpage>543</fpage><lpage>554</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jmb.2005.01.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15755449</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28" publication-type="journal">Bou-Abdallah, F., Santambrogio, P., Levi, S., Arosio, P. &#x00026; Chasteen, N. D. Unique iron binding and oxidation properties of human mitochondrial ferritin: A comparative analysis with human H-chain ferritin. <italic>J. Mol. Biol.</italic><bold>347</bold>, 543&#x02013;554 (2005).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15755449</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR29" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Direct spectroscopic and kinetic evidence for the involvement of a peroxodiferric intermediate during the ferroxidase reaction in fast ferritin mineralization</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>1998</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>9871</fpage><lpage>9876</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/bi980847w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9665690</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29" publication-type="journal">Pereira, A. S. et al. Direct spectroscopic and kinetic evidence for the involvement of a peroxodiferric intermediate during the ferroxidase reaction in fast ferritin mineralization. <italic>Biochemistry</italic><bold>37</bold>, 9871&#x02013;9876 (1998).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9665690</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR30" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Reaction of O<sub>2</sub> with a diiron protein generates a mixed-valent Fe<sup>2+</sup>/Fe<sup>3+</sup> center and peroxide</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2019</year><volume>116</volume><fpage>2058</fpage><lpage>2067</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1809913116</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30659147</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30" publication-type="journal">Bradley, J. M. et al. Reaction of O<sub>2</sub> with a diiron protein generates a mixed-valent Fe<sup>2+</sup>/Fe<sup>3+</sup> center and peroxide. <italic>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</italic><bold>116</bold>, 2058&#x02013;2067 (2019).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30659147</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Yeh, C. C. G., Mokkawes, T., Bradley, J. M., Le Brun, N. E. &#x00026; De Visser, S. P. Second coordination sphere effects on the mechanistic pathways for dioxygen activation by a ferritin: involvement of a Tyr radical and the identification of a cation binding site. <italic>Chembiochem</italic>10.1002/cbic.202200257 (2022).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR32" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baaghil</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Brun</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Core formation in Escherichia coli bacterioferritin requires a functional</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>2003</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>14047</fpage><lpage>14056</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/bi035253u</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14636073</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32" publication-type="journal">Baaghil, S., Lewin, A., Moore, G. R. &#x00026; Le Brun, N. E. Core formation in Escherichia coli bacterioferritin requires a functional. <italic>Biochemistry</italic><bold>42</bold>, 14047&#x02013;14056 (2003).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14636073</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR33" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sc<sup>3+</sup>-promoted O-O bond cleavage of a (mu-1,2-peroxo)diiron(III) species formed from an Iron(II) precursor and O<sub>2</sub> to generate a complex with an Fe<sub>2</sub>(IV)(mu-O)<sub>2</sub> Core</article-title><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source><year>2020</year><volume>142</volume><fpage>4285</fpage><lpage>4297</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jacs.9b12081</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32017545</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR33" publication-type="journal">Banerjee, S. et al. Sc<sup>3+</sup>-promoted O-O bond cleavage of a (mu-1,2-peroxo)diiron(III) species formed from an Iron(II) precursor and O<sub>2</sub> to generate a complex with an Fe<sub>2</sub>(IV)(mu-O)<sub>2</sub> Core. <italic>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</italic><bold>142</bold>, 4285&#x02013;4297 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32017545</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR34" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A short Fe-Fe distance in peroxodiferric ferritin: control of Fe substrate versus cofactor decay?</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2000</year><volume>287</volume><fpage>122</fpage><lpage>125</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.287.5450.122</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10615044</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR34" publication-type="journal">Hwang, J. et al. A short Fe-Fe distance in peroxodiferric ferritin: control of Fe substrate versus cofactor decay? <italic>Science</italic><bold>287</bold>, 122&#x02013;125 (2000).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10615044</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR35" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moenne-Loccoz</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The ferroxidase reaction of ferritin reveals a diferric mu-1,2 bridging peroxide intermediate in common with other O<sub>2</sub>-activating non-heme diiron proteins</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>1999</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>5290</fpage><lpage>5295</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/bi990095l</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10220314</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR35" publication-type="journal">Moenne-Loccoz, P. et al. The ferroxidase reaction of ferritin reveals a diferric mu-1,2 bridging peroxide intermediate in common with other O<sub>2</sub>-activating non-heme diiron proteins. <italic>Biochemistry</italic><bold>38</bold>, 5290&#x02013;5295 (1999).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10220314</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zhao, Z. W., Treffry, A., Quail, M. A., Guest, J. R. &#x00026; Harrison, P. M. Catalytic iron(II) oxidation in the non-haem ferritin of Escherichia coli: the early intermediate is not an iron tyrosinate. <italic>J. Chem. Soc. Dalton Trans.</italic><bold>21</bold>, 3977&#x02013;3978 (1997).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR37" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Three aromatic residues are required for electron transfer during iron mineralization in bacterioferritin</article-title><source>Angew. Chem. Int. Ed.</source><year>2015</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>14763</fpage><lpage>14767</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/anie.201507486</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR37" publication-type="journal">Bradley, J. M. et al. Three aromatic residues are required for electron transfer during iron mineralization in bacterioferritin. <italic>Angew. Chem. Int. Ed.</italic><bold>54</bold>, 14763&#x02013;14767 (2015).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR38" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ebrahimi</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hagedoorn</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hagen</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A conserved tyrosine in ferritin is a molecular capacitor</article-title><source>Chembiochem</source><year>2013</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1123</fpage><lpage>1133</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cbic.201300149</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23737293</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR38" publication-type="journal">Ebrahimi, K. H., Hagedoorn, P. L. &#x00026; Hagen, W. R. A conserved tyrosine in ferritin is a molecular capacitor. <italic>Chembiochem</italic><bold>14</bold>, 1123&#x02013;1133 (2013).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23737293</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR39" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Structural, EPR, and M&#x000f6;ssbauer characterization of (mu-alkoxo)(mu-carboxylato)diiron(II,III) model complexes for the active sites of mixed-valent diiron enzymes</article-title><source>Inorg. Chem.</source><year>2012</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>2917</fpage><lpage>2929</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ic2021726</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22360600</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR39" publication-type="journal">Li, F. F. et al. Structural, EPR, and M&#x000f6;ssbauer characterization of (mu-alkoxo)(mu-carboxylato)diiron(II,III) model complexes for the active sites of mixed-valent diiron enzymes. <italic>Inorg. Chem.</italic><bold>51</bold>, 2917&#x02013;2929 (2012).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22360600</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR40" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tatur</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hagen</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The dinuclear iron-oxo ferroxidase center of Pyrococcus furiosus ferritin is a stable prosthetic group with unexpectedly high reduction potentials</article-title><source>FEBS Lett.</source><year>2005</year><volume>579</volume><fpage>4729</fpage><lpage>4732</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.febslet.2005.07.045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16107254</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR40" publication-type="journal">Tatur, J. &#x00026; Hagen, W. R. The dinuclear iron-oxo ferroxidase center of Pyrococcus furiosus ferritin is a stable prosthetic group with unexpectedly high reduction potentials. <italic>FEBS Lett.</italic><bold>579</bold>, 4729&#x02013;4732 (2005).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16107254</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR41" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ciambellotti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Iron binding in the ferroxidase site of human mitochondrial Ferritin</article-title><source>Chem. Eur. J.</source><year>2021</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>14690</fpage><lpage>14701</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/chem.202102270</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34343376</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR41" publication-type="journal">Ciambellotti, S. et al. Iron binding in the ferroxidase site of human mitochondrial Ferritin. <italic>Chem. Eur. J.</italic><bold>27</bold>, 14690&#x02013;14701 (2021).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34343376</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR42" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kudin</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Augustynek</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lehmann</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kovacs</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunz</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The contribution of thioredoxin-2 reductase and glutathione peroxidase to H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> detoxification of rat brain mitochondria</article-title><source>Biochim. Biophys. Acta-Bioenerg.</source><year>2012</year><volume>1817</volume><fpage>1901</fpage><lpage>1906</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbabio.2012.02.023</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR42" publication-type="journal">Kudin, A. P., Augustynek, B., Lehmann, A. K., Kovacs, R. &#x00026; Kunz, W. S. The contribution of thioredoxin-2 reductase and glutathione peroxidase to H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> detoxification of rat brain mitochondria. <italic>Biochim. Biophys. Acta-Bioenerg.</italic><bold>1817</bold>, 1901&#x02013;1906 (2012).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR43" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wofford</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Bolaji</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Dziuba</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Outten</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindahl</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence that a respiratory shield in Escherichia coli protects a low-molecular-mass Fe(II) pool from O<sub>2</sub>-dependent oxidation</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2019</year><volume>294</volume><fpage>50</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.RA118.005233</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30337367</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR43" publication-type="journal">Wofford, J. D., Bolaji, N., Dziuba, N., Outten, F. W. &#x00026; Lindahl, P. A. Evidence that a respiratory shield in Escherichia coli protects a low-molecular-mass Fe(II) pool from O<sub>2</sub>-dependent oxidation. <italic>J. Biol. Chem.</italic><bold>294</bold>, 50&#x02013;62 (2019).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30337367</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR44" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wofford</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindahl</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mitochondrial iron-sulfur cluster activity and cytosolic iron regulate iron traffic in Saccharomyces cerevisiae</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2015</year><volume>290</volume><fpage>26968</fpage><lpage>26977</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M115.676668</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26306041</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR44" publication-type="journal">Wofford, J. D. &#x00026; Lindahl, P. A. Mitochondrial iron-sulfur cluster activity and cytosolic iron regulate iron traffic in Saccharomyces cerevisiae. <italic>J. Biol. Chem.</italic><bold>290</bold>, 26968&#x02013;26977 (2015).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26306041</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR45" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jezek</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hlavata</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mitochondria in homeostasis of reactive oxygen species in cell, tissues, and organism</article-title><source>Int. J. Biochem. Cell Biol.</source><year>2005</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>2478</fpage><lpage>2503</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biocel.2005.05.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16103002</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR45" publication-type="journal">Jezek, P. &#x00026; Hlavata, L. Mitochondria in homeostasis of reactive oxygen species in cell, tissues, and organism. <italic>Int. J. Biochem. Cell Biol.</italic><bold>37</bold>, 2478&#x02013;2503 (2005).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16103002</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR46" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bauminger</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Iron Incorporation into ferritins - evidence for the transfer of monomeric Fe(III) between ferritin molecules and for the formation of an unusual mineral in the ferritin of Escherichia coli</article-title><source>Biochem. J.</source><year>1994</year><volume>302</volume><fpage>813</fpage><lpage>820</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/bj3020813</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7945207</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR46" publication-type="journal">Bauminger, E. R. et al. Iron Incorporation into ferritins - evidence for the transfer of monomeric Fe(III) between ferritin molecules and for the formation of an unusual mineral in the ferritin of Escherichia coli. <italic>Biochem. J.</italic><bold>302</bold>, 813&#x02013;820 (1994).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7945207</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR47" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Franzen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghiladi</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Reeder</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Svistunenko</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Compound ES of dehaloperoxidase decays via two alternative pathways depending on the conformation of the distal histidine</article-title><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source><year>2010</year><volume>132</volume><fpage>17501</fpage><lpage>17510</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ja106620q</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21090708</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR47" publication-type="journal">Thompson, M. K., Franzen, S., Ghiladi, R. A., Reeder, B. J. &#x00026; Svistunenko, D. A. Compound ES of dehaloperoxidase decays via two alternative pathways depending on the conformation of the distal histidine. <italic>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</italic><bold>132</bold>, 17501&#x02013;17510 (2010).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21090708</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article>