<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Carbon Balance Manag</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Carbon Balance Manag</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Carbon Balance and Management</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1750-0680</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer International Publishing</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Cham</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40411694</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12102928</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">297</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13021-025-00297-1</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>From linear to circular: the impact of economic policies and technological innovations on greenhouse gas emissions in the Netherlands</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-0672-9025</contrib-id><name><surname>Abbas</surname><given-names>Qamar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3807-1483</contrib-id><name><surname>Imran</surname><given-names>Muhammad</given-names></name><address><email>imran.buic@bahria.edu.pk</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sattar</surname><given-names>Abdul</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/021cj6z65</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.410645.2</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0455 0905</institution-id><institution>School of Business, </institution><institution>Hengxing University Qingdao, </institution></institution-wrap>Qingdao, China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/02v8d7770</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.444787.c</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0607 2662</institution-id><institution>Bahria Business School, </institution><institution>Bahria University Islamabad, </institution></institution-wrap>Islamabad, Pakistan </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>24</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>24</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>12</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>20</volume><elocation-id>11</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">The Netherlands, recognized as a leader in promoting circular economy principles, is actively implementing laws, incentives, and public&#x02013;private collaborations to reduce raw material consumption by minimizing extraction and encouraging sharing and reuse. Emphasizing the durability and extended use of materials and goods is crucial in this transition. This study investigates the long-term and causal impacts of circular economy practices, technological innovation, environmental tax policies, economic instability, and industrialization on greenhouse gas (GHG) emissions in the Netherlands, covering the period from the first quarter of 2010 to the fourth quarter of 2022. Employing advanced econometric techniques, including the bounds test of co-integration, autoregressive distributed lag models, wavelet coherence analysis, and gradual shift causality tests, the study reveals that circular economy practices, technological advancements, and environmental taxation significantly reduce GHG emissions in both the short-run and the&#x000a0;long-run. Conversely, economic instability and industrialization are found to contribute positively to GHG emissions. The wavelet coherence analysis further highlights the substantial interplay between GHG emissions and the independent variables studied. Based on these findings, the study underscores the need for the Netherlands to intensify efforts in reducing GHG emissions, curbing the use of virgin materials in construction, and investing in recycling technologies to advance its circular economy goals.</p></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Circular economy</kwd><kwd>Greenhouse gases emissions</kwd><kwd>Technological innovation</kwd><kwd>Environmental Tax Policy</kwd><kwd>Wavelet coherence analysis</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Springer Nature Switzerland AG 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Each year, approximately 100 billion tons of resources are extracted and supplied to the global economy, encompassing a diverse range of materials such as metals, minerals, fossil fuels, and organic matter derived from plants and animals. However, according to the circulatory gap report (2020), only a mere 8.6% of these resources are repurposed or recycled [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. This unsustainable and excessive consumption has severe consequences for human health, biodiversity, and the overall well-being of our planet. As a result, the urgency to transition from traditional linear economic models&#x02014;characterized by the use-and-dispose paradigm&#x02014;to a circular economy is increasingly evident [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>].</p><p id="Par3">The circular economy is designed with the primary objectives of minimizing waste and pollution, extending the lifecycle of resources and products, and allowing natural systems to regenerate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. A significant driver of the need for a circular economy is the escalating levels of GHG in the Earth&#x02019;s atmosphere, which are already causing profound changes in our climate. Solid waste management practices contribute directly to GHG emissions, with incineration facilities releasing nitrous oxide and landfills generating methane as waste decomposes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. In this context, the circular economy presents an opportunity to optimize the use of products, materials, and natural resources while simultaneously transforming waste into valuable inputs and reducing overall waste production [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. Moreover, in the face of an escalating ecological deficit, it is imperative that humanity expedite its efforts to achieve the Sustainable Development Goals (SDGs) to avert irreversible environmental degradation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. The urgency of this transition requires transformative actions across sectors, aligning economic, social, and environmental objectives to create a resilient, low-impact global framework that ensures long-term sustainability for future generations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>].</p><p id="Par4">The focus of this research is the Netherlands, a country selected due to its relatively high per capita GHG emissions compared to other European nations. In 2018, the Netherlands recorded per capita emissions of 11 tons of CO<sub>2</sub>, a figure that surpasses the European average by over 30% (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). When compared to countries with similar per capita GDPs, such as Austria, Denmark, France, Italy, Norway, Sweden, and the United Kingdom (UK), whose emissions range from 5 to 8 tons, the Netherlands&#x02019; emissions are significantly higher [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Despite this, the Dutch economy has made strides in reducing its carbon intensity, achieving a 29% reduction between 2005 and 2019, albeit at a slightly slower pace than the European Union (EU) average. Notably, the energy sector in the Netherlands achieved a 15% reduction in emissions during this period, driven in part by policy measures such as the introduction of carbon pricing. The Netherlands supports the EU climate goals, which include reaching net-zero GHG emissions by 2050. By 2030, the EU "Fit for 55" package seeks to reduce GHG emissions by 55% from 1990 levels, which will have an impact on national policy.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn1">1</xref><fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>GHG emissions (metric tons per capita) in&#x000a0;the Netherlands.</p><p>Source: Eurostat (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://ec.europa.eu/eurostat">https://ec.europa.eu/eurostat</ext-link>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13021_2025_297_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p id="Par6">Recognizing the critical need to address its elevated GHG emissions, the Netherlands took a pioneering step in 2016 by launching the government-wide program &#x02018;A Circular Economy in the Netherlands by 2050.&#x02019; This initiative not only demonstrated the country&#x02019;s commitment to reducing emissions but also played a crucial role in raising public awareness and fostering a culture of sustainability. The Netherlands&#x02019; proactive approach aligns with the growing recognition of the circular economy as a viable strategy for achieving global climate goals, particularly the targets outlined in the Paris Agreement [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">95</xref>]. Moreover, the Netherlands has established extended producer responsibility (EPR) for a wide range of items, including packaging, electronics, and batteries. These systems hold manufacturers responsible for the recycling and reuse of items at the end of their lifespan [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>].</p><p id="Par7">The Netherlands has set ambitious targets to reduce GHG emissions through a combination of policy initiatives and legislative measures. By 2023, the country aims for at least 16% of its energy production to be derived from renewable sources. Furthermore, GHG emissions are projected to decrease by 49% by 2030 compared to 1990 levels, with a more aggressive target of reducing CO<sub>2</sub> emissions by at least 55% by the same year. These milestones are part of a broader strategy to achieve a climate-neutral economy by 2050, culminating in a remarkable 95% reduction in GHG emissions from 1990 levels. These targets underscore the Netherlands&#x02019; commitment to mitigating climate change and transitioning toward a sustainable future (Ministry of Infrastructure and Water Management &#x00026; Ministry of Economic Affairs, 2016).</p><p id="Par8">A critical component of this strategy is the circular economy, which emphasizes the reuse and recycling of products and materials within the economy for as long as possible, thereby minimizing waste and reducing the demand for new resources [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref>]. In this study, the circular material use rate serves as a proxy for measuring the effectiveness and progress of the circular economy, following the methodologies of Hondroyiannis et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>] and Neves and Marques [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>]. The circular economy fundamentally differs from the traditional linear economic model, which operates on a &#x02018;take-make-dispose&#x02019; basis. Instead, it focuses on sustainable economic development by maximizing the reuse of materials and reducing environmental impacts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR105">105</xref>].</p><p id="Par9">The Netherlands is among the leading nations in advancing circular economy principles, alongside the UK, Belgium, Spain, France, Italy, and Germany [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>]. The Netherlands&#x02019; leadership in this area is well-established, having initiated circular economy activities as early as 2011. By 2013, the country had produced a pivotal report titled &#x0201c;Opportunities for a Circular Economy in the Netherlands&#x0201d; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>], marking a significant milestone in its commitment to this economic model. Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> illustrates the circularity rate of the Dutch economy over the selected period, highlighting the progress made and the potential for further improvement.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Circular material use rate (annual %) in&#x000a0;the Netherlands.</p><p>Source: Eurostat (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://ec.europa.eu/eurostat">https://ec.europa.eu/eurostat</ext-link>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13021_2025_297_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p><p id="Par10">The implementation of targeted strategies across four critical sectors&#x02014;consumer goods, construction, polymers, manufacturing, and biomass and food&#x02014;could potentially triple the national circularity rate. Such progress would be instrumental in helping the Netherlands achieve its goal of a fully circular economy by 2050 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. Moreover, the shift to a circular economy presents opportunities for stimulating economic development and creating new jobs through innovation and sustainable practices. Recognizing these benefits, the Netherlands launched a nationwide initiative in 2016, focusing on reducing the reliance on natural resource imports and enhancing sovereignty over raw material supplies. This approach not only contributes to environmental sustainability but also ensures greater security and resilience in the supply chain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">86</xref>].</p><p id="Par11">This study aims to strengthen our knowledge of the three main processes via which the circular economy affects GHG emissions in the Netherlands. First, circular economy techniques have a lot of promise in areas like transportation, the built environment, and food systems. They do this by reducing the need for new goods and virgin raw materials, which lowers emissions throughout manufacturing. Further potential to reduce emissions is provided by consumption-side policies and innovative product design, and operational energy savings may be realized in sectors like transportation and heating. Second, these tactics solve material management issues in mineral supply and trash from decommissioned technology while easing the shift to renewable energy sources like solar, wind, and electric cars. Third, while less studied, circular economy techniques may also help with climate adaptation by increasing flood resistance, promoting soil health, and delaying environmental deterioration. Although mitigation has been the main emphasis, a more thorough approach is required to properly grasp the potential of circular economy methods in climate adaptation. The study makes several key contributions to the existing literature. First, it focuses on the Netherlands, a leading European nation in the circular economy, and fills a gap in the research by using Dutch data to examine the impact of the circular economy on GHG emissions. This study investigates the relationship between GHG emissions and variables such as the circular economy, technological innovation, environmental taxes, economic instability, and industrialization in the Netherlands. Its primary objective is to provide insights into the policy implications for emission reduction initiatives in the Netherlands, particularly by exploring the interrelationships among these variables and their influence on GHG emissions. Second, the research employs the autoregressive distributed lag (ARDL) bounds test to examine the cointegration relationship between GHG emissions and specific variables, focusing on the long-run equilibrium. Additionally, the study uses Wavelet Coherence Analysis (WCA) to investigate the time&#x02013;frequency dependence between GHG emissions and multiple factors, offering a novel approach in this context. As far as we know, no previous research has utilized WCA to explore the relationship and causality between GHG emissions and factors such as the circular economy, technological innovation, environmental taxes, economic instability, and industrialization. WCA provides a continuous representation of time series in the time&#x02013;frequency domain, enabling a more profound understanding of these relationships.</p><p id="Par12">The structure of this paper is as follows: "<xref rid="Sec2" ref-type="sec">Literature review</xref>" section provides a comprehensive review of the literature; "<xref rid="Sec3" ref-type="sec">Research methodology</xref>" section discusses the research methodology; "<xref rid="Sec4" ref-type="sec">Results and discussions</xref>" section presents the main results and discusses their implications; and "<xref rid="Sec5" ref-type="sec">Conclusions and policy implications</xref>" section concludes the research, offering recommendations for future studies and policy considerations.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Literature review</title><p id="Par13">To provide a comprehensive understanding of the complex interplay between economic activities, environmental policies, and technological advancements in the context of climate change, this literature review delves into the multifaceted impact of human activities on the environment.</p><sec id="Sec3"><title>Human activities and environmental impacts</title><p id="Par14">Human activities are intricately linked to both the exacerbation and mitigation of climate change, creating a complex and interconnected dynamic that shapes environmental outcomes. On one hand, the industrial and residential actions that drive economic growth and societal development have led to significant environmental degradation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>]. This includes pollution across various forms&#x02014;air, CO<sub>2</sub>, water, and light&#x02014;coupled with the heightened consumption of fossil fuels and the generation of GHG emissions. These processes not only contribute to global warming but also result in the accumulation of residential and industrial waste, which presents ongoing challenges in terms of effective waste management and environmental sustainability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref>].</p><p id="Par15">This narrative is not entirely one of environmental decline. Human activities have also sparked positive environmental changes, particularly through initiatives like recycling and waste sorting [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>]. Recycling, for example, has emerged as a critical response to the environmental pressures brought about by mass manufacturing and the widespread use of materials like plastics throughout the twentieth century. Sustainable development goals can be achieved through innovation by fostering the development and implementation of eco-friendly technologies and practices that reduce environmental impact while promoting economic growth [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. By prioritizing innovations in clean energy, resource efficiency, and sustainable production, green innovation aligns economic progress with environmental preservation, helping to meet global sustainability targets [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>] and COP27 targets [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94">94</xref>]. The benefits of recycling extend beyond merely reducing waste; it conserves valuable resources, curtails environmental degradation, and fosters a more sustainable interaction between human activities and the natural world [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>].</p><p id="Par16">In exploring the broader implications of these practices, Stahel [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">90</xref>] offers a profound analysis of circularity, positioning it as a fundamental strategy for achieving long-term economic and environmental sustainability. The concept of circularity&#x02014;where resources are reused and repurposed to minimize waste&#x02014;has garnered significant academic interest as a viable approach to restore both economic and ecological balance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. However, the bulk of the existing literature has predominantly concentrated on theoretical explorations of circularity, often neglecting empirical, data-driven analyses. This gap is largely due to the scarcity of comprehensive data at both the industrial and household levels, which limits the ability to fully assess the practical implications of circularity in real-world contexts.</p><p id="Par17">Nonetheless, some empirical studies have made important strides in this area. For instance, Slorach et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">89</xref>] conducted a thorough investigation into food waste treatment in the UK, demonstrating how circular economy principles can drive both environmental and economic sustainability. Their research highlights that employing anaerobic digestion for food waste not only mitigates environmental pollution but also enhances the quality of life and offers substantial economic advantages. Similarly, Gallego-Schmid et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>] examined the role of circular economy practices within the European Union&#x02019;s construction industry&#x02014;a sector known for its significant contribution to atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> and GHG emissions. Their findings underscore the crucial role of using recycled materials in improving resource efficiency and reducing environmental disparities across different EU member states.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Circular economy and GHG emissions</title><p id="Par18">Recycling and waste management practices have emerged as pivotal strategies in the global effort to combat climate change, offering significant environmental benefits that extend beyond mere waste reduction. Cudjoe et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>] underscore the crucial role that recycling plays in this context, highlighting its ability to substantially mitigate CO<sub>2</sub> and methane emissions through the effective recycling of materials like steel, nonferrous metals, plastic, and paper. Their research illustrates the tangible impact that such practices can have on reducing GHG emissions, positioning recycling as a cornerstone of sustainable environmental management.</p><p id="Par19">However, the narrative surrounding circular economy practices is not without its complexities. Li et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>] offer a nuanced perspective, examining the trade dynamics between China and Nigeria and the potential of the circular economy to reduce energy intensity in countries with prominent mining and extractive industries. Despite improvements in energy efficiency, their findings reveal a critical disconnect: the anticipated reduction in CO<sub>2</sub> emissions did not materialize, underscoring the challenges and limitations of circular economy strategies in sectors with high energy demands. Similarly, energy security is required for countries (such as France, Germany, Japan, the United States, and the UK) to continue their sustainable energy policies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Combustible renewables, waste, and modern renewables significantly contribute to environmental sustainability and the reduction of ecological footprints [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>]. Their&#x000a0;contribution highlights the need for a more tailored approach to implementing circular economy practices, one that accounts for the specific characteristics and constraints of different industries.</p><p id="Par20">Adding another layer to this discussion, Bayar et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]&#x000a0;investigated the effects of renewable energy adoption and recycling waste management on environmental sustainability across EU member states. Their analysis, spanning from 2004 to 2017, yielded surprising results: no direct causality was found between recycling rates, renewable energy usage, and reductions in CO<sub>2</sub> emissions. Similarly, Caglar et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>] indicate that solid waste management has a positive relationship with environmental quality and helps to achieve SDG-11 goals. This finding challenges the conventional wisdom that these practices are straightforward solutions to environmental challenges, suggesting instead that a more complex array of factors&#x02014;including technological innovation, policy frameworks, and economic conditions&#x02014;may play a more critical role in driving substantial emissions reductions.</p><p id="Par21">Liu et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>] examine the development of China&#x02019;s plastic recycling sector, emphasizing the intricate interactions between commercial, regulatory, and technical elements that affect the decrease of GHG emissions. The necessity for more accurate measurement of emission reductions via circular economy methods is also emphasized by Gallego-Schmid et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>], who call for a sophisticated methodology that considers the circumstances and trade-offs involved. The transition of Denmark&#x02019;s waste management industry from a linear to a circular economy is examined by Magazzino et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>], who highlight the policy implications for lowering emissions. The potential of circular economy techniques to mitigate climate change internationally is further supported by research from 29 European nations presented by Hailemariam and Erdiaw-Kwasie [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>], which demonstrates a substantial association between the advancement of the circular economy and lower CO<sub>2</sub> emissions.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Technological innovation, environmental tax, economic instability, and industrialization</title><p id="Par22">Technological innovation is another critical variable that influences the relationship between the circular economy and GHG emissions. Technological advancements have the potential to either increase or decrease global GHG emissions, depending on how they are implemented. Following the Environmental Kuznets Curve (EKC) theory, emissions first increase as economies expand and industrialize, but once a certain degree of economic development and innovation is attained, emissions eventually fall as cleaner technologies and more effective production techniques are adopted. Houston and Reay [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>] noted that while technological innovation is a growing source of emissions from energy and manufacturing sectors throughout its lifecycle phases, it also offers the potential to significantly reduce emissions in sectors like transportation by circumventing traditional energy-intensive processes. In order to accelerate the adoption of sustainable technologies that eventually reduce emissions, the &#x02018;Diffusion of Innovations Theory&#x02019; highlights the need for policy, market incentives, and social acceptability. It also explains how innovative technologies spread throughout sectors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. Using the&#x000a0;Wavelet Quantile-on-Quantile Regression (WQQR) approach, Ozkan et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>] indicated that green technologies mitigate CO<sub>2</sub> emissions in Germany for the period of 1974 to 2019. Malmodin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>] further suggested that technological innovation can have both positive and negative effects on GHG emissions. Appiah-Otoo et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>] demonstrated that technological innovation enhances environmental sustainability in countries with high innovation quality but can have detrimental effects in nations with lower innovation quality. Their causality study revealed a two-way causal relationship between technological innovation and CO<sub>2</sub> emissions in countries with high and moderate innovation quality, but only a one-way causal relationship from CO<sub>2</sub> emissions to technological innovation in countries with poor innovation quality. Amari et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>] found that greater technological readiness, use, and intensity can reduce CO<sub>2</sub> emissions and energy consumption, thereby improving environmental sustainability in lower- and lower-middle-income countries.</p><p id="Par23">Environmental taxes are another important factor in the circular economy-GHG emissions nexus. In this context, the &#x02018;Pigovian Taxation&#x02019; is foundational, positing that environmental taxes, such as carbon taxes, internalize the external costs of pollution by making carbon-intensive activities more expensive, thus encouraging businesses and consumers to reduce emissions and adopt cleaner alternatives [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. The effectiveness of environmental taxes, including CO<sub>2</sub> and energy taxes, in reducing GHG emissions has been widely recognized. Ghazouani et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>] highlighted the effectiveness of environmental taxes and the promotion of cleaner energy sources in reducing pollution in nine leading European countries. Similarly, Hsu et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>] emphasized the crucial role of environmental taxes in mitigating GHG emissions in China. Their study revealed that environmental taxes could significantly reduce haze pollution, particularly PM2.5 levels, in China. Do&#x0011f;an et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>] discussed the potential benefits of environmental taxes in reducing the impact of energy consumption and natural resource usage while promoting renewable energy sources. These measures positively affect the environment and help mitigate GHG emissions. Wolde-Rufael and Mulat-Weldemeskel [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98">98</xref>] also found a significantly negative association between environmental taxes and CO<sub>2</sub> emissions across 20 European countries. Moreover, to provide a double dividend of economic and environmental advantages, &#x02018;Environmental Tax Reform&#x02019; theory goes one step further and proposes that the money collected from environmental taxes be reinvested in renewable energy, green technology, or tax breaks elsewhere, as suggested by Ekins et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>].</p><p id="Par24">Economic instability is another variable considered in the relationship between the circular economy and GHG emissions. The study used bank non-performing loans (NPLs) as a proxy to measure economic instability. Economic instability can negatively impact a nation&#x02019;s overall economic development, leading to business difficulties, reduced investments, and fewer employment opportunities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98">98</xref>]. Economic stability is necessary to allocate funds to mitigate GHG emissions, as Emre Caglar et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>] argue that improving environmental quality requires countries to prioritize development investments, particularly by increasing their research and development budgets. This investment is crucial for advancing the transition to a low-carbon economy through innovation in sustainable technologies and practices. Moreover, as suggested by Caglar et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>], economic well-being enhances income quality&#x000a0;and eventually leads to improved environmental outcomes. As income rises, the capacity for investing in cleaner technologies and sustainable practices increases, promoting environmental quality. This also supports the&#x000a0;EKC hypothesis.</p><p id="Par25">Finally, industrialization is a key variable in examining the link between the circular economy and GHG emissions. Industrialization has been largely acknowledged as a major catalyst of climate change due to the significant CO<sub>2</sub> emissions and other GHG released into the atmosphere as a result of human activity during the Industrial Revolution. Aslam et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>] illustrated the positive and bidirectional causal relationship between industrialization and CO<sub>2</sub> emissions in China. Azam et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>] found that industrialization leads to an increase in environmental pollution through GHG emissions. Moreover, energy production, transportation, industry, agriculture, and construction are some of the key industries that contribute significantly to emissions as a result of industrialization. Due to its reliance on fossil fuels, the energy industry is a significant emitter, and transportation also contributes through the use of fuel in cars and airplanes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Research methodology</title><sec id="Sec7"><title>Theoretical framework</title><p id="Par26">The linear economy, characterized by its "take-make-dispose" model, relies on the extraction of raw materials, production, consumption, and disposal of products, leading to the depletion of natural resources and environmental degradation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>]. This traditional model focuses on financial gains and consumer convenience, often disregarding the long-term ecological consequences, with products designed for single use and waste generation. In contrast, the circular economy offers a paradigm shift by promoting resource efficiency and minimizing waste through practices like recycling, reusing, and remanufacturing. Transitioning to a circular economy, however, requires overcoming challenges such as technological limitations, economic barriers, and shifts in consumer behavior [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>], all of which must be addressed to ensure successful implementation.</p><p id="Par27">The circular economy emphasizes sustainability by optimizing resource use, reducing waste, and minimizing emissions from resource extraction and processing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]. This model involves innovative approaches to maintain environmental balance and addresses not only ecological concerns but also social factors like human well-being [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Implementing a circular economy requires a collaborative effort among governments, corporations, and consumers to drive regulatory frameworks, innovative business practices, and sustainable consumption behaviors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>]. Ultimately, the transition to a circular economy offers a more sustainable alternative to the linear model [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>], fostering long-term ecological balance while reducing environmental impacts (see Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> for a comparison of linear and circular economies).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Linear economy vs circular economy. <bold>a</bold> Linear economy, <bold>b</bold> circular economy</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13021_2025_297_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Model specifications</title><p id="Par28">In alignment with the methodologies employed by Shahzad et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref>] and Wang et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">96</xref>], our study utilizes a modified model to investigate the impact of circular economy practices on GHG emissions. While previous studies predominantly focused on CO<sub>2</sub> emissions as the dependent variable, our analysis expands this scope by using GHG emissions to capture a more comprehensive range of emissions affecting climate change. Additionally, whereas many studies have used waste management metrics to represent circular economy practices, our research adopts the circular material use rate as the primary independent variable. This adjustment allows us to directly evaluate how the extent of material circularity influences overall GHG emissions. The basic model is expressed as Eq.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Equ1" ref-type="disp-formula">1</xref>.<disp-formula id="Equ1"><label>1</label><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e534">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\text{GHG emissions}}_{\text{t}} = \vartheta_{0} + \vartheta_{1} {\text{GHG emissions}}_{{\text{t}} - 1} + \vartheta_{2} {\text{Circular economy}}_{{\text{t}}} + \vartheta_{3} {\text{Technological innovation}}_{{\text{t}}} + \vartheta_{4} {\text{Environmental tax}}_{{\text{t}}} + \vartheta_{5} {\text{Economic instability}}_{{\text{t}}} + \vartheta_{6} {\text{Industralization}}_{{\text{t}}} + \varepsilon_{{\text{t}}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="d33e540" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>GHG emissions</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003d1;</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003d1;</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>GHG emissions</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003d1;</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Circular economy</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003d1;</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Technological innovation</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003d1;</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Environmental tax</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003d1;</mml:mi><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Economic instability</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003d1;</mml:mi><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mtext>Industralization</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13021_2025_297_Article_Equ1.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <inline-formula id="IEq1"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e609">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\vartheta_{0}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="d33e614"><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003d1;</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13021_2025_297_Article_IEq1.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> denotes the constant term, whereas <inline-formula id="IEq2"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e620">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\vartheta_{1} , \cdots ,\vartheta_{6}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="d33e625"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003d1;</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x022ef;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003d1;</mml:mi><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13021_2025_297_Article_IEq2.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> represent the parameters that need estimation.</p><p id="Par29">Furthermore, whereas many studies have utilized waste management as an indicator of circular economy practices [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">89</xref>], this study adopts the circular material use rate as the independent variable to more accurately reflect material circularity. The choice of this variable is informed by Wolde-Rufael and Mulat-Weldemeskel [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98">98</xref>], who argue that circular material use rate provides a clearer picture of resource efficiency and recycling efforts.</p><p id="Par30">The dataset employed consists of quarterly observations from the Netherlands, covering the period from 2010Q1 to 2022Q2. To convert annual data into a quarterly frequency, we applied the quadratic match-sum method, as described by Shahbaz et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">84</xref>]. This method ensures a detailed temporal resolution of the data, aligning with practices outlined by Dehghan Shabani and Shahnazi [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. All variables were transformed into their natural logarithmic form, enhancing the accuracy of the analysis and allowing for clear interpretation of the coefficients as elasticities, representing proportional differences in the context of the study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>].</p><p id="Par31">The dependent variable, GHG emissions, is measured in tons per capita and sourced from the Eurostat database. This metric provides a comprehensive view of the total emissions produced by a country, echoing the findings of Magazzino et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>], who highlighted the importance of using comprehensive emission indicators.</p><p id="Par32">This study assesses the impact of circular economy practices by focusing on the circular material use rate, a data source from Eurostat. This rate shows how much recycled materials are put back into the economy as a percentage of all the materials that are used. It shows how well efforts to promote circularity are working to lower our need for new raw materials [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>].</p><p id="Par33">In addition to focusing on the primary variables, this study integrates several control factors to thoroughly examine their potential impact on GHG emissions. The role of technological innovation is captured through the gross value added in the information and communication technologies (ICT) sector, which includes both manufacturing and services. This measure reflects the complex effects of technological advancements: while innovations in manufacturing may contribute to increased emissions due to higher energy consumption [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref>], advancements in services have the potential to enhance efficiency and reduce resource use, as noted by Abbas, et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Similarly, Caglar et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>] demonstrate that environmental quality increases when industries are competitive and technological advancement is high.</p><p id="Par34">We incorporate the influence of environmental tax revenue to evaluate its effect on GHG emissions. Measured as a percentage of total tax and social contribution revenue, this tax aims to incentivize emission reductions by imposing a fee on each ton of GHG and CO<sub>2</sub> emitted. The goal is to encourage more cost-effective abatement measures, thereby aligning with the findings of Ghazouani et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>], who emphasize the role of taxation in driving environmental improvements.</p><p id="Par35">Bank non-performing loans, expressed as a percentage of total loans, serve as a proxy for economic instability. This variable provides insight into how financial stability fluctuations can impact investments in sustainable practices [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103">103</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR104">104</xref>]. The connection between bank loans and emissions illustrates the evolving role of financial institutions in promoting environmentally friendly investments, a trend highlighted by Abbas et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. This variable helps understand how financial disruptions can influence the capacity for green investments and sustainability efforts.</p><p id="Par36">Finally, industrialization is evaluated through the value added in the industrial sector, including construction, as a percentage of GDP. The relationship between industrialization and GHG emissions is multifaceted: early stages of industrial development are often associated with increased emissions due to greater fossil fuel use [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR102">102</xref>].</p><p id="Par37">These considerations are summarized and detailed in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, providing a comprehensive view of the variables and their interconnections within the model.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Variables description</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Variable</th><th align="left">Description</th><th align="left">Units</th><th align="left">Source</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">GHG emissions</td><td align="left">Net greenhouse gas emissions</td><td align="left">Tones per capita</td><td align="left">Eurostat</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Circular economy</td><td align="left">Circular material use rate</td><td align="left">Annual %</td><td align="left">Eurostat</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Technology innovation</td><td align="left">Technological innovation service (gross value added)</td><td align="left">% of the technological innovation sector in gross value added</td><td align="left">Eurostat</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Environmental tax</td><td align="left">Environmental tax revenue</td><td align="left">% of total revenue from taxes and social contributions</td><td align="left">Eurostat</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Economic instability</td><td align="left">Bank non-performing loans</td><td align="left">% of total gross loans</td><td align="left">WDI</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Industrialization</td><td align="left">Industry value added</td><td align="left">% of GDP</td><td align="left">WDI</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Methodological framework</title><p id="Par38">The methodological framework outlines the approach used to analyze the relationship between GHG emissions and the various factors discussed previously. By employing sophisticated econometric techniques, the study aims to ensure robust and reliable results. This framework integrates both primary and control variables, facilitating a comprehensive evaluation of their impacts on environmental outcomes.</p><p id="Par39">This section delineates the econometric methods employed in this study, as illustrated in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Methodological framework</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13021_2025_297_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p><p id="Par40">Unit root tests are fundamental in time series analysis, providing critical insights into the stationarity properties of the data. Stationarity is a key assumption in time series modeling, influencing the accuracy of statistical inferences and forecasts. The primary tests used for detecting unit roots are the Augmented Dickey-Fuller (ADF) test and the Phillips-Perron (PP) test. These tests help researchers understand the temporal behavior of a series and guide the selection of appropriate models for analysis. By identifying unit roots, these tests prevent misleading regression results and ensure that statistical analyses are based on sound assumptions.</p><p id="Par41">The ADF test is defined by the following Eq.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Equ2" ref-type="disp-formula">2</xref>:<disp-formula id="Equ2"><label>2</label><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e804">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\Delta {\text{Y}}_{{\text{t}}} = \beta {\text{D}}_{{\text{t}}} + \tau {\text{Y}}_{{\text{t}} - 1} + \mathop \sum \limits_{{\text{j}} - 1}^{{\text{p}}} \sigma_{{\text{j}}} \Delta {\text{Y}}_{{\text{t}} - {\text{j}}} + \varepsilon_{{\text{t}}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="d33e810" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x00394;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mtext>Y</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mtext>D</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mtext>Y</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo movablelimits="false">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>j</mml:mtext><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>p</mml:mtext></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mtext>j</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x00394;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mtext>Y</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mtext>j</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13021_2025_297_Article_Equ2.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>Where D<sub>t</sub> represents the deterministic term vector, and <inline-formula id="IEq3"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e859">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\upvarepsilon }_{\text{t}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="d33e864"><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003b5;</mml:mi><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13021_2025_297_Article_IEq3.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is the error term. Similarly, the PP test is expressed as in Eq.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Equ3" ref-type="disp-formula">3</xref>:<disp-formula id="Equ3"><label>3</label><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e875">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\Delta {\text{Y}}_{{\text{t}}} = \beta {\text{D}}_{{\text{t}}} + \tau {\text{Y}}_{{\text{t}} - 1} + \varepsilon_{{\text{t}}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="d33e881" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x00394;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mtext>Y</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mtext>D</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mtext>Y</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13021_2025_297_Article_Equ3.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par42">Pesaran et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>] developed the ARDL bounds testing approach, which offers several advantages over traditional cointegration tests, primarily its flexibility in handling series integrated with different orders, whether I(0) or I(1). The ARDL method allows for the derivation of the unrestricted error correction model (ECM), which captures both short-term and long-term dynamics within the data. This advantage&#x000a0;makes it particularly useful even with relatively small sample sizes, producing consistent and reliable results [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. To determine the maximum lag length for each variable, the ARDL approach uses (P&#x02009;+&#x02009;1)<sup>k</sup> regressions, where p is the maximum number of lags and k is the number of variables in the equation. The lag selection criteria are based on the Akaike Information Criterion (AIC) and Schwarz Bayesian Criterion (SBC). The joint F-statistic evaluates the null hypothesis of no cointegration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>].</p><p id="Par43">In the context of this study, the ARDL bounds testing is applied to evaluate the cointegration relationship among GHG emissions and various independent variables. The methodology begins with the inclusion of lagged levels of the independent variables in the ARDL equation and subjecting them to an F-test to determine the presence of a long-run relationship [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. The empirical application of this approach is illustrated by the following Eq.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Equ4" ref-type="disp-formula">4</xref>:<disp-formula id="Equ4"><label>4</label><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e934">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\Delta {\text{lnGHG emissions}}_{{\text{t}}} = \vartheta_{0} + \mathop \sum \limits_{{{\text{I}} = 1}}^{{\text{n}}} \vartheta_{{1{\text{i}}}} \Delta {\text{lnGHG emissions}}_{{{\text{t}} - {\text{i}}}} + \mathop \sum \limits_{{{\text{I}} = 0}}^{{\text{n}}} \vartheta_{{2{\text{i}}}} \Delta {\text{lnCircular economy}}_{{{\text{t}} - {\text{i}}}} + \mathop \sum \limits_{{{\text{I}} = 0}}^{{\text{n}}} \vartheta_{{3{\text{i}}}} \Delta {\text{lnTechnological innovation}}_{{{\text{t}} - {\text{i}}}} + \mathop \sum \limits_{{{\text{I}} = 0}}^{{\text{n}}} \vartheta_{{4{\text{i}}}} \Delta {\text{lnEnvironmental tax}}_{{{\text{t}} - {\text{i}}}} + \mathop \sum \limits_{{{\text{I}} = 0}}^{{\text{n}}} \vartheta_{{5{\text{i}}}} \Delta {\text{lnEconomic instability}}_{{{\text{t}} - {\text{i}}}} + \mathop \sum \limits_{{{\text{I}} = 0}}^{{\text{n}}} \vartheta_{{6{\text{i}}}} \Delta {\text{lnIndustralization}}_{{{\text{t}} - {\text{i}}}} + \xi_{1} {\text{lnGHG emissions}}_{{{\text{t}} - 1}} + \xi_{2} {\text{lnCircular economy}}_{{{\text{t}} - 1}} + \xi_{3} {\text{lnTechnological innovation}}_{{{\text{t}} - 1}} + \xi_{4} {\text{lnEnvironmental tax}}_{{{\text{t}} - 1}} + \xi_{5} {\text{lnEconomic instability}}_{{{\text{t}} - 1}} + \xi_{6} {\text{lnIndustralization}}_{{{\text{t}} - 1}} + \varepsilon_{t}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="d33e940" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x00394;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>lnGHG emissions</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003d1;</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo movablelimits="false">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>I</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003d1;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x00394;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>lnGHG emissions</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo movablelimits="false">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>I</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003d1;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x00394;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>lnCircular economy</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo movablelimits="false">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>I</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003d1;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x00394;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>lnTechnological innovation</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo movablelimits="false">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>I</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003d1;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x00394;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>lnEnvironmental tax</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo movablelimits="false">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>I</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003d1;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>5</mml:mn><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x00394;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>lnEconomic instability</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo movablelimits="false">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>I</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003d1;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>6</mml:mn><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x00394;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mtext>lnIndustralization</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003be;</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>lnGHG emissions</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003be;</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>lnCircular economy</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003be;</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>lnTechnological innovation</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003be;</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>lnEnvironmental tax</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003be;</mml:mi><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>lnEconomic instability</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003be;</mml:mi><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mtext>lnIndustralization</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13021_2025_297_Article_Equ4.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par44">In this equation, <inline-formula id="IEq4"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e1171">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\vartheta_{0}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="d33e1176"><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003d1;</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13021_2025_297_Article_IEq1.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> represents the intercept, while &#x003be;<sub>1</sub> to &#x003be;<sub>6</sub>, and <inline-formula id="IEq5"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e1186">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\vartheta_{1}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="d33e1191"><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003d1;</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13021_2025_297_Article_IEq5.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> to <inline-formula id="IEq6"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e1197">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\vartheta_{6}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="d33e1202"><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003d1;</mml:mi><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13021_2025_297_Article_IEq6.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> are the long- and short-run coefficients, respectively.</p><p id="Par45">The null and alternative hypotheses for cointegration in this context are:<disp-formula id="Equa"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e1210">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{gathered} {\text{H}}_{0} : \xi_{1} = \xi_{2} = \xi_{3} = \xi_{4} = \xi_{5} = \xi_{6} = 0 \hfill \\ {\text{H}}_{{\text{a}}} : \xi_{1} \ne \xi_{2} \ne \xi_{3} \ne \xi_{4} \ne \xi_{5} \ne \xi_{6} \ne 0 \hfill \\ \end{gathered}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="d33e1215" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>H</mml:mtext><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003be;</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003be;</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003be;</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003be;</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003be;</mml:mi><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003be;</mml:mi><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mrow/><mml:msub><mml:mtext>H</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>a</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003be;</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02260;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003be;</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02260;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003be;</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02260;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003be;</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02260;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003be;</mml:mi><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02260;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003be;</mml:mi><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02260;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13021_2025_297_Article_Equa.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par46">Choosing the correct lag length is crucial for accurately capturing variable dynamics. An incorrect lag length can result in biased estimates and false conclusions about long-run relationships. Careful selection ensures reliable findings and avoids misspecification. The error correction model estimates short-run relationships as given by Eq.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Equ5" ref-type="disp-formula">5</xref>:<disp-formula id="Equ5"><label>5</label><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e1294">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\Delta {\text{lnGHG emissions}}_{{\text{t}}} = \vartheta_{0} + \mathop \sum \limits_{{{\text{I}} = 1}}^{{\text{n}}} \vartheta_{{1{\text{i}}}} \Delta {\text{lnGHG emissions}}_{{{\text{t}} - {\text{i}}}} + \mathop \sum \limits_{{{\text{I}} = 0}}^{{\text{n}}} \vartheta_{{2{\text{i}}}} \Delta {\text{lnCircular economy}}_{{{\text{t}} - {\text{i}}}} + \mathop \sum \limits_{{{\text{I}} = 0}}^{{\text{n}}} \vartheta_{{3{\text{i}}}} \Delta {\text{lnTechnological innovation}}_{{{\text{t}} - {\text{i}}}} + \mathop \sum \limits_{{{\text{I}} = 0}}^{{\text{n}}} \vartheta_{{4{\text{i}}}} \Delta {\text{lnEnvironmental tax}}_{{{\text{t}} - {\text{i}}}} + \mathop \sum \limits_{{{\text{I}} = 0}}^{{\text{n}}} \vartheta_{{5{\text{i}}}} \Delta {\text{lnEconomic instability}}_{{{\text{t}} - {\text{i}}}} + \mathop \sum \limits_{{{\text{I}} = 0}}^{{\text{n}}} \vartheta_{{6{\text{i}}}} \Delta {\text{lnIndustralization}}_{{{\text{t}} - {\text{i}}}} + \varrho {\text{ECM}}_{{{\text{t}} - {\text{i}}}} + \varepsilon_{{\text{t}}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="d33e1300" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x00394;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>lnGHG emissions</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003d1;</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo movablelimits="false">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>I</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003d1;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x00394;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>lnGHG emissions</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo movablelimits="false">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>I</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003d1;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x00394;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>lnCircular economy</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo movablelimits="false">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>I</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003d1;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x00394;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>lnTechnological innovation</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo movablelimits="false">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>I</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003d1;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x00394;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>lnEnvironmental tax</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo movablelimits="false">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>I</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003d1;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>5</mml:mn><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x00394;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>lnEconomic instability</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo movablelimits="false">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>I</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003d1;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>6</mml:mn><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x00394;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mtext>lnIndustralization</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003f1;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mtext>ECM</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13021_2025_297_Article_Equ5.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Robust analyses</title><p id="Par47">For robustness, we employed the fully modified ordinary least squares (FMOLS), dynamic ordinary least squares (DOLS), and wavelet coherence analysis&#x000a0;to check the consistency&#x000a0;of ARDL bounds testing.</p><sec id="Sec11"><title>FMOLS and OLS</title><p id="Par48">FMOLS and DOLS represent sophisticated time-series techniques employed for cointegration analysis, effectively tackling challenges such as serial correlation and endogeneity. FMOLS addresses the issues of serial correlation and endogenous regressors by making adjustments to the estimator&#x02019;s bias, whereas DOLS utilizes leads and lags of the first-differenced regressor to mitigate potential endogeneity and serial correlation. These methods outperform traditional OLS as they yield more consistent and efficient estimates when addressing non-stationary, cointegrated time series, thus enhancing the reliability of long-term relationship analysis.<disp-formula id="Equ6"><label>6</label><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e1479">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\hat{\beta }^{*}_{{\text{FMOLS or DOLS}}} = {\text{N}}^{ - 1} \mathop \sum \limits_{{{\text{i}} = 1}}^{{\text{N}}} \hat{\beta }^{*}_{{\text{FMOLS or DOLS}}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="d33e1485" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mmultiscripts><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>FMOLS or DOLS</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>&#x02217;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mmultiscripts><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:munderover><mml:mo movablelimits="false">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext></mml:munderover><mml:mmultiscripts><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>FMOLS or DOLS</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>&#x02217;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mmultiscripts></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13021_2025_297_Article_Equ6.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <inline-formula id="IEq7"><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e1525">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\hat{\beta }^{*}_{{\text{FMOLS or DOLS}}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="d33e1530"><mml:mmultiscripts><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>FMOLS or DOLS</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>&#x02217;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mmultiscripts></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13021_2025_297_Article_IEq7.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> are estimators FMOLS and DOLS conventionally. Moreover, the t-statistic associated the estimators can be obtained as given by Eq.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Equ7" ref-type="disp-formula">7</xref>:<disp-formula id="Equ7"><label>7</label><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e1546">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\text{t}}_{{\hat{\beta }^{*}_{{\text{FMOLS, DOLS}}} }} = {\text{N}}^{{ - \frac{1}{2}}} \mathop \sum \limits_{{{\text{i}} = 1}}^{{\text{N}}} {\text{t}}_{{\hat{\beta }^{*}_{{\text{FMOLS, DOLS}}} }}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="d33e1552" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mmultiscripts><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mmultiscripts><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>FMOLS, DOLS</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>&#x02217;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mmultiscripts><mml:mrow/></mml:mmultiscripts><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:munderover><mml:mo movablelimits="false">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext></mml:munderover><mml:mmultiscripts><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mmultiscripts><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>FMOLS, DOLS</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>&#x02217;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mmultiscripts><mml:mrow/></mml:mmultiscripts></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13021_2025_297_Article_Equ7.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Wavelet coherence analysis</title><p id="Par49">Wavelet coherence analysis has become increasingly significant in economics, providing a sophisticated tool for examining the relationships, interactions, and dynamics between economic time series data. Originating from the work of Goupillaud et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>], this method has been pioneering in its application across various fields, including economics. Given that economic variables often exhibit time-varying relationships, wavelet coherence allows researchers to analyze how coherence and phase relationships between different economic indicators evolve over time and across different frequency components. Wavelet coherence analysis not only provides access to the local phase connection of time sequences in the time&#x02013;frequency field but also identifies noteworthy correlations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99">99</xref>]. Wavelet coherence analysis allows for the extraction of correlation characteristics throughout a wider frequency range, unlike cross-wavelet analysis, which is limited to certain frequency points due to scale smoothing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. This capability is crucial for understanding the cyclical patterns and interactions within economic data, as highlighted by Abbas et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. The application of wavelet coherence analysis begins with the use of the Morlet wavelet family, represented mathematically as:<disp-formula id="Equ8"><label>8</label><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e1615">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\varpi ({\text{t}})={\pi }^{-\frac{1}{4}}{{\text{e}}}^{- {\text{i}} \varpi {\text{t}}}{{\text{e}}}^{-\frac{1}{2}{{\text{t}}}^{2}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="d33e1621" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003d6;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c0;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>e</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mi>&#x003d6;</mml:mi><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>e</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13021_2025_297_Article_Equ8.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par50">By transforming the wavelet&#x000a0;&#x003c8;(t), the expression for &#x003c8;k, f(t)&#x000a0;is derived, as shown in:<disp-formula id="Equ9"><label>9</label><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e1662">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\varpi }_{{\text{k,f}}} ({\text{t}})=\frac{1}{\sqrt{{\text{h}}}}\varpi \left(\frac{{\text{t}}-{\text{k}}}{{\text{f}}}\right), \;\;\; {\text{k,f}}\in {\mathbb{R}},{\text{f}}\ne 0$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="d33e1668" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003d6;</mml:mi><mml:mtext>k,f</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:msqrt><mml:mtext>h</mml:mtext></mml:msqrt></mml:mfrac><mml:mi>&#x003d6;</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mtext>k</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>f</mml:mtext></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mtext>k,f</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x02208;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">R</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>f</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x02260;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13021_2025_297_Article_Equ9.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par51">The cross wavelet transform (CWT) is a fundamental component of this analysis and is given by:<disp-formula id="Equ10"><label>10</label><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e1708">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\varpi }_{{\text{p}}}\left({\text{k,f}}\right)={\int }_{-\infty }^{\infty }{\text{p}}({\text{t}})\frac{1}{\sqrt{{\text{f}}}}\varpi \left(\frac{{\overline{{\text{t}}-{\text{k}}}}}{{\text{f}}}\right){\text{dt}},\; {\text{N}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="d33e1714" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003d6;</mml:mi><mml:mtext>p</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mtext>k,f</mml:mtext></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#x0222b;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x0221e;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x0221e;</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mtext>p</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:msqrt><mml:mtext>f</mml:mtext></mml:msqrt></mml:mfrac><mml:mi>&#x003d6;</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mfrac><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mtext>k</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mtext>f</mml:mtext></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced><mml:mtext>dt</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13021_2025_297_Article_Equ10.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par52">Further refinement of the process involves adding a coefficient&#x000a0;&#x003c8;&#x000a0;to obtain&#x000a0;p(p(t), which is represented by:<disp-formula id="Equ11"><label>11</label><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e1757">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\text{p}}({\text{t}})=\frac{1}{{{\text{C}}}_{\varpi }}{\int }_{0}^{\infty }\left[{\int }_{-\infty }^{\infty }{\left|{{\text{W}}}_{{\text{p}}}({\text{a,b}})\right|}^{2}{\text{da}}\right]\frac{{\text{db}}}{{{\text{b}}}^{2}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="d33e1763" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>p</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mtext>C</mml:mtext><mml:mi>&#x003d6;</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#x0222b;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x0221e;</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mfenced close="]" open="["><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#x0222b;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x0221e;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x0221e;</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close="|" open="|"><mml:msub><mml:mtext>W</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>p</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>a,b</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mtext>da</mml:mtext></mml:mfenced><mml:mfrac><mml:mtext>db</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>b</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13021_2025_297_Article_Equ11.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par53">The wavelet power spectrum (WPS) then illustrates the vulnerability of the time series, capturing its dynamics as shown in:<disp-formula id="Equ12"><label>12</label><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e1813">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${{\text{WPS}}}_{{\text{p}}}({\text{k,f}})={\left|{{\text{W}}}_{{\text{p}}}({\text{a,b}})\right|}^{2}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="d33e1819" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>WPS</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>p</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>k,f</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close="|" open="|"><mml:msub><mml:mtext>W</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>p</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>a,b</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13021_2025_297_Article_Equ12.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par54">The cross wavelet transform of time series, specifically for variables like GHG emissions, circular economy, technological innovation, environmental tax, economic instability, and industrialization in the Netherlands over the period from 2010Q1 to 2022Q4, is denoted by:<disp-formula id="Equ13"><label>13</label><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e1847">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${{\text{W}}}_{{\text{pq}}}({\text{k,f}})={{\text{W}}}_{{\text{p}}} ({\text{k,f}})\overline{{{\text{W}}}_{{\text{q}}}({\text{k,f}})}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="d33e1853" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>W</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>pq</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>k,f</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mtext>W</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>p</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>k,f</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>W</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>q</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>k,f</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13021_2025_297_Article_Equ13.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par55">The interaction between these variables is then quantified through the squared wavelet coherence&#x000a0;R<sup>2</sup>(k,f), defined as:<disp-formula id="Equ14"><label>14</label><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e1891">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${{\text{R}}}^{2}({\text{k,f}})=\frac{{\left|{\text{C}}\left({{\text{f}}}^{-1}{{\text{W}}}_{{\text{pq}}} ({\text{k,f}})\right)\right|}^{2}}{{{\text{C}}({\text{f}}}^{-1}{\left|{{\text{W}}}_{{\text{p}}} ({\text{k,f}})\right|}^{2}) {{\text{C}} ({\text{f}}}^{-1}{\left|{{\text{W}}}_{{\text{q}}} ({\text{k,f}})\right|}^{2})}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="d33e1897" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>R</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>k,f</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close="|" open="|"><mml:mtext>C</mml:mtext><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>f</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mtext>W</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>pq</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>k,f</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>C</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>f</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close="|" open="|"><mml:msub><mml:mtext>W</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>p</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>k,f</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>C</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>f</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close="|" open="|"><mml:msub><mml:mtext>W</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>q</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>k,f</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13021_2025_297_Article_Equ14.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par56">Here, the R<sup>2</sup>(k,f)&#x000a0;value serves as an indicator of the strength and magnitude of the interaction between the economic time series. Adebayo and Odugbesan [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>] further explored the coherence between variables using lags in two-time series, offering a linked orientation argument that adds depth to the analysis. The phase difference between the series is captured through the phase angle, denoted by:<disp-formula id="Equ15"><label>15</label><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e1990">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\varphi }_{{\text{pq}}}({\text{k,f}})={\tan}^{-1}\left(\frac{{\text{L}}\left\{{\text{C}}\left({{\text{f}}}^{-1}{{\text{W}}}_{{\text{pj}}} ({\text{k,f}})\right)\right\}}{{\text{O}}\left\{{\text{C}}\left({{\text{f}}}^{-1}{{\text{W}}}_{{\text{pj}}} ({\text{k,f}})\right)\right\}}\right)$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="d33e1996" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mtext>pq</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>k,f</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>tan</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>L</mml:mtext><mml:mfenced close="}" open="{"><mml:mtext>C</mml:mtext><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>f</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mtext>W</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>pj</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>k,f</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mfenced close="}" open="{"><mml:mtext>C</mml:mtext><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>f</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mtext>W</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>pj</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>k,f</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13021_2025_297_Article_Equ15.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par57">This robust test, employed as a supplementary method alongside the ARDL approach, provides a comprehensive framework for analyzing the intricate relationships between economic indicators over time and across varying frequencies, thus enhancing the robustness and reliability of the econometric analysis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Causality analysis</title><p id="Par58">The Toda and Yamamoto [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">92</xref>] methodology enhances traditional Granger causality testing by allowing for causality assessment between variables, regardless of their integration order. This method is crucial in addressing the problem of spurious causality, which can arise from non-stationary data or omitted variables. The Toda-Yamamoto method makes sure that causality results are more solid and reliable by using an augmented vector autoregression (VAR) model with extra lags. This method also effectively handles endogeneity, capturing the bidirectional feedback effects often observed in economic variables and providing a more comprehensive understanding of their interactions. Moreover, the Gradual Shift Causality test and the Toda-Yamamoto test are advanced methods for analyzing causal relationships in time series data that address limitations of the traditional Granger causality test. The Gradual Shift Causality test is designed to handle situations where the relationship between variables may change over time, accounting for non-linear dynamics and structural breaks that could be overlooked by traditional methods. On the other hand, the Toda-Yamamoto test improves upon the Granger causality test by allowing for variables that are integrated in different orders (such as I(0) or I(1)) without the need for pre-testing or differencing, making it more robust in the presence of unit roots or non-stationarity. Both tests offer greater flexibility and robustness, providing more reliable results in complex data structures where traditional Granger causality may fail to capture the true causal relationships [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>].</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Results and discussions</title><p id="Par59">In this study, statistical measures like skewness and kurtosis were employed to assess the normality of the data, providing insights into potential deviations from a normal distribution. To rigorously examine the normality of the variables, the Jarque and Bera [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>] test was applied. The results, as presented in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, indicate that all variables exhibit non-linear behavior, suggesting deviations from normality.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Summary statistics</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Variables</th><th align="left">ln GHG emissions</th><th align="left">lnCircular economy</th><th align="left">lnEconomic instability</th><th align="left">lnEnvironmental tax</th><th align="left">lnTechnology innovation</th><th align="left">lnIndustrialization</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Mean</td><td align="left">2.468</td><td align="left">3.284</td><td align="left">0.857</td><td align="left">2.149</td><td align="left">1.548</td><td align="left">2.923</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Median</td><td align="left">2.502</td><td align="left">3.279</td><td align="left">0.933</td><td align="left">2.168</td><td align="left">1.544</td><td align="left">2.904</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Maximum</td><td align="left">2.665</td><td align="left">3.373</td><td align="left">1.178</td><td align="left">2.293</td><td align="left">1.620</td><td align="left">3.010</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Minimum</td><td align="left">2.207</td><td align="left">3.215</td><td align="left">0.450</td><td align="left">1.690</td><td align="left">1.490</td><td align="left">2.865</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Std. Dev</td><td align="left">0.108</td><td align="left">0.043</td><td align="left">0.235</td><td align="left">0.118</td><td align="left">0.033</td><td align="left">0.051</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Skewness</td><td align="left">&#x02212;0.726</td><td align="left">0.457</td><td align="left">&#x02212;0.242</td><td align="left">&#x02212;1.968</td><td align="left">0.469</td><td align="left">0.447</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Kurtosis</td><td align="left">2.686</td><td align="left">2.406</td><td align="left">1.576</td><td align="left">7.543</td><td align="left">2.553</td><td align="left">1.579</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Jarque&#x02013;bera</td><td align="left">4.783</td><td align="left">2.575</td><td align="left">4.903</td><td align="left">78.285</td><td align="left">2.338</td><td align="left">6.106</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Probability</td><td align="left">0.091</td><td align="left">0.276</td><td align="left">0.086</td><td align="left">0.000</td><td align="left">0.311</td><td align="left">0.047</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Obs</td><td align="left">52</td><td align="left">52</td><td align="left">52</td><td align="left">52</td><td align="left">52</td><td align="left">52</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par60">The stationarity of variables was assessed using the Augmented Dickey-Fuller (ADF) and Phillips-Perron (PP) tests before conducting ARDL bounds testing to ensure the integration order was suitable. The results, as shown in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>, confirm that all variables&#x02014; GHG emissions, circular economy, economic instability, environmental tax, technological innovation, and industrialization&#x02014;are non-stationary at their levels I(0), but become stationary after taking their first differences I(1).<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Unit root test</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Variables</th><th align="left" colspan="2">ADF test</th><th align="left" colspan="2">PP test</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Level</th><th align="left">First difference</th><th align="left">Level</th><th align="left">First difference</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">lnGHG emissions</td><td align="left">&#x02212;1.819</td><td align="left">&#x02212;3.936***</td><td align="left">&#x02212;1.936</td><td align="left">&#x02212;3.832***</td></tr><tr><td align="left">lnCircular economy</td><td align="left">&#x02212;1.554</td><td align="left">&#x02212;3.568***</td><td align="left">&#x02212;1.709</td><td align="left">&#x02212;3.482***</td></tr><tr><td align="left">lnEconomic instability</td><td align="left">&#x02212;1.782</td><td align="left">&#x02212;3.787***</td><td align="left">&#x02212;1.929</td><td align="left">&#x02212;4.192***</td></tr><tr><td align="left">lnEnvironmental tax</td><td align="left">&#x02212;1.683</td><td align="left">&#x02212;3.698***</td><td align="left">&#x02212;1.710</td><td align="left">&#x02212;3.642***</td></tr><tr><td align="left">lnTechnological innovation</td><td align="left">&#x02212;1.851</td><td align="left">&#x02212;4.002***</td><td align="left">&#x02212;1.795</td><td align="left">&#x02212;4.279***</td></tr><tr><td align="left">lnIndustrialization</td><td align="left">&#x02212;1.823</td><td align="left">&#x02212;3.916***</td><td align="left">&#x02212;1.882</td><td align="left">&#x02212;4.073***</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>***<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par61">Before applying the ARDL technique to estimate the model, it is essential to determine the appropriate lag length for the variables. The Akaike Information Criterion (AIC) was used to identify the optimal lag length, ensuring accurate model specification. The results of the ARDL cointegration test, presented in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>, indicate a significant long-run relationship among GHG emissions, circular economy, technological innovation, environmental tax, economic instability, and industrialization in the Netherlands. The F-statistic of 7.002, which exceeds the critical values at the 1, 5, and 10% significance levels, confirms the existence of cointegration among the variables, suggesting that these factors are interconnected in the long term.<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Cointegration test</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Model</th><th align="left">Optimal lag length</th><th align="left">F-statistics</th><th align="left">Cointegration</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">lnGHG emissions&#x02009;=&#x02009;f(lnCircular economy, lnTechnological innovation, lnEnvironmental tax, lnEconomic instability, lnIndustrialization)</td><td align="left">(1,1,0,1,1,1)</td><td align="left">7.002***</td><td align="left">Yes</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Significance level</td><td align="left">I (0)</td><td align="left">I (1)</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">1%</td><td align="left">3.21</td><td align="left">4.19</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">5%</td><td align="left">2.33</td><td align="left">3.41</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">10%</td><td align="left">2.01</td><td align="left">3.02</td><td align="left"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Based on the Akaike Information Criterion and intercept only. The period of analysis is 2010Q1&#x02013;2022Q4. Maximum lag&#x02009;=&#x02009;2, n&#x02009;=&#x02009;52. The critical values for the lower I(0) and upper I(1) bounds were taken from Narayan [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>]. ***<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par62">After establishing the presence of a long-run equilibrium relationship between the circular economy and the associated factors, this research delves into the short-run and long-run dynamics between GHG emissions and variables such as the circular economy, technological innovation, environmental tax, economic instability, and industrialization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. The findings reveal several key insights with significant implications for sustainability and policy-making.</p><p id="Par63">The results indicate a negative long-run relationship between the circular economy and GHG emissions,&#x000a0;such that a 1% increase in circular economy results in a decrease of 0.540% of GHG emissions. This suggests that as the circular economy develops, GHG emissions decrease, highlighting the effectiveness of circular economy practices in mitigating environmental impact. The results align with previous research, such as the work of Hailemariam and Erdiaw-Kwasie [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>] and Gallego-Schmid et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>], which similarly found that circular economy initiatives play a critical role in reducing environmental footprints. Our study contradicts the findings of Eweade et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>], who showed that the use of combustible renewable waste adversely affects the ecological footprint in&#x000a0;the UK. The Netherlands&#x02019; commitment to transitioning to a fully circular economy by 2050 reflects this understanding, with strategies focused on reducing material consumption, promoting sustainable alternatives, extending product lifecycles, and enhancing recycling processes. These efforts are not only crucial for lowering GHG emissions but also for creating a more sustainable economic framework that balances resource efficiency with environmental stewardship. Moreover, by altering consumer behavior, legislative incentives, and production methods, the circular economy lowers GHG emissions. The circular economy decreases waste and the need for resource extraction and energy-intensive production, which lowers emissions, by designing items for longevity, repair, and recyclability. Carbon taxes, extended producer responsibility, and recycling requirements are a few examples of policy incentives that push companies to implement emission-reducing, sustainable practices. Furthermore, consumers are choosing services over ownership or reusing, repairing, and recycling objects, which reduces the need for new products and the emissions associated with their manufacture [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. When combined, these processes provide a more sustainable and effective system that reduces GHG emissions throughout the course of a product&#x02019;s lifespan.</p><p id="Par64">Technological innovation also has a negative long-run relationship with GHG emissions,&#x000a0;such that a 1% increase in technological innovation results in a decrease of 0.607% of GHG emissions, indicating that advancements in technology are pivotal in reducing the country&#x02019;s carbon footprint and achieving environmental sustainability. This finding supports the views of Adebayo et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>], who emphasize the role of technological innovation in enhancing efficiency, reducing energy consumption, and substituting traditional methods with more sustainable alternatives. Different types of innovations, such as clean energy technologies and energy efficiency improvements, help reduce GHG emissions in complementary ways. By substituting low- or zero-emission energy sources for fossil fuel-based ones, clean energy technologies such as solar, wind, and geothermal power directly lower emissions from the production of electricity. Conversely, energy efficiency enhancements like improved insulation, energy-efficient appliances, and smarter systems lower the total amount of energy required for industrial operations, heating, and cooling. This lowers the demand for electricity and, consequently, lowers emissions from power generation. By addressing emissions from both the supply (clean energy) and demand (efficiency) sides, these advances collectively offer a comprehensive strategy for reducing climate change. In the Netherlands, the adoption of digital technologies and innovative solutions is projected to significantly cut down on GHG emissions. By improving energy management, optimizing transportation systems, and advancing industrial processes, technological innovation can lead to considerable reductions in environmental impact, underscoring its importance in the nation&#x02019;s sustainability agenda.</p><p id="Par65">Furthermore, the study finds&#x000a0;that&#x000a0;there is a negative long-run relationship between environmental taxes and GHG emissions,&#x000a0;such that a&#x000a0;1% increase in environmental taxes&#x000a0;results in a decrease of 0.531% of GHG emissions. The results indicate&#x000a0;that the implementation of environmental taxes is associated with a reduction in GHG emissions. This finding is consistent with the&#x000a0;studies such as Do&#x0011f;an et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>] and Ghazouani et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>], which demonstrate the efficacy of environmental taxes in promoting cleaner energy use and reducing reliance on fossil fuels. The gradual tightening of these tax policies, as seen in the Tax Plan 2023, further illustrates the Dutch commitment to achieving long-term environmental goals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]. This suggests that such fiscal measures effectively incentivize businesses and individuals to reduce their carbon emissions by adopting cleaner practices and investing in energy efficiency. The Dutch government&#x02019;s introduction of a GHG tax as part of its environmental protection strategy illustrates this principle in action. By taxing high-emission industries and encouraging the adoption of carbon capture and storage technologies, the Netherlands is curbing emissions and&#x000a0;fostering a more sustainable industrial sector (Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab5"><label>Table&#x000a0;5</label><caption><p>Long-run and short-run results</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Variable</th><th align="left">Coefficient</th><th align="left">t-statistics</th><th align="left">Prob</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Dependent variable: lnGHG emissions</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Long-run estimation</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;lnCircular economy</td><td align="left">&#x02212;0.540***</td><td align="left">&#x02212;5.703</td><td char="." align="char">0.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;lnTechnological innovation</td><td align="left">&#x02212;0.607***</td><td align="left">&#x02212;5.370</td><td char="." align="char">0.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;lnEnvironmental tax</td><td align="left">&#x02212;0.531***</td><td align="left">&#x02212;5.175</td><td char="." align="char">0.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;lnEconomic instability</td><td align="left">0.099***</td><td align="left">2.842</td><td char="." align="char">0.007</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;lnIndustrialization</td><td align="left">0.517***</td><td align="left">3.107</td><td char="." align="char">0.003</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Short-run estimation</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;lnCircular economy</td><td align="left">&#x02212;0.253***</td><td align="left">&#x02212;6.929</td><td char="." align="char">0.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;lnTechnological innovation</td><td align="left">&#x02212;0.363***</td><td align="left">&#x02212;6.687</td><td char="." align="char">0.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;lnEnvironmental tax</td><td align="left">&#x02212;0.077**</td><td align="left">&#x02212;2.382</td><td char="." align="char">0.022</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;lnEconomic instability</td><td align="left">0.093***</td><td align="left">2.833</td><td char="." align="char">0.008</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;lnIndustrialization</td><td align="left">0.083**</td><td align="left">2.632</td><td char="." align="char">0.019</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Constant</td><td align="left">&#x02212;0.582***</td><td align="left">&#x02212;3.365</td><td char="." align="char">0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ECM(&#x02212;1)</td><td align="left">&#x02212;0.842***</td><td align="left">&#x02212;5.558</td><td char="." align="char">0.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left">R<sup>2</sup></td><td align="left">0.998</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Adjusted R<sup>2</sup></td><td align="left">0.998</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup> ARCH</td><td align="left">2.127 (0.126)</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup> RESET</td><td align="left">1.735 (0.139)</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup> normality</td><td align="left">0.442 (0.531)</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup> LM</td><td align="left">0.185 (0.728)</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup> ARCH for autoregressive conditional heteroscedasticity, &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup> Reset for Ramsey Reset test, &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup> normality is for Jargue-Bera test of normality, and &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup> LM for Breusch-Godfrey serial correlation LM test. <italic>p</italic> values of diagnostic tests are in parenthesis. ***<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, and **<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par66">The relationship between economic instability and GHG emissions is found to be significant and positive, such that&#x000a0;that a&#x000a0;1% increase in economic instability&#x000a0;results in an&#x000a0;increase of 0.099% of GHG emissions&#x000a0;in the long-run. The results&#x000a0;indicate that as economic instability increases, GHG emissions also rise&#x000a0;in the Netherlands. This finding is in line with previous research by Ozili [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>], which suggests that economic instability can lead to increased emissions due to the financial decisions made during such periods. Banks and financial institutions play a critical role in this dynamic, as their lending practices can influence corporate behavior. During times of economic instability, banks may be more inclined to finance high-emission sectors or industries that are less environmentally sustainable, exacerbating the environmental impact [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100">100</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103">103</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR104">104</xref>]). This relationship highlights the need for financial institutions to integrate climate risk into their decision-making processes, prioritizing investments that support low-carbon initiatives and environmentally responsible practices [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101">101</xref>]. By doing so, banks can contribute positively to the environment, even in the face of economic challenges.</p><p id="Par67">The study also reveals a positive relationship between industrialization and GHG emissions,&#x000a0;such that a 1% increase in industrialization results in an increase of 0.517% of GHG emissions in the long-run, with industrialization identified as a significant contributor to environmental degradation in the Netherlands. This finding is consistent with previous studies by Raihan et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>], and Sikder et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">87</xref>], which demonstrate the adverse environmental effects of industrial activities, particularly those reliant on fossil fuels for energy production [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93">93</xref>]. Industrialization, while driving economic growth, also leads to increased GHG emissions due to the energy-intensive nature of manufacturing processes, transportation, and the use of construction materials like cement [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100">100</xref>]. The Dutch government&#x02019;s National Climate Agreement, which targets a 95% reduction in GHG emissions by 2050, underscores the urgency of mitigating the environmental impact of industrialization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">91</xref>]. While efforts are being made to reduce emissions through technological advancements and regulatory measures, the study emphasizes the importance of balancing industrial growth with environmental sustainability.</p><p id="Par68">The ARDL short-run analysis further supports the findings, showing that the circular economy, technological innovation, and environmental taxes have a mitigating effect on GHG emissions in the Netherlands. In contrast, economic instability and industrialization are associated with higher emissions. The estimated error correction model coefficient indicates that any short-term deviations from the long-run equilibrium are quickly corrected, reinforcing the stability of the relationships observed. Diagnostic tests confirm the robustness of the model, and the stability plots suggest that the results are reliable. Figures&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> and <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref> display the stability of the models at a 5% significance level through the CUSUM and CUSUMQ plots. These findings have significant implications for policy-making, emphasizing the need for continued support of circular economy practices, technological innovation, and environmental taxes to achieve long-term sustainability goals.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;5</label><caption><p>The cumulative sum of the recursive residual plot</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13021_2025_297_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig><fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;6</label><caption><p>The cumulative sum of the square of the recursive residual plot</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13021_2025_297_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p><sec id="Sec15"><title>Robustness check</title><sec id="Sec16"><title>FMOLS and DOLS</title><p id="Par69">This study employs FMOLS and DOLS techniques to validate the robustness of the long-run estimates obtained from the ARDL model. Both FMOLS and DOLS are sophisticated methods designed to address potential endogeneity and serial correlation issues in time series analysis. The consistency of the results from FMOLS and DOLS with those obtained from the ARDL model, as presented in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref>, confirms the reliability of the long-run relationships identified between GHG emissions and various explanatory variables. This alignment underscores that the observed relationships are robust and not artifacts of econometric concerns.<table-wrap id="Tab6"><label>Table&#x000a0;6</label><caption><p>Robustness check</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Dependent variable: lnGHG emissions</th><th align="left" colspan="3">FMOLS</th><th align="left" colspan="3">DOLS</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Coefficient</th><th align="left">t-statistics</th><th align="left">Prob</th><th align="left">Coefficient</th><th align="left">t-statistics</th><th align="left">Prob</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">lnCircular economy</td><td align="left">&#x02212;0.667***</td><td align="left">&#x02212;2.999</td><td char="." align="char">0.004</td><td align="left">&#x02212;0.619***</td><td align="left">&#x02212;3.364</td><td char="." align="char">0.002</td></tr><tr><td align="left">lnTechnological innovation</td><td align="left">&#x02212;0.404***</td><td align="left">&#x02212;3.747</td><td char="." align="char">0.000</td><td align="left">&#x02212;0.660***</td><td align="left">&#x02212;3.801</td><td char="." align="char">0.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left">lnEnvironmental tax</td><td align="left">&#x02212;0.785***</td><td align="left">&#x02212;7.926</td><td char="." align="char">0.000</td><td align="left">&#x02212;0.951***</td><td align="left">&#x02212;5.763</td><td char="." align="char">0.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left">lnEconomic instability</td><td align="left">0.176*</td><td align="left">2.172</td><td char="." align="char">0.088</td><td align="left">0.208*</td><td align="left">2.185</td><td char="." align="char">0.065</td></tr><tr><td align="left">lnIndustrialization</td><td align="left">0.558***</td><td align="left">3.254</td><td char="." align="char">0.002</td><td align="left">0.428***</td><td align="left">3.664</td><td char="." align="char">0.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Constant</td><td align="left">2.804***</td><td align="left">3.439</td><td char="." align="char">0.000</td><td align="left">2.638***</td><td align="left">3.793</td><td char="." align="char">0.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left">R<sup>2</sup></td><td align="left">0.910</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/><td align="left">0.976</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Adjusted R<sup>2</sup></td><td align="left">0.900</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/><td align="left">0.958</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>***<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, **<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, and *<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.10</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par70">The robustness analysis affirms that promoting circular economy practices, technological innovation, and the environmental tax effectively reduces GHG emissions in the Netherlands, while economic instability and industrialization are positively associated with increased GHG&#x000a0;emissions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97">97</xref>]. These findings support the use of these strategies in policy and decision-making, ensuring that efforts to mitigate GHG emissions are grounded in reliable and consistent evidence. By reinforcing the stability of the ARDL results, the robustness analysis highlights the importance of integrating environmental sustainability into economic and industrial policies to achieve meaningful and enduring reductions in GHG&#x000a0;emissions.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Wavelet coherence analysis</title><p id="Par71">The Wavelet Coherence Analysis (WCA) provides a comprehensive view of the interactions between GHG emissions and several explanatory variables, including circular economy, technological innovation, environmental tax, economic instability, and industrialization, over the period from the first quarter of 2010 to the fourth quarter of 2022. The gray cone in the WCA visualizations represents the area of effect, while the thick black line, derived from Monte Carlo simulations, denotes the significance level. This approach captures both the causation and correlation in the relationships, offering insights into how these dynamics evolve across different time scales and frequencies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>].</p><p id="Par72">Figures&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>a&#x02013;e illustrate the findings from the WCA. The findings illustrated in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>a indicate a noticeable&#x000a0;correlation between the circular economy and GHG emissions, especially during the period from 2014Q2 to 2019Q2. The prevalent upward and leftward arrows across various frequencies suggest that the adoption of circular economy practices is associated with a decrease in GHG emissions. Circular economy principles emphasize resource efficiency, waste reduction, and the reuse and recycling of materials, resulting in lower emissions by minimizing the demand for raw materials, reducing energy consumption, and decreasing emissions from waste processing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR104">104</xref>]. From 2014Q2 to 2019Q2, the relationship became more evident, suggesting that the increased adoption of circular economy practices corresponded with a significant reduction in GHG emissions. This trend indicates that the circular economy is effective in reducing emissions and serves as a reliable predictor of fluctuations in emissions. The data indicates that the circular economy can predict substantial changes in GHG emissions in the Netherlands, underscoring its potential as an effective mechanism for reducing environmental impact.<fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;7</label><caption><p>Wavelet coherence analysis. Time and frequency are presented on the horizontal and the vertical axis, respectively. On the wavelet coherence plots, the black contour shows the 5% significance level, and regions with strong co-movements are represented by warmer colors (<italic>red</italic>), whereas colder colors (<italic>blue</italic>) represent regions with weak co-movements. The <italic>arrows</italic> provide the direction of interdependence and causality relationships. <italic>Arrows</italic> pointing to the <italic>right</italic> (&#x02192;) indicate that variables are positively correlated. <italic>Arrows</italic> pointing to the <italic>left</italic> (&#x02190;) indicate that variables are negatively correlated. The &#x02197; and &#x02199; <italic>arrows</italic> mean that first variable leads second variable, whereas the &#x02198; and &#x02196; <italic>arrows</italic> indicate that the second variable leads the first variable. The <italic>straight up</italic> (&#x02191;) and <italic>down</italic> (&#x02193;) <italic>arrows</italic> imply that the first variable is leading and lagging, respectively. <bold>a</bold> WCA between GHG emissions and circular economy. <bold>b</bold> WCA between GHG emissions and technological innovation. <bold>c</bold> WCA between GHG emissions and environmental tax. <bold>d</bold> WCA between GHG emissions and economic instability. <bold>e</bold> WCA between GHG emissions and industrialization</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13021_2025_297_Fig7_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig></p><p id="Par73">Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>b illustrates a strong negative correlation between technological innovation and GHG emissions, indicating that technological advancements significantly contribute to&#x000a0;GHG emissions reduction over time. The persistent upward and leftward trends across various frequencies from 2010Q1 to 2019Q3, along with the sustained negative correlation at low frequency between 2019Q4 and 2021Q2, indicate a direct relationship between technological innovations and reduced emissions. Technological innovations, including the advancement of cleaner energy sources, enhanced industrial processes, and optimized resource management technologies, mitigate the environmental impact of production and consumption. The adoption of advanced technologies enables industries to decrease energy consumption, reduce waste, and minimize carbon emissions. The persistent occurrence of these negative arrows supports the notion that technological advancement is a dependable indicator of emissions reductions, aiding in the prediction of substantial decreases in GHG emissions in the Netherlands throughout the examined timeframe.</p><p id="Par74">Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>c illustrates a negative correlation between GHG emissions and environmental tax, underscoring the efficacy of environmental tax policies in mitigating GHG&#x000a0;emissions over time. The leftward-up arrows across various scales (frequencies) indicate that an increase in environmental tax correlates with a decrease in GHG emissions, demonstrating a clear inverse relationship. Environmental taxes increase the cost associated with carbon-intensive activities, thereby incentivizing businesses to adopt sustainable practices, invest in cleaner technologies, and reduce their carbon footprint. This policy mechanism promotes energy efficiency and facilitates a transition to greener alternatives, resulting in reduced emissions. Between 2010Q1 and 2022Q4, a consistent negative relationship was found between environmental taxes and GHG&#x000a0;emissions. This supports the idea that these taxes are a reliable way to predict decreases in GHG emissions in the Netherlands, as businesses and consumers change their behavior in response to the financial incentives created by these policies.</p><p id="Par75">Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>d indicates a robust positive correlation between economic instability and GHG emissions, as evidenced by the consistent presence of rightward-up arrows across multiple scales from 2013Q4 to 2022Q4. This suggests that economic instability correlates with heightened GHG emissions. Economic instability frequently results in unpredictable fluctuations in production levels, alterations in energy consumption patterns, and a possible dependence on more polluting energy sources as industries endeavor to sustain stability. Moreover, during periods of economic distress, there is often an increase in resource consumption and a decline in efficiency, which further intensifies emissions. Between the first quarter of 2010 and the third quarter of 2013, the relationship is predominantly observed at high scales (low frequency), indicating that long-term fluctuations in economic instability exert a more substantial influence on GHG emissions during this timeframe. The data indicates that economic instability serves as a reliable predictor of heightened GHG emissions in the Netherlands, illustrating how it&#x000a0;can lead to significant alterations in emission levels through changes in industrial activity, energy consumption, and regulatory responses.</p><p id="Par76">The results in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>e illustrate a clear positive relationship between industrialization and GHG emissions over the period from 2010Q1 to 2022Q4, as indicated by the predominance of rightward and upward arrows at various scales. From 2010Q1 to 2014Q1, this correlation is visible across low, medium, and high-frequency scales, suggesting that industrialization consistently drives an increase in GHG emissions across different time frames. This is likely due to increased energy consumption, higher production outputs, and greater resource utilization associated with industrial processes. From 2014Q2 to 2022Q4, the association is particularly strong at high and intermediate scales (low and middle frequencies), which suggests that as industrialization progresses, it continues to be a dominant factor in the rise of GHG emissions, reinforcing the idea that industrial expansion leads to greater emissions. Thus, the unfolding of industrialization in the Netherlands serves as a reliable predictor of significant fluctuations in GHG emissions during this period.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Causality tests</title><p id="Par77">To validate the findings from the Wavelet Coherence Analysis, this study utilized the Gradual Shift Causality (GSC) and Toda-Yamamoto (TYC) tests, revealing distinct causal relationships between GHG emissions and various factors. The results demonstrate a bidirectional causality between GHG emissions and the circular economy, indicating that the circular economy both impacts and is influenced by GHG levels. This aligns with prior studies, which emphasize the reciprocal influence between these variables. In contrast, a unidirectional causality is observed from technological innovation, environmental tax, economic instability, and industrialization to GHG emissions. Technological innovation reduces emissions, environmental taxes provide economic incentives for emission reductions, economic instability affects emission levels, and industrialization increases emissions. These findings are consistent with existing literature and underscore the need for integrated strategies that address both predictive and reactive aspects of GHG&#x000a0;emissions management (Table <xref rid="Tab7" ref-type="table">7</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab7"><label>Table&#x000a0;7</label><caption><p>Causality results</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Causality path</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Gradual shift causality test</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Toda-yamamoto causality test</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Mwald</th><th align="left"><italic>p</italic>-value</th><th align="left">Wald</th><th align="left"><italic>p</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">GHG emissions&#x02009;&#x02192;&#x02009;Circular economy</td><td char="." align="char">19.231*</td><td char="." align="char">0.000</td><td char="." align="char">19.897*</td><td char="." align="char">0.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Circular economy&#x02009;&#x02192;&#x02009;GHG emissions</td><td char="." align="char">20.312*</td><td char="." align="char">0.00</td><td char="." align="char">21.036*</td><td char="." align="char">0.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left">GHG emissions&#x02009;&#x02192;&#x02009;Technological innovation</td><td char="." align="char">3.787</td><td char="." align="char">0.544</td><td char="." align="char">2.998</td><td char="." align="char">0.636</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Technological innovation&#x02009;&#x02192;&#x02009;GHG emissions</td><td char="." align="char">18.676*</td><td char="." align="char">0.003</td><td char="." align="char">19.687*</td><td char="." align="char">0.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left">GHG emissions&#x02009;&#x02192;&#x02009;Environmental tax</td><td char="." align="char">2.782</td><td char="." align="char">0.502</td><td char="." align="char">1.778</td><td char="." align="char">0.628</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Environmental tax&#x02009;&#x02192;&#x02009;GHG emissions</td><td char="." align="char">9.983*</td><td char="." align="char">0.027</td><td char="." align="char">10.019*</td><td char="." align="char">0.023</td></tr><tr><td align="left">GHG emissions&#x02009;&#x02192;&#x02009;Economic instability</td><td char="." align="char">1.782</td><td char="." align="char">0.318</td><td char="." align="char">2.136</td><td char="." align="char">0.309</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Economic instability&#x02009;&#x02192;&#x02009;GHG emissions</td><td char="." align="char">16.527*</td><td char="." align="char">0.009</td><td char="." align="char">17.390*</td><td char="." align="char">0.007</td></tr><tr><td align="left">GHG emissions&#x02009;&#x02192;&#x02009;Industrialization</td><td char="." align="char">3.672</td><td char="." align="char">0.539</td><td char="." align="char">3.905</td><td char="." align="char">0.532</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Industralization&#x02009;&#x02192;&#x02009;GHG emissions</td><td char="." align="char">18.562*</td><td char="." align="char">0.004</td><td char="." align="char">17.951*</td><td char="." align="char">0.006</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>* indicates the presence of causality</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Conclusions and policy implications</title><sec id="Sec20"><title>Concluding remarks</title><p id="Par78">The Netherlands has committed to the European Union&#x02019;s ambitious targets of reducing GHG emissions by 2030 and achieving carbon neutrality by 2050. To meet these goals, the Dutch government has introduced a range of policy initiatives focused on sustainability and the circular economy. Central to this effort is the aim to transition to a circular economy by 2050, which involves utilizing sustainable and renewable materials, designing products for durability and recyclability, and minimizing waste through practices such as reuse, repair, and refurbishment. The circular economy plays a crucial role in reducing GHG emissions by enhancing the efficiency of material flows and extending the lifespan of products, thus reducing waste. Despite these efforts, a significant challenge remains: the Netherlands consumes approximately 221 million tons of materials annually, with 167 million tons not being reintegrated into the economy, underscoring the need for more effective circular practices.</p><p id="Par79">In examining the long-term and causal effects of the circular economy, technological innovation, environmental tax, economic instability, and industrialization on GHG emissions from 2010Q1 to 2022Q4, this study employed ARDL bounds testing methods to analyze these relationships. The co-integration tests confirmed that GHG emissions, the circular economy, technological innovation, environmental tax, economic instability, and industrialization are interrelated. The ARDL analysis found that the circular economy, technological innovation, and environmental tax have a negative association with GHG emissions, whereas economic instability and industrialization contribute positively to emissions. The finding&#x000a0;highlights the significant impact of the circular economy in reducing GHG emissions through improved material flows and decreased reliance on fossil fuels and non-metallic minerals.</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Policy implications</title><p id="Par80">To advance these findings and facilitate sustainable development, the study recommends several policy measures for Dutch decision-makers. Enhancing construction practices to focus on material reuse and renovation, implementing a circular food system with local production and waste utilization, and transitioning from fossil fuels to renewable energy sources are critical steps. Additionally, boosting the recycling and high-value recycling of imported materials and promoting repair and remanufacturing processes will be vital. Transforming cities into exemplars of the circular economy can drive behavioral and business changes regionally and nationally. Embracing risks and learning from setbacks will be essential for success. Local governments should lead by example, adopting sustainable products and circular infrastructure practices, such as recycled materials for roads and buildings, to position themselves as leaders in the transition to a circular economy and reduce reliance on fossil fuel extraction.<list list-type="order"><list-item><p id="Par81">In line with the European Green Deal and the Netherlands&#x02019; Climate Agreement, policies should encourage sustainable practices in important industries in order to lower GHG emissions and strengthen the country&#x02019;s circular economy. Stronger implementation of carbon pricing mechanisms, such as a more robust carbon tax or an expansion of the EU Emissions Trading System (ETS) to encompass more industries, are among the specific proposals. By supporting technological innovation in recycling, encouraging expanded producer responsibility, and offering tax incentives or subsidies to companies that embrace circular models, the government may help promote the circular economy. Furthermore, strengthening public&#x02013;private partnerships to promote cooperation on waste reduction and green technology will support the EU&#x02019;s goals of reaching net-zero emissions by 2050. These policies will significantly reduce emissions while promoting economic growth through the circular economy, especially when combined with initiatives from the Netherlands&#x02019; Climate Agreement.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par82">To guarantee that manufacturers assume accountability for the whole lifespan of their goods, promoting eco-friendly design and cutting waste, strengthen and broaden extended producer responsibility programs. Create required product information systems that reveal environmental effects and provide financial rewards to companies that embrace eco-design concepts (e.g., recyclability, durability, and the use of sustainable materials).</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par83">To promote sustainable production and consumption, provide financial incentives (such as grants or tax breaks) to companies using circular models like leasing, remanufacturing, and sharing. To lessen dependency on virgin resources, make investments in updating recycling systems, guaranteeing effective waste separation and collection, and providing incentives for the use of recycled materials in manufacturing processes.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par84">To encourage the adoption of circular processes and lower carbon footprints, strengthen carbon pricing systems (such as carbon taxes) and set emission reduction objectives for industries. Include circular economy standards in public procurement guidelines, giving sustainable, recyclable, and repairable goods first priority when it comes to government purchases. This will increase demand for circular solutions.</p></list-item></list></p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Research limitations and future research directions</title><p id="Par85">This study is constrained by its sole emphasis on the Netherlands, and future research might benefit from using panel data to improve the generalizability and robustness of the findings across several nations or regions. Furthermore, while this study used ARDL, FMOLS, DOLS, and the&#x000a0;wavelet coherence analysis, future studies might use more sophisticated approaches to reflect the complex and dynamic nature of energy diversification. Machine learning, for example, has the potential to find non-linear correlations between variables and enhance prediction accuracy. Structural Equation Modeling (SEM) might be used to investigate complex interdependencies across various elements, whereas Granger Causality with Time-Varying Parameters would provide a better understanding of causal links over time, adjusting to changes in economic and policy contexts.</p><p id="Par86">Future research would benefit from broadening the scope of the study to include variables such as natural capital, structural changes, and government governance. Furthermore, it would be interesting to investigate the moderating or mediating role of these variables in the link between the circular economy and GHG emissions. These elements may have a substantial impact on the circular economy and give a more complete knowledge of the dynamics that shape circular economy systems. Furthermore, future research should look at whether including these factors changes the current study&#x02019;s findings, thereby refining policy recommendations and improving the accuracy of circular economy models.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title>Declaration of generative AI in scientific writing</title><p id="Par87">During the preparation of this work the author(s) used ChatGPT in order to improve the readability and language of the manuscript. After using this tool/service, the author(s) reviewed and edited the content as needed and take(s) full responsibility for the content of the published article.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn id="Fn1"><label>1</label><p id="Par5">NEDERLAND FIT FOR 55? Mogelijke gevolgen van het voorgestelde EU-klimaatbeleid (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://open.overheid.nl/documenten/ronl-29514ee5-ee92-44f6-aec0-4910c6afb6f6/pdf">https://open.overheid.nl/documenten/ronl-29514ee5-ee92-44f6-aec0-4910c6afb6f6/pdf</ext-link>) (In Dutch language). Accessed on 15 March 2025.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Publisher's Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>The idea of current paper is presented by Dr. Qamar Abbas who completed this manuscript with the help of the remaining coauthors. Prof. Dr. Abdul Sattar appreciated the idea and helped in data analyses at different stages, while Prof. Dr. Muhammad Imran supervised the whole process and helped in drafting the paper.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>The study received no funding directly or indirectly.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The data used in this study is openly available on the official websites of "World Development Indicators" and "Eurostat".</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par88">The author/s declare no human or animals involved in the study. The idea of current paper is presented by Dr. Qamar Abbas who completed this manuscript with the help of the remaining coauthors. Prof. Dr. Abdul Sattar appreciated the idea and helped in data analyses at different stages, while Prof. Dr. Muhammad Imran supervised the whole process and helped in drafting the paper.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for publications</title><p id="Par89">All authors of the manuscript have read and agreed to its content and are accountable for all aspects of the accuracy and integrity of the manuscript in accordance with ICMJE criteria and is not currently been published or under consideration by another journal.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par90">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abbas</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>HongXing</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramzan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fatima</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Achieving carbon neutrality through digital infrastructure and public debt</article-title><source>Clean Technol Environ Policy</source><year>2024</year><volume>26</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>4455</fpage><lpage>4470</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10098-024-02846-7</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Abbas Q, HongXing Y, Ramzan M, Fatima S. Achieving carbon neutrality through digital infrastructure and public debt. Clean Technol Environ Policy. 2024;26(12):4455&#x02013;70. 10.1007/s10098-024-02846-7.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abbas</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>HongXing</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramzan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fatima</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Total factor productivity and environmental quality: measuring the role of financial stability in BRICS countries</article-title><source>Environ Develop Sustain</source><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10668-024-05395-7</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Abbas Q, HongXing Y, Ramzan M, Fatima S. Total factor productivity and environmental quality: measuring the role of financial stability in BRICS countries. Environ Develop Sustain. 2024. 10.1007/s10668-024-05395-7.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abbas</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Hongxing</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shahbaz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramzan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fatima</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metallic minerals production and environmental sustainability in China: insights using ARDL bounds testing and wavelet coherence approaches</article-title><source>Resour Policy</source><year>2024</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>105037</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.resourpol.2024.105037</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Abbas Q, Hongxing Y, Shahbaz M, Ramzan M, Fatima S. Metallic minerals production and environmental sustainability in China: insights using ARDL bounds testing and wavelet coherence approaches. Resour Policy. 2024;92:105037. 10.1016/j.resourpol.2024.105037.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adebayo</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Odugbesan</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modeling CO2 emissions in South Africa: empirical evidence from ARDL based bounds and wavelet coherence techniques</article-title><source>Environ Sci Pollut Res</source><year>2021</year><volume>28</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>9377</fpage><lpage>9389</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11356-020-11442-3</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Adebayo TS, Odugbesan JA. Modeling CO2 emissions in South Africa: empirical evidence from ARDL based bounds and wavelet coherence techniques. Environ Sci Pollut Res. 2021;28(8):9377&#x02013;89. 10.1007/s11356-020-11442-3.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adebayo</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x000d6;zkan</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Eweade</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Do energy efficiency R&#x00026;D investments and information and communication technologies promote environmental sustainability in Sweden? A quantile-on-quantile KRLS investigation</article-title><source>J Clean Prod</source><year>2024</year><volume>440</volume><fpage>140832</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jclepro.2024.140832</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Adebayo TS, &#x000d6;zkan O, Eweade BS. Do energy efficiency R&#x00026;D investments and information and communication technologies promote environmental sustainability in Sweden? A quantile-on-quantile KRLS investigation. J Clean Prod. 2024;440:140832. 10.1016/j.jclepro.2024.140832.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wahab</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Imran</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ageli</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessing the impact of geopolitical, economic, and institutional factors on China&#x02019;s environmental management in the Russian-Ukraine conflicting era</article-title><source>J Environ Manage</source><year>2024</year><volume>356</volume><fpage>120579</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jenvman.2024.120579</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38503230</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Ahmed B, Wahab S, Rahim S, Imran M, Khan AA, Ageli MM. Assessing the impact of geopolitical, economic, and institutional factors on China&#x02019;s environmental management in the Russian-Ukraine conflicting era. J Environ Manage. 2024;356:120579. 10.1016/j.jenvman.2024.120579.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38503230</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alam</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Baig</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghanem</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanif</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Causality between transportation infrastructure and economic development in Pakistan: an ARDL analysis</article-title><source>Res Transport Econ</source><year>2021</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>100974</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.retrec.2020.100974</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Alam KM, Li X, Baig S, Ghanem O, Hanif S. Causality between transportation infrastructure and economic development in Pakistan: an ARDL analysis. Res Transport Econ. 2021;88:100974. 10.1016/j.retrec.2020.100974.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Amari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mouakhar</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Jarboui</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ICT development, governance quality and the environmental performance: avoidable thresholds from the lower and lower-middle-income countries</article-title><source>Manag Environ Qual</source><year>2022</year><volume>33</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>140</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1108/MEQ-12-2020-0299</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Amari M, Mouakhar K, Jarboui A. ICT development, governance quality and the environmental performance: avoidable thresholds from the lower and lower-middle-income countries. Manag Environ Qual. 2022;33(2):125&#x02013;40. 10.1108/MEQ-12-2020-0299.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Appiah-Otoo</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Acheampong</surname><given-names>AO</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The impact of information and communication technology (ICT) on carbon dioxide emissions: Evidence from heterogeneous ICT countries</article-title><source>Energy Environ</source><year>2022</year><volume>34</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>3080</fpage><lpage>3102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0958305X221118877</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Appiah-Otoo I, Acheampong AO, Song N, Chen X. The impact of information and communication technology (ICT) on carbon dioxide emissions: Evidence from heterogeneous ICT countries. Energy Environ. 2022;34(8):3080&#x02013;102. 10.1177/0958305X221118877.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aslam</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Shahab</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Saleem</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>SSA</given-names></name><name><surname>Javed</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Aslam</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hassan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The nexus of industrialization, GDP per capita and CO2 emission in China</article-title><source>Environ Technol Innov</source><year>2021</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>101674</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eti.2021.101674</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Aslam B, Hu J, Shahab S, Ahmad A, Saleem M, Shah SSA, Javed MS, Aslam MK, Hussain S, Hassan M. The nexus of industrialization, GDP per capita and CO2 emission in China. Environ Technol Innov. 2021;23:101674. 10.1016/j.eti.2021.101674.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Azam</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rehman</surname><given-names>ZU</given-names></name><name><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Causal nexus in industrialization, urbanization, trade openness, and carbon emissions: empirical evidence from OPEC economies</article-title><source>Environ Develop Sustain</source><year>2022</year><volume>24</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>13990</fpage><lpage>14010</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10668-021-02019-2</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Azam M, Rehman ZU, Ibrahim Y. Causal nexus in industrialization, urbanization, trade openness, and carbon emissions: empirical evidence from OPEC economies. Environ Develop Sustain. 2022;24(12):13990&#x02013;4010. 10.1007/s10668-021-02019-2.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bastein</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Roelofs</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Rietveld</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoogendoorn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><source>Opportunities for a circular economy in the Netherlands</source><year>2013</year><publisher-loc>Delft</publisher-loc><publisher-name>TNO</publisher-name></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="book">Bastein A, Roelofs E, Rietveld E, Hoogendoorn A. Opportunities for a circular economy in the Netherlands, vol. 125. Delft: TNO; 2013.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Batini</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Black</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Luca</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><name><surname>Parry</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><source>A comprehensive greenhouse gas mitigation strategy for the Netherlands</source><year>2021</year><publisher-loc>Washington DC</publisher-loc><publisher-name>International Monetary Fund</publisher-name></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="book">Batini N, Black MS, Luca MO, Parry I. A comprehensive greenhouse gas mitigation strategy for the Netherlands. Washington DC: International Monetary Fund; 2021.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bayar</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Gavriletea</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Paun</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of municipal waste recycling and renewable energy consumption on CO2 emissions across the European Union (EU) Member Countries</article-title><source>Sustainability</source><year>2021</year><volume>13</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/su13020656</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Bayar Y, Gavriletea MD, Sauer S, Paun D. Impact of municipal waste recycling and renewable energy consumption on CO2 emissions across the European Union (EU) Member Countries. Sustainability. 2021;13(2):1&#x02013;12.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caglar</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Avci</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x000f6;k&#x000e7;e</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessing the role of green investments and green innovation in ecological sustainability: From a climate action perspective on European countries</article-title><source>Sci Total Environ</source><year>2024</year><volume>928</volume><fpage>172527</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2024.172527</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38631639</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Caglar AE, Avci SB, Ahmed Z, G&#x000f6;k&#x000e7;e N. Assessing the role of green investments and green innovation in ecological sustainability: From a climate action perspective on European countries. Sci Total Environ. 2024;928:172527. 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2024.172527.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38631639</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caglar</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Avci</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x000f6;k&#x000e7;e</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Destek</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A sustainable study of competitive industrial performance amidst environmental quality: new insight from novel Fourier perspective</article-title><source>J Environ Manag</source><year>2024</year><volume>366</volume><fpage>121843</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jenvman.2024.121843</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Caglar AE, Avci SB, G&#x000f6;k&#x000e7;e N, Destek MA. A sustainable study of competitive industrial performance amidst environmental quality: new insight from novel Fourier perspective. J Environ Manag. 2024;366:121843. 10.1016/j.jenvman.2024.121843.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caglar</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bortecine</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Muhammet</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Destek</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Investigation of the effect of natural resource dependence on environmental sustainability under the novel load capacity curve hypothesis</article-title><source>Int J Sustain Develop World Ecol</source><year>2024</year><volume>31</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>431</fpage><lpage>446</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13504509.2023.2296495</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Caglar AE, Bortecine AS, Muhammet D, Destek MA. Investigation of the effect of natural resource dependence on environmental sustainability under the novel load capacity curve hypothesis. Int J Sustain Develop World Ecol. 2024;31(4):431&#x02013;46. 10.1080/13504509.2023.2296495.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caglar</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Da&#x0015f;tan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Avci</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Persistence of disaggregate energy RD&#x00026;D expenditures in top-five economies: evidence from artificial neural network approach</article-title><source>Appl Energy</source><year>2024</year><volume>365</volume><fpage>123216</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apenergy.2024.123216</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Caglar AE, Da&#x0015f;tan M, Avci SB. Persistence of disaggregate energy RD&#x00026;D expenditures in top-five economies: evidence from artificial neural network approach. Appl Energy. 2024;365:123216. 10.1016/j.apenergy.2024.123216.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caglar</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Da&#x0015f;tan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Avci</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x000f6;nen&#x000e7;</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modeling the influence of mineral rents and low-carbon energy on environmental quality: new insights from a sustainability perspective</article-title><source>Nat Resour Forum</source><year>2024</year><volume>48</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1456</fpage><lpage>1476</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1477-8947.12472</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Caglar AE, Da&#x0015f;tan M, Avci SB, Ahmed Z, G&#x000f6;nen&#x000e7; S. Modeling the influence of mineral rents and low-carbon energy on environmental quality: new insights from a sustainability perspective. Nat Resour Forum. 2024;48(4):1456&#x02013;76. 10.1111/1477-8947.12472.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caglar</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x000f6;k&#x000e7;e</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x0015e;ahin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sustaining environment through municipal solid waste: evidence from European Union economies</article-title><source>Environ Sci Pollut Res</source><year>2024</year><volume>31</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>6040</fpage><lpage>6053</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11356-023-31494-5</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">Caglar AE, G&#x000f6;k&#x000e7;e N, &#x0015e;ahin F. Sustaining environment through municipal solid waste: evidence from European Union economies. Environ Sci Pollut Res. 2024;31(4):6040&#x02013;53. 10.1007/s11356-023-31494-5.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caglar</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Senem</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Destek</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The influence of nuclear energy research and development investments on environmental sustainability: evidence from the United States and France</article-title><source>Int J Sustain Dev World Ecol</source><year>2024</year><volume>31</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>861</fpage><lpage>872</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13504509.2024.2341797</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Caglar AE, Senem G, Destek MA. The influence of nuclear energy research and development investments on environmental sustainability: evidence from the United States and France. Int J Sustain Dev World Ecol. 2024;31(7):861&#x02013;72. 10.1080/13504509.2024.2341797.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Innovating sustainability: VQA-based AI for carbon neutrality challenges</article-title><source>J Organ End User Comput</source><year>2024</year><volume>36</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4018/JOEUC.337606</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">Chen Y, Li Q, Liu J. Innovating sustainability: VQA-based AI for carbon neutrality challenges. J Organ End User Comput. 2024;36(1):1&#x02013;22. 10.4018/JOEUC.337606.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Imran</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The impact of resource spatial mismatch on the configuration analysis of agricultural green total factor productivity</article-title><source>Agriculture</source><year>2024</year><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>23</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/agriculture15010023</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Chen P, Ding X, Chen M, Song H, Imran M. The impact of resource spatial mismatch on the configuration analysis of agricultural green total factor productivity. Agriculture. 2024;15(1):23. 10.3390/agriculture15010023.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cudjoe</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of the potential energy and environmental benefits of solid waste recycling in China</article-title><source>J Environ Manag</source><year>2021</year><volume>295</volume><fpage>113072</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jenvman.2021.113072</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">Cudjoe D, Wang H, Zhu B. Assessment of the potential energy and environmental benefits of solid waste recycling in China. J Environ Manag. 2021;295:113072. 10.1016/j.jenvman.2021.113072.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dehghan Shabani</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Shahnazi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Energy consumption, carbon dioxide emissions, information and communications technology, and gross domestic product in Iranian economic sectors: a panel causality analysis</article-title><source>Energy</source><year>2019</year><volume>169</volume><fpage>1064</fpage><lpage>1078</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.energy.2018.11.062</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="journal">Dehghan Shabani Z, Shahnazi R. Energy consumption, carbon dioxide emissions, information and communications technology, and gross domestic product in Iranian economic sectors: a panel causality analysis. Energy. 2019;169:1064&#x02013;78. 10.1016/j.energy.2018.11.062.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR26" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Do&#x0011f;an</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Diep Truong</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name><surname>Balsalobre-Lorente</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How environmental taxes and carbon emissions are related in the G7 economies?</article-title><source>Renewable Energy</source><year>2022</year><volume>187</volume><fpage>645</fpage><lpage>656</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.renene.2022.01.077</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26" publication-type="journal">Do&#x0011f;an B, Chu LK, Ghosh S, Diep Truong HH, Balsalobre-Lorente D. How environmental taxes and carbon emissions are related in the G7 economies? Renewable Energy. 2022;187:645&#x02013;56. 10.1016/j.renene.2022.01.077.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Economy C. 2023. The circularity gap report 2020. Amsterdam. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.circularity-gap.world">https://www.circularity-gap.world</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR28" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eichner</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Pethig</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Kantians defy the economists&#x02019; mantra of uniform Pigovian emissions taxes</article-title><source>Ecol Econ</source><year>2022</year><volume>200</volume><fpage>107514</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecolecon.2022.107514</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28" publication-type="journal">Eichner T, Pethig R. Kantians defy the economists&#x02019; mantra of uniform Pigovian emissions taxes. Ecol Econ. 2022;200:107514. 10.1016/j.ecolecon.2022.107514.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR29" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ekins</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pollitt</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Summerton</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Chewpreecha</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Increasing carbon and material productivity through environmental tax reform</article-title><source>Energy Policy</source><year>2012</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>365</fpage><lpage>376</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.enpol.2011.11.094</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29" publication-type="journal">Ekins P, Pollitt H, Summerton P, Chewpreecha U. Increasing carbon and material productivity through environmental tax reform. Energy Policy. 2012;42:365&#x02013;76. 10.1016/j.enpol.2011.11.094.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR30" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Emre Caglar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x000f6;k&#x000e7;e</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Balsalobre-Lorente</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Towards the vision of going green: the role of different energy research and development investments, urbanization and income in load capacity factor</article-title><source>Sustainable Energy Technol Assessments</source><year>2024</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>103888</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.seta.2024.103888</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30" publication-type="journal">Emre Caglar A, G&#x000f6;k&#x000e7;e N, Balsalobre-Lorente D. Towards the vision of going green: the role of different energy research and development investments, urbanization and income in load capacity factor. Sustainable Energy Technol Assessments. 2024;68:103888. 10.1016/j.seta.2024.103888.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR31" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Erum</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Musa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tufail</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Said</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zakaria</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of the circular economy on human development: evidence from Germany</article-title><source>Environ Develop Sustainability</source><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10668-024-04918-6</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR31" publication-type="journal">Erum N, Musa K, Tufail S, Said J, Zakaria NB. Impact of the circular economy on human development: evidence from Germany. Environ Develop Sustainability. 2024. 10.1007/s10668-024-04918-6.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR32" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eweade</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Akadiri</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Olusoga</surname><given-names>KO</given-names></name><name><surname>Bamidele</surname><given-names>RO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The symbiotic effects of energy consumption, globalization, and combustible renewables and waste on ecological footprint in the United Kingdom</article-title><source>Nat Res Forum</source><year>2024</year><volume>48</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>274</fpage><lpage>291</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1477-8947.12392</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32" publication-type="journal">Eweade BS, Akadiri AC, Olusoga KO, Bamidele RO. The symbiotic effects of energy consumption, globalization, and combustible renewables and waste on ecological footprint in the United Kingdom. Nat Res Forum. 2024;48(1):274&#x02013;91. 10.1111/1477-8947.12392.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR33" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eweade</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x000fc;ng&#x000f6;r</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Karlilar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The determinants of ecological footprint in the UK: The role of transportation activities, renewable energy, trade openness, and globalization</article-title><source>Environ Sci Pollut Res</source><year>2023</year><volume>30</volume><issue>58</issue><fpage>122153</fpage><lpage>122164</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11356-023-30759-3</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR33" publication-type="journal">Eweade BS, G&#x000fc;ng&#x000f6;r H, Karlilar S. The determinants of ecological footprint in the UK: The role of transportation activities, renewable energy, trade openness, and globalization. Environ Sci Pollut Res. 2023;30(58):122153&#x02013;64. 10.1007/s11356-023-30759-3.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR34" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eweade</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Joof</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Adebayo</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analyzing India&#x02019;s coal, natural gas, and biomass energy consumption: evidence from a Fourier technique to promote sustainable development</article-title><source>Nat Res Forum</source><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1477-8947.12423</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR34" publication-type="journal">Eweade BS, Joof F, Adebayo TS. Analyzing India&#x02019;s coal, natural gas, and biomass energy consumption: evidence from a Fourier technique to promote sustainable development. Nat Res Forum. 2024. 10.1111/1477-8947.12423.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR35" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eweade</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Karlilar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pata</surname><given-names>UK</given-names></name><name><surname>Adeshola</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Olaifa</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Examining the asymmetric effects of fossil fuel consumption, foreign direct investment, and globalization on ecological footprint in Mexico</article-title><source>Sustainable Develop</source><year>2024</year><volume>32</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>2899</fpage><lpage>2909</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/sd.2825</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR35" publication-type="journal">Eweade BS, Karlilar S, Pata UK, Adeshola I, Olaifa JO. Examining the asymmetric effects of fossil fuel consumption, foreign direct investment, and globalization on ecological footprint in Mexico. Sustainable Develop. 2024;32(4):2899&#x02013;909. 10.1002/sd.2825.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR36" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Figge</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Thorpe</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Gutberlet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Definitions of the circular economy: circularity matters</article-title><source>Ecol Economics</source><year>2023</year><volume>208</volume><fpage>107823</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecolecon.2023.107823</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR36" publication-type="journal">Figge F, Thorpe AS, Gutberlet M. Definitions of the circular economy: circularity matters. Ecol Economics. 2023;208:107823. 10.1016/j.ecolecon.2023.107823.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR37" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Asymmetric impacts of climate policy uncertainty, investor sentiment on energy prices and renewable energy consumption: evidence from NARDL and wavelet coherence</article-title><source>J Environ Manag</source><year>2024</year><volume>367</volume><fpage>122057</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jenvman.2024.122057</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR37" publication-type="journal">Fu L, Tu X, Liao J. Asymmetric impacts of climate policy uncertainty, investor sentiment on energy prices and renewable energy consumption: evidence from NARDL and wavelet coherence. J Environ Manag. 2024;367:122057. 10.1016/j.jenvman.2024.122057.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR38" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gallego-Schmid</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H-M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharmina</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mendoza</surname><given-names>JMF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Links between circular economy and climate change mitigation in the built environment</article-title><source>J Cleaner Product</source><year>2020</year><volume>260</volume><fpage>121115</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jclepro.2020.121115</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR38" publication-type="journal">Gallego-Schmid A, Chen H-M, Sharmina M, Mendoza JMF. Links between circular economy and climate change mitigation in the built environment. J Cleaner Product. 2020;260:121115. 10.1016/j.jclepro.2020.121115.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR39" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garrone</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Grilli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Is there a relationship between public expenditures in energy R&#x00026;D and carbon emissions per GDP? An empirical investigation</article-title><source>Energy Policy</source><year>2010</year><volume>38</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>5600</fpage><lpage>5613</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.enpol.2010.04.057</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR39" publication-type="journal">Garrone P, Grilli L. Is there a relationship between public expenditures in energy R&#x00026;D and carbon emissions per GDP? An empirical investigation. Energy Policy. 2010;38(10):5600&#x02013;13. 10.1016/j.enpol.2010.04.057.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR40" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Imran</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Natural resource-driven prosperity: unveiling the catalysts of sustainable economic development in the United States</article-title><source>Nat Res Forum</source><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1477-8947.12456</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR40" publication-type="journal">Ge X, Imran M, Ali K. Natural resource-driven prosperity: unveiling the catalysts of sustainable economic development in the United States. Nat Res Forum. 2024. 10.1111/1477-8947.12456.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR41" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Geisendorf</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pietrulla</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The circular economy and circular economic concepts&#x02014;a literature analysis and redefinition</article-title><source>Thunderbird Int Bus Rev</source><year>2018</year><volume>60</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>771</fpage><lpage>782</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/tie.21924</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR41" publication-type="journal">Geisendorf S, Pietrulla F. The circular economy and circular economic concepts&#x02014;a literature analysis and redefinition. Thunderbird Int Bus Rev. 2018;60(5):771&#x02013;82. 10.1002/tie.21924.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR42" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghazouani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jebli</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Shahzad</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impacts of environmental taxes and technologies on greenhouse gas emissions: contextual evidence from leading emitter European countries</article-title><source>Environ Sci Pollut Res</source><year>2021</year><volume>28</volume><issue>18</issue><fpage>22758</fpage><lpage>22767</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11356-020-11911-9</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR42" publication-type="journal">Ghazouani A, Jebli MB, Shahzad U. Impacts of environmental taxes and technologies on greenhouse gas emissions: contextual evidence from leading emitter European countries. Environ Sci Pollut Res. 2021;28(18):22758&#x02013;67. 10.1007/s11356-020-11911-9.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR43" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghazouani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Ben Jebli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shahzad</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exploring the role of carbon taxation policies on CO2 emissions: contextual evidence from tax implementation and non-implementation european countries</article-title><source>Sustainability</source><year>2020</year><volume>12</volume><issue>20</issue><fpage>8680</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/su12208680</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR43" publication-type="journal">Ghazouani A, Xia W, Ben Jebli M, Shahzad U. Exploring the role of carbon taxation policies on CO2 emissions: contextual evidence from tax implementation and non-implementation european countries. Sustainability. 2020;12(20):8680.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR44" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghisellini</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Cialani</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ulgiati</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A review on circular economy: the expected transition to a balanced interplay of environmental and economic systems</article-title><source>J Clean Prod</source><year>2016</year><volume>114</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jclepro.2015.09.007</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR44" publication-type="journal">Ghisellini P, Cialani C, Ulgiati S. A review on circular economy: the expected transition to a balanced interplay of environmental and economic systems. J Clean Prod. 2016;114:11&#x02013;32. 10.1016/j.jclepro.2015.09.007.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR45" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goupillaud</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Grossmann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Morlet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cycle-octave and related transforms in seismic signal analysis</article-title><source>Geoexploration</source><year>1984</year><volume>23</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0016-7142(84)90025-5</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR45" publication-type="journal">Goupillaud P, Grossmann A, Morlet J. Cycle-octave and related transforms in seismic signal analysis. Geoexploration. 1984;23(1):85&#x02013;102. 10.1016/0016-7142(84)90025-5.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR46" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recycling is not enough to make the world a greener place: prospects for the circular economy</article-title><source>Green Carbon</source><year>2023</year><volume>1</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>150</fpage><lpage>153</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.greenca.2023.10.006</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR46" publication-type="journal">Guo J, Ali S, Xu M. Recycling is not enough to make the world a greener place: prospects for the circular economy. Green Carbon. 2023;1(2):150&#x02013;3. 10.1016/j.greenca.2023.10.006.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR47" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hailemariam</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Erdiaw-Kwasie</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Towards a circular economy: implications for emission reduction and environmental sustainability</article-title><source>Bus Strategy Environ</source><year>2023</year><volume>32</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1951</fpage><lpage>1965</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bse.3229</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR47" publication-type="journal">Hailemariam A, Erdiaw-Kwasie MO. Towards a circular economy: implications for emission reduction and environmental sustainability. Bus Strategy Environ. 2023;32(4):1951&#x02013;65. 10.1002/bse.3229.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR48" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hartley</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Roosendaal</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirchherr</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Barriers to the circular economy: the case of the Dutch technical and interior textiles industries</article-title><source>J Industrial Ecol</source><year>2022</year><volume>26</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>477</fpage><lpage>490</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jiec.13196</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR48" publication-type="journal">Hartley K, Roosendaal J, Kirchherr J. Barriers to the circular economy: the case of the Dutch technical and interior textiles industries. J Industrial Ecol. 2022;26(2):477&#x02013;90. 10.1111/jiec.13196.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR49" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hondroyiannis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Sardianou</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Nikou</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Evangelinos</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nikolaou</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Circular economy and macroeconomic performance: evidence across 28 European countries</article-title><source>Ecol Econ</source><year>2024</year><volume>215</volume><fpage>108002</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecolecon.2023.108002</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR49" publication-type="journal">Hondroyiannis G, Sardianou E, Nikou V, Evangelinos K, Nikolaou I. Circular economy and macroeconomic performance: evidence across 28 European countries. Ecol Econ. 2024;215:108002. 10.1016/j.ecolecon.2023.108002.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR50" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Houston</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Reay</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The impact of information and communication technology on GHG emissions: how green are virtual worlds?</article-title><source>Carbon Manag</source><year>2011</year><volume>2</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>629</fpage><lpage>643</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4155/cmt.11.62</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR50" publication-type="journal">Houston K, Reay DS. The impact of information and communication technology on GHG emissions: how green are virtual worlds? Carbon Manag. 2011;2(6):629&#x02013;43. 10.4155/cmt.11.62.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR51" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>C-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ch</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Aqdas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Chupradit</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nawaz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A step towards sustainable environment in China: the role of eco-innovation renewable energy and environmental taxes</article-title><source>J Environ Manag</source><year>2021</year><volume>299</volume><fpage>113609</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jenvman.2021.113609</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR51" publication-type="journal">Hsu C-C, Zhang Y, Ch P, Aqdas R, Chupradit S, Nawaz A. A step towards sustainable environment in China: the role of eco-innovation renewable energy and environmental taxes. J Environ Manag. 2021;299:113609. 10.1016/j.jenvman.2021.113609.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR52" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Weng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spatial network and driving factors of low-carbon patent applications in China from a public health perspective</article-title><source>Front Public Health</source><year>2023</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1121860</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2023.1121860</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36875394</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR52" publication-type="journal">Hu F, Qiu L, Xiang Y, Wei S, Sun H, Hu H, Weng X, Mao L, Zeng M. Spatial network and driving factors of low-carbon patent applications in China from a public health perspective. Front Public Health. 2023;11:1121860. 10.3389/fpubh.2023.1121860.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36875394</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR53" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Imran</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Alam</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Jijian</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Ozturk</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Wahab</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Do&#x0011f;an</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>From resource curse to green growth: exploring the role of energy utilization and natural resource abundance in economic development</article-title><source>Nat Res Forum</source><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1477-8947.12461</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR53" publication-type="journal">Imran M, Alam MS, Jijian Z, Ozturk I, Wahab S, Do&#x0011f;an M. From resource curse to green growth: exploring the role of energy utilization and natural resource abundance in economic development. Nat Res Forum. 2024. 10.1111/1477-8947.12461.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR54" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Imran</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Alam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wahab</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tufail</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jijian</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The implications of the ecological footprint and renewable energy usage on the financial stability of South Asian countries</article-title><source>Financial Innov</source><year>2024</year><volume>10</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40854-024-00627-1</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR54" publication-type="journal">Imran M, Khan MK, Alam S, Wahab S, Tufail M, Jijian Z. The implications of the ecological footprint and renewable energy usage on the financial stability of South Asian countries. Financial Innov. 2024;10(1):1&#x02013;23. 10.1186/s40854-024-00627-1.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR55" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Imran</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Wahab</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Jijian</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The paradox of resource-richness: unraveling the effects on financial markets in natural resource abundant economies</article-title><source>Financial Innov</source><year>2025</year><volume>11</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40854-024-00696-2</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR55" publication-type="journal">Imran M, Khan MK, Wahab S, Ahmed B, Jijian Z. The paradox of resource-richness: unraveling the effects on financial markets in natural resource abundant economies. Financial Innov. 2025;11(1):1&#x02013;30. 10.1186/s40854-024-00696-2.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR56" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Imran</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tufail</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wahab</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoo</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>From resources to resilience: understanding the impact of standard of living and energy consumption on natural resource rent in Asia</article-title><source>Energ Strat Rev</source><year>2025</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>101590</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.esr.2024.101590</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR56" publication-type="journal">Imran M, Tufail M, Mo C, Wahab S, Khan MK, Hoo WC, Ling Z. From resources to resilience: understanding the impact of standard of living and energy consumption on natural resource rent in Asia. Energ Strat Rev. 2025;57: 101590. 10.1016/j.esr.2024.101590.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR57" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jarque</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bera</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A test for normality of observations and regression residuals</article-title><source>Int Statist Rev</source><year>1987</year><volume>55</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>163</fpage><lpage>172</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/1403192</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR57" publication-type="journal">Jarque CM, Bera AK. A test for normality of observations and regression residuals. Int Statist Rev. 1987;55(2):163&#x02013;72. 10.2307/1403192.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR58" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kirikkaleli</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sowah</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A wavelet coherence analysis: nexus between urbanization and environmental sustainability</article-title><source>Environ Sci Pollut Res</source><year>2020</year><volume>27</volume><issue>24</issue><fpage>30295</fpage><lpage>30305</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11356-020-09305-y</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR58" publication-type="journal">Kirikkaleli D, Sowah JK. A wavelet coherence analysis: nexus between urbanization and environmental sustainability. Environ Sci Pollut Res. 2020;27(24):30295&#x02013;305. 10.1007/s11356-020-09305-y.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR59" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lamma</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The impact of recycling in preserving the environment</article-title><source>IJAR</source><year>2021</year><volume>7</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>297</fpage><lpage>302</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR59" publication-type="journal">Lamma OA. The impact of recycling in preserving the environment. IJAR. 2021;7(11):297&#x02013;302.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR60" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bian</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sani Mohammed</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Green environment and circular economy: a state-of-the-art analysis</article-title><source>Sustainable Energy Technol Assessments</source><year>2022</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>102106</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.seta.2022.102106</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR60" publication-type="journal">Li J, Song G, Cai M, Bian J, Sani Mohammed B. Green environment and circular economy: a state-of-the-art analysis. Sustainable Energy Technol Assessments. 2022;52:102106. 10.1016/j.seta.2022.102106.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR61" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Artificial intelligence for reducing the carbon emissions of 5G networks in China</article-title><source>Nature Sustainability</source><year>2023</year><volume>6</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1522</fpage><lpage>1523</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41893-023-01208-3</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR61" publication-type="journal">Li T, Li Y. Artificial intelligence for reducing the carbon emissions of 5G networks in China. Nature Sustainability. 2023;6(12):1522&#x02013;3. 10.1038/s41893-023-01208-3.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR62" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>ZhouJinLiJiang</surname><given-names>YDYT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Carbon emissions of 5G mobile networks in China</article-title><source>Nature Sustainability</source><year>2023</year><volume>6</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1620</fpage><lpage>1631</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41893-023-01206-5</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR62" publication-type="journal">Li T, Yu L, Ma Y, Duan T, Huang W, ZhouJinLiJiang YDYT. Carbon emissions of 5G mobile networks in China. Nature Sustainability. 2023;6(12):1620&#x02013;31. 10.1038/s41893-023-01206-5.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR63" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lieder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rashid</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Towards circular economy implementation: a comprehensive review in context of manufacturing industry</article-title><source>J Clean Prod</source><year>2016</year><volume>115</volume><fpage>36</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jclepro.2015.12.042</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR63" publication-type="journal">Lieder M, Rashid A. Towards circular economy implementation: a comprehensive review in context of manufacturing industry. J Clean Prod. 2016;115:36&#x02013;51. 10.1016/j.jclepro.2015.12.042.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR64" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Faridi</surname><given-names>MZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Nazar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Green shoots in uncertain times: decoding the asymmetric nexus between monetary policy uncertainty and renewable energy</article-title><source>Energy Environ</source><year>2025</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0958305X241310198</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR64" publication-type="journal">Liu K, Luo J, Faridi MZ, Nazar R, Ali S. Green shoots in uncertain times: decoding the asymmetric nexus between monetary policy uncertainty and renewable energy. Energy Environ. 2025. 10.1177/0958305X241310198.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR65" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cote</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How does circular economy respond to greenhouse gas emissions reduction: an analysis of Chinese plastic recycling industries</article-title><source>Renew Sustain Energy Rev</source><year>2018</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>1162</fpage><lpage>1169</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rser.2018.04.038</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR65" publication-type="journal">Liu Z, Adams M, Cote RP, Chen Q, Wu R, Wen Z, Liu W, Dong L. How does circular economy respond to greenhouse gas emissions reduction: an analysis of Chinese plastic recycling industries. Renew Sustain Energy Rev. 2018;91:1162&#x02013;9. 10.1016/j.rser.2018.04.038.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR66" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Can the energy conservation and emission reduction demonstration city policy enhance urban domestic waste control? Evidence from 283 cities in China</article-title><source>Cities</source><year>2024</year><volume>154</volume><fpage>105323</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cities.2024.105323</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR66" publication-type="journal">Ma Q, Zhang Y, Hu F, Zhou H. Can the energy conservation and emission reduction demonstration city policy enhance urban domestic waste control? Evidence from 283 cities in China. Cities. 2024;154:105323. 10.1016/j.cities.2024.105323.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR67" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Magazzino</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mele</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarkodie</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Waste generation, wealth and GHG emissions from the waste sector: is Denmark on the path towards circular economy?</article-title><source>Sci Total Environ</source><year>2021</year><volume>755</volume><fpage>142510</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.142510</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33032130</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR67" publication-type="journal">Magazzino C, Mele M, Schneider N, Sarkodie SA. Waste generation, wealth and GHG emissions from the waste sector: is Denmark on the path towards circular economy? Sci Total Environ. 2021;755:142510. 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.142510.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33032130</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR68" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mallick</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Salling</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name><name><surname>Pigosso</surname><given-names>DCA</given-names></name><name><surname>McAloone</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Designing and operationalising extended producer responsibility under the EU Green Deal</article-title><source>Environ Challenges</source><year>2024</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>100977</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envc.2024.100977</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR68" publication-type="journal">Mallick PK, Salling KB, Pigosso DCA, McAloone TC. Designing and operationalising extended producer responsibility under the EU Green Deal. Environ Challenges. 2024;16:100977. 10.1016/j.envc.2024.100977.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR69" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Malmodin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x000f6;vehagen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergmark</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lund&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ICT sector electricity consumption and greenhouse gas emissions &#x02013; 2020 outcome</article-title><source>Telecommunications Policy</source><year>2024</year><volume>48</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>102701</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.telpol.2023.102701</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR69" publication-type="journal">Malmodin J, L&#x000f6;vehagen N, Bergmark P, Lund&#x000e9;n D. ICT sector electricity consumption and greenhouse gas emissions &#x02013; 2020 outcome. Telecommunications Policy. 2024;48(3):102701. 10.1016/j.telpol.2023.102701.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR70" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mazur-Wierzbicka</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Circular economy: advancement of European Union countries</article-title><source>Environ Sci Europe</source><year>2021</year><volume>33</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>111</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12302-021-00549-0</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR70" publication-type="journal">Mazur-Wierzbicka E. Circular economy: advancement of European Union countries. Environ Sci Europe. 2021;33(1):111. 10.1186/s12302-021-00549-0.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR71"><label>71.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR71" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Michelini</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Moraes</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Cunha</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>JMH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ometto</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>From linear to circular economy: PSS conducting the transition</article-title><source>Proc CIRP</source><year>2017</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>2</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.procir.2017.03.012</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR71" publication-type="journal">Michelini G, Moraes RN, Cunha RN, Costa JMH, Ometto AR. From linear to circular economy: PSS conducting the transition. Proc CIRP. 2017;64:2&#x02013;6. 10.1016/j.procir.2017.03.012.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR72"><label>72.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR72" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mohamed Sultan</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mativenga</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>2019/06/20/). Sustainable Location Identification Decision Protocol (SuLIDeP) for determining the location of recycling centres in a circular economy</article-title><source>J Clean Prod</source><year>2019</year><volume>223</volume><fpage>508</fpage><lpage>521</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jclepro.2019.03.104</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR72" publication-type="journal">Mohamed Sultan AA, Mativenga PT. 2019/06/20/). Sustainable Location Identification Decision Protocol (SuLIDeP) for determining the location of recycling centres in a circular economy. J Clean Prod. 2019;223:508&#x02013;21. 10.1016/j.jclepro.2019.03.104.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR73"><label>73.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR73" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Narayan</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The saving and investment nexus for China: evidence from cointegration tests</article-title><source>Appl Economics</source><year>2005</year><volume>37</volume><issue>17</issue><fpage>1979</fpage><lpage>1990</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00036840500278103</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR73" publication-type="journal">Narayan PK. The saving and investment nexus for China: evidence from cointegration tests. Appl Economics. 2005;37(17):1979&#x02013;90. 10.1080/00036840500278103.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR74"><label>74.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR74" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neves</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Marques</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Drivers and barriers in the transition from a linear economy to a circular economy</article-title><source>J Cleaner Production</source><year>2022</year><volume>341</volume><fpage>130865</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jclepro.2022.130865</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR74" publication-type="journal">Neves SA, Marques AC. Drivers and barriers in the transition from a linear economy to a circular economy. J Cleaner Production. 2022;341:130865. 10.1016/j.jclepro.2022.130865.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR75"><label>75.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR75" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ozili</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sustainable development and bank non-performing loans: are they correlated?</article-title><source>Arab Gulf J Scientific Res</source><year>2023</year><volume>42</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>551</fpage><lpage>565</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1108/AGJSR-01-2023-0028</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR75" publication-type="journal">Ozili PK. Sustainable development and bank non-performing loans: are they correlated? Arab Gulf J Scientific Res. 2023;42(3):551&#x02013;65. 10.1108/AGJSR-01-2023-0028.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR76"><label>76.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR76" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ozkan</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Eweade</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Usman</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessing the impact of resource efficiency, renewable energy R&#x00026;D spending, and green technologies on environmental sustainability in Germany: evidence from a Wavelet Quantile-on-Quantile Regression</article-title><source>J Cleaner Product</source><year>2024</year><volume>450</volume><fpage>141992</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jclepro.2024.141992</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR76" publication-type="journal">Ozkan O, Eweade BS, Usman O. Assessing the impact of resource efficiency, renewable energy R&#x00026;D spending, and green technologies on environmental sustainability in Germany: evidence from a Wavelet Quantile-on-Quantile Regression. J Cleaner Product. 2024;450:141992. 10.1016/j.jclepro.2024.141992.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR77"><label>77.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR77" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parajuly</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitzpatrick</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Muldoon</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuehr</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Behavioral change for the circular economy: a review with focus on electronic waste management in the EU</article-title><source>Resources Conserv Recycling X</source><year>2020</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>100035</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rcrx.2020.100035</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR77" publication-type="journal">Parajuly K, Fitzpatrick C, Muldoon O, Kuehr R. Behavioral change for the circular economy: a review with focus on electronic waste management in the EU. Resources Conserv Recycling X. 2020;6:100035. 10.1016/j.rcrx.2020.100035.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR78"><label>78.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR78" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pata</surname><given-names>UK</given-names></name><name><surname>Karlilar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Eweade</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An environmental assessment of non-renewable, modern renewable, and combustible renewable energy in Cameroon</article-title><source>Environ Develop Sustainability</source><year>2025</year><volume>27</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>7279</fpage><lpage>7296</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10668-023-04192-y</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR78" publication-type="journal">Pata UK, Karlilar S, Eweade BS. An environmental assessment of non-renewable, modern renewable, and combustible renewable energy in Cameroon. Environ Develop Sustainability. 2025;27(3):7279&#x02013;96. 10.1007/s10668-023-04192-y.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR79"><label>79.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR79" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pata</surname><given-names>UK</given-names></name><name><surname>Karlilar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kartal</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>On the road to sustainable development: the role of ICT and R&#x00026;D investments in renewable and nuclear energy on energy transition in Germany</article-title><source>Clean Technol Environ Policy</source><year>2024</year><volume>26</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>2323</fpage><lpage>2335</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10098-023-02677-y</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR79" publication-type="journal">Pata UK, Karlilar S, Kartal MT. On the road to sustainable development: the role of ICT and R&#x00026;D investments in renewable and nuclear energy on energy transition in Germany. Clean Technol Environ Policy. 2024;26(7):2323&#x02013;35. 10.1007/s10098-023-02677-y.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR80"><label>80.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR80" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pesaran</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bounds testing approaches to the analysis of level relationships</article-title><source>J Appl Econometrics</source><year>2001</year><volume>16</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>289</fpage><lpage>326</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jae.616</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR80" publication-type="journal">Pesaran MH, Shin Y, Smith RJ. Bounds testing approaches to the analysis of level relationships. J Appl Econometrics. 2001;16(3):289&#x02013;326. 10.1002/jae.616.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR81"><label>81.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR81" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raihan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Muhtasim</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Farhana</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pavel</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Faruk</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahmood</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nexus between carbon emissions, economic growth, renewable energy use, urbanization, industrialization, technological innovation, and forest area towards achieving environmental sustainability in Bangladesh</article-title><source>Energy Climate Change</source><year>2022</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>100080</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.egycc.2022.100080</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR81" publication-type="journal">Raihan A, Muhtasim DA, Farhana S, Pavel MI, Faruk O, Rahman M, Mahmood A. Nexus between carbon emissions, economic growth, renewable energy use, urbanization, industrialization, technological innovation, and forest area towards achieving environmental sustainability in Bangladesh. Energy Climate Change. 2022;3:100080. 10.1016/j.egycc.2022.100080.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR82"><label>82.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR82" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ryen</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaustad</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Babbitt</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Babbitt</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ecological foraging models as inspiration for optimized recycling systems in the circular economy</article-title><source>Resour Conserv Recycl</source><year>2018</year><volume>135</volume><fpage>48</fpage><lpage>57</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.resconrec.2017.08.006</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR82" publication-type="journal">Ryen EG, Gaustad G, Babbitt CW, Babbitt G. Ecological foraging models as inspiration for optimized recycling systems in the circular economy. Resour Conserv Recycl. 2018;135:48&#x02013;57. 10.1016/j.resconrec.2017.08.006.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR83"><label>83.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR83" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saxena</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Water quality, air pollution, and climate change: investigating the environmental impacts of industrialization and urbanization</article-title><source>Water Air Soil Pollut</source><year>2025</year><volume>236</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>73</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11270-024-07702-4</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR83" publication-type="journal">Saxena V. Water quality, air pollution, and climate change: investigating the environmental impacts of industrialization and urbanization. Water Air Soil Pollut. 2025;236(2):73. 10.1007/s11270-024-07702-4.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR84"><label>84.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR84" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shahbaz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Siddiqui</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Financial development as a new determinant of energy diversification: The role of natural capital and structural changes in Australia</article-title><source>Energy Economics</source><year>2023</year><volume>126</volume><fpage>106926</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eneco.2023.106926</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR84" publication-type="journal">Shahbaz M, Siddiqui A, Ahmad S, Jiao Z. Financial development as a new determinant of energy diversification: The role of natural capital and structural changes in Australia. Energy Economics. 2023;126:106926. 10.1016/j.eneco.2023.106926.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR85"><label>85.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR85" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shahzad</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Elheddad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Swart</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dogan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of biomass energy consumption and economic complexity on environmental sustainability in G7 economies</article-title><source>Bus Strategy Environ</source><year>2023</year><volume>32</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>781</fpage><lpage>801</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bse.3175</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR85" publication-type="journal">Shahzad U, Elheddad M, Swart J, Ghosh S, Dogan B. The role of biomass energy consumption and economic complexity on environmental sustainability in G7 economies. Bus Strategy Environ. 2023;32(1):781&#x02013;801. 10.1002/bse.3175.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR86"><label>86.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR86" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sig&#x000fc;enza</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Cucurachi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tukker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Circular business models of washing machines in the Netherlands: material and climate change implications toward 2050</article-title><source>Sustainable Product Consumption</source><year>2021</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>1084</fpage><lpage>1098</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.spc.2021.01.011</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR86" publication-type="journal">Sig&#x000fc;enza CP, Cucurachi S, Tukker A. Circular business models of washing machines in the Netherlands: material and climate change implications toward 2050. Sustainable Product Consumption. 2021;26:1084&#x02013;98. 10.1016/j.spc.2021.01.011.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR87"><label>87.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR87" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sikder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Huai</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>KwameYeboah</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Dou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The integrated impact of GDP growth, industrialization, energy use, and urbanization on CO2 emissions in developing countries: Evidence from the panel ARDL approach</article-title><source>Sci Total Environ</source><year>2022</year><volume>837</volume><fpage>155795</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2022.155795</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35561911</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR87" publication-type="journal">Sikder M, Wang C, Yao X, Huai X, Wu L, KwameYeboah F, Wood J, Zhao Y, Dou X. The integrated impact of GDP growth, industrialization, energy use, and urbanization on CO2 emissions in developing countries: Evidence from the panel ARDL approach. Sci Total Environ. 2022;837:155795. 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2022.155795.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35561911</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR88"><label>88.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR88" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>&#x00160;krinjari&#x00107;</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Empirical assessment of the circular economy of selected European countries</article-title><source>J Cleaner Product</source><year>2020</year><volume>255</volume><fpage>120246</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jclepro.2020.120246</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR88" publication-type="journal">&#x00160;krinjari&#x00107; T. Empirical assessment of the circular economy of selected European countries. J Cleaner Product. 2020;255:120246. 10.1016/j.jclepro.2020.120246.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR89"><label>89.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR89" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Slorach</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeswani</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Cu&#x000e9;llar-Franca</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Azapagic</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Environmental and economic implications of recovering resources from food waste in a circular economy</article-title><source>Sci Total Environ</source><year>2019</year><volume>693</volume><fpage>133516</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.07.322</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31635000</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR89" publication-type="journal">Slorach PC, Jeswani HK, Cu&#x000e9;llar-Franca R, Azapagic A. Environmental and economic implications of recovering resources from food waste in a circular economy. Sci Total Environ. 2019;693:133516. 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.07.322.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31635000</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR90"><label>90.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR90" publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stahel</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group><source>The circular economy: a user&#x02019;s guide</source><year>2019</year><publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR90" publication-type="book">Stahel WR. The circular economy: a user&#x02019;s guide. Routledge; 2019.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR91"><label>91.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR91" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Imran</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trade-offs and synergies: Examining the impact of natural resource rents and energy efficiency on financial development in the RCEP context</article-title><source>Nat Res Forum</source><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1477-8947.12561</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR91" publication-type="journal">Tang Y, Imran M. Trade-offs and synergies: Examining the impact of natural resource rents and energy efficiency on financial development in the RCEP context. Nat Res Forum. 2024. 10.1111/1477-8947.12561.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR92"><label>92.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR92" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Toda</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Statistical inference in vector autoregressions with possibly integrated processes</article-title><source>J Econometrics</source><year>1995</year><volume>66</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>250</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0304-4076(94)01616-8</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR92" publication-type="journal">Toda HY, Yamamoto T. Statistical inference in vector autoregressions with possibly integrated processes. J Econometrics. 1995;66(1):225&#x02013;50. 10.1016/0304-4076(94)01616-8.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR93"><label>93.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR93" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ullah</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Altay Topcu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Dogan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Imran</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exploring the nexus among hydroelectric power generation, financial development, and economic growth: Evidence from the largest 10 hydroelectric power-generating countries</article-title><source>Energ Strat Rev</source><year>2024</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>101339</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.esr.2024.101339</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR93" publication-type="journal">Ullah A, Altay Topcu B, Dogan M, Imran M. Exploring the nexus among hydroelectric power generation, financial development, and economic growth: Evidence from the largest 10 hydroelectric power-generating countries. Energ Strat Rev. 2024;52: 101339. 10.1016/j.esr.2024.101339.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR94"><label>94.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR94" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Usman</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Ozkan</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Adeshola</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Eweade</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysing the nexus between clean energy expansion, natural resource extraction, and load capacity factor in China: a step towards achieving COP27 targets</article-title><source>Environ Dev Sustain</source><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10668-023-04399-z</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR94" publication-type="journal">Usman O, Ozkan O, Adeshola I, Eweade BS. Analysing the nexus between clean energy expansion, natural resource extraction, and load capacity factor in China: a step towards achieving COP27 targets. Environ Dev Sustain. 2024. 10.1007/s10668-023-04399-z.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR95"><label>95.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR95" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Costanza-van den Belt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Heath</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Walzberg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Curtis</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Berrie</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Schr&#x000f6;der</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lazer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Altamirano</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Circular economy as a climate strategy: current knowledge and calls-to-action</article-title><source>NREL Tech Rep</source><year>2022</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>28</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2172/1897625</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR95" publication-type="journal">Wang K, Costanza-van den Belt M, Heath G, Walzberg J, Curtis T, Berrie J, Schr&#x000f6;der P, Lazer L, Altamirano JC. Circular economy as a climate strategy: current knowledge and calls-to-action. NREL Tech Rep. 2022;1:1&#x02013;28. 10.2172/1897625.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR96"><label>96.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR96" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hossain</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Si Mohammed</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Cifuentes-Faura</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Heterogenous effects of circular economy, green energy and globalization on CO2 emissions: policy based analysis for sustainable development</article-title><source>Renewable Energy</source><year>2023</year><volume>211</volume><fpage>789</fpage><lpage>801</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.renene.2023.05.033</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR96" publication-type="journal">Wang M, Hossain MR, Si Mohammed K, Cifuentes-Faura J, Cai X. Heterogenous effects of circular economy, green energy and globalization on CO2 emissions: policy based analysis for sustainable development. Renewable Energy. 2023;211:789&#x02013;801. 10.1016/j.renene.2023.05.033.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR97"><label>97.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR97" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Imran</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sattar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Green policies and financial development in G7 economies: an in-depth analysis of environmental regulations and green economic growth</article-title><source>Nat Res Forum</source><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1477-8947.12424</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR97" publication-type="journal">Wang W, Imran M, Ali K, Sattar A. Green policies and financial development in G7 economies: an in-depth analysis of environmental regulations and green economic growth. Nat Res Forum. 2024. 10.1111/1477-8947.12424.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR98"><label>98.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR98" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wolde-Rufael</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Mulat-weldemeskel</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effectiveness of environmental taxes and environmental stringent policies on CO2 emissions: the European experience</article-title><source>Environ Develop Sustainability</source><year>2023</year><volume>25</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>5211</fpage><lpage>5239</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10668-022-02262-1</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR98" publication-type="journal">Wolde-Rufael Y, Mulat-weldemeskel E. Effectiveness of environmental taxes and environmental stringent policies on CO2 emissions: the European experience. Environ Develop Sustainability. 2023;25(6):5211&#x02013;39. 10.1007/s10668-022-02262-1.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR99"><label>99.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR99" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Abban</surname><given-names>OJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Boadi</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Addae</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Akhtar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hongxing</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ofori</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Time&#x02013;frequency contained co-movement of renewable electricity production, globalization, and co2 emissions: a wavelet-based analysis in Asia</article-title><source>Energy Rep</source><year>2022</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>15189</fpage><lpage>15205</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.egyr.2022.11.054</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR99" publication-type="journal">Wu J, Abban OJ, Boadi AD, Addae EA, Akhtar M, Hongxing Y, Ofori C. Time&#x02013;frequency contained co-movement of renewable electricity production, globalization, and co2 emissions: a wavelet-based analysis in Asia. Energy Rep. 2022;8:15189&#x02013;205. 10.1016/j.egyr.2022.11.054.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR100"><label>100.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR100" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Does smart city pilot policy reduce CO2 emissions from industrial firms? Insights from China</article-title><source>J Innov Knowl</source><year>2023</year><volume>8</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>100367</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jik.2023.100367</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR100" publication-type="journal">Xu A, Wang W, Zhu Y. Does smart city pilot policy reduce CO2 emissions from industrial firms? Insights from China. J Innov Knowl. 2023;8(3): 100367. 10.1016/j.jik.2023.100367.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR101"><label>101.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR101" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Pei</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Nie</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A sustainable development benchmarking framework for energy companies based on topic mining and knowledge graph: The case of oil and gas industry</article-title><source>Renew Sustain Energy Rev</source><year>2024</year><volume>196</volume><fpage>114350</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rser.2024.114350</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR101" publication-type="journal">Xu X, Liu Z, Liu W, Pei C, Wu X, Nie Z. A sustainable development benchmarking framework for energy companies based on topic mining and knowledge graph: The case of oil and gas industry. Renew Sustain Energy Rev. 2024;196: 114350. 10.1016/j.rser.2024.114350.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR102"><label>102.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR102" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Kou</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>2018/07/01/). Can urbanization process and carbon emission abatement be harmonious? New evidence from China</article-title><source>Environ Impact Assess Rev</source><year>2018</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>70</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eiar.2018.04.005</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR102" publication-type="journal">Yao X, Kou D, Shao S, Li X, Wang W, Zhang C. 2018/07/01/). Can urbanization process and carbon emission abatement be harmonious? New evidence from China. Environ Impact Assess Rev. 2018;71:70&#x02013;83. 10.1016/j.eiar.2018.04.005.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR103"><label>103.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR103" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Eweade</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Adebayo</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of eco-innovation and financial globalization on ecological quality in China: a wavelet analysis</article-title><source>Energy Environ</source><year>2024</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0958305X241228518</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR103" publication-type="journal">Zhang H, Khan KA, Eweade BS, Adebayo TS. Role of eco-innovation and financial globalization on ecological quality in China: a wavelet analysis. Energy Environ. 2024;1:1&#x02013;9. 10.1177/0958305X241228518.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR104"><label>104.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR104" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Imran</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Juanatas</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Innovate, conserve, grow: a comprehensive analysis of technological innovation, energy utilization, and carbon emission in BRICS</article-title><source>Nat Res Forum</source><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1477-8947.12510</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR104" publication-type="journal">Zhang M, Imran M, Juanatas RA. Innovate, conserve, grow: a comprehensive analysis of technological innovation, energy utilization, and carbon emission in BRICS. Nat Res Forum. 2024. 10.1111/1477-8947.12510.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR105"><label>105.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR105" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Geng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>K-H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Circular economy practices among Chinese manufacturers varying in environmental-oriented supply chain cooperation and the performance implications</article-title><source>J Environ Manag</source><year>2010</year><volume>91</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1324</fpage><lpage>1331</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jenvman.2010.02.013</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR105" publication-type="journal">Zhu Q, Geng Y, Lai K-H. Circular economy practices among Chinese manufacturers varying in environmental-oriented supply chain cooperation and the performance implications. J Environ Manag. 2010;91(6):1324&#x02013;31. 10.1016/j.jenvman.2010.02.013.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article>