<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="brief-report" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Signal Transduct Target Ther</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Signal Transduct Target Ther</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Signal Transduction and Targeted Therapy</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2095-9907</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2059-3635</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40393966</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12092805</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2257</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41392-025-02257-0</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Highlight</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Targeting conserved epitopes in structural proteins: a next-generation vaccine strategy against the newly identified HKU5-CoV-2 virus</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>de Ara&#x000fa;jo</surname><given-names>Leonardo Pereira</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>Evandro Neves</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>Andr&#x000e9; Luiz Caliari</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Corsetti</surname><given-names>Patr&#x000ed;cia Paiva</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-1886-5080</contrib-id><name><surname>de Almeida</surname><given-names>Leonardo Augusto</given-names></name><address><email>leonardo.almeida@unifal-mg.edu.br</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/034vpja60</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411180.d</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0643 7932</institution-id><institution>Laboratory of Molecular Biology of Microorganisms, Federal University of Alfenas (UNIFAL), </institution><institution>Alfenas, </institution></institution-wrap>37130-001 Minas Gerais, Brazil </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>21</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>164</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>19</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>16</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Infectious diseases</kwd><kwd>Vaccines</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Coordena&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o de Aperfei&#x000e7;oamento de Pessoal de N&#x000ed;vel Superior (CAPES) (Grant/Award Number: 001), Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Cient&#x000ed;fico e Tecnol&#x000f3;gico and Funda&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o de Amparo &#x000e0; Pesquisa do Estado de Minas Gerais (CNPq / FAPEMIG) (Grant/Award Number: BPD-00626-22 and APQ-01297-23).</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; West China Hospital, Sichuan University 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p id="Par1">A recent study published in <italic>Cell</italic> by Chen et al., highlighted by <italic>Nature</italic> journal, identified the <italic>HKU5-CoV-2</italic> lineage, a coronavirus detected in bats with the potential to interact with the human ACE2 receptor.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup> Experiments conducted in intestinal and airway cells indicated that <italic>HKU5-CoV-2</italic> binds to the receptor less efficiently than <italic>SARS-CoV-2</italic>. However, the broad ACE2 ortholog tropism suggests a potential risk of adaptation to the human host.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup></p><p id="Par2">The spillover of zoonotic viruses poses a persistent challenge to global health, driving successive health crises.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup> The COVID-19 pandemic, caused by <italic>SARS-CoV-2</italic>, resulted in approximately 7 million deaths, but it was not an isolated event.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup> Recurring outbreaks of emerging and re-emerging viruses, such as <italic>SARS-CoV</italic>, <italic>MERS-CoV</italic>, and Mpox, among others, highlight a concerning epidemiological pattern.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup> These events underscore the need for continuous surveillance, genomic monitoring, and robust preventive strategies to anticipate and mitigate future pandemic threats.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup></p><p id="Par3">Given this emerging threat, antiviral strategies such as neutralizing antibodies, fusion inhibitors, and small molecules&#x02014;including nirmatrelvir, remdesivir, and GC376&#x02014;have been evaluated and demonstrated potential against <italic>HKU5-CoV-2</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup> However, the absence of diagnostic and vaccine tools exposes our vulnerability to a potential &#x0201c;Disease X&#x0201c;.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup> The infectivity of this virus has not yet been assessed in vivo, making further investigations essential.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup> For this reason, we intend to determine whether epitopes previously identified by our research group in <italic>SARS-CoV-2</italic> structural proteins are conserved in <italic>HKU5-CoV-2</italic>, following an approach validated by our team in a study previously published in <italic>The Lancet Microbe</italic> in 2024 for the Mpox and <italic>Alaskapox</italic> viruses.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup> If conservation was not confirmed, we aimed to identify new epitopes in the structural proteins of this virus with potential applications in diagnostics and as vaccine candidates.</p><p id="Par4">The sequences of the structural proteins&#x02014;envelope protein, membrane glycoprotein, nucleocapsid phosphoprotein, and spike glycoprotein&#x02014;were obtained from the GenBase database (accession numbers: C_AA085189.1, C_AA085190.1, C_AA085191.1, C_AA085192.1, C_AA085193.1, and C_AA085194.1). We then aligned previously identified <italic>SARS-CoV-2</italic> epitopes with <italic>HKU5-CoV-2</italic> proteins. Additionally, we performed predictions of B-cell and T-cell (MHCI and MHCII) epitopes and analyses related to antigenicity, allergenicity, physicochemical properties, transmembrane regions, N-glycosylation sites, and three-dimensional modeling of the spike glycoprotein, following the methodology previously described by our group.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup></p><p id="Par5">Given the approach previously reported for Mpox and <italic>Alaskapox</italic>, we investigated the conservation of <italic>SARS-CoV-2</italic> epitopes in <italic>HKU5-CoV-2</italic>, which could enable a bivalent vaccine candidate.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup> However, our findings reveal that <italic>HKU5-CoV-2</italic> shares only 80% amino acid sequence identity with MERS-CoV and 72% with <italic>SARS-CoV-2</italic>, indicating significant structural differences. This divergence may explain the lack of conservation of previously mapped epitopes, as described in Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. Furthermore, in the analysis of the six available <italic>HKU5-CoV-2</italic> genomes, we identified 77 mutations in the spike protein, further reinforcing the substantial structural alterations of this virus. As represented in Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, most of these mutations (shown in red in the three-dimensional structure) and N-glycosylations (shown in blue) are located in the RBD region, while the central region exhibits a higher degree of conservation, represented in gray.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Comparison of <italic>MERS-CoV, HKU5-CoV-2</italic>, and <italic>SARS-CoV-2</italic> proteins, emphasizing amino acid identity and differences in the Spike glycoprotein. The top diagram illustrates the phylogenetic relationship between these viruses and the lack of conserved epitopes between <italic>HKU5-CoV-2</italic> and <italic>SARS-CoV-2</italic>. The three-dimensional structure of Spike, predicted using AlphaFold3, and the accompanying graph highlight N-glycosylation sites (blue), mutations (red), and transmembrane regions (green). The lower graph presents the protein sequence alignment, marking epitopes in brown and conserved regions, offering a comprehensive view of structural and functional variations</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41392_2025_2257_Fig1_HTML" id="d33e330"/></fig></p><p id="Par6">Despite these mutations, the <italic>HKU5-CoV-2</italic> spike glycoprotein exhibited approximately 1088 antigenic and stable epitopes, along with a high number of N-glycosylation sites. These characteristics, together with the identified mutations, reflect a pattern similar to that observed by our research group in <italic>SARS-CoV-2</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup> Nonetheless, we identified a conserved region between amino acids 750 and 1200, with only one mutation at residue 1043 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). In addition to spike, structural proteins such as envelope, membrane, and nucleocapsid also exhibited conserved and antigenic epitopes (data not shown), highlighting these potential targets for vaccine development and the need for continuous monitoring of this virus.</p><p id="Par7">The identified conserved region emerges as a promising target for the development of effective vaccines. Furthermore, as demonstrated by our group and suggested by Chen et al.,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup> conserved epitopes across different viral species can be explored to create broad-spectrum immunological strategies. Identifying mutated epitopes not only enables tracking of viral evolution but also facilitates the development of immunodiagnostic tools for the differential early detection of emerging variants. Nonetheless, it is important to consider that, despite their high conservation, the epitopes may exhibit suboptimal antigenicity, potentially limiting their ability to induce potent neutralizing antibody responses. This highlights the essential role of subsequent in vitro and in vivo studies to validate their immunogenic potential and functional relevance in protective immunity.</p><p id="Par8">The development of immunodiagnostic tests and vaccines against <italic>HKU5-CoV-2</italic> is essential. Our findings confirm that its structural proteins exhibit antigenicity patterns similar to those of <italic>SARS-CoV-2</italic>. Thus, as highlighted by Chen et al. and corroborated by our investigations, the conservation of epitopes in zoonotic viruses should be extensively explored to strengthen our defenses against future pandemics.</p></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors acknowledge the financial support from the Brazilian agencies. This study was supported in part by the Coordena&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o de Aperfei&#x000e7;oamento de Pessoal de N&#x000ed;vel Superior (CAPES) (Grant/Award Number: 001), Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Cient&#x000ed;fico e Tecnol&#x000f3;gico, and Funda&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o de Amparo &#x000e0; Pesquisa do Estado de Minas Gerais (CNPq / FAPEMIG) (Grant/Award Number: BPD-00626-22 and APQ-01297-23).</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>L.P.D.A. conceptualization, data curation, formal analysis, investigation, methodology, validation, design figure, and writing - original draft. E.N.S. and A.L.C.C. data curation, formal analysis, investigation, design figure, and methodology. P.P.C. and L.A.D.A. conceptualization, data curation, formal analysis, investigation, resources, supervision, validation, visualization, and writing - original draft. All authors have read and approved the article.</p></notes><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par9">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Bat-infecting merbecovirus HKU5-CoV lineage 2 can use human ACE2 as a cell entry receptor</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2025</year><volume>188</volume><fpage>1729</fpage><lpage>1742.e16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2025.01.042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39970913</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Chen, J. et al. Bat-infecting merbecovirus HKU5-CoV lineage 2 can use human ACE2 as a cell entry receptor. <italic>Cell</italic><bold>188</bold>, 1729&#x02013;1742.e16 (2025).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39970913</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Newfound bat virus that uses notorious receptor poses &#x02018;spillover&#x02019; risk. <italic>Nature</italic>. <bold>638</bold>, 863 (2025).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Emerging and re-emerging fatal viral diseases</article-title><source>Exp. Mol. Med.</source><year>2021</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>711</fpage><lpage>712</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s12276-021-00608-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33953321</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Choi, Y. K. Emerging and re-emerging fatal viral diseases. <italic>Exp. Mol. Med.</italic><bold>53</bold>, 711&#x02013;712 (2021).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33953321</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Ara&#x000fa;jo</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Epitope identification of SARS-CoV-2 structural proteins using in silico approaches to obtain a conserved rational immunogenic peptide</article-title><source>Immunoinformatics</source><year>2022</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>100015</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.immuno.2022.100015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35721890</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">De Ara&#x000fa;jo, L. P. et al. Epitope identification of SARS-CoV-2 structural proteins using in silico approaches to obtain a conserved rational immunogenic peptide. <italic>Immunoinformatics</italic><bold>7</bold>, 100015 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35721890</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Ara&#x000fa;jo</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>EN</given-names></name><name><surname>Corsetti</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name><surname>De Almeida</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Shared immunogenic epitopes between host entry and exit proteins from monkeypox and Alaskapox viruses</article-title><source>Lancet Microbe</source><year>2024</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>624</fpage><lpage>625</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2666-5247(24)00095-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38653317</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">De Ara&#x000fa;jo, L. P., Silva, E. N., Corsetti, P. P. &#x00026; De Almeida, L. A. Shared immunogenic epitopes between host entry and exit proteins from monkeypox and Alaskapox viruses. <italic>Lancet Microbe</italic><bold>5</bold>, 624&#x02013;625 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38653317</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article>