<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Orphanet J Rare Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Orphanet J Rare Dis</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Orphanet Journal of Rare Diseases</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1750-1172</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40001078</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11863566</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">3611</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13023-025-03611-9</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>How does overweight affect bone mineral density and oral health in adult hypophosphatasia?&#x02013; A single center experience</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1287-9775</contrib-id><name><surname>Dudde</surname><given-names>Florian</given-names></name><address><email>floriandudde@gmx.de</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fildebrandt</surname><given-names>Dominik</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Petz</surname><given-names>Karin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Smeets</surname><given-names>Ralf</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gosau</surname><given-names>Martin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Amling</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Beikler</surname><given-names>Thomas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Barvencik</surname><given-names>Florian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/01zgy1s35</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.13648.38</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2180 3484</institution-id><institution>Department of Osteology and Biomechanics, </institution><institution>University Medical Center Hamburg- Eppendorf, </institution></institution-wrap>Lottestra&#x000df;e 59, 22529 Hamburg, Germany </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/01zgy1s35</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.13648.38</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2180 3484</institution-id><institution>Department of Periodontics, Preventive and Restorative Dentistry, </institution><institution>University Medical Center Hamburg-Eppendorf, </institution></institution-wrap>Hamburg, Germany </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/01zgy1s35</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.13648.38</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2180 3484</institution-id><institution>Department of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery, </institution><institution>University Medical Center Hamburg- Eppendorf, </institution></institution-wrap>Hamburg, Germany </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/01zgy1s35</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.13648.38</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2180 3484</institution-id><institution>Department of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery, Division of Regenerative Orofacial Medicine, </institution><institution>University Medical Center Hamburg-Eppendorf, </institution></institution-wrap>Hamburg, Germany </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>25</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>25</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>20</volume><elocation-id>85</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>26</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Aim</title><p id="Par1">The aim of this study was to investigate the influence of overweight (BMI&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;25 (kg/m&#x000b2;)) on the oral health status in patients with adult hypophosphatasia (HPP).</p></sec><sec><title>Materials and methods</title><p id="Par2">Throughout a retrospective assessment both oral health status and bone metabolism including dual x-ray absorptiometry (DXA) for bone mineral density (BMD) measures were analyzed. The oral health status was assessed by the decayed/missing/filled teeth index (DMFT), clinical attachment level (CAL), probing pocket depth (PPD), and the periodontal screening index (PSI). The study population was divided into two groups based on the overweight classification by BMI (Overweight&#x02009;=&#x02009;BMI&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;25&#x000a0;kg/m&#x000b2;; <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;17) vs. non-overweight (&#x02009;BMI&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;25&#x000a0;kg/m&#x000b2;; <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;31).</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">48 HPP patients were included in this study. Overweight HPP patients showed a significantly reduced oral health status regarding filled teeth, DMFT, PSI, PPD and periodontitis severity index compared to non-overweight HPP patients. Furthermore, overweight HPP patients revealed significantly higher DXA findings regarding BMD, T- and Z-scores.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par4">In the present study overweight (BMI&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;25 (kg/m&#x000b2;)) is associated with a poorer oral health status and higher BMD in adult HPP.</p></sec><sec><title>Clinical relevance</title><p id="Par5">Since overweight is associated with a poorer oral health status in the general population and promotes the development of periodontal disease, the findings of the present study indicate that overweight also affects oral health in adult HPP.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Adult</kwd><kwd>Hypophosphatasia</kwd><kwd>Oral health</kwd><kwd>BMI</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Universit&#x000e4;tsklinikum Hamburg-Eppendorf (UKE) (5411)</institution></funding-source></award-group><open-access><p>Open Access funding enabled and organized by Projekt DEAL.</p></open-access></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Institut National de la Sant&#x000e9; et de la Recherche M&#x000e9;dicale (INSERM) 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par6">Hypophosphatasia (HPP) is a rare metabolic disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. This disease is due to a restricted function of the non-tissue-specific alkaline phosphatase (TNSAP), which can be caused by various mutations in the alkaline phosphatase liver/bone/kidney type (ALPL) gene [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. TNSAP is an important enzyme in bone metabolism and consequently leads to mineralization disorders if its function is impaired [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Various studies have shown a wide range of symptoms in HPP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. In addition to non-specific symptoms such as arthralgia, myalgia and fatigue, an increased susceptibility to fractures and an increased incidence of atraumatic tooth loss are typical symptoms for HPP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Furthermore, initial studies have shown that the oral health status is also disturbed in the sense of increased prevalence/ severity of periodontitis and is associated with increased DMFT (Decayed, Missing, Filled Teeth) indices in HPP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. In addition to atraumatic tooth loss, HPP patients often present with enamel hypoplasia, poor cementum formation, and delayed tooth eruption [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. These factors significantly affect oral health by increasing susceptibility to dental caries, periodontal disease, and subsequent tooth loss [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Enamel hypoplasia results in a thinner and more brittle enamel structure, predisposing teeth to decay and structural failure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Poor cementum formation compromises the periodontal ligament attachment, leading to an increased risk of atraumatic tooth exfoliation. Delayed eruption of primary and permanent teeth contributes to malocclusion and crowding, further exacerbating the risk of periodontal disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Collectively, these conditions highlight the multifaceted impact of HPP on oral health.</p><p id="Par7">Although HPP can be classified into various subforms depending on the onset of clinical symptoms almost all HPP patients show a negatively affected oral health status [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>].</p><p id="Par8">Another risk factor for impaired oral health in the general population is overweight (Body-Mass-Index&#x02009;=&#x02009;BMI&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;25 (kg/m&#x000b2;) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Reviews have shown that increased weight promotes the development of periodontitis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Furthermore, a current publication showed that overweight is associated not only with periodontitis but also with the occurrence of decayed teeth and tooth loss [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. In addition to that, a current meta-analysis reported that individuals with overweight tend to have higher bone mineral density (BMD) values than non-overweight adults [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Qiao et al. showed that overweight is positively associated with higher BMD and negatively correlated with the prevalence of osteoporosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. However, if and to what extent overweight affects BMD values in HPP patients has hardly been investigated yet. Since overweight seems to positively correlate with BMD values and negatively with the oral health status in the general population, the question arises whether overweight (BMI&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;25 (kg/m&#x000b2;) also affects the oral health status and BMD in adult HPP. Previous work by our group has reported DXA scan results and oral health findings in patients with HPP in the context of laboratory parameters [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. This study provided important insights into the bone and oral health challenges faced by this population. In the current study, we extend these findings by specifically investigating the influence of overweight on oral health outcomes in adult HPP patients, an area that has not been previously explored.</p><p id="Par9">Due to the rarity of this disease the oral health in adult HPP has rarely been studied.</p><p id="Par10">Furthermore, no study on the correlation of overweight and the oral health status in HPP patients has been published yet. Therefore, the aim of this study was to investigate the influence of overweight on the oral health status and BMD in adult HPP.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Data collection</title><p id="Par11">This retrospective study examined German HPP patients who were treated in the Department of Osteology and Biomechanics at the University Hospital Hamburg and in the Department of Periodontics, Preventive and Restorative Dentistry between 2017 and 2023. Inclusion criteria were a genetically proven adult form of HPP (pathogenic and likely pathogenic variants of ALPL gene, ACMG class III&#x02013; V (American College of Medical Genetics and Genomics)) and a clear diagnosis of HPP based on the HPP major and minor criteria according to the International Working Group (IWG) on HPP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Data of the respective study population have already been published elsewhere [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Exclusion criteria were incomplete medical and/or dental documentation (patient records). Data collection regarding bone metabolism and clinical findings was carried out using the patient files in the Department of Osteology and Biomechanics. The data collection of the oral health status was carried out from the patients&#x02019; digital patient files (Charly Program by Solutio, Holzgerlingen, Germany) in the Department of Periodontics, Preventive and Restorative Dentistry. A total of 48 patients were included in this study.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Clinical data &#x00026; molecular information</title><p id="Par12">For each patient, the clinical characteristics (age, body-mass-index&#x02009;=&#x02009;BMI, sex, mutation, ACMG class) as well as laboratory parameters (alkaline phosphatase&#x02009;=&#x02009;AP, bone specific alkaline phosphatase&#x02009;=&#x02009;bAP, PLP, Copper, Magnesium, parathyroid hormone&#x02009;=&#x02009;PTH, Vitamin D, Calcium, Phosphate) were analyzed. Furthermore, the results of the dual x-ray absorptiometry (DXA) scan were also analyzed for these patients. Using DXA, measurements of BMD can be determined on the spine, femur (femoral neck) and other specific regions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. The values of DXA are presented in bone mineral density, T-Scores and Z-Scores. The intraoral examination was carried out within two weeks after initial diagnosis of HPP and simultaneous serum collection.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Oral health status</title><p id="Par13">During the routine dental examination the following parameters were investigated:</p><p id="Par14">
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p id="Par15">Decayed missing filled/tooth (DMFT) index.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par16">Number of natural teeth in situ (excluding third molars).</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par17">Periodontitis screening index.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par18">Periodontitis severity grade (PSI).</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par19">Probing Pocket Depth (PPD).</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par20">Clinical attachment level (CAL).</p></list-item></list>
</p><p id="Par21">The PPD and CAL were determined using a standardized manual periodontal probe (CP-11; Hu-Friedy, USA). According to Holfreter et al. PPD and CAL were recorded on six sides of the tooth (mesiobuccal, buccal, distobuccal, mesiooral, oral and distooral) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Furthermore the age of the first permanent tooth eruption was noted. The oral assessment was performed by at least two years trained, experienced dentists, in the field of periodontology (DF, KP, TB).</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Overweight classification (BMI)</title><p id="Par22">The present study aimed to analyze the influence of overweight on the oral health status and BMD in adult HPP patients. Consequently, based on the diagnostical criteria for overweight (BMI&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;25 (kg/m&#x000b2;)) the study population was divided into two groups (Group A with a BMI&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;25 (kg/m&#x000b2;) (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;17) vs. Group B with a BMI&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;25 (kg/m&#x000b2;) (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;31)) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. A further subgroup analysis by BMI&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;25 (kg/m&#x000b2;) (i.e. obesity, extreme obesity) was not performed due to the limited number of HPP patients (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;48).</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par23">Descriptive analysis was used to display patients baseline characteristics. Normally distributed continuous variables are presented as mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;standard deviation and binary variables are using absolute and relative frequencies. Comparison of continuous variables was performed by student&#x02019;s t-test. Chi-square test was used for analysis of binary variables. Bar plots and scatter plots were used as graphic elements. A p-value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 was considered statistically significant. All statistical analyses were performed using the SPSS version 28.0 statistical package (IBM, Markham, Canada).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec9"><title>Baseline</title><p id="Par24">A total of 48 HPP patients were included in the present study. Based on the diagnostical criteria for overweight (BMI&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;25 (kg/m&#x000b2;)) the population was divided into two groups (Group A with a BMI&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;25 (kg/m&#x000b2;) (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;17) vs. Group B with a BMI&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;25 (kg/m&#x000b2;) (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;31)). Consequently, overweight patients showed significantly higher BMI values than non-overweight patients (Group A&#x02009;=&#x02009;BMI 30.28 (kg/m&#x000b2;) vs. Group B&#x02009;=&#x02009;21.11 (kg/m&#x000b2;); p&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Overweight patients revealed significantly lower Vitamin D levels than non-overweight patients (Group A&#x02009;=&#x02009;24.27&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/l vs. Group B&#x02009;=&#x02009;31.45&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/l; <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.047) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Consecutively, overweight patients tended to have higher PTH levels with simultaneously reduced calcium and phosphate levels (non-significant) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Furthermore, patients in group A showed higher AP and bAP levels with consecutively lower PLP levels (non-significant) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p><p id="Par25">
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Patient characteristics (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;48)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Variable</th><th align="left">Total<break/>(<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;48)</th><th align="left">BMI&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;25 (kg/m&#x000b2;)<break/>(<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;17)</th><th align="left">BMI&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;25 (kg/m&#x000b2;)<break/>(<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;31)</th><th align="left"><italic>p</italic>-Value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Age</td><td align="left">42.21 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;15.78)</td><td align="left">46.76 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;14.52)</td><td align="left">39.71 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;16.12)</td><td char="." align="char">0.140</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Gender</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">0.161</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Male</td><td align="left">9 (18.8)</td><td align="left">5 (29.4)</td><td align="left">4 (12.9)</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Female</td><td align="left">39 (81.3)</td><td align="left">12 (70.6)</td><td align="left">27 (87.1)</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">BMI (kg/m&#x000b2;)</td><td align="left">24.35 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.86)</td><td align="left">30.28 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.52)</td><td align="left">21.11 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.66)</td><td char="." align="char">
<bold>&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ACMG Class</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">0.112</td></tr><tr><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0 (0)</td><td align="left">0 (0)</td><td align="left">0 (0)</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">0 (0)</td><td align="left">0 (0)</td><td align="left">0(0)</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">16 (33.3)</td><td align="left">2 (11.8)</td><td align="left">14 (45.2)</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">8 (16.7)</td><td align="left">3 (17.6)</td><td align="left">5 (16.1)</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">24 (50.0)</td><td align="left">12 (70.6)</td><td align="left">12 (38.7)</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">PLP (&#x000b5;g/l)</td><td align="left">87.10 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;68.31)</td><td align="left">68.15 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;44.04)</td><td align="left">96.75 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;98.38)</td><td char="." align="char">0.179</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AP (U/l)</td><td align="left">33.83 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;20.83)</td><td align="left">36.52 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;24.95)</td><td align="left">28.94 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;8.21)</td><td char="." align="char">0.232</td></tr><tr><td align="left">bAP (U/l)</td><td align="left">5.93 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;7.23)</td><td align="left">6.68 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;8.82)</td><td align="left">4.56 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.21)</td><td char="." align="char">0.336</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Magnesium (mmol/l)</td><td align="left">0.85 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.07)</td><td align="left">0.88 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.06)</td><td align="left">0.84 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.07)</td><td char="." align="char">0.090</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Copper (&#x000b5;g/l)</td><td align="left">1075.55 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;395.43)</td><td align="left">1175.13 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;340.51)</td><td align="left">1010.61 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;421.93)</td><td char="." align="char">0.214</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Calcium (mmol/l)</td><td align="left">2.37 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.12)</td><td align="left">2.35 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.13)</td><td align="left">2.41 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.11)</td><td char="." align="char">0.131</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Phosphate (mmol/l)</td><td align="left">1.14 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.26)</td><td align="left">1.12 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.28)</td><td align="left">1.19 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.21)</td><td char="." align="char">0.415</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Vitamin D (&#x000b5;g/l)</td><td align="left">28.98 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;15.39)</td><td align="left">24.47 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;17.49)</td><td align="left">31.45 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;13.78)</td><td char="." align="char">
<bold>0.047</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">PTH (ng/l)</td><td align="left">44.15 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;18.82)</td><td align="left">49.39 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;21.34)</td><td align="left">41.27 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;17.04)</td><td char="." align="char">0.155</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Note: Data are presented as mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD and/or percentage</p><p>Abbreviations: AP&#x02009;=&#x02009;alkaline phosphatase, bAP&#x02009;=&#x02009;bone specific alkaline phosphatase, BMI&#x02009;=&#x02009;Body-mass-index, ACMG&#x02009;=&#x02009;American College of Medical Genetics, PLP&#x02009;=&#x02009;Pyridoxal phosphate, PTH&#x02009;=&#x02009;Parathyroid hormone</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>DXA-Scan</title><p id="Par26">There were significant differences between the two groups regarding the DXA findings. Overweight HPP patients showed significantly higher T- and Z-scores for both femora and the spinal column (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). BMD was significantly increased, particularly for both femora in overweight HPP patients (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p><p id="Par27">
<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>DXA scan (SD)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Variable</th><th align="left">Total<break/>(<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;48)</th><th align="left">BMI&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;25 (kg/m&#x000b2;)<break/>(<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;17)</th><th align="left">BMI&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;25 (kg/m&#x000b2;)<break/>(<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;31)</th><th align="left"><italic>p</italic>-Value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">BMD SC (g/cm&#x000b2;)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.14 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.22)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.27 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.19)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.08 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.17)</td><td char="." align="char">0.232</td></tr><tr><td align="left">T-Score SC</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">&#x02212;&#x02009;0.16 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.59)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0,72 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.31)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">&#x02212;&#x02009;0.75 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.34)</td><td char="." align="char">
<bold>0.003</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Z-Score SC</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">&#x02212;&#x02009;0.03 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.33)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.63 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.31)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">&#x02212;&#x02009;0.42 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.20)</td><td char="." align="char">
<bold>0.008</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">BMD Left Femur (g/cm&#x000b2;)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.95 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.15)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.05 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.15)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.89 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.12)</td><td char="." align="char">
<bold>&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">T-Score Left Femur</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">&#x02212;&#x02009;0.49 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.10)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.16 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.08)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">&#x02212;&#x02009;0.92 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.91)</td><td char="." align="char">
<bold>0.002</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Z-Score Left Femur</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">&#x02212;&#x02009;0.21 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.98)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.26 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.08)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">&#x02212;&#x02009;0.49 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.82)</td><td char="." align="char">
<bold>0.011</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">BMD Right Femur (g/cm&#x000b2;)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.94 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.14)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.03 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.14)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.89 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.11)</td><td char="." align="char">
<bold>&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">T-Score Right Femur</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">&#x02212;&#x02009;0.57 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.00)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.01 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.89)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">&#x02212;&#x02009;0.95 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.90)</td><td char="." align="char">
<bold>0.002</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Z-Score Right Femur</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">&#x02212;&#x02009;0.28 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.95)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.14 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.00)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">&#x02212;&#x02009;0.53 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.84)</td><td char="." align="char">
<bold>0.022</bold>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Note: Data are presented as mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD</p><p>SC&#x02009;=&#x02009;Spinal column, BMD&#x02009;=&#x02009;Bone mineral density</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Oral health status&#x02013; DMFT</title><p id="Par28">Overweight HPP patients revealed a lower number of natural teeth than non-overweight HPP patients (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Overweight HPP patients showed higher numbers of decayed and missing teeth than non-overweight HPP patients (non-significant) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Significant differences were found for the number of filled teeth between the two groups (Group A&#x02009;=&#x02009;9.06 vs. Group B&#x02009;=&#x02009;5.71; <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.018) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Consecutively, overweight HPP patients showed a significantly higher DMFT-Index than non-overweight HPP patients (Group A&#x02009;=&#x02009;14.65 vs. Group B&#x02009;=&#x02009;10.29; <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.025) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).</p><p id="Par29">
<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Oral health status&#x02013; DMFT in HPP patients (SD)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Variable</th><th align="left">Total<break/>(<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;48)</th><th align="left">BMI&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;25 (kg/m&#x000b2;)<break/>(<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;17)</th><th align="left">BMI&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;25 (kg/m&#x000b2;)<break/>(<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;31)</th><th align="left"><italic>p</italic>-Value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Number of natural permanent teeth</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">25.21 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.94)</td><td align="left">24.82 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.64)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">25.42 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.13)</td><td char="." align="char">0.621</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Decayed</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2.15 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.44)</td><td align="left">2.41 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.85)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2.00 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.22)</td><td char="." align="char">0.291</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Missing</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2.79 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.94)</td><td align="left">3.18 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.64)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2.58 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.13)</td><td char="." align="char">0.331</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Filled</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6.90 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.76)</td><td align="left">9.06 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.24)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">5.71 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.67)</td><td char="." align="char">
<bold>0.018</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">DMFT-Index</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">11.83 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.53)</td><td align="left">14.65 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.78)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">10.29 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.49)</td><td char="." align="char">
<bold>0.025</bold>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Note: Data are presented as mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD</p><p>DMFT&#x02009;=&#x02009;Decayed-Missing-Filled-Teeth-Index</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par30">
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Scatter plot&#x02013; number of filled teeth&#x02013; correlation of age and BMI (kg/m&#x000b2;)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13023_2025_3611_Fig1_HTML" id="d33e1073"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Oral health status&#x02013; periodontal status</title><p id="Par31">There were significant differences between the two groups regarding the periodontal status (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). Overweight HPP patients showed significantly higher PSI values in all sextants in comparison with non-overweight HPP patients (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). Overweight HPP patients also showed higher relative frequencies of sites and teeth per mouth with a CAL&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;3&#x000a0;mm and &#x0003e;&#x02009;5&#x000a0;mm than non-overweight HPP patients (non-significant) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). There were significant differences between the two groups, particularly regarding PPD (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). HPP patients with a BMI&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;25 (kg/m&#x000b2;) showed significantly more sites and teeth per mouth with a PPD&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;4&#x000a0;mm / 6&#x000a0;mm than HPP patients with a BMI&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;25 (kg/m&#x000b2;) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). Consequently, overweight HPP patients showed significantly worse periodontitis severity scores than non-overweight HPP patients (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).</p><p id="Par32">
<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Detailed periodontal data (SD and/or percentage) in HPP patients</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Variable</th><th align="left">Total<break/>(<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;48)</th><th align="left">BMI&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;25 (kg/m&#x000b2;)<break/>(<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;17)</th><th align="left">BMI&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;25 (kg/m&#x000b2;)<break/>(<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;31)</th><th align="left"><italic>p</italic>-Value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">PSI - S1</td><td align="left">2.19 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.02)</td><td align="left">2.71 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.85)</td><td align="left">1.90 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.02)</td><td char="." align="char">
<bold>0.008</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">PSI - S2</td><td align="left">1.94 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.93)</td><td align="left">2.41 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.80)</td><td align="left">1.68 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.91)</td><td char="." align="char">
<bold>0.008</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">PSI - S3</td><td align="left">2.13 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.04)</td><td align="left">2.76 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.83)</td><td align="left">1.77 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.99)</td><td char="." align="char">
<bold>0.001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">PSI - S4</td><td align="left">2.04 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.97)</td><td align="left">2.53 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.87)</td><td align="left">1.77 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.92)</td><td char="." align="char">
<bold>0.007</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">PSI - S5</td><td align="left">2.10 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.03)</td><td align="left">2.47 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.72)</td><td align="left">1.90 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.79)</td><td char="." align="char">
<bold>0.018</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">PSI - S6</td><td align="left">1.92 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.03)</td><td align="left">2.35 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.00)</td><td align="left">1.68 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.98)</td><td char="." align="char">
<bold>0.028</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Sites per Mouth CAL&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;3&#x000a0;mm (%)</td><td align="left">11.80 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;12.62)</td><td align="left">14.95 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;13.16)</td><td align="left">10.08 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;12.18)</td><td char="." align="char">0.204</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Sites per Mouth CAL&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;5&#x000a0;mm (%)</td><td align="left">2.31 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.10)</td><td align="left">2.61 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.99)</td><td align="left">2.15 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.26)</td><td char="." align="char">0.806</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Teeth per Mouth CAL&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;3&#x000a0;mm (%)</td><td align="left">13.10 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;12.09)</td><td align="left">16.35 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;12.67)</td><td align="left">11.31 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;11.58)</td><td char="." align="char">0.169</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Teeth per Mouth CAL&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;5&#x000a0;mm (%)</td><td align="left">2.38 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.41)</td><td align="left">2.79 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.58)</td><td align="left">2.15 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.40)</td><td char="." align="char">0.703</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Sites per Mouth PPD&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;4&#x000a0;mm (%)</td><td align="left">11.55 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;19.11)</td><td align="left">19.44 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;22.63)</td><td align="left">7.22 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;15.63)</td><td char="." align="char">
<bold>0.033</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Sites per Mouth PPD&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;6&#x000a0;mm (%)</td><td align="left">3.69 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;9.70)</td><td align="left">6.81 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;12.44)</td><td align="left">1.98 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;7.50)</td><td char="." align="char">
<bold>0.009</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Teeth per Mouth PPD&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;4&#x000a0;mm (%)</td><td align="left">20.30 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;24.09)</td><td align="left">32.81 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;28.65)</td><td align="left">13.38 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;18.22)</td><td char="." align="char">
<bold>0.006</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Teeth per Mouth PPD&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;6&#x000a0;mm (%)</td><td align="left">4.29 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;11.36)</td><td align="left">8.52 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;16.51)</td><td align="left">1.97 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.40)</td><td char="." align="char">
<bold>0.005</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Age at first tooth exfoliation</td><td align="left">5.06 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.63)</td><td align="left">5.00 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.63)</td><td align="left">5.18 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.63)</td><td char="." align="char">0.361</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Periodontitis Severity Grade*</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">
<bold>&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">No/mild PD</td><td align="left">27 (56.3)</td><td align="left">3 (17.6)</td><td align="left">24 (77.4)</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Moderate PD</td><td align="left">14 (29.2)</td><td align="left">10 (58.9)</td><td align="left">4 (12.9)</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Severe PD</td><td align="left">7 (14.6)</td><td align="left">4 (23.5)</td><td align="left">3 (9.7)</td><td align="left"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Note: Data are presented as mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD and/or percentage</p><p>Abbreviations: PSI&#x02009;=&#x02009;Periodontitis screening index per sextant (S2&#x02013; S6), CAL&#x02009;=&#x02009;Clinical attachment level, PPD&#x02009;=&#x02009;Probing pocket depth, PD&#x02009;=&#x02009;Periodontitis, * Eke PI, et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par33">
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Bar plot&#x02013; comparison of periodontitis severity grade with DMS-V findings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. </p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13023_2025_3611_Fig2_HTML" id="d33e1416"/></fig>
</p><p>Note: Data are presented as percentage. Abbreviations: PD&#x02009;=&#x02009;Periodontitis, BMI&#x02009;=&#x02009;Body-Mass-Index, DMS-V&#x02009;=&#x02009;Deutsche Mundgesundheitsstudie V, HPP&#x02009;=&#x02009;Hypophosphatasia.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par34">HPP is a rare metabolic disease with varying symptoms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Recently, it was reported that most HPP patients also show dental manifestations of this entity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. However, the study situation on the oral health status in HPP is rare [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. In the present study, the influence of overweight on oral health status and BMD was examined in patients with genetically confirmed adult HPP.</p><p id="Par35">Overweight is a well-studied risk factor for a variety of diseases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Current studies have shown that overweight is associated not only with heart and circulatory diseases, but also with poorer oral health status [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Current publications showed that overweight can be associated in particular with increased DMFT indices, increased numbers of decayed teeth and an increased prevalence of periodontitis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Particularly regarding the DMFT index and the number of decayed teeth, the results of the present study are in line with the current literature, revealing that overweight is also associated with an increased prevalence of decayed and filled teeth in HPP patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. In the present study, overweight HPP patients showed significantly higher numbers of filled teeth and a consecutively increased DMFT index compared to non-overweight HPP patients. Possible pathophysiological reasons that lead to decayed and filled teeth in the context of overweight include excessive consumption of foods containing high amounts of sugar, as overweight can often be due to unhealthy and/or disordered eating behavior [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>].</p><p id="Par36">In particular, the frequent and excessive consumption of food containing a lot of sugar (low molecular carbohydrates), and the presence of cariogenic microorganisms (i.e. <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic>) coupled with inadequate tooth brushing technique and insufficient topical fluoride application can lead to a disruption in the balance of demineralization and remineralization of the dental structures (i.e. enamel) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. Regular and correct dental care can prevent the onset and progression of tooth decay. Furthermore, emerging evidence highlights the association between overweight and changes in the oral microbiome, often referred to as dysbiosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Overweight and obesity are linked to systemic low-grade inflammation, which may alter the composition of the oral microbiome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Dysbiosis can disrupt the balance between commensal and pathogenic bacteria, increasing susceptibility to oral diseases such as periodontitis and caries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. This phenomenon is supported by recent findings indicating that metabolic disorders can exacerbate inflammatory responses within the oral cavity, potentially through mechanisms involving microbial imbalance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. In the context of HPP, where patients are already predisposed to oral health issues due to defective mineralization, dysbiosis could further amplify the oral disease burden. While our study did not directly assess the oral microbiota, its potential role as a mediator between overweight and oral health outcomes represents an important avenue for future research.</p><p id="Par37">Focusing on high BMI-levels, Baskaradoss et al. was able to show that adolescents with a metabolic syndrome tended to brush their teeth less frequently compared to adolescents without a metabolic syndrome in a longitudinal study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. In addition to that, caries is strongly influenced by sugar intake from energy-rich foods, which also play a crucial role in the development of overweight [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. Furthermore, it is known that caries and overweight are often associated with a lower socioeconomic status [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>].</p><p id="Par38">In addition, overweight leads to a dysbalance between anti- and pro-inflammatory cytokines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Issrani et al. revealed that, particularly in the context of overweight, increased concentrations and sometimes uncontrolled release of proinflammatory cytokines (i.e. IL-1&#x003b2; (Interleukin), TNF-a (Tumor-necrosis factor), Prostaglandin E2) can be observed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. These proinflammatory cytokines are crucial in the development and maintenance of periodontitis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Consequently, studies have shown that overweight patients revealed higher prevalences and increased severity of periodontitis than non-overweight individuals in the general population [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. In a recent publication Cetin et al. was able to detect a direct correlation between BMI and clinical attachment loss, probing pocket depth, plaque index, stage and grade of periodontitis, and the number of remaining teeth [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. In their study it was stated that BMI increases the risk of developing severe stages of periodontitis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>].</p><p id="Par39">These findings were also demonstrated in the present study. Overweight HPP patients showed significantly higher numbers of sites and teeth per mouth with PPD&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;4&#x000a0;mm and &#x0003e;&#x02009;6&#x000a0;mm than non-overweight HPP patients. Furthermore, severe grades of periodontitis were significantly more common in overweight HPP patients in direct comparison with non-overweight HPP patients. Even in comparison with the results of the German Oral Health Study-V (DMS-V, age-correlated healthy normal population aged 35&#x02013;44), the rates of severe periodontitis of all HPP patients but especially those of overweight HPP patients exceeded the results of the age-matched general population clearly (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Current studies have been able to demonstrate that the oral health status in HPP correlates with various biochemical markers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Weider et al. demonstrated that the number of ALPL mutations correlates significantly with a negative oral health status [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>].</p><p id="Par40">Furthermore, it was proven that the oral health status is consecutively associated with reduced TNSAP activity and subsequently increased substrate levels of pyridoxal-5-phosphate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. However, since in the present study overweight HPP patients tended to have lower levels of PLP than non-overweight HPP patients, BMI seems to have a more lasting influence on oral health status than initially assumed.</p><p id="Par41">The relationship between BMI and oral health-related quality of life (OHRQoL) is increasingly recognized in the literature. Overweight and obesity have been associated with negative perceptions of oral health, potentially due to higher susceptibility to periodontal disease and caries, as well as psychosocial factors such as self-esteem and social interactions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. In the context of HPP, the additional burden of oral diseases, exacerbated by overweight status, may further diminish OHRQoL [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. While our study primarily assessed clinical oral health outcomes, the impact of these outcomes on patients&#x02019; perceived quality of life is a critical consideration for future research. Integrating patient-reported outcomes, such as OHRQoL scores, could provide a more comprehensive understanding of the interplay between BMI, oral health, and overall well-being in this population.</p><p id="Par42">Another laboratory factor influencing oral health is the Vitamin D level. Since Vitamin D deficiency is also associated with poorer oral health in the general population and further promotes the occurrence of periodontitis, the influence of this key hormone should not be left unmentioned regarding HPP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. In the present study, overweight HPP patients revealed significantly lower levels of Vitamin D than non-overweight HPP patients (data not shown). Consequently, a lower Vitamin D level needs to be considered at least a cofactor for the poor periodontal status (i.e. PPD, PSI) and appears to aggravate the worse oral health status in HPP.</p><p id="Par43">In the present study, overweight HPP patients had significantly higher T-scores and Z-scores in the spinal column and both femora. Significantly higher BMD was recorded in both femora. A current meta-analysis reported that individuals with overweight tend to have higher BMD values than non-overweight individuals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Qiao et al. showed that overweight was positively associated with higher BMD and negatively correlated with the prevalence of osteoporosis in comparison with non-overweight individuals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>].</p><p id="Par44">In HPP, the complete effects of impaired bone metabolism on BMD are not fully understood. Genest et al. showed that BMD in adult HPP patients is not systematically reduced [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. Hepp et al. examined biochemical and clinical parameters of HPP patients in their cross-sectional study and compared them to healthy non-HPP patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. Here, BMD as well as parameters of body composition did not differ between adults with HPP and the control group [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. Since there is a lack of studies investigating the influence of overweight on BMD in HPP patients, the current findings revealed a similar association between BMI and BMD as in the general population. Therefore, overweight seems to increase BMD in HPP despite the fact that the overweight group showed lower Vitamin D levels which is generally associated with impaired bone metabolism and a higher risk of osteoporosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. The observation that overweight appears to increase BMD in HPP despite lower Vitamin D levels may be explained by several mechanisms in our opinion. Increased mechanical loading in overweight individuals can stimulate bone formation, potentially leading to higher BMD. Additionally, adipose tissue-derived hormones such as leptin might positively influence bone metabolism. While Vitamin D deficiency is generally associated with impaired bone metabolism and increased osteoporosis risk, the metabolic adaptations seen in overweight individuals, such as greater nutrient availability or compensatory mechanisms, may counterbalance these effects. These findings underscore the complexity of bone metabolism in HPP and highlight the need for further research into the interplay between metabolic status, Vitamin D, and bone health in this population. The current findings are limited to several aspects. The present study was conducted as a monocentric study with a limited population size. In addition to that, this study is retrospective in nature and therefore without follow-up protocol. Hence, the long-term influence of HPP and overweight adjustment on the oral health status and BMD was not examined. Nevertheless, it can be concluded that overweight (BMI&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;25 (kg/m&#x000b2;) correlates with a poorer oral health status and higher BMD when compared to non-overweight HPP patients. Significant differences were found, regarding decayed teeth, DMFT-Index, PPD, periodontitis severity index, T-Scores and Z-Scores in all regions and BMD values for both femora. The present study represents the first publication that revealed a negative influence of overweight on the oral health status in HPP patients.</p><p id="Par45">While these findings highlight the potential impact of metabolic factors on oral health, the retrospective design of the study precludes causal inferences. Confounding factors, such as dietary habits, systemic inflammation, and socioeconomic influences, may contribute to the observed associations.</p><p id="Par46">Nevertheless, the findings of this study highlight the importance of considering metabolic factors, such as overweight, in the management of oral health in patients with HPP. Overweight HPP patients exhibited significantly poorer periodontal health and increased caries prevalence, suggesting that addressing weight management could be a valuable strategy for reducing oral disease burden. Clinicians should adopt a multidisciplinary approach, integrating dental care with metabolic and nutritional counseling to optimize outcomes in this vulnerable population. Furthermore, targeted periodontal therapies and preventive measures, such as tailored oral hygiene education and regular dental check-ups, are critical for mitigating the impact of these oral health challenges.</p><p id="Par47">This study underscores the need for further research to elucidate the mechanisms linking overweight to oral health in HPP patients. Key areas for future investigation include the role of the oral microbiota in mediating these associations, the impact of systemic inflammation on periodontal disease progression, and the interplay between metabolic and genetic factors in HPP. Incorporating longitudinal study designs and advanced tools, such as microbiome analysis and patient-reported outcomes like OHRQoL, could provide deeper insights into these relationships and inform personalized treatment approaches. In addition to the recent findings, further studies with larger HPP populations are needed to confirm these results and to examine the influence of overweight as well as (extreme) obesity on the oral health status in HPP patients in more detail.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn><fn><p>Thomas Beikler and Florian Barvencik contributed equally to the study and share the position as last author.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>Not applicable.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>FB, DF, KP, TB, MA treated the patients and revised the article. FD researched the scientific literature, provided statistical findings/analysis and wrote the article. RS and MG edited the manuscript. All Authors gave final approval for publication.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>Open Access funding enabled and organized by Projekt DEAL.</p><p>TB received speaker honorarium from Alexion. The other authors declare that no funds, grants, or other support were received during the preparation of this manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The data that support the findings of this study are not openly available due to reasons of sensitivity and are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar2"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par48">This study was conducted in accordance with the principles of the Declaration of Helsinki and approved by the local ethics committee (MC 386&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;18). All the procedures/diagnostics being performed were part of the routine care.</p></notes><notes id="FPar8"><title>Consent to participate</title><p id="Par49">All the procedures/diagnostics being performed were part of the routine care. Due to the retrospective analysis of the data consent was waived by.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par50">All authors gave final approval for publication. The authors affirm that human research participants provided informed consent for publication of the images/figures.</p></notes><notes id="FPar4" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par51">FB received speakers fees and research grants by Alexion, UCB and Diasorin but not for this study. The authors have no relevant financial or non-financial interests to disclose.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Simon S, Resch H, Klaushofer K, Roschger P, Zwerina J, Kocijan R, Hypophosphatasia. From Diagnosis to Treatment. Curr Rheumatol Rep. 2018;20(11):69. 10.1007/s11926-018-0778-5. PMID: 30203264.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Tournis S, Yavropoulou MP, Polyzos SA, Doulgeraki A, Hypophosphatasia. J Clin Med. 2021;10(23):5676. 10.3390/jcm10235676. PMID: 34884378; PMCID: PMC8658462.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Fenn JS, Lorde N, Ward JM, Borovickova I, Hypophosphatasia. J Clin Pathol. 2021;74(10):635&#x02013;40. 10.1136/jclinpath-2021-207426. Epub 2021 Apr 30. PMID: 33931563.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sinha</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gabor</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Haupt-Harrington</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Deering</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Steiner</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dental manifestations in adult hypophosphatasia and their correlation with biomarkers</article-title><source>JIMD Rep</source><year>2022</year><volume>63</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>434</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jmd2.12307</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36101824</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Sinha P, Gabor R, Haupt-Harrington R, Deering L, Steiner RD. Dental manifestations in adult hypophosphatasia and their correlation with biomarkers. JIMD Rep. 2022;63(5):434&#x02013;45. 10.1002/jmd2.12307. PMID: 36101824; PMCID: PMC9458606.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36101824</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Dudde F, Fildebrandt D, Smeets R, Gosau M, Amling M, Beikler T, Barvencik F. Role of PLP-Level as a predictive marker for oral health status in adult hypophosphatasia. (2024) Clin Oral Investig. 28(8):419. 10.1007/s00784-024-05809-w. PMID: 38976034.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weider</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlagenhauf</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Seefried</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oral health status of adult hypophosphatasia patients: a cross-sectional study</article-title><source>J Clin Periodontol</source><year>2022</year><volume>49</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1253</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jcpe.13718</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36054522</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Weider M, Schlagenhauf U, Seefried L. Oral health status of adult hypophosphatasia patients: a cross-sectional study. J Clin Periodontol. 2022;49(12):1253&#x02013;61. 10.1111/jcpe.13718. Epub 2022 Sep 7. PMID: 36054522.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36054522</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bangura A, Wright L, Shuler T, Hypophosphatasia. Current literature for pathophysiology, clinical manifestations, diagnosis, and treatment. Cureus. 2020;12(6):e8594. 10.7759/cureus.8594. PMID: 32676235; PMCID: PMC7362651.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Issrani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bader</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Albalawi</surname><given-names>RFH</given-names></name><name><surname>Alserhani</surname><given-names>EDM</given-names></name><name><surname>Alruwaili</surname><given-names>DSR</given-names></name><name><surname>Alanazi</surname><given-names>GRA</given-names></name><name><surname>Alruwaili</surname><given-names>NSR</given-names></name><name><surname>Sghaireen</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exploring an association between body Mass Index and oral Health-A scoping review</article-title><source>Diagnostics (Basel)</source><year>2023</year><volume>13</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>902</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/diagnostics13050902</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36900046</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Issrani R, Reddy J, Bader AK, Albalawi RFH, Alserhani EDM, Alruwaili DSR, Alanazi GRA, Alruwaili NSR, Sghaireen MG, Rao K. Exploring an association between body Mass Index and oral Health-A scoping review. Diagnostics (Basel). 2023;13(5):902. 10.3390/diagnostics13050902. PMID: 36900046; PMCID: PMC10000970.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36900046</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>WHO</collab></person-group><source>Physical status: the Use and Interpretation of Anthropometry: report of a World Health Organization (WHO) Expert Committee</source><year>1995</year><publisher-loc>Geneva, Switzerland</publisher-loc><publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="book">WHO. Physical status: the Use and Interpretation of Anthropometry: report of a World Health Organization (WHO) Expert Committee. Geneva, Switzerland: World Health Organization; 1995.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abu-Shawish</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Betsy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Anil</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Is obesity a risk factor for Periodontal Disease in adults? A systematic review</article-title><source>Int J Environ Res Public Health</source><year>2022</year><volume>19</volume><issue>19</issue><fpage>12684</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph191912684</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36231983</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Abu-Shawish G, Betsy J, Anil S. Is obesity a risk factor for Periodontal Disease in adults? A systematic review. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2022;19(19):12684. 10.3390/ijerph191912684. PMID: 36231983; PMCID: PMC9566678.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36231983</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohde</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Raymond</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Heitmann</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association between periodontal disease and overweight and obesity: a systematic review</article-title><source>J Periodontol</source><year>2015</year><volume>86</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>766</fpage><lpage>76</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1902/jop.2015.140589</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25672656</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Keller A, Rohde JF, Raymond K, Heitmann BL. Association between periodontal disease and overweight and obesity: a systematic review. J Periodontol. 2015;86(6):766&#x02013;76. 10.1902/jop.2015.140589. Epub 2015 Feb 12. PMID: 25672656.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25672656</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qiao</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association of obesity with bone mineral density and osteoporosis in adults: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Public Health</source><year>2020</year><volume>180</volume><fpage>22</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.puhe.2019.11.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31837611</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Qiao D, Li Y, Liu X, Zhang X, Qian X, Zhang H, Zhang G, Wang C. Association of obesity with bone mineral density and osteoporosis in adults: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Public Health. 2020;180:22&#x02013;8. Epub 2020 Feb 21. PMID: 31837611.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31837611</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Khan AA, Brandi ML, Rush ET, Ali DS, Al-Alwani H, Almonaei K, Alsarraf F, Bacrot S, Dahir KM, Dandurand K, Deal C, Ferrari SL, Giusti F, Guyatt G, Hatcher E, Ing SW, Javaid MK, Khan S, Kocijan R, Linglart A, M&#x02019;Hiri I, Marini F, Nunes ME, Rockman-Greenberg C, Roux C, Seefried L, Simmons JH, Starling SR, Ward LM, Yao L, Brignardello-Petersen R, Lewiecki EM. Hypophosphatasia diagnosis: current state of the art and proposed diagnostic criteria for children and adults. (2024) Osteoporos Int. 35(3):431&#x02013;438. 10.1007/s00198-023-06844-1. PMID: 37982857.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Aziz</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bale</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bick</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gastier-Foster</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Grody</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Hegde</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyon</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Spector</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Voelkerding</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Rehm</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><collab>ACMG Laboratory Quality Assurance Committee</collab></person-group><article-title>Standards and guidelines for the interpretation of sequence variants: a joint consensus recommendation of the American College of Medical Genetics and Genomics and the Association for Molecular Pathology</article-title><source>Genet Med</source><year>2015</year><volume>17</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>405</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/gim.2015.30</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25741868</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Richards S, Aziz N, Bale S, Bick D, Das S, Gastier-Foster J, Grody WW, Hegde M, Lyon E, Spector E, Voelkerding K, Rehm HL, ACMG Laboratory Quality Assurance Committee. Standards and guidelines for the interpretation of sequence variants: a joint consensus recommendation of the American College of Medical Genetics and Genomics and the Association for Molecular Pathology. Genet Med. 2015;17(5):405&#x02013;24. 10.1038/gim.2015.30. Epub 2015 Mar 5. PMID: 25741868; PMCID: PMC4544753.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25741868</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">El Maghraoui A, Roux C. DXA scanning in clinical practice. (2008) QJM. 101(8):605&#x02013;17. 10.1093/qjmed/hcn022. PMID: 18334497.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Holtfreter B, Albandar JM, Dietrich T, Dye BA, Eaton KA, Eke PI, Papapanou PN, Kocher T, Joint EUUSA, Periodontal Epide- miology Working Group. Standards for reporting chronic periodontitis prevalence and severity in epidemiologic studies: Proposed standards from the Joint EU/USA Periodontal Epidemi- ology Working Group. (2015) J Clin Periodontol. 42(5):407&#x02013;12. 10.1111/jcpe.12392. PMID: 25808877.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Eke PI, Page RC, Wei L, Thornton-Evans G, Genco RJ. Update of the case definitions for population-based surveillance of periodontitis. (2012) J Periodontol. 83(12):1449-54. 10.1902/jop.2012.110664. PMID: 22420873.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Jordan AR, Micheelis W, Cholmakow-Bodechtel C, F&#x000fc;&#x000df;l-Gr&#x000fc;nig E, Geyer S, Hertrampf K, Hoffmann T, Holtfreter B, Kocher T, Nitschke I, Noffz S, Scharf L, Schiffner U, Sch&#x000fc;tzhold S, Stark H, Zimmer S. F&#x000fc;nfte Deutsche Mundgesundheitsstudie (DMS-V). Deutscher Zahn&#x000e4;rzte Verlag D&#x000c4;V; 2016.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Powell-Wiley</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Poirier</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Despr&#x000e9;s</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Gordon-Larsen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lavie</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lear</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ndumele</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Neeland</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanders</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>St-Onge</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><collab>American Heart Association Council on Lifestyle and Cardiometabolic Health; Council on Cardiovascular and Stroke Nursing; Council on Clinical Cardiology; Council on Epidemiology and Prevention; and Stroke Council</collab></person-group><article-title>Obesity and Cardiovascular Disease: A Scientific Statement from the American Heart Association</article-title><source>Circulation</source><year>2021</year><volume>143</volume><issue>21</issue><fpage>e984</fpage><lpage>1010</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIR.0000000000000973</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33882682</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Powell-Wiley TM, Poirier P, Burke LE, Despr&#x000e9;s JP, Gordon-Larsen P, Lavie CJ, Lear SA, Ndumele CE, Neeland IJ, Sanders P, St-Onge MP, American Heart Association Council on Lifestyle and Cardiometabolic Health; Council on Cardiovascular and Stroke Nursing; Council on Clinical Cardiology; Council on Epidemiology and Prevention; and Stroke Council. Obesity and Cardiovascular Disease: A Scientific Statement from the American Heart Association. Circulation. 2021;143(21):e984&#x02013;1010. 10.1161/CIR.0000000000000973. Epub 2021 Apr 22. PMID: 33882682; PMCID: PMC8493650.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33882682</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Alswat K, Mohamed WS, Wahab MA, Aboelil AA. The Association Between Body Mass Index and Dental Caries: Cross-Sectional Study. J Clin Med Res. 2016;8(2):147&#x02013;&#x02009;52. doi: 10.14740/jocmr2433w. Epub 2015 Dec 28. PMID: 26767084; PMCID: PMC4701071.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kushner</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of unhealthy lifestyle patterns among overweight and obese adults</article-title><source>Obes (Silver Spring)</source><year>2010</year><volume>18</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1160</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/oby.2009.376</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Kushner RF, Choi SW. Prevalence of unhealthy lifestyle patterns among overweight and obese adults. Obes (Silver Spring). 2010;18(6):1160&#x02013;7. 10.1038/oby.2009.376. Epub 2009 Oct 29. PMID: 19875995.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lagerweij M, van Loveren C. Chapter 7: Sugar and Dental Caries. Monogr Oral Sci. 2020;28:68&#x02013;76. doi: 10.1159/000455373. Epub 2019 Nov 7. PMID: 31940627.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Struzycka</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The oral microbiome in dental caries</article-title><source>Pol J Microbiol</source><year>2014</year><volume>63</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.33073/pjm-2014-018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25115106</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Struzycka I. The oral microbiome in dental caries. Pol J Microbiol. 2014;63(2):127&#x02013;35. PMID: 25115106.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25115106</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>K&#x000f6;nig</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><source>Karies Und Kariesprophylaxe</source><year>1971</year><publisher-loc>M&#x000fc;nchen</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Wilhelm Goldmann Verlag GmbH</publisher-name></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="book">K&#x000f6;nig K. Karies Und Kariesprophylaxe. M&#x000fc;nchen: Wilhelm Goldmann Verlag GmbH; 1971.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lemos JA, Palmer SR, Zeng L, Wen ZT, Kajfasz JK, Freires IA, Abranches J, Brady LJ. The Biology of <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic>. Microbiol Spectr. 2019;7(1). 10.1128/. PMID: 30657107; PMCID: PMC6615571. microbiolspec.GPP3-0051-2018.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR26" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Marzooq</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Saad</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Benzina</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Al Kawas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dysbiosis of the Subgingival Microbiome and Relation to Periodontal Disease in Association with obesity and overweight</article-title><source>Nutrients</source><year>2023</year><volume>15</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>826</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/nu15040826</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36839184</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26" publication-type="journal">Rahman B, Al-Marzooq F, Saad H, Benzina D, Al Kawas S. Dysbiosis of the Subgingival Microbiome and Relation to Periodontal Disease in Association with obesity and overweight. Nutrients. 2023;15(4):826. 10.3390/nu15040826. PMID: 36839184; PMCID: PMC9965236.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36839184</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR27" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baskaradoss</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Tavares</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Mulla</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Ozairi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Abu-Farha</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bin-Hasan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Alsumait</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Devarajan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Alqaderi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association between frequency of Toothbrushing and metabolic syndrome among adolescents: a 5-Year Follow-Up study</article-title><source>Int J Environ Res Public Health</source><year>2022</year><volume>19</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>508</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph19010508</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35010768</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27" publication-type="journal">Baskaradoss JK, Tavares M, Al-Mulla F, Al-Ozairi E, Abu-Farha M, Bin-Hasan S, Alsumait A, Devarajan S, Alqaderi H. Association between frequency of Toothbrushing and metabolic syndrome among adolescents: a 5-Year Follow-Up study. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2022;19(1):508. 10.3390/ijerph19010508. PMID: 35010768; PMCID: PMC8744688.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35010768</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR28" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Awad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bani Issa</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Radwan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Fakhry</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Yateem</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossiter</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association between obesity and dental caries among adolescents in UAE: a pilot cross sectional study</article-title><source>Front Oral Health</source><year>2023</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1160428</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/froh.2023.1160428</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37441619</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28" publication-type="journal">Awad M, Bani Issa W, Radwan H, Fakhry R, Al-Yateem N, Rossiter R. Association between obesity and dental caries among adolescents in UAE: a pilot cross sectional study. Front Oral Health. 2023;4:1160428. 10.3389/froh.2023.1160428. PMID: 37441619; PMCID: PMC10333752.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37441619</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR29" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manohar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fahey</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Arora</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Obesity and dental caries in early childhood: a systematic review and meta-analyses</article-title><source>Obes Rev</source><year>2020</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>e12960</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/obr.12960</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31721413</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29" publication-type="journal">Manohar N, Hayen A, Fahey P, Arora A. Obesity and dental caries in early childhood: a systematic review and meta-analyses. Obes Rev. 2020;21:e12960. 10.1111/obr.12960.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31721413</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR30" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interleukin-1&#x003b2; is a potential therapeutic target for periodontitis: a narrative review</article-title><source>Int J Oral Sci</source><year>2020</year><volume>12</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>2</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41368-019-0068-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31900383</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30" publication-type="journal">Cheng R, Wu Z, Li M, Shao M, Hu T. Interleukin-1&#x003b2; is a potential therapeutic target for periodontitis: a narrative review. Int J Oral Sci. 2020;12(1):2. 10.1038/s41368-019-0068-8. PMID: 31900383; PMCID: PMC6949296.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31900383</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ramadan DE, Hariyani N, Indrawati R, Ridwan RD, Diyatri I. Cytokines and Chemokines in Periodontitis. Eur J Dent. 2020;14(3):483&#x02013;495. doi: 10.1055/s-0040-1712718. Epub 2020 Jun 23. PMID: 32575137; PMCID: PMC7440949.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR32" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cetin</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Sezgin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Onder</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bakirarar</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The relationship between body mass index and stage/grade of periodontitis: a retrospective study</article-title><source>Clin Oral Investig</source><year>2022</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>1937</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00784-021-04172-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34709456</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32" publication-type="journal">Cetin MB, Sezgin Y, Onder C, Bakirarar B. The relationship between body mass index and stage/grade of periodontitis: a retrospective study. Clin Oral Investig. 2022;26:1937&#x02013;45. 10.1007/s00784-021-04172-4.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34709456</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR33" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dibello</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Lobbezoo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Sardone</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lozupone</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Castellana</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Zupo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pilotto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Daniele</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Solfrizzi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Manfredini</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Panza</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The relationship between oral health-related quality of life and body Mass Index in an older Population from Southern Italy: the Salus in Apulia Study</article-title><source>J Pers Med</source><year>2023</year><volume>13</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1300</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jpm13091300</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37763068</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR33" publication-type="journal">Dibello V, Lobbezoo F, Sardone R, Lozupone M, Castellana F, Zupo R, Pilotto A, Daniele A, Solfrizzi V, Manfredini D, Panza F. The relationship between oral health-related quality of life and body Mass Index in an older Population from Southern Italy: the Salus in Apulia Study. J Pers Med. 2023;13(9):1300. 10.3390/jpm13091300. PMID: 37763068; PMCID: PMC10533155.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37763068</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR34" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of vitamin D in periodontal health and disease</article-title><source>J Periodontal Res</source><year>2023</year><volume>58</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>213</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jre.13083</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36537578</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR34" publication-type="journal">Lu EM. The role of vitamin D in periodontal health and disease. J Periodontal Res. 2023;58(2):213&#x02013;24. 10.1111/jre.13083. Epub 2022 Dec 20. PMID: 36537578.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36537578</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR35" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Botelho</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Machado</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Proen&#x000e7;a</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Delgado</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Mendes</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vitamin D Deficiency and oral health: a Comprehensive Review</article-title><source>Nutrients</source><year>2020</year><volume>12</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1471</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/nu12051471</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32438644</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR35" publication-type="journal">Botelho J, Machado V, Proen&#x000e7;a L, Delgado AS, Mendes JJ. Vitamin D Deficiency and oral health: a Comprehensive Review. Nutrients. 2020;12(5):1471. 10.3390/nu12051471. PMID: 32438644; PMCID: PMC7285165.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32438644</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR36" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Genest</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Clau&#x000df;en</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Rak</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Seefried</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bone mineral density and fracture risk in adult patients with hypophosphatasia</article-title><source>Osteoporos Int</source><year>2021</year><volume>32</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>377</fpage><lpage>85</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00198-020-05612-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32879991</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR36" publication-type="journal">Genest F, Clau&#x000df;en L, Rak D, Seefried L. Bone mineral density and fracture risk in adult patients with hypophosphatasia. Osteoporos Int. 2021;32(2):377&#x02013;85. 10.1007/s00198-020-05612-9. Epub 2020 Sep 2. PMID: 32879991; PMCID: PMC7838076.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32879991</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR37" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hepp</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Frederiksen</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Duno</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>J&#x000f8;rgensen</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biochemical and clinical manifestations in adults with hypophosphatasia: a national cross-sectional study</article-title><source>Osteoporos Int</source><year>2022</year><volume>33</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>2595</fpage><lpage>605</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00198-022-06536-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35986118</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR37" publication-type="journal">Hepp N, Frederiksen AL, Duno M, J&#x000f8;rgensen NR, Jensen JB. Biochemical and clinical manifestations in adults with hypophosphatasia: a national cross-sectional study. Osteoporos Int. 2022;33(12):2595&#x02013;605. 10.1007/s00198-022-06536-2. Epub 2022 Aug 19. PMID: 35986118.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35986118</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">De Martinis M, Allegra A, Sirufo MM, Tonacci A, Pioggia G, Raggiunti M, Ginaldi L, Gangemi S, Vitamin D, Deficiency. Osteoporosis and effect on Autoimmune diseases and hematopoiesis: a review. Int J Mol Sci. 2021;22(16):8855. 10.3390/ijms22168855. PMID: 34445560; PMCID: PMC8396272.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>