<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mar Life Sci Technol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Mar Life Sci Technol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Marine Life Science &#x00026; Technology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2096-6490</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2662-1746</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer Nature Singapore</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Singapore</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12102460</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">275</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s42995-024-00275-5</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Paper</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Rediscovery and morpho-molecular characterization of three astome ciliates, with new insights into eco-evolutionary associations of astomes with their annelid hosts</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Obert</surname><given-names>Tom&#x000e1;&#x00161;</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Tengyue</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rurik</surname><given-names>Ivan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>V&#x0010f;a&#x0010d;n&#x000fd;</surname><given-names>Peter</given-names></name><address><email>peter.vdacny@uniba.sk</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/0587ef340</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.7634.6</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0940 9708</institution-id><institution>Department of Zoology, Faculty of Natural Sciences, </institution><institution>Comenius University in Bratislava, </institution></institution-wrap>842 15 Bratislava, Slovak Republic </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/01p884a79</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.256885.4</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1791 4722</institution-id><institution>The Key Laboratory of Zoological Systematics and Application, College of Life Sciences, </institution><institution>Hebei University, </institution></institution-wrap>Baoding, 071002 China </aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn fn-type="com"><p>Edited by Jiamei Li.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>17</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>231</fpage><lpage>255</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>7</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Astome ciliates live in the digestive tract of a broad spectrum of marine, freshwater, and terricolous annelids. In aquatic lumbriculid and criodrilid oligochaetes collected in Central Europe, we rediscovered three insufficiently known astomes: <italic>Hoplitophrya secans</italic>, <italic>Mesnilella clavata</italic>, and <italic>Buchneriella criodrili</italic>. Their morphology was studied using in vivo observation, protargol, and dry silver nitrate impregnation. Multiple nuclear and mitochondrial molecular markers were used to determine their phylogenetic positions and reconstruct their evolutionary history. According to our phylogenetic analyses: (1) mouthless ciliates isolated from annelids form a robustly supported monophylum within the class Oligohymenophorea, (2) the progenitor of astomes invaded the digestive tract of marine polychaetes during the Paleozoic era, (3) lumbricid earthworms likely served as a source of astomes for criodrilid, almid, and megascolecid earthworms, (4) the ancestral host of the earthworm-dwelling astome clade led an endogeic lifestyle, and (5) there were multiple independent transfers of astomes from endogeic to epigeic and anecic earthworms. These findings support previous views of the annelid phylogeny, suggesting that astomes reside and evolve in tandem with annelids for several hundred million years.</p><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1007/s42995-024-00275-5.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Comparative network analyses</kwd><kwd>Endosymbionts</kwd><kwd>Integrative taxonomy</kwd><kwd>Oligochaeta</kwd><kwd>Oligohymenophorea</kwd><kwd>Phylogeny</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Comenius University in Bratislava</institution></funding-source></award-group><open-access><p>Open access funding provided by The Ministry of Education, Science, Research and Sport of the Slovak Republic in cooperation with Centre for Scientific and Technical Information of the Slovak Republic</p></open-access></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Ocean University of China 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">The phylum Ciliophora Doflein, 1901 (ciliates) is one of the most diverse clades of eukaryotic microorganisms, with a long evolutionary history dating back to the Proterozoic period more than a billion years ago (Jiang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2024</xref>; Lynn <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">2008</xref>; Parfrey et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">2011</xref>). Over geological time, approximately one-third of ciliate species have become symbionts of animals, ranging from platyhelminths, annelids, mollusks, and arthropods through echinoderms to both poikilo- and homoiotherm vertebrates (for reviews, see Corliss <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2000</xref> and Lynn <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">2008</xref>). Within invertebrate hosts, annelids harbor a diverse ciliate assemblage comprising four groups: the family Plagiotomidae from the class Spirotrichea (Obert and V&#x0010f;a&#x0010d;n&#x000fd; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">2020a</xref>; Obert et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">2022</xref>), the family Nyctotheridae from the class Armophorea (Albaret and Njin&#x000e9; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1975</xref>; Fokam et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2014</xref>; Ngassam <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">1983a</xref>), the family Hysterocinetidae (Obert et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">2023</xref>; Raabe <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">1972</xref>) and the subclass Astomatia (de Puytorac <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">1954</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">1969</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">1972</xref>) both from the class Oligohymenophorea. According to molecular clock analyses, ciliates first populated the digestive tract of annelids in the Paleozoic period, between 587 and 247 million years ago (Zhang and V&#x0010f;a&#x0010d;n&#x000fd; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">2022</xref>). Further independent colonizations of the annelid mid- and hindgut occurred more recently, e.g., in the Cenozoic about 35 million years ago (Obert et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">2022</xref>).</p><p id="Par3">The subclass Astomatia is the most diverse among the four ciliate groups populating the annelid digestive tract, with over two hundred species from more than 50 genera (Lynn <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">2008</xref>). These ciliates have lost their oral ciliature and cytostome (cell mouth), as their name implies. They typically attach to the intestinal epithelium by a variety of holdfast and skeletal organelles located on the anterior pole or in the anterior region of the cell (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>A&#x02012;D), although the skeletal attachment apparatus has been lost multiple times (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>E). Astomes range from&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;80&#x000a0;&#x000b5;m to&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1&#x000a0;mm (de Puytorac <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">1954</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">1969</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">1972</xref>), with varying cell shapes (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>E). The macronucleus is elongate, often almost as long as the cell, and the micronucleus is globular, ellipsoidal, or fusiform (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>A, E). Contractile vacuoles are arranged in one or two rows, form a stripe, or are scattered throughout the cell (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>A, E). Finally, the somatic ciliation is usually dense, holotrichous, and formed by monokinetids arranged in meridional or spiraling rows often creating anterior and posterior sutures (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>C, D).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Introduction to morphological characters (<bold>A</bold>&#x02012;<bold>D</bold>) and phylogenetic relationships of astome ciliates (<bold>E</bold>). <bold>A</bold> A typical astome to show the key morphological structures. <bold>B</bold> Skeletal apparatus of two representatives of the family Hoplitophryidae. <bold>C</bold> Skeletal apparatus of a representative of the family Maupasellidae (upper part) and ciliary pattern in the anterior body portion of the genus <italic>Njinella</italic> (lower part), which completely lost the skeletal apparatus<italic>.</italic>
<bold>D</bold> Skeletal apparatus and ciliary pattern in the anterior body portion of the genus <italic>Metaradiophrya</italic> (left) as well as the anterior and posterior sutures of the closely related genus <italic>Anoplophrya</italic> (right), which completely lost the skeletal apparatus. <bold>E</bold> The subclass Astomatia stemmed within the paraphyletic subclass Scuticociliatia. Astomes living in terrestrial and freshwater oligochaetes (Almidae, Criodrilidae, Lumbriculidae, Lumbricidae, and Megascolecidae) branched off after astomes inhabiting marine polychaetes. <italic>Durchodniella</italic> from Sauvadet et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">2017</xref>), <italic>Eudrilophrya</italic>, <italic>Metaracoelophrya</italic> and <italic>Paraclausilocola</italic> from Fokam (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2012</xref>), and <italic>Njinella</italic> from Ngassam (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">1983b</xref>). <italic>CV</italic> contractile vacuoles, <italic>FI</italic> fibers, <italic>MA</italic> macronucleus, <italic>MI</italic> micronucleus, <italic>S</italic> spicule, <italic>SA</italic> skeletal apparatus, <italic>SK</italic> somatic kineties</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="42995_2024_275_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p id="Par4">Annelid hosts of astomes live in marine, freshwater, and terrestrial environments. Terricolous earthworms are subdivided into three ecological groups (Jeffery et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2010</xref>): epigeic (litter- or surface-dwelling), anecic (topsoil-dwelling), and endogeic (subsoil-dwelling). Phylogenetic studies suggested that astome ciliates cluster according to associations with higher taxa of their hosts and/or their ecological groups (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>E; Fokam et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2011</xref>; Obert and V&#x0010f;a&#x0010d;n&#x000fd; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">2019</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">2020b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2021</xref>; Obert et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2021</xref>). Astomes isolated from terrestrial megadrilid oligochaetes form a sister group to astomes from marine polychaetes (Sauvadet et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">2017</xref>), or astomes inhabiting polychaetes are placed more basally than astomes living in oligochaetes (Park and Leander <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">2024</xref>). Astomes inhabiting the digestive tract of megascolecid and almid earthworms form distinct and well-separated clades (Fokam et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2011</xref>). Astomes living in endogeic earthworms form deep-branching lineages, while astomes from epigeic and anecic earthworms emerged multiple times independently in the terminal radiation of the subclass Astomatia (Obert and V&#x0010f;a&#x0010d;n&#x000fd; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">2019</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">2020b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2021</xref>; Obert et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2021</xref>). This eco-evolutionary pattern mirrors the fact that the endogeic lifestyle (subsoil-dwelling and geophagy) represents the ground pattern of lumbricid earthworms, and epigeic and anecic earthworms evolved several times convergently from endogeic ancestors (Dom&#x000ed;nguez et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2015</xref>). However, after the inclusion of further astomes in phylogenetic analyses, it seems that ciliates isolated from terrestrial and semi-aquatic lumbricid earthworms form a paraphyletic assemblage comprising also astomes from megascolecid and almid earthworms (Obert et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2021</xref>). It, therefore, seems that further analysis of astomes is needed to assess their phylogeny.</p><p id="Par5">The morphological and molecular diversity of astome ciliates associated with soil earthworms of the family Lumbricidae have been investigated in detail (Obert and V&#x0010f;a&#x0010d;n&#x000fd; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">2019</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">2020b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2021</xref>; Obert et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2021</xref>). However, the taxonomy and phylogeny of astomes living in freshwater oligochaetes is still poorly understood. To better understand the eco-evolutionary associations of ciliates and annelids, we selected two aquatic oligochaetes: one representing an old lineage (<italic>Lumbriculus variegatus</italic>, Lumbriculidae) and one representing a more recent lineage (<italic>Criodrilus lacuum</italic>, Criodrilidae). By necessity, due to questionable taxonomic reports, we have also provided a historical and current reassessment of the ciliate taxa (<italic>Hoplitophrya secans</italic>, <italic>Mesnilella clavata</italic>, and <italic>Buchneriella criodrili</italic>) isolated from the worms. By examining astomes from these oligochaetes, we were able to test the following hypotheses: (1) astomes first invaded marine polychaetes, then freshwater lumbriculid oligochaetes, and finally terrestrial and aquatic earthworms and (2) endogeic lumbricids were the first terrestrial earthworms to be colonized.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Material and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Sampling and morphological taxonomic methods</title><p id="Par6">The host oligochaetes, <italic>L. variegatus</italic> M&#x000fc;ller, 1774 and <italic>C. lacuum</italic> Hoffmeister, 1845, were collected from three localities in western Slovakia, Central Europe (see ciliate descriptions for details). They were morphologically (Timm <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">2009</xref>) and molecularly identified using barcoding of the nuclear 18S rRNA gene, ITS region, partial 28S rRNA gene sequences as well as of the mitochondrial genes coding for NADH-ubiquinone oxidoreductase chain 1 (ND1) and cytochrome <italic>c</italic> oxidase subunit I (COI). Primers and PCR protocols used are described elsewhere (Obert et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2021</xref>).</p><p id="Par7">The digestive tracts were dissected and examined for ciliates, which were isolated and identified in vivo at 50&#x02012;400&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;and 1000&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;(oil immersion) magnification, with bright field and DIC optics, following guidelines of Foissner (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2014</xref>). The nuclear apparatus and somatic ciliary patterns were visualized with protargol staining (Wilbert <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">1975</xref>). The silverline system was revealed using dry silver nitrate impregnation (Klein <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">1958</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Molecular methods</title><p id="Par8">Ciliates were cleaned in Ringer&#x02019;s solution (0.6% NaCl) and stored in 180 &#x003bc;L of cell lysis buffer (Promega, Fitchburg, Wisconsin, USA) at 6&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. Each sample contained one cell (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;5 cells for <italic>H. secans</italic> and <italic>B. criodrili</italic> and 9 for <italic>M. clavata</italic>). Genomic DNA was isolated using the ReliaPrep<sup>&#x02122;</sup> Blood gDNA Miniprep System (Promega, Fitchburg, Wisconsin, USA). Three nuclear rRNA genes (18S, 5.8S, 28S), their spacers (ITS1, ITS2), and the barcoding mitochondrial COI and 16S rRNA genes were PCR amplified, following the protocols of Obert et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2021</xref>). PCRs were conducted with GoTaq<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> Long PCR Master Mix (Promega, Fitchburg, Wisconsin, USA). Sequences were acquired by bidirectional Sanger sequencing on an ABI 3730 automatic sequencer in Macrogen Europe B.V. (Amsterdam, The Netherlands).</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Phylogenetic tree-building methods</title><p id="Par9">The quality of acquired sequences was checked in Chromas ver. 2.6.6 (Technelysium Pty Ltd, South Brisbane, Australia). High-quality sequences (Phred score&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;20) were assembled into contigs using BioEdit ver. 7.2.5 (Hall <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">1999</xref>). Individual genes were aligned on the MAFFT ver. 7 server (Katoh et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2019</xref>), using the E-INS-i strategy and the 200PAM/&#x003ba;&#x02009;=&#x02009;2 scoring matrix with a gap opening penalty at 1.53. No masking was employed.</p><p id="Par10">Three datasets were assembled to determine the phylogenetic position of acquired sequences within the subclass Astomatia. The first dataset contained only 18S rRNA gene sequences sampled across the class Oligohymenophorea, with the subclass Peritrichia as an outgroup, following the study of Jiang et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2019</xref>). The second dataset consisted of sequences from the mitochondrial and nuclear rRNA genes and their spacers obtained from members of the subclass Astomatia. The third dataset comprised the mitochondrial and nuclear rRNA genes and their spacers plus the mitochondrial COI sequences. For GenBank accession numbers of sequences used in datasets 1&#x02012;3, see Supplementary Tables 1 and 2.</p><p id="Par11">Phylogenetic trees were constructed using the maximum likelihood (ML) approach and Bayesian inference. ML trees were built in IQ-TREE ver. 1.6.12 (Nguyen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">2015</xref>) on the IQ-TREE web server (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://iqtree.cibiv.univie.ac.at/">http://iqtree.cibiv.univie.ac.at/</ext-link>) (Trifinopoulos et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">2016</xref>). The best evolutionary model was determined for each molecular marker using the built-in ModelFinder (Kalyaanamoorthy et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2017</xref>). The robustness of the inferred ML tree topologies was assessed by 1000 ultrafast bootstrap pseudoreplicates, and the bnni algorithm was used to avoid overestimating bootstrap support (Hoang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2018</xref>). Bayesian analyses were conducted using MrBayes on XSEDE ver. 3.2.7a (Ronquist et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">2012</xref>) on the CIPRES portal (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.phylo.org/">http://www.phylo.org/</ext-link>) (Miller et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">2010</xref>) with the following settings: (1) five million generations for the first and second datasets and two million generations for the third dataset; (2) a sampling frequency of trees and parameters at one hundred; (3) a relative burn-in fraction at 25%; and (4) prior parameters of the best evolutionary models (as determined by ModelFinder) were implemented with the &#x02018;lset&#x02019; and &#x02018;prset&#x02019; commands. The convergence of Bayesian analyses was considered successful since the standard deviation of split frequencies was consistently &#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, the average potential scale reduction factor was 1.00, and the effective sample sizes of all parameters were&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;200, with no obvious trends in the plots of generations versus log probability. All trees were visualized in FigTree ver. 1.2.3 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://tree.bio.ed.ac.uk/software/figtree/">http://tree.bio.ed.ac.uk/software/figtree/</ext-link>).</p><p id="Par12">Since phylogenetic positions of some astome taxa were poorly resolved, tree topology testing was conducted. In each alternative scenario, only the monophyly of/kinships within a certain group was forced; all other relationships were left unspecified. The best unconstraint ML tree and five constraint trees (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) were constructed from the first dataset in IQ-TREE with the aforementioned settings. The reliability of alternative tree topologies was assessed using the approximately unbiased test (Shimodaira <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">2002</xref>), the weighted Shimodaira&#x02012;Hasegawa test (Shimodaira and Hasegawa <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">1999</xref>), the weighted Kishino&#x02012;Hasegawa test (Kishino and Hasegawa <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">1989</xref>), and 10,000 re-samplings using the RELL method (Kishino et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">1990</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Statistical tree topology tests to compare different evolutionary scenarios</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Evolutionary scenario</th><th align="left">logL</th><th align="left">&#x00394; logL</th><th align="left">WKH</th><th align="left">WSH</th><th align="left">RELL</th><th align="left">AU</th><th align="left">Conclusion</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Best scoring maximum likelihood tree (unconstrained)</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02012;&#x000a0;21,807.8136</td><td align="left">&#x02012;</td><td char="." align="char">0.578</td><td char="." align="char">0.961</td><td char="." align="char">0.294</td><td char="." align="char">0.777</td><td align="left">&#x02012;</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Durchoniella</italic> sister to <italic>Pennarella</italic></td><td char="." align="char">&#x02012;&#x000a0;21,814.7580</td><td align="left">6.9444</td><td char="." align="char">0.091</td><td char="." align="char">0.217</td><td char="." align="char">0.029*</td><td char="." align="char">0.104</td><td align="left">Rejected</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Monophyly of astomes isolated from oligochaetes</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02012;&#x000a0;21,810.7032</td><td align="left">2.8896</td><td char="." align="char">0.220</td><td char="." align="char">0.567</td><td char="." align="char">0.108</td><td char="." align="char">0.351</td><td align="left">Not rejected</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(<italic>Anoplophrya vulgaris</italic>, ((<italic>A. lumbrici</italic>, <italic>A. octolasionis</italic>), (<italic>A. allolobophorae</italic>, <italic>A. aporrectodeae</italic>)))</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02012;&#x000a0;21,812.2793</td><td align="left">4.4657</td><td char="." align="char">0.291</td><td char="." align="char">0.536</td><td char="." align="char">0.137</td><td char="." align="char">0.329</td><td align="left">Not rejected</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(<italic>Metaradiophrya varians</italic>, (<italic>M. speculorum</italic>, (<italic>M. lumbrici</italic>, <italic>M. chlorotica</italic>)))</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02012;&#x000a0;21,809.4902</td><td align="left">1.6766</td><td char="." align="char">0.422</td><td char="." align="char">0.635</td><td char="." align="char">0.354</td><td char="." align="char">0.475</td><td align="left">Not rejected</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Subanoplophrya</italic> sister to all other astomes isolated from crassiclitellates</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02012;&#x000a0;21,809.2686</td><td align="left">1.4550</td><td char="." align="char">0.230</td><td char="." align="char">0.664</td><td char="." align="char">0.078</td><td char="." align="char">0.351</td><td align="left">Not rejected</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>logL</italic> log likelihood, <italic>&#x00394; logL</italic> difference between log likelihoods of a constrained and the best (unconstrained) tree, <italic>WKH</italic> weighted Kishino&#x02012;Hasegawa test, <italic>WSH</italic> weighted Shimodaira&#x02012;Hasegawa test, <italic>RELL</italic> bootstrap proportion using the RELL method, <italic>AU</italic> approximately unbiased test</p><p>*<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Comparative phylogenetic network methods</title><p id="Par13">The first dataset was pruned to contain only astomes and the outgroup scuticociliates. Evolutionary scenarios that could not be rejected by tree topology testing served to build constrained time-calibrated trees. Unconstrained and constrained trees were constructed with BEAST ver. 2.6.7 (Bouckaert et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2014</xref>) using the GTR&#x02009;+&#x02009;I (=&#x02009;0.5732)&#x02009;+&#x02009;&#x00393;<sub>4</sub> (=&#x02009;0.4898) evolutionary model as selected by ModelFinder, relaxed lognormal clock, and the birth&#x02013;death process model for the tree prior with lognormal birth and death rates. All other parameters were left as the default. A uniform distribution with a maximum age of 261&#x000a0;Ma (mega annum) and a minimum age of 200&#x000a0;Ma was assigned to the node uniting astomes inhabiting earthworms; this was based on molecular clock analyses of earthworms (Dom&#x000ed;nguez et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2015</xref>). Settings in Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) simulations were as follows: start from a random seed, 10 initialization attempts, five million pre-burnin iterations, followed by 50 million generations, and a sampling frequency of trees and parameters at 10,000. All BEAST analyses converged to the stationary distribution, with an effective sample size&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;200 for all parameters. Altogether four independent MCMC runs were conducted for each alternative scenario, and the resulting tree files were merged in LogCombiner ver. 2.6.7. The final maximum clade credibility trees were summarized in TreeAnnotator ver. 2.6.7 (Bouckaert et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2014</xref>). A time-calibrated phylogenetic network was built from the unconstrained and constrained BEAST trees using the Julia library PhyloNetworks ver. 0.16.3 (Karimi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2020</xref>).</p><p id="Par14">Ancestral hosts of astome ciliates and their life histories were reconstructed for nodes of each alternative time-calibrated BEAST tree topology, using stochastic mapping and the SIMMAP function (Bollback <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2006</xref>) as implemented in the R library phytools ver. 1.2-0 (Revell <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">2012</xref>). For settings and the flowchart of how the best fit evolutionary models were selected and the <italic>Q</italic> matrices and posterior probabilities of ancestral host groups and their life histories were computed, see Pecina et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">2024</xref>). Finally, posterior probabilities were mapped onto the time-calibrated phylogenetic network using PhyloNetworks.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec8"><title>Characterization of new sequences</title><p id="Par15">The length and GC content of 18S varied from 1757 nt and 45.36% in <italic>B. criodrili</italic> through 1758 nt and 44.65% in <italic>M. clavata</italic> to 1763 nt and 44.64% in <italic>H. secans</italic>. ITS region-28S sequences were more variable in length and GC content than 18S: their length and GC content were 1337 nt and 47.12% in <italic>B. criodrili</italic>, 1357 nt and 43.70% in <italic>M. clavata</italic>, and 1328 nt and 45.86% in <italic>H. secans</italic>. 18S and ITS region-28S sequences were identical within species. The PCR amplified region of 16S included the C, 3&#x02032;M, and 3&#x02032;m domains. The length and GC content of this 16S fragment varied: 772 nt and 27.59% in <italic>B. criodrili</italic>, 950 nt and 36.53&#x02012;36.84% in <italic>M. clavata</italic>, and 995 nt and 35.38% in <italic>H. secans</italic>. No intraspecific variability occurred within <italic>B. criodrili</italic>, <italic>H. secans</italic>, or <italic>M. clavata</italic> populations, but the two <italic>M. clavata</italic> populations differed by 1.2%. A similar pattern occurred for the mitochondrial COI sequences; their length and GC content were 693 nt and 31.60&#x02012;34.46% in <italic>B. criodrili</italic>, 711 nt and 39.80&#x02012;40.08% in <italic>M. clavata</italic>, and 729 nt and 40.47% in <italic>H. secans</italic>. No intraspecific variability occurred within <italic>H. secans</italic>. Specimens of <italic>B. criodrili</italic> differed by a maximum of 0.2%. Similarly to 16S, no variability occurred within the two <italic>M. clavata</italic> populations, but COI sequences of both populations differed by 1.5%. The large interspecific and small intraspecific distances make the mitochondrial 16S and COI optimal DNA barcodes for astome ciliates. See Supplementary Table&#x000a0;3 for GenBank accession numbers.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Phylogenetic analyses</title><p id="Par16">The monophyly of the subclass Astomatia was supported (95% ML bootstrap/1.00 Bayesian posterior probability [PP]) in the 18S trees (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). However, relationships at the base of the astome clade were poorly resolved. Three <italic>Durchoniella</italic> species isolated from the marine polychaete <italic>Cirriformia tentaculata</italic> formed a fully supported monophylum that branched off first. Then, a strongly supported clade (95% ML/1.00 PP) comprising <italic>H. secans</italic> and <italic>M. clavata</italic>, both obtained from the freshwater <italic>L. variegatus</italic>, followed. <italic>Pennarella elegantia</italic>, isolated from the marine polychaete <italic>Myxicola aesthetica</italic>, never clustered with the polychaete-dwelling <italic>Durchoniella</italic> spp. but was placed in a sister-group position to all other astomes isolated from crassiclitellates (=&#x02009;true earthworms) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Since the positions of the <italic>Durchoniella</italic>, <italic>Pennarella</italic>, and <italic>Hoplitophrya&#x02012;Mesnilella</italic> clades received a maximum ML bootstrap support of 61% and a posterior probability of 0.80, we considered their interrelationships to be unresolved. Therefore, we performed multiple tree topology tests (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The monophyletic origin of the analyzed polychaete-dwelling astomes, <italic>Durchoniella</italic> and <italic>Pennarella</italic>, and their basal position was only rejected by the RELL method. The monophyletic origin of the analyzed oligochaete-dwelling astomes, i.e., astomes isolated from lumbriculids (<italic>Hoplitophrya&#x02012;Mesnilella</italic> clade) and crassiclitellates (i.e., true earthworms), was not be refuted by any topology test (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The clade uniting crassiclitellate-dwelling astomes was fully supported by ML and Bayesian analyses. The position of <italic>Subanoplophrya</italic> was, however, unstable and weakly supported (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). It either grouped with a clade comprising <italic>Anoplophrya</italic>, <italic>Metaradiophrya</italic>, and astomes isolated from African almid earthworms or with a clade comprising <italic>Maupasella</italic>, <italic>Buchneriella</italic>, and astomes isolated from African megascolecid earthworms. Any of these two scenarios could be excluded (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Adding further molecular markers (ITS region-28S and 16S) did not resolve the phylogenetic position of <italic>Subanoplophrya</italic>. The grouping of <italic>Anoplophrya</italic>, <italic>Metaradiophrya</italic>, and almid-dwelling astomes had strong support (96% ML/1.00 PP) in the 18S phylogenies (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). The clustering of <italic>Maupasella</italic>, <italic>Buchneriella</italic>, and megascolecid-dwelling astomes was moderately to strongly supported (89% ML/1.00 PP) in the 18S trees. Phylogenetic interrelationships within these two clades were well resolved. However, the monophyly of <italic>Metaradiophrya</italic> and its kinship to <italic>Anoplophrya</italic> were poorly supported. Adding further molecular data (ITS region-28S, 16S, and COI) supported the monophyly of each genus and their sister-group relationship. However, the intra-generic branching pattern could not be well resolved, either in the six or seven molecular marker trees (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;1A, B). Topology tests could not reject the phylogenetic relationships suggested for <italic>Anoplophrya</italic> and <italic>Metaradiophrya</italic> in coalescent-based species trees from previous analyses (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Phylogenetic tree based on the nuclear 18S rRNA gene sequences, showing the systematic positions of astome ciliates isolated from <italic>Lumbriculus variegatus</italic> and <italic>Criodrilus lacuum</italic>. The subclass Peritrichia was used to root the tree. Bootstrap values for maximum likelihood conducted in IQ-TREE and posterior probabilities for Bayesian inferences conducted in MrBayes were mapped onto the best scoring IQ-Tree. Sequences marked in red were obtained during this study. Fully statistically supported nodes are marked with red solid circles. Dash (&#x02012;) indicates a mismatch in tree topologies. The scale bar denotes eight substitutions per one hundred nucleotide positions</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="42995_2024_275_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p><p id="Par17">SIMMAP analyses suggested that the last common ancestor of the subclass Astomatia colonized the digestive tract of polychaetes in the Paleozoic about 330&#x000a0;Ma (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>A). Astomes living in lumbriculids branched off during the early radiation of the subclass Astomatia. Lumbriculid-dwelling astomes of the genera <italic>Hoplitophrya</italic> and <italic>Mesnilella</italic> diverged in the Jurassic about 176&#x000a0;Ma. The radiation of astomes living in true earthworms took place in the Triassic about 223&#x000a0;Ma. According to SIMMAP reconstructions, the ancestral host of this diverse clade was a representative of the family Lumbricidae. In different time frames, astomes switched from Lumbricidae to Almidae, Megascolecidae, and Criodrilidae hosts. No backward transfers to lumbricids were detected (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>A).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>SIMMAP reconstruction of ancestral hosts (<bold>A</bold>) and life histories (<bold>B</bold>) of astome ciliates based on 10,000 stochastic character maps simulated under the equal rates (ER) model. Relative proportions of character states were mapped onto a phylogenetic network constructed from alternative time-calibrated maximum clade credibility trees built in BEAST. Dashed vertical lines indicate alternative evolutionary trajectories in the network. The time scale shows age in millions of years</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="42995_2024_275_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p><p id="Par18">The ancestral habitat of host annelids was likely the sea regardless of the phylogenetic position of the polychaete-dwelling <italic>Pennarella</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>B). SIMMAP analyses suggested at least three independent transfers to (semi)aquatic oligochaetes: (1) lumbriculids for <italic>Hoplitophrya</italic> and <italic>Mesnilella</italic>; (2) lumbricids for <italic>Subanoplophrya</italic>; and (3) criodrilids for <italic>Buchneriella</italic>. The ancestral host of the crassiclitellate-dwelling astome clade likely led an endogeic lifestyle. Mirroring the evolutionary history of life strategies of true earthworms, the transfer to epigeic and anecic earthworms happened from endogeic ancestors multiple times independently and in rather recent time frames, i.e., in the Eocene and Oligocene epochs about 35&#x02012;25&#x000a0;Ma (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>B).</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Ciliate taxonomy</title><p id="Par19">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Phylum Ciliophora Doflein, 1901</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par20">Class Oligohymenophorea de Puytorac et al., 1974</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par21">Subclass Astomatia Schewiakoff, 1896</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par22">Order Astomatida Schewiakoff, 1896</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par23">Family Hoplitophryidae Cheissin, 1930</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par24">Genus <italic>Hoplitophrya</italic> Stein, 1860 (type species: <italic>Opalina secans</italic> Stein, 1859)</p></list-item></list>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title><italic>Hoplitophrya secans</italic> (Stein, 1859) Stein, 1861 (Figs. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>-<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>)</title><fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p><italic>Hoplitophrya secans</italic> in vivo (<bold>A</bold>, <bold>B</bold>, <bold>C</bold>, <bold>D</bold>, <bold>G</bold>, <bold>I</bold>) and after protargol impregnation (<bold>E</bold>, <bold>F</bold>, <bold>H</bold>, <bold>J</bold>&#x02012;<bold>L</bold>), neotype population. <bold>A</bold> Ventral view of a representative specimen, showing the general body organization. <bold>B</bold> Semi-schematic diagram of the ventral side, showing the ciliary pattern, the nuclear and contractile vacuole apparatus, as well as the skeletal system. <bold>C</bold> Detail of the skeletal apparatus. <bold>D</bold> Prokaryotic cytoplasmic symbionts. <bold>E</bold>&#x02012;<bold>L</bold> Variability of body shape and size as well as of the nuclear and contractile vacuole apparatus. <italic>CV</italic> contractile vacuoles, <italic>DA</italic> dorsal spicule arm,<italic> FI</italic> fibers, <italic>MA</italic> macronucleus, <italic>MI</italic> micronucleus, <italic>S</italic> spicule, <italic>SK</italic> somatic kineties, <italic>VA</italic> ventral spicule arm. Scale bars: 20&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m (<bold>C</bold>), 50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m (<bold>E</bold>), 100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m (<bold>A</bold>, <bold>B</bold>, <bold>F</bold>&#x02012;<bold>K</bold>), 100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m (<bold>L</bold>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="42995_2024_275_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig><fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;5</label><caption><p><italic>Hoplitophrya secans</italic> in vivo, neotype population (<bold>A</bold>&#x02012;<bold>E</bold>). <bold>A</bold>, <bold>B</bold> Details of the dorsal (<bold>A</bold>) and ventral (<bold>B</bold>) anterior body portion, showing the ciliary pattern and the skeletal system. Arrowhead denotes the ventral spicule arm. <bold>C</bold>, <bold>D</bold> Detail of the posterior body portion, showing the nuclear apparatus and the ciliary pattern. Note that all ciliary rows terminate slightly ahead of the posterior body pole, leaving a small blank field (asterisks). <bold>E</bold> Somatic cilia are very narrowly arranged, while somatic kineties are widely spaced. <italic>CI</italic> cilia, <italic>CV</italic> contractile vacuoles, <italic>FI</italic> fibers, <italic>LD</italic> lipid droplets, <italic>MA</italic> macronucleus, <italic>SK</italic> somatic kineties. Scale bars: 10&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m (<bold>E</bold>), 20&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m (<bold>A</bold>&#x02012;<bold>D</bold>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="42995_2024_275_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig><fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;6</label><caption><p><italic>Hoplitophrya secans</italic> after protargol impregnation, neotype population (<bold>A</bold>&#x02012;<bold>H</bold>). <bold>A</bold>&#x02012;<bold>C</bold> Variability of body shape and size as well as of the nuclear apparatus. Arrow denotes the micronucleus. <bold>D</bold> Detail of the ciliary pattern around the ventral spicule arm (arrowhead). <bold>E</bold>, <bold>F</bold> Details of the ventral (<bold>E</bold>) and dorsal (<bold>F</bold>) anterior body portion, showing the ciliary pattern. Arrowhead denotes the ventral spicule arm. <bold>G</bold> Somatic kineties are widely spaced and composed of very narrowly arranged basal bodies. <bold>H</bold> Detail of the posterior body portion, showing the ciliary pattern. Ciliary rows end slightly ahead of the posterior body pole, leaving a small blank field (asterisks). <italic>MA</italic> macronucleus, <italic>SK</italic> somatic kineties. Scale bars: 10&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m (<bold>D</bold>, <bold>G</bold>), 30&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m (<bold>E</bold>, <bold>F</bold>, <bold>H</bold>), 100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m (<bold>A</bold>, <bold>C</bold>), 200&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m (<bold>B</bold>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="42995_2024_275_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig><sec id="Sec12"><title>Synonymy</title><p id="Par25">Heidenreich (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">1935</xref>) and de Puytorac (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">1957</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">1960</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">1972</xref>) reviewed the extensive synonymy history of <italic>H. secans</italic>. We assessed their synonymy lists and surveyed the old literature. The following records could be assigned to <italic>H. secans</italic>:<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>1859</label><p id="Par26"><italic>Opalina secans</italic> Stein, Abhandlungen der K&#x000f6;niglichen b&#x000f6;hmischen Gesellschaft der Wissenschaften, 5. Folge, Band 10, years 1857&#x02012;1859: 36 (brief description without figure, type hosts: <italic>Saenuris variegata</italic> and <italic>Enchytraeus vermicularis</italic>)</p></list-item><list-item><label>1860</label><p id="Par27"><italic>Opalina secans</italic> St. &#x02012; Stein, Sitzungsberichte der K&#x000f6;niglichen b&#x000f6;hmischen Gesellschaft der Wissenschaften in Prag year 1860: 56 (listing the species, without figure)</p></list-item><list-item><label>1861</label><p id="Par28"><italic>Hoplitophrya secans</italic> &#x02012; Stein, Sitzungsberichte der K&#x000f6;niglichen b&#x000f6;hmischen Gesellschaft der Wissenschaften in Prag year 1861: 88 (combining author, correction of type host name from <italic>Saenuris variegata</italic> to <italic>Lumbriculus variegatus</italic>)</p></list-item><list-item><label>1862</label><p id="Par29"><italic>Opalina lumbriculi</italic> mihi &#x02012; Buchholz, Schriften der K&#x000f6;niglichen physikalisch-&#x000f6;konomischen Gesellschaft zu K&#x000f6;nigsberg year 1863: 130 (size 580&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;21&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m; host: not provided, very likely <italic>Lumbriculus</italic> as suggested by the species epithet)</p></list-item><list-item><label>1881</label><p id="Par30"><italic>Hoplitophrya secans</italic> Stein &#x02012; Kent, Manual of Infusoria II: 572 (brief description without figure; hosts: <italic>Lumbriculus variegatus</italic> and <italic>Enchytraeus vermicularis</italic>)</p></list-item><list-item><label>1926</label><p id="Par31"><italic>Hoplitophrya lumbriculi</italic> Kijenskij, V&#x0011b;stn&#x000ed;k Kr&#x000e1;lovsk&#x000e9; &#x0010d;esk&#x000e9; spole&#x0010d;nosti nauk, T&#x00159;&#x000ed;da matematicko-p&#x00159;&#x000ed;rodov&#x0011b;deck&#x000e1; year 1925 (I): 8, Obr. 4, 6, Tab. I obr. 2 (size 225&#x02012;240&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;20&#x02012;30&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m, spicule 45&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m long, 10&#x02012;13 contractile vacuoles; host: <italic>Lumbriculus variegatus</italic>)</p></list-item><list-item><label>1929</label><p id="Par32"><italic>Protoradiophrya armata</italic> Rossolimo and Perzewa, Archiv f&#x000fc;r Protistenkunde 67: 247, Figs. 11&#x02012;17 (size 285&#x02012;665&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;24&#x02012;32&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m, spicule 40&#x02012;45&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m long, 25&#x02012;30 contractile vacuoles; host: <italic>Lumbriculus variegatus</italic>)</p></list-item><list-item><label>1935</label><p id="Par33"><italic>Hoplitophrya secans</italic> Stein &#x02012; Heidenreich, Archiv f&#x000fc;r Protistenkunde 84: 326, Fig. 1 (taxonomic revision, illustration showing the skeletal apparatus)</p></list-item><list-item><label>1954</label><p id="Par34"><italic>Hoplitophrya secans</italic> Stein, 1861 &#x02012; Meier, Archiv f&#x000fc;r Protistenkunde 100: 217 (notes on a German population, 280&#x02012;900&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;18&#x02012;45&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m in size, without figure, observed together with <italic>M. clavata</italic>; host: <italic>Lumbriculus variegatus</italic>)</p></list-item><list-item><label>1957</label><p id="Par35"><italic>Hoplitophrya secans</italic> (Stein 1859) &#x02012; de Puytorac, Archives de zoologie exp&#x000e9;rimentale et g&#x000e9;n&#x000e9;rale 94: 104 (brief synonymy list)</p></list-item><list-item><label>1960</label><p id="Par36"><italic>Hoplitophrya secans</italic> &#x02012; de Puytorac, Journal of Protozoology 7: 279, Fig. 2 (microphotograph of the anterior body region showing the fibrillar spicule)</p></list-item><list-item><label>1972</label><p id="Par37"><italic>Hoplitophrya secans</italic> (Stein 1859) Stein, 1861 &#x02012; de Puytorac, Protistologica 8: 10, Fig. 1, 2, Tab. 2 Fig.&#x000a0;14 (taxonomic revision, microphotograph and illustration of the ciliary pattern in the anterior body region, 240&#x02012;500&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;20&#x02012;60&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m in size, spicule 60&#x02012;70&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m long, 44 ciliary rows, 15&#x02012;30 contractile vacuoles; host: <italic>Lumbriculus variegatus</italic>)</p></list-item></list></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Misidentifications</title><p id="Par38">Although Heidenreich (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">1935</xref>) and de Puytorac (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">1972</xref>) assigned the following records from Lankester (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">1870</xref>), Warpachowsky (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">1886</xref>), B&#x000fc;tschli (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">1889</xref>), Schewiakoff (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">1896</xref>), and C&#x000e9;p&#x000e8;de (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">1910</xref>) to <italic>H. secans</italic>, their conspecificity could be excluded due to morphological differences and/or very different host organisms. Therefore, the following records should not be attributed to <italic>H. secans</italic>:<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>1870</label><p id="Par39"><italic>Opalina naidos</italic> Dujardin &#x02012; Lankester, Quarterly Journal of Microscopical Science 10: 143, Pl. IX (differs from <italic>H. secans</italic> by contractile vacuoles arranged in a row, the thick macronucleus extending along most of the cell length, and by the lack of fibrillar spicule; hosts: <italic>Nais serpentina</italic> and <italic>Lumbriculus</italic> sp.; C&#x000e9;p&#x000e8;de (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">1910</xref>) suggested transfer of <italic>O. naidos</italic> to <italic>Anoplophrya</italic>)</p></list-item><list-item><label>1886</label><p id="Par40"><italic>Opalina spiculata</italic> Warpachowsky, Bulletin de l&#x02019;Acad&#x000e9;mie imp&#x000e9;riale des sciences de Saint-P&#x000e9;tersbourg 30: 513 (differs from <italic>H. secans</italic> by the long fibrillar spicule occupying&#x02009;~&#x02009;66% of the body length; host: not mentioned)</p></list-item><list-item><label>1889</label><p id="Par41"><italic>Hoplitophrya</italic> (?) <italic>secans</italic> St. &#x02012; B&#x000fc;tschli, Bronn&#x02019;s Klassen und Ordnungen des Thierreichs: 1717, Taf. 65, Fig.&#x000a0;4a&#x02012;b (likely a misidentification because fission anisotomic with catenulation, i.e., with chain formation; host: <italic>Nais</italic>)</p></list-item><list-item><label>1896</label><p id="Par42"><italic>Hoplitophrya secans</italic> Stein &#x02012; Schewiakoff, M&#x000e9;moires de l&#x02019;Acad&#x000e9;mie imp&#x000e9;riale des sciences de Saint-P&#x000e9;tersbourg 4: 385, Tab. 6 Fig.&#x000a0;147 (Schewiakoff <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">1896</xref> considered his species to be conspecific with <italic>Opalina spiculata</italic> sensu Warpachowsky <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">1886</xref>; hosts: <italic>Lumbricus terrestris</italic>, <italic>Lumbricus variegatus</italic>, and <italic>Enchytraeus vermicularis</italic>)</p></list-item><list-item><label>1910</label><p id="Par43"><italic>Mesnillella secans</italic> Stein &#x02012; C&#x000e9;p&#x000e8;de, Archives de zoologie exp&#x000e9;rimentale et g&#x000e9;n&#x000e9;rale 5: 550, Fig. XXXII (likely a misidentification because fibrillar spicule extends behind the mid-body; hosts: <italic>Lumbricus terrestris</italic> and <italic>Lumbricus variegatus</italic>)</p></list-item></list></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Neotypification</title><p id="Par44">We neotypify <italic>H. secans</italic> with a Slovak population from the Jursk&#x000e9; jazierko pond for the following objections: (1) the original description is incomplete, lacks figures, and the type locality is not known (see Art. 75.3.1 of the ICZN <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">1999</xref>); (2) there are several similar species that might be confused with the species to be neotypified (see above), and characters differentiating <italic>H. secans</italic> from congeners are provided in &#x02018;Improved diagnosis&#x02019; below (see Art. 75.3.2); (3) the neotype is properly labeled to ensure its recognition (see Art. 75.3.3); (4) no type material is available from the species described by Stein (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">1859</xref>) (see Art. 75.3.4); (5) the neotype matches the species considered to be <italic>H. secans</italic> in the authoritative revision of de Puytorac (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">1972</xref>) (see Art. 75.3.5); (6) the neotype is from the same biogeographic region (Palearctic) and type host (<italic>L. variegatus</italic>) (see Art. 75.3.6 and Foissner <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2002</xref>); and (7) genomic DNA, as well as genetic data from the nuclear rDNA operon and two mitochondrial genes are available for the neotype and have been deposited in a recognized scientific institution (see Art. 75.3.7 and &#x02018;Type material&#x02019; below) and in the GenBank database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nucleotide/">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nucleotide/</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Improved diagnosis (based on neotype population)</title><p id="Par45">Body size 200&#x02012;350&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;100&#x02012;130&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m in vivo. Shape broadly to narrowly elliptical to ovate. Fibrillar spicule extends along midline in anterior body fifth, composed of two unevenly long arms: ventral arm 41&#x02012;58&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m long, dorsal arm inconspicuous, hook-like, and only 6.0&#x02012;7.5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m long; left side of ventral spicule arm associated with approximately 10 fibers running underneath ciliary rows. Macronucleus rod-like to filiform and tortuous, micronucleus globular and situated in posterior body half close to macronucleus. About 22 contractile vacuoles form an irregular and wide stripe along macronucleus. About 20&#x02012;25 meridional ciliary rows both on ventral and dorsal body sides, ventral rows gradually commence right and left of long spicule arm while dorsal rows start at anterior body pole, all ciliary rows terminate slightly ahead of posterior body pole leaving a small blank field.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Type locality</title><p id="Par46">Not provided in the original description. The neotype is from the Jursk&#x000e9; jazierko pond situated in an urban oak-hornbeam forest, district of the village of Sv&#x000e4;t&#x000fd; Jur, Mal&#x000e9; Karpaty Mts., Slovakia, 48&#x000b0;15&#x02032;28.0&#x02033;N 17&#x000b0;09&#x02032;14.6&#x02033;E. According to Article 76.3 of the ICZN (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">1999</xref>), the place of origin of the neotype becomes the type locality.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Type host</title><p id="Par47">Stein (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">1859</xref>) mentioned that <italic>H. secans</italic> was found in the intestine of <italic>Saenuris variegata</italic> and <italic>Enchytraeus vermicularis</italic>. Later, Stein (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">1861</xref>) corrected the name of the type host from <italic>Saenuris variegata</italic> (Hoffmeister, 1843) to <italic>Lumbriculus variegatus</italic>. ND1 and COI sequences of the <italic>L. variegatus</italic> individual (JJ 58) carrying the neotype specimen of <italic>H. secans</italic> have been deposited in GenBank under the following accession numbers: PQ247164 and PQ243270, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Type material</title><p id="Par48">No material is available from the type population. A DNA sample of the neotype specimen (JJ 226 LV) has been deposited in the Natural History Museum, Vajansk&#x000e9;ho n&#x000e1;bre&#x0017e;ie 2, 810 06 Bratislava, Slovakia (ID Collection Code 01427561). The 18S rRNA gene, ITS1-5.8S-ITS2-28S rRNA gene, 16S rRNA gene, and cytochrome <italic>c</italic> oxidase subunit I sequences of the neotype specimen have been deposited in GenBank under the following accession nos. PQ238882, PQ240648, PQ249009, and PQ247145, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Etymology</title><p id="Par49">The species epithet <italic>sec&#x00101;ns</italic> [m, f, n] (cutting, cleaving, dividing) is a participle in the nominative singular of the Latin verb <italic>sec&#x0014d;</italic> (cut, cleave) (Article 11.9.1.1 of the ICZN <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">1999</xref>). The species-group name very likely refers to the asymmetric (anisotomic) cell division, causing the opisthe to be much smaller than the proter.</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Description of neotype population</title><p id="Par50">Body size&#x02009;~&#x02009;200&#x02012;350&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;100&#x02012;130&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m in vivo and 216&#x02012;450&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;110&#x02012;160&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m after protargol impregnation, length:width ratio 2.0&#x02012;2.8:1 both in vivo and in protargol preparations; dorso-ventrally flattened, not contractile. Body outline broadly to narrowly elliptical to ovate, often with anterolateral shoulders providing an angular appearance to living cells; cell apex appears spiny in vivo at low magnifications due to fibrillar spicule extending from ventral side onto dorsal one; anterior end usually slightly more narrowly rounded than posterior end; posterior end narrowly to broadly rounded, sometimes bluntly truncated (Figs. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>A, B, E&#x02013;L, 5A&#x02012;D, 6A&#x02012;C, E, F, H).</p><p id="Par51">Fibrillar spicule extends along midline of cell in anterior body fifth, composed of two unevenly long arms: ventral arm distinctly longer, i.e., about 41&#x02012;58&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m long, while dorsal arm inconspicuous, hook-like, and only 6.0&#x02012;7.5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m long; left side of ventral spicule arm associated with&#x02009;~&#x02009;10 fibers running underneath ciliary rows and well recognizable with differential interference contrast optics (Figs. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>A&#x02012;C, E&#x02012;L, 5B).</p><p id="Par52">Nuclear apparatus begins close to anterior body end or slightly posterior to rear end of ventral spicule arm, extends almost to posterior body end both in vivo and in protargol preparations. Macronucleus rod-like to filiform and tortuous,&#x02009;~&#x02009;210&#x02012;300&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m long in vivo when uncoiled, 10&#x02012;15&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m wide in vivo while 8&#x02012;11&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m after protargol impregnation; nucleoli small and globular to ellipsoidal, evenly distributed over macronucleus. Micronucleus 6&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m in diameter after protargol impregnation, close but not attached to macronucleus, situated in posterior body half, not recognized in vivo and only rarely observed in protargol preparations (Figs. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>A, B, E&#x02013;L, <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>C, <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>A&#x02012;C). As many as 22 contractile vacuoles forming an irregular and comparatively wide stripe along macronucleus; excretory pores observed neither in vivo nor after protargol impregnation (Figs. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>A, B, G, I, <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>C). Cortex flexible; not, or only slightly, furrowed by ciliary rows; no specific granules recognizable in vivo. Cytoplasm colorless, hyaline, contains lipid droplets and rod-like prokaryotes about 3.5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m long in vivo, prokaryotic endosymbionts weakly impregnate with the protargol method used (Figs. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>D, <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>A&#x02012;E).</p><p id="Par53">Somatic ciliature holotrichous and composed of monokinetids. Somatic cilia about 11&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m long in vivo, very narrowly spaced and arranged in 20&#x02012;25 meridional rows both on ventral and dorsal body sides. Individual ciliary rows widely spaced, i.e., interkinetal distance&#x02009;~&#x02009;4.2&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m after protargol impregnation. Ventral ciliary rows gradually commence right and left of long spicule arm, while dorsal ciliary rows start at anterior body pole (Figs. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>B, <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>A, C, E, <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>D&#x02013;G). All ciliary rows terminate slightly ahead of posterior body pole, leaving an inconspicuous blank field recognizable both in vivo and after protargol impregnation (Figs. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>D, <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>H, asterisk).</p><p id="Par54">Genus <italic>Mesnilella</italic> C&#x000e9;p&#x000e8;de, 1910 (type species: <italic>Leucophrys clavata</italic> Leidy, 1855)</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title><italic>Mesnilella clavata</italic> (Leidy, 1855) C&#x000e9;p&#x000e8;de, 1910 (Figs. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>-<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>)</title><fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;7</label><caption><p><italic>Mesnilella clavata</italic> in vivo (<bold>A</bold>&#x02012;<bold>D</bold>, <bold>G</bold>&#x02012;<bold>M</bold>), after protargol (<bold>E</bold>) and silver nitrate (<bold>F</bold>) impregnation, neotype population. <bold>A</bold> Ventral view of a representative specimen, showing the general body organization. <bold>B</bold> Semi-schematic diagram, showing the ciliary pattern, the nuclear and contractile vacuole apparatus (arrows), as well as the skeletal system. <bold>C</bold>, <bold>D</bold> Details of the skeletal apparatus. <bold>E</bold> Detail of the posterior body portion, showing the ciliary pattern. <bold>F</bold> Silverline system. <bold>G</bold>&#x02012;<bold>M</bold> Variability of body shape and size as well as of the nuclear and contractile vacuole apparatus. <italic>a&#x02012;c</italic> fibers <italic>a&#x02012;c</italic>, <italic>MA</italic> macronucleus, <italic>MI</italic> micronucleus, <italic>SK</italic> somatic kineties. Scale bars: 10&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m (<bold>F</bold>), 20&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m (<bold>D</bold>, <bold>E</bold>), 40&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m (<bold>M</bold>), 50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m (<bold>A</bold>, <bold>B</bold>, <bold>G</bold>&#x02012;<bold>L</bold>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="42995_2024_275_Fig7_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig><fig id="Fig8"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;8</label><caption><p><italic>Mesnilella clavata</italic> in vivo, neotype population (<bold>A</bold>&#x02012;<bold>G</bold>). <bold>A</bold>&#x02012;<bold>C</bold> Variability of body shape and size as well as of the nuclear apparatus. Arrows in (<bold>C</bold>) denote contractile vacuoles. <bold>D</bold>, <bold>E</bold> Details of the skeletal apparatus. <bold>F</bold> Detail showing the micronucleus, lipid droplets, and innumerable granules scattered throughout the cytoplasm. <bold>G</bold> Detail showing the posterior portion of fiber <italic>a</italic>. <italic>a&#x02012;c</italic> fibers <italic>a&#x02012;c</italic>, <italic>LD</italic> lipid droplets, <italic>MA</italic> macronucleus, <italic>MI</italic> micronucleus, <italic>SK</italic> somatic kineties. Scale bars: 5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m (<bold>F</bold>), 10&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m (<bold>D</bold>, <bold>E</bold>, <bold>G</bold>), 40&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m (<bold>A</bold>&#x02012;<bold>C</bold>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="42995_2024_275_Fig8_HTML" id="MO8"/></fig><fig id="Fig9"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;9</label><caption><p><italic>Mesnilella clavata</italic> after silver nitrate (<bold>A</bold>, <bold>D</bold>) and protargol (<bold>B</bold>, <bold>C</bold>, <bold>E</bold>) impregnation, neotype population. <bold>A</bold> Silverline system of the right body side. <bold>B</bold>, <bold>C</bold> Right (B) and left (C) view of representative specimens, showing the ciliary pattern and nuclear apparatus. <bold>D</bold> Detail of the silverline system. Arrowheads mark short silverlines connecting every fourth to fifteenth basal body of adjacent somatic kineties. <bold>E</bold> Detail of the anterior portion of the macronucleus. Note that the macronucleus narrows and fades in its anterior portion. <italic>a</italic> fiber <italic>a</italic>, <italic>MA</italic> macronucleus, <italic>MI</italic> micronucleus, <italic>SK</italic> somatic kineties. Scale bars: 10&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m (<bold>D</bold>), 20&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m (<bold>E</bold>), 40&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m (<bold>A</bold>&#x02012;<bold>C</bold>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="42995_2024_275_Fig9_HTML" id="MO9"/></fig><sec id="Sec22"><title>Synonymy</title><p id="Par55">Heidenreich (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">1935</xref>) and de Puytorac (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">1957</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">1972</xref>) assembled the synonymy history of <italic>M. clavata</italic>. We critically reviewed and updated their synonymy lists:<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>1855</label><p id="Par56"><italic>Leucophrys clavata</italic> Leidy, Journal of the Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia 3: 144 (without description and figure, type locality: Rhode Island and New Jersey; host: <italic>Lumbriculus tenuis</italic>)</p></list-item><list-item><label>1861</label><p id="Par57"><italic>Hoplitophrya securiformis</italic> Stein, Sitzungsberichte der K&#x000f6;niglichen b&#x000f6;hmischen Gesellschaft der Wissenschaften in Prag: 89 (brief description without figure; host: <italic>Lumbriculus variegatus</italic>)</p></list-item><list-item><label>1881</label><p id="Par58"><italic>Anoplophrya clavata</italic> Leidy &#x02012; Kent, Manual of Infusoria II: 566, Pl. XXVI Fig.&#x000a0;21 (brief description with figure; host: <italic>Lumbriculus limosus</italic> (Leidy, 1850) [=&#x02009;<italic>Lumbriculus variegatus</italic> (M&#x000fc;ller, 1774)])</p></list-item><list-item><label>1881</label><p id="Par59"><italic>Hoplitophrya securiformis</italic> Stein &#x02012; Kent, Manual of Infusoria II: 573 (brief description without figure; host: <italic>Lumbriculus variegatus</italic>)</p></list-item><list-item><label>1889</label><p id="Par60"><italic>Hoplitophrya clavata</italic> Leidy &#x02012; B&#x000fc;tschli, Bronn&#x02019;s Klassen und Ordnungen des Thierreichs: 1717, Taf. 65, Fig.&#x000a0;4c (listed, with figure; host: not mentioned)</p></list-item><list-item><label>1896</label><p id="Par61"><italic>Hoplitophrya clavata</italic> Leidy sp. &#x02012; Schewiakoff, M&#x000e9;moires de l&#x02019;Acad&#x000e9;mie imp&#x000e9;riale des sciences de Saint-P&#x000e9;tersbourg 4: 386 (description without figure; host: <italic>Lumbriculus variegatus</italic>)</p></list-item><list-item><label>1910</label><p id="Par62"><italic>Anoplophrya</italic> (?) <italic>clavata</italic> Leidy &#x02012; C&#x000e9;p&#x000e8;de, Archives de zoologie exp&#x000e9;rimentale et g&#x000e9;n&#x000e9;rale 5: 536, Fig. XXIV (brief description with figure; host: <italic>Lumbriculus limosus</italic> (Leidy, 1850) [=&#x02009;<italic>Lumbriculus variegatus</italic> (M&#x000fc;ller, 1774)])</p></list-item><list-item><label>1910</label><p id="Par63"><italic>Mesnilella clavata</italic> Leidy &#x02012; C&#x000e9;p&#x000e8;de, Archives de zoologie exp&#x000e9;rimentale et g&#x000e9;n&#x000e9;rale 5: 551, Fig. XXXIII (combining author, brief description with figure; host: <italic>Lumbriculus variegatus</italic>)</p></list-item><list-item><label>1912</label><p id="Par64"><italic>Hoplitophrya clavata</italic> (Leidy sp. B&#x000fc;tschli) &#x02012; Schuster, Spis&#x0016f; poct&#x0011b;n&#x000fd;ch jubilejn&#x000ed; cenou Kr&#x000e1;lovsk&#x000e9; &#x0010d;esk&#x000e9; spole&#x0010d;nosti n&#x000e1;uk v Praze 21: 19 (listed, without figure; host: <italic>Lumbriculus variegatus</italic>)</p></list-item><list-item><label>1922</label><p id="Par65"><italic>Mesnilella clavata</italic> (Leidy) C&#x000e9;p&#x000e8;de (1910) &#x02012; Penard, &#x000c9;tudes Infusoires: 11 (detailed description with figure, description of cysts; host: <italic>Lumbriculus</italic>)</p></list-item><list-item><label>1924</label><p id="Par66"><italic>Mesnilella clavata</italic> (Leidy) &#x02012; Mackinnon and Adam, Quarterly Journal of Microscopical Science 68: 224 (detailed description with figure; host: <italic>Lumbriculus variegatus</italic>)</p></list-item><list-item><label>1926</label><p id="Par67"><italic>Mesnilella clavata</italic> (Leidy) &#x02012; Kijenskij, V&#x0011b;stn&#x000ed;k Kr&#x000e1;lovsk&#x000e9; &#x0010d;esk&#x000e9; spole&#x0010d;nosti nauk, T&#x00159;&#x000ed;da mathematicko-p&#x00159;&#x000ed;rodov&#x0011b;deck&#x000e1; year 1925 (I): 2, Obr. 1, Tab. 1 obr. 1 (detailed description with figures; host: <italic>Lumbriculus variegatus</italic>)</p></list-item><list-item><label>1930</label><p id="Par68"><italic>Anoplophrya clavata</italic> Leidy &#x02012; Cheissin, Archiv f&#x000fc;r Protistenkunde 70: 608 (only listed, without figure)</p></list-item><list-item><label>1930</label><p id="Par69"><italic>Mesnililla clavata</italic> Leidy &#x02012; Cheissin, Archiv f&#x000fc;r Protistenkunde 70: 610 (only listed, without figure, incorrect subsequent spelling of the genus name and therefore unavailable according to Articles 33.3 and 33.5 of the ICZN <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">1999</xref>)</p></list-item><list-item><label>1935</label><p id="Par70"><italic>Mesnilella clavata</italic> Leidy &#x02012; Heidenreich, Archiv f&#x000fc;r Protistenkunde 84: 341 (revision, description without figure)</p></list-item><list-item><label>1954</label><p id="Par71"><italic>Mesnilella clavata</italic> (Leidy 1855) &#x02012; Meier, Archiv f&#x000fc;r Protistenkunde 100: 230 (brief description of a German population, without figure, observed together with <italic>H. secans</italic>; host: <italic>Lumbriculus variegatus</italic>)</p></list-item><list-item><label>1957</label><p id="Par72"><italic>Mesnilella clavata</italic> (Leidy 1855) &#x02012; de Puytorac, Archives de zoologie exp&#x000e9;rimentale et g&#x000e9;n&#x000e9;rale 94: 104 (brief synonymy list)</p></list-item><list-item><label>1965</label><p id="Par73"><italic>Mesnilella clavata</italic> &#x02012; Kaczanowski, Acta Protozoologica 3: 227, Fig.&#x000a0;2D (only figure provided)</p></list-item><list-item><label>1972</label><p id="Par74"><italic>Mesnilella clavata</italic> (Leidy, 1855) C&#x000e9;p&#x000e8;de, 1910 &#x02012; de Puytorac, Protistologica 8: 12, Fig.&#x000a0;4, Tab. II Fig.&#x000a0;23 (revision, figure showing the anterior body portion; host: <italic>Lumbriculus variegatus</italic>)</p></list-item></list></p></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title>Neotypification</title><p id="Par75">We neotypify <italic>M. clavata</italic> with a Slovak population from the Jursk&#x000e9; jazierko pond for the following reasons: (1) the species lacks original description and figures (see Art. 75.3.1 of the ICZN <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">1999</xref>); (2) characters differentiating <italic>M. clavata</italic> from congeners are provided in &#x02018;Improved diagnosis&#x02019; below (see Art. 75.3.2); (3) the neotype is properly labeled to ensure its recognition (see Art. 75.3.3); (4) it is generally known that no type material is available from Leidy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">1855</xref>) (see Art. 75.3.4); (5) the neotype matches very well the species considered to be <italic>M. clavata</italic> in the authoritative revisions of C&#x000e9;p&#x000e8;de (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">1910</xref>), Penard (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">1922</xref>), Kijenskij (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">1926</xref>), and de Puytorac (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">1972</xref>) (see Art. 75.3.5); (6) the neotype is from the same biogeographic region (Holoarctic) and type host oligochaete (Stein <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">1861</xref> stated that &#x0201c;<italic>Lumbriculus tenuis</italic>&#x0201d; mentioned by Leidy <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">1855</xref> is, in fact, <italic>L. variegatus</italic>) (see Art. 75.3.6 and Foissner <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2002</xref>); and (7) genomic DNA, as well as genetic data from the nuclear rDNA operon and two mitochondrial genes are available for the neotype and have been deposited in a recognized scientific institution (see Art. 75.3.7 and &#x02018;Type material&#x02019; below) and in the GenBank database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nucleotide/">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nucleotide/</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec24"><title>Improved diagnosis (based on neotype population)</title><p id="Par76">Body size 125&#x02012;150&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;35&#x02012;45&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m in vivo. Shape clavate to elongate elliptical, with anterior body end slanted, posterior end narrowly rounded, and both body margins slightly sigmoidal. Skeletal apparatus composed of three intertwined and unequally long fibers: fiber <italic>a</italic>&#x02009;~&#x02009;100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m long, begins at cell apex, runs underneath anterior body margin and soon turns posteriorly to extend along midline of cell; fiber <italic>b</italic>&#x02009;~&#x02009;30&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m long, runs underneath truncated anterior body margin to terminate before reaching left body margin; fiber <italic>c</italic> only 18&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m long in vivo, runs slightly obliquely with respect to fibers <italic>a</italic> and <italic>b</italic> to terminate about in mid-portion of anterior body margin. Macronucleus filiform and tortuous, micronucleus broadly ellipsoidal to broadly fusiform and usually situated far away from macronucleus close to mid-portion of right body margin. Usually 4&#x02012;6 contractile vacuoles arranged in a single row extending along macronucleus. About 20&#x02012;23 meridional ciliary rows both on ventral and dorsal body sides.</p></sec><sec id="Sec25"><title>Type locality</title><p id="Par77">Leidy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">1855</xref>) mentioned three sites where he recorded <italic>Leucophrys clavata</italic>: Point Judith (Rhode Island), Absecom Beach (Atlantic City), and Beesley&#x02019;s Point (New Jersey). The neotype is from the Jursk&#x000e9; jazierko pond situated in an urban oak-hornbeam forest, district of the village of Sv&#x000e4;t&#x000fd; Jur, Mal&#x000e9; Karpaty Mts., Slovakia, 48&#x000b0;15&#x02032;28.0&#x02033;N 17&#x000b0;09&#x02032;14.6&#x02033;E. According to Article 76.3 of the ICZN (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">1999</xref>), the place of origin of the neotype becomes the type locality.</p></sec><sec id="Sec26"><title>Type host</title><p id="Par78">Leidy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">1855</xref>) isolated <italic>Leucophrys clavata</italic> from the visceral cavity (presumably the digestive tract) of <italic>Lumbriculus tenuis</italic>. Later, Stein (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">1861</xref>) corrected the host name to <italic>L. variegatus</italic>. ND1 and COI sequences of the <italic>L. variegatus</italic> individual (JJ 37) carrying the neotype specimen of <italic>M. clavata</italic> have been deposited in GenBank under the following accession numbers: PQ247165 and PQ243271, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="Sec27"><title>Type material</title><p id="Par79">No material is available from the type population. A DNA sample of the neotype specimen (JJ 82 LV) has been deposited in the Natural History Museum, Vajansk&#x000e9;ho n&#x000e1;bre&#x0017e;ie 2, 810 06 Bratislava, Slovakia (ID Collection Code 01427562). The 18S rRNA gene, ITS1-5.8S-ITS2-28S rRNA gene, 16S rRNA gene, and cytochrome <italic>c</italic> oxidase subunit I sequences of the neotype specimen have been deposited in GenBank under the following accession nos. PQ238887, PQ240653, PQ249014, and PQ247150, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="Sec28"><title>Etymology</title><p id="Par80">The species epithet is derived from the Latin noun <italic>cl&#x00101;v</italic>&#x000b7;<italic>a</italic>, -<italic>ae</italic> [f] (club, cudgel) and used as an adjective in the nominative singular (Article 11.9.1.1 of ICZN <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">1999</xref>). The species-group name alludes to the club-shaped (clavate) body of the species.</p></sec><sec id="Sec29"><title>Description</title><p id="Par81"><italic>Mesnilella clavata</italic> was recorded in <italic>L. variegatus</italic> collected at two locations: Jursk&#x000e9; jazierko pond, district of the village of Sv&#x000e4;t&#x000fd; Jur, Mal&#x000e9; Karpaty Mts. (48&#x000b0;15&#x02032;28.0&#x02033;N 17&#x000b0;09&#x02032;14.6&#x02033;E) and Kr&#x000e1;&#x0013e;ovsk&#x000e1; l&#x000fa;ka, riparian zone of the River Danube (47&#x000b0;52&#x02032;59.5&#x02033;N 17&#x000b0;31&#x02032;02.8&#x02033;E). The conspecificity of both populations was confirmed by three nuclear rRNA genes (18S, 5.8S, and 28S), their spacers (ITS1 and ITS2), as well as by the barcoding mitochondrial COI and 16S rRNA genes. Since both populations match very well also morphologically, the description combines all observations.</p><p id="Par82">Body size about 125&#x02012;150&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;35&#x02012;45&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m in vivo and 130&#x02012;160&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;40&#x02012;45&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m after protargol impregnation, length:width ratio 3.2&#x02012;3.6:1 both in vivo and in protargol preparations; dorso-ventrally flattened, not contractile. Shape clavate to elongate elliptical, with both body margins slightly sigmoidal. Anterior body end straight, 30&#x02012;35&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m long in vivo, and slanted by about 45&#x000b0; providing the living cells with a&#x000a0;<italic>Spathidium</italic>-like appearance. Posterior body end usually narrowly rounded, rarely broadly rounded in some protargol-impregnated cells (Figs. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>A, B, G&#x02013;M, <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>A&#x02012;C, M, <xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>A&#x02012;C).</p><p id="Par83">Skeletal apparatus composed of three intertwined and unequally long fibers originating at cell apex (i.e., at place where anterior margin meets right cell margin). Fiber <italic>a</italic> most conspicuous because robust and very long (ca. 100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m); begins at cell apex, runs underneath anterior body margin, soon turns posteriorly to extend along midline of cell; occupies about 70% of body length; faintly impregnates with the protargol method used. Fiber <italic>b</italic> about 30&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m long in vivo; runs underneath truncated anterior body margin to terminate before reaching left body margin, i.e., occupies ca. 90% of anterior margin length; not recognizable after protargol impregnation. Fiber <italic>c</italic> shortest, i.e., only 18&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m long in vivo; runs slightly obliquely with respect to fibers <italic>a</italic> and <italic>b</italic> to terminate about in mid-portion of anterior body margin; not recognizable after protargol impregnation (Figs. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>A&#x02013;D, H&#x02012;M, <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>A&#x02012;E, G, <xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>C, E).</p><p id="Par84">Nuclear apparatus begins about 12&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m apart from cell apex and terminates about 15&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m ahead of posterior body end, occupying ca. 80% of body length. Macronucleus filiform and tortuous, with anterior portion sometimes narrowing and fading in protargol preparations (very likely opisthe post-dividers), about 90&#x02012;100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m long in vivo when uncoiled, 3&#x02012;5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m wide in vivo and 3&#x02012;7&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m after protargol impregnation; nucleoli small and more or less globular to ellipsoidal, evenly distributed over macronucleus. Micronucleus broadly ellipsoidal to broadly fusiform, 3.5&#x02012;4.5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m in largest diameter after protargol impregnation, typically situated conspicuously far away from macronucleus, viz., close and slightly above mid-portion of right body margin, only rarely close but not attached to macronucleus (Figs. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>A, B, K&#x02013;M, <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>B, C, F, <xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>B, C, E). Usually 4&#x02012;6 contractile vacuoles arranged in a single row extending along either right or left side of macronucleus, individual vacuoles very conspicuous because 7&#x02012;11&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m across during diastole; excretory pores observed neither in vivo nor after protargol impregnation (Figs. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>A, B, H&#x02013;M, <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>A&#x02012;C). Cortex flexible; not, or only slightly, furrowed by ciliary rows; no specific granules recognizable in vivo. Cytoplasm colorless, hyaline, contains some lipid droplets and innumerable granules (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>A&#x02012;F).</p><p id="Par85">Somatic ciliature holotrichous and composed of monokinetids. Somatic cilia about 15&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m long in vivo, very narrowly spaced and arranged in about 20 meridional rows on ventral and 23 meridional rows on dorsal body side. Individual ciliary rows ordinarily spaced, i.e., interkinetal distance approximately 1.8&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m after protargol impregnation (Figs. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>B, E, <xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>B, C). Silverline system very loosely meshed, meshes relatively large and roughly rectangular; primary meridians connect kinetids within somatic kineties; short silverlines connect every fourth to fifteenth basal body of adjacent somatic kineties (Figs. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>F, <xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>A, D).</p><p id="Par86">Family Maupasellidae C&#x000e9;p&#x000e8;de, 1910</p><p id="Par87">Genus <italic>Buchneriella</italic> Heidenreich, 1935 (type species: <italic>Buchneriella criodrili</italic> Heidenreich, 1935)</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec30"><title><italic>Buchneriella criodrili</italic> Heidenreich, 1935 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>)</title><fig id="Fig10"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;10</label><caption><p><italic>Buchneriella criodrili</italic> in vivo, neotype population (<bold>A</bold>&#x02012;<bold>I</bold>). <bold>A</bold>, <bold>C</bold>, <bold>F</bold> General body organization of representative specimens. <bold>B</bold> Semi-schematic diagram, showing the ciliary pattern, the nuclear and contractile vacuole apparatus, as well as the skeletal system. <bold>D</bold>, <bold>H</bold> Details of the skeletal apparatus. Arrowheads denote the thorn. <bold>E</bold>, <bold>I</bold> A very late divider. Arrows mark the contractile vacuoles. <bold>G</bold> Detail of the anterior body portion, showing the macronucleus, contractile vacuole (arrow), and fibers of the skeletal apparatus. The thorn (arrowhead) is curved backward forming a right angle with the ventral side.<italic> FI</italic> fibers, <italic>MA</italic> macronucleus, <italic>SK</italic> somatic kineties. Scale bars: 20&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m (<bold>G</bold>, <bold>H</bold>), 40&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m (<bold>A</bold>&#x02012;<bold>C</bold>, <bold>F</bold>), 100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m (<bold>E</bold>, <bold>I</bold>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="42995_2024_275_Fig10_HTML" id="MO10"/></fig><p id="Par88">
<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>1935</label><p id="Par89"><italic>Buchneriella criodrili</italic> Heidenreich, 1935, Archiv f&#x000fc;r Protistenkunde 84: 349, Taf. 6 Fig.&#x000a0;11, Taf. 7 Figs. 13&#x02012;17 (detailed description with figures; type host: <italic>Criodrilus lacuum</italic>)</p></list-item><list-item><label>1952</label><p id="Par90"><italic>Buchneriella criodrili</italic> Heidenreich &#x02012; de Puytorac, Bulletin de la Soci&#x000e9;t&#x000e9; zoologique de France 76: 332 (listed)</p></list-item><list-item><label>1957</label><p id="Par91"><italic>Buchneriella criodrili</italic> Heidenreich 1935 &#x02012; de Puytorac, Archives de zoologie exp&#x000e9;rimentale et g&#x000e9;n&#x000e9;rale 94: 106 (listed)</p></list-item><list-item><label>1960</label><p id="Par92"><italic>Buchneriella criodrili</italic> Heidenreich, 1935 &#x02012; de Puytorac, Journal of Protozoology 7: 279, Figs. 3, 5&#x02012;9, 11&#x02012;14 (description of a population from Lake Ohrid, with figures showing the detail of the skeletal apparatus and silverline system; hosts: <italic>Criodrilus lacuum</italic> and <italic>C. ohridanum</italic>)</p></list-item><list-item><label>1972</label><p id="Par93"><italic>Buchneriella criodrili</italic> Heidenreich, 1935 &#x02012; de Puytorac, Protistologica 8: 32, Fig.&#x000a0;43 (taxonomic revision, microphotograph showing the silverline system, hosts: <italic>Criodrilus lacuum</italic> and <italic>C. ohridanum</italic>)</p></list-item></list></p><sec id="Sec31"><title>Neotypification</title><p id="Par94">We neotypify <italic>B. criodrili</italic> with a Slovak population from the Stupavsk&#x000fd; potok stream for the following objections: (1) the type locality is not mentioned in the original description (see Art. 75.3.1 of the ICZN <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">1999</xref>); (2) characters differentiating <italic>B. criodrili</italic> from related species are provided in &#x02018;Improved diagnosis&#x02019; below (see Art. 75.3.2); (3) the neotype is properly labeled to ensure its recognition (see Art. 75.3.3); (4) it is generally known that no type material is available from the species described by Heidenreich (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">1935</xref>) (see Art. 75.3.4); (5) the neotype matches very well the original description; (6) the neotype is from the same biogeographic region (Palearctic) and type host (<italic>C. lacuum</italic>) (see Art. 75.3.6 and Foissner <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2002</xref>); and (7) genomic DNA, as well as genetic data from the rDNA operon and two mitochondrial genes are available for the neotype and have been deposited in a recognized scientific institution (see Art. 75.3.7 and &#x02018;Type material&#x02019; below) and in the GenBank database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nucleotide/">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nucleotide/</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec32"><title>Improved diagnosis (based on neotype population)</title><p id="Par95">Body size 100&#x02012;200&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;30&#x02012;75&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m in vivo. Shape elliptical with both body ends rounded. Skeletal apparatus at cell apex and composed of a basal plate, a thorn, and 9&#x02012;16 supporting fibers. Macronucleus rod-like and&#x02009;~&#x02009;85&#x02012;180&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;8&#x02012;12&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m in size. Two or three contractile vacuoles arranged in a single row. About 30&#x02012;40 bipolar and helically extending ciliary rows.</p></sec><sec id="Sec33"><title>Type locality</title><p id="Par96">Not provided in the original description. The neotype is from the hyporeal of the Stupavsk&#x000fd; potok stream, Stupava, Slovakia, 48&#x000b0;16&#x02032;38.2&#x02033;N 17&#x000b0;02&#x02032;25.0&#x02033;E. According to Article 76.3 of the ICZN (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">1999</xref>), the place of origin of the neotype becomes the type locality.</p></sec><sec id="Sec34"><title>Type host</title><p id="Par97">Heidenreich (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">1935</xref>) described <italic>B</italic>. <italic>criodrili</italic> from the intestinal tract of <italic>Criodrilus lacuum</italic>. Later, de Puytorac (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">1960</xref>) confirmed the type host <italic>C. lacuum</italic>. ND1 and COI sequences of the <italic>C. lacuum</italic> (ST 34) specimen carrying the neotype specimen of <italic>B</italic>. <italic>criodrili</italic> have been deposited in GenBank under the following accession numbers: PQ247166 and PQ243272, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="Sec35"><title>Type material</title><p id="Par98">No material is available from the type population. A DNA sample of the neotype specimen (ST 77 CL) has been deposited in the Natural History Museum, Vajansk&#x000e9;ho n&#x000e1;bre&#x0017e;ie 2, 810 06 Bratislava, Slovakia (ID Collection Code 01427563). The 18S rRNA gene, ITS1-5.8S-ITS2-28S rRNA gene, 16S rRNA gene, and cytochrome <italic>c</italic> oxidase subunit I sequences of the neotype specimen have been deposited in GenBank under the following accession nos. PQ238896, PQ240662, PQ249023, and PQ247159, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="Sec36"><title>Etymology</title><p id="Par99">The species epithet is a singular genitive case of the Latin noun <italic>Criodril</italic>&#x000b7;<italic>us</italic>, -<italic>i</italic> [m], meaning a <italic>Buchneriella</italic> from <italic>Criodrilus</italic>. The species-group name is to be treated as an adjective used as a substantive in the genitive case, because of its derivation from the host&#x02019;s generic name (Article 11.9.1.4. of the ICZN <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">1999</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec37"><title>Description of neotype population</title><p id="Par100">Body size about 100&#x02012;200&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;30&#x02012;75&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m in vivo, length:width ratio 2.6&#x02012;3.3:1; slightly dorso-ventrally flattened, not contractile. Body outline elliptical to narrowly elliptical, both body ends narrowly to broadly rounded (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>A&#x02012;C, F). Cell apex bears skeletal apparatus composed of a basal plate, a thorn, and 9&#x02012;16 supporting fibers. Basal plate about 3&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m wide in vivo, very broadly V-shaped, i.e., plate arms form an obtuse angle of 210&#x000b0;. Thorn inconspicuous because only&#x02009;~&#x02009;4.5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m long in vivo, fixed or mobile, directed forward or curved backward forming an acute or a right angle with ventral side. Supporting fibers radiate into cytoplasm from posterior side of basal plate in a fan-like pattern, about 4&#x02012;5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m long in vivo (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>A&#x02012;D, G, H).</p><p id="Par101">Macronucleus rod-like, about 85&#x02012;180&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;8&#x02012;12&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m in size in vivo, extends along main cell&#x02019;s axis, begins about 11&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m apart from anterior body pole and terminates about 4&#x02012;12&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m ahead of posterior body pole, occupying ca. 90% of body length (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>A&#x02012;C, F, G). Micronucleus not observed. Two or three contractile vacuoles arranged in a single row: anterior vacuole at beginning of second body third, posterior vacuole at end of second body third, individual vacuoles about 5&#x02012;6&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m across during diastole; excretory pores not observed (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>A, B, G). Cortex flexible; not, or only slightly, furrowed by ciliary rows; no specific granules recognizable in vivo. Cytoplasm colorless, hyaline, contains innumerable granules; prokaryotic endosymbionts not observed (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>F&#x02012;H).</p><p id="Par102">Somatic ciliature holotrichous and composed of monokinetids. Somatic cilia&#x02009;~&#x02009;5&#x02012;7&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m long in vivo, very narrowly spaced and arranged in about 30&#x02012;40 rows. Ciliary rows helical and bipolar, i.e., commence at level of skeletal basal plate and terminate slightly ahead of posterior body pole, leaving a small blank field. Individual ciliary rows ordinarily spaced, i.e., interkinetal distance approximately 2&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>A, B, F).</p><p id="Par103">Only one very late divider was observed. The division occurred in freely motile (non-encysted) conditions. Binary fission was homothetogenic (i.e., the axes of the proter and the opisthe had the same orientation) and anisotomic without catenulation (i.e., asymmetric and without chain formation). Thus, the posterior daughter cell (opisthe) was distinctly smaller than the anterior daughter cell (proter) (94&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;45&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m vs. 165&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;36&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>E, I).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec38"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="Sec39"><title>Eco-evolutionary associations of astome ciliates with their annelid hosts</title><p id="Par104">Members of the subclass Astomatia inhabit the digestive tract of planarians, mollusks, annelids (including polychaetes, oligochaetes, and leeches), and poikilotherm vertebrates (newts and frogs) (Lynn <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">2008</xref>). Molecular analyses have, however, revealed that mouthless ciliates classified in the Astomatia (Lynn <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">2008</xref>) do not form a monophyletic group, questioning the broad host spectrum. Mouthless ciliates inhabiting annelids form a monophylum that is separated from mouthless ciliates isolated from planarians or mollusks (Obert and V&#x0010f;a&#x0010d;n&#x000fd; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">2019</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">2020b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2021</xref>; Obert et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2021</xref>; Park and Leander <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">2024</xref>). The planarian-dwelling mouthless <italic>Haptophrya</italic> clusters within the subclass Scuticociliatia along with the free-living <italic>Dexiotricha</italic> and the symbiotic <italic>Conchophthirus</italic> (Antipa et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2020</xref>; Li et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">2024</xref>; Rataj and V&#x0010f;a&#x0010d;n&#x000fd; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">2019</xref>; Rataj et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">2022</xref>; Zhang and V&#x0010f;a&#x0010d;n&#x000fd; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">2024</xref>), while the mollusk-dwelling mouthless <italic>Clausilocola</italic> belongs to the subclass Hymenostomatia (Zhang and V&#x0010f;a&#x0010d;n&#x000fd; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">2022</xref>). The astome affinity of <italic>Protoanoplophrya</italic> and <italic>Desmophrya</italic>, which were discovered in gastropods and bivalves (Raabe <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">1932</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">1933</xref>), awaits to be tested with molecular methods. Since there are no molecular data from mouthless ciliates infecting newts and frogs, their classification within the subclass Astomatia should be taken with caution (Rataj and V&#x0010f;a&#x0010d;n&#x000fd; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">2018</xref>; Rataj et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">2022</xref>).</p><p id="Par105">So far, only astomes associated with marine polychaetes and terrestrial earthworms have been studied with molecular tools (Fokam et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2011</xref>; Obert and V&#x0010f;a&#x0010d;n&#x000fd; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">2019</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">2020b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2021</xref>; Obert et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2021</xref>; Park and Leander <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">2024</xref>; Sauvadet et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">2017</xref>). Polychaetes were suggested as the ancestral hosts of all astomes and endogeic earthworms as the ancestral hosts of astomes living in terrestrial habitats. To better understand the coevolution of astomes and annelids, ciliates from freshwater oligochaetes need to be added to phylogenetic analyses. We selected one representative from an old lumbriculid lineage belonging to the Lumbriculata clade and another representative from a more recent criodrilid lineage belonging to the Crassiclitellata clade (=&#x02009;true earthworms) (Ers&#x000e9;us et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2020</xref>). By adding astomes from these two aquatic oligochaete lineages, we could test whether (1) astomes first colonized marine polychaetes, then freshwater lumbriculids, and finally aquatic and terrestrial crassiclitellates and (2) endogeic lumbricids were the first colonized terrestrial earthworms that spread astomes to epigeic and anecic earthworms.</p><p id="Par106">Our SIMMAP reconstruction analyses revealed that the last common ancestor of astomes invaded the digestive tract of marine polychaetes&#x02009;~&#x02009;428&#x02012;241&#x000a0;Ma, then freshwater lumbriculids were invaded&#x02009;~&#x02009;345&#x02012;227&#x000a0;Ma, and finally terrestrial earthworms were colonized&#x02009;~&#x02009;255&#x02012;200&#x000a0;Ma (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>A, B). These findings parallel those of annelid phylogeny. Polychaetes are a mostly marine paraphyletic assemblage that contains clitellates (i.e., oligochaetes and leeches), and the oldest stem-group polychaete fossils come from the Early Cambrian about 520&#x000a0;Ma (Conway Morris and Peel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2008</xref>). Astomes from marine polychaetes form at least two independent deep-branching lineages (represented here by the genera <italic>Durchoniella</italic> and <italic>Pennarella</italic>) that might have emerged&#x02009;~&#x02009;100&#x000a0;Ma after the presence of polychaetes in the fossil record. As concerns phylogenetic relationships among clitellate oligochaetes, Lumbriculata (Lumbriculida&#x02009;+&#x02009;Hirudinea) are sister to the Crassiclitellata&#x02009;+&#x02009;Moniligastridae&#x02009;+&#x02009;Haplotaxidae clade and, according to phylogenomic analyses, these sister groups separated&#x02009;~&#x02009;310&#x000a0;Ma (Ers&#x000e9;us et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2020</xref>). Crassiclitellata comprise at least 21 families of true (mostly terrestrial) earthworms, including Lumbricidae, Criodrilidae, Almidae, Megascolecidae, and Glossoscolecidae (Anderson et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2017</xref>; Schmelz et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">2021</xref>). Astomes isolated from lumbriculids branched off before the radiation of astomes inhabiting crassiclitellates. Lumbriculid- and crassiclitellate-dwelling astomes diverged&#x02009;~&#x02009;300&#x000a0;Ma, matching the divergence of their host groups. Astomes associated with crassiclitellates form a monophylum whose radiation (255&#x02012;200&#x000a0;Ma) corresponds to the root age (261&#x02012;200&#x000a0;Ma) of the time-calibrated phylogeny of earthworms (Dom&#x000ed;nguez et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2015</xref>). Phylogenomic analyses revealed a deep split at the base of crassiclitellates into two major clades: one (comprising, for instance, Lumbricidae and Criodrilidae) with a largely Northern Hemisphere (Laurasian) distribution and the other one (comprising, e.g., Almidae, Glossoscolecidae, and Megascolecidae) with a primarily Southern Hemisphere (Gondwanan) distribution. The north&#x02013;south split dates to&#x02009;~&#x02009;161&#x02013;185&#x000a0;Ma, supporting the role of the breakup of Pangaea during the Mesozoic in earthworm phylogeny and biogeography (Anderson et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2017</xref>). However, the north&#x02013;south split of earthworms is not recognizable in the phylogeny of astomes, as almid- and megascolecid-dwelling astomes are not closely related and are nested within the paraphyletic group of lumbricid-dwelling astomes. This indicates that lumbricids served as a source of astomes for almid and megascolecid earthworms when paleocontinents made possible the occupation of South American, African, and Asian landmasses.</p><p id="Par107">As concerns habitat evolution, annelids lived ancestrally in the sea where the majority of polychaetes still reside. On the other hand, the most recent common ancestor of clitellates colonized freshwater during the Devonian (419&#x02013;359&#x000a0;Ma), and all major extant clitellate lineages arose over the next&#x02009;~&#x02009;150 million years, with multiple lineages subsequently returning to marine habitats or invading land (Ers&#x000e9;us et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2020</xref>). The endogeic lifestyle (subsoil-dwelling and geophagy) represents the ancestral life history of true earthworms, while epigeic (surface-dwelling and feeding on decomposing litter) and anecic (topsoil-dwelling and feeding on dead organic materials mixed with ingested soil) earthworms evolved several times convergently from endogeic ancestors (Dom&#x000ed;nguez et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2015</xref>). Phylogeny of astomes copies this habitat evolution of annelids. Deep-branching astomes were found in marine polychaetes, and our SIMMAP analyses also reconstructed the sea to be the ancestral habitat of astomes (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>B). Astomes colonized freshwater via lumbriculids in which they further radiated. Finally, astomes were brought to the land by crassiclitellates that ancestrally led an endogeic lifestyle (Dom&#x000ed;nguez et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2015</xref>; Ers&#x000e9;us et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2020</xref>). Endogeic lumbricid earthworms served as a source of astomes for the aquatic criodrilids as well as for the endogeic almid and megascolecid earthworms (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>A, B). Mirroring the evolutionary history of life strategies of lumbricid earthworms, the transfer to epigeic and anecic earthworms happened multiple times independently (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>B). The host and the habitat evolution of astomes are correlated, indicating a tight bond of astomes with annelids both in space and time.</p></sec><sec id="Sec40"><title>Taxonomy and nomenclature of <italic>Hoplitophrya secans</italic></title><p id="Par108">Stein (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">1859</xref>) discovered <italic>H. secans</italic> in the digestive tract of <italic>Saenuris variegata</italic> and <italic>Enchytraeus vermicularis</italic>, and described it under the name <italic>Opalina secans</italic> without providing a figure and information about its type locality. Stein (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">1861</xref>) transferred <italic>O</italic>. <italic>secans</italic> to a newly established genus <italic>Hoplitophrya</italic>, corrected the name of its type host to <italic>Lumbriculus variegatus</italic>, and provided a brief description without a figure. Because the original description is incomplete, we based the identification of the neotype population on the authoritative re-description of de Puytorac (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">1972</xref>). Although most taxonomic features (body shape, skeletal and nuclear apparatus, contractile vacuole pattern, presence of cytoplasmic prokaryotic symbionts, and number of ciliary rows) match, the neotype population is more stumpy (200&#x02012;350&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;100&#x02012;130&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m) than the literature reports: 580&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;21&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m (Buchholz <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">1862</xref>), 225&#x02012;240&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;20&#x02012;30&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m (Kijenskij <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">1926</xref>), 285&#x02012;665&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;24&#x02012;32&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m (Rossolimo and Perzewa <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">1929</xref>), 280&#x02012;900&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;18&#x02012;45&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m (Meier <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">1954</xref>), and 240&#x02012;500&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;20&#x02012;60&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m (de Puytorac <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">1972</xref>). Molecular information from slender populations is needed to test whether <italic>H. secans</italic> has two forms, stumpy and slender. Figure&#x000a0;14 in Table&#x000a0;2 illustrated by de Puytorac (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">1972</xref>) suggests that the width differences might be attributed to the stage in the life cycle. Slender cells might be pre-dividers or derived from proters, while the stumpy cells might correspond to opisthe post-dividers. In this light, we consider all aforementioned populations to be conspecific.</p><p id="Par109">Heidenreich (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">1935</xref>) and de Puytorac (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">1972</xref>) revised <italic>H. secans</italic> and proposed many synonyms. We support, however, only three of them: <italic>Opalina lumbriculi</italic> erected by Buchholz (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">1862</xref>), <italic>Hoplitophrya lumbriculi</italic> established by Kijenskij (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">1926</xref>), and <italic>Protoradiophrya armata</italic> discovered by Rossolimo and Perzewa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">1929</xref>). On the other hand, we do not find <italic>O. naidos</italic> described by Lankester (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">1870</xref>), <italic>O. spiculata</italic> by Warpachowsky (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">1886</xref>), and <italic>H. secans</italic> sensu B&#x000fc;tschli (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">1889</xref>), Schewiakoff (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">1896</xref>), and C&#x000e9;p&#x000e8;de (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">1910</xref>) to be conspecific with <italic>H. secans</italic>. <italic>Opalina naidos</italic>, which was discovered in <italic>Nais serpentina</italic> and <italic>Lumbriculus</italic> sp. from Hampstead, England by Lankester (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">1870</xref>), differs from <italic>H. secans</italic> by the lack (vs. presence) of a fibrillar spicule. C&#x000e9;p&#x000e8;de (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">1910</xref>) suggested transferring <italic>O. naidos</italic> to <italic>Anoplophrya</italic>, which seems to be reasonable since this genus does not exhibit any fibrillar spicule. <italic>Opalina spiculata</italic>, described by Warpachowsky (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">1886</xref>), can be distinguished from <italic>H. secans</italic> by the longer fibrillar spicule (extending almost along the whole cell length vs. in the anterior body fifth). B&#x000fc;tschli (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">1889</xref>) reported <italic>H. secans</italic> from <italic>Nais</italic>. Its conspecificity with <italic>H. secans</italic> can be, however, excluded based on the anisotomic fission with catenulation, that is, chain formation, which has been never reported for the true <italic>H. secans</italic>. Schewiakoff (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">1896</xref>) found <italic>H. secans</italic> in <italic>Lumbricus terrestris</italic>, <italic>Lumbriculus variegatus</italic>, and <italic>Enchytraeus vermicularis</italic> and considered it to be conspecific with <italic>O. spiculata</italic> sensu Warpachowsky (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">1886</xref>). Such a broad host spectrum for one astome species is unlikely (Obert et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2021</xref>). Moreover, <italic>Lumbricus terrestris</italic> is phylogenetically distant from and has very different ecological demands than <italic>Lumbriculus variegatus</italic>. C&#x000e9;p&#x000e8;de&#x02019;s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">1910</xref>) species is likely also a misidentified <italic>H. secans</italic> because its fibrillar spicule extends behind the mid-body (vs. terminates in the anterior body fifth). The heterogeneous host spectrum (<italic>Lumbricus terrestris</italic> and <italic>Lumbriculus variegatus</italic>) reported for <italic>H. secans</italic> by C&#x000e9;p&#x000e8;de (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">1910</xref>) is doubtful as well. C&#x000e9;p&#x000e8;de (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">1910</xref>) transferred <italic>H</italic>. <italic>secans</italic> to the genus &#x0201c;<italic>Mesnillella</italic>,&#x0201d; which is an incorrect subsequent spelling of <italic>Mesnilella</italic> and therefore unavailable according to Articles 33.3 and 33.5 of the ICZN (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">1999</xref>). He also assigned <italic>O. spiculata</italic> to the genus <italic>Mesnilella</italic> and synonymized it with <italic>H</italic>. <italic>secans</italic>. The combination of <italic>H. secans</italic> with <italic>Mesnilella</italic> was, however, not accepted by subsequent revising authors (de Puytorac <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">1972</xref>; Heidenreich <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">1935</xref>), as both genera conspicuously differ in the architecture of their skeletal apparatuses.</p></sec><sec id="Sec41"><title>Taxonomy and nomenclature of <italic>Mesnilella clavata</italic></title><p id="Par110"><italic>Mesnilella clavata</italic> was discovered by Leidy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">1855</xref>) in <italic>Lumbriculus tenuis</italic> (species inquirenda) and established under the name <italic>Leucophrys clavata</italic> without any description or figure. Stein (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">1861</xref>) stated that <italic>L. tenuis</italic> sensu Leidy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">1855</xref>) is <italic>L. variegatus</italic>, and erected <italic>Hoplitophrya securiformis</italic> for a ciliate isolated from <italic>L. variegatus</italic>, providing a brief description but no figure. Kent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">1881</xref>) also mentioned <italic>H</italic>. <italic>securiformis</italic> from <italic>L. variegatus</italic>, again with a brief description and without a figure. B&#x000fc;tschli (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">1889</xref>) gave the first illustration of <italic>H. clavata</italic> and proposed <italic>H</italic>. <italic>securiformis</italic> to be its junior synonym. C&#x000e9;p&#x000e8;de (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">1910</xref>) accepted this synonymization and established a new genus, <italic>Mesnilella</italic>, for <italic>H. clavata</italic>. He also proposed that <italic>Anoplophrya</italic> (?) <italic>clavata</italic> isolated from <italic>Lumbriculus limosus</italic> might be conspecific with <italic>M</italic>. <italic>clavata</italic>, which was repeated by Cheissin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">1930</xref>). Schuster (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">1912</xref>), however, overlooked C&#x000e9;p&#x000e8;de&#x02019;s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">1910</xref>) work and transferred <italic>H. clavata</italic> to a new genus, <italic>Plagiophrya</italic> Schuster, 1912, which was not recognized by subsequent revisers (Cheissin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">1930</xref>; de Puytorac <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">1972</xref>; Heidenreich <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">1935</xref>; Kijenskij <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">1926</xref>; Penard <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">1922</xref>).</p><p id="Par111">All reliable reports of <italic>M. clavata</italic> come exclusively from <italic>L. variegatus</italic> (C&#x000e9;p&#x000e8;de <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">1910</xref>; de Puytorac <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">1972</xref>; Heidenreich <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">1935</xref>; Kijenskij <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">1926</xref>; Mackinnon and Adam <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">1924</xref>; Meier <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">1954</xref>; Penard <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">1922</xref>; Schewiakoff <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">1896</xref>; Schuster <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">1912</xref>). The available descriptions are consistent, matching our observations very well (B&#x000fc;tschli <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">1889</xref>; C&#x000e9;p&#x000e8;de <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">1910</xref>; de Puytorac <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">1972</xref>; Heidenreich <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">1935</xref>; Kaczanowski <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">1965</xref>; Kent <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">1881</xref>; Kijenskij <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">1926</xref>; Mackinnon and Adam <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">1924</xref>; Penard <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">1922</xref>; Schewiakoff <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">1896</xref>). Besides the typical stumpy form, Heidenreich (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">1935</xref>) mentioned huge variability in body size. Some specimens were not longer than 90&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m (very likely post-dividers), while other individuals were 150&#x02012;240&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m long. De Puytorac (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">1972</xref>) also reported a much longer and slender variety (225&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;15&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m). Whether these size differences are population-specific, depend on life stage, and/or just reflect phenotypic plasticity, needs to be addressed using detailed morphological observations and multigene data from the larger and slender forms. We did not observe the longer and slender variety either in the neotype population from the Jursk&#x000e9; jazierko pond or from Kr&#x000e1;&#x0013e;ovsk&#x000e1; l&#x000fa;ka in the riparian zone of the River Danube.</p></sec><sec id="Sec42"><title>Taxonomy and nomenclature of <italic>Buchneriella criodrili</italic></title><p id="Par112">Besides the original description by Heidenreich (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">1935</xref>), <italic>B. criodrili</italic> was mentioned only a few times in the literature (de Puytorac <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">1952</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">1957</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">1960</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">1972</xref>). We have rediscovered <italic>B. criodrili</italic> after more than a half of century, indicating that it is a rare species that may sometimes co-occur with <italic>Maupasella criodrili</italic> (de Puytorac <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">1960</xref>). All reports including the present one come consistently from <italic>C. lacuum</italic>. In addition, de Puytorac (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">1960</xref>) isolated <italic>B. criodrili</italic> also from <italic>C. ohridanum</italic>, which is suggestive of high structural and phylogenetic host specificity. Nevertheless, the conspecificity of <italic>Buchneriella</italic> populations isolated from different <italic>Criodrilus</italic> species needs to be confirmed by multi-gene data.</p><p id="Par113">The neotype population matches those studied by Heidenreich (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">1935</xref>) and de Puytorac (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">1960</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">1972</xref>) in body shape and size (100&#x02012;200&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;30&#x02012;75&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m in neotype specimens, 110&#x02012;220&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;22&#x02012;28&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m according to Heidenreich <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">1935</xref>, 140&#x02012;160&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;40&#x02012;50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m according to de Puytorac <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">1972</xref>), the skeletal and nuclear apparatus as well as in the contractile vacuole and somatic ciliary pattern. The variability in body width most likely reflects the stage in the life cycle. The much more slender cells are derived from proters, while the stumpy cells from opisthes (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>E, I).</p><p id="Par114">Our neotypification will promote stability in the use of the name <italic>B. criodrili</italic> especially when further congeners are discovered in various criodrilids in the Oriental biogeographic region. Hitherto, only one other congener, <italic>B. pheretimae</italic> de Puytorac and Rakotoarivelo, 1965, was described from the megascolecid earthworm <italic>Pheretima</italic> sp. by de Puytorac and Rakotoarivelo (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">1965</xref>). Besides the host earthworm, <italic>B. pheretimae</italic> differs from <italic>B. criodrili</italic> by a much larger body (270&#x02012;500&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;45&#x02012;50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m vs. 100&#x02012;220&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;22&#x02012;75&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m) and a higher number of ciliary rows (59&#x02012;60 vs. 36&#x02012;42).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec43"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par115">Our comparative phylogenetic network analyses suggested that: (1) astomes evolved in the sea during the Paleozoic and their ancestral hosts were polychaetes, then they were brought to freshwater where they colonized lumbriculids, and finally reached terrestrial habitats in tandem with their true earthworm hosts; (2) lumbricid earthworms likely spread astomes to criodrilid, almid, and megascolecid earthworms before the breakup of Pangaea in the Mesozoic; (3) the ancestral host of the earthworm-dwelling astome clade led an endogeic lifestyle; (4) there were multiple independent transfers of astomes from endogeic to epigeic and anecic as well as back to (semi)aquatic earthworms such as criodrilids; and (5) host and the habitat evolution of astomes are correlated, indicating a tight bond of astomes with annelids both in space and time.</p></sec><sec id="Sec44" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary information</title><p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="42995_2024_275_MOESM1_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Supplementary file1 (PDF 614 KB)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This work was financially supported by the Slovak Research and Development Agency under contract No. APVV-19-0076 and No. APVV-23-0015 and by the Grant Agency of the Ministry of Education, Science, Research and Sport of the Slovak Republic and Slovak Academy of Sciences under the Grant VEGA 1/0013/21. We are grateful to Daniel Gru&#x0013e;a for providing samples of <italic>Criodrilus lacuum</italic> from the Stupavsk&#x000fd; potok stream.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>PV conceived and guided the study. TO performed dissections, morphological and molecular analyses, and created visualizations. TZ conducted protargol and dry silver nitrate impregnation. TO, PV, and IR analyzed data. PV and TO wrote the original draft of the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final version of the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>Open access funding provided by The Ministry of Education, Science, Research and Sport of the Slovak Republic in cooperation with Centre for Scientific and Technical Information of the Slovak Republic.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>All data generated or analyzed during this study are included in this published article and supplementary material and can be found in online repositories. The names of the repositories and accession numbers can be found at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/genbank/">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/genbank/</ext-link>.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p id="Par116">The authors declare that they have no conflict of interest.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Animal and human rights statement</title><p id="Par117">We declare that all applicable international, national, and/or institutional guidelines for sampling, care, and experimental use of organisms for the study have been followed and all necessary approvals have been obtained.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Albaret</surname><given-names>J-L</given-names></name><name><surname>Njin&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Description de cinq esp&#x000e8;ces nouvelles de cili&#x000e9;s heterotriches des genres <italic>Metanyctotherus</italic> Albaret, <italic>Pronyctotherus</italic> n. gen. et <italic>Plagiotoma</italic> Dujardin, endocommensaux d&#x02019;oligoch&#x000e8;tes du Cameroun</article-title><source>Protistologica</source><year>1975</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>305</fpage><lpage>311</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Albaret J-L, Njin&#x000e9; T (1975) Description de cinq esp&#x000e8;ces nouvelles de cili&#x000e9;s heterotriches des genres <italic>Metanyctotherus</italic> Albaret, <italic>Pronyctotherus</italic> n. gen. et <italic>Plagiotoma</italic> Dujardin, endocommensaux d&#x02019;oligoch&#x000e8;tes du Cameroun. Protistologica 11:305&#x02013;311</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name><name><surname>Horn</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ers&#x000e9;us</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Halanych</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>James</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phylogenomic analyses of Crassiclitellata support major Northern and Southern Hemisphere clades and a Pangaean origin for earthworms</article-title><source>BMC Evol Biol</source><year>2017</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>e123</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12862-017-0973-4</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Anderson FE, Williams BW, Horn KM, Ers&#x000e9;us C, Halanych KM, Santos SR, James SW (2017) Phylogenomic analyses of Crassiclitellata support major Northern and Southern Hemisphere clades and a Pangaean origin for earthworms. BMC Evol Biol 17:e123</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Antipa</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Str&#x000fc;der-Kypke</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lynn</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular phylogeny, taxonomic relationships and North American distribution of <italic>Conchophthirus</italic> (Conchophthiridae, Scuticociliatia)</article-title><source>Aquat Ecosys Health Manag</source><year>2020</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>58</fpage><lpage>68</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14634988.2020.1735919</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Antipa GA, Str&#x000fc;der-Kypke MC, Lynn DH (2020) Molecular phylogeny, taxonomic relationships and North American distribution of <italic>Conchophthirus</italic> (Conchophthiridae, Scuticociliatia). Aquat Ecosys Health Manag 23:58&#x02013;68</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bollback</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SIMMAP: stochastic character mapping of discrete traits on phylogenies</article-title><source>BMC Bioinform</source><year>2006</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>e88</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-7-88</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Bollback JP (2006) SIMMAP: stochastic character mapping of discrete traits on phylogenies. BMC Bioinform 7:e88</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bouckaert</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Heled</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#x000fc;hnert</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaughan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C-H</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Suchard</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rambaut</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Drummond</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>BEAST 2: a software platform for Bayesian evolutionary analysis</article-title><source>PLoS Comput Biol</source><year>2014</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>e1003537</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003537</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24722319</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Bouckaert R, Heled J, K&#x000fc;hnert D, Vaughan T, Wu C-H, Xie D, Suchard MA, Rambaut A, Drummond AJ (2014) BEAST 2: a software platform for Bayesian evolutionary analysis. PLoS Comput Biol 10:e1003537<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24722319</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buchholz </surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Beitr&#x000e4;ge zur Anatomie der Gattung <italic>Enchytraeus</italic>, nebst Angabe der um K&#x000f6;nigsberg vorkommenden Formen derselben</article-title><source>Schr K Phys-&#x000d6;kon Ges K&#x000f6;nigsberg</source><year>1862</year><volume>1863</volume><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>132</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Buchholz R (1862) Beitr&#x000e4;ge zur Anatomie der Gattung <italic>Enchytraeus</italic>, nebst Angabe der um K&#x000f6;nigsberg vorkommenden Formen derselben. Schr K Phys-&#x000d6;kon Ges K&#x000f6;nigsberg 1863:93&#x02013;132</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>B&#x000fc;tschli</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Bronn</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Erster Band. Protozoa. III. Abtheilung: Infusoria und System der Radiolaria</article-title><source>Klassen und Ordnungen des Thier-Reichs, wissenschaftlich dargestellt in Wort und Bild. Erster Band</source><year>1889</year><publisher-loc>Heidelberg</publisher-loc><publisher-name>CF Winter&#x02019;sche Verlagshandlung</publisher-name><fpage>1585</fpage><lpage>2035</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="book">B&#x000fc;tschli O (1889) Erster Band. Protozoa. III. Abtheilung: Infusoria und System der Radiolaria. In: Bronn HG (ed) Klassen und Ordnungen des Thier-Reichs, wissenschaftlich dargestellt in Wort und Bild. Erster Band. CF Winter&#x02019;sche Verlagshandlung, Heidelberg, pp 1585&#x02013;2035</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>C&#x000e9;p&#x000e8;de</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recherches sur les infusoires astomes. Anatomie, biologie, ethologie parasitaire, syst&#x000e9;matique</article-title><source>Arch Zool Exp G&#x000e9;n</source><year>1910</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>341</fpage><lpage>609</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">C&#x000e9;p&#x000e8;de C (1910) Recherches sur les infusoires astomes. Anatomie, biologie, ethologie parasitaire, syst&#x000e9;matique. Arch Zool Exp G&#x000e9;n 5:341&#x02013;609</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheissin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Morphologische und systematische Studien &#x000fc;ber Astomata aus dem Baikalsee</article-title><source>Arch Protistenkd</source><year>1930</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>531</fpage><lpage>618</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Cheissin E (1930) Morphologische und systematische Studien &#x000fc;ber Astomata aus dem Baikalsee. Arch Protistenkd 70:531&#x02013;618</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Conway Morris</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Peel</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The earliest annelids: lower Cambrian polychaetes from the Sirius Passet Lagerst&#x000e4;tte, Peary Land, North Greenland</article-title><source>Acta Palaeontol Pol</source><year>2008</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>137</fpage><lpage>148</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4202/app.2008.0110</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Conway Morris S, Peel JS (2008) The earliest annelids: lower Cambrian polychaetes from the Sirius Passet Lagerst&#x000e4;tte, Peary Land, North Greenland. Acta Palaeontol Pol 53:137&#x02013;148</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Corliss</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Raven</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biodiversity, classification, and numbers of species of protists</article-title><source>Nature and human society. The quest for a sustainable world</source><year>2000</year><publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc><publisher-name>National Academies Press</publisher-name><fpage>130</fpage><lpage>155</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="book">Corliss JO (2000) Biodiversity, classification, and numbers of species of protists. In: Raven PH (ed) Nature and human society. The quest for a sustainable world. National Academies Press, Washington, DC, pp 130&#x02013;155</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Puytorac</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Maupasella glossoscolecis</italic> sp. nov. et <italic>Maupasella lubeti</italic> sp. nov., Cili&#x000e9;s Astomes commensaux du tube digestif de <italic>Glossoscolex grandis</italic> (Michaelsen). Remarques sur les Maupasellinae</article-title><source>Bull Soc Zool Fr</source><year>1952</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>323</fpage><lpage>333</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">de Puytorac P (1952) <italic>Maupasella glossoscolecis</italic> sp. nov. et <italic>Maupasella lubeti</italic> sp. nov., Cili&#x000e9;s Astomes commensaux du tube digestif de <italic>Glossoscolex grandis</italic> (Michaelsen). Remarques sur les Maupasellinae. Bull Soc Zool Fr 76:323&#x02013;333</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Puytorac</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Contribution &#x000e0; l&#x02019;&#x000e9;tude cytologique et taxonomique les infusoires astomes</article-title><source>Ann Sci Nat Zool Biol Anim</source><year>1954</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>270</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">de Puytorac P (1954) Contribution &#x000e0; l&#x02019;&#x000e9;tude cytologique et taxonomique les infusoires astomes. Ann Sci Nat Zool Biol Anim 11:85&#x02013;270</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Puytorac</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nouvelles donn&#x000e9;es sur les Cili&#x000e9;s Hoplitophryidae</article-title><source>Arch Zool Exp G&#x000e9;n Notes Rev</source><year>1957</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>120</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">de Puytorac P (1957) Nouvelles donn&#x000e9;es sur les Cili&#x000e9;s Hoplitophryidae. Arch Zool Exp G&#x000e9;n Notes Rev 94:89&#x02013;120</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Puytorac</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Observations sur quelques Cili&#x000e9;s astomes des Oligoch&#x000e8;tes du lac d&#x02019;Ohrid (Yougoslavie). II. Familles des Hoplitophryidae (Hoplitophryinae et Maupasellinae), des Intoshellinidae et des Anoplophryidae</article-title><source>J Protozool</source><year>1960</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>278</fpage><lpage>289</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1550-7408.1960.tb00742.x</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">de Puytorac P (1960) Observations sur quelques Cili&#x000e9;s astomes des Oligoch&#x000e8;tes du lac d&#x02019;Ohrid (Yougoslavie). II. Familles des Hoplitophryidae (Hoplitophryinae et Maupasellinae), des Intoshellinidae et des Anoplophryidae. J Protozool 7:278&#x02013;289</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Puytorac</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Les cili&#x000e9;s astomes Hoplitophryidae</article-title><source>I Description De Nouvelles Esp&#x000e8;ces Protistologica</source><year>1969</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>255</fpage><lpage>268</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">de Puytorac P (1969) Les cili&#x000e9;s astomes Hoplitophryidae. I Description De Nouvelles Esp&#x000e8;ces Protistologica 5:255&#x02013;268</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Puytorac</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Les cili&#x000e9;s astomes Hoplitophryidae. II. R&#x000e9;vision de la syst&#x000e9;matique de ce groupe</article-title><source>Protistologica</source><year>1972</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>42</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">de Puytorac P (1972) Les cili&#x000e9;s astomes Hoplitophryidae. II. R&#x000e9;vision de la syst&#x000e9;matique de ce groupe. Protistologica 8:5&#x02013;42</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Puytorac</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rakotoarivelo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sur quelques Cili&#x000e9;s Astomes des Oligoch&#x000e8;tes Megascolecidae</article-title><source>Arch Zool Exp G&#x000e9;n</source><year>1965</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>229</fpage><lpage>243</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">de Puytorac P, Rakotoarivelo J (1965) Sur quelques Cili&#x000e9;s Astomes des Oligoch&#x000e8;tes Megascolecidae. Arch Zool Exp G&#x000e9;n 105:229&#x02013;243</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dom&#x000ed;nguez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Aira</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Breinholt</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Stojanovic</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>James</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>P&#x000e9;rez-Losada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Underground evolution: new roots for the old tree of lumbricid earthworms</article-title><source>Mol Phylogenet Evol</source><year>2015</year><volume>83</volume><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ympev.2014.10.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25463017</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Dom&#x000ed;nguez J, Aira M, Breinholt JW, Stojanovic M, James SW, P&#x000e9;rez-Losada M (2015) Underground evolution: new roots for the old tree of lumbricid earthworms. Mol Phylogenet Evol 83:7&#x02013;19<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25463017</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ers&#x000e9;us</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name><name><surname>Horn</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Halanych</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>James</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>des Ch&#x000e2;telliers</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phylogenomic analyses reveal a Palaeozoic radiation and support a freshwater origin for clitellate annelids</article-title><source>Zool Scr</source><year>2020</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>614</fpage><lpage>640</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/zsc.12426</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">Ers&#x000e9;us C, Williams BW, Horn KM, Halanych KM, Santos SR, James SW, des Ch&#x000e2;telliers MC, Anderson FE (2020) Phylogenomic analyses reveal a Palaeozoic radiation and support a freshwater origin for clitellate annelids. Zool Scr 49:614&#x02013;640</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Foissner</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comments on the neotypification of protists, especially ciliates (Protozoa, Ciliophora)</article-title><source>Bull Zool Nomencl</source><year>2002</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>165</fpage><lpage>169</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Foissner W (2002) Comments on the neotypification of protists, especially ciliates (Protozoa, Ciliophora). Bull Zool Nomencl 59:165&#x02013;169</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Foissner</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An update of &#x02018;basic light and scanning electron microscopic methods for taxonomic studies of ciliated protozoa&#x02019;</article-title><source>Int J Syst Evol Microbiol</source><year>2014</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>271</fpage><lpage>292</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/ijs.0.057893-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24198058</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">Foissner W (2014) An update of &#x02018;basic light and scanning electron microscopic methods for taxonomic studies of ciliated protozoa.&#x02019; Int J Syst Evol Microbiol 64:271&#x02013;292<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24198058</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fokam</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Ngassam</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Str&#x000fc;der-Kypke</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lynn</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic diversity and phylogenetic position of the subclass Astomatia (Ciliophora) based on a sampling of six genera from West African oligochaetes (Glossoscolecidae, Megascolecidae), including description of the new genus <italic>Paraclausilocola</italic> n. gen</article-title><source>Eur J Protistol</source><year>2011</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>171</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejop.2011.02.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21398102</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Fokam Z, Ngassam P, Str&#x000fc;der-Kypke MC, Lynn DH (2011) Genetic diversity and phylogenetic position of the subclass Astomatia (Ciliophora) based on a sampling of six genera from West African oligochaetes (Glossoscolecidae, Megascolecidae), including description of the new genus <italic>Paraclausilocola</italic> n. gen. Eur J Protistol 47:161&#x02013;171<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21398102</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fokam</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Nana</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ngassam</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bricheux</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouchard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Vigues</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Sime-Ngando</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Morphological description of four new species of <italic>Nyctotherus</italic> (Ciliophora: Nyctotheridae: Heterotrichida), commensal ciliates of the digestive tract of a terrestrial Oligochaete (Megascolecidae) from the northwest region of Cameroon</article-title><source>Protistology</source><year>2014</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>62</fpage><lpage>70</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">Fokam Z, Nana PA, Ngassam P, Bricheux G, Bouchard P, Vigues B, Sime-Ngando T (2014) Morphological description of four new species of <italic>Nyctotherus</italic> (Ciliophora: Nyctotheridae: Heterotrichida), commensal ciliates of the digestive tract of a terrestrial Oligochaete (Megascolecidae) from the northwest region of Cameroon. Protistology 8:62&#x02013;70</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Fokam Z (2012) Etude morphologique et phylog&#x000e9;nie des Cili&#x000e9;s Astomes endocommensaux d&#x02019;Oligoch&#x000e8;tes terricoles de la r&#x000e9;gion de Yaound&#x000e9; et ses environs. PhD Thesis, University of Yaound&#x000e9; I</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR26" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>BioEdit: a user-friendly biological sequence alignment editor and analysis program for Windows 95/98/NT</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Symp Ser</source><year>1999</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>98</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26" publication-type="journal">Hall TA (1999) BioEdit: a user-friendly biological sequence alignment editor and analysis program for Windows 95/98/NT. Nucleic Acids Symp Ser 41:95&#x02013;98</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR27"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR27" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heidenreich</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Untersuchungen an parasitischen Ciliaten aus Anneliden. Teil I: Systematik</article-title><source>Arch Protistenkd</source><year>1935</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>315</fpage><lpage>392</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27" publication-type="journal">Heidenreich E (1935) Untersuchungen an parasitischen Ciliaten aus Anneliden. Teil I: Systematik. Arch Protistenkd 84:315&#x02013;392</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR28"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR28" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoang</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Chernomor</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>von Haeseler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Minh</surname><given-names>BQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Vihn</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>UFBoot2: improving the ultrafast bootstrap approximation</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>2018</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>518</fpage><lpage>522</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msx281</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29077904</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28" publication-type="journal">Hoang DT, Chernomor O, von Haeseler A, Minh BQ, Vihn LS (2018) UFBoot2: improving the ultrafast bootstrap approximation. Mol Biol Evol 35:518&#x02013;522<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29077904</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR29"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR29" publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>ICZN</collab></person-group><source>International Code of Zoological Nomenclature</source><year>1999</year><edition>4</edition><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>International Trust for Zoological Nomenclature</publisher-name></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29" publication-type="book">ICZN (1999) International Code of Zoological Nomenclature, 4th edn. International Trust for Zoological Nomenclature, London</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR30"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR30" publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Jeffery</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gardi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Montanarella</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Marmo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Miko</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ritz</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Peres</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>R&#x000f6;mbke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Putten</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name></person-group><source>European Atlas of Soil Biodiversity</source><year>2010</year><publisher-loc>Luxembourg</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Publications Office of the European Union</publisher-name></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30" publication-type="book">Jeffery S, Gardi C, Jones A, Montanarella L, Marmo L, Miko L, Ritz K, Peres G, R&#x000f6;mbke J, van der Putten WH (eds) (2010) European atlas of soil biodiversity. Publications Office of the European Union, Luxembourg</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR31"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR31" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>CQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Miao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Insights into the origin and evolution of Peritrichia (Oligohymenophorea, Ciliophora) based on analyses of morphology and phylogenomics</article-title><source>Mol Phylogenet Evol</source><year>2019</year><volume>132</volume><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ympev.2018.11.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30496843</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR31" publication-type="journal">Jiang CQ, Wang GY, Xiong J, Yang WT, Sun ZY, Feng JM, Warren A, Miao W (2019) Insights into the origin and evolution of Peritrichia (Oligohymenophorea, Ciliophora) based on analyses of morphology and phylogenomics. Mol Phylogenet Evol 132:25&#x02013;35<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30496843</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR32"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR32" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>CQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>XX</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Miao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dynamics and timing of diversification events of ciliated eukaryotes from a large phylogenomic perspective</article-title><source>Mol Phylogenet Evol</source><year>2024</year><volume>197</volume><fpage>e108110</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ympev.2024.108110</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32" publication-type="journal">Jiang CQ, Gu SY, Pan TT, Wang XY, Qin WW, Wang GY, Gao XX, Zhang J, Chen K, Warren A, Xiong J, Miao W (2024) Dynamics and timing of diversification events of ciliated eukaryotes from a large phylogenomic perspective. Mol Phylogenet Evol 197:e108110</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR33"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR33" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaczanowski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>About a presumable phylogenetic link between <italic>Mesnilella</italic> (Astomata) and <italic>Conchostoma longissimum</italic> Faur&#x000e9;-Fremiet (Trichostomata)</article-title><source>Acta Protozool</source><year>1965</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>232</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR33" publication-type="journal">Kaczanowski A (1965) About a presumable phylogenetic link between <italic>Mesnilella</italic> (Astomata) and <italic>Conchostoma longissimum</italic> Faur&#x000e9;-Fremiet (Trichostomata). Acta Protozool 3:225&#x02013;232</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR34"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR34" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kalyaanamoorthy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Minh</surname><given-names>BQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>TKF</given-names></name><name><surname>von Haeseler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jermiin</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ModelFinder: fast model selection for accurate phylogenetic estimates</article-title><source>Nat Methods</source><year>2017</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>587</fpage><lpage>589</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.4285</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28481363</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR34" publication-type="journal">Kalyaanamoorthy S, Minh BQ, Wong TKF, von Haeseler A, Jermiin LS (2017) ModelFinder: fast model selection for accurate phylogenetic estimates. Nat Methods 14:587&#x02013;589<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28481363</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR35"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR35" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karimi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Grover</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallagher</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Wendel</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>An&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Baum</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reticulate evolution helps explain apparent homoplasy in floral biology and pollination in baobabs (<italic>Adansonia</italic>; Bombacoideae; Malvaceae)</article-title><source>Syst Biol</source><year>2020</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>462</fpage><lpage>478</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sysbio/syz073</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31693158</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR35" publication-type="journal">Karimi N, Grover CE, Gallagher JP, Wendel JF, An&#x000e9; C, Baum DA (2020) Reticulate evolution helps explain apparent homoplasy in floral biology and pollination in baobabs (<italic>Adansonia</italic>; Bombacoideae; Malvaceae). Syst Biol 69:462&#x02013;478<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31693158</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR36"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR36" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Katoh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Rozewicki</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MAFFT online service: multiple sequence alignment, interactive sequence choice and visualization</article-title><source>Brief Bioinform</source><year>2019</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>1160</fpage><lpage>1166</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bib/bbx108</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28968734</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR36" publication-type="journal">Katoh K, Rozewicki J, Yamada KD (2019) MAFFT online service: multiple sequence alignment, interactive sequence choice and visualization. Brief Bioinform 20:1160&#x02013;1166<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28968734</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR37"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR37" publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kent</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name></person-group><source>A manual of the infusoria: including a description of all known flagellate, ciliate, and tentaculiferous protozoa British and foreign, and an account of the organization and affinities of the sponges</source><year>1881</year><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>David Bogue</publisher-name><fpage>433</fpage><lpage>720</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR37" publication-type="book">Kent WS (1881) A manual of the infusoria: including a description of all known flagellate, ciliate, and tentaculiferous protozoa British and foreign, and an account of the organization and affinities of the sponges, vol 2. David Bogue, London, pp 433&#x02013;720</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR38"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR38" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kijenskij</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>N&#x000e1;levn&#x000ed;ci za&#x0017e;&#x000ed;vac&#x000ed; roury n&#x0011b;kter&#x000fd;ch Oligochaet&#x0016f; pra&#x0017e;sk&#x000e9;ho okol&#x000ed; (Morfologie. Nepohlavn&#x000ed; mno&#x0017e;en&#x000ed;. Systematika) [Ciliates in the intestinal cavity of Oligochaeta from the surroundings of Prague]</article-title><source>V&#x0011b;stn&#x000ed;k Kr&#x000e1;lovsk&#x000e9; &#x0010c;esk&#x000e9; Spole&#x0010d;nosti Nauk, T&#x00159;&#x000ed;da Matematicko-P&#x00159;&#x000ed;rodov&#x0011b;deck&#x000e1; Year</source><year>1926</year><volume>1925</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>32</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR38" publication-type="journal">Kijenskij G (1926) N&#x000e1;levn&#x000ed;ci za&#x0017e;&#x000ed;vac&#x000ed; roury n&#x0011b;kter&#x000fd;ch Oligochaet&#x0016f; pra&#x0017e;sk&#x000e9;ho okol&#x000ed; (Morfologie. Nepohlavn&#x000ed; mno&#x0017e;en&#x000ed;. Systematika) [Ciliates in the intestinal cavity of Oligochaeta from the surroundings of Prague]. V&#x0011b;stn&#x000ed;k Kr&#x000e1;lovsk&#x000e9; &#x0010c;esk&#x000e9; Spole&#x0010d;nosti Nauk, T&#x00159;&#x000ed;da Matematicko-P&#x00159;&#x000ed;rodov&#x0011b;deck&#x000e1; Year 1925:1&#x02013;32</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR39"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR39" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kishino</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasegawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of the maximum likelihood estimate of the evolutionary tree topologies from DNA sequence data, and the branching order in Hominoidea</article-title><source>J Mol Evol</source><year>1989</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>170</fpage><lpage>179</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02100115</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2509717</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR39" publication-type="journal">Kishino H, Hasegawa M (1989) Evaluation of the maximum likelihood estimate of the evolutionary tree topologies from DNA sequence data, and the branching order in Hominoidea. J Mol Evol 29:170&#x02013;179<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2509717</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR40"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR40" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kishino</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyata</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasegawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Maximum likelihood inference of protein phylogeny and the origin of chloroplasts</article-title><source>J Mol Evol</source><year>1990</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>151</fpage><lpage>160</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02109483</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR40" publication-type="journal">Kishino H, Miyata T, Hasegawa M (1990) Maximum likelihood inference of protein phylogeny and the origin of chloroplasts. J Mol Evol 30:151&#x02013;160</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR41"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR41" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The &#x0201c;dry&#x0201d; silver method and its proper use</article-title><source>J Protozool</source><year>1958</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>103</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1550-7408.1958.tb02535.x</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR41" publication-type="journal">Klein BM (1958) The &#x0201c;dry&#x0201d; silver method and its proper use. J Protozool 5:99&#x02013;103</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR42"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR42" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lankester</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Remarks on <italic>Opalina</italic> and its contractile vesicules, on <italic>Pachydermon</italic> and annelidan spermatophors</article-title><source>Quart J Microsc Sci</source><year>1870</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>143</fpage><lpage>150</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR42" publication-type="journal">Lankester ER (1870) Remarks on <italic>Opalina</italic> and its contractile vesicules, on <italic>Pachydermon</italic> and annelidan spermatophors. Quart J Microsc Sci 10:143&#x02013;150</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR43"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR43" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leidy</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Contributions towards a knowledge of the marine invertebrate fauna of the coasts of Rhode Island and New Jersey</article-title><source>J Acad Nat Sci Philad</source><year>1855</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>132</fpage><lpage>152</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR43" publication-type="journal">Leidy I (1855) Contributions towards a knowledge of the marine invertebrate fauna of the coasts of Rhode Island and New Jersey. J Acad Nat Sci Philad 3:132&#x02013;152</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR44"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR44" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Farraj</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Findings on three endocommensal scuticociliates (Protista, Ciliophora) from freshwater mollusks, including their morphology and molecular phylogeny with descriptions of two new species</article-title><source>Mar Life Sci Technol</source><year>2024</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>212</fpage><lpage>235</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s42995-024-00230-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38827127</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR44" publication-type="journal">Li T, Zhang T, Liu M, Zhang Z, Zhang J, Niu J, Chen X, Al-Farraj SA, Song W (2024) Findings on three endocommensal scuticociliates (Protista, Ciliophora) from freshwater mollusks, including their morphology and molecular phylogeny with descriptions of two new species. Mar Life Sci Technol 6:212&#x02013;235<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38827127</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR45"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR45" publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lynn</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group><source>The ciliated protozoa. Characterization, classification, and guide to the literature</source><year>2008</year><edition>3</edition><publisher-loc>Dordrecht</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR45" publication-type="book">Lynn DH (2008) The ciliated protozoa. Characterization, classification, and guide to the literature, 3rd edn. Springer, Dordrecht</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR46"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR46" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mackinnon</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Adam</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Notes on four astomatous ciliates from oligochaete worms</article-title><source>Quart J Microsc Sci</source><year>1924</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>228</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR46" publication-type="journal">Mackinnon DL, Adam DI (1924) Notes on four astomatous ciliates from oligochaete worms. Quart J Microsc Sci 68:211&#x02013;228</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR47"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR47" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Parasitische Ciliaten bei Oligoch&#x000e4;ten</article-title><source>Arch Protistenkd</source><year>1954</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>212</fpage><lpage>245</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR47" publication-type="journal">Meier M (1954) Parasitische Ciliaten bei Oligoch&#x000e4;ten. Arch Protistenkd 100:212&#x02013;245</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR48"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Miller MA, Pfeiffer W, Schwartz T (2010) Creating the CIPRES Science Gateway for inference of large phylogenetic trees. In: Proceedings of the Gateway Computing Environments Workshop. Piscataway, NJ, New Orleans, LA, pp 1&#x02013;8</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR49" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ngassam</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Description de quatre esp&#x000e8;ces nouvelles de cili&#x000e9;s h&#x000e9;t&#x000e9;rotriches des genres <italic>Nyctotherus</italic> Leidy et <italic>Paranyctotherus</italic> nov. gen. endocommensaux d&#x02019;un oligoch&#x000e8;te terricole du Cameroun</article-title><source>Protistologica</source><year>1983</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>167</fpage><lpage>175</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR49" publication-type="journal">Ngassam P (1983a) Description de quatre esp&#x000e8;ces nouvelles de cili&#x000e9;s h&#x000e9;t&#x000e9;rotriches des genres <italic>Nyctotherus</italic> Leidy et <italic>Paranyctotherus</italic> nov. gen. endocommensaux d&#x02019;un oligoch&#x000e8;te terricole du Cameroun. Protistologica 19:167&#x02013;175</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR50"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR50" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ngassam</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trois esp&#x000e8;ces nouvelles de cili&#x000e9;s Astomes des genres: <italic>Almophrya</italic> de Puytorac et Dragesco, 1968, <italic>Maupasella</italic> C&#x000e9;p&#x000e8;de, 1910, <italic>Njinella</italic> nov. g. endocommensaux d&#x02019;Ann&#x000e9;lides oligoch&#x000e8;tes de la r&#x000e9;gion de Yaound&#x000e9;</article-title><source>Potistologica</source><year>1983</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>135</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR50" publication-type="journal">Ngassam P (1983b) Trois esp&#x000e8;ces nouvelles de cili&#x000e9;s Astomes des genres: <italic>Almophrya</italic> de Puytorac et Dragesco, 1968, <italic>Maupasella</italic> C&#x000e9;p&#x000e8;de, 1910, <italic>Njinella</italic> nov. g. endocommensaux d&#x02019;Ann&#x000e9;lides oligoch&#x000e8;tes de la r&#x000e9;gion de Yaound&#x000e9;. Potistologica 19:131&#x02013;135</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR51"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR51" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>von Haeseler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Minh</surname><given-names>BQ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>IQ-TREE: a fast and effective stochastic algorithm for estimating maximum-likelihood phylogenies</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>2015</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>268</fpage><lpage>274</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msu300</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25371430</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR51" publication-type="journal">Nguyen LT, Schmidt HA, von Haeseler A, Minh BQ (2015) IQ-TREE: a fast and effective stochastic algorithm for estimating maximum-likelihood phylogenies. Mol Biol Evol 32:268&#x02013;274<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25371430</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR52"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR52" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Obert</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>V&#x0010f;a&#x0010d;n&#x000fd;</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Integrative taxonomy of five astome ciliates (Ciliophora, Astomatia) isolated from earthworms in Central Europe</article-title><source>Eur J Taxon</source><year>2019</year><volume>559</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>37</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR52" publication-type="journal">Obert T, V&#x0010f;a&#x0010d;n&#x000fd; P (2019) Integrative taxonomy of five astome ciliates (Ciliophora, Astomatia) isolated from earthworms in Central Europe. Eur J Taxon 559:1&#x02013;37</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR53"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR53" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Obert</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>V&#x0010f;a&#x0010d;n&#x000fd;</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolutionary origin and host range of <italic>Plagiotoma lumbrici</italic> (Ciliophora, Hypotrichia), an obligate gut symbiont of lumbricid earthworms</article-title><source>J Eukaryot Microbiol</source><year>2020</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>176</fpage><lpage>189</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jeu.12768</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31603571</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR53" publication-type="journal">Obert T, V&#x0010f;a&#x0010d;n&#x000fd; P (2020a) Evolutionary origin and host range of <italic>Plagiotoma lumbrici</italic> (Ciliophora, Hypotrichia), an obligate gut symbiont of lumbricid earthworms. J Eukaryot Microbiol 67:176&#x02013;189<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31603571</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR54"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR54" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Obert</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>V&#x0010f;a&#x0010d;n&#x000fd;</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Delimitation of five astome ciliate species isolated from the digestive tube of three ecologically different groups of lumbricid earthworms, using the internal transcribed spacer region and the hypervariable D1/D2 region of the 28S rRNA gene</article-title><source>BMC Evol Biol</source><year>2020</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>e37</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12862-020-1601-2</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR54" publication-type="journal">Obert T, V&#x0010f;a&#x0010d;n&#x000fd; P (2020b) Delimitation of five astome ciliate species isolated from the digestive tube of three ecologically different groups of lumbricid earthworms, using the internal transcribed spacer region and the hypervariable D1/D2 region of the 28S rRNA gene. BMC Evol Biol 20:e37</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR55"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR55" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Obert</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>V&#x0010f;a&#x0010d;n&#x000fd;</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multi-gene phylogeny of the subclass Astomatia (Protista: Ciliophora) refreshed with two rare astome ciliates from the digestive tube of endogeic earthworms</article-title><source>Org Divers Evol</source><year>2021</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>77</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13127-020-00469-6</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR55" publication-type="journal">Obert T, V&#x0010f;a&#x0010d;n&#x000fd; P (2021) Multi-gene phylogeny of the subclass Astomatia (Protista: Ciliophora) refreshed with two rare astome ciliates from the digestive tube of endogeic earthworms. Org Divers Evol 21:59&#x02013;77</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR56"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR56" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Obert</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Rurik</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>V&#x0010f;a&#x0010d;n&#x000fd;</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diversity and eco-evolutionary associations of endosymbiotic astome ciliates with their lumbricid earthworm hosts</article-title><source>Front Microbiol</source><year>2021</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>e689987</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2021.689987</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR56" publication-type="journal">Obert T, Rurik I, V&#x0010f;a&#x0010d;n&#x000fd; P (2021) Diversity and eco-evolutionary associations of endosymbiotic astome ciliates with their lumbricid earthworm hosts. Front Microbiol 12:e689987</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR57"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR57" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Obert</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Rurik</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>V&#x0010f;a&#x0010d;n&#x000fd;</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>First molecular evidence of hybridization in endosymbiotic ciliates (Protista, Ciliophora)</article-title><source>Front Microbiol</source><year>2022</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>e1067315</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2022.1067315</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR57" publication-type="journal">Obert T, Zhang T, Rurik I, V&#x0010f;a&#x0010d;n&#x000fd; P (2022) First molecular evidence of hybridization in endosymbiotic ciliates (Protista, Ciliophora). Front Microbiol 13:e1067315</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR58"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR58" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Obert</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>V&#x0010f;a&#x0010d;n&#x000fd;</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The search finds an end: the morphologically chimeric hysterocinetids belong to the subclass Hymenostomatia (Ciliophora: Oligohymenophorea)</article-title><source>Zool J Linn Soc</source><year>2023</year><volume>199</volume><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>123</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/zoolinnean/zlad023</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR58" publication-type="journal">Obert T, Zhang T, V&#x0010f;a&#x0010d;n&#x000fd; P (2023) The search finds an end: the morphologically chimeric hysterocinetids belong to the subclass Hymenostomatia (Ciliophora: Oligohymenophorea). Zool J Linn Soc 199:97&#x02013;123</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR59"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR59" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parfrey</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lahr</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Knoll</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimating the timing of early eukaryotic diversification with multigene molecular clocks</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2011</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>13624</fpage><lpage>13629</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1110633108</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21810989</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR59" publication-type="journal">Parfrey LW, Lahr DJ, Knoll AH, Katz LA (2011) Estimating the timing of early eukaryotic diversification with multigene molecular clocks. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 108:13624&#x02013;13629<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21810989</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR60"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR60" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Leander</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coinfection of slime feather duster worms (Annelida, <italic>Myxicola</italic>) by different gregarine apicomplexans (<italic>Selenidium</italic>) and astome ciliates reflects spatial niche partitioning and host specificity</article-title><source>Parasitology</source><year>2024</year><volume>151</volume><fpage>400</fpage><lpage>411</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0031182024000209</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38465385</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR60" publication-type="journal">Park E, Leander B (2024) Coinfection of slime feather duster worms (Annelida, <italic>Myxicola</italic>) by different gregarine apicomplexans (<italic>Selenidium</italic>) and astome ciliates reflects spatial niche partitioning and host specificity. Parasitology 151:400&#x02013;411<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38465385</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR61"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR61" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pecina</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Rurik</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>V&#x0010f;a&#x0010d;n&#x000fd;</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Macroevolutionary trends and diversification dynamics in the hindgut order Clevelandellida (Ciliophora Armophorea)</article-title><source>Zool Scr</source><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/zsc.12701</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR61" publication-type="journal">Pecina L, Rurik I, V&#x0010f;a&#x0010d;n&#x000fd; P (2024) Macroevolutionary trends and diversification dynamics in the hindgut order Clevelandellida (Ciliophora Armophorea). Zool Scr. 10.1111/zsc.12701</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR62"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR62" publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Penard</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><source>&#x000c9;tudes sur les infusoires d&#x02019;eau douce</source><year>1922</year><publisher-loc>Gen&#x000e8;ve</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Georg &#x00026; Cie</publisher-name></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR62" publication-type="book">Penard E (1922) &#x000c9;tudes sur les infusoires d&#x02019;eau douce. Georg &#x00026; Cie, Gen&#x000e8;ve</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR63"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR63" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raabe</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Protoanoplophrya bithyniae</italic> sp. n., eine neue parasitische Ciliaten-Art aus dem Subordo Astomata</article-title><source>Ann Mus Zool Pol</source><year>1932</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>354</fpage><lpage>358</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR63" publication-type="journal">Raabe Z (1932) <italic>Protoanoplophrya bithyniae</italic> sp. n., eine neue parasitische Ciliaten-Art aus dem Subordo Astomata. Ann Mus Zool Pol 9:354&#x02013;358</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR64"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR64" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raabe</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Desmophrya contorta</italic> gen. nov., sp. nov., ein im Darm von <italic>Pisidium</italic> parasitierender Ciliate aus der Familie Hoplitophryidae Cheissin (Infusoria, Astomata)</article-title><source>Ann Mus Zool Pol</source><year>1933</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>51</fpage><lpage>56</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR64" publication-type="journal">Raabe Z (1933) <italic>Desmophrya contorta</italic> gen. nov., sp. nov., ein im Darm von <italic>Pisidium</italic> parasitierender Ciliate aus der Familie Hoplitophryidae Cheissin (Infusoria, Astomata). Ann Mus Zool Pol 10:51&#x02013;56</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR65"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR65" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raabe</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ordo Thigmotricha (Ciliata &#x02212; Holotricha). V. Familiae Hysterocinetidae et Protoanoplophryidae</article-title><source>Acta Protozool</source><year>1972</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>184</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR65" publication-type="journal">Raabe Z (1972) Ordo Thigmotricha (Ciliata &#x02212; Holotricha). V. Familiae Hysterocinetidae et Protoanoplophryidae. Acta Protozool 10:115&#x02013;184</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR66"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR66" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rataj</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>V&#x0010f;a&#x0010d;n&#x000fd;</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dawn of astome ciliates in light of morphology and time-calibrated phylogeny of <italic>Haptophrya planariarum</italic>, an obligate endosymbiont of freshwater turbellarians</article-title><source>Eur J Protistol</source><year>2018</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>54</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejop.2018.03.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29674178</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR66" publication-type="journal">Rataj M, V&#x0010f;a&#x0010d;n&#x000fd; P (2018) Dawn of astome ciliates in light of morphology and time-calibrated phylogeny of <italic>Haptophrya planariarum</italic>, an obligate endosymbiont of freshwater turbellarians. Eur J Protistol 64:54&#x02013;71<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29674178</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR67"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR67" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rataj</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>V&#x0010f;a&#x0010d;n&#x000fd;</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Living morphology and molecular phylogeny of oligohymenophorean ciliates associated with freshwater turbellarians</article-title><source>Dis Aquat Org</source><year>2019</year><volume>134</volume><fpage>147</fpage><lpage>166</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3354/dao03366</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR67" publication-type="journal">Rataj M, V&#x0010f;a&#x0010d;n&#x000fd; P (2019) Living morphology and molecular phylogeny of oligohymenophorean ciliates associated with freshwater turbellarians. Dis Aquat Org 134:147&#x02013;166</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR68"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR68" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rataj</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>V&#x0010f;a&#x0010d;n&#x000fd;</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nuclear and mitochondrial SSU rRNA genes reveal hidden diversity of <italic>Haptophrya</italic> endosymbionts in freshwater planarians and challenge their traditional classification in Astomatia</article-title><source>Front Microbiol</source><year>2022</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>e830951</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2022.830951</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR68" publication-type="journal">Rataj M, Zhang T, V&#x0010f;a&#x0010d;n&#x000fd; P (2022) Nuclear and mitochondrial SSU rRNA genes reveal hidden diversity of <italic>Haptophrya</italic> endosymbionts in freshwater planarians and challenge their traditional classification in Astomatia. Front Microbiol 13:e830951</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR69"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR69" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Revell</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phytools: an R package for phylogenetic comparative biology (and other things)</article-title><source>Methods Ecol Evol</source><year>2012</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>217</fpage><lpage>223</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.2041-210X.2011.00169.x</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR69" publication-type="journal">Revell LJ (2012) Phytools: an R package for phylogenetic comparative biology (and other things). Methods Ecol Evol 3:217&#x02013;223</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR70"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR70" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ronquist</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Teslenko</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Mark</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayres</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Darling</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#x000f6;hna</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Larget</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Suchard</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Huelsenbeck</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MrBayes 3.2: Efficient Bayesian phylogenetic inference and model choice across a large model space</article-title><source>Syst Biol</source><year>2012</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>539</fpage><lpage>542</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sysbio/sys029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22357727</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR70" publication-type="journal">Ronquist F, Teslenko M, van der Mark P, Ayres DL, Darling A, H&#x000f6;hna S, Larget B, Liu L, Suchard MA, Huelsenbeck JP (2012) MrBayes 3.2: Efficient Bayesian phylogenetic inference and model choice across a large model space. Syst Biol 61:539&#x02013;542<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22357727</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR71"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR71" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rossolimo</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Perzewa</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Zur Kenntnis einiger astomen Infusorien: Studien an Skelettbildung</article-title><source>Arch Protistenkd</source><year>1929</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>237</fpage><lpage>252</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR71" publication-type="journal">Rossolimo LL, Perzewa TA (1929) Zur Kenntnis einiger astomen Infusorien: Studien an Skelettbildung. Arch Protistenkd 67:237&#x02013;252</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR72"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR72" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sauvadet</surname><given-names>A-L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lynn</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Roussel</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Panse</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bigeard</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Schr&#x000e9;vel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Guillou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Redescription and phylogenetic analyses of <italic>Durchoniella</italic> spp. (Ciliophora, Astomatida) associated with the polychaete <italic>Cirriformia tentaculata</italic> (Montagu, 1808)</article-title><source>Eur J Protistol</source><year>2017</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>265</fpage><lpage>277</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejop.2017.06.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28778555</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR72" publication-type="journal">Sauvadet A-L, Lynn DH, Roussel EG, Le Panse S, Bigeard E, Schr&#x000e9;vel J, Guillou L (2017) Redescription and phylogenetic analyses of <italic>Durchoniella</italic> spp. (Ciliophora, Astomatida) associated with the polychaete <italic>Cirriformia tentaculata</italic> (Montagu, 1808). Eur J Protistol 61:265&#x02013;277<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28778555</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR73"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR73" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schewiakoff</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Organizacia i sistematika infusoria Aspirotricha (<italic>Holotricha auctorum</italic>) [The organization and systematics of the infusoria Aspirotricha (<italic>Holotricha auctorum</italic>)]</article-title><source>Zap Imp Akad Nauk (8e S&#x000e9;r)</source><year>1896</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>395</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR73" publication-type="journal">Schewiakoff W (1896) Organizacia i sistematika infusoria Aspirotricha (<italic>Holotricha auctorum</italic>) [The organization and systematics of the infusoria Aspirotricha (<italic>Holotricha auctorum</italic>)]. Zap Imp Akad Nauk (8e S&#x000e9;r) 4:1&#x02013;395</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR74"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR74" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmelz</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ers&#x000e9;us</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>van Haaren</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Timm</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A proposed order-level classification in Oligochaeta (Annelida, Clitellata)</article-title><source>Zootaxa</source><year>2021</year><volume>5040</volume><fpage>589</fpage><lpage>597</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.11646/zootaxa.5040.4.9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34811021</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR74" publication-type="journal">Schmelz RM, Ers&#x000e9;us C, Martin P, van Haaren T, Timm T (2021) A proposed order-level classification in Oligochaeta (Annelida, Clitellata). Zootaxa 5040:589&#x02013;597<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34811021</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR75"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR75" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schuster</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>V&#x000fd;voj opalin</article-title><source>Spis&#x0016f; Poct&#x0011b;n&#x000fd;ch Jubilejn&#x000ed; Cenou Kr&#x000e1;lovsk&#x000e9; &#x0010c;esk&#x000e9; Spole&#x0010d;nosti N&#x000e1;uk v Praze</source><year>1912</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>62</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR75" publication-type="journal">Schuster F (1912) V&#x000fd;voj opalin. Spis&#x0016f; Poct&#x0011b;n&#x000fd;ch Jubilejn&#x000ed; Cenou Kr&#x000e1;lovsk&#x000e9; &#x0010c;esk&#x000e9; Spole&#x0010d;nosti N&#x000e1;uk v Praze 21:1&#x02013;62</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR76"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR76" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shimodaira</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An approximately unbiased test of phylogenetic tree selection</article-title><source>Syst Biol</source><year>2002</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>492</fpage><lpage>508</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10635150290069913</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12079646</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR76" publication-type="journal">Shimodaira H (2002) An approximately unbiased test of phylogenetic tree selection. Syst Biol 51:492&#x02013;508<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12079646</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR77"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR77" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shimodaira</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasegawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiple comparisons of log-likelihoods with applications to phylogenetic inference</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>1999</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1114</fpage><lpage>1116</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/oxfordjournals.molbev.a026201</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR77" publication-type="journal">Shimodaira H, Hasegawa M (1999) Multiple comparisons of log-likelihoods with applications to phylogenetic inference. Mol Biol Evol 16:1114&#x02013;1116</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR78"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR78" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>&#x000dc;ber die mir bisher bekannt gewordenen und von mir genauer erforschten Infusionsthiere, welche im Inneren anderer Thiere eine parasitische Lebensweise f&#x000fc;hren</article-title><source>Abh K B&#x000f6;hm Ges Wiss</source><year>1859</year><volume>1857&#x02013;1859</volume><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>38</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR78" publication-type="journal">Stein F (1859) &#x000dc;ber die mir bisher bekannt gewordenen und von mir genauer erforschten Infusionsthiere, welche im Inneren anderer Thiere eine parasitische Lebensweise f&#x000fc;hren. Abh K B&#x000f6;hm Ges Wiss 1857&#x02013;1859:35&#x02013;38</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR79"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR79" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>&#x000dc;ber die Eintheilung der holotrichen Infusionsthiere und einige neue Gattungen und Arten aus dieser Ordnung</article-title><source>Sber K B&#x000f6;hm Ges Wiss Prag</source><year>1860</year><volume>1860</volume><fpage>56</fpage><lpage>62</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR79" publication-type="journal">Stein F (1860) &#x000dc;ber die Eintheilung der holotrichen Infusionsthiere und einige neue Gattungen und Arten aus dieser Ordnung. Sber K B&#x000f6;hm Ges Wiss Prag 1860:56&#x02013;62</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR80"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR80" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>&#x000dc;ber ein neues parasitisches Infusionsthier aus dem Darmkanal von Paludinen und &#x000fc;ber die mit demselben zun&#x000e4;chst verwandten Infusorienformen</article-title><source>Sber K B&#x000f6;hm Ges Wiss Prag</source><year>1861</year><volume>1861</volume><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>90</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR80" publication-type="journal">Stein F (1861) &#x000dc;ber ein neues parasitisches Infusionsthier aus dem Darmkanal von Paludinen und &#x000fc;ber die mit demselben zun&#x000e4;chst verwandten Infusorienformen. Sber K B&#x000f6;hm Ges Wiss Prag 1861:85&#x02013;90</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR81"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR81" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Timm</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A guide to the freshwater Oligochaeta and Polychaeta of Northern and Central Europe</article-title><source>Lauterbornia</source><year>2009</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>235</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR81" publication-type="journal">Timm T (2009) A guide to the freshwater Oligochaeta and Polychaeta of Northern and Central Europe. Lauterbornia 66:1&#x02013;235</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR82"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR82" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trifinopoulos</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name><surname>von Haeseler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Minh</surname><given-names>BQ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>W-IQ-TREE: a fast online phylogenetic tool for maximum likelihood analysis</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2016</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>W232</fpage><lpage>W235</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkw256</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27084950</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR82" publication-type="journal">Trifinopoulos J, Nguyen LT, von Haeseler A, Minh BQ (2016) W-IQ-TREE: a fast online phylogenetic tool for maximum likelihood analysis. Nucleic Acids Res 44:W232&#x02013;W235<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27084950</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR83"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR83" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Warpachowsky</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Eine neue Form von <italic>Opalina</italic></article-title><source>Bull Acad Imp Sci St P&#x000e9;tersbourg</source><year>1886</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>512</fpage><lpage>514</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR83" publication-type="journal">Warpachowsky N (1886) Eine neue Form von <italic>Opalina</italic>. Bull Acad Imp Sci St P&#x000e9;tersbourg 30:512&#x02013;514</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR84"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR84" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilbert</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Eine verbesserte Technik der Protargolimpr&#x000e4;gnation f&#x000fc;r Ciliaten</article-title><source>Mikrokosmos</source><year>1975</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>179</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR84" publication-type="journal">Wilbert N (1975) Eine verbesserte Technik der Protargolimpr&#x000e4;gnation f&#x000fc;r Ciliaten. Mikrokosmos 64:171&#x02013;179</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR85"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR85" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>V&#x0010f;a&#x0010d;n&#x000fd;</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiple independent losses of cell mouth in phylogenetically distant endosymbiotic lineages of oligohymenophorean ciliates: a lesson from <italic>Clausilocola</italic></article-title><source>Mol Phylogenet Evol</source><year>2022</year><volume>166</volume><fpage>e107310</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ympev.2021.107310</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR85" publication-type="journal">Zhang T, V&#x0010f;a&#x0010d;n&#x000fd; P (2022) Multiple independent losses of cell mouth in phylogenetically distant endosymbiotic lineages of oligohymenophorean ciliates: a lesson from <italic>Clausilocola</italic>. Mol Phylogenet Evol 166:e107310</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR86"><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR86" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>V&#x0010f;a&#x0010d;n&#x000fd;</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Deciphering phylogenetic relationships of and delimiting species boundaries within the controversial ciliate genus <italic>Conchophthirus</italic> using an integrative morpho-evo approach</article-title><source>Mol Phylogenet Evol</source><year>2024</year><volume>190</volume><fpage>e107931</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ympev.2023.107931</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR86" publication-type="journal">Zhang T, V&#x0010f;a&#x0010d;n&#x000fd; P (2024) Deciphering phylogenetic relationships of and delimiting species boundaries within the controversial ciliate genus <italic>Conchophthirus</italic> using an integrative morpho-evo approach. Mol Phylogenet Evol 190:e107931</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article>