<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="letter" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Signal Transduct Target Ther</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Signal Transduct Target Ther</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Signal Transduction and Targeted Therapy</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2095-9907</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2059-3635</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39668182</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11638257</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2053</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41392-024-02053-2</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Letter</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>CD4 T cell contact drives macrophage cell cycle G0-G1 transition</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mlcochova</surname><given-names>Petra</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-0426-384X</contrib-id><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Na</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1947-8018</contrib-id><name><surname>Shabana</surname><given-names>Omar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>Roman</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9751-1808</contrib-id><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>Ravindra K.</given-names></name><address><email>rkg20@cam.ac.uk</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/013meh722</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5335.0</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2188 5934</institution-id><institution>Cambridge Institute of Therapeutic Immunology &#x00026; Infectious Disease (CITIID), </institution><institution>University of Cambridge, </institution></institution-wrap>Cambridge, UK </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/052gg0110</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.4991.5</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 8948</institution-id><institution>University of Oxford, </institution></institution-wrap>Oxford, UK </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>13</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>13</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>348</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>19</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>21</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>8</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2024, corrected publication 2024</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Infection</kwd><kwd>Senescence</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/100004440</institution-id><institution>Wellcome Trust (Wellcome)</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>NA</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>Ravindra K.</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; West China Hospital, Sichuan University 2024</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p id="Par1">
<bold>Dear Editor</bold>
</p><p id="Par2">Macrophages are cells implicated in a diverse array of functions such as defence against pathogens, tissue repair /homoeostasis, and anti-cancer activity.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup> Macrophages are also targets of virus infection, and SAMHD1 is known to restrict lentiviruses through depletion of intracellular dNTP and inhibition of reverse transcription. We previously showed that HIV-1 bypasses this restriction by infecting macrophages that have entered the cell cycle and deactivated SAMHD1 antiviral activity through CDK1 mediated phosphorylation of SAMHD1 at T592.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup></p><p id="Par3">Macrophages form &#x02018;immunological synapses&#x02019; with CD4 T cells during MHC II dependent antigen presentation. These involve contact between the two cells via a number of interacting surface proteins including LFA-1 and ICAM-1 in addition to peptide loaded MHC interaction with the cognate TCR on CD4 T cells. Much less is known regarding antigen-independent contact between macrophages and T cells. Here we show that contact leads to cell cycle progression in macrophages.</p><p id="Par4">Monocyte derived macrophages were co-cultured with autologous CD4&#x02009;+&#x02009;T cells, as well as under control conditions of media alone (M0), or stimulated with LPS/IFNgamma to induce M1-like macrophages or IL4/IL-13 to induce M2-like polarised macrophages. Macrophages were then washed to remove CD4 T cells and (i) infected with VSV-G pseudotyped HIV-1 lentivirus (PV), or (ii) stained for markers of cell cycle progression.</p><p id="Par5">Macrophages co-cultured with CD4 T cells were an order of magnitude more susceptible to infection compared to M0 macrophages, co-incident with increased expression of the marker for G0-G1 transition, MCM2 (minichromosome maintenance protein 2)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup> (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a</xref>). MCM2 is a nuclear protein expressed from G1 through to mitosis and absent from cells in G0 phase.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup> Western blot analysis confirmed higher cellular expression of MCM2 under co-culture conditions and also demonstrated increased CDK1 expression and SAMHD1 phosphorylation with little change in overall SAMDH1 expression (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a</xref>), consistent with changes that are known to be associated with G0-G1 transitions in MDM.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup><fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Direct contact with CD4&#x02009;+&#x02009;T cells drives EGFR dependent G0-G1 transition in macrophages <bold>a</bold> Differentiated macrophages were co-cultured with activated autologous CD4&#x02009;+&#x02009;T-cells, or stimulated by LPS/Interferon gamma (to polarize cells into M1 macrophages), or IL-4/IL-13 (into M2 macrophages). CD4&#x02009;+&#x02009;T-cells were washed off 2 days later and cell cycle, viral permissivity was analysed. <bold>a</bold> Macrophages were infected with VSV-G pseudotyped HIV-1 expressing GFP (left panel). Cells were fixed 2 days post-infection and percentage of GFP positive cells was quantified by using automated microscopic platform. Graphs represent average of <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;15 (M0, M0_CD4); <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;6 (M1-like, M2-like) biological replicates. Statistical analysis was performed using one-way ANOVA with Dunnett&#x02019;s multiple comparisons test. ns, non-significant; <sup>&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.1; <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01. Bars indicate mean with SD. Middle panel: Macrophages were fixed and stained for MCM2 (a marker of cell cycle entry) and percentage of positive cells was determined by using automated microscopic platform. Graphs represent average of <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;16 (M0, M0_CD4); <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;4 (M1-like, M2-like) biological replicates. Statistical analysis was performed using one-way ANOVA with Dunnett&#x02019;s multiple comparisons test. ns, non-significant; <sup>&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.1. Bars indicate mean with SD. Right panel Macrophages were lysed and cell lysates from a representative donor were used for immunoblotting using antibodies against CDK1, MCM2, SAMHD1 and pSAMHD1 T592. <bold>b</bold> A diagram of cell cycle depicting an expression of several cell cycle markers. None of the markers are present in G0; MCM2 is expressed in G1, S, G2,M; Ki67 is expressed in late G1, S, G2,M; geminin is expressed in S, G2,M. Macrophages following cell-cell contact (M0_CD4) were fixed and stained for cell cycle markers. A representative acquisition field from microscopic platform is shown in middle panel. Scale bars: 40&#x02009;&#x003bc;m. Right panel shows Percentage of positive cells. At least 10<sup>4</sup> cells were acquired and used for analysis. <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3 biological replicates; Ordinary two-way ANOVA with Sidak&#x02019;s multiple comparisons test: <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001. Bars indicate mean with SD. <bold>c</bold>. Macrophages were plated at the bottom of transwell, CD4&#x02009;+&#x02009;T-cells were added directly to macrophages to allow direct cell-cell contact or added in the top of transwell to prevent direct contact. CD4&#x02009;+&#x02009;T-cell were washed off 2 days later, infected (HIV-1 GFP, left panel) or stained for MCM2 (middle panel). The percentage of GFP or MCM2 positive cells was quantified by using an automated microscopic platform. <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3 biological replicates. Statistical analysis was performed using one-way ANOVA with Dunnett&#x02019;s multiple comparisons test. ns, non-significant; <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001. Bars indicate mean with SD. Right panel: Macrophages were lysed and cell lysates from a representative donor were used for immunoblotting with antibodies to CDK1, MCM2, SAMHD1 and pSAMHD1 T592. <bold>d</bold> left panel: Volcano plot showing differentially expressed phosphoproteins in macrophages following CD4&#x02009;+&#x02009;T cell contact from 0 vs. 120&#x02009;min versus the absence of T cell contact. Coloured proteins were significantly up or down regulated with a significance level of 0.1; right upper panel. Macrophages were untreated (M0) or co-cultured with CD4&#x02009;+&#x02009;T-cells for 2 days in the presence or absence (mock) of inhibitors. T-cells were washed off and macrophages infected with VSV-G pseudotyped HIV-1 expressing GFP. Percentage of GFP positive cells was quantified 2 days later. Macrophages were lysed and cell lysates from a representative donor were used for immunoblotting. CDK1, MCM2 and SAMHD1 phosphorylation are markers of cell-cycle re-entry. <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3 biological replicates. Statistical analysis was performed using one-way ANOVA with Dunnett&#x02019;s multiple comparisons test. <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01; <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001. Bars indicate mean with SD. right bottom panel Macrophages were untreated (M0) or co-cultured with CD4&#x02009;+&#x02009;T-cells for 2 days in the presence of control isotype IgG antibody or increasing concentration of anti-EGFR antibody. T-cells were washed off and macrophages lysed. Cell lysates from a representative donor were used for immunoblotting</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41392_2024_2053_Fig1_HTML" id="d33e294"/></fig></p><p id="Par6">We next performed detailed analysis of cell cycle status to quantify cell cycle progression markers Geminin, MCM2 and Ki67 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1b</xref>) by flow cytometry. G0 is quantified as cells with the absence of MCM2, Ki67, and Geminin. MDM cultured in human serum showed only modest MCM2 and Ki67 expression, consistent with our previous data<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup> (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1b</xref>). By contrast, macrophages co-cultured with CD4 T cells demonstrated significantly higher expression of MCM2 and Ki67 compared to M0 macrophages, indicating G0-G1 progression following co-culture.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup></p><p id="Par7">We next sought to establish whether direct cell-cell contact was required for CD4 T cells to induce G0-G1 progression in macrophages. Using a transwell system (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1c</xref>) we observed that placement of a barrier between macrophages and T cells abrogated the increased susceptibility to infection with VSG pseudotyped HIV-1 particles, as well as the cell cycle G0-G1 transition (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1c</xref>). Immunoblot confirmed that the transwell prevented an increase in MCM2, CDK1 and pSAMHD1 protein levels following the addition of CD4 T cells (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1c</xref>). We conclude that direct cell contact is required for T cells to induce G0-G1 transition and relieve SAMHD1-mediated viral restriction in macrophages.</p><p id="Par8">In order to elucidate pathways that might be involved in mediating CD4 T cell contact dependent G0-G1 transition in macrophages we performed phosphoproteomic analysis. A number of phosphoproteins were either upregulated or downregulated. Frequently altered phosphoproteins included MAPKs, GSK3a, RASA1, CDKN2AIP and CDC42 that are known to be involved in the regulation of signal transduction and cell proliferation pathways (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1d</xref>). Given this result, activation of signal transduction and our previous work recognising the importance of the MEK/ERK pathway in the activation of macrophage G0-G1 transitioning,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup> we hypothesised that MEK/ERK pathway is involved in CD4 T cell contact dependent cell cycle progression in macrophages. To test whether this pathway was responsible for the cell contact phenotype we used inhibitors of MEK (U0126), CDK4/6 (Palbociclib) and CDK1 (RO-3306). Each of the inhibitors almost completely inhibited MCM2, CDK1 and pSAMHD1 expression following T cell - macrophage contact, indicative of cell cycle arrest in G0 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1d</xref>). This was reflected in concomitant blockade of infection with VSG pseudotyped HIV-1 particles following drug treatment, reminiscent of prior findings where genotoxic drugs induced macrophage cell cycle arrest<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup> (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1d</xref>).</p><p id="Par9">Growth factors and mitogens use the canonical Ras-Raf/MEK/ERK signalling cascade to transmit signals from their receptors to regulate gene expression and cell cycle progression. EGFR (epidermal growth factor receptor) is one of the most important receptors in this pathway and is a well known cancer therapy target. We therefore treated macrophages with a monoclonal antibody to EGFR prior to co-culture with CD4 T cells. The antibody prevented G0-G1 transition even in the presence of CD4 T cells based on the expression of cell cycle associated markers MCM2 and CDK1, and pSAMHD1 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1d</xref>). This suggests that EGFR signalling regulates cell cycle in macrophages following CD4 T cell contact.</p><p id="Par10">These experiments demonstrating cell cycle progression following antigen-independent T cell contact represent a new phenotype. Phosphoproteomic analysis revealed that within 2&#x02009;h of contact, cell cycle associated proteins were activated, and this was confirmed biochemically through inhibition of this pathway. We hypothesise that EGFR Ab blocks the interaction between EGFR on macrophages and ligands for EGFR on the T cell surface. Unlike exocrine secreted EGF, other EGFR ligands, including transforming growth factor-&#x003b1;, heparin-binding EGF (HB-EGF), and amphiregulin, are expressed by a variety of cells. Therefore, blockade of EGFR-ligand interactions at the macrophage surface would block downstream MEK/ERK signalling and changes in cell cycle.</p><p id="Par11">Tissues such as lymph nodes and the genital tract are characterised by close cell contact between T cells and macrophages and are known HIV-1 reservoir sites. Our data suggest that T cell contact leads to deactivation of SAMHD1 antiviral activity following cell contact, and may contribute to observations that macrophages are a bona fide target for HIV-1. Similarly, other viruses infecting macrophages may be impacted by cell-cell contact and therefore blockade of cell-cell interaction may represent a future therapeutic opportunity in combating viral infections in myeloid cells.</p><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary information</title><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41392_2024_2053_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><caption><p>supplementary material</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></body><back><sec><title>Supplementary information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1038/s41392-024-02053-2.</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We would like to acknowledge The Wellcome Trust and Lister Institute for funding this study. We would like to thank Ralph Heilig for technical assistance. This research was supported by the NIHR Cambridge Biomedical Research Centre (NIHR203312). The views expressed are those of the authors and not necessarily those of the NIHR or the Department of Health and Social Care.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>Conceived and designed the study: PM, RKG and RF. Performed experiments: PM, OS. Analysed data: PM, NZ, OS. Wrote the first draft: RKG, PM.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The mass spectrometry proteomics data have been deposited to the ProteomeXchange Consortium via the PRIDE partner repository (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ebi.ac.uk/pride/">https://www.ebi.ac.uk/pride/</ext-link>) with the dataset identifier PXD048462 and 10.6019/PXD048462.</p></notes><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par12">The author declares no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mantovani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Allavena</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Marchesi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Garlanda</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Macrophages as tools and targets in cancer therapy</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Drug Discov.</source><year>2022</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>799</fpage><lpage>820</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41573-022-00520-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35974096</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Mantovani, A., Allavena, P., Marchesi, F. &#x00026; Garlanda, C. Macrophages as tools and targets in cancer therapy. <italic>Nat. Rev. Drug Discov.</italic><bold>21</bold>, 799&#x02013;820 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35974096</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Silvin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ginhoux</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Merad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Macrophages in health and disease</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2022</year><volume>185</volume><fpage>4259</fpage><lpage>4279</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2022.10.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36368305</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Park, M. D., Silvin, A., Ginhoux, F. &#x00026; Merad, M. Macrophages in health and disease. <italic>Cell</italic><bold>185</bold>, 4259&#x02013;4279 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36368305</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mlcochova</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A G1-like state allows HIV-1 to bypass SAMHD1 restriction in macrophages</article-title><source>EMBO J.</source><year>2017</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>604</fpage><lpage>616</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15252/embj.201696025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28122869</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Mlcochova, P. et al. A G1-like state allows HIV-1 to bypass SAMHD1 restriction in macrophages. <italic>EMBO J.</italic><bold>36</bold>, 604&#x02013;616 (2017).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28122869</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Multi-omics analysis of MCM2 as a promising biomarker in pan-cancer</article-title><source>Front Cell Dev. Biol.</source><year>2022</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>852135</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fcell.2022.852135</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35693940</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Yuan, J. et al. Multi-omics analysis of MCM2 as a promising biomarker in pan-cancer. <italic>Front Cell Dev. Biol.</italic><bold>10</bold>, 852135 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35693940</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mlcochova</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Caswell</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name><surname>Towers</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DNA damage induced by topoisomerase inhibitors activates SAMHD1 and blocks HIV-1 infection of macrophages</article-title><source>EMBO J.</source><year>2018</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>50</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15252/embj.201796880</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29084722</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Mlcochova, P., Caswell, S. J., Taylor, I. A., Towers, G. J. &#x00026; Gupta, R. K. DNA damage induced by topoisomerase inhibitors activates SAMHD1 and blocks HIV-1 infection of macrophages. <italic>EMBO J.</italic><bold>37</bold>, 50&#x02013;62 (2018).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29084722</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article>